Hey everyone welcome to the 229th episode of The Internet of Things podcast
This is your house and your co-host
Kevin tofel
And we have
Excellent show
Albeit a bit brief
For you today we are going to be talking about
Oh and other company listening to your record
Plus
Tons of updates on the smart home front about who's partnering with whom who has a new OS who's taking
Voice Assistant off at certain
Not very useful or popular thermostat
And more
And
For those of you who have Smart speakers everywhere we're going to tell you about a
Acoustical attack that can happen over them just to keep you up at night
Our Guest this week
Is going to be Adam
Smith
Not The Wealth of Nations
Economist who is also dead
But
The director of marketing at litepoint he's going to be talking about the fear of stander
And
What makes a good wireless tech
So if you're trying to evaluate Wireless Technologies this is a good interview
For you
And if you're just curious about fira and fine ranging
Location also
Interview
We're also going to hear from our sponsor nutanix
And
End
He's got a lot more
So
Let's kick this show off
With
IMessage from another one of our sponsors
This week's episode is sponsored by digital ocean the digitalocean developer cloud simplifies
Modern app creation by combining the power Simplicity love for the developer community
Obsession with customer service and the advantages of Open Source iot businesses
Love digitalocean for their simple predictable pay-as-you-go pricing for cloud infrastructure services
With flat rates across all data centers digital ocean makes it easy to scale-up and expand globally without being surprised by
Cloud bill each month get started for free with a $50 digitalocean credit at
Do. Co
/ Stacy d o. Co /
Stacy
Already
Kevin
You know the last couple shows we've kicked off with the news that
Hey
Insert tech company here listen to your voice recording for
Quality assurance and has contractors paid to do that
And this week we find out that
Facebook
Insert Facebook here
As we've been talking about it
The biggest she was leasing for going to contractors
And people are listening to things that P
People thought only machines
I would say the other issue is that it's going to contractors and not him
Please because contractors have a little bit less
You know loyalty I would say to a
Company sold
They may sign an NDA but they may feel free to share the
Did you see pets with their friends wearing
Employee-employer relationship has
Little bit more
Heft
2in lights
Right yeah this is found out by Bloomberg
According to
Them Facebook has told them that they actually stopped his practice about a week ago so
It's not that they're currently doing it none of the company's alright I believe doing it now that we talked about
Including Apple Google and Amazon
But yeah some contractors even named the
Company taskus was the name of the contractor
Some of those employees Hertz
Conversations and other things they probably shouldn't have heard and
Kind of spoke to Bloomberg anonymously on this
The issue is that that
It's gone cuz this isn't happening anymore
But it's nice to see that we saw these companies are updating their terms of service
To be explicit about
Transcription Services people could be listening and so on and
Facebook does not have that in their terms of service yet I don't believe it
Added it so I am not sure how they're going to handle
And I thought some companies
They would let you opt out but they were still sending a small amount
If their work
Glad it's over.
I know Apple said they stopped
But I believe Google and Amazon stick
Google let's shoot
An Amazon Alexa to opt-out
Facebook doesn't let you opt out but they have apparently stopped
Is Facebook's case I think it's a little more specific because this all started when they
Adding voice transcription to Messenger
So you can have your voice chats transcribed and I
Where's the other companies were doing it too
Verify that
The Voice Services were working as expected so to speak
That is a live
But yeah I need anytime we're going to have a eye or
Any sort of computer
Do something for us there's going to be a human in the loop
Eventually to check
To make sure things are proceeding
You're supposed to
It's just basically
It's testing Avenue want to test that the system you design is working as intended
And it doesn't get weird
Piss
The thing we know about any sort of a eyes
You know left to his own devices for long enough
Can't get weird
CD tree
Well actually see our next topic
Excellent you're right
All right
Just keep going let's keep going
Scariest continues its Amazon rekognition this time which is
Amazon's face analysis system that we took
Police agencies have actually used the there's been a lot of
Debate over it because their facial recognition is not as accurate as
Definitely skewed
When their people colors that are being analyzed
It's not a
A great thing in my opinion
But they have
They added
A new emotion that Amazon rekognition can
Detect
Beer
And that's real
They've already been able to
Look for happy sad angry surprised disgusted comment confused
We can prove that your emotions
But now they've added
Pierce
I just worry when a system can do this hoot how it will be used
I guess against us
Yeah
Or even just to manipulate us
I mean it doesn't have to be
Malicious it could just be
Just to bring up
Hot Topic here in the States you could have political ads for example when you could see it
They tried fear
With people or
Etcetera
Oh yeah
Can you sell fewer products
With happy ads than you do
Do with that
Engender
So
There's that but there's also things like
Hey if you're
If your phone early nearby camera recognizes that you're
You're sad
Maybe it'll send you
Coupon for an ice cream
Even though maybe you don't want the ice cream
But you're sad
Add and you don't make it feel better
And those kind of things I think
Really
Insidious
Insidious good word
Isn't it though I bet we'll use that again
That's where we're going
With all of this
And I also would like to see so this is just a little blog item for
AWS butt
When they talk about improving accuracy
I would like to see their percentages
You know so anytime you're dealing with something like this you're getting up probability
Anytime you got a machine
Learning
Something you're getting
I'm ninety something percent
Sure
That this person is
I think we should start
Calling
For that sort of
Information
I know that they're going to say
Proprietary and they don't want to talk about it
But I think that's actually really important especially if we're going to be
Pulling the center
Service for
Policing
I want to know that
If someone says they're surprised
Disgusted
Before
Does facial recognition said they were disgusted and angry beforehand
And I really think it's important if we're going to
Decided that's valid that we get percentages about
How sure the system is
And how short is for
Men vs women
White people versus black people
That's just me thinking about down the road is a
Lyerly figure
Cuz I think that's going to
Color people's Perceptions in a way that
Absolutely
I feel like a six-year-old I don't think it's fair if it's not right
Excuse me is that what you think
So
Well I guess let's move on to some
Happy news
Brilliant the light switches that are very expensive and become a point of integration for your entire smart
They have now added native lifx support
Participative right lifx Wi-Fi
And other
This is
Useful so I tried Brillion
Probably a year ago
I had a really bad experience because they were
Really tricky
To install
And then I had a brilliant person come out and install a new panel for me
He even said it was trick
But
When they were working properly
They were little too much for me
Personally
But I could integrate all of my life
Is my Nest to my Sonos
I could actually do a lot from these light switches it was a big upfront
Time investment
But for someone who wants to have
Instead of like a
Amazon Echo 2
It felt almost like having like a savant or a
Control 4 system
That you programmed yourself
It didn't have the AP
Functionality but
This is probably
No switch for everybody because as you said it's for you is too much I mean it's got to
Touch screen
Scott sensors
That's
Would you call him
Touch sliders like
2-din sliders dim there at
Capacitive touch Sliders in
Actually one of the biggest you I can
Complaints I had about toes
Sometimes you just want to slap a light switch and have it work it this I had to
Look at your finger in the groove
At the same time
They're nice yeah they're very contemporary modern looking in
If you like that look it's obviously a larger than a regular
Switch because that
Touchscreen independent divots for the dinning
Uncensored
To become a
Whole home internet
If you have them all over your home they become a whole home
Yeah
I wouldn't want these in every room that's what I would say
But I'm intrigued because I do
Adopted for Life X
Extra color bulb
Versus you with
Junior color bulbs
Maybe now's the time how much are they
Brilliant light switches
Okay for a single switch control which is essentially just a touch screen
That is 299
When you go to a two switch control 34093 switches a399 for switches
Is 449
These are not cheap
But they do act as this integration
Again
Them too much
Yeah they work with a ton of stop
Connect to Sonos nest
Ring hue ecobee
Hilton madhumeh
Very nice
Yeah once you install them correctly which I have
Recommend
All right
They have left EXO Now Kevin there may not be
I think they're a little too
I think so considering that really only have one life Expo
Okay
Other Partnerships or Integrations LG and Lumia
This is something
China
But LG and Lemme have collaborated to create AI based smart home services
What is this mean
But first we should tell you who
Lumia
Yeah Lumi is considered by one of the largest
Iot companies in China
It was founded in Shenzhen which is like the
Electronics capital of the world everything is made knocked off
Sold Etc
Horses eating at
Lumia sold 100 million devices
As of the end of 2018
They've got smart sensors and Gateway so get ahold of ecosystem
United States
But now I know I haven't seen the prize it's it's
China sails
Yes but
Bradley
I like this deal cuz it's like hey
These two big companies have
Created
Automations that work automatic
Your stuff so you don't have to set it up
But if you have this Lumi sensor and have the LG air conditioning
You didn't you can turn it on so it basically
Uses that sensor is an external sensor
Your air conditioning
This is cool
In many ways because it makes the smart home easier for
People it's a bummer in the sense that
Oh my gosh you're going to have to rely on all of your
Device makers and Appliance makers to decide to opt into in
Integration testing
Which
Psy
It's going to take awhile
And has a possibility of going away as we
We see with
What will happen if you
This month with Nest shutting down at work
You know it's kind of interesting and I don't know the answer to this question but I'm wondering
What Louise voice
+ smart speaker integration Tsar
Because it's China
I don't know
Number one but never
Probably but then again
Here we have LG has integrated with
Padme and some tablets
Take me to we turn your tablet into a smart
Speaker Echo Show like device so
But you're probably right I would imagine a Chinese just Baidu maybe not in the Amazon integration
Google
Ask if they have contra
Will add them to the list when they do
Okay
And in a partnership
Breakdown
Cortana
Was removed from the glass thermostat
How many people bought this
Is a Johnson Controls
Glass
Glass thermostat
Is beautiful
It is beautiful
But
It came with Microsoft Cortana we were
And Johnson Controls then bought Lux products which is a smart home thermostats
Maker
And take that deals with both Google
In Amazon
And I'm sure that
Anybody who brought the glass with love Frances ha
Google Earth
And Microsoft is getting out of the smart home a spy
Cortana she's going to be virtual assistant for the Enterprise
So this totally makes
Did you have one of these have been notified about this yet but it looks like glass I said moving forward you have other voices
Distance through the works with functionality of Madame a and
Awesome
Another breakdown
We've been getting reports that the Google home and wink
The wink link
Is now week
No it's non-existent
Somewhere between those two clouds
There was a breakdown
And both Google and pink thought it would be
Be fixed but so far
Right before we started this show recording I
Testing mine again cuz I noticed it for about 3 days and
Now she says that
I cannot connect to wink right now
That is a bummer
And
Be aware that both parties are
Aware of it
And they're working on it
It's a little disconcerting.
And what I'm doing in the meantime as I'm just using my Wink app
Getting out your phone
It's always happening
And
Another breakdown cash so many divorces
The tp-link
Casa
System
Which makes a line of wonderful smart
Ground plugs
They
Are not going to
Yeah and they said back in January that they were so it's a total reversal at this point
It's not going to get the update the smart plug Mini
Get updates in the future
Right so
We are sad
Or at least kind of
Flummoxed
Mend
I feel like we're like TMZ or something
Like that has dating show
The iot paparazzi are out
But
Removing off
Partnerships
More scary stuff
Monster High stuff
A break from our light and happy news to
Alright at Defcon
My favorite show that I would never attend because I'm terrified of getting
Completely hacked
We're screwed over at some point in time
Sorry y'all
But I do love you and I love talking to
To all the people who do this
But
There was a researcher who basically demonstrated malware that they could stick
On any sort of speaker system
And then use that
It said I need physical or remote access to the device but once it's on there
They can actually
Melt the speaker components
By sending out these high-pitched frequencies and also possibly damage
People in
I don't know animals they didn't test it on
People are animals so we're not sure how that damage
It wasn't good
Yeah I just like smart speakers as you said any speaker so a laptop speaker
Your phone speaker a Bluetooth speaker
Headstones xiamen
I mean all kinds
Speakers
Yeah like if we were at the Muse the work
Insidious we could actually insert the
Frequency in this podcast and melt everybody smart speakers
So we're not.
But we could do that
You would have known that's true
But yes
We could be in City
Play it
Terrifying
I'll link is back to the mystery of Cuba where we had us diplomats in Cuba
Had something
Happen
Weather
Carrying their heads I don't even know
Nobody knows
It's it's like the Bermuda Triangle
Don't know their butt
Keep an eye out
On that and then the other thing from
Defcon did I just
I don't think it's funny I just think it's a case of
Old people
Look at us
Was this idea I'm sure you guys saw that the Avaya desk phones
Now are vulnerable
What's interesting about it isn't that you're invited us phone is wrong
Logo patch
It's that this is a vulnerability that is 10 years old
When it was found
Avaya actually issued a patch
What happened then is some point in time later
The forked the code for the phones and use the old unpatched version
So then
Reintroduce the vulnerability
Good news is they have a patch
Version Control revision Control
I just thought this was a perfect example I picture it like
If you're dealing with code inside
Source code
Control system whatever you use
And you got 10 years or so
Cotrip single devices or devices
This kind of oversight
Unfortunate going to happen
Outside of Defcon we also got news late last week about hallways new operating
This is the
Harmony OS
Are humming OS
In Chinese
Speaking Mandarin
But
They say they can switch over from Android and this is a big deal because
Cuz
The US government has decided that no Huawei
Short version of that which means companies from the US like Google
Have to pull their stuff from Huawei they can't
What's my name
Which means
No Android
This is bad
What ways has
That's okay cuz we've got the harmony iOS which is actually designed for the
And
Also smartphones but it'll be smart phone smart speakers sensors blah blah blah
And it makes me wonder like this is what Google's fuchsia OS has you know
I was just going to say that because why we've been working on this since 2017 we've since found out we know
That's this is their back-up plan to Android and as you said
It's going to actually start on smart TVs
But it is a microcurrent when open source microkernel
Which fuchsia is also a
Source
Maybe
I think Google's been working on and we still don't know a lot about that but I suspect these are like mirror
Like approaches
To bring a
Standard
Corset of
Features and functions that can scale across any device by size or
Screen
Size as well
Even though scream
Exactly
And that makes sense because that's where we are going we're going to need a OS is that
Work across everything because otherwise developers are going to
Hate your butt for
Seeking a developer setting platform so I did catch some interesting information that
If and when we bring this to
Phones work
Things that run Android today
That Huawei has a conversion program to convert an Android APK which is a
Basically zip file of all the Android components for programs
That will work on Harmony OS
Nice
And our final bit of news today is from
The nrdc
This is an environmental
NGO
And
They protect the animals protect
Environment protect Airport
Somebody has to do so
We're not
So they actually retained a company called Pacific Crest labs to test the power consumption
Smart speakers and video streaming
And as you can imagine
There are
Problems
Efficiency
Generally the research says
Hey
These devices are pretty energy efficient
But
When you link for example a smart speaker
Television
It causes it standby power in overall annual
Energy used to Skyrock
That's because basically the TV doesn't go to sleep
So they're saying hey
Maybe you can make the TV models go to sleep
When
They're connected to a Smart speaker
Some people do this some
People don't
But
I was like oh
That's kind of a bummer cuz I'm sitting here
Because I've got a Chromecast plugged in and
I've got it connected to my
Google Assistant
I don't know if Google is one of those people
Yeah I don't know I mean since a guideline that they're trying to get
Device makers to start following because they say
The spike in energy consumption from the always listening bits
Could exceed a billion dollars annually
The device makers could actually Implement something that you know that makes it more efficient as you were saying
You can just give us a scheduling thing
Smart speakers that says hey
Pretty much asleep for my 10 at night till 6 p.m.
No he's downstairs watching TV
Can you just not be listening from 10 to 6 p.m.
Yeah
Exactly and
There we go
They gave a chart full of
On Power vs standby power in a variety of devices
And some of them
Surprisingly
The Apple homepod
Consumes a lot
Of energy
Turn on power mode
In terms of Watts
The Google home is 2.2 the Amazon Echo is 2.4 Watts
Apple homepod as 5.91
Which
Holy cow
What is it doing
I don't know I know it's a very heavy and have to device but not that I had much to do with it
I see if these devices get bigger they seem to be using more power like the Google home mini the smallest amongst this test
Purposely 1.7 watch when it's on
Yeah but that's
1.7 vs
2.46
Yeah 2.44 the Hub
Okay
Well
I don't know about that
Unplug everything
We are plugging in a lot more things I thought we would stop plugging
Note this is why I'm changing all my Outlets to add like USB
Reports and such because I'm running out of outlets
Well and if you imagine something like the wireless power Consortium like bringing the tri-power not just to like
Connected devices
Imagine they have an effort to put it in
Kitchens
If you're not even aware
Of what has wires you just said it in places
Imagine how that might Skyrocket
The use of things
Need to be charged
Well I say
Is wireless charging
Under the floors and everything will just
Wirelessly magically
Evil be baked in
NRF Olga
I might lose my hair and grow a third arm but hey everything's chart
It might be warm
History like radiant heat
Pick up good for news we didn't have a ton of great news this week
Attentive
Scab use so let's go to the Internet of Things podcast
Hotline
And get a question from one of our listeners
The iot podcast hotline is sponsored by a pharaoh
What the fifth largest iot patent portfolio in the world a pharaoh provides a proven platform that doesn't risk your bra
Afero customers have
Experienced as much as an 80% reduction in time to Market
Antenex hire at
Oxidation rates
Learn more out of pharaoh
.
All right
It's August everyone's on vacation but we haven't been getting as many voicemails so if you would like to be entered to win
An ecobee Smart Switch
Give us a call with your questions
How many wh questions
So I don't know
We are at 5126 to 3
I will say halfway through the month
You have a really good chance of winning that ecobee
Oh yeah
And it's a good Smart Switch
Yep
If you're into that sort of thing
Go for it
So
This week's question is from
Rent
Let's hear it
Hello this is Brent from Utah I am
I have an older home and very small bathroom
With no fan
And the humidity gets
And then I gets crazy cuz up to six
60 65%
Listen to take a shower or bath
And a fan but I'd love to her
The fan run automatically
Until it produces dantu
30% humidity temp step point
I think also that would want to be able to hit the fan and have it run
For 15 minutes or just turn the fan on and leave it running
CC IMAX
Accessing turning it on leaving it on
Until it drops
And also way to trigger it is
It's not even at the humidity so I can get
Bad smells out of the way
Thanks for your help
Oh Brent this is such a good question because Kevin has already done the research because he wanted to
You do the same thing
I did half of it actually bought a product I just didn't install it yet
Basically
You can go to your local Lowe's Home Depot Etc
And check the shelves for bathroom exhaust fans
But have integrated humidity sensors in them
Again I bought ones
I did not
Actually install it yes I can't tell you how well it works but there's a range of these
Depending on the
Amount of air that you need moved any features you want some headlights in them and such
I found one
Kind of like better than one I bought it's a NuTone
Odyssey 1
CFM ceiling bathroom exhaust fan with humidity sensor
He's $139 it has a small integrated light in it which is just a nice add-on
And basically I think this will do what you needed to do
I say that because I look at the specs
You can adjust the set point of humidity
So that it's anywhere between 50 and 80% and if
Can recognize that the humidity levels in that range that you said
He will automatically turn on
For you
He will also stay on for user adjustable 5 to 60 minutes once the set point
Is Matt so once the humidity drops say below 50% if you want it set for the max
You can have it stay on for 5 to 60 minutes
And since it automatically goes on
You don't have to like turn it on when there's
It just will do it for you
So I think that will really meet your needs however
I know Stacy was looking at another potential option
Yes there are two
The first is if you want to make this whole thing smart
You can buy a normal exhaust fan
Install it
And then put a Smart Switch on it
And then buy a humidity sensor
Connect those two
That's a lot of work and you said you had an old home
So you may not have a neutral wire
Smart Switch
So I found something even easier
You can buy an awair glow
For about 90 bucks they might even be 79
Buy this thing
It's a
Indoor air quality monitor
Plug-in
A dehumidifier so you have to buy a separate little dehumidify
And then when the humidity gets to a certain point that the aware says it's not great
And I think you can actually set that
Do I actually turn on
Your dehumidifier for you and then turn it off
Either at a time setting or when the
Humidity has dropped
That is the no install
Way but it's going to be super easy
Then you have like a dehumidifier sitting in your bathroom
It doesn't address your
Automatic
Fan
Question exactly
Because it's a dehumidifier only
Then you're still
Kind of stuck with that
Right but it is simple and that does not require any Hub everything
It just requires two
Basic dehumidifier and
Ace Mart
Outlet
Right and if you went with the other option of a switching humidity sensor
You're looking at a property
And I'm thinking you're going to need a hug because of the sensor
Oh yeah you will need a
You're really looking like two hundred bucks
What's plus an install plus you've actually got to put the fan on
None of that
Options
There's some options depending on what you think you want and need
And can
A four-door reasonably
Expect to do
As you can see Kevin
Afforded something
I just haven't got around to it it's been 3 years Mike my deal is
It's not that I'm five years that's
Then you sell it at a garage sale
Exactly
That's a way to yours brand you can just buy my phone
There you go
Okay well this is great thanks Kevin for helping me out with the news I would
Encourage everyone to stay tuned
For Adam Smith of light point Who's going to be talking about the
Brand New fira Consortium
How is secure
How does location
And
How other companies can assess what makes a good Wireless technology like how they know where they should be
Investing
It's going to be fun
Staging for that but first a message from our sponsor
Hey everyone we're taking a quick break from The Internet of Things podcast
Message from our sponsor sponsor is nutanix and I have such a Bugatti
Botanics here
What to talk about
Hi Sachin how are you doing
Hi Stacy I'm good thanks for having me on
So such an eye associate nutanix with Hyper converged infrastructure
What is it specifically that you guys offer in The Internet of Things
It is called
Vallarta
That allows users to
Modernity application
Flextime manager
Literally Atlantic Scale from a central point of control
And last but not least
It enables users to do data processing across the aisle in the clock for ideas
Excellent so what is nutanix is
Core mission
In the iot
They say it's about getting
Insights out of raw data as soon as possible
600 billion terabytes of information next year
This is compared to 15 billion
That's kind of excited in all the public and private clubs combined
Cesar Perez possible
And very close to other states created end of year ideas
All right
There's a lot of data
You got to deal with it if so can you walk us through a customer story to illustrate the sconce
Smart cities customer and
Thinking about applying new type of cameras
License plate recognition cameras and AI cameras
To figure out traffic violation Center track cars and son
And
American listen to use their existing cameras and all that they that they were already collecting
Go get all those insights anyway
Ki Base traffic management project
Apply new devices for it
18 months
From start to finish
Lifeline software
That sounds very cool so if I wanted to use my existing data and device
To discover insights where could I go to find out more about natanic
Call Tyrone
Flashlight
Any other case studies
And your listeners can also sign up for a free trial
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham
Today's guest is Adam Smith
Who is director of marketing at
Hi I don't know how are you
Tight 18 doing great how are you doing
Excellent
Testing for
And you guys have tested all kinds of dip
Standards and you recently joined the fear of Consortium
And I shouldn't say you I should say your
So before we get into
Ciara let's talk about
Why you guys join the alliance
Your
Business case for doing sex
Yes so we recently joined be up here at the Consortium there are relatively new organization and we are a
Entirely Wireless
And I'd like to say that if there's like a product out there
Consumer Industrial
In some capacity
What we look to do is we look to help companies
Bring devices to Market
In the rectum into the manufacturer
Industrial
Actually
Put some structure and organization around a new technology
As the 15.4 IEEE
Here is doing is putting together an ecosystem
Bringing multiple players together to help bring
Some structure and organization and
Certified products
To make sure that they operate with each other
Okay
So this is important obviously to you guys because this is
Businesses
How many standards organizations do the guys
What part of a few organizations that lot of would like
Businesses has been historically in Wi-Fi
Remember the Wi-Fi Alliance today and we are currently bringing Wi-Fi six Market as part of
We're not going to talk about that
We are going to go back to Sarah
The fear Consortium was started
Bear recently by nxp
Assa abloy
And Samsung and one of the things that it's
Same as provide
Ranging
Location
What does that mean
This is one of the reasons why we're excited about this
Historically when we think about Wireless technology
And this is a little different
So this is not so much about how do I get gigabytes of data through the air this is more about how do I
Precisely position to devices relative to each other
And so it's about knowing
Bachelorette
Positioning
If you will so it's not so much about
We got megabits to gigabits per second going through the air it's more about I can very accurately
Of two devices that are that are talking to
That's what it's opened up some really interesting use cases
List of existing Technologies
In products moving forward
All right so I'm going to quibble with you just a little bit because I feel
In the industrial iot in Enterprise iot
Location is a big deal
And I see all kinds of wirelessly
Location app
Tell me the most popular game
Bluetooth
How is fira maybe better than blue shoes
For Enterprise
I'm thinking the same thing as multiple Technologies I need Wi-Fi
Bluetooth
5.1 is looking to enhance the capability
And then client conversation that goes on their phone
Different
Personals very very very white
So it's it's about 5
You can cut up the Bluetooth which is only
You have some more precise you can be with position answer what people are looking to achieve with ultra-wideband is
That is super impressive accuracy
It makes a lot of sense and the fact that it's
It comes out
Pulses as opposed to greetings
Between
Radios is definitely going to help with power
Secure access
I'm assuming this is why I said blaze
Right now I might walk by my
Connected door locks and it'll open with Bluetooth
Consumer applications but also things like
Yes definitely have heard of this technology being used in the context
Buildings
With the precise positioning you can't be a person that's not trying to do good that's sitting next to the car and
That basically do what's called relay hack where you be rebroadcast
Unique about
Why is this concept
Just because you're free broadcasting a signal in the other radio receives it you need to also messed that up with the value of the season
So it knows that you're not spoofing
You physically right there at the door of the car it's not somebody hiding over in the bushes after you leave Andre broadcasting the signal
So then the question becomes
You're experienced in the world
Wireless
How do we determine if something like this is going to be a success
I feel like Wireless standards pop up all the time and some of them are amazing and some of them just going to die a slow death
Whichever
A great migration is so many different times I mean
I've been Wi-Fi and Bluetooth
And some of this is a little bit of
The technology was waiting for an application in the application just hit a really sweet spot
Minnesota's the smartphone came out pretty much Wi-Fi Bluetooth
Just had cemented a place in history
Looking forward of backwards compatibility
But what does it take for a new technology to get adoption cuz we're seeing all kinds of industrial iot technology
It's kind of like
No one tool is the best one out there they're all just
Different tools in the toolbox
And depending on the millions of applications in the industrial space
One might be better than the other
Ultra wideband
A particular you'll have some interesting advantages
Nice about it is that
It can operate in
Spectrum
But it's operating under the FCC part 15 limit
So it's allowed
Because it is very wide bandwidth
Very low power
Call me when you can notice it
And it because it's white van with its it's not very susceptible to near Bandon or
You're not going to jam the signal
500 + 9
Listen interesting things about the physical layer part of
The technology
The thing that were excited about it
Thumbs up this new use cases
Actually I almost
To The Internet of Things
Because you can precisely know where something is
Sensors can touch and feel and see relative
You're also not looking to displace Wi-Fi or Bluetooth
It's looking there to enhance the use cases that can be done to products so there's this
High point of view because
Interesting
You don't have to worry about some of these other things with historically worried about that intercepting signals
Okay that is a lot so let's break that down a little bit
So
I'm going to use a fancy word that I hate trying to stay up Podcast but I'm going to go for
With this idea of nerve endings you're basically giving things
Proprioception
Which is the sense of where you are in space
You can do with that but I'd be curious to see if you have ideas about taking that forward what that means
It was a Enterprise in industrial custom
To be honest this is one of these things where
It's a new technology
But I can certainly Envision things
Maybe a medical industrial application where you're wearing some sort of identification
Batch that have the technology in it
And there's some sensor on a door and senses that you're walking towards it
And
You're authenticated to go in that door so it open
Your colleagues
Walking around the corner has their own badge and they're not
It's somewhat of a new way of thinking about
Building access
Security access in the automotive space that this is being discussed in in multiple ways I mean
People talking about
Know your wallet
If your car keys
Interesting use cases out there that I think
Interesting
See what happens with the forward
No broccoli
As a person who is seeing many Wireless standards
Let's talk about
Success in the consumer realm vs the Enterprise
Because the consumer realm it feels like
That is everyone's Holy Grail but I could be wrong
What does it mean
If your pushing a wireless standard for Consumer versus Inter
Success what are those look like
What are the impacts on the cup
If we're talking about specifically around the iot
In the consumer space frankly what you wanted to put your product to be adopted
And so what you're going to want to take your time
The technology that is
Has a high rate of adoption
Any type of product
It's going to have
Wi-Fi as well
You're not going to have to force your way into the ecosystem
That makes sense
And in the Enterprise
It feels like there's already so many Technologies and they're very purpose-built
So maybe this will be fine there and
What does success look like
The Enterprise is a wild animal
Wireless technology
So if I look at for example
Why don't we just take these well adopted consumer Technologies and put them in the industrial space
What are the challenges are
So Wi-Fi to me is this elegant
Technology that was really designed to be super robust in the fact that
Descended from an industrial and Enterprise
The pragmatic Pro
Networks that you don't know
Spectrum so if you set up a private Network where nobody else can be on there
Christine
Okay as someone who evaluates
What do you look for when trying to figure out which Wireless
I might answer this in two different ways because in a way point is
Agnostic
To the wireless technology
And we're not there to make judgment
That being said certainly we need to choose
Where we spend our investment dollars onto which technology
And so when we are
Evaluating
Where should we put our dollars
We have to make some judgments
Different Wireless personalities on
We design a flexible platform
Can be programmed to be a differ
I hate the term software-defined radio but if you will
We are at the end of the day
Then from a software development point of view clearly we prioritize based on where we think
Receive momentum that we will check our checks and we check our checks in our checks
And that's the beginning of this will work with some Consortium
Got it and I like this idea of Wireless personnel
I'm trying to sit here and efficiently
2 personalities
Given your view with the market
What are you excited about for The Internet of Things specifically
Coming up
What is the next big Tech
Technology
I don't want to focus so much on what's the next big technology because there's always
The wireless Market in two different sites
Spectrum Technologies
Most recently things like sigfox Lora and in the
Industrial
They tend to be governed by not only
From the government
They're also typically working with standard bodies that move on a slower
Did it pretty quickly
In the volume
It's one thing to say
Consumer space
7 billion people the planet of everybody's hands
Ciot just kind of exponentially growing
For me as a marketer
What we try to look for our high-value at Coyote
Devices so we're looking for things
It does matter where
Security or safety quality
That's where we tend to focus on the industrial space
Okay so
That doesn't answer the question of what you're excited about
I'm always excited
To be constantly
So as we move into the 5G World here I think 5G
Akira but 5G working with multiple different Technologies is going to be a pretty cool thing
But some of the things that people are looking at with private Networks
Is opening up some new business cases that we have
Okay I agree with you I look at like 5G plus like the cbrs band radio
Spectrum auction that were thinking about how to do something like that and like oh my gosh
I can have my own corporate Network
What is that mean
In my career I've never seen so much Spectrum activity as we've seen it the last two years it's just
Wild how much Spectrum
Motion is going on
Some of the
Unlicensed bands in SEC should be hopefully
Adopting either later this year into the middle of next
I just opened up new Spectrum where devices can operate more networks and makes the world go round
And we'll see hopefully
Wireless radios
Absolutely
All right well I don't think so much for coming on the show this week I really appreciate it
That's it for this week thanks so much for listening and remember if you'd like more iot news sign up
For my newsletter and Stacey on iot. Cam will see you next week