Hey everyone welcome to the 220th episode of The Internet of Things
News podcast
This is your host Stacey Higginbotham
And today is
Co-host
Kevin tofel
As always
Alrighty
Awesome stuff for you
We're going to talk about a dystopian future with facial Rick
Condition
Also selling Advertising based on
Emotion
State and
Facebook is not giving up on the portal
Unless disturb your news we're going to be talking about
Uber's Elevate services
How it be work with
What's 5G Network
Amazon has halted sales of one of its connected devices and Google
As a $25.
Actually worth taking a look at
We're going to hear from our sponsor Dell Technologies
And our guest this week is Dominique
Node
Who is the CTO of
Everything
Hope it's not
All the things
That's just the
Platform for RFID NFC
Cetera tags that are placed into
Consumer goods
It's a really fun interview we're going to talk about how to connect a billion
Let's go to a message
Another one of our sponsors
This week sponsor is
Nordic semiconductor
Kickstart your short-range wireless application ideas with the NRF
5 to 8
Did the most advanced and flexible short-range Wireless solution available today
The NRF
50 to 8:40 is a
Highly Advanced Ultra low-power system-on-chip that can meet just about any requirement in ultra low
Power Wireless applications it has broad protocols support including Bluetooth 5 and all of its features
Bluetooth LE thread
Zippy
24 gigahertz proprietary with protocols and currency options
B nrf52 840
Can support the most demanding applications
Redis cortex m4f CPU and 1GB of Flash and 256gb
Rams
It's death with a bunch of peripherals including USD crypto sell quad as bi and NFC
Everyone knows somewhere makes a difference in the nrf52 8:40 is backed up with an unrivalled selection of comprehensive
Plasticade
Covering a vast range of applications to get your building tomorrow's great product
Find out more at www. Nordic simmi.com
Flash nrf52840
All right
Kevin are you ready for
Disturbia
Dystopia and surveillance yes I am
Okay
Well
Get started we've got
A couple big stories happening this week first I'm going to
I'll start off with the
Hacking of the US
Customs and Border Patrol database
Partially because here I am in Canada this week
As I was walking through customs in Montreal I was like
I wonder if my photo
And it is
It is
In front of the little
Passport machine in it
So I guess we should start with the story
Do you want to tell us what's going on yes yes
Well you are a way out of the country
Apparently
The Customs and Border Protection Agency
Which had stored
Restoring images of Travelers in license plates
Nearest tens of thousands of those images I don't know exactly how many yet
Basically hacked
Us
Government reportedly says no more than a hundred thousand people had their
Compromise
The way this
Hackworth it wasn't
Customs and Border Protection
Self which has the data
Contractor subcontractor
That works
For the CDP transfer copies of images
And that Network
Was hacking
They're not supposed to be actually transferring was images
So that's the story
But it was too much larger questions about
Surveillance
But lots of things
So this is actually very similar Sony
The big Sony hack from a couple years ago happen the same way it was a third-party contractor
Which first off
Everybody who's Gathering anytime
Consumers
You should be evaluating your third-party contractors
Security practice
Like as much as your own
So we'll just get that out of the way
Now let's talk about the
The second aspect
Surveillance
Tissue
So this is disturbing for a cup
Couple of reasons
The US government has been
Using facial rash
Definition in pulling this data
Without really talking
People about
How is being
It even gives Airlines
Access to this data
If they want
So there's been a lot of
Controversy right now
About
How people are using
Image data
And facial
Recognition
Without talking to people about how they
I think the underscore your point it was only a few months ago
Everybody was up in arms when some people wore
Going to flights at US airports that was an artist
These little cameras
And there was no
Knowledge
Which is there and say What are you do at that point decide not to go on your flight
Because you want to review
The terms and conditions
First you check and make sure it's not a
Boeing Max 770 or whatever that was a butt second yeah you check and see if
Your picture there
It's very quiet that's a thing I guess you said this not being discussed at least
In China we know this is all happening at maybe
I would imagine the Chinese
And they're Building Services on it
Their advertising services
Right here it is
It's a little bit more clandestine
There's also no consent happening
The frustrating thing is what happens when it says haxo now
People have
Picture
Disassociated very accurate
What's my name
So accurately enough for
I used Tabitha expression is good enough
Which usually means it's not
I I don't know if I should rethink that
Particular era
So they have access to this
I don't know it talks about license plate government also has a lot of biomass
Didn't they have my fingerprint data for example is part of
Customs and Border
Protection agency has my fingerprint data is part of the
Nexus global entry program
Is that kind of information gets hacked and suddenly people have a way to
Possibly
Access things that it in the physical
And as we start moving to biometric
Authenticators
That's a given
Strangers easy access to ways to
Get into
Any number of other people
Tails or
Homes or that's what
I hate to ask this question
Cuz I only want to think about the answer but
Longer here in the US do you think it will be
Before it's more like what China does
Today in terms of
Surveillance
The newsletter
A week or two ago
There was a great video about being in China what it's like to be there if you're not a citizen maybe you're
Startup company Oregon Shenzhen
And one of the guys who's from Australia for some companies building
Digital ski coach
Products
DJ walkzz
The camera caught him
In 20 seconds he got his ticket
Over WeChat
And because I have funds in WeChat
The ticket was safe for me to take it out
He's not even a Chinese citizen
Lesbian China
How long before we get there
Because I think we're going to
I want to be
Especially about that
Is
I think we could be there very cool
I think we won't get there
From a practical standpoint because there would be less
Lawsuit over things like that
But the
Larger issue
In one that's inherently about
Fairness is
If you have
This automated Eye in the Sky the
Can enforce every law
Right so see if someone's jaywalker
And then enforce them
If it's automated it creates a much more fair
Society
In the sense that
Right now predominantly African-American
Please. Them as opposed
And
The question that makes
What laws does a society decide to add
X-Force
If you're going to have it
Art by autumn
Right where it applies to everybody regardless
Yes
You know it's true
There's pros and cons of ultimately
Knee-jerk reaction is woke that is
We also then took a hard look at the laws that we want
Force or the out
Comes we would like to see from those laws
We might actually be able to
Make a more fair Society
Alright Lizzie and speaking of
Enforcement
And facial
Rescue Mission
You came across the pretty
Creepy story
I did and it's about a new set of smart glasses
American company
Music switch
Almost every year at CVS I see some new
Products from them in this space but I've never really
Bible come to Market
And I'm really hoping this one doesn't but unfortunately
Looks like it is
They are making
Smart glasses
That works on
Basic software and services from a dubai-based firm
Call nntc
INTC
Facial recognition algorithms
Megapixel camera and glasses
Where these and scan faces
Krowd
Data is compared against
A database of 1 million images and literally
These things can detect 15 pieces per frame
Second
Dirty Clippers
Yeah so you can you can scan through
A crowd to find maybe a suspect.
Something safe your police which it is
What I think they are starting to
Target PS4
And I know that in China going back to that they do have some
Something similar
To these we don't hear in the US but I think we might soon
I don't know yet
50 pairs produce
So
It's not like these are mass-produced
I could see some places
Imagine the scene you said like a
Protest
That would be Beyond Scared
It's just in your lawn
Is right now
People's Facebook pages
To see where they are
And there are a lot of places like I remember me now going through London a couple years back there's cameras everywhere
So there are tons of like
Closed-circuit cameras
Various
Countries and regions
Where is
They can apply facial recognition algorithms to the date of there so it's not like
This is new what's new about it
Right
Yes
And imagine being able to hack into
Biometric data
For example
Imagine being able to not just hack into it but maybe
Hack into the system in
Change that data
Suddenly
You have this
Hey
If you're Criminal
Change your own face or maybe
If your friend somebody not to make them not to make a pun with glasses
Alright dictionary
Entering
Creepy Zone
Talk about
Another scary things witches
Scary
Spotify
Create a playlist based on
Oceans
We've been doing that for a while
Which I use that picture all the time but now I'm like
I don't know if I want to use that anymore because now
Was just found out they're selling
The data
About your moods
Advertising purposes
Wow I mean that's a whole different set of advertising data
Yeah cuz I got often
You know I look at Spotify and I go in and in
Tweaked my privacy settings I actually everytime I buy a new device or new subscription I go to the privacy setting first and I
Make sure everything is
Is private right
As my default
I recommend everyone
But now I'm like
When I'm in my Mellow Mood there going to be
Selling at
States is in a Mellow Mood right now
Picture of candle
Yeah exactly yet
The story that we listen to work
You know there's likely to be
Feeling pressure and stress
So
You know you you start advertising something at work distressing
Candle or whatever it is
Yeah and
Tighten a couple weeks ago Amazon the news came out
Just playing around
Wrist-worn wearable that would track
People's moods
Impossibly
Some of the theories were like oh yeah
Maybe we could help people interact
With other people
More social
I think I should like this idea
Discover that what they do with it
I would be thrilled if my digital assistant
Read my moon that way cuz
DOT cameras it's not that invasive if you know
What if your mood was
Well
They would know what music you're playing
I would know to do the lights
That I'm like
Pair
There's a lot of movies like
Sometimes when I'm in a bad mood I don't even tell my family cuz I'm like
Sometimes you know when you're like pouting or really salty
You like I know I should not
Don't talk to Mom anime says she's in a bad mood I don't really want people to know I'm having a temper tantrum
Cuz that is not cool
Close to my family does know anyway but
But still
So I don't trust any of these companies enough to give them that
Kind of level data even if it does make my home
A better place
I think I'm willing to draw the line
Emotional survey
I don't know where Kevin Skinner
Maybe we'll hit it maybe we will
I don't have many rides that I won't cry so
Just cuz I like to try things and learn about vacations of upsetting what the value is for the cost song
If they said that we do have this product
Thatcher open
So which beta the new Facebook portal
I didn't even pay the old ones cuz I won't touch those
This is this is curious so did
Did you draw the line
Facebook did you drive
No it's result video chat I mean I video chat with my son almost everyday
We video chat
You and I do video chat sometimes
I am always wonderful
Okay
No I get utility out of video chatting without a doubt
But
I don't need to use Facebook's platforms
Do so and
Get what I need
From them
If I use their platform so why bother is my taken
I know there's people that bought this thing I've never seen them
There's a there's a market for it
Certain people I'm just not one of them
Bring in another
Stories
There is a story
About
AI
Recognizing Common Place household objects
Looks like soapstone
Vision
And I was thinking about old Facebook would love to know like the products in my
Amazon Echo Show has lots of products
Yeah I don't know if it's pulling that data
So
This particular story was about how
They are much better at recognizing
Things from
First World countries basically so if you're in a poor country with
Generic for people soap
Bransford
African country
Heyde Eye doesn't recognize those because the engineers usually
Yeah they need to expand the model
With these other products that teach it
So it's going to be there
The Blind Side
You know it's at I don't think I don't think that are
They're trying to get the most bang for buck here
So
All right they don't
I asked my opinion
I care but
Figure model it is some more the better
You know I don't think we said you mentioned beta test these Facebook portal
Apparently
CNBC Facebook has said that they have
New versions of their portal video chat
This fall different form-factors perhaps
We
Before the show try to guess what this form factors would be and you don't even want
Think about what we thought about cuz I have no idea what it was like to be doing
What about it
You talk to your wife
You do not care what I do talk to you on your way
Right place
Because video chat for me tends to be a long
So I'm kind of thing well I'll spend
510 30 minutes whatever depending on the person in the
Ana purpose
Whereas talking to my watch is there any micro transactional send a text
Reply to somebody
Etc
9 that's it
Legendary chest
Tend to be very
Transactional
It's like let me show you this place that I'm at
Check this out and then we switch to
Different
Holy cow
Alrighty let's talk about 5G
Man
Because we haven't we haven't
Yasso
Couple exciting things about the story
She is actually that would it be more exciting things but AT&T is working with Uber's elevate
To test out
Basically how do you bring cell service
Into
Your taxi
Syndromes
YG is really just throwing in here
Market purpose because right now luberon 80
AT&T reusing
BL2 E network
To see how to connect
The Ubers
Potential are taxis
The interesting thing about this press release was that they were saying that
Expects Elevate to launch its first taxis
In 2023 which is only 4 years
Well that's something else I would beta test although not a very tall height
Like you said the 5G biddestone here because of marketing
Even question why it's in there at all because we talked about millimeter wave and
Line of sight
Why you do that with an air taxi
Without spending billions and billions are there
Line of sight I mean if you're going up your orienting your antennas up there's not actually as much stuff
You know there's no buildings
The latency
Elements are
Compelling
Just think the power management though I mean a lot of
5G what it's going to look like
Actually talk to somebody from Annex
Speed recently about
Managing
The radios
And what's going to happen is a lot of these companies are going to deploy
GE service
If that millimeter-wave isn't available or it's just
That processing that's going to happen
That has to happen like on the Drone and at the base station level
And that's going to
Gobs of
Just suck up
Types of power saws
Museum
Yeah that becomes important when
If you run out of power
In the air
No millimeter-wave is going to help you
Is a bigger battery
We'll see
I guess that really sums up my
I think it's going to have to be like
Coruscant Star Wars I apologize for the reference but they're just going to have space Lane
Driving there
I'm not even asked
I think people who know Star Wars
They'll understand
All right
Trust me
Hey did you buy the
Amazon blink
Xt2 video camera
I know we talked about doing it but
I never did
We we did I did not get $1 / 150 battery power
Yeah in the blink cameras have been around for a while Amazon
This one was around for
How long has this been around
2 weeks
It was just back in May that they started taking orders and
Marshalls products
Already
Yeah Amazon has temporarily stop taking orders for this camera
They did it because
Cuz it was getting
Mapreduce with some buyers
Saying that it had poor range between their camera in the router
Bad software bad movement detection
And so am
Sunset
Let's take a closer look
I don't know if this is true but
Reportedly a Amazon reviewer for the product
Rote
Amazon review
I got an email from the founder of blank letting you know they are working out
Unexpected issues with
Does expand on
Enter very willing to work with me to get this figured out
There's issues
And this is hard and
How hard is it is so hard that
I don't know if you guys remember wechat
August
View doorbell
Vegetable that like 3 weeks after it's lost
Lunch in this was a battery power
Are just like the blink camera battery power
Video doorbell
And
This was also
Because it
Behaving inconsistent
What can we say it's hard to do battery-powered video tube
Especially because they have to use Wi-Fi so that's
Powersox
They've got to figure something out there
You got to have this
Sleeping awake mozyr very difficult on this because you basically
You know if it's movement detection you're after the second
It detects movement he wanted to start recording are you want to already
I've been
And just like
Delete recordings continuously
So this is really
Is really a struggle
Four companies
I suspect this is why we don't
Battery power
Camera
Yeah I mean Arnold's done a good job here
Even Arlo actually gets
Get yelled at sometimes for
Basically sucking up battery
And they've actually got their own Wireless in their early cameras
They had a hug that
Work with a cam
Which I assume is a
More robust
Wireless protocol
To handle things like lag
What about Google and their environmental sensors and iot
Yeah this is cool for the tinkerers out there if you have a Raspberry Pi
You can now buy for $25 and add on board on board
That's
Is 4
Google
Coral
Mental boards the coral Dev board
It has
Machine learning board with
How to use yes
So the TPU is a separate USB plugin
And what that does is that let you do machine learning without the cloud you kind of
Bring it down to the edge connect connect this board to that
Daisy chain
You can get tensorflow on the edge TPU to work with a python and SQL
Scott a humidity and temperature sensor ambient light sensor
Pressure
You know it's like I said it's something for like iot development it's not something
Consumers are going to go by but I thought was kind of
Could you use it to make our our fabled washer
Hair dryers
The infamous washer dryer sensor I think you could I don't see why
Not
I wish I had vibration
He doesn't have that
Humidity
Maybe when the washer is going
Politely
All right there's a lot of ways we can skin that cat
We just have
I figured it out yet
Okay well
I think that's enough for this week especially since I'm traveling and just coming out the movie
Guys I cannot wait for the move to be finished we're so close now so maybe in the next week or two
Actually know the first thing I'm going to do and it relates to this week's voicemail question
Witches from Lynn
Before we hear it the iot podcast hotline is sponsored
This month by a pharaoh with the fifth largest iot patent
Portfolio in the world
A pharaoh provides a proven iot platform that doesn't risk your brand
Affero customers have experienced as much as an 80% reduction in time to mark
M10x higher activation rates
Learn more at a pharaoh
All right
And now
To the voicemail
Stacy and Kevin
When's the Maryland
Your most underrated
Picture of your smart home
That you would tell a new
Thanks
Lynn
It's such a good question
And
I will tell you the first thing I'm going to do when I get back
Since I now have internet access in my house
And my smart devices unpacked
Actually get a setup
Motion sensor in my hue light bulbs motion sensor the Hue bulbs so that you can do it with
Thompson Center
SmartThings
Who said that
Lighting thing
Did my laundry
I cannot get over how much
I miss walking into my laundry room with
Purse full of laundry and having the lights turn on automatically
Then turn off
You have 2 minutes after
No motion has been detected
It's such a small thing but
I love it
And not having it is driving me absolutely crazy
And I haven't wish I had because I would love that perspectives like what I miss the most will be
The very first thing I have to put back in place
I'm just turn the internet off
Could do that just make
The family will love that
Yes
No YouTube TV for you come back one year
But I have to say the most
Unexpected
Expected as well as underrated
Value that I've gotten
From my smart home and I've mentioned this probably a year ago cuz I think it's going to happen
Was having
A webcam
Inside my house looking out the front window
Where my driveway and the road as whatever townhouse communities
We sometimes park on the road
Sometimes have cars in the driveway
But I did put it out there for that I put out there to see who's walking up there
Pass to come around to the front door Etc
And yet
A $20 wyze cam
Whichever it is now it was a mess when I had a pack and play for this particular
Instance
Save me $1,500 because it captured
A neighbor
Eating my Park
Car on the street
And that was used as evidence for the insurance claim because the neighbor claims
She did not have
The car
I never thought I would use it for that
I need the money back on that webcam
Many many times over and I would never get rid of it for that very reason because
You never know when
You're going to have fuse for like that
Slightly more expensive
Camera similar use case I would recommend
The Logitech Circle 2
It's not as cheap as the wise cam
But
It has discrete filtering
That makes it so when you
Use it
In these specific I am
Cricket inside and outside
It doesn't get the glare off the window at night
It's also homekit certified and it will be one of the first cameras that work with
Apple secure video
API that Apple talked about last week
WWDC
And I'm in Canada right now so I'm looking at prices and seeing Canada prices
Kevin how much is that in the US
Here in the US that looks like it retails for about $180 at Amazon
Does have it for $12 less
Excellent so it's more expensive
But if you're trying to catch like things happening at night in your house
And you have money you'd like to birds
That is another option
Okay I realized we didn't talk about any of apples
You did mention the video
Camera API and
Set real quick to say what it is I basically
Really clever
Continue to double down on privacy as a way to stand out from the crowd here
Homekit cameras
Better enabled with this API
The video streams won't be sent
To the
Cloud of the hardware manufacturer
Which could often be a third-party cloud provider
Dean's dad will be encrypted and then sent
ICloud
And you will not pay for the
Storage
10 days
And even app will not be able to see what's been captured on video so therefore there's no
Privacy implications
It's new advertising location Etc
Erodditys Hardware makers
Basically from the
Bobby's camera monitoring services
Yeah and they also actually Apple also addressed another big question
We Care a Lot
At the
Podcast
Which is how do you secure your home network for your iot device
Ww.w
BGC
Apple did say
They're working with a few router maker
Spectrum
Linksys
And Gyro
Which ironically
Brazilian by Amazon
But what they're going to be doing is homekit certified routers and these are going to have
Three different layers of
Troll
So all of your homekit devices on the network
You'll be able to select the device and then you'll be able to say hey restrict this only to the home
Which means
Only talk to things
In the home
Homekit devices
Automatic which is
Restricted
I'm talking to the outside weird websites but
Its own website and a few others are fine
And then no restrictions
Let it do whatever I want
Which is open up your front door and walk away from your house
So that's
Really interesting and I can't wait to hear about people's experiences on this cuz it does seem like
One is an extra layer of
Complexity
People I think are going to be like most secure restricted home
But then they're going to be pissed when things like Amazon
Echo Cloud Integrations
It's kind of the big news from Apple will talk about more of that as we see iOS 30
Because they're so cool
Homekit related short
That's that'll be happening
But wait till we can
You play with it
That's all the news for this week
Let's stay tuned for our guest
Dominique
Getting out
Who is the CTO of
Everything
We are going to be talking about what it means we have a trillion connected devices
Either NFC Bluetooth bass tags
Even our can of Campbell's Soup
Might one day have a little
What does that mean for the rest of
But before we get into that let's hear from this week sponsor
Hey everyone we're taking a quick break from this week's Internet of Things podcast for a message from our sponsor this week
Sponsor is
Dell Technologies
And I'm here today with John Curtis
Or JD
The sales VP of solutions for Dell Technologies
Your team is talking about becoming datafirst
What does that mean
That's a great question and given just a sheer quantity of data has been created nowadays remember
Ice cream gigabytes
By the year 2025
Cloud first point of view
Everything should be pushed to the Public's cloud
It's just not practical
Directions to cut generating from the edge
Interpret all of it into the cloud is just
Impractical
We need to think today
The cloud first
Delaware
Rather than starting to
Determine what they do
Testicular clog can do for you
Thinking of it more from what is your data
And what can your data do
So that means an increasing focus on the edge
And why is Edge Computing essential for success and Industrial scale iot
Yeah energy the first world
Removing the data
In performing actions closer to the edge is going to be critical
There are three main reasons
We feel
You need to look at that
Overall volume
The sheer volume of data generated at the edge today
Is Mass
And it's grown exponentially
Thunder prediction
Stitched it up Spotify 75% of the Enterprise data by the year 2022 and it's up 10% today
Active again based on the amount of data
It is just
Too expensive to move everything to the cloud more activities and analytics needs to be done at the edge
And then Speed most important
The ability to make a decision
Right there at the edges
Critical
This is autonomous car
If a destron suddenly walks in front of the car
For the until the car hit the brakes
Too late
That decision needs to be done FBI
Aside from
Cars what are customers doing it is
What are you seeing
He actually seemed quite a bit of work done but just recently finished up some research with Forester
They basically took and looked at some of the iot enabled use cases
In ones where we're ready to go
Security surveillance
No doubt number one in the highest General use case
They're also starting to see a big traction and in track and Trace
NV Energy Management
Awesome
So what does Dell Technologies offer
For those looking
We've come to the market with very specific purpose
Stilt Edge devices for iot
In the form of an iot embedded PC
As well as in a Gateway product
We also have an incredible range of
A servers
Hyper-converged solution
Scale Computing I can meet a wide range of needs
Axilla
So where can boats go
To learn more
If I know more information your listeners can come to Dell Technologies. Com
4 / iot
Teresa Forrester report I mention as well as find out about their growing portfolio of edge Prada
Everyone
Welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is
And today's guest
Is Dominique
Do you know
Who is CTO at
Everything
How are you
Thanks for having me on the show
I'm super glad you're here and we should probably take it off
What
Everything is
Sure everything is in identity
See provider for old Kansas
But in particular CPT apparel
Luxury goods
Food products
Essentially provide a unique web identity
For each of these products
These identities can be used for all kinds of applications consumer-facing applications
Related app
Applications product authenticity and Analytics
We are going to get into that and I should tell everybody
Campbell Soup
So
I have been
Operating or aware of everything
I feel like you were
You guys were very early in the
Cuz I think there's a lot of
So what have you learned
The past
2 years of doing this
After we started
Indeed will change quite a bit
Since then
We started in the space we're in today so we started really
Sinking of connecting absolutely everything
The company ever
And then
The markets that we are targeting we're not quite ready back then
We already targeting cpg
To Market Square
Interface Technologies serialization smart tax with no
Lights at the cost
But that they needed to be
So
12 the evolution of everything
We went
Two more I'd say traditional iot
Although the root Society are very matching RFID tagging items but when I say
People assume Azure iot today which is
Smart home connect
Cities
So we did that
But then it was a lot of competition in this Payson and as we were
Exploring
Let's connect
Tag sayings
Started
Cost of tags
Cost of circulation
Nosal generating consumer demands for more transparency more information about the brand stats
We're working with
And so all of that actually
Made it possible for us to rely on our initial objective
Okay tender questions here
You guys are
Using
RFID tags
And let's talk about how the cost of changed over
Because
100% up to date on where things used to be in where they are now
Yeah so we don't only use RFID
Agnostic
The technology song
Or even LT1 devices
For your question specifically about RFID tags there was always this Holy Grail
$0.05
Fertagyl or less
Many analysts promise
This actually didn't materialise for real until
Probably one
One and a half year ago
4 hours ID
Where the prices when actually Dlow
5 Stanton and even even
Close to 1:17 in Massapequa
For other transponder technology such as the NFC for instance took a little bit longer
4 North massive volumes
It's about 10003 order to reach $0.05
Which really unlock
Launch number
It sure does I remember when
50 Cent
And then you were like value items
So it sounds like
Better standard
Switch deals
Obvious
What's happening
Absolutely standardization
For my scale adoption and for really reaching the trillions and that
Darren I'm really excited
Part of the standard that didn't make much noise yet but I think we make a lot of noise in the future you probably know the one
This one's a barcode is actually not accessible to
Consumers are not accessible on the internet and the web
With the gs1 digital link standard that was released last August
You know have a way of sterilizing
Product identities
Open urls
Dtrl sardana
Crates
To put into charcoals NFC tags are old Kansas
Two dimensional data carriers
So that standard is basically turning the good old one barcode
Talk about before this year
Digital scale
Market
And lots of Pilots are happening would be friends now
Behind you digitally standard
What is a diplomat look like
Chevrolet
Network agnostic
Pakistan
How does this work in
The first thing you want to reach is sterilization because
Look up the CPD markets are appearing more cats or or food market
We haven't reached their ization at my scale with serialization come
Large number
When you're at the genetic level
Did you pick up a product
CBD products
You have an identification of this product
It's usually taking the phone with the 1D barcode
UPC or Ean
Kittens as their cold today
Do you have in your hand
The salad
Identify the class of product
Sol de Janeiro
Identifiers
Civilization
To be able to identify dicm you have in your hands
Each item has a different number has a different address
Because it enables a large number of before
We're talking
Trillium
Yeah
To reach 1 trillion
Slightly ambitious goal is to reach 1 trillion
Depends who you ask why did you have to CT or tomorrow
The CTO would like to reach it as soon as possible but I also know that one trillion date
The point is this
Is a very very hard
Manage and I also know it's not going to happen overnight
This could be possible
Exactly
Okay
Look at that
Cuz I am curious what kind of technology and what kind of resources you're going to need
Support battalion
But in the meantime
Let's go back
How this works oh no
How does that work
Put the tag on
Packaging to it is
Coming out of the store
No seriously she is not entirely new you during your has mass Concerta sational on expensive items
Swiss watches are certain dictionary items had certification for a 4-1 ready and I think a break
Two in the past few years
Ization truly accessible
Two-way Biden
So what to do with everything is that every item gets a URL you need your else know what that means is that true
You can interact with the API of this thing so every single thing religious an API
Applications much more easy
This identity was not
Also means that we can
Put this web identity into
Tags or data carriers
You can put this identity
Very easy
QR codes are NFC tags
Which allow consumers to scan them very very easy
Same thing with your culture
IOS camera
Charcoals with your ass out of the box
So just by changing this
Identigene to sterilize identity
API integration
From Beyond the supply chain
All right so let's talk about what that means
I think you have one with a
Yeah that's at the princess in one week
Leaders India
And they have
Cruising demand from consumers
Just like fresh food into
Is really under pressure from consumers
To provide full transparency so
Star Trek
Daisy being able to identify
Solomon
Kiss at The Bachelor
And to provide information
The consumers in a way that's really fairly accessible
So that they can read you know where the silo
Comes from
Teach anywhere
Was first put in water
When does Siloam was moved from the river
When the song was harvested
Exactly which way the silent hiding in the Junior
To the store so you can learn alot about it
Do consumers actually scan their items
I don't know if I'm going to scan every single item
That's what
Trying to figure out what the consumer
Into
How can this help Beyond
Yes I'm in your urine marking
Is there any interesting cuz I would tend to rewrite I'm not going to go to the store and scan every single item
I think I'm certain items We Care a lot more than others
Princes
Fresh food spacer
Just kidding. Seafood space where much more inclined to
You want to know what we're eating
There are several studies that that show that people are
Honda brands
Lodi public staff that was
The customers would switch to a brand that is more transparent
Then another brand
Story story but it's a big party
I don't think we would
Ashley
Can of Coke for incense
However
Kolkata
Is one of our customers in
News can you would be surprised
Cruising
In Europe in the US
Nathan Marcus
Sorry you very very present
Every transaction Millet days on a mobile phone goes through a door key or code
You should also now changing the US in Europe
Beyond marketing
I feel like it would be really interesting
Lettuce for example
So that seems like a place where we might see something like this have benefits outside of
Gamification War chest
Making me feel good about where my stuff came from
Absolutely
SKS
Bacterial rash
The same kind of problem setting these food safety
Food recalls field marketing are are great examples
Today when we were a food out the trash
Much more effective
Ic1 brands we worked with
Angry calls and icons mentioned their names.
Stop that was saying
Before
Truservice ation and to the use of online services you like everything
So that's that's one thing
Safety in Germany products safety
I think it was a lot of internal use cases
Luxury items
Luxury brands have
3 big problems
Two big ones are
Counterfeit
The concert is I think we all know damn those are the items that are being copied by
Play sakhi sterilizing the products and
Tracing
Food near life
Psycho
3D helps fighting counterfeit products
Bactrim
Are Goods that are actually
But produced
Illegally in the Factories at the luxury brand store or employee
Usually at night
So having a unique identity web-enabled
And let's go back to that the broader Trend here
So take me to the world
Where I have
Every single items
Sweaters
Can of soup
What is this mean
Krumdieck tissue level is means
You'll be able to see me
They appear
Here and there usually with
Message apps
Teaching two steps
Where is here you be able
How to trace them much more accurately to know where they are to know who is
Using products
And also
I think obviously we need to
Interaction mechanism
I don't think you when I would like the world where we have to scan
Every single item we buy
Cpg
I think we will see some very interesting evolutions
Is that you see with Frontier between
Uni connect
Products
Erasing step-by-step you have today things like printed Electronics
Prince
NFC tags
Scale
Slayer Inc
You can actually in bed
These layers of things into a product label
Becomes an NFC tag
You also have things like that tree free Bluetooth
Partner we work with you capable of doing see my printed battery
Stag's head very low cost
So you can read Emagine today luxury products having
Tomorrow probably
Different kind of CPU processor
So I actually have
And I don't know
It's pretty awesome
Right now the world seems to be very focused on
Market to me
It doesn't
If I had a Bluetooth
I would want it to be
Let me know if
At best go to website but usually it's asking me to download
Apps
Marketing
And to me this just seems like
Colossal waste
Really good Technologies
Curious if we just have to get through this marketing first step
I totally agree with you and I think this is the first step in the water capable
Quitting today in disguising his printed Electronics tax or identities
Interaction between
Fencing
Yep
Coming very quickly when we can do that
I think you've become a lot more compelling
Consumer standpoint
Imagine when you were with your hands
Temperature Wisconsin
Alerting you when when you're actually walking
For too long in the polluted area
That's far away anymore ice
Racino printed Electronics combined with
I was sensing
Rosie battery-free
Consumer standpoint is largely marketing
Provenance
Critical condition
I think tomorrow is much more exciting YouTube
What is my thing have this type of identity
I wonder about
Is there a point
Which we should be communicating with people who buy this stuff
There's information that can be cleaned
Possibly about them or from them from
Everyday products
I think we'll have to explain that there is a active
Tagging deer
Semi-active tags
Explain that only for from an interaction standpoint
If it's not the visual tag then how do you know where you can interact with your with your back
And I think Dan yes
Define a language to be able to explain to Consumers the type of information that
Deer items are gathering
Russian golden mask
Challenge
Make it accessible truly developing language that people can understand
No cost to their privacy versus benefits
For that to happen we really need to understand
Sort of answered a lot of the questions I have around
This big macro question which is
A trillion sensors
What are some of the things we need to think about
1D sing that I
Promoted throughout my career is
How to connect these things into decreasing networks things that are happening
Intranet
I'm dedicating my research career
Might my business
Ensuring that is not the case and that things are really connected to the internet
Things are really connected to the web
As if we want things to happen at large-scale this is what needs to happen we don't we shouldn't think of coyotes
Cynthia's
One phone
1iota
We really have to sync up
Interconnecting two different things over the internet in order to web
More down-to-earth Sweeney
Technology sweet rolls in particular
If we consider
Banks that don't have access to
Normal source of power
Battery free technology
Harvesting energy
Completely unprecedented
Just one trillion
Unique something already very very hard to handle for a database
Yet alone
Flow of these identities
Reconsidering
Trillions and trillions of datapoint
Setting on the dating site we still have a way to go to be able to Leverage
Today to streams.
It does that mean we need different
Database Brown
Is it mean to be different
Ways of handling streaming data I don't know what the
Json Analytics
Stevenson's Lake machine learning can help to analyze massive amounts of data
Indian Summer
Just for friends
I think the good news
Billions 2
Trillions in one go
Technology is evolving
Interesting ways
Excellent
Alright.
Thank you so much for coming on the show today
Thank you
That's it for this week thanks so much for listening and remember if you'd like more iOS
Sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot. Cam will see you next week