Hey everyone welcome to the 222nd episode of The Internet of Things podcast
This is your house
Stacey Higginbotham
Kevin tofel
And we have a stupendous show for you today we're going to talk about the smaller Echo Show
Little bit about
Google assistant and what it can do
SmartThings Samsung SmartThings released
Malware that
Bricking iot devices
And we've got some cool use cases for
Smart factories are coming to the US
There's a new Raspberry Pi
And
I found a watch that's really smart and then Kevin tells me he's already had
So
All of this
Plus a little bit more including
Our Guest this week who is
Comedy stem the CEO of Monarch bio
She's going to be talking about
How the world of
Clinical testing is influencing
How we think about wearables and medical devices for the future
We're also going to hear from our sponsor Dell technology
She's all about the open-source Edge
Foundry
So
Gear Up
Get ready
Here we go starting with a message from another one of our sponsors nordics
Nordic semiconductor is launching an exciting new cellular iot prototyping platform this August
Nordic thingy 91 cellular iot prototyping platform is perfect for building a
Applications using lte-m
Nb-iot GPS different sensors including hygiene
Accelerometers air quality in altitude and many more the Nordic thingy 91 comes with
Application pre-installed and with a free SIM card for my bases to use anywhere in the world
In addition to Cellular that stinky 91 has an nrf52 8:40 multi-protocol SOC
I'm bored so you could build exciting hybrid applications
At Nordic thingy 91 will be available in August and it is
The most exciting thing in cellular right now.com
It looks fun
I kind of do too I mean I like to Tinker with these kind of things so
Well that's the Nordic thingy 91 but I have
The Amazon
Tiny thingy which is the
Echo Show 2
Released
Not with much fanfare
What's released this week
Actually so it's a $90 5 in
Smaller Echo Show that supposed to go in your
Nightstand is probably the ideal location for this it's got a
Camera
You can shut her that cameraman
He is got the microphone
It does everything else that
An Echo Show does like tok
People
And show your
I don't know certain certain
Certain
It will not show your nest security cameras but it will show your ring
Pro doorbell in
I believe still your Arlo's so
But yes
Alright so this looks like a direct response
Monster Google
Messed up I was like I don't even know what it's called
Yeah
And you have that so what do you think
I do have I have the police because of Google home however I guess you can't open Desktop now
Mine has a 7-inch display if I recall correctly sitting right in front of me with the microphone off
We actually have two of them I wanted the office I have
One in the
Bedroom
There is
No camera on it
Which I kind of like
But with Echo Show V
Even though it has a camera
You can shut her that you said which is
Import
Having
Yeah I mean we have a manual shutter on the Lenovo smart display the tonnage one that is down on our kitchen island
And it's usually shuddered Hemingway
Need to hang out with other cameras
In that area anyway for security reasons and such but
I think it's important
It's a smarter than hooking up at the camera and I think
Honestly every
If I saw the camera should have a shutter at this point
I agree
The original Echo Show
Right so the question is really
Should I buy the
Who should buy
Well I mean if you're on the Madam a platform and
You're in the market for a small display that's not too expensive 90 bucks is reasonable
Yeah I think it's
Worth it
Do you like your eggs smaller
Viceroy
Baidu
I think it does a little bit more
Then the
Devices unless something has changed like YouTube TV iOS
Stream on this thing
Sometimes as I'm working and walking to go watch a soccer match or something
The services that I use may not be fully supported on the Echo Show us that's about the best way to say
Fairy taipei
All right
But if you're all in on Amazon
You don't want to watch a lot of YouTube
You know what the other thing is I will say the Google
My favorite thing about my Google displays actually
The photos of shows
And
With Amazon do you have the option of storing your photos in it
Storage place
Does my phone automatically
Google photos which is
Is awesome and so everything I get
Not everything but anything that's in a certain
File folder
Basically there's a picture
In there that face matches to my
My daughter
My family or friends
Pops right up on my Google photos
Right I do the same thing I actually use a custom photo album that are just nothing but pictures of Norm the dog
Works great
Even if you're looking
IPhone user like even are both using Android right now
Maybe you're not tied to Google photos some people do actually use Google photos for
The free storage on iOS
You not likely uploading from IOS to Amazon's total Locker
Alright so
Let's talk about the new smart
Kiss
Samsung
Basically launched a bunch of new stuff
Breathing
They're not terribly expensive cuz I think he's a really aim towards like
You don't have a smart home yet you want like a store
Couple things to get right what do you start with you obviously
You get the SmartThings Hub
Now they have a new $90 SmartThings camera
Which of the Wi-Fi camera that have a
$18 Wi-Fi smart plug
And a $10 smart bulb
Which
Might be
Bluetooth is actually sick me so you do neither the hub for that
And that makes sense
By the way you can get the 3rd Generation SmartThings Hub
Amazon
Yes it's relatively cheap
So
Yay I will say for anybody contemplating SmartThings
It's not the most user-friendly platform very powerful you can do a lot especially with automations but there is
Learning curve
They're so
Be aware it's fun I like it
I have smart
There's a lot of people are happier than them and I don't
Think they're wrong obviously they're happy they're happy that's fine
I find smart things to be very sensible as well you could actually
A non-supportive
Device on either find or
Build your own driver to make it work
Door device Handler is what they call them
So we can figure out
Programmer you can do a lot more with us than you can with I think the other hubs on the market so for everyday people I ate
Know that the problem that
I guess I have is that we kind of stop recommending wink as that user friendly hub
Yeah disposal
But wait
Wait we just got an email from
Scary
Yasso carry
In a very sunny
Set us
Wink
Is alive
Dirty sprite
Link appears to be in I got this just a few hours ago so I can shut off an email to the week
People
Got an email from
Wing said they were reaching out to long-time customers
To purchase the wink Hub 2
And he expected to be. But lo and behold it was not we went to check in
Yep
No they have actually a lot of it or Wing It branded products available now
If you're interested I'll probably buy them from the wing site the wreck I know you can buy
Some of these devices on Amazon
And even though it's sold by
Amazon from wink the
How to raise $150 for some reason on Amazon
Wow is supposed to 99
Yes as opposed to 99 so
Interesting bit to this news is we've been wondering for
How many year
Just cuz we haven't heard anything
Newsworthy out of Lincoln
That long
Are they still open the business
Sending that still making products in the answer is yes
Yes cuz it may have been out of stock
We'll see
We also get software updates for the Hub recently though
So who knows
We'll keep an eye on wink
Maybe
Gyarados
How he feels
All right
Okay
That's
Good news
Wink
Sarcasm
Oh that's
It's actually
Been a couple episodes where we talk about are needed to talk about a raise awareness of a
I'm making a malware or any kind of security issues
And
This one is really scary that happened this week it's
Called Cyrax and it is basically breaking iot devices
The only way to
Fix
This if you are infected
Instalike
Kohler install the device firmware which
Most people don't have access to the front of the devices to do that number one
Number to the probably don't know how to do with that
So
Ice not good
What's really scary is what we started
Finding out
We just came from and
Who's responsible
Do you want to talk about that yeah so
This is kind of like my nightmare this is like a teenage prank
Real they tried to hack her back and it's a 14 year old boy
We basically we're creating a world where 14 year old boys kid
Wreak havoc in
We all know 14 year old boys in
You're going to grow into lovely people most of them but
Very few people are
Discerning members of society I don't know how else to put that
He built this and he's like
Hey
I think I'm going to add more features and in
I don't know if he's going to turn into a business you think that's going to happen
I would hope not I would hope nobody would
Son that business he said
Project
Kind of a joke but now it's a full-time project
That's scary
Yeah
So guys
We're building a world where
We're getting the tools of Destruction to 1400 Boyson
14 year olds are going to take it
Boys
Some girls
You know
That's what teenagers do
They make poor decisions
It's not what I did I did some packing when I was that age but it was mostly
Changing the names of characters video games to me and my friends like
Good night so we would play a video game instead of dr. J and Larry Bird play basketball that would be me and my next door neighbor
Would be showing on the screen with our names do you know
I know I mean it
It's not so much
Alright well maybe one day we'll get
Microphones throughout her house that will detect
Teenage boy hacking
But until then
Schools and hospitals are
M4
Weird
Weird stuff
So they're using them to detect
Kodak code
Aggression
Which I understand because of all of the
Terrible tragedies we've had it in public places where somebody just goes off in people
Loser lives needlessly
But it gets back to that
Cost of privacy and then do you want to be walking through Hospital knowing that you're being listened to the whole time
Maybe you won't even know to be honest it off if you disclose to you
I think disclosure and something like this is important
And
I promise to delete that
Recordings
And some sort of independent audit to make sure that that's actually have
Go to think about things again we're dealing in schools not necessarily hospitals
Teenagers and teenagers say a lot of stupid stuff
And they should have the ability to say that stupid stuff and not
I agree
So this is on the scary side
Hydrate and
Here is
The algorithm they are using to detect aggression
Isn't peer-reviewed it's not it's not really proven so
Now you can set it off by
Again doing all kinds of things that teenagers actually off
Often do like
Scream
Or
And clearly this isn't 100%
Foolproof either that's the other thing that I noticed I think there's a three-year trial
Happy Valley Hospital in Ridgewood New Jersey
After
For years they were facing out
Because
You're a lot of things like somebody speaking loud with set it off work
Or somebody slamming a cash register in the cafeteria with Set It Off
So they tweaked it to make it less sensitive and then they missed a very agitated person screaming and pounding on the desk so
It's clearly not foolproof
People are weird they can go from 0 to 60 in like no time
On the flip side
Seriously
Microphone
Always on microphones being used possibly not transparently
End
Or something that may not even be
Researchers at the University of
Washington
Announced last week that they detect
Heart attacks of the breathing associated
With heart attacks
Figure it out
When I tried it on and
Amazon Echo
So the idea is they envision
Some sort of acolyte device or microphone base device that could listen for this in people's homes and then
Quickly send help
There's a heart attack
Now
That's in my opinion
82 invasive and B
That's
Problem is
I think already solved with wearable
I would agree with you on that
I would say though that having a $40 device like an echo. In someone's nursing home
For example
Detecting that sort of thing
To be more cost
Effective
Sure sure you move to Washington State and I are defending University of Washington
That's exactly what's happening I would not want this and I would be curious though if I
I were someone who has had a history of heart attack
Would that change my
Acceptance of some
And would a robust
Data
Privacy
Policy I really don't know
And I don't know either but I think about it
People who have no history of heart disease or they
Suffered a heart attack already
They probably don't mind
Shelling out money from Modern devices that probably do a better job
Well but what about insurance so Insurance could look this and I could be like
The nice thing about insurance
Tactics online
Aggression
Detection
But if you could prove that
And then only the inside so not the metadata itself but just the inside of this person is having
Heart attack
If there were enough Protections in place I would
But there would have to be in
The places we are not there yet is a pipa
Stefano
So did you see what you can do with sound
And
Also chair
Okay
What's the best smart batteries the u.s. is home to two
You smart
Schneider Electric last week
They have a factory in Lexington
Chucky that builds load centers and safety switch
Things that are outside your house
Well in an industrial settings there outside
But they control the electricity going in in
Out to various
Places
In Philly
That was a terrible
But that's what they do
And last week we had the CIA
On the show
Hey if you miss that
But what they're doing with their smart Factory is there turning into a showcase for their
Ecostruxure
Products which is building management software
It ties into
Factory automation software in all of this other stuff
Cohere sustainability
I think it's interesting
They've got
Couple other smart factories when in France
Mexico
And they seen actually things like a 20% reduction in meat
Repair on their critical equipment
They've eliminated 90%
Their paperwork or limited paperwork by 90%
So
Some of those things are
The investment to actually implement this may seem like a lot but when you start looking at the ROI
I think the payback is free
I think it's this is the investment it takes to Lake
Quit prepping
That's a cost but
If the value that sits on top of that is amazing
Alright the other smart Factory was announced this week
It is Erikson they are going to
Builder first fully automated smart Factory in the US unlike the Schneider Electric Factory this is going to be built
That one
And it is going to build Advanced antenna system radios so this is like
Those are fun
So Erickson doesn't have a location I guess they're still negotiating with various Economic Development groups my guess is
Cool your place
They also did announce the new R&D site which just happens to be where you used to live
Austin
Austin actually has a lot of 5G research AT&T and Intel have a research center there
About lots of Wireless Engineers they're so this makes sense
The point here
Smart factories
They're all the rage this week
Or maybe Tunis smart Factory
Tune-ups
Raspberry Pi that is
Powerful
This is the
Raspberry Pi
They're saying it's designed for industrial iot
Locations
It probably can be used for that but of course I was on campus with my comp sci class and
I saw this news
And we're not
Where does Prius
But we want to buy one of these
Just for
Code projects another little
Efforts
It's got a quad-core arm cortex a72 process
Running at 1.5 gigahertz that's crazy I think
Well my last MacBook Reddit that
Right right I took a look to see cuz of course everybody ask me when I told him about the snuza what's different from the Raspberry Pi already have
Eeyore
Are all the runs
The price starts at $35 get you a gig of RAM
You also have options 45 and $55 to get 2 or 4 gig of RAM which
That's great for like for the type of things we would use it for
Also it's USBC for the power which is awesome
Mitsubishi
Give me speed Mini
And they have
Added
Added one but now has two HDMI
Put all of the mini HDMI port
So you can run up to 4k on
Two simultaneous HDMI displays
Yeah and that's really interesting for the industrial iot
Cuz you could start
Play Machines to set up sensors
You could actually put this in and monitor that information from the sensors
You can run applications on this that are
Fairly sizable
Hey 35 bucks
Or maybe 50
The other thing is from an industrial standpoint of me
Like most consumers, just buy the pie and use it to make it like a desktop computer or Linux Boxes Etc
Having the
IO pins
And the ability to add okash several dozen
Options of other radios other sensors
So on
Really
I think it speaks to the industrial Market meet this that's exactly what we used for
Increase in the clouder are hacking diabetes project we had it up
NRF radio hat
That's it on to our pie so you can so many choices
Yeah and
I'm assuming that there will be ruggedized cases for
That is the other thing
Papaya system
You can't just leave that in it
Industrial eyeglass
Yeah I thought cases I didn't buy rugged I so I'm supposed to know for 5 or 10 bucks out he's in case my in
Arbonne rep near my hand this act as a clear case so I can see
The parts a new Land Rover
It would
And then I saw this device and I got super excited
This is
The Parlor
Smartwatch
What day does
This is
It basically tells you
Where you are at
In your day or if you should exercise or maybe not train a little
Train too hard
It combines like your sleep
Your workout
All of this to help you optimize your
Workouts and I like this because
I left my Fitbit charge 3
Which is what I'm current
You know I love counting steps I love all that but
It doesn't actually tell me
How to change to
It does actually
Every few hours to get up
For the most part it doesn't feel super smart it just feels like a
A data logging
Device
This will smart
So I thought this was cool
Yeah it's not terribly expensive either it's $230
Pair device play ignite
GPS that has GPS perfectly Runner
Spike etcetera and so on
Your point about the actual smartness of using the data analyzing and giving you
Actionable information is is key
It's not the first watch to do that
And I say that because I have a Garmin
Forerunner 245 on my wrist right now that I've had for about six weeks
Pretty much does the same thing I might become more value from that then
I would have expected instead of just telling you for example
How many hours of sleep you got an
What the different stages were in the time in those stages
It actually has a feature called body battery in
Basically if your body battery is 100 you're fully charged and you want to go train hard
The run marathon today is the day to do Etc
It does that and also reduces the body battery based on how many steps you taken and
Your heart rates at the day and your email your workouts and so on
I'm so it's actually
Is useful Durbin days are like
I think I'm okay to go do a long run
I left the wash my car so so I think I will rest up today
This is highly informal
But I think it'd be interesting
Is 2
Having now
Experiment with the body battery
A few weeks
I would like without you
Looking at your body battery
To guesstimate where it's
At the same point in time each day right guesstimate where it's at
And write that down and
Then check it
See how
On point because I'm curious like
You may feel awesome and it's like
So do you want to do that
I can do that and in fact
Before I had this feature I would just go off of my
Feel-Rite
And they were times when I felt great and I go say I'm going to go do an 8 Mile
Loop over around the
On the trail near my house
And yet
I get two or three into it and like what was I thinking today my body is not responding well
Right so it's
Butts
Experiment of one
And if anyone else has anything like
Just because
Sometimes I worry that
Their influence
Computers
You're trusting the algorithm for sure
Yeah without a doubt put Garmin and polar I've used both their devices before I still have
Stop order
Smartwatch
They've been working towards this with different
Indices in
And such a to be honest
I
Fuel
Just for my experience that there
Worth trusting
Interesting algorithms
For those of us with a
How to say who are too lazy to clean their house but really this is for anyone
Google Assistant Canal support
Control robot mop
They could control Roomba vacuums for
A while
Yeah but
Is a way for developers to add support to the smart mop that are out there
Aaron boster iRobot makes some of those and others do as well
So what Google has done is basically
Extended what the vacuum class was for for developers to make skills and such
Tamara has a mop device type so
I don't have one of these I was kind of wish I did but
Stop tickling very well
I'm sure they're better now but the last one I tested it
It's not on
But that was like the first generation brother
You could have come a long way by now
All right
So
It feels like we're at that moment in our show
When it is time
It is time for the iot podcast hotline
What's the fifth largest coyote pad portfolio with a world of pharaoh provides a proven iot platform that doesn't risk
Your brand
A pharaoh customers have experienced as much as an 80% reduction in time-to-market and tenex higher activation
Should learn more at a pharaoh
Dot IO
All right
This month on the iot pipe
Hotline
If you call us at 512-2623
We are giving away a wise sensor pack
In camera
So yes you could buy this for 40 bucks but
You can also maybe when it
So I say give us a call and
Maybe we'll also answer your
I have a question
This week's question comes from
Bobby
Let's hear it
Hi my name is Bobby and my wife I just bought a house
And
I have many other questions to the other recommendations
Now is
Leak detector sensors
I was given a Honeywell lyric
I want
Free and like it that
Was looking at buying more
I was just
Turn signal recommendations
For other ones
Thoughts where the
Samsung SmartThings
But I didn't know if there was any other Leak Detectors that you guys recommended
Thank you very much
I was so excited because you have already in your hot little hands
My favorite lie detector
Which is kind of expensive
But the Honeywell
Lyric Wi-Fi water leak and freeze detector is
Power device and I liked it so much because it's accurate but it's also got this long
Entail
The wraps around pipes
It detects
They said leaks and fries
And I think it's just so much more effective than waiting for like a
Puddles
Reach ascensor
So it feels like you get more coverage
But it does come at a price and that price is 80 bucks for that
Which is
A lot
And it only works with the
Echo ecosystem it does not work
Assistant
So that is the one you already have
I'm going to recommend if you are hardcore interested in leak detection
To go with one of the smart
Home
Whole-home leak
Detection model
They are
Receita
The cheaper one is the flow
Buy Moen that is a $500 device
What you do
Yeah but
What it does is
It measures the water flowing through your pipes and uses an algorithm
To detect
Changes in water pressure it will detect not just like catastrophic
At least it'll also detect slow leaks or things like a toilet
Flapper the
Not secure not
Not slapping
I don't know how to describe it
You got to replace
The flapper if you hear the water running all the time and actually
Uses a lot of water
Who knew
And this is awesome because it automatically turns off
So
Is it expensive
Yes
Is it possible you might get a discount from your insurance
Baby
But it's like
No but the key differences is not just a detector it can actually shut the water off and you're not going to find
That was just a sensor let me know lots of sensors that will
To detection
If you're not home and a detective
Bass Pro
So the other option in this category is
It's the same thing this actually needs a plumber to install it the other one does too
When you're messing with your water main you should
Recommendation
The thing is $700
It is a company that was spun out of Belkin it also was created in partnership with
Plumbing company called uponor
So
It's
Pricier
It has
Quality Brands behind it I've never tested
Any of these devices because
Well because now I've moved into a rental house and beforehand
They weren't actually ready for testing so these are relatively new
But
Don't know how you feel.
What about the buoy folks
Oh yes because you're already the Honeywell ecosystem earlier this year because March
How do you spell actually
It's no longer honey that's resideo is be smart home
Company
It's behind the Smart Home
Honeywell gear
Securus still Honeywell the company making it now is called resideo
So resideo bought Bowie
Which was an MIT lab space company that also made
A whole home.
Vice
Now
It is unclear exactly what huh
That they talked about making their sensor leak detection system smarter
But
You cannot buy the buoy system
So
I don't know what to tell you
Right
Venusaur is other non whole-home options I mean there's there's a number on the market that are probably less
Expensive in the lyric
Yes but we're really flogging a whole-home real
So if you want to do it right and have a budget for it I think that's the way to go
But if not I know you can do it for a lot less
You just want to look for ones like the lyric that have
Extendable cable to
Improve your coverage of leak detection
So
One option that also has an extendable sensor cable
A freezing Rod what
Accenture coverage
Is the D-Link
WiFi water
It's a little cheaper it's 60 bucks from D-Link as a
Close to the 80 bucks for
Honeywell version
It's also Wi-Fi
And
Performs the same function
I can't remember if I've tried this or no
But with this one it doesn't have an integrated siren
In the Honeywell
Definitely
That is because you have to like
Disconnected taxes stop the siren
Listen to my problems
This is kind of
But
Really useful
When there's actually
Your house
Let's find when you're testing and leaking things left and right but really good when
There's actually
Those are options there's also
Without the cable unit for 20 bucks you can get a Samsung SmartThings water leak
Detection sensor that you just Stickney
Troublesome spot
Grandma just has contacts on the bottom of it
Not any cable dirty like that
So in there in there several of those
I mean tons of companies make out
If you buy one of those a lot of them are cheaper because they use as a BRZ Wave radio
And you're going to need a hug
So just bear that in mind if
But their battery life will be amazing
Has to actually be
So
Keypad
Lots of options
Many options
For my money if I were doing it all over again
I would probably do the Smart Home
Whole home detection but I would also before I buy it call my insurance company and be like
Hi
Is there a way to get a discount if I do this
All right
That hopefully answers your question Bobby or gives you
A lot of options in
You might be overwhelmed by them that we're sorry
Kiefer hauling and everyone else please give us a call five one two
623-7424 and you will be entered to win
DIYs sensor pack
Camera
All right
Now I would love for everyone to stay tuned
For our guest
Who is, destem
The CEO of Monarch bio
She is going to be talking about how we can
It's actually relevant to what we talked about earlier because she's talking about how we can certify
Wellness and medical devices
Is accurate
So these algorithms that were relying on like
Body battery
They would actually look at that and see
How accurate is Porsche in a peer-reviewed
So she's going to talk about why we need that
The future of medicine and a lot more
Stay tuned for her
The first
IMessage from this we sponsor
Dell Technologies
Hey everyone we are taking a quick break from The Internet of Things podcast for a message from our sponsor this we sponsor
Is Dell Technologies and I have Jason Sheppard who is CTO of iot and Edge adult
Technology
So json
Must we talk about Dell Technologies efforts it was around Edge X Foundry
So let's start off with an update about where that is and why it's so important
And we took a look at the market actually back in 2015 and
We're looking at all the platforms that were proliferating
And saw this problem
You're shaping where there was this need to have more flexibility and how Solutions were deployed taking the
Cloud native principles at UC
Cloud architectures in extending them to the edge where you have the ability to kind of rapidly deploy different functions around
You're going to common element
Ajax for iot as what what Android did for mobile
Anybody to create a Marketplace
Commercial value add
Around just enough in terms of open apis to bind together all the inherently
Heterogeneous
Components within iot we architect that it based on feedback from a bunch of Partners and customers then put it into the underneath
Open source as a project
That was the initial goal
Come up with the right architecture
Collaborate
Neutral open sores and then once it gets going
Then you use that
As a vehicle to create
Commercial value-add on top of it
Can you imagine the internet without opening our ability to Ajax is really about creating that open
Baseline that then you can
Start building value
Without Reinventing the wheel
Excellent
All right so what is Dell strategy with Ajax
And how does that relate to your openedge stack
Yes our strategy is
Get that going but no
Foundationally we're about
Creating consistent infrastructure I always say we build the guts or Partners can bring the glory we want that's open ecosystem
Attached to that so that you can bend
Scale-out
Relationships
You can have special breed solution
Come together around a common core you will attach our Security Management tools
You can use them stand alone but menus with Ajax and them safe ati's you get the benefit
Defender neutral ecosystem
So what is the status
Imagix
We're going one now though it's going commercial
Yeah there's actually companies that are basing business models around
You a jacksepticeye attack as an example is a company that's creating a redbad model around offering commercially supported
Versions of it then you have companies like redis redis Edge is a database optimized for time series data but then they saw
That's also got support for tensorflow
Analytics Dave made a decision token
How to plug into a TV
Replace the existing database in there what's credits if you'd like what Pros out there publicly talking about using Ajax there's a
Initiative sponsored by Intel
Downloader
Going up very quickly of April it was 2500 downloads
You're made 4500 a miniature starting a ramp so we're definitely seeing that ramp it out in the market
Excellent and where can we go to find out more about Dell Technologies
And the open Edge
Dell Technologies. Com coyote
A good starting point and then there's been some links off of there to go learn more
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham
And today's guest is
Comedy stem who is CEO and founder at
Monarc bionetworks
Hi, how are you doing
Great thanks for having me sleepy
Oh I'm really excited because we're going to talk about one of my favorite
Topics which is this concept of digital snake oil
And the idea that we have
All of these companies and devices that are coming onto the market that
Say
Hey I'm going to make your life better make you healthier
As consumers we really don't have a sense of how accurate any of these are and
We don't understand what your doctor may not want her Fitbit
Random
Other data from
Connected mattress or something
So you're going to tell us a little bit about
Why things are the way they are
So let's first get started with
Your background because
It ties directly into why you founded
I think they see what I actually am
I'm from the pharmaceutical backgrounds I have been a clinical researcher
Story about 20-plus years across multiple pharmaceutical companies and Ivory
Actually execute clinical trials for the development of new treatments
And about
6 years ago I started heading up an Innovations need to figure out how could we actually
They make up a good 70
Billion dollars
And as I was doing this I realize that you know what
We do in clinical trials as we generate
And to ensure the safety and efficacy of a drug that goes out on the market
Realizes that we
Haley
Generated
In the clinic
And all of these new wearable
Sensors that are coming out the possibility of collecting data in between the clinic
Which is completely new set of data that we've never had before that could really help us understand how
Outpatient
Arguing
In between clinic visits in the context of Their Own
Look at me really
Excited about
The internet of things and all the devices but I also think
It's really important
Just having a lot of data
You actually have to
Transform it into evidence
But you can trust and that can
Julian form
Research and treatment of new drug
But also how it can
Influence
Do you use your health care is provided
So that's a super tall order let's start there cuz that seems like
The core of the issue
It sounds like it's a mix of
Hey is this device
Reliable and accurate
Consistent
Play probably across a bunch of populations
And then the other is
Is this device actually useful it
Detecting or monitoring a specific
Disease
That I don't know if there's another site
This is there
What what starts with devices
Cuz I think that's a good way to start and maybe we can use
Is we create t-shirt
Communities of people that have a condition and
Interested in
Contributing their data
And pulling it together to give better
Insight for me
So we started a network in idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis
And in ITF
The way they measure progression
A pulmonary function
Anthem company is that is divided
A parameter which is what measure is your
Pasadena
Bear
Manufacturers that develop devices that could
Actually measure that in the
Howdy
What does FDA cleared 510 K clearance they call it and basically
How do you put that
Device
Consistently measure a person's lung function in the home
That's all it tells you how do you use
How do you
How do you know that
Really important
We integrate
That is
Trial
And we said we want to know
Who is
Patience can actually
Recently uses device
Accurately
A measurement that they take from the device
And the measurement of
Using an in-clinic
So I think that's really important
To make sure that we're doing trials and research to validate
Not that the device work for that it
Actually works in the context in which it
Going to be
Because these things will be used to inform decisions
And it's not
The same as he
Directions
Didn't quite work
Clinical decision on
Treatment
It really hurts
What's really important
That we validate
We integrated that device
To the trial and we measure the patient using the spirometer from the home
As well as he measured that data or week
Compared that data
The data that we generated in
And look for a strong correlation
Okay this is interesting
Because
A spirometer is actually a tool that has been
Used for
Forever
But this is an established medical device so the only new thing here was connecting it and I'm making sure that
Patients could use it accurately
In the home
Correct
Another aspect of it
Infinite
Spirometers I'm you have to do a lot of calibration
So even in clinical trials when I've used in clinics
Providence actually calibrate
And then the patient immediately
Don't give them Direct
Feedback whether they use the device right and then the data gets
Awesome
Savannah is very different than me sayings
One of my products that I really think it would be perfect for iot in the home in for medicine
Would be like a device were
When my child has
Cost
I could have her coffin to my
Amazon Echo for example and have
The AI on the device say
Oh
Is totally something you should go to the doctor right away or that sounds like
The common cold
Don't stress Jesse
I lived in fear of my daughter getting
Terrifying
But I'm a little weird
So what happens if you have an entirely new device that maybe isn't a medical device or if you want to bring some
Something like a common wearable or an Amazon Echo or something else
Into
Netty clinical testing
What my thought process look like or what needs to have
Or maybe it won't happen at all cuz that's crazy
No no no it's really important actually we're starting to introduce more of these devices into clinical trial
Because the reality is more more
Then bringing it into the doctor and saying
So what do you think of this data
Clinical trials
My experience has been right
Future right now
We need to start introducing devices and doing research
In the same way that Keras
An example of how we what I've previously done in
Introducing somebody's wearable so for example we had to study
For hemophilia
But one of the challenges with haemophilia is people accommodate to their disease
Afraid they're going to get
Bleed for this
Moving around alot
Activities and so forth and so way to measure the
The impact on the quality of life typically what we've done is me to ask questions
These are very no they're not very objective
Subjective what the patient might be
Their activity very possibly
Remind
Tasty and we actually did see a difference
Impatient
They took the treatment and they had left
Bleed
They became more confident
Actually became more active
The Weeknd
Actively measure now
That impact outside of the
In their daily life
That's a powerful way to
Did you
That is awesome and so when you were doing that how did you have to
I guess evaluate the Fitbit
Was it an actual Fitbit or what
Was it something else
When did the variety
I think it's a matter of
Visioning what you want
If you need
Really precise measurement
Often times what you'll do with your pride of validate
The measurement in an earlier trial for that
You can use it in a
Registration trial for example
But if you wanted to
So just depends on what the is it a primary endpoint of the secondary
War of the
Impact and quality of life
Singer going to use that data to
Discussion
Around getting reimbursed for that drug
Because it has a Major Impact
On the quality of life of a patient and their productivity depends on how you're going to use it
As to what grade
When you go to different devices
Tuesday
Babe I'm developing something where I'm going to encourage my
Inition
Monitor Act
Cavity in the patient and you want them to not have to go by
Xiaomi devices
You want to use something as commercially available
A commonly used
Kind of depends
That makes a lot of sense
Imagine you could cut costs and boost participation if you had something like
Hey
If you have an Apple Watch or Fitbit
You're wearing what I need
So
Exactly
And that broadens act
Participate in the trial
Which gives more diversity of patients which that makes the data more generalized
Market
Although then we have to deal with like complying
Tissues cuz I can't be the only person who's been dissatisfied with their step count
10 digit off to their kid to be like
Hey
Take this for a while
I know I'm only lying to me
But is that something people
About when they're thinking about
Medical testing
Absolutely looking at compliance and adherence
Remembering
Clinical research and clinical trials
More compliance in that than they are in the real world
Staying face to figure out okay
This is the level of
Science Theater
In the trial will be achieved
Same level
In the real world and that's why it's really important
Even after we do these trials
But we continue trial
Do things
I need a bring your own device
Wearable
Because then we really understand what happens in the context
All right so you had mentioned earlier
That clinical trials are kind of
The future of Medicine
Where were heading so I am curious with what you're doing today
Clinical trials where do you think the future of medicine is heading
At Monarch her vision is that research is integrated into
I could care
And that we have a
Early Learning health systems Dynamic and adopt
So you're not we
Have a visit with your doctor you're generating data and
Informing you
In that same way but constantly integrating Research into care
Then when learning very quickly and you Solutions are being adopted very quickly
So to give you an example
When you
Medical
Device
Is approved
It's hate another
7 years or to actually be adopted in integrated
Unbelievable right
There is a huge guy
Between when something isn't approved
An integrated is
Hair We imagine a world
Where is your console
Silly integrating Research into care
Then you're going to be able to accelerate that adoption
Inhibition
More and more clinical decisions will be very data-driven
Because
It's almost like every decision you're making as a trial of Anna
Because you've got so much data and your
And as we get two more
Personalized
And customized
Madison
That's the way we need to operate
I like it alright so
If we're moving towards this world
I know that we've been talking about what you call is regulatory grade evidence
But what else do we need it feels like
We might need our physicians to
To change a little bit
I don't know if there's much we can do his patients but
Tell me
Where the hoes
Well I think it's huge huge hole that we have right now is
With what major in
Across the US
Is digitizing all of our health records and there's been a lot of work
All of that Digital Data is
Sitting in silos
It's really important
In order for
Really GATRA bus evidence
We need to get larger pool the data and people need to share their
In a way that
For the greater good and we have to figure out how do we do that
Client way so that side to see isn't walk
As well as
That we we can have Innovations on top of that the
Spell is not the it I think we have to get over the river hold the date
Do with that data that makes the difference
We need to
Owning data to accessing data
And sharing data
So I think this is
Awesome
Except I read a story probably
Probably a couple months back about it was a CPAP machine that ensures or paying for
And
Ensures were gathering data for these connectors at machines
And they were looking to see if the patients were actually using it
And if they weren't
They work
Cutting off insurance payments for the CPAP machine rental
In one hand I get it
You don't want to pay for something that someone's night
Using
But on the other hand the patients didn't actually realize this was happening nor did their doctors
And so I think
It's good to talk about privacy
It's even better to talk about in the context of
How we're going to pay for things and how who's going to have access to data
Not just
To build a business but even to make kind of
Care decisions
I don't know if
Got any ideas around this but
Feel like
Feel like we've got to do something before we start implementing
Too much data
Into the medical Realm
I see it's really important
Uber transparent on who has access to the data
Can you use an interesting example cuz my mother actually using the CPAP machine
And she's well aware
That
She doesn't
Benefits get removed or reduced or whatever
I put it on for a minimum of 5 hours and then I take it off
I like my teacher that is so that you know you don't you don't get hurt
But anyway
Commission using it for those for 5 hours
Got their measure
Be more accurate than I think she would have
I don't disagree with you that you have
There needs to be transparency there needs to be understanding
That's happening as a result of
That's fair cuz in some cases like I might have no problem
Donating my blood testator
Echocardiograms or whatever data that might be interesting
Josiah
I might say yeah I totally want you to have this data for research
But I would be
Considerably at giving that data to an insurance firm or navy to my Corporation
As part of a Wellness Plan
I think the raw data
Is something that it's not
It should be protected because
This kind of data can be used to infer some
Crazy things in overtime will make more correlations and we will be able to infer a lot more from that day.
End
I don't think there's a way to put that Genie back in the bottle once it's out
Yeah I would agree with you and I think you know if we just be really careful
When did Jada goes in 18
Verde.
Should have the right to deter
Hammond where it goes what's interesting is when you're really sick with a life-threatening or chronic debilitating
You're more than willing
Archer view that data
1G distillate in Hope
Start a treatment will be developed for yourself or for your your children
You just that you had really great care
A lot of people would say
I had really great
I'm going to donate a bunch of money
And what about doctors and medical professionals because I know that I come to my daughter and I'll be like here's my
My data is there like
Please take it out of my
My face I don't want it
How do we get there
Clinically validated but how do we get there
And give them the tools to actually be able to use this information in providing care
Yeah
Synthesizing for research is really important because peer-reviewed validated
Sources of information right now or peer review.
That the way to
Delivered the information
Time in a way that there YouTube
They're super busy overworked and when
Come in with a dataset they're not
Many of them want to
But
They don't have
What time is the currency that we have to figure out
Is an increased by the
Introduction
Starting those are two important things to think about is
Looking forward delivery evidence through publication vincere review
Into that it's integrated into workflow
Awesome
All right
Thank you so much for coming on the show today I feel like
I've learned a lot and I'm actually
Cautiously optimistic about
Advancing Medical Care
Incredible
With both technology and medicine and patients themselves being more empowered to be part of the
Definition
That's it for this week thanks so much for listening and remember if you'd like more iot
Sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot. Cam will see you next week