Hey everyone welcome to the 202
25th episode of The Internet of Things podcast
This is your host Stacey Higginbotham
And your co-host
Kevin tofel
And we have got eight
Chauffeur
Today we're going to be talking about misgivings on Google +
Amazon echos
Plus
Azlo is buying such a light will give you an update on
We're all that
Is
And
Intel has some new Chips
Worth talking about
Has a new lights
Strategy
Going to give you an update on those wise bulbs we talked about and discuss a new Weis product that was
We're going to talk about some news bits in
Including updates
2 drones
Funding for iot satellites
And a Bluetooth extender for
Eve
And
Because it is a day that ends at y we've got us
Dirty story
We'll also hear from our sponsor Dell Technologies
Talking about
Retail
And our guest this week
Is
Rags srinivasan
Of Seagate
He's talking about how Seagate has implemented a i and
Cameras
To improve their manufacturing process
It's a really great interview he really
Does a great job explaining
How they did this
And why they made the decisions they did
And anybody who's trying to implement any sort of iot or
Shooting at the edge should really listen
Elvis
Coming up but first
IMessage from another one
One of our sponsors
This week sponsor is a pharaoh
We're doing multiple iot projects
The work well together
In a single app that strengthens your brand
That's really hard and it requires the right platform with a pharaoh Kenmore Lodge 42 smart
Appliance models in just two years apparel customers have experienced as much as a 80% reduction in time to mark
99% pure support calls and a 10x higher activation rate
Plus we can reuse 90% of their work from one project to the next
Make a pharaoh like Kenmore Mitsubishi baked and dealing did and beat your competition with a solution that you're
13 loves to build and your customers love to use
Learn more at a pharaoh. IO flash go big
Okay
Hey Kevin
Right after
Recorded the show last
We heard
Big news from
Belgian Dulce
The journalist at
Svrta Belgian broadcaster brought the news
That's rather scary I guess we shouldn't be surprised by this because smart speakers we know they listen to us
But what happens after that we're finding out more
Google is saving all of those voice recordings
And using contractors to
Transcribe them which
I supposed to improve the voice
Results right
They're using it to make sure every
Correct
But
What was shocking to me was I had read in
How to say was a CNET article
When Amazon had the same story come out about them
Probably a month ago
Google said that they actually use voice modulation so people couldn't understand
Or identify the voices
And this is proving that completely wrong
Sound like
That's really sad cuz I really thought that was a good thing for
Google to be doing
Yeah it's that was probably one of the I should laugh out of it one of the funniest things in this
In this article that came from brt
We let ordinary Flemish people hear some of their own recordings it says
And here's a quote
This is undeniably my own voice says one man clearly surprised
Yeah
And
The big thing for me
Isn't it
Google or Amazon
Annotate sand has to
Pick up
Will recordings and make sure you're in check it for
Accuracy
I feel like that has to have
And it makes sense that that happens I would like to see
Any
Buddy who's doing this
And sending it on
The contractors to actually
Modular people's voices so that's not
Grenadier still be identifiable in
Information if there's addresses since
Stuff in there
What really caught my eye here and made me really uncomfortable
What's the false positives
So brt had over a thousand recordings
In
That
We're triggered without someone saying the words
Haji
I don't want to say the words
So
Tennessee
Rentable
False positive
That's
15% at its highest
We don't actually know
What more than a thousand is
Less than 2000
But wear them
That's too high
It is and you think at this point considering all of the
Breakthrough analysis and
Syrian technology and math that Google has been applying to its NLP
You would think they wouldn't have that
Iowa
False positive rate by now
Yeah well
You would think that and I remember someone
From Google talking about
Using a a I in
Smart Homes and
Using AI to
Autonomy
And he talked about the false positive
Rates in for something to actually automatically happen
They wanted to see a false positive
1%
Port to take action
Now
Privacy is not the same as like ordering
You think someone's
If you think someone wants
A pizza
But
I would like to see privacy move
Up in
Is there a steam or rankings so
Maybe your false positive rate is more like
5%
That's still pretty high but
To me it makes up for the inconvenience if you
So what I I guess
It's time to stop talking
About
Things like this is a violation of
Our privacy and I think it
It's time to actually talk about what we should see
So our Dimension voice modulation
I would also like to
Public audit independent yes
Independent public
Got its worst case scenario
I would like to see
Google published
Are false positive
And
Probably
Publish the percent of recordings
That are sent to
Contract
Discus people information that
Could really help them decide cuz right now it's like
And
They should say where those car
Wendy's in the story these contractors were actually local to the area where the recordings were
Where the speakers were
It's not like they're
In this case they were farmed around the world
Look like
And I should say
I was a contractor for Google for 18 months
And I had to sign all the same nda's and all that
In my case I presume that standard practice ER
Just to get people that information
Sure Google is really pissed Google's
Google slide is like yeah but these guys broke
Brocar NBA
I'm like Google
They did but what you're doing here isn't
Exactly right
I know a lot of people are saying hey this is how these things
And I agree with that
That doesn't mean they have to be that way yeah and it doesn't mean that that's
That particular false positive rate is okay or that
You know you shouldn't take steps to preserve people's privacy in the
When you're using
Real contractors and not just
Kind of related to this actually very religious and very Timely
How does Amazon actually
Check the recordings will they give you the option
In the app
Spaceway say hey I heard this
Padme says that this is what you meant is
Do the right thing right
So in a sense we all helped train or can that waste
I bet most people don't go in there and do this but
We all help Madame a
The funny thing is
And the story broke
Last week
Over the weekend
An infectious yesterday
I got the Google Assistant
Pop up on my screen on my Chromebook
And said hey
Please read that last voice command and I had actually said to come into my Google
Home device my smart display
To raise the volume I was listening to Spotify
And they gave me a ranking and then I can leave a comment as well
So I had never seen that before the story
Coincidence
Maybe
I'm wondering
How recently
I don't know
Time is like a river for me
Close
Cuz I'm on these devices all day long and
It's built into my Chromebook and I have all the
Display I never seen it
Don't care about your opinion
Maybe they only care about buying them
People like you made it obvious he doesn't work anymore for a reason that's not even bother with this guy
Yes so I will say
Given this news and
The lack of
For me it was the false positive
The Lacs
Protection here
Does this change your comfort level with having these around your house is the convenience still
Worth it to you
Well it's
It's funny you say that because I am not having a change of heart and things because I've always
Just put myself out there with all these devices and sensors and social networks
But over the past couple weeks I have been rethinking everything as more and more these
Types of
Privacy intrusions in
Data
Hacks and things
Going to
You know up here
I'm probably not going to change the way I use these devices
But I think I'm
A little more aware of
Basically maybe when I want to say and why don't at times
And it sounds silly cuz I'm in my own home and I should be able to say what I want
Well here
Let me tell you
So there's some options for people who still want to use
Space and they range from
You probably should do this to
Wow this is pretty extreme so first option is you can switch off recording
For Google
Devices
And you just go into
Your Google account in web and app at
You can manage your activity
Controls
And there's a section called voice and audio activity
And you can
Pause that so I have mine pause
And that means it doesn't make recordings
Voice so I can't send those
What does mean I'm not
But I did turn that off
A while back
So anyone can do that
You can always go and delete your old recordings as well
And so those will be gone
And
Going forward
If you're really uncomfortable you can turn off the microphone
On your Google devices and on your Amazon
Devices
And then
It won't be listen
And then I won't be listened
But then it also when you shout across the room
To be honest I've actually done that little more than I used to do as of late
Like if I'm not going to be accurately
Google do something for me here at my office or example
Like if I know I
Just want peace and quiet I'm not going to want music I don't care if somebody sure comes the doorbell even it was still show me that
Manhattan Town Center in
I have in my coffee
If I know I'm going to be
Changing music and
You know maybe want to ask Google some questions
I turn it back on
Additionally again
My Chromebook has Google Assistant built-in
There's an option if you have a Chromebook that has the support
You can in the settings
You can have it on for always listening or not always listening which is effectively
Shutting off B
The microphone from listening all the time and it said there's a Google Assistant key that you can hit
To any basically take the place of a
Awake work that's exciting cuz if you're working at your desk you leave them
All right yeah interior I could still change things
Music
What not so
There are options and we should probably mention
Only because we talked about it last week I believe
The Google home local SDK
Is now available for developers and what that should do
Is not send I think
You should send a recording to the cloud because all going to happen all the
Language should happen on the device
Yes we'll see it how that actually
Exactly
We're looking for today
All right
Moving on
This week
Big news in the
I'm going to call the pro
And even sort of the DIY smart home front
Which is a company called azlo his bought the assets of central
Probably back in
I don't know was it April
We talked about centralite
I filed for bankruptcy and centralite mayday
A bunch of
Sensors they made a bunch of zigbee sensors
They didn't see me anyway
They made a bunch of sensors they were lovely
I'm thinking in the world for a long time
And all of a sudden
It went bankrupt
Azlo
Has bought that
However
I had an email conversation with James Busby who is the
One of the founders of centralized
Original Sin
Just to check in on where things were
And he says that
He's forming
Support old Central
Projects
And
Tire repair in Salisbury
Hearts so hopefully
If you got a legacy system
You can
Still
Akai service that
And you can find that at www. Centralite support
Dot-com
And
He's hoping that
After all of this goes down he'll be able to
Make new products as well and so it could be another company that is going to develop new II
That's a rather smart move on his part cuz usually when these companies go under that's it you know they're they're done people move on
Products are bought acquired Etc
But your support
Potential for older
Devices now
I didn't see that happened to us
Yeah you really don't
And I should add that as low they actually
Acquired a company called me a house that was a smart home services platform
That made the Vera Z-Wave products
And they also in
October of last year purchased a couple
Fortress
Which was a leak detection in
Sandfly prevention
So so is probably a company that we're going to see more of
Okay
600 Kevin
This is exciting chipped
It is you're the chip girl I mean it I like having chips but you really get into and I mean really in a ditch
Baidu
Intel announced
A new chip
It mimics
Brain computer
And why does this matter
Okay long story short is
We have reached
Buford
Of
Which means we cannot pack more chips
McKenna
Get the power advancements and the energy
Advancements
That we used to get
So no more shrinkage
Catch and
This is a problem
Because now we
Right we're going to try a new architecture
So Intel's new architecture is
Oh here we go he's names they're hard for me practice we practice but
Why don't African Palace 100 Intel announced an 8 million or under amorphic system
Price of 64 of what they called loihi
Research chip
That particular system is called
I'll do it
Poke
Pohoiki Beach
So all of this is on their
So lot of Hawaiian names
Okay sure
But what this is is
They change the architecture such that
This particular chip can
Process information a thousand times faster
In ten thousand times more efficiently than a CPU
For certain Apple
Locations
And
Some of those applications include
Mapping so the kind of
Mapping the
Like your Roomba does in a room
The car does
Something called sparse
Coding
I don't know what's up
Will I have a general idea remember I'm only my third semester hero cop side but
Sparse learning is
Basically trying to take a lot of data
It is something and putting into something like a structure
Meridian dictionary
Not that Webster's Dictionary but take a dictionary
Encode
And
What's parse
Learning should do
Is
Kind of represent the data with a few inputs as path
Aunt without losing
Too much
What it really means if that makes sense
So
If you have like a machine learning model flask
I have like a gazillion
Data points
We need a lot of computing power to get through all of them
But you can model that data in a dictionary with far fewer points
Accurately
You can
Run the computer for FasTrak
Safeway
Plants versus
Okay
So
Intel has announced this it this is not something we expect to see used anytime
Truly so
They're researching how to put this particular
The loihi
On a USB stick
If they could do that we would see something like what they did with the
The movie Dias a position where they
Put those
I put those chips on a USB stick in allowed people
Go to play with them is
Set developer
So that was at the video computer vision
Chip acquisition so
That's kind of where I was
Expect to see this next that's the
The next thing I would see here
And if you're wondering ibm has been working on neuromorphic
Computing
Other companies in the chip space have been working on this this is
Kind of one of the next big things but
What's likely to happen is where
Probably going to
Figure
Some jobs for this
Amber still can have CPUs or still can have gpus but basically we're going to have more Ark
Pictures
Only because you mentioned neuromorphic
And we talked about architectures
The whole idea here if I'm understanding it is
The architecture they're using
Is cartoon mimic
The human brain
Synapses and so on would that be accurate
The brain is the most efficient computer and I remember as far back is like 2008 talking to
People who were trying to mimic
The brain
There's dozens of different
Ways to do this
A lot of them hit
It's both a complex Computing problem
Just designing the stuff
Encoding problem
So this is
So far
Been promising but it's not scalable
By any stretch
Take all of this with the greatest
But speaking of chips here something that's actually real arm
This week
Has announced a new licensing
And I look at this and I'm like
Who who are
You are
You are reacting to
Threats at risk 5
Respite
Open source architecture
Free chips
But
What arm has decided is they have a new licensing strata
So initially
If you want to build
An arm-based chip
Youlicense the Arctic
Texture from them
And then
You
Add stuff to it
So add stuff to their
Or you can buy an architectural
And that allows you to
Change
The architecture
A little bit and so the big companies like Amazon Apple
Qualcomm
Etc day he'll have architecture licenses so they can
Tweak that
A little bit
More granularly
But
What are missing now is
Instead of Licensing at the
The front end you can actually
Get access to the license
Design for a little bit
And then pay when you start taping out and see
Finger chips
This is a big
Change
Yeah
Well this opens up access for a lot of
Smaller companies that maybe don't have
The funds to pay the current
Licensing terms
And therefore they can't even get into this market for their product
That is so they can get in for much
Cheap price upfront
And then of course in both cases are charges a per-unit royalty
You don't have to worry about
Bat
Until you taste
Yeah but here's my question.
Okay I assume that you when you would license these things you have like some type of
NDA or something
Like how much
Inside information on the arm architecture going to have before you actually have to start
Oh but I think this is like any other lice
Which is now you
Get everything
You need to design a chip
When you sell it
Is when you pee
I think you get
Annie maybe they're Secret
Ricky's someone else who
Works with biscuit LS
For manufacturing
And there are two things that matter
What is what we just talked about with Intel how we
Hit the end of Moore's Law we've got so many different applications out there as weave
Got chips yet
The range hood light
Supercomputing type jobs are cloud computing type jobs all the way down to like
Turning on and off
Sensor
So
Arm is hoping to take advantage of
That and let other companies licenses stuff
The other thing is what I said about risc V
They are seen
Companies choose to
Use the risc V architecture for things like iot
And I don't want to lose that business
So that's that's what happen
Okay
Chips
God
Let's talk about
Wise last week I talked about the wise bulbs and I said something that was wrong
Cuz I couldn't
Kevin Quinn
Why is people could
And I told us about it so
When I talk about the wise balls I said you
Could not tie it
To the sets are actually what I said I could not find a way to tie it to the sensors and that frustrated
And why's let me know that there is a way to tie the bulbs
Turn them on and off
To the sensors
The way you do that is you going to the home screen
And then you go into edit shortcuts
And you have to create a shortcut
You click on create a shortcut
You're going to pick your action
Your action is going to be a bulb
And then you're going to
Click on an automation
Are you going to say autumn
And then you're going to
Pek
Bee sensor
And then
Walla
Yeah I'm glad it's there because it is
Just didn't make sense to not have the functionality
Maybe it's just because I really don't have one
Why is product at One wyze cam version 2
Side door
Have anything connected
Too but even so I was looking all around
I can't find this thing
I didn't love
That but as I said last weekend.
I think this is design for people who may not
Neither want all of that
It's so cheap
30 bucks for a bulbs in
People can just buy this
Play with a nap and
They may not want all this
Crazy stuff that you and I try to do
So otherwise newses
Yes and speaking of cheap
And why is that
The products are
Cheap crappy products there cheap good products
And wise
Debuting a Wi-Fi smart plug
2Pac
According to Home Depot's website
I'm looking at it right now it says
$19.98
Package
So they've got
2Pac Lee's Wi-Fi smart
Slugs they are just single
Slugs
Some of them have two outlets know they may take one out and turn into two
But that's not the case
141 Outlets
Will work according to this with
Google
Also
Scheduling and as you just pointed out you can automate
Bwise plug
WIS license based on open closed and motion detection
Again according to this product website
Cool alright we'll look for that
Alright Chinese Wi-Fi
It is Wi-Fi
Because it's got power
It makes sense
Why is only does
A proprietary protocol for the sense devices cuz they're battery
Battery make sense so
All right
Quick news bet so we've got to run through these fast so let's go
Alphabet swing lunch is the Open Sky air traffic
Control platform for trone
This is interesting and it's already been in use in Australia
Alphabet swing group has
Got to post on medium for people who want to see all the bits of details but essentially
Things created Open Sky which is
A
A method of platform rather to understand flight rules with buildings roads trees and terrain all the stuff that
Google has
Google Maps
And the idea is to help drones navigate safely
They'll even get information like if your drone is flying too close to a restricted area
Where there's an emergency in the area need to clear the air so
We'll see if people
Legends opensky platform as an expense
All right and my news is from
Ubiquiti link which is a satellite that I have to satellite play
And they have raised
5.2 million in seed funding
Total funding to 12 million
And this weekend they are going to do another satellite
Launch
I wrote about this
A while back
Basically they have built modules that allow
Devices to connect to their satellite Network
Satellite they don't have
Universal
Coverage yet so what happens is like
A couple times a day
The satellite will pass overhead and
You'll be able to send it
Little tiny message
They already have customers
So
It's a big deal
And funding is going to be
Useful
Obviously they have to launch and build all those smallsat
That's so there we have it
Next up
Eve
The maker of homekit enabled Bluetooth sensors has announced
Brand new
Ble extender will be available in August in Europe
Almost fifty Euros which is about $56
And
This particular device basically extend your Bluetooth range
Yay
Because I hate Bluetooth that is not Bluetooth mesh because
Go upstairs you like I can't control my lights anymore
So that device will work
With Bluetooth accessories
And it will show you what
Range
Pick which ones it wants to assign to eat extend and
Yeah it seems like a good product for anyone who's all in on homekit and wants to add
Make their sensor experience
Finally
You got our source ads
Security story of the day
Yeah we talked about this a while back and it
Soda has been mitigated but it's worth
Bring up again
Medtronic which makes insulin pumps
They have
Some older models that are still in use
My people that
Essentially can easily be hacked
And
Medtronic hainan
Left it off and then say it's a big deal
So
Two researchers actually
Build an Android app to prove it is a problem
Basic saying hey this app we know that we reverse-engineer the frequency
To the Medtronic pump and we can send it commands to
Shut up somebody's insulin Spike their insulin or whatever we could kill somebody
They did this to Spur Medtronic to do exactly what Medtronic has finally done
They've issued a recall and they're going to replace those pumps which is great
I'm not surprised by this because
I actually I know the frequency
For that because I thought
A radio
Hat for Raspberry Pi to send commands to electronic but we used it for good
To help
Automatically regulate insulin based on
Blood sugar readings for RCS class so
Good on these guys more white hats
Showing that these things need to be resolved
Yes and initially it would be awesome if these things
Kingston happening
We're getting
Okay I think now it is time for The Internet of Things
Podcast
How do you say Kevin
Absolutely
This week's podcast hotline is brought to you by Schlage
Slate's wide variety of smart locks
Lets you create the smart home of your dreams
Learn more about Schlage Smart Home Solutions and compatibility with Amazon
Apple and Google products at schlage.com
Slash
Iot
Okay
Y'all
If you call us
Before the end of this month
You will be entered to win
Schlage Smart Lock
So give us a call five one two
742 4
And
You could be entered to win
And how cool would that be
This week's
Color
Is
Who is it
It's Steve Steve alright this week's color is Steve who has a pressing question that I imagine a lot of us have
Let's hear it
Hey guys my name is
Steve Zahn from Dallas Texas I was recently outside
Grilling and I had an idea that it was
The Great
Anime
Type object
Do communication between
Devices I already have which include
Show
Couple.
And a regular Echo
And have something outside
I in order to play music and communicate with my wife
Any suggestions or ideas you might have would be great leap
Thank you
Okay Steve
We have
Pretty much bad
The particular use case you're looking for the drop in
That is only something that can be found on Amazon
Echo devices
Does third-party third-party outdoor capable speaker
Is it going to work
For this
Sorry
But
You can buy at a third party
Outdoor capable speaker in
Plug the Amazon
Input
Intuit this is a $35 device
You will have to plug it in using the 3.5 L
Your headphone jack
So
Using that cable
Plug that in
You're also going to have to plug it into power
And you probably shouldn't leave it outside
So what is awesome
Not right now
But if you can live without the calling in the drop-in
I didn't know this until just this morning you could get a Madam a speaker
For outdoors that's water-resistant and dust-resistant IP67 rated
Ultimate Ears makes the blast which is a small
Battery powered Wi-Fi and Bluetooth speaker with Madame a built-in
Again because it's third-party you can't use the calling in the drop-in
But at least you could
You listen to music outside change it by voice and so on so forth
And I'm even wondering maybe there's some skills out there or you could use if this the naturally
Send a text message to the family there might be a way to do it but
Needily that's not going to work for the eagle with the Ultimate Ears blast
You can just bring your smartphone outside
I know that's true that's not it
It's not exciting
But
Do you really have to have dropped
Good-news-bad-news
Couple options I also looked for outdoor enclosures for the Amazon Echo devices
I didn't find anything
That was for
Sorry Steve
I feel like you're trying failed you
It's not us
Amazon
Maybe it'll make an outdoor speaker I imagine the reason it doesn't
Is because it doesn't want to give flake
Controller something
To somebody walking by 2
Lean over the fence and be like
Unlock the door
Or that's what voice matches for that's why I work so well
Maybe maybe it's a call Voice match but
Oh I was
I thought that was Google but yes
Guess you could do that but
Be aware that if you leave one of these outside
You are opening up
A whole world of excitement to mischievous Neighbors
Who know you have
Already
That concludes this portion of the show please
Stay tuned for our interview with
Rags srinivasan
Who is from
Seagate talking about project
Bina and how they helped improve their manufacturing process using
Iot and AI
Before that
Let's hear from our sponsor
District sponsor is Dell Technologies
Hey everyone we are taking a quick break from The Internet of Things podcast for a message from Mars
Sponsor sponsor is Dell Technologies
And I have
Craig Wetzel
Who is director of iot channels
Intel
Here to talk to you about their relationship
With gel
So what is on the horizon for Intel in the iot space and how do you see Dell engaging
Tell to bring that
Industries that are seen the greatest benefits from iot and Edge computing
Enabled IAAI includes Healthcare
Manufacturing
Retail
And smart cities
Take retail for example
We see an interesting future in this area of interactive retail and had quite a few engagements in the retail Market
Together we're exploring ways that we can turn those traditional retail interactions
It's more unique retail experiences
We're doing this by leveraging
The latest computer vision technology
Instrumental such as the openvino toolkit which stands for open visual inference and neural network optimization
This toolkit allows for developers to innovate
Deep learning inference at the edge
So weird the point across the different solutions and platforms
Blockers
Let me give you an example
Imagine if a shopper
To go to a retail location and a retailer could use various iot
Technology
Identify that shopper
Personalize their shopping
The retail will be able to allow customer to set up a shopping profile they could be accessed
Window Shopper in
Stores video
To be used to identify that Shoppers they entered and begin an interactive engagement
Is that retailer for Sadie's a clothing store
That history could include the shoppers
Clothing sizes
Favorite colors
Branford
An accessory
They could then use this digital signage
The guy The Shopper
What's the area of the store
What do you have the most interest
Use the interactive mirror
To show the clothing in different colors
Then you lies a real-time inventory
Deliver the chosen item to the shoppers home
If the item they want is out of stock
They can have it delivered to their home
Taking these types of Analytics
Can revolutionize a traditional
And bring a better process
These types of solutions are easy to install with the breadth of products that Dell offer
From their servers to their Dell Edge Gateway
Vicki Craig
Any final thoughts or observations you'd lie
In regards to the Internet of Things
Iot is not an easy
It requires multiple products
Woven together
With the right app
Applications installed in locations that are in many times challenging
No one company
Can do it alone
Dell Intel together
What are strong
Are developing into Point Solutions across Industries in Dragonsreach
For integrated there's an end users looking to see the benefits of iot today we have a selection of Intel iot Market
An Intel iot RF
Powered by Dell
That are available
Check out these offerings as well as many others
Dell Technologies. Com iot
Everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest is
Rags srinivasan
Who is
Senior director
Roads verticals at Seagate
Rags how are you
ICC I'm doing very well how are you doing
I am super well and I'm really excited
Because
We met a couple months ago and you talk to me about bringing AI into
Your Manufacturing
The Wayfarer menu
We'll talk a little bit about
What that entails and the choices that you made around
Iot and AI
In your business operations
First. Explain to people most people know what Seagate does
But you may want to explain a little bit about
How you do it and why you guys decided to
To update your mail
The most people Noah's from the diet most people run into me in the street say I saw your advice that the cost
It's it's that's all they know us
Baltimore Drive
Run most of the Claudia Sanchez everywhere like we could use about tens of millions of fives at Porter
Caleb would be a Manufacturing
Otis technology company
A lot of manufacturing behind
To produce 30 + million units of guys every quarter and make sure the war
Black inside the driveway
Truly and engineering
Ikeda's multiple pliers and drive it
All bags in such a small form-factor is like a drive head
Floating over
Spinning platter
Delete coolant all like a 747
Flying seven
Times the speed of sound
Close to the ground
So it is every bit of it is
Complex and high position matters
On anything we can do there to improve the process
Improve depression
All the quality
Is going to have a direct impact on a business
So that's why we decided to take a careful look at our retirement election process I'm take advantage of
Coyote mint
So what you guys decided to
Upgrade your manufacturer
Check process what was your first Insider what was your first
When we started out we started like most people be
Got in the room and started talking technology first
But we looked at the iot sensors we looked at our entire manufacturing process that Got7 Factory
The central machinery
I got excited by what we see and hear about happening in the AI instead of there
Very quickly recognized
Everything that we do our Starwood technology is not the direct
Answered
Do what we want to solve intensive business and back
Although
All these projects
You can start off bite off much bigger than you could going to begin with
So we also needed to scale a CO2 emissions
Every bit of the cycle you can put them in categorization DHS simple
Manufacturing product inventions project
It could be a quality improvement process where is it we want to start
Reasonably hard enough but others I'm not done it
As well as solving it will have a direct business impact
Narrow down the public space to pick that one aspect
Drive
Head quality
In the whole chain drive had manufacturing process has aborted.
Takes 6 months to complete
Solving. One with a I and II RT will give us the biggest energy of wind that we wanted
And then from that scale back to the rest of the processes
Awesome
You guys basically said hey
We could like do this low-hanging predictive maintenance on our machines and maybe make our factories
Perform a little bit more efficiently
Or
We could go big
And say hey we're going to take this
Really intricate process and see how we can improve it
And that's hopefully have
Away Barrett
That is exactly correct focus on the outcomes more
If you look at that the commercial that has seen better salesman coming out before that everybody's dogs
Everyone's imagination very quickly but what really matters is if you go down to the real heart number
Please like if I can predict a particular entity that we're making is going to be flawed
Before we go to the 1400 steps
Stop flow directly into our body
Outside to tell a bigger story but he has a great comeback so that's where we roll back and start it there and yes
It will be a big enough problem for us to take on Unsolved
That's a really good thing I mean yes no I don't think anyone
Is like yes I want to make spinning platters and the heads that read those more efficient
The number one problem facing
Production line but for you
It makes sense
So
How much is that per
Just getting to it like figuring out
What you guys were going
What did you learn
Twisted our initial setup brainstorming analysis
Problems faced reduction if you will
We wanted to do a lot of things we have very qualified very smart Buy
Wanted to try a few things
What you brought in this like I got involved with the tmb put it more of a structure around
Games focus on the priorities ourselves of more aggressive gold starting from the point to do
One thing
Promise to
How much bigger
Across-the-board going to do it for one Factory
One Pilot
And then from there I have a plan how am I going to scale that from that one line one Factory do 7
Other taxis worldwide
And the first thing also we did it
Branded the project first easier to going in there and say like I'm going to do it
Turn everything but after that abuses
Internal organizational attachment
We branded the Catalyst project Athena
That helped us
Create a rallying cry around the entire organization we got the name out in front of the execs we got the
Exact Pi in to do this
How do you saw that everyone riding around let's
Let's all work together to make project Athena SX
Everyone was able to Define
What's part of it
Decided that this is about anomaly detection
Braverman factoring from the way of the papers. Cut into head
Illegally this is about delivering the quality improvement improvement
Reduction in the need for future Investments
Keymander the one common umbrella and then everyone started speaking the language
Gateway
Enough of momentum that is needed to get going
I'm from the completion it was about 12-15 months or so to complete the pilot
The process of taking this
And then how you can become scalable and Deployable in a way it's easier without the
Same level of Steven Waldman Insanity Factory
Sisters VR app
Okay
So let's talk about what you guys learned initially with project
Athena you started out
You were using cameras
Brett to analyze the
Defects in
Wafers
And let's see there was like 10 I think was 10 terabytes of data add a 17 million photos there's there's a lot
That was happening so
Talk to me exactly about
What you guys did
And even how
Cute Ranger neural network to
Analyze the state
Listen to Parts I make sure I'll hit the second tiny parts
Basketball
TriStar you got the numbers right in there so
This is.
17 million images just for that one process
Where we talked with us 200 nanometer wafers
And then to let the 49ers stuff we cut them into multiple sliders that are then stacked into
I would go into the desk
Assembly there
There are multiple stages where we have
Electron microscopes located that take pictures
Today in some of these parts as well he's analyzed by the human operators the experts
For anomalies
But we have complemented this with certain level of Rude by AJR
You go on to write down
All the known anomalies
What it looks like I fired
Operator gets in wall
Even if we were asking our operators to make coasters
Way too complicated
The problem says the anomalies are not fixed
We can't codify everything changes over time out of gross as well
Created a real
Ideal space where we can apply machine learning
Let it learn the anomaly patterns
I didn't continue to claim that every 3 months
Spell the patterns change
So the model is always up-to-date
For us to use it
A better way
Do you make those predictions
What would be the New Orleans are there
If you take the image classification there are many models are there
We are using one of the standard image classification models there
But we did about 30 different zomato to see which one works
Spellforce
Remodeled has about 20 + layers
I need to find out the pixel level
Ridges in at 6:11 and be able to say if it's a defect
Or not
Does that allows
To find it a very high level of accuracy whether a particular way for has an anomaly or not
A weak acid
We stopped us from going through the process being made into dryvit
Which failed or worse
The customer side which is data management all those things
So we helped to avoid all the things
By finding those defects
Much much earlier in the production process.
Got it
Yay finding defects early as is
So what is the underlying architecture that you using
Because I
I think that's a lot of data
It's happening in real time
I don't know how fast your Wafers come off the manufacturing
For that particular process but it seems like
There's a lot of data processing
Edge so what is it that you're using what are you calculating
We are processing things like 1 billion x uses tens of millions of guys 1/4
We actually wanted to focus on process
Much much earlier
Rather than trying to improve down the chain quality improvement process
So we have looked at
It's 17 million are so images. Coming through
WeChat label all supervised learning when you go it depends on
Someone looking at
All images trying to label them say this is a good one this is a bad one
Stop possible to onexton we can do that
So we devised our own internal algorithm
But can't look at
These images
Are segmentation off them cuz this could be in The Bachelor this could be in the other set
Other music human interpretation
Do you stumble a sampling from it to say is this correct
Labeling algorithm
Can be corrected
I hate running in the Free Loop there once we have it kind of training day. We were able to build out
A Chooser process with the training like they're on the edge because 10 terabytes of data per day is not
Something we can head over to the cloud
Inference that happens quite there on the manufacturing line
Good morning about 20 or so decisions per second
What's the sauce is good food to make which river is good in between fridge not bad and do so at a high level of confidence
So we can end up with a much better quality there
It sounds like you have done a lot of the work already that a lot of companies are trying to
You're out so
How did you set this up was it easy
Did you have to hire in
Experts to
Create this platform
If there existed an off-the-shelf solution
13 /
People who wanted to solve the problem not just
Let me go and invented a game here mentality but when we looked outside something that takes
And use it to solve anomaly detection there was none existed
So we brought into HP Park as a partner
Two main exports
With a good understanding of how the machine learning and deifies worth
I'm having deployed in a similar scale but something else
Together the team help develop an architecture
An easier orchestration where the model gets trained
Correctly
Homologous deploy easily
Orange red
Alan you have a way to retrain them all ugly deployed over the pier is not just one and done
Take me to work continuously
So that helped us having HPV as a partner
We need help.
Build
Amore maintainable solution that grows or the time
Existed
So we wanted to Cheryl experience as well that's one of the reasons why we go to lightsaber defining or problems
Architecture
Weed and applying to different architectures the one we usually built out with HP
The one is without the hitch.
We did with the dgx the big one from Nvidia
And use that as a parallel architecture to test this will knock
How does architecture work
One you end up with a lot more then in our case than what we needed but both of those definitely would work
For anyone wanting to build
Image-based
Spell isolation in the factory
Different from iot but I'll say this
The most
Pulisic IAT sensor that is out there is a camera lens
I'm getting stressed out thinking about those
Camera first use cases lochmoor
I'm just looking at say a few sensors here and there
A camera captured so much more information that is which
I need to work in ways that we did not even think of
That is true
Totally on board with
The camera being the most important
Center especially in things like Manufacturing
Industrial
Applications
Obviously it's awesome and Holmes 2
But I have
Issues with
Everyone's home
Let's go into
You've obviously done this you guys did a little bit faster than I thought
3 months getting into it and then
12215 actually implementing it
Until your next step is to bring this to all 7 of your Manufacturing
Plantain and maybe
Doing some additional use cases
Talk to me about the next day
Able to achieve
Because of Define
Are goals clearly to one process one aspect
Elevate my entire Factory every part of it into smart manufacturing lights
One line
So that helped as well so we do not deviate we did not try to add on one thing or the other
Casas Renta long so we focus on one thing
Is we have a timeline we want to take this one and then replicated and 7UP
This requires a bit of packaging with any of those projects anything else you do
We all focus on solving the problem not about shipping it or not about how other people use it like so weird
Making sure the second aspects come through
Where is this becomes more of a package solution
How are teams can ticket deployed across
Please have another factories there
All the AI in cameras and everything is Kim. What is it
You're solving it came down to its anomaly detection
Is this one fits within the pattern of acceptable range
Synonym for doesn't matter
Your environment are the Domaine doesn't matter easy to comes out to the anomaly detection case
She has a lot of potential
Outside
Affectionate could we use Public Safety yard could be smart cities are you in
Having a direct
Application
To check the solution on a clock
We are not looking at
Seeking some of the models of rebuilt
Any direct application in WhatsApp for collecting making another use case is as what
We talked about a lot of the technical stuff we've been dumped into some of the biz
What is your advice to
People who are listening to this and they're like oh that sounds awesome I totally want to do it
How should they do this from
Getting the management on board a wheelie number one
Connie Jo it's not going and making a pitch that is still with
Machine learning and deep-learning
Jorgensen there but moral focus on what is it we're going to do that's going to move the needle there
It's really celebrate like our Carly purses
It's time consuming
Alone on Valentine's Day
We are operating at
Full capacity and we needed a way to get more order for existing Investments
Put forward a solution that help directly address
Does business challenges there
Using a machine learning pod
Make sure you put in
Expect to see by even doing the initial pilot investment
We actually have any children collected at 300% return of Hawaii Polynesian
Time to get there
The second part is I just said getting people exact not just that small group
Direct organizational
Turn the story that's why we had the brand
Be able to tell everyone what's happening with
I'm getting them at full view of
As well as
Dealing with them the initial excitement of the results
Today is it going to take away all our jobs
If we help solve this problem you actually freezes up to do some of the higher the changes
We don't need to stand there and look at those for the Glen
We could be solving way out
Erection quality in the manufacturing process
Starting with execs
Getting any excitement from everyone with proper branding even if it is in Channel you need to do The Branding and marketing why
I've been getting the buy-in from all the other teams that is involved with numbers
Help us get there
Excellent
Alright well racks
Thanks so much for coming on the show today I feel smarter and I think a lot of people will find this really helpful as they embark on their own
Iot
All right sissy thank you I enjoyed talking to you and sharing with you experience
That's it for this week thanks so much for listening
Remember if you'd like more iot news sign up for my newsletter and Stacey on iot
Dot-com will see you next week