Hey everyone welcome to the 223rd episode of the
Internet of Things podcast
This is your host Stacey
Kevin tofel
Chauffeur
Today
Astonishing because we're going to talk about
Amazon
Finally answering some questions about
What it does with your
Voice
Data
Plus we are going to be talking about another smart home platform
Data leak
We got
D-Link settlement with the FTC over at security failures
We've got a hat
Smart Home
It might be
Put in lots of apartment buildings around the country
We got some news about hpe and its plan to
Continue its own digital transformation
Kevin tried out some new software
Could replace if
Or could it
And we got lots of little updates on
Products and stuff you probably use
Plus
We have
Andy Lowery the CEO of real whereas Our Guest on the show this week
Realwear just raised
80 million dollars
I will talk to him about using heads-up displays in industrial settings
Why
That's taking so long
So we're going to talk about this plus hear from our sponsor Dell Technologies
But before we get to that
Let's hear from another one of our sponsors
This week sponsor is a pharaoh
Are you doing multiple iot projects that work
Well together is there a single app that strengthens your brand this is really tough stuff and it requires
The right platform but with a pharaoh Kenmore launch 42 smart Appliance models in just two years
Anna Farrell customers realized as much as an 80% reduction in time to Market
99% pure support calls and 10x higher activation rates plus they can reuse
Is 90% of their work from one project to the next so
If you're looking to do multiple iot projects or just one pic of pharaoh
Just like Kenmore Mitsubishi ufj group and dealing did and you can beat your carpet
Addition with a solution that your team loves to build on and your customers love to use
Learn more at a pharaoh. IO
Okay Kevin
Big news on the Privacy front this week
We've called privacy friend are we just call it the Madame de France
Email specific to matamata but it is
Privacy so
Here's the deal cuz there's a lot happening here and there's a lot of concern and I would say these are legitimate
Questions
So what has happened
It is
Journalist discovered a while back that the Amazon Echo
A couple things when we all
No
Listings for Wake word and then when it hears that way
Wake word it records
What you say
So it can actually
Complete the command and Amazon keeps the transcript and the actual utterance
A couple weeks back what
People discovered is that
There were call centers of people who
Took the actual utterances and annotated them
Check them against Amazon
Actions
And I did that because that's its quality
Basically
But people were kind of up in arms
In general
People are very concerned about having a microphone
Their house and I guess
That's kind of how we got to hear so
Delaware senator
Sent a letter to Amazon
On asking
About how long it kept voice recording what to do with transcripts and all of the
Data it gets used to
So
That's okay right
So the Senators like hey
We need more information
And this week Amazon Center
Some people are really
Tweaker taking kind of the wrong message
Amazon basically says
Did they're going to retain
Customers voice recordings and transcripts
Until you choose to delete them
If you delete
It's going to make every effort to delete the voice recordings
And the transcripts themselves
But
Metadata
What was learned from
Voice recording some such as particular actions or skills
That information is not really scrub ignores any information
That is so cute
Exactly
And nor is any sort of
If you have a recurring thing or there's transactions associated
Stick around
Because it
Peter has to have something
If you tell it to set your alarm at such-and-such time everyday it can't
Remove the data
Because would not know when
Tomorrow 2
So there a couple things
It is really in
In
I think
We should stop having the same conversation about
Privacy in these homes like as a binary thing
It's either there or it isn't there
I think we should start having more conducive conversations about
How did make sure this data if people are going to use it
Stays out of the hams
People
And is used for
Sound or is not tied individual
So
That's that's
So I think there's a couple things that you
Amazon
And Google actually already does
So
The Senators asked if Amazon takes any measure to anonymizer Identity and other information in relation to
Transcripts
And the answer appears to
Yeah
It partly because some of this means to be associated
You know if
If I'm telling Amazon to do something on my account
It makes sense that
It has to be associated
Because I'm buying something from Whole Foods
Amazon needs to know where to send it in
That's so that's never going to be
Google for example takes utterances
The actual voice commands and they run their vocal distortion
Through it so
They still get the benefit
Having the ability to like
Check their work
As it were
Are there AI
They can do annotations on
Peoples voices
They can make sure that
Command actually
Did what it was supposed to do
They can do all of that without actually knowing
You are meeting
And I'm glad you brought that up because if anybody
Hasn't already done if you can go into 2
And listen to go through the history and listen to
What matinee actually her
You will hear your own voice obviously
There is a
A mechanism to report to the matinee do what you requested or did she not
Sao innocence you can help
Train mad about yourself
And you wouldn't be able to do that obviously without
Having that
Transcription history available
Exactly
So I think first off
To anonymize people's voices problem
Privacy protection
The other thing I would say is some of these recurring commands
They could probably live locally on the
Edifice
And
I imagined
Google I mean Google is working very hard
Hartford local control
And
Being able to say
Hey
Keep my recurring alarm
Here
That's great
Take rate you get if you get the benefit of having
Some of that
Madame a features
Without worrying that you know
Everybody knows
5 in the morning
Or whatever time you wake up
That's another thing that I think would be
Very proactive and then the other thing is with skills
I think wouldn't download a skill you should see what data they're trying to get
Were able to get
From a transaction
And
You should be able to read their privacy policies and hopefully there are easy to understand and not like
16 pages of legalese
Those are just some thoughts that I think
I think we need to move
Forward from
This is Carrie there's a microphone in my house
Hey if there's a microphone in my house
What are the steps the concrete steps
That should be taken
And maybe should be should be regulated
Will protect
Glitter
There's a lot of cars here which I think
I think we had all the high points in the important things
I still have an open question
In that
Unresponsive says we design Echo devices at matamata to use on device
Keywordspy technology
To detect when a customer intends to interact with
Anime
And
It's interesting that they didn't say hotword or something to that effect
Is there anything
Other than the Wake word
Part of that guy
Keyword spotting
That's a question I would ask as a follow-up
That is a good follow-up cuz I know sometimes I can think of a perfect use case right
We are sitting around our dinner table and we're arguing over you
You know something silly
One of us will be like
Let's take it to
And then be like
Who was the 42nd president
And will get a response
When we say things like let's take it to Amazon or maybe put it on the grocery list
Or whatever
I could see
I don't know what the
Shooting action is in my brain I'm the metaphor is like
You like oh
Maybe I should pay closer attention
Is it my name
Yes it is
The only other thing in his letter that thank you
Explained very clearly
How
Madam
Works which is
It listens for awake
When it hears that wake word
It turns on
And open some microphone
To take in the voice command that you're going to say
When you stop speaking
It turns that off
It sends only that chunk of command
Amazon
Adoption
And
So many people are concerned that it is always listening
And they're they're just not sure it like Amazon can talk till it's blue in the face and explain this
But people are still free
So
I wish they would have addressed the weird laughing issues
What exactly is happening with
You know one in the house has said anything related to
Matinee at all
And yet it still wakes up
Or we heard
Jerry edge cases something like
2 hours of non-stop recording was actually captured
I remember that happened was reported about a year ago
I think it's with the right Edge case
There was some also there were some questions about 5 because
Natchez
You said the Wake words matter I use you say something
And then make it responsible action happens and then you take another action without saying awake or tinnitus continue to listen
They were clear in the letter and it has been clear from day one that follow-up mode
Conversation would you rather call that way
Has to be
Enable by the customer
So it's not on by default
The point here is
I feel like we should have more transparency there always computer
People who are like
This is how these things were
Work and could Amazon be better yes I think they should take a page from Google right now if you are more privacy-conscious you may want to pick
OK Google smart assistant
So we'll see
Hopefully Amazon
Guess what the program
I guess I don't know
E-services on whoever Mason
Whether it's Samsung Bixby or the other two that we just talked about
They're always evolving and frankly
If you're going to use one of these devices
Yes you are putting microphone in your house and you know that
If you're not comfortable with that actually don't do it
If you're comfortable enough with the way they
Transcriptions and data are handled again
If you're not
Against don't put one of these in your house
Exactly
All right
Let's talk about other security issues because they are out there
A company called orvibo
Has
Apparently
Not been awesome
They left their database
Open it is a smart home
Products maker
They make
Cheap outlets in
And other stuff like a smart plug Wi-Fi outlet for 7 Bucks
Amazon
Which
Vici sounds good
But
Except they're based in Shenzhen China
Which nut
My soul is a problem however
They had over two billion logs in their database that was wide open
Usernames emails addresses and passwords
And
Your precise location
Yeah this has stuff from
Around the world
I found this is a company called vpnmentor
And they said they contacted
Orvibo via email on June 16th they didn't hear
Anything from them
So they tweeted the company and
It was left open until at least July 2nd
So
Yay
3 weeks from the time they are notified
And apparently
It doesn't sound like
Actually responded they just closed it and the
Recaptcha
This is something that like when we talked about
Recommended devices for people cuz we get tons of questions about what's the best device during this this mess you know
We tend to stick with
More well-known brands
Anime
And they are more expensive that is correct
Now that doesn't mean
Just because
It's a well-known Brand X
Insecure
What time is it
Give me well but the minute we didn't had questions or people were like hey I
When the wise cancerous came out today
It's not always knowing where this data is stored in cap so
It's not always easy for us to find out it's certainly not easy for anyone to find out
You got to pay attention to that though if you can
And yes
And that's why we say brands
And I also do recommend that you look for a companies that have a history of responding to security incidences
Buy response I don't mean soothe
Hacker I mean
Hey
Do they issue a patch today
Engaged Community to that talk to their customer base about it
So those are those are other thing
That you should look for when you're buying action
You may not mind but you know I certainly don't
My my family name
My Wi-Fi password
My device password
And
My address
If you know that I turn on my light
But otherwise
Direct Security news
D-Link has settled
Lawsuit
That was filed two years ago by the FTC
CC file this lawsuit
Were advertised as secure but they were
Not
Secure
And it was over the security of their routers and IP
The FTC was like look you guys stored passwords on your app and play
Plaintext used hard-coded login credentials this is a
A big No-No
That was actually hard-coded login credentials were one of the issues behind the bar Ibotta
Back in 2016
So all the way back in
Well I guess it was
We were like really hard could have passwords you guys that's weird
That means your password is
It's stored in the device which is not a good
It's like taping your key to the underside of your
I know people do it
It's not secure
The FCC said
The company was
Negligent
Basically
In the court was like
No
You didn't say this enough proof FTC
What combat
D-Link is basically by settling
Is probably
Okay
Yeah we did have V6 which it did and those are not best practices today
Today admitted argument that back in 2018
14 when they were building these devices these were fine
Probably
But we didn't know
Basically it's like we didn't know
Now it's clearly problem
What they're going to do with the settlement is D-Link is going to implement a comprehensive software security program
Vulnerability testing
And monitoring of its products to address
It will also issue automatic security updates
And it will begin accepting
Vulnerability
Basic math practice
Just consider these are all things that we always have her eggs
I think the bigger
Then use that
Requires a D-Link has to
Have an independent
Assessment of its software security program
Once a year for 10 years
Hey
D-Link is the way to go for the next few years they've got
This
Partial review
Check it out their stuff a lot of companies actually hire
Impartial reviewers to security test their stuff so
This is not
No but
Does this feel like the bare minimum
Yes but at least we're establishing a Baseline
In some we don't have any laws protecting us but with the FTC in this case we've actually establish someone
Baseline
And actually that
Bring some to a question I was going to ask you when I took a look at this
Because I got the same impression here's a baseline could it be a
A model for a particular law
Or will the FTC do you think just keep
Going after companies in this way which would kind of stink of this point
Is this a good starting
I think so and
I would also say it should not have to be as long of a process because
Court case dismissed the original one
But now they have this president
One conservative company
Could go
Will see this and be like you
These are not
Probably 90%
Hopefully they're good
At least 90%
And then
The FTC can say
Great here's this implemented
Do it and the company be like okay sure
I think we will get
Again
In trouble
Is with companies that are not really concerned about pleasing the FTC
D-Link is based
Sharon Leal
Steak-Out
Millions of custom
When we talked about like some random Fly by Night
We're just
Quit
Quick-hit
Product
Maybe like the smartplug we're just talking about the or Vevo
Stuff
Those companies Medicare
The SEC might go after them and they'll be like
No
So
I think it'll be good for conscientious companies I think it's kind of the bare minimum but
Yay we have a bare minimum and it should be easier
The next time
Baby steps
So speaking of hard-coded passwords
Security researchers have
Discovered
That the zapato hub
Which is actually a hub people have asked us about I have actually played with it it's
Github
Except maybe it's not
So
Security researchers have discovered that
It has her good passwords inside and they could
Extract those passwords
And
Get access
The Hub Lincoln
But
Yeah and I believe the Potter has a an updated
Actual aptitude Hardware or throwing out a different hub
For multi-tenant properties which is
Where this is
Yes
The reason these guys started hacking it
Is because
Cuz
One of their fellow hackers had and we talked about this on the show
Was
Notified by her
Apartments
That they were
Transitioning to a
Smart apartment building
Connected lock
The security researcher was like I do not want this
But was unclear if she had the ability to say no as a tenant
And
That'll
That kerfuffle died down I believe to
Most people satisfaction we also saw a different company
It was doing automated lock smart locks in the park
Building
The tenants actually sue the landlord who is trying to put the smart locks in
And demanded a physical key
So
The bottom line
Is
This is still an unclear area
Dessert
Maybe not secure spin tested
Is is better for a problem
And the company is smart rent
And you may have heard of them because last week they raised
32 million dollars
So
What are we saying here
Security is not
It's not at a place where you should be like
Complacent yet
Isis
Being sad
People can break into non-smart
Princess well it's just
It's a little bit more difficult I feel more more okay with a Smart Lock in my single family home
Because
If someone really wants to get in they can break a window they can
Pick a lock it's not
That hard
In an apartment complex though
Having this sort of vulnerability opens a bunch of locks at once which makes it a Richard
And I would also say
If your
For example
Potential high-risk
If you have a high risk profile for hackers
Like that
Then you can actually bolster
Your
Normal dachshund
Could be easily hack
With a lot more stuff
Things that would make it harder
So
Okay so
Ascot a lot of bad
Amazon news
It's good that we got
More clarity here
I'm not surprised by any of it
I do think it's being made out to be a little bit
More traumatic
And it really is
And I think that's because of how you started this this whole
Podcast in conversation
It's not a binary thing privacy around privacy right
It still is
Wow subtlety
It's the death of us
Hey what's talk about Enterprise iot
Hpe hpe
Is HP Enterprises it is the
Server in
All kinds of other stuff
HP they've got server software
Cloud computing
Crazy stuff
They
Hyatt we should have done this last week but we did not
Basically
Hpe wants to
Deliver their entire
Portfolio as a service by
What
Heck
That mean
Basically this is interesting because
In the industrial iot in Enterprise iot
We talked a lot about this
Concept of digital transformation
The idea is once you have a lot of data about your products about how people are using your products
You can turn something from a capex expense into an object's expense
Just cool
And you can deliver all kinds of crazy things like
Steam traps or
Elevators or
Palace deliver Services service because that's what Amazon
Web services is
But hpe witch
Bill's of physical Hardware
I was like huh
That's kind of crazy
They're still going to provide Hardware
And
Their software
So you could still buy it out
But if you want
You can also buy a service after 20
I thought that was really
They're really pushing forward with what everybody else is trying
And
I don't know
What do you think
Microsoft Word example don't really
Bill much hard when I do did you some like that the service product line and whatnot
They have Services Azure and everything have in-house where is HP
Traditionally been a hardware
You're so
They integrate software
Datacenter in a box
But maybe you don't want
To buy their boxes because it's cheaper for you to host their services on another cloud
Yeah they have spacing expanded and new Partnerships with cyrusone
Acronym and
Google Cloud
So
HP Services you don't have to buy hpe
Software Hardware
You could have it posted on
Yeah I thought this was kind of cool
For the Enterprise people cuz these are the kind of big efforts that we talked about a lot with our guests and
Harbor Freight
You just rather have everybody else matters at McLeod
Personal
We're seeing a shift to like the
Economy right so this is basically
Instead of capex instead of buying something big once
An amortizing IT overtime
Depreciating it
Every time
You just
Like Me by Rent the Runway instead of doing my clothes are by my clothes
Which by the way
Okay
Let's talk about something that you tried out this week
I tried something I was a piece of software for Android or iOS
Runs in the cloud but you can even ask for it
There's no web interface for it
Any
Touts itself
Like a potential replacement
Competitor to
If this then that or stringify or
Any one of the other
Integration type services to make your smart home more degraded
And
I guess the best way to say this is
It's good at what it does
Becca has some
Benefits over
If this then that person
But it doesn't
Do much yet and that's because there are not a ton of integration
I dug around it turns out this product on 27
And it's an amsterdam-based company
They created a I believe it's a smart thermostat
34 years ago
And they decided to make this over snow app and
Start to integrate other services not just with their thermostat but with everything
But when you look at the channels for example such as
Integrates with
They're just
Aren't nearly enough messages on here
Are you can do notifications you can interview with Twitter cryptocurrency
It does work with home connect Honeywell lyric
Trust Smart Home lifx
Tune which is the
Smart thermostat that kick this project off
Netatmo and it's some other names I just not familiar with like Yuki and
Something is on there
I do know that masonis is on there
But
Acardia
Quick and
Quick yuan
I don't know what that is crownstone
Zelig
I would say so
In Europe perhaps this is a good
Option for you to look at
Here in the US I don't find a compelling enough
My testing showed pretty good
I couldn't present will get up with any things on my wink hub
Can I get you anything that might be on a smartphone side because that's not supported either
And I can do with it
I can send text messages with I could have any notifications when something happen
And even though
Google home and Manet integration is kind of weird
You have to create
A virtual button
Can you connect that to your voice assistant and then you
Put a trigger with a collect rig
On the button so that tiny that you can create his virtual buttons for
Trig's because their whole approach is protease triggers that
When this happens what happens next if this then that
It's just weird
So
What does it do better than
After what
UE mentioned that they does something saved
I'm so glad you asked
You could have multiple when things multiple triggers
So yeah so you could say if this happens and that happened and this happen
Only this time of day
Then do that
Got it so that's actually more powerful
That that's more like a smart things are stringify effort
Correct
Correct and it's far easier to use stringify array SmartThings
But again the problem is
For me and probably I think for both of you asked
You want to look at the channels that are offered to see what you can do or rather what you cannot do
I have no reason to replace anything with this
Right now I'm not saying it's a bad product I'm saying it needs to mature
Okay
Hey what's talk about some tiny little updates that are fun to do so Kevin you want to kick ass off with
Chamberlain
Yes Google Assistant
And if this then that integration
You can get it for
Free for a limited
Time
Wilt Chamberlain start
Charging
For the microservices on if this then that
So does costume the nominal fee right now
But for one year you can actually get for free
All right and I will tell you that
I love my MyQ
It's great
It's one of the one devices that I'd want to
Replace here in this house
Lucia
They updated their
Hub and so now instead of $50 which was the last limit
Did not let you control 75 bulbs or switches are whatever you
April 75
So
This is great for people with lots of
I guess lots of house
Is the lack of lamb
That doesn't require any new hardware
If you only have 50 now you can go buy 25 more
Do you need a new bridge or no
Speaking of balls and speaking of I was actually excited to see
Is currently the owner of Philips Hue
And
Philips Hue bulbs
Yes well I never really invested in the Philips Hue bulb
And you need that
Philips Hue now makes balls with
So you can get Philips Hue bulbs
White tunable white and
Color
With Bluetooth and no Philips Hue Bridge needed
I am curious what you need
Is there some things
I think you will need and I'm serious actually to test this out
Because
The last time I tested Bluetooth bulbs
Well
The first time I tested them I hated them because
Cuz my house was bigger than
The range and then the second time I was trying still with
Awesome so I can't wait to see if this means blue
Bluetooth mask
Actually
More useful
Set temperature to 8
All right
Is he Bluetooth
Okay
And find a little bit
SmartThings they have updated the app and you can now integrate
A hub connected
Device so this is any sort of
Connects through
SmartThings compatible
Rather still like your weight
And
It will use the SmartThings Cloud execute those
So now you can have your hubs talk to your other hubs
It's great
But it's all in the cloud and I want local
Alright well
This isn't for you you don't even want
But
If I can open if you do want hugs
Good news
All right now I think it's time for
Two things one the voicemail but also
Shoes
Winner
All right and they win a wise
Sensor
So
Very exciting and our winner is
We heard from him last week this is Bobby
Do asses smell
Congratulations
Yay
You know that's two months in a row that we've had the last
Caller
Actually win and the funny thing is
We actually
And then ask
The Google assistant pick a random number from 1 to the number
Kind of weird but that's how it work out
So yes it's it is random for any of you
Are you guys were like
But I encourage
Because
This week
And rather for the entire month of July
Voicemail question askers
Will be enter to win a Schlage
Lock
Because
Slings wide variety of smart locks let you create
Smart home of your dreams
Learn more about Schlage Smart Home Solutions and compatibility with Amazon
Apple
And Google Assistant products
Atchley
So if you want to be entered to win Schlage
And why wouldn't you
Please give us a call on the hotline at 5 1/2
6 to 3
742 4
And we
Mets
Play it and answer your question on the air and
You'll be entered to win
This week
Let's hear from
Larry
Hi this is Larry Reed still free to use
The message on the air
And I moved in together and
I switched everything
Over
Plum
My Amazon Echo
Google
What have you
My account
But I'm wondering
Should he have a loan account
And it's just her and I
Read this. The tile system
And I just added her
Under one account
That's the question
Kristoff
Congratulations for a big step in your relationship
There's a couple ways to answer this one is
By no means
No means at all due to accounts because you will end up doubling up on all of your stuff
I have tried this it
Not good
Amazon will think you have
Two lights
When you really only have one
And state gets messed up
It doesn't work just don't
Now
If it's already under your name and you don't want to mess with anything just keep it there and she can still do the commands of that sort of thing
This is for Madame a household
And then
The other option though
In their pros and cons to this
Is creating an email app
Your house
So
Have a house account
That you tie into your
Madam
The advantages are things like
I don't know if you Spotify but certain certain things that have limits associated with them
Well now
Be associated
The downside
Is
I don't remember how many adults you can have in a household
And you want your house email
An account to be
An adult
Then you may not be able to add your girlfriend to your car
Might be awesome for her cuz she could like order things on
Your account
So we'd have to check that but
The challenge if you don't do that is
Location stuff
Will still work but things like ordering
If you order stuff from Amazon it will
That's taking your relationship to a whole new level.
I do have a question only because you have multiple devices in multiple family members
Would you recommend
In either platform golang with like a voice match as well
No
I thought you might not
I hate the voice match
It doesn't work well for us
Because you also mentioned and you said you might be switching
Situation
Don't do voice match at all if you do Google home you can each have your separate accounts and tie them to one
Google device
At that actually solve the problem because you're going to have that individual
Accounts and data all tied into one platform
Voice match has to work a hundred percent or you're going to be miserable
Brightside my family refuses to be trained so I can't speak to it either
So there's your
You could always try the voice match if it doesn't work
Hopefully
That helps Larry and
Now
It is time
To say goodbye to Kevin
And say hello
Guest
Our guests coming up after the break is Andy Lowry who is the CEO of real where they make a
Connected
Head-mounted display
It is a voice-controlled for industrial settings
It's pretty cool and they just raised 80 million dollars which
It's kind of a lot so he's going to talk about
Why people use these
Some use cases and what they're going to do with it
For this
Hey everyone we are taking a quick break from The Internet of Things podcast for a message from our sponsor this
Sponsor is Dell Technologies and I have Jason Sheppard who is CTO of iot in
Edge at Dell Technologies here to talk to us
So json
Last week we talked about edgex Foundry and how that's going
This week let's talk about your
Scaling to the grey Lyndell strategy what is Dells as strategy
And how does it relate to Edge X Foundry
Yeah so basically the strategy was
Get an architecture that works for the edge out in the open crate open interoperability through that collaboration and then attached
Best commercial value add to it
Where infrastructure provider we bring Partners in for their domain expertise and we wanted that edge X
API that's developed through that collaboration
Value-add not only from ourselves but also partners
So this openedge stack is taking VMware pulse iot Center as a device management platform
Bison application
Are Photon OS
Which is a Linux variant running containers you can use any what you want but that Jack's that looks rating
Experience with a tough course Ajax
Is part of that
Where you get the benefit of
Consistent security and Management Open API driven by The Edge X Eco cyst
And then you were choices application stack so it's developer you can get get started really quickly and easily build on something that scale
But not get locked into any given platform which is currently this
The case with many of the platforms that are creating their own apis are on sdks who kept to get connected to their ass if they want to
Milwaukee went early and we're getting people choice
Okay and
Get our conversations around this you keep talking about scaling to the Grail and data monetization
Around the edge
What do you mean by that
Yes it's going to look really nice talk about that
My stuff online it's really about this notion of pervasive
Steering or monetization especially on your terms
Of data which is the obvious one
Resource
Compute storage networking
Rideshares anything consumable
Knowledge
Feeling like that sharing selling
Across
Complete strangers
I've never built a relationship with you
Able to sell you something in the way you do that is he build pervasive Truss
I need to get to the base of trust
You cannot have any single entity on the trucks he was in a water system system
Public and private domains Etc and sew
To get to the Grail you need technology to help
And you need an open Edge
This is why you know we're investing heavily here and then that enables you it's me sound far-fetched as notion of pervasive
Date of motivation but also the only
Pastor is it open
Edge and so the scale of the Grail is starting out with a simple use case just get going
Towards that ultimate goal
That's right Jason so where can we go to find out more about Dell Technologies
Dell Technologies. Com coyote is a good starting point and then there's been some banks offer their took over more
Hey every
I would welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest
Is Andy Lowry who is the CEO of
Hi Andy how are you doing
Good Stacy
Man I am super excited to have you here about to talk about something
Oh I don't know if I've been skeptical but we're about to talk about using AR in
The workplace in the Enterprise all the way from manufacturing to
Back in warehouses even two people riding around an ambulance
So there's a lot of stuff here first off
And let's talk about what it is the real where does
Our mission here at real where is
Train
Skilled industrial workers
We provide knowledge
And what I mean by that is there's tons of data
Out there in Cloud
What we do is we provide class
Hardware
Wearable computer heads up display computer that's a Android driven
Tablet
But it's shaped in a way that
Baseball caps that you can wear it hands-free
And you communicate and control the system using your voice
Particular voice
That allows this hands-free control
How's the computer that you're wearing is done and very very high noise
Environment
100 decibels you can barely
Kill yourself
Ekans
You can still control the system much better than most people's opinion
Home system
The device itself if I were to give you an elevator pitch were in an elevator going up
New York Tire
Taking only a few floors
The simplest way
The pictures is that it's an Android tablet
So start with that
It's got Wi-Fi
Bluetooth has got a nice Qualcomm processor
Has a little micro display that looks like a heads-up display
Which one dude
Looks about like a 7-inch tablet
Held at arm's length
Then you have a voice
System that uses a little bit of gestures like your head moving left and right
Keep scrolling
White things like that as a secondary input modality
The primary modality is just voice
And so
Where a lot of systems out there today have swipes or gestures
Halloween people are familiar with the hololens
Types of gestures there this blue man
Poke drag
What we do is we do
All of the heads-up display database
And that's just in a very big differentiator
Compared to a lot of the other
Systems that are out there
Something a little bit more Blended
Okay so
We figured out what it is you guys do
Where does it make sense what are the use cases that people are predominantly choosing
Your system for
What are the simplest ways
Disfigured stats at at the beginning
A lot of people talk about
Digitizing iot
Industrial iot
And what we see him on the home side is
You know a lot of sort of fragmented but ever-growing iot Solutions
Smart refrigerator
Stove mr.
On our side of the fence
Coyote takes
Extra step
And I tell a lot of folks that worked at Raytheon as a chief engineer
And iPhones came out in Circa 08
Raytheon didn't allow an iPhone
And the reason was all the stuff we're dealing with now in the iot
I said stuff like security
Safety ergonomics
Stability stability of the software
Need to check the block on
Actually
Moving towards an acquisition or
I'm more significant roll out
Consumers on the other side new Gadget comes out they want to see the latest
Greatest to go to the Best Buy that buy it
Integrated math Sawdust
Show in general what we're doing is taking those same digital stuff
FaceTime Netflix
Applying it to the industrial sector
What we're doing it a way that conforms to all the industry
That's about losing data.
Sure has to be 6 war in all of these different things
And what about the use cases for these head-mounted
Displays in general
Now if you're asking specifically what it when they get out there and they get the
All connected
What is it doing with these HMT
Well apart from doing
Capturing video and all that stuff
Which was
Stop sort of the elements of the digitization
Revolution that we need we need videos we need content
Get stuffed
Put into these systems that aren't
A pieces of paper and write written down notes Wheatley the actual digital content
So it's a great machine
Cuz you can wear it and can move the boom arm out of the way with no display just where is a GoPro on your heart
And everything you were doing you could capture all day long work
If you're in the warehouse you might have a baseball cap on you can capture your activity
And then those films can be basically slice two dice and they little YouTube videos on
How to do things inside the factory
Barbie on the concert
Three major classes
Software
That get deployed the first is collaboration software
Her folks are talking to each other
Come up remotes
Before maybe someone would call a headquarters and use your telephone to just get a voice
Walkthrough on how to fix something
Now with the today's text it's not
I required to have only
You can actually do video and voice
So with video and voice will you
You're sharing a screen and your doing this hands-free
You're able to talk to the person coach the person but then show the person
In the real world what were talking about
That you need to go do so maybe
Switch the switch off
Pekin Circle that switch with his lap
On his laptop with his Mouse
And see that switch from your camera
And then apply those to your circles
Huron your little screen
And then the third category
Is the category of human machine interface and this has to do with the data visualization but it also
You can think of Rockwell Collins Mitsubishi ABB Emerson
A number of folks are have
Iot systems that basically have
Giving machine interface in
Control things and push buttons and do that sort of stuff
Well in our system you can take that software put it on our computer
Now you can roll over on the plant in summer
500 yards away
The machine that has an alarm or or overheats and you can
Pull up that data
Control the machine from
500 meters away in in
All of these things have been
Really powerful from an Roi perspective Soak City
Come back to me and say
Charlotte like BMW came back inside a 75% reduction
In time to fix things and then all that and so there's no question
Return on investment
I believe I have actually played with your glasses I believe I tried them on an Emerson user event
One point in time
I'm so now I'm like oh
I think I found this
There are actual practical use cases you mentioned that BMW is seeing a 75% increase in productivity
Using this system
But
Why is it everybody used
Well it's just the time
I think it takes really to get
The Enterprise
Shillings
Face picture
Unstable enough with the
Device the technology and then the ecosystem
Support around
Specifically in the security Dimension you've got a lot of corporate forms and devices they absolutely have
Have to be encrypted
You can't take us with a backend API and have
Unencrypted data going from sap to a device I cars
It's absolutely has to have the rights
Deploy something to your folks that hopefully makes them work faster
It just doesn't work it just can't do that everything has to
Start with safety in today's day and age
And then finish with a higher productivity so safeties II
7/3 is
Just the
Stability and and what I mean by that is
When we get into the deployments at
Scale we're not talking about this
200 South
What are you talkin about that amount of scale and investment
Companies like Mitsubishi Electric Japanese company wants to see
Stability in space and stability
To ensure that the support will be there for
Perpetuity
So let's talk about some of the use cases you got here
Such as in remote guidance you were telling me a little bit about some of the medical use cases
What are people doing
Those are the type of use cases that get me
Excited due to the impact
We've got a couple different case
The Radio podcast show people are listening to imagine
The first thing we're talking about here
What were literally talking about
I think those people know what that is where you have
The video and the voice in your kind of at the same time collaborating what we're doing this from
Perspective the eyes out
Versus Two-Face
Are cameras focused out into the world
So can see through your eyes basic
What you're looking
Join the case of EMTs
In both the countries of Finland and Norway
Deploy into the axle ambulance
What they do is they come across the young boy who might have fallen down and has a very nasty abrasion
They actually use the HMT as they're treating the person insult you where they find of young man
Wasps they have an H
What the hmt-1 is doing this through cellular Networks
Screen Rant video
Back to the emerge
To see Rome. They're going to go to next
And showing these doctors what exactly is going on without the EMT having
Pause
Stop to do anything
MTC
Turn out the resuscitative types of medical procedures
And at the same time the doctors and nurses
They can prepare that
Arrival they can
Get the right beds the right doctors
Wright Medical Equipment ready and prepared
And then
Precious minutes
But that can save
Okay well there's a lot going on there
Hair sew-in something like that
There's so many questions that start with the technical question
This seems like one of those oh my gosh 5G use cases
We don't actually have five
Is this like an LTE network or how does this work in practice from a network level and even from Abyss
Who pays for these
That a great questions and there's lots of answers to it cuz it depends a little bit
I even have the issues in the US because EMTs are often insured by a different insurance
Hospitals are in feathers
Conflict in the business you know he say hey let's just do what's best for patients but then you always run up against business challenge
From time to time
I guess from a technology point of view you're right you've nailed it when you focus
Connectivity is what makes us
First of all it is not an LTE
Riven Android tablet it is a wifi-only
So if we do go to LTE we connect via hotspot so Verizon has a hotspot and a number of other
Companies Huawei has one that we actually connect to
Basically that then
Kansas off into the cellular network mostly for Jeeps
Chihuahua and stuff for doing the local to an actual
Facility that they've begun to sort of
Experiment with
White area coverage
5G that's not here yet
And as we're looking at why they recover
Certified G
This frequency spectrum is
Is all over the place
Depending on where you are from a geography point of view
Until we do have plans to continue
The modularity approach
Because our customers are so global
IGN China versus 5G in the US
That's kind of Honor roadmap
For future products and everything else will come out about the time 5G starts to gain momentum
So you guys recently raised 80 million in debt and equity and that is a lot of
Money
What are you guys going to do
Two major areas of frost one is around getting these
Deployments
Be a little bit more
Easy to do and and what I mean by that is
Water solution
Weird
The moving towards sort of a real where is a service model where we'll bundle
Things together into kind of a single offering and then just drop it in
Install a train and then leave and and that sort of
Motions different than today's motion where a lot of it is
Hey do a trade study on the hardware do a trade study on the soft
ZR1 price per user per month for everything installation Hardware shopper
On the tailor that is basically and
Expansion of Versailles
Especially when it comes to the installation folks in the training folks in the technical folks sets
But nevertheless can help deploy
And then the second area is around research and development
Mostly developed
We got two classes of products
Schlitterbahn
The bounding edges of where we sit in the ecosystem and and industries
I want is the hololens which
Isaiah stereoscopic system
Ideas
Towards products that may make immersive AR a little bit more
Easy to do so there's a better way to do that
And still keep it safe than the way we're doing it today
I am we got a work-in-progress right now that will take away eventually to something that looks more
Like immersive AR or something that would be able to
Soda compared immersive AR
And then on the other end of the steps
We have folks like Google Glass and a whole bunch of
Chinese competitors in the same sort of will
Sugar is in need for lighter-weight indoor systems as well
There's a couple different ways or else we can go to market looking at lightweight systems but basically I have those from a
Hardware perspective in my bullseye
And then from a software perspective it's all about the
Platform show at each one of these
If you think of them
We need to build the nest as well make sure that Nest is
Go Boston comfortable
What about you I'm talking about his mobile device
Mobile application manager
Different microservices in the cloud to help enable these things
Because while you deploy 10000
Hmt-1 sore
Any wearable system for Enterprise or even any
Phones
Or tablets for Enterprise
Is very different than the way you do it as a consumer because there's a consumer kind of your own admin your own it it's sort of us
Team of one
Whereas in Enterprise you're deploying 10,000 systems you might have one admin
She's running all 10006
Needs to be a little bit different
Then what Google provides consumers and others like that and that's what we're building
In a world where we have these this awesome connectivity and we have
This sort of technology in the in the nest that you are so thoughtfully build for us
What becomes possible what is that look for
What we love to think about it real where what we're doing is
Enabling sort of the 21st century maker
Jones furniture makers are Folks at work with their hands
I come from a family of sheet metal workers
Grassland
Next Generation
Digital worker
With the same sort of
The Clark College of the road
Where we sit here and Vancouver Washington
I bet trains new automotive tech
Patience
How to do edging
Well, part of their curriculum now for a day they spend
Learning about the HMT
Because how that will turn them into a 21st century worker
Is so much faster
Then the workers
20th century
Because they're able to get the
Basics
Word directly to a contributional sort of
Position on the team
Because they have with some of these digital tools to help them be the sort of half
Human half computer type
I watch did you ever hear of something called
Centaur chess
I have no idea what you're
This is a fascinating thing and trust me I mean if we
State came out with
The beat of
Kasparov
Grandmaster chess champion in 1997
Beat Buy
Deep blue with IBM computer
We all kind of
Echoed across the whole globe about this idea
Oh man the computers are smarter than people
But what Gary did was say na they're not smarter than
Because the computer didn't play the game of chess that I play
However
Computer to maximize with a computer
Centaurs
Mythological creature
Half horse half man
The idea would be the man would be the
Intuitive
Creative
Type source of knowledge
And the horse would be your bootstrap
Powercranks rocks
Make sure it's Eric fruits that sort of thing
It was a little bit
More harmonious than a cyborg
Some people caught cyborg chest
But this chess is played at the highest level of chest
History
Play time
It's virtually are proof and you got the greatest chess Minds the world
Creatively
Doing each other
On a chessboard at a very high high high level
What we're doing is doing the same work reading a centaur works
This Workforce of centaurs
That'll be
Digital
What's the tools like the HMT that
Go into the field and take a vacation
It's a very well take these folks will be welcome
Because other skills are so much higher than a conventional
That has to go back home not sure how to fix this
Let me get someone else out there
I get my supervisor there
Additional worker
Will be able to diagnose people in
Pedialyte
Minor it is
When you try to make
Translate that out to a global scale and as we're building infrastructure of things like
Wind power
Geothermal
And all of these things that will begin a world that will be
Truly lower lower marginal cost
Truly less and less dependent on scarce resources
So that the idea of sharing economy something that is
Jeremy Rifkin does a very good speech on this
About a sharing economy where we reduce the margin
Anything that we do energy we make Logistics
The knowledge
She nearly zero and then in that sort of contest
We told the world that is
A lot less prone to have us fighting over
The scraps
Like we do today like we did in the industrial
Play the next two generations will be the workforce that actually
Implement
Wechat infrastructure
Build the world
That is much more orientated on creativity
And the
Potential of the human race
Fighting over little scribbles and scraps
Okay that's a fun big vision
All right will Andy I feel like I've learned a lot
Thank you so much
For coming on the show The
You're very welcome say you had a great time that's it for this week thanks
How much for listening and remember if you'd like more iot news sign up for my newsletter at Stacy on ice
Coyote.com will see you next week