Hey everyone welcome to the 217th episode of The Internet of Things podcast
This is your house
Stacey Higginbotham
Kevin tofel
And we have a show that is designed to make your life
Easier we are going to
Talking about a new product
New products from
Wise
Comcast
Thinking about your health
Mediatek
As lunch some rich iot chips
Networking explained
GMC car manufacturer is now doing one of the best product
This is insecurity
Yay
What is the one-year anniversary of GDP are the European General data protection regulation so we're going to talk about what
That has meant
Europe tech companies and us
And we got a lot of little news from Google to find Lenovo
Arduino and more
I guess this week is Zach
Sao Paulo
Who is CEO of particle he's going to be talking about the big mistakes people make when they scale-out their iot to play
And where you have a message from our sponsor Dell Technologies
So is it Jam
Impact show I'm going to
Kick It Off
What the message from one of our other sponsors
Nordic semiconductor
Kickstart your short-range wireless application ideas with the nrf52840
40 is the most advanced and flexible short-range Wireless solution available today the NRA
RF 52 8:40 is a highly Advanced ultra-low-power system-on-a-chip that can eat just about any required
In ultra-low-power Wireless applications is Broad protocol support including
All of its features Bluetooth LE thread zigbee ant
And 2.4 gigahertz proprietary radios with protocol concurrency options
The NRF
50 to 840 can support the most demanding applications which is cortex
M4f CPU
And one megabyte of Flash and 256 GB of RAM
Was it stack with on-chip peripherals including
USB
Giselle
Quad SPI in NFC
Everyone knows the software makes the difference in the NRF
50 to 8:40 is backed up with an unrivalled selection of comprehensive sdks covering of Vassar
Gradle application
Get you building tomorrow's great products
Find out more at
Www.nordictrack.com nrf52 8:40
Hey
Heaven
I am super excited about this product we saw it at
CES
Amazing
Everybody who has smart
Connected light bulbs
It is upset with the fact
If you turn the switch off
Bulbs
You're both stopped working
There's now a solution
And it's an easy solution
So easy
Lutron is made
The Aurora which is a device that you're going to stick on your traditional lights
And then
It basically converts them to a Smart Switch without any
Wiring in a screwdriver eating anything like that
And
I
So excited about the
It's cuz I'm about to move into a rental house
And I have Philips hue light bulbs that I'm going to want to connect this to
Then I can basically in my rental house
How smart lighting that doesn't break
When someone turns off
Wichita
Whatever that is Keith this it this is interesting because you said there's no wiring involves right
Traditional you'd have to
Swap out a switch
To make it tomorrow
It literally has a little
I caught like a plastic round part that goes over your existing light switch
And then on top of that you basically snapping a
Rotary
Dial
And the product has a queen-size battery that lasts for 3 years
That's it you just snap it on
Yeah
So you can turn on your lights
From the switch
Nobody will be like
You've broken my functionality
And it also helps because people who don't
Know about Smart Homes are do not want to talk to like Madam and tell her to turn on and off the lights
This is wonderful
The downside to this
Is
It only works if you like
And you have to have a hue
You do not however have to have a flu shot
So yeah
You win some you lose
Yeah you been using me for this so you have to have some kind of
Sometimes Bridge box
If you already have one
It's really a non-issue
The other thing I question the price at $40 a pop because
There's not much to this thing so I would look at things like that and like
Panel
A piece of plastic and a battery and
What radio
Save you a ton of time
Keeper
Then irregular
Smart Switch
And I would say I mean again if someone who's moving into a rental and I'm sure we're going to have a show all about
Gadgets that Stacy is put into a rental unit to make it
Behave intelligently
But as someone in that position I was actually thinking about
I have become dependent on my Smart switches that I have throughout my
My home
And what am I going to do to replace a
Now the answer is
Buy a bunch of expense
They're still like $15 a ball
So it's still an investment
When you're talking about like having legs
4 downlights or something
But
Then you never have to get up
Couch
Yay
So this should actually work even if like you're humming
Yes
It should
So I'm actually getting
Some of these so in about a week or two when I finally moved into my new house
Hallelujah
Try them out
Write a review and tell you guys about it on the Pike
Cast because
Also
In lighting
Wise
The company that is famous for its $20 camera and the fact that it makes profit
Has
Launched LIPA
Oops
And basically with the wise light bulbs you can buy
A 4-pack for 30 bucks which I did so
Going to try these out there
Ship in the middle of June
And unfortunately they will not work
With the Philips Hue Lutron setup
But why it does not work
With Google
Assistant
It does and this actually just happened earlier this week and some people may go into their Google Assistant
Settings and not find wise in there to link to their account
Is it a staged rollout
It should have for me earlier this week
And linked It Up by like I would with anything else but
I think there's still some work that needs to be done because they're testing it with my Nest holographic all the nest
It's going to be Google home hub or whatever
When I tell the Google Assistant to show like my driveway where I have a wyzecam
Sometimes it takes 5 seconds and it works sometimes it takes 15 seconds
Think there's some optimization that really need to happen
However
I'm thrilled that it's finally here
And I would expect those optimizations to happen and things
Better
You know as again
Staged rollout usually things are like what is demand for this how can we optimize for this
We'll see then
Right
I presume that when these bulbs
How to
Cancel pre-order right now
Expect automatically work with
Google Assistant
Because that integration is already there
Watusi
Just to be clear of those balls that you ordered
Cartoon
Snot color
But for the price I was like heck yeah they're like
Less at their 7
Which is
Excellent
Christ will see how long they last
They're only in the a19 so
If you burn down
And I should also mention
Four people cuz why is his
They're in a row right now they just launched their sensor
Can't we talked about last week
All of these work
Proprietary sub
It's 915
What they're using
Xian Subway
But it's not going to work with a Bluetooth there's a beer things like that so
That is a
A little bit of a bummer
Your trade off here is
It's so cheap
So you don't need a hub for this
Connect directly to Wi-Fi so
Yay for that but
It will work with like the sensors in
Basically
You can use like normal things like scheduling vacation mode
You can also
Group the lights in the wise app
Control them is one
There's no light switch them
We'll get there and it works with shift so I wonder actually you'd have latency that
Everybody hates
I wonder if you could actually connect
Bia Italy
The Hue stuff off to play around
So we'll see what happens here but
Smoking hot deal otherwise light bulbs if you're in the wise world
Maybe try these out
For cheap mine I mean these things could replace my cheapie Cree bulb so I tend to buy
I know you said cheap but I'm going to say creep
As in Comcast
Is creeping on your health
CNBC reporter this week
The Comcast
Was working on some sort of device
It was going to be focused on people's hell
They said it was a smart speaker
Comcast later clarified
It's actually going to be
Sensor
And what it sounds like
Emotion detection sensor
Yeah
It's going to use algorithm
Determined
Is someone moving around the house
Yes that means there
Not Dead
Are they moving at this range
Yes that mean
Things are probably pretty healthy
And we talked about this a couple times in the show but there are definite research studies that show things like
Hey
How many times a day a person goes to the bathroom is an indicator of how healthy they are
And so you can see Comcast pulling
Data like that from the motion sensor to give
Some sort of Health score or
Let people know that their loved ones are okay without involving the camera or anything weird
Right and help Focus
Comcast cable
They're going to pitch this towards people with
Etcetera
Please talk to Lourdes Hospital licorice Engadget about using devices
Hospitals as well so
Aye yai battling mainstream
Consumers that are healthy healthy or going to
Going on a desperate haste there's a huge need for this
Species or population
Yeah and I actually get I filled a couple questions from people when they find out what I do about aging-in-place like there
What can I get for my parents so I know that there are
We may not want them at our house is a relatively younger and healthier person
But we may want them for
I left
And
Not having a camera is going to be
But you'll have to wait
Comcast is going to start testing this at the end of
2019 release date
Is probably 20 20 or
Possibly even later
The other question that's raises in my mind
And is holy cow
What kind of Privacy Rule
Rosewill Comcast
Map to follow
And
Look at how Comcast is like really Building Services in the Smart Hub I have long said that they have
Very forward-looking
Very good at offering
Compelling services in this is
Possibly another one
Yes maybe definitely
Branching out
I just don't know
And I could be just as arguable quotes
They have a stigma
Cable operations
Customer service in service and general is not good
That is arguable
I'm sure many people are happy with
The compass that's fine
But I wonder if they can overcome
On people who haven't believe
And also
People worry about how much
Other data Comcast already Jets
Yeah you know between
Your internet you so maybe
MTV cetera
Do you really want now get very personal data
Going to them
Well I will let you know because
Again in about 2 weeks I'm going to become a Comcast
I say two weeks it's actually
This week's podcast will be produced in Austin
Ashley next week's will be produced in Oz
What time it goes out I will be in Seattle
But I will become a Comcast customer so I'll let you know how
I'm dying to know how your experience goes
They're my backyard here in Philadelphia
Yes and your Verizon FiOS
Yes I am
Also this week in chip news because I can't leave the chips
Out of this mediatek
Which
Is a Taiwanese chip company that
Came to prominence for making
Really good soces at a lower price than Qualcomm
They have done really well in the smart
Market
And now they've announced date what they call a rich iot program
And what this is is a bunch of their chipsets are going to have the ability
Do a eye on them at a lower battery
Consumption
And this is going to be for voice so AI algorithms associate with boys
With object recognition
Computer vision
And then also for powering displays so all of this is the smart home stuff
Design for
Again
Low battery consumption
Cheap pricing
And the ability to have some sort of intelligence
All this means from a consumer perspective
Is we're going to see a lot of devices come on the market with Laura
Yeah just to give a vacation all because I followed them in the smartphone
Tablet market for years
If you take a look at two very similar products whether to phone or tablet doesn't matter
Run has a
Qualcomm chip one has a mediatek chip
You probably looking at
Andrew East I-25
Percent cost
Difference on the low side
Wow
At least
Cheap displays, your way
All right
That is it that news and let's talk about sex
Security specifically uses
Security at 4
Vehicles in best practices
So one of the best practices for security
Patching is over there updates when I
When people ask me like what can I do to make sure my connected devices are secure
I tell them all the stuff about hate
Google and see how they react
Problems are vulnerabilities
Bounty program
Good passwords and I always ask and I'm like they should have over the air update
What GM is now saying that it will offer over the air updates to most of its Vehicles by 22
I think this is good
I do drive a Tesla and it updated software all the time
Most automakers have not done this in a
Heart is because they were worried about connecting cars to the internet because it introduces
It is a surface area of attack in
It could be scary
Yes
I know you have your Tesla and
You can have any software updates and haven't had issues and so on so forth
IC
Tesla as a leader in this
Kinetic artistry
Very capable
I am a little leery when
GM and others I'm sure there will be other car manufacturers get into this space
I just don't have the faith that
It will work
Properly
All the time and it needs to and I say that because just look at
Not quite the same situation but the aircraft
Software introduced problem
I would say in something like that
What the challenge that's not an over-the-air
Correct
Yes
It's a testing problem and I think
The capability
Is really important
Challenge associated with that capability is too full
You have to secure that
Connection to
If you can change the functionality of a vehicle
Anytime you want
That doesn't add a responsibility and QA it's an added responsibility
In terms of life cycle
Software lifecycle management
And hopefully
GM it has
The capabilities and it is aware of
So it is kind of like going cuz like
Now we're seeing with the Boeing 747
737 Max
We're talking about like oh they were unaware that
This update actually
Change the functionality of this particular button
A machine like that
Cedar stained with every line of code does it how
You're right it's more about that not the delivery mechanism it is more about the testing
I don't know something just skeeves me out about this site I guess I just don't
Faith energy
That's a person
And that's something all of these companies are going to have to deal with
And
If since we're talking about it I'll bring up the fact that there's an opinion article in the New York Times this week all about
Driver data
And
How customers
Consumer to buy
Why cars are not aware
Not aware of the type of data that
Parking
Gather
This is my man named Bill
Handy who is President Chief Executive
Of the Auto Care Association
The Articles actually called
Your car knows when you gain weight
Which I guess it does cuz they do have sensors in the seats now that you're there
I don't know if I
I want my car to be like you should drive me lesson walk mower
Possibly
But the point there is like
Hey
When you have over the air updates
You also have this two-way communication where your car could be like
Tattling on you in a way that
I know you had to stick those OBD Port monitors
I've also wonder and this is for cars that have built-in Connectivity Source not like
You will connect your car to your home internet and get the
The downloading update there
So I don't know how big these updates can be and probably
Does Tesla actually tell you or you just
Say
It just shows you hey I update your software
I'm sometimes it'll tell you anything cuz a time estimate like this will take about 40 minutes
Some of that dates are quite
But Tesla pays for my connectivity
Yes
I don't know that
GM. Blind a Chevy Bolt
I would love to see them spell that out because I I don't
Use the
LTE integrated into my Chevy Volt
I get software updates
Dealer which is very rare mean
Once a year I get an oil change
Rotate tires every
Power off Lionel drive that much
So
I'd like to know that you have to pay for that
Realty service
Jesus all right well
Well I hope they do that and have data
Car sharing data other things sharing data
What is the first anniversary of the general data protection regulations from the EU
And
It's time to say
Kush
What's happened
He answered
At least in the EU not much here in the US
Just as a refresher gdpr basically cave
People rights around their data
And
You as an individual or as a citizen of the EU basically could say
Hey stop collecting my day
What data are you collecting use
Requested
You could ask companies to change data that wasn't right you could retroactively pool access to your data
The EU has published data about
The number of cases and
Things like that associated with
This legislation
Should I pull citizens and
As of March 2019
Two-thirds of EU citizen
Hold said they knew with gdpr was
They are about 1/3 a little over 1/3 new what it is
Tails
And
Over half said
Yes they know that there is an agency out there trying to
Protect their data
What that means
Cases is
They had
A lot a lot they have
I was like
Yeah
And these cases are just
Complaints maybe maybe
Customer found that there
Data wasn't being cryptic because that's required as part of
Tpr's well
Yeah like a half of them we're just like
Complaints
Almost 90000 of data breach notifications and then the rest were
I don't know whatever
But two-thirds of those cases have been closed I presume to people satisfaction because
1%
Cases have been appealed
And the rest are still ongoing
This is great because it shows how active
These
Restrictions are being
Recognized by consumers
Being questioned cementation questioning
Licensing issue
I think it's great for the night
Yeah and I haven't seen it at wholesale stoppage of the European economy
So also good there
As part of this and maybe because
Maybe because it's Brad Smith and he's being a thought leader here but Brad Smith over at Microsoft
Is called for
The US
To implement its own
Version of gdpr
An Apple has also called for the
Best and
That's now Microsoft and app
Apple saying
Hey this law isn't terrible
Let's get something like that here
And the big things that they're focused on is
You have to have a reason to process the data you can just gather data for
So you don't like your car can't just be like
This is how much someone weighs
Personal data must be encrypted
People in consumers have a right to a copy of their data
And they have a right to ask for their data to be.
I'm all for it
I'm not going to lie
A sticking point
Is who enforces the rules
Will in the EU they created a separate agency
Who does that
So
I would imagine
We would have some sort of federal agency FTC
I know there's lots of
Debate
The FTC resent not the FTC
I hate the creation of new government agencies with the FTC can be like really held over by politics
But
Something is better than nothing I don't know or not
But if we did though
Not about gdpr
But about enforcing privacy rules Mozilla has created a
Petition
Calling on Amazon
To make sure all the Smart Home Products are all the connected products sold on its site
Come with a privacy
Because not everything does
I think that's actually not a number
I think
Having Amazon or a federal legislation actually helps because if it's Amazon
What happens is
You'll have to click through or see a privacy policy associated with the device if everyone has one is not a competitive advantage
Are people who don't
Two processes may be a little
So horsing everyone to behave
According to the same rules is actually a nice thing to
Is not part of this conversation company we're going to talk about a little bit next
That would be correct
I'll take what is Google for $500
Yay
About the new glass Google Glass
Yes the new one is for Enterprise has its fancy rats
Cheaper and
More battery efficient
I believe in better
Just generally better
It's more better
And another little news bits
Savant
Which is a
I always call it the apple of smart home systems like professional smart home systems they have rolled out
How can support including something pretty neat which is circuit breaker control
Explain why the school
So it's about already has a circuit breaker controls but now they have a
Pinion module
That
Is Chromecast compatible so
Like I'm assuming I could like when I'm swapping out switches and what not
Instead of running up and down two flights of stairs
See if I switch the right breaker
Mentally I could
Turn the breaker off using homekit
Yes that is my thought here to end
This was actually a future
I feel like Savant launched it back at
Syria in 2017 and there are actually several
Other professionals EDS type installers who are
Messing around with circuit breaker
Boxes in control of those in Part B
Because
They were thinking about things like demand response in the future
Electricity
And apparently really wealthy people like
Dedicated control of these things I don't know but it was a big deal
So
This is it it's a nice product it's a nice add onto a nice system if
And in fact that homekit support does go beyond just
Circuit breaker band
It works with light bulbs in their LED DMX LED light strips
It's a broader solution
Yes and
There is a new smart clock in town the Lenovo smart clock for
Google
Have already gone live
And this device ships on June 2nd $79
I actually saw this at CES this year back in January
And I've wondered about I thought it was just like a
A reference is on or something when it when I walk into the
I guess I should say for the Press
But no it said it was an actual projects
Little smart clock it's like a
Maybe a forage displayed at 4
IPS screen
It looks like
The Lenovo smart display that I have
Obviously it smaller
It's not something to watch a video on and do things regular screen or larger screen
It does have a 6 watt speaker
You can add it to a home speaker group
It's got the microphone privacy switch that the nest Hub has
School
And yeah I mean it's just perfect
Size 4
Display
Especially one with camera
Cuz it doesn't have one
On their nightstand
Another Google home
Nice
Okay
And
We've got a
Other tiny little bits of news
Which is the
A German smart thermostat maker has
Stay home 2 compatible smart AC controller
It's really for the UK and EU area so, coming or going to get here
In the US at least
But they make a nice looking
Thermostat product
You do and they make a nice radiator turning knob date they make some really good looking
So this is basically you can
AC controls to your home with us
So this will work ethics and also
Amazon so
It's available there for 90 pound
Guess that's roughly
100 letter $10
But it doesn't matter cuz you can't buy here
This is our gift to our UK listeners
Find a little bit of news is Arduino has available
And we
We love our Arduino
The cheapest one
Is the Nano every it's a
Actually $10
It's got a microcontroller
She's got it
Clash a rama and
They also have the Nano
33 iot is $18 it has Wi-Fi and Bluetooth and
Also a microcontroller
Again
M32
Gabby's abuser
Small tomato
Products project Etc not a smart home system
I gave us play around with some stuff they have
To Nubia Bluetooth low-energy boards as well
So
You don't just check out if you're
You're hankering for a project and you went you don't need much you just want to build something that does a little something
All right and now it is our favorite time of the week it's time for The Internet of Things podcast hotline where we listen
Questions from you and
Try to give a dancer
Ciot podcast hotline is brought to you by Schlage
Saints wide variety of smart locks lets you create the smart home of your dreams
Learn more about Schlage Smart Home Solutions and compatibility with Amazon
Apple
Google assistant and more
At schlage.com iot
Baidu
Love these locks and I cannot wait
To get into my new home so I can actually try the encode lot which is their wife
It is about time
All right
So this week's voicemail is from
Josh
Let's hear it
Hi Stacy and Kevin this is Josh.
Eagan Minnesota
Please feel free to use this on your show if you'd like
My question is regarding automation I really would like
To be able to know with high degree of accuracy
If people are in or not in a given room
The bedroom
The family room
Wherever so that I
Can adjust light
Denim-on-denim off
Depending upon if there is anybody in
That room
And I'm just wondering what's the best solution for that what's up is it a combination of sensors
Korath our special sensors to help with that kind of a problem
How what is the best way to
No
If there is somebody in a room or not
Thank you so much for all your help
Appreciate it
Josh
This is something
Men
Kevin and I've been talking about
Years and years and years
And we actually have some options for you which is a surprise
Because we looked at this
You know when you when you left your voicemail we're like okay
We don't have anything great for it we've got
Motion sensors
Which will tell you that someone has entered a room and you could use
Turn on lights in
AC in
Things like that
But it's kind of sucky if you want to do like
Personalization or something a little bit
But we just discovered
A new product
Buy in
Tell her things
We discovered
Rumor me it is a
Sensor that basically
The Bluetooth readings from your phone and uses that to say out
Kevin's phone
Kevin
Has entered the room
And
You can buy a starter kit
For $124
And a sensor on its own without the starter kit
It's going to be $70
What does this do
Well
Basically just says this Smartphone is
Mounts on the ceiling
And
It's actually kind of cool
I do everything reminds me
I got excited about the beacon technology
Several years back which
Never really made it to the smart
Yeah we talked about a company called zuly they actually made they
Put beacons basically
Smart outlets and I was super excited about them and
Yeah
Just hasn't happened
I think a lot of people kiss I didn't want to do this there like that tells me that somebody is in the room
As opposed to what I can do and I want is
It tells me
A particular someone is in the room
Customizes automation controls based on purses
Personal choices
That just hasn't happened since she's just makes sense
If you're carrying your phone around the house most people do I know Stacy
I think most people do or this evening
Yeah I was just going to say but a lot of people
Absolutely thin
Caring wearing it so
I think this is a great idea
There is a bit of a downside because of his
It doesn't work
Anastasia
So it does work with some but not all Philips Hue smart bulbs
Works with lifx original and mini smart bulbs
The Bose sound wireless speakers
And ecobee
Yeah which is a smallest when you think about
Product that is not what they made for worship Google or works with matinee program play
To that program
Because then the whole world approximately
I would also say that the wages work
Is whoever set this up becomes
The Room Master
I really like the state of I am the Ambassador
I am done
What was at the GateKeeper
The key master key master
There we go
Ghostbusters
Anyway as a roommaster whenever you enter the room all settings will revert to your preference
And when you leave it will revert to the next highest ranked person in the room
Oh that's the problem with the kids
Isn't that guy is he ranked higher than me
Oh Lord
I'm going to say that's going to be a problem would like the spouses
My husband be like
Why is it suddenly so hot and
How it's so wonderful
Thanks nobody ever
Josh this is your problem I'm not owning this one cuz I have not going to rain tonight
There you go so Josh that is our solution for you I wish we had something that works with everything
What is more comprehensive
There is another option I mean aside from the motion sensor switch
There are tons of motion sensor options were there in a light switch
Or they're just a standalone Center like that the borrower
There are tons of motion sensors out there
There and their
Not a problem did you have a hub in most cases
Just for the show we also found this
Minute Prada
Oh yes I forgot about the minute
Yeah that we can't speak to how well it works because we literally just got out of
For the show
Can you reach out to them already for
Getting some
Yes this is a security product it is a device that use lap onto a magnetic
East Gretta magnetic plate to your ceiling and you slept this
Sensor packed
Talk to it
And it does
Motion humidity
Temperature
Detection
It so it'll listen for window glass breakage as the
Madame agar does now
But it doesn't have
Tamara so the people who are focused on
Privacy error going to be
Kind of excited about
Set a remind me kind of like
Maybe something that Comcast is
So it has all of these kind of neat features plus it works with Madam a and Google Assistant
Which means you might be able to and I can't tell you until I try this
Use the sensors in that to control things happen
House
Again it won't
Detective
If a text doesn't detect individual
Rice device is $149
And you can get a two pack
230.
I think it's got a pretty sweet
It is security-focused for the most part
Motion detection or personal
Presence
President General
Which is why we brought it up
That's the key because a lot of people don't want cameras in every room
Which I totally
Yep all right we'll Josh hopefully this helps you and
Everyone else please stay tuned because
We'll have our guest Zach's Apollo who is the CEO of particle
He's going to be talking about a survey they just released
All about what industries are using iot
What use Industries
And
Some of the Lessons Learned as company scale
Which is a big deal
Before we get to that
We are going to hear from
This week's sponsor Dell Technologies
From The Internet of Things podcast for a message from our sponsor sponsor is Dell Technologies and today
We're doing by Brian Jones was a general manager for the
OEM and iot solutions
Installation at Delta
Brian I understand you were also recently asked to serve as one of the executive sponsors
Technologies iot and Edge
Can you please please share with us how your group is
Thank you thanks for having me on it's really great to have an opportunity to chat with
So from an alien perspective
Helping them take their IP combined it with our technology and create a new product that they take the market
And our customers have been doing iot since long before iot had a name
Natural
Place that help with the iot and adjectives
And so what we do is we really help customers focus on and delivery
Health and compress their time-to-market
So they focus on their it
We focus on
The technology platform in the integration of it
The second piece is really delivering tier-1 technology and that should one technology gets them the very best Quality Inn
Customer experience
And then the last piece is one of their multinational or they're a small software startup
We help them scale globally reducing cost
Complexity
And taking their product to a global market
Excellent and I understand that your division is Pretty in Pink
Compared to what most of my audience thinks about
Sunday think about Dell Technologies
They're thinking servers in PC
But your division focuses more on Factory floors than data set
It's OT
Not it
Is that right
That's right
Example of an oem customer is their developing software
So a lot of
Champs cancer medical device
They're developing the software in the actual
Scan devices
All of that needs to run
On a server ditch in a maybe it's very hard
Operational environment high temperature
Vibration and so we help them develop
Platform solution
Okay and so how does your OEM division
Really help those
Customers
Get ahead
We are really focused on
First
The IP that they're developing is
And we help them surround that I T with
The right technology +
And we're drawing from all of Dell Technologies to not just deli and seeing Hardware
Everything that makes up Dell technology
This is part of the pallet that we can help a customer to paint their product
And so at the Dell Technologies
Hardware software services
Program manager
Engineering
All of that together too
Creating that new product based on their IP and our technology
But that customer then takes the market
Awesome
So where can folks go
To learn more
For more information
Cabela's
Go out to Delhi nc.com
Hey everyone
Welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham at today's guest is Zach Supply
Halle who is the CEO of
Particle
Hi Zach how are you
I'm doing great how are you
Excellent all right we have not talked in
Like
A year or two and I'm hearing that things are
Different
At particles so let's
Kick it off with
An update on where things are at particle
Probably for everyone who doesn't know you
Guys what you actually do
Yeah absolutely so
Backstory on particle we are
Internet of Things device platform so we help companies who are
Making Internet of Things products
Connect those products to the internet
Work with a bunch of different manufacturers and
Distributors a lot of folks
Made
Products that weren't yet connected and wanted to add connectivity those products
He also worked a lot of entrepreneurs and startups were building new products from
Incorporate connectivity
And we provide all of the
Connectivity networking infrastructure
Ranging from the hardware that's embedded
Buy the product
Chill
Networking stack to cloud services that expose devices for API
Everything in between
End
Right now
Your customers
I assume Spanish
Dammit so let's talk about
You recently did a survey where you asked about 800 Developers
What they're using iot for how they're building stuff
And
What did you find
Let's let's start with the top probably Industries where I'm at
Yeah
So we'll start with where I think I accused
Become most successful if we think about
The market
The most excited about Ice-T
Oec is a
Manufacturing
Healthcare
Energy agriculture technology
Because
Any technology company is
Thinking about
Some way
Engage with it
Interesting about that is
Okay those Industries makes sense it makes sense that you would see this Earth heavier Industries
With often more
More expensive products
With more like maintenance problems that those are the places where we see is you being successful
I think what's interesting is was not on that
Which is to say consumer and I think that consumer adoption of it has
Of course a number of
Like they break out successes but if you look more broadly across the industry
I think we're in a little bit of
The trough
Can I cycle
I'd like the trough of disillusionment
Yes exactly
Which is to say like that was a
. we're
Andorra founded
Really
Early days of it when things will really start to take off and it was a lot of interesting excitement around consumer
We're just not seeing the best
Yesterday and it squeaks
Anecdotal
The customer is where
More and more we're helping
Connect big dirty heavy machines where there's a lot of
Operational burden of managing that piece of equipment and
Text people who have to deal with maintenance
Uptime
And those creator
Opportunities to solve real problems variety because
I can do a better job of making
Machine
He's working because I have sensors in the machine
I can get it from them
Machine that leads to various
Very clear
Solutions
The problems that
Meaning of these initiatives actually get out the door and do actually scale
Yes cuz I feel like in the consumer
Even today
The use cases are not clear the expense associated with connected devices is
Hi
And the maintenance and ability to like make things work
Pull something
Together
Is really difficult because there's no stand
So I'm I'm with you on that so let's talk about how those kind of Trends related to
I don't know if we want to break it out by industry cuz he may be a little bit different but
When we start the use cases very clear a lot of the things that are happening happen
Roi associate with them it's pretty easy to see
What about standards like
Howard Lee agricultural or manufacturing or healthcare companies buying the
Is today do they think about things working across many different platforms or do they just like
I need something to monitor my
Trunks in refrigerators
I need something
Track the
The placement of
Seeds in my feels
So I think it really ends up being a question of what environment is the product
Sequoia
Important
Is it that it work with other products in that entire
Example of like
Factory
Pretzel Factory is a place where you have
A whole bunch of
Problem
That you want to try
Find salt dr-t
Are about the Inn
Interactions of those machine
For instance if I'm trying to
You know make my manufacturing line more efficient and I want to be able to track for the levels of like work in progress
Inventory I can't just have
One machine for sending me that day.
I need sort of all of the
Machines in the line to be
Giving me data and then I have a
Problem
Figure out how to get all the
Hands together and so we think of that is
Heterogeneous
Which is to say like lots of different I have
Nike products
One another and that's where I think
Standards are really important
Keurig 2.0
A lot of dust
Sandra's haven't been
Settled and are
Still in development and
Standards Wars that are going on in the crease of challenging Mini cases with successfully DuQuoin heterogeneous
He'd appointment
Is inhomogeneous
Which is to say
Widgets and I make $100,000
And they're almost
Deploy them all over the world
And a lot of cases
Supreme since we have a customer who's using us to monitor air condition
Air conditioner is r
Different air conditioners are a little different and they're in residential units in their commercial units but the fundamental principle
How to operate are the same
And every air conditioner is
Is a stand-alone Prada
So when you're trying to for insta
Monitor the air
And if you want to be able to improve
Service
Air conditioner
Then you really only need data from that
One device
And so standards and integrating with other
Machines and equipment
Isn't as important in that environment another example this is working with a company that manufactures
Dental operatory equipment the machines that are in
Dentist offices
Machines but they tend to be more
Stand-alone equipment
Not as complex of an environment at a factory
And those are cases where we seen products be
Successful getting to Market because essentially you're not
Waiting on
Ecosystem to develop you have a
Product
The problem
Directly
And the fact that there is
Continuing standard warranty IIT doesn't really keep you from being able to go out and solve your problem
Have you had any clients that have built out a homogeneous infrastructure
And then suddenly looked up in bed like
Oh I really wish we could connected to this thing
Tried to move to the next level if you have what has happened
What did they learn
What I see happening with
Those kinds of customers is they might say wouldn't it be nice if all these other pieces of equipment around here
Connected but they're not oh well so I'll just
Just keep trying to find other problems I can solve with this product
And
The downside is of course
That means that there
Are some interesting opportunity that are being left on the table
But on the other hand
What I find is it once people start shipping a Nike product the things they can do with it
The long-term opportunities start to become
Clear over time we're friends since you might say
I make a widget and the reason that I want
The widget is Kazan
And I want to be able to fix it
Okay that's the justification
A little rolling it out
You know what the widget also uses
Filters
Anna's filters
Go battle
Being used so now I can do an automatic
Consumables business I can start sending people new filters
Every 3 months on the filters bad or not every 3 months everytime the filter needs to be replaced
Naga
Subscription business
And that's life
Second
Stage
Of my IIT products and then they start thinking about what is 1/3 / Opera
What time does Bracken start
Create do something better for my customers and there's enough juice there
There's enough
Extra things to go after once you launch a Nike product
That
It doesn't matter
How many cases that you
You can't do the interesting things that require in Iraq
Vices because there's there's enough
To go after I get plenty busy basically
Got it in the end that make sense
When it comes to the actual business use cases that people are
Deploying
Particle stuff in
It sounds like
Remote monitoring there's a little bit of Providence
4/2 or doing preventive maintenance and then a third or so or doing acid
The tracking
Are there
Other use cases that you're seeing developed
The other use cases
Is that we see happening but they're less frequent are
Just some kind of premium product
This is the like I make a widget but I make a smart widget that's more compelling for some reason and I sell at a premium
That was less than
30%
Then we have
To use
Particle to track
Consumables
Replacing filters and detergent and
Black coffee
Pods
Those were less than
And then
The least common was
Regulatory
I would think that would be high
So here's my I think
Those use cases are really strong which is like let's say that you are you do natural gas
Extraction
And you want to track methane emissions because UTA regulate
Particle
And they are very
Helen yusuke
Is because
They regulated again
And so
You have to do that if
If you're not if you're not business
And so I think that the fact that they
A small orange
Number customers
Is just
Reflective of the factors might be great use cases but they're only relevant
Whereas
Monitoring
Environment
Spencer's is something very broadly
Across a whole bunch of
Industries and use cases
All right so getting back to
Adoption in how people are scaling up
From Pilot tip reproduction reproduction
You know when I talk to people who are looking at
This space and building prototype
They usually start with something like a
The particle or maybe it's a Raspberry Pi
And then in a certain point like a thousand maybe it's 10,000 there like
We need to move some
To something else
Talk to me about what you're seeing
In your customer base
Because you got this year
You got the cloud associated with
So you're basically starting
With particle and hopefully scaling all the way up
What is that process
So a lot of customers
Start with particle end of skin
I think the reason is that
The case
Anacortes Harbor
Business works better we we have a huge Community opportunity
We make your business
Israeli Tusa
Support those companies as they
Ring products to scale
So
I think if you are
Making the decision
Prototype
When you're deciding whether to continue to laptop
The question is what is the
Strategic
Or economic reason that you would want to build
And icing
That
In a lot of parallel speaker
Drawn between icing for structure and
Web infrastructure
Is essentially about dataset
Rick 30 years ago if you wanted
Build-A-Bear application you had to build a data center
Set up some kind of
Infrastructure
And then you're dealing with a lot of heart problems
Like
Getting
Real estate and
Construction
Temperature
Controls and replacing servers
Go bad
None of which actually makes
Is your project
Register table Stakes to be able to
Build a web application
Since then
You got Microsoft
Google
And overtime or more people have shifted the cloud because essentially there is no good
Economical
Versace justification for most
Companies
Builder
America
Dropbox
Spent $400 building their own software infrastructure
Because what they needed to
To do was easier and more economical for them
Delivered directly then
Using AWS
Another really big
Mastiff
Netflix
Hosted on AWS
And so
There are exception
Dropbox
Most of the time even large-scale what applications
Hotel on the cloud
Because there isn't a good read
And I think the same
The same fundamental decisions are true for it infrastructure which is that
There aren't generally Goods
Strategic Lacoste reasons why somebody should build their own infrastructure
It doesn't
Make your product better than somebody else's but it's not there isn't good strategic value
Economically perspective in life
Get cheaper on a unit basis but if you include all the overhead net
Saria's managing overseeing the infrastructure in Bluetooth devices
And so what you're left with is
The same reasons that caused
To be slow to adopt the cloud
Even though the underlying
Which is do you trust somebody else
Infrastructure for the
This product is super important and our job is to
Prove overtime by
Supporting a lot of customers who are happy and successful game across markets in that trust
Betfair
And
For a company that is looking at
Buying Hardware
And doing a prototype and then scaling up
Where do you see
The challenges
So
Your customers who are like
Yeah we run a successful proof-of-concept in
To roll this out further
Where do they hit the road bumps
Some of the biggest challenges
The one counters when your deployment actually product are
Different than what you expected to be when we ask customers about a bunch of different technical challenges and said
What have you found to be
The number one
What is debugging on health advice
Which is to say
Let's say you have a
But you could collapse
And generally speaking
But there's like a thousand
That are misbehaving
Why are they
Frank cell Princeton samite
The having issues connecting to whatever this other Tower is
They might
Tennis shoes where they're not getting
The necessary 3.3 volts to be able to for the system to be able to
To behave
Lively
Daylight
Something wrong
Haystak so this
Secureconnect
In between the Bison
If you experience you have is just at 99
Onager devices are
Sending messages but one
It can be really difficult to figure out why they're not write any one of those problems could be the problem
Device is out in the world
Hearing from it can be really tough to figure out what's going
We've been building a bunch
Features around
Which is providing more
Or inside
To our customers about when you have a device been going to see what exactly is going on and what you do about it
Those are the kinds of challenges when we talked to companies who have delivered product that they say this is a really high
Start stopwatch
Before they deliver
That one might not be
The number to Forest in terms of
What we hear is is most challenging in the
We don't suffer.
Speakeasy
Children's Opera
Reprogramming devices
Remotely
Create a lot of opportunities
Security risk
Or
Listening devices
Way too many
Public cases of devices that got ripped through an over-the-air software update that went bad
And so is another of these big technical challenges that we solve for customers to say we've we've tried to take
Artist
Senate results
Are you there other problems which
I think they're often for them it is difficult but if you ask
Customers
What we found in the survey is they weren't they weren't as challenging
Storing and collecting data
Visualizing
Data
Generating insights with data
We generally found the cusp
And I think that's in contrast to of the
Something like 450 iot platforms that exist in the world
Analytics
Find as if those are actually the hardest problem
The reason for that is the date
Not hard it's just because there's a lot of great product that already
Best about
Solving problems with data that are relevant
I see you don't necessarily need like a specialist it products to go and solve those problems
The one that
We heard as most challenging the generating insights
Which is to say not just collecting
But I kept turning that in
Into a solution to a problem
Generally true
Super any business with larger quantities of data is
Another thing to actually
Problem
You see the same challenges than
Like every marketing product ever
Babe like you get all this clickbait
What you doing on the website
Turning that into
Something to go do
Is the hard part
A bear in there
Companies that have been successful in helping generate those insights
But yeah I mean one of the things that I found
I'm looking at these survey results is that some of the things that are often painted as being the hardest problem
Don't actually seem to be that way and the hardest problems really tend to be more about this like nitty-gritty infrastructure
Sure of fundamentally how do you
Reliably connected
100000 physical devices
To the web
So that you can regularly communicate back
Zach thanks so much for
For coming on the show this week
I really appreciate
Absolutely thin grabbing me
That's it for this week thanks so much for listening and remember if you'd like more iot news
Sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot. Com