Hey everyone welcome to the 212th episode of the internet
Podcast this is your house Stacey Higginbotham
And your co-host
Kevin tofel
And we have
At a astonishing show for you today
This week we're going to be talking about a new
Program that you can load on your back book that will actually help you understand what iot devices are running
In your network
And how
Well behaved
Where else would I be talking about
Scary scary stories in the New York Times about
Facial recognition and overall privacy
Their supplies related to that plus
Intel's big news about getting out of modems doesn't apply to SMS
Inside but it does apply maybe on the iot side
We'll talk about that
We got a lot of self-driving car news you love news from Apple the US Army and wave
We've got
News about
Madame de and how to become
I'm a skill developer
A new sport created by AI
And a program
That allows things to work
With ring
What's will also talk about the Norse
Hydro ransomware
And what that means for industrial iot security and
Our Guest this week is nadir Israel who is the CTO
Arvest which is
And iot security firm
So we're going to talk about
A lot of industrial iot and Enterprise iot security
Episode
We're also going to hear from our sponsor software AG
Talking about
Common pitfalls
For the iot
And now
Let's kick it off
With a message from another one of our sponsors
This week sponsor is iot world you yes all of you are
Invited to iot world this is the intersection of Industries and iot Innovation until May 3rd
16th at the Santa Clara Convention Center in Silicon Valley
It's going to bring together 12,500 iot strategist acknowledges
Developers and implementers to put iot into action within tea industry vertical
We at the iot podcast have an exclusive listener discount of 25% off
Bob your past with the code Stacey 25s Stacey 25
Prices are going to go up next Friday April 26th so visit iot world event.
Register
Okay Kevin let's get this show started
First step
We saw it last week
A couple of new stories about
Service called iot inspector
Everything about this
I realize that we'd actually talked about this
Almost a year ago we had a
Nick feamster over at Princeton
He and I talked about this
Program called iot inspector
An idea was he wanted to build something
That would monitor the iot devices on a user's Network
And see how they behave
And lo and behold
Last week
He launched
That app
So this is a
Princeton
Research project
Basically so when you download this to see how your devices Behavior also going to be in sharing that device data
With the research
It is important to know if anybody does plan to use it Princeton does list all of the data that i r t s
Spectre collect
It's actually a lengthy list
I don't
Think I would person be concerned about it but if you're not willing to share any of that information
Certainly this is not something you want to run
Well actually
You can delete
All of your day
At the end so you could just for yourself
And then you could
But
It's nice of you
If you don't have qualms about it
This is the sort of
Third-party research that is hopefully going to
24 scumpa
I needs to be better
You can fight it iot - Inspector.
Princeton
. EDU
I downloaded it
And had it running for a while
Meister
Now I'm going to tell you my network is a little wacky right now because I am
In the midst of the moving
Time dismantling all of my iot device
So not everything is
Giving data
But the things that are
Giving data or actually
That's a pretty good devices on my
On my network
Believe it or not
They're good actors
They are good at
So
Many of them such as some of the
The better actors
Where's that I see so
So far my Nest Thermostat
That behaves very well
Talking about encryption we're talking about not going weird places on the internet
Amazon Echo is actually doing
Pretty well and so is my Roku
So
Who knew
I would love to see my
Google devices but unfortunately May
Family unplugged
Okay
Well they're not sending any data that's the good news
Some things that are a little bit trouble
Not Troublesome but
Not user-friendly
The things that this program
Picks up
They're not labeled
So like for me to figure out that my August video doorbell
Was listed on
I'm here I had to go and see
What that particular mystery device was talking
The fact that I was talking
Into august.com at Rackspace CDN
And some other
Video sites
That's my dawg
So there is that
It is hard to tell this is not like
Odoo user
Most user
And some of my iot devices such as my wink
Carmi Ikea tradfri Gateway
Those are labeled as non iot
And if it thinks
That something is a
A phone or a tablet it actually doesn't
Collect the data you need on it
So you have to enter the MAC address of these divide
Spices
To get it to download
Which is kind of frustrating
It is but I can understand why they took that approach it as there's a lot of a lot more personal information on people's phones and
What so if they don't want to
Cross that line and I totally respect that
Yes but as a warning
Do all of you guys were like yes I totally wanted
I do this you're probably going to want to you know have the Mac
Prefer some of your hub
Devices that most of the ones that
It seems to think
ARROW computers
Are hubs
And in one case there's a thermostat that is
Homekit enabled so I'm not sure if it's
Homekit functionality that
That seems to be a common denominator here
I've got a couple devices that are using
Weekend
Scription butt
Actually I was surprised out of the 31 devices I have only 5 or using week or no in crib
So
Yay
No that's good that's very good to me then everybody smart home is different so obviously your results will vary if you use this but
It's nice that this is
The types of information that says checking
Such as
Who is contact who are the devices
Pinging servers
Vagina is itchy
In the middle of nowhere or is it where you would expect
How much data is exchanged
Between the devices and how often
I think it looks for hard-coded passwords and such to but I'm not a hundred percent sure
Well we will get Shore
Because next week's guest is actually go
When are the creators of
So we'll get a lot
Information on
What does is going to be used for so if you're a little uncertain you're like how I don't know if I want to download this yet until I really know I'm doing good in the world
Think you can wait
And
We will
Put that question
Danny who is one
The creators
And if you don't want to wait because right now this is only available for Mac OS
It is coming to Linux and coming to Windows
So you can sign up for waitlist if you're on either of those platforms
Or if you like me I just noticed that the source code is available written in Python
And I might put it together
Linux and
See if I can get a ride
The folks over at Prince
NFL say hey great let's give us that and we'll just Distributing
Make a cake
All right
So that's how you can monitor
What devices are
Baby
Giving up some of your privacy and
Security on your own network
Let's talk about the loss of privacy in everyday life the New York Times has been doing a story
Are series on privacy
Rio Tierra
Alternatively like
Excited me because
It's great coverage and enrage me
Because it's stupid
So
One of the better stories though
Was
Basically
Reporters at the New York Times
Accessed
Publicly available webcams in the city
And then they ran
That
Data that they had
Against
They used Amazon's recognition
Facial recognition service and they pulled photos from
The websites of offices around the places where the cameras were
And then
They were able to identify someone
People walking around
As you said they looked at
Public data public photos that were available on the web of people that may be in the area supposed to be
People who worked in the area
So it's not like they
You know we're spying
Were using
Photo is that working illegally to
Train the model of work yet
Actual results here
Rates
If it's
This is all publicly available photos
Tied to the recognition system
Across from 60 bucks to do this for a day
And
Yeah they recognize actual people
And even talk to her
Who was actually on his way to an appointment to meet a
Job candidate
Tencent
So the way I look at this is
There's a couple
Personally I look at this and I'm like hey
If someone has my photo
They can actually use a service like this
Pull camera data
From all over the place just to see if they
That's not crazy
And
As someone who's had a stalker in the fartist
To pass the scariest
And even if you think about governments have access to our
Face
Because they have our passports and
Driver's license
A lot of our drivers license
Data is now our face and our names are tied together
Database
There's a new standard of driver's license
So if you imagine law enforcement being able to use the sort of service
Manhunt
Is it if there's a serial killer on the loose
Yay
They're just tracking like a dissident
Oh that's real nice
It really makes the surveillance State cheap
Inaccessible to
More and more people and
It also
Makes it cheap and accessible to just anyone who wants to find out where you are like maybe your boss is like
Where they really sick
That's kind of where I was going this is not something that
Is
Difficult to do
It is easily accessible both be public
Photos liked an image search for me to be a hundred photo serum Shore
And then using
Amazon service or any any similar service they want to pin this on Amazon of course
As well as publicly available cameras and
A New York City and it listen I know when I can have been over to London there's cameras everywhere so I know there
Regions of the world where this is already commonplace
But I'm in New York City in Atlanta's link
NYC kiosks which I used to use all the time there were there wi-fi kiosks
Better up and down
Various parts of Manhattan
They all have two security cameras on those when you add in the actual traffic cams that are New York City you have access to light
3000 cameras
In
New York City
Dying at 2
Publicly available photos
I'm probably pretty easy to track when I go to New York City
I'm so anybody could really do this
Oh yeah
And
Again
The stalking issue
Government surveillance is scary
And I'm definitely
We concerned about that
Imagine using it to profile pic
People who
Are in the ice databases
Sure
Or in just think about all the mistakes that cover
Hornets make rate
The people who are on the no-fly list without
Recourse you know when
I got their life turns into a pain
Imagine something
Like a government era
Apply to some
Something like this
Suddenly you're being monitored all the time by the government may be without any sort of due process
You don't have to match I just talked to anybody lives in China right now
And I say that because
We've covered what's going on over there with the
Cameras in the social scores and so on and so forth but
One of my classmates lived in China for 20 years and she's been in the US for the last five
We had a lengthy discussion
Over all of that
What's going on over there
The stories that you told me were scary
She's very careful how she speaks to her parents over
Video chat from the US to China I mean it's
Really scary so you don't have to imagine it just look what's going on there
Yeah that's my very inarticulate
The cravory
And I do think we need some pushback
On the legislation
I hate when people are like it's too late
Like no it's not too late it is getting late
Don't get me wrong
The horse has run out of the barn
We can still
I'll pick some up
But that won't happen anytime soon
Illinois
I know it's rather convenient that they were just looking at the keep Internet devices SAFE Act
The Illinois state senate they passed this act on April 10th
And basically it's a bill that would ban internet
Device manufacturers from collecting audio
From
Internet-connected devices
But without disclosing it to Consumers
Do seem to have a lot of teeth and there's a $50,000 fine and so on so forth
But the actual bill DACA
Past has a lot less
Teeth
And that's mainly because of two companies that were familiar with Amazon and Google
Who
Where
Kind of against it
Because why well they've got their neck microphones all over the place
People dying left and right so
Will said
You had to disclose if they
Yay
Creative penalties for accidental
Activations
In required
Companies to explain what happened
And I can't Jackson
When suddenly you're sitting there and the TVs on or maybe don't say anything and all of a sudden Madame a pops
The weather in Kazakhstan is
Is cold
Yes
You write an n and I've had Phantom digital assistant
Answers to questions I did not ask from time to time and it always makes me wonder but
You know
Certainly advocate for Consumer privacy
And controls
I also understand that
The technology is not perfect and some things are just
Gosh darn it honest glitches
But there are times when
These things are getting hacked and people are listening to us when they shouldn't be well and I don't know if companies are necessarily
Putting in place the right practices to protect our privacy
We just found out that
There's a team of
Oaks at Amazon that
Listening on
Summit
It's a small percentage
On the flip side
It takes the
Voice utterances and
Tries to
Warped the the audio so you can't tell
Who it is Amazon just
You need some sort of human accountability
Right humans have two
Check and make sure
Birthday is
Health Canada
But you know are there ways you can do it with
With more respect
People whose
Voice Taylor you're using problem
Yeah and I wonder I'm sure this wasn't the primary impetus of this
We spoke a few weeks ago about Google moving
Natural language processing to the edge
On devices
Supposed to being connected and sending it
To the cloud all the time
That's kind of like a benefit in my book that
They're gaining a little bit of
Saying hey you know not everything is going in the cloud anymore your data is local and more protected as a result
It gives them a chance to say that although again I don't think that was the reason I think the reason was
To enable more functionality when you don't have internet access and get more people using the service doesn't feel comfortable with them so
All right
That's all about connect
Let's talk about until which
Is disconnecting from its modem business
It's actually
It's exiting is 5G smartphone
Modem business and then it will evaluate
Its modem business
PCS
Iot devices and
Also in line with this
These two stories are definitely related
Qualcomm and Apple
Settled their big
Licensing
Lawsuit
These are related because Qualcomm is basically
Should I say the best the only
The de facto standard when it comes to mobile modem
There you go that was good
The Defector
And Intel got into this business and
We heard a lot
Years ago when Intel got into this business and started actually producing these modems
We heard that they weren't very good
And my hunch is
Apple ended up settling with Qualcomm
Because they realize that
They're going to Intel's not producing of Iowa
Basically
So they're just going to have to suck it up
Continue working
I think that's part of it
Intel modems actually have
Improved and certainly not to the standard of a
Qualcomm modem but the most recent iPhones
Some models do you use the Intel modem
So Apple at least
Had enough
Faith in the product to
You know actually use them
But there was also talk
Recently about until being
Further behind on developing its 5
Cheap modem
Then Qualcomm
That put a pelota
I guess across roads like what we going to do here if we rely on them as a supplier
So I think they wanted to just go with
Call Camas results
It was just easier to settle and I don't know the settlement terms
But
I believe it dropped all
Lawsuits there must be some money changing hands or some deal that says
We will use you as a primary modem supplier
Going forward for at least X number of years so
Yeah no
Twenty-something Tyler lights
Versus a $7
Licensing a so
My hunch is they
Damn it in the middle somewhere
Tia
Probably
But again it from Mobile standpoint we don't care as much for the show but Intel seems out of that business
What does it mean for Intel
Connectivity in smaller devices iot devices
They're going to look into it my gut says they're just going to exit this Market entirely
Because until it's finally after years and years of dominating so many
Key markets
Dave
Had a lot of frustration against the smaller upstarts and I wouldn't call arm small I was sleep but
Talk on being an arm licensee
I think they finally realized we have to pick and choose our battles a little bit more carefully
And yeah this is
Fun battle in Intel's gotten out of some of the iot
The smaller iot
Teechips in
So it does make sense
Kind of sad
And I don't know why I was never really
Sold on this I mean Intel had its a scale business way back in the day that was arm-based and they got rid of that
It really double down on
The current
Conjecture
I see a lot more promise with Intel in there
Fpga business
The one thing I will say they do seem to be with movidius doing a lot with
Inference at the edge
Anti revisionism
That's not the radio side that's a processor side
So we'll probably still see them
There really were
That makes sense they should really
Hey speaking of
Computer vision
Apple
Apple apple apple
I still don't hate apples going to build
Car but it's clear to me that at the very least
Apple wants to be the platform that an autonomous vehicle runs on at some point in the future
They have been investing and lidar
Technology with their own internal groups
But
According to Reuters they have held talks with four companies are at least four companies
As possible suppliers for
Next-gen lidar sensors so
I'm not sure what their overall strategy is I still think it's to be the platform in up the vehicle
Per say not not a Tesla they're taking their time getting there for sure
But that's typical Apple will wait till everybody else
Enters the market and then will come in with a
Better product
And
Hopefully everybody will buy it
Everybody being used
Correct
Correct in this case
Is correct
You don't seem too enthused though that was a kind of a half-hearted yeah this whole area is so
Up in the air speaking of
Wavo
They have an app
And we might be excited because like
Maybe it's not going to be the car manufacturer
Maybe it's going to be these weird
Third-party Transportation providers for self-driving cars
And
I don't I don't
So Weymouth
You can get it you can get it right now on the Google Play Store
And still unless you live in the Phoenix Metro area it really doesn't do you a bit of good
But
It suggests that
Or alphabets waymo division
Is ready to start expanding Beyond its test area
In the Phoenix Metro area so that's a yay I guess depending on where they roll it out
I did not install the app but I saw the screenshots and I don't see any mention of
Cost of a
Arrived
I don't get that
You know who does have driverless cars
Baidu
And this makes a lot of sense for me the US Army
They actually have
I wouldn't call him self-driving cars are more like self-driving
Trucks that would deliver supplies
People food and other supplies in
Combat zone
That makes total sense I mean why have
Why run the risk of injury to somebody or a group of people
You're deploying supplies in a Battlefield
When you can just have a self-driving
Filled with supplies handle it for you
I think it's selling some wonderful they're moving quickly on this
They demonstrated their first 10
Down to your way Fort Bliss Texas
And they have 60 additional trucks
Planning to be deployed it to other US military bases
Over the next year
They're on bases
It will be nice if they didn't have any combat to tuipulotu but yes
Yes
Get rid of the entire defense system
And poo
Yay
All right let's do some quick news bits
I've actually been looking into certifications I'm going to take my
Google Cloud
Developer associate certification test in a month or two but I just realized today that you can
Also be
A certified
Madame a skill Builder
So if you want to pad your resume and you like building meta mage skills
You can take a test to be a certified skill Builder
Speaking of other developments
AI
Has actually created a brand new sport that you yes you can play
The game is called speedgate I'll talk about the game in a second but what's really interesting is
How this was created
A group of
Developers
Akqa which is a global Innovation agency
Has trained a neural network
By feeding it
Information on over 400 traditional Sports
And the AI came out
With a sport called
It looks really cool
It's got a ball very similar to what rugby has
You kicking pass that ball kind of like
Rugby & Soccer
There is no
Kicking hitting biting scratching her than like that allow thank you AI for that
Basically there are three sets of gates
On the field that the AI develops
You kick
Or pass the ball through the center gate
Which lets you then
Score you would then have possession to score
In the end gate
I wish you can do this by throwing or kicking the rug be blackballed
There are three forwards and three Defenders on every team
And I think it's kind of cool there's a whole speedgate
Website where you can see the
Rules the field and you can say I want spaghetti in my community in
I don't think this will be the next
Sport of America on TV but
It looks like fun
When you go
Only four more people
Yes we can go tell him about it
Okay
Play Quidditch
Is a
Sometimes sponsor the show
They have their own code lock which is there wi-fi lock and now it works with the ring doorbell so when people come
Senior ring
You can
Unlock your lock
Write 4 with
Open the app
Cool
And mortifications are always good
Yes
I'd love to see that with
Other doorbells I know she likes Ben
With Amazon for their Amazon
Key programmer
I assume this is an outlet
Play or something like that
It is this is Amazon key
As someone who
Does not have
Ring doorbell
Right now I have an August
If I had a nest doorbell which is the next
Doorbell I will have
Ben
Love for that
To work together
One day I will
Question actually this week
Not for me
Loser hotline this was a email question about reading openhab
Or home assistant
We had someone who wanted to run it
In the cloud so
Kevin
Can I answer that question on our blog but we also wanted to talk about it
Yeah for those who aren't familiar openhab and homeassistant are
Localized open source
Smart home platforms so if you want like total control over everything
And you're a DIY person you can do this with
Like a $35 Raspberry Pi
What
This was an interesting question because
The person who wrote inside is there an easy way to set up a site-to-site VPN to Azure or AWS or I presume Google Play
The platform YouTube
Didn't mention that one
And host my
Containers in the cloud that way I could host them and compare them easily until I get a final solution to run
Locally
I love that idea
Because yeah I mean you got to set up Ally systems and spend time to figuring them and
By the time you set it all up your kind like
It's good enough I'm not going to try the other system cuz I don't have to have more hours to figure this all out but
It's actually quite easy to do this
With openhab
It is not so easy if I can
Find a way to do it with home assistant
And the main reason is
Homeassistant they don't believe in the cloud as a
Smart Home
Platform I guess
They have a nice
Blog posts that I've liked you in my post
Basically saying you know the clouds magical it's great
But if it
Breaks down
Your house should be able to continue functioning so
It's really an extension of your smart home not running your smart home is what they say so I get why I could not find
Home assistant in the cloud
Openhab know you could do it and you can do with containers if you
I want to set up a Docker container that are easy to follow instructions
Do you want to set it up yourself
Command lines I found tutorials and
Most of them are on AWS but the same principles apply to say Google Cloud platform on Microsoft azure
You pretty much have to set up a
Computing instance very low power you don't need any massive witch
Your cost increase as you add more resources to the cloud
Set everything up in
You you could do it
I'd say just bite the bullet
It's been 35 bucks on a Raspberry Pi
Even if
You
Don't use it for this long-term there's so many things you can do with a pie so that's just me
I would do that as opposed to
Running in the cloud and entering
Some cost
Although you can get a free 2-year free
Trial of these Cloud products
I cycle with the pie but yes you can do with it with that
Copart
Okay
And I promise you guys a
Discussion of iot industrial security
Because
Bossman
From the middle of March
We all heard about
In aluminum
Company called norsk Hydro
What happened is they had ransomware that infected their systems and shut them down costing them up to 41
Million dollars
Is pretty bad
And a company called cyberex which does industrial iot security they published a blog post about the ransomware
Which is called
Locker Goga
Basically talking about
What it is
Or what they think it is cuz we don't have a full post
So what they did is they now can identify Locker go go
And they talked about how
Attack
So what they think happened
Was the attackers gain access to the system
Through an exposed remote
Connection so I can RDP
They also likely use stolen credentials or they did it
Password at
The stolen credentials if they stole them
In a lot of the Industrial
Hacking attacks
What cyber axes
David Arch tour
This week was that
A lot of times they're getting those passwords
From contractor so third-party contract
The IT world is pretty familiar with this after the Sony hack which happened because
The attackers got access
Through third-party
Contractors to Sony's
Computer system
So I think a lot of
Corporate it Department separately Earth with this but maybe not a lot of
Industrial
Companies and there's a lot of sharing have
Not only are there 3rd party contractors that you might share
Files and data width and let the money
Corporate Network
A lot of times those people can actually come on your OT
Your operational Tech Network that isn't even connected to
Internet
So those guys might come in and plug their laptops directly into like some equipment so they
Can diagnose something
Wrong in that case that's when the mall
On your OT Network
This is a big problem it shuts down Manufacturing
Cuz like safety issues can cause a
A lot of problems
And it is becoming more
Common because manufacturers
Because it is so expensive to shutdown a Manufacturing
They will pay rental
That makes them a delicious Target
In addition cybrex found that the
Rental car here actually increased in sophistication
Over a few months
So earlier versions of the software were not as good
And they saw that there was plenty of food that have been
Adapted basically to make it a little bit more
A little bit better
We're not going to get too into the weeds here
So
Basically this points to the sophistication
The growing sophistication
Attack
It also highlights what I would say is a key
Best practice if you're going to bring contractors in
Which many many companies do for very good reason
They should be
Given
A corporate-owned device
That has been
You know found to be clean and clear
Sanitizer
I'd rather than using maybe their own devices and such which
You know you if you've brought in a potential bad actor by allowing
Non manage devices on to your network for good reason you brought them in but still that doesn't justify it
So they mean
Particular software for Diagnostics and such but
That should be worked out in advance and that should be added to the managed
Devices
And make sure that they are clean and then that's at the shouldn't be
Using their own devices to connect to network
Or two devices
Yeah and I will say in the industrial world
Companies like Honeywell and Emerson have done a lot of work with me
Like USB drive so they will inspect
USB drives
There are devices on the factory
Plug in your us
Ensure device
Shoot a text anyting it shuts it
Can't use it
So maybe
Given
How highly specific some of the software is and how
Proprietary it is
If you could have some sort of help scan
Other device
Before it gets in
And the other solution which obviously cybrex is promoting
Because they are in network
Work monitoring solution
Is to have some sort of
Awareness of what's traversing your network
And there are tons of companies not just cybrex doing this but it is becoming increasingly important
How do I coyote inspector for the home
I was just going to say that
Full circle
Dunedin and the industrial version of that
So
Stay tuned for more on IO
The first
We are going to go to our voicemail
This week's voice mail from the iot podcast hotline is brought to you by a pharaoh
With the fifth largest iot patent
Portfolio in the world
Arrow provides a
Proven iot platform
It doesn't risk your brand
A pharaoh customers have experienced as much as an 80% reduction in time-to-market at 10x hire at
Activation rates
Learn more at
A pharaoh.
Okay and if you have a question for us you can call us at 5 1/2
6 to 3
And
For the month of April
We will be giving away at
Connect
. IO
Alarm system
Diggy
Thinking is a really terrible way to do this but what this device does is it connect to SmartThings Hub and
Your alarm panel
It's a very much a DIY Thing
And it allows you
To turn your old alarm system your old wired alarm system into something that you can use
Command
Very cool
Get a lot of questions about that so somebody else can
Try this and play with it
Aspen device
This week's question is from
Scott
Hi Stacy and Kevin this is Scott in Houston
I have a question regarding smart locks which I've been researching
Quite some time
Is there any such thing as a double cylinder
Smart Lock
I noticed the sealant single-cylinder smart locks but I would like to have a double cylinder Smart Lock
Security
And yes this can be used online
Thank you
Okay Scott this is actually pretty easy answer
Because right now these things don't exist and they don't exist because most modern building codes don't allow
Double cylinder
These are locks for those of you or not
Two player that need to be
Unlocked with a key from both the inside and the outside
The reason people tend to gravitate to them is because they are concerned about someone like breaking a window and then reaching in
Hainan opening up the
And then getting access to
My in-laws actually had these locks
For a long time
And I had nightmares about the
I'm dying in fires
Because they never knew where the keys were in
It was such a pain
So
In the case of a connected lock if you had a keypad on both sides that might actually
Address some of the issues in the sense that
If you don't know the keypad you can unlock
Leave in a few
Broken Window you couldn't get in because you wouldn't know the combinations cuz if you knew the combination you would bring the window
But it does
There's still the issue of if you need to get out what if you're a guest in the house if you don't know the cam
Combination
How do you get
Or the batteries go out on the
Lock
Yeah it still has a safety concern issue there
I don't I don't love her
Yeah I mean some people I know I wouldn't mind locking them in their house but no in general now
I'd be shocked if a manufacturer came out with a just because the
Building codes have moved away from this
No
And Manuel Roxas
But nobody makes a smart one right now
There you go Scott
Alright that concludes this week's News segment
Kevin thank you so much and everyone else
Stay tuned for
Nadir Israel the CTO of harvest
He's going to be talking about some
Dorothy Wacker and crazy devices
That he's found connected on corporate Networks
Could pose problems
Plus we're going to talk about Bradley industrial & Enterprise iot security
Hey everyone we are taking a quick break from The Internet of Things podcast for a message from our sponsor this week sponsor
Where is software Ag and I have Mark Olsen
Who is part of the sitter
Of Excellence
At software AG
On the iot and Analytics
Let's kick this off by reminding our listeners what it is that software AG does and how you guys were
Within the iot
Suffrage has been innovating for some 50 years
We operate in
70 countries headquartered in Germany are solutions deployed across 70% of Fortune 1000 clients
Software segments
Include iot
Analytics integration
And business Process Management
Specifically to iot
Varsity is a iot device application platform
To connect and manage
Advise or advice
We then apply AI machine learning and analytics to find root causes to problems
In real time
Cumulus see-through automation
Then operationalize has these insights to solve real-world business Prof
Our go-to-market
Focus and strategy is around
Three areas OEM
Horizontal invitations to specific use cases
And a vertically focused go-to-market around Manufacturing
Smart City energy utility Transportation Medical in Orland
Okay that's awesome so we're here today to talk about how
Companies
Succeed in the iot
What do you recommend
First
Define the use case of business value at the start of your iot journey
Second
Think about integration and devops Alignment from the Inception
Of your project
3rd
Think about driving intelligence and insights
To the edge
Or device is extremely important achieve automation
And real business value
And finally
Extending Cloud platforms
With sdks really means a long and costly development cycle
And time to value in terms of years
Depending on the
Specific use case
Those are some pretty big pitfalls
How does software AG help you solve those
Out of the box Camellia city of delivering commoditize 85% of the technical requirements components to deliver
A true end-to-end it Solutions
It support 250 + gateway's + 400 + protocols
Deployment models include cloud on-prem
Hybrid and Edge
Ecosystems include some the largest
Companies in the world
Software AG provides
Solution accelerator
To achieve
The remaining 50%
Against your particular use case
Multi-tenancy is offered out of the box
Provides
Support for devops
Hello I'm into it
Additional plugins
Can be made available
How to connect to any data source and work
And time to value
Is measured in a matter of days weeks
If not
A month
Awesome and Mark where can I go to learn more about software Ag and cumulus
You can go do suffer a g.com iot to start your free trial today
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest is done.
Deer Israel who is the CTO and co-founder
A security firm
Arvest
Hi dear how are you doing
Hi Stacy I'm great how are you
I am really excited to talk to you
Although
I better not as a
Excited as you guys because you just raised
Last week 65 million in funding
That is a lot of money what is happening with our
Pharmacist doing really great
I think it will
Great for the company maybe slightly more problematic
The fact that we're seeing a lot of
Problems in the world with iot so in that sense
There's a lot of space for us to come and help organizations
Help them protect themselves
Dangers about but we've had quite a year say that's a lot of new clients
A lot of very large organizations that are
Using us for disability and security of different devices that they have
And I realize that's a made-up word but it's what we're trying to say so
It's been tremendous
In that
I think that the new investment is really about doubling down and
Being able to provide that
Solution
Better for everybody
Okay and I would say
How big is actually I'm going to say all the way since Mariah
We've been hearing a lot about diode
Security
Now I would love to make the distinction between some of the devices that the original Mirai botnet
I took over which word Network video cameras printers routers
They actually were devices that
They had more processing power they were little bit smarter
And they had access to more bandwidth
And I think
It's worth talking about the distinction between those types of devices
And some of the iot devices that were a little bit more worried about
Now which might
Like you say their agent list Maybe
If they're resource-constrained maybe there
Hard to find
So can you kind of make the distinction between
Where We Are
In our sophistication when it comes to understanding and securing iot devices
Yeah I would separate the world probably
Not So Much by
Processing power but by the types of devices are out there and what are they running
Basically
The world pretty much separates into
Devices that run
Standards albeit old operating systems
And then the devices that run
Criteri software firmware
Now there is a correlation in a way to what you described the wrong kind of
Compute power
Really boils down into what's running really old windows Android limit
And what's running very very specific
Very big I would say that
A lot of device
She's out there that you wouldn't even
Consider
Types of Opera
All the way to digital microscopes
ATMs that you can tour controller that are running Windows
There's all kinds of smart assistant
Something like that
Old versions of Linux and Android
This is the thing where you sign into work every day a lot of those things are
Running really old Android well so I would say that the world of those devices actually very very large in the reason I bring them up
It's because these are devices that very easily
Can track any type of malware that you can imagine
Craft something very special they don't need to do something that specifically targets those devices they're just really really easy pickings
Because they're vulnerable to things that should have gone away
A long time ago
Operating
Up to date and patched
Those are
For the most part the resurface that organizations are worried about now naturally there's all kinds of things that are
And specifically abused devices that have
Specific
We'd even seen you mention the ride but we've even seen a variant of Mirai in Singapore
Just a month ago
What specifically crafted to take advantage of things that are there but for the most part
The wannacry is not pictures of the world the variety of different botnets and crypto mining
Ransomware
General malware all these things the reason
Iot is
So so dangerous is because you don't need to do anything
Specialty
Problems for organization that they try to clean up
What is the Trenta
Obviously we're reading in surveys there plenty of surveys that come out each month
How to say oh my gosh
CIO CTO CEOs are all worried about the security of their connected devices
And there feels like a sense of panic
And many are not sure what to do about
This
But we've been here before
I feel like
We've had this Panic before we talked about
Viruses on
Computers that sort of thing that says
Still happening
We've had it with app system so Lake
How should we think about the
This is the world really ending or can we solve
I think generally optimistic approach about solving problems I think that this
Pierpoint
Comes in Cycles
I think that's the best thing to equate this to is 10 years ago the world application
Same deal all kinds of applications running on my devices or being accessed by my devices
I as a cecilware CIO
Have no idea what they are I completely blind into what people use what they tag is transferred into them
And specifically the risks around that or the ability to just one anything was a problem
Income
All kinds of solutions including connection firewalls or things like that which basically gives you a good idea
What's running and also provide the Intelligencer on understanding what should run and what should men take action against
I think the
Coyote in essence
Is physical application
Cytus basically
It's purpose-built devices
That function is applications except they have a physical reality
And I would say that the same problem
That existed 10 years ago for applications exist today for devices
Most organizations don't know what devices they have even if they do know all kinds of devices
They have no idea
What they should be worried about with
Princeton
They don't necessarily know that a particular brand of Chinese IP camera has a known Chinese government back door built-in
And this is something that comes up
I would say someone scary time schedule
Come up a lot
What is various forms in various ways. The point is that
Disability
Is the first driver in
Security for almost
What do I have
And what do I need to know about
Then the second piece of that puzzle is what do I do about it
Basically what can I do to
Securities devices
And thankfully a lot of these devices are
Bring me reliant on their connectivity
Which is also what creates the resurface
In the first place
I would say that being able to intelligently
Limited connectivity intelligently police what these devices can do
Is a very very effective method at
Securing them and that's really the bread and butter of what
Imagine
An organization that has no idea what devices they have
At all and then you come in and show them if we show them a complete inventory of all the devices that they have
On top of that layer in the intelligence of what they should know about all these devices
What they know about the risk provide easy steps into
Securing them
This is really in a nutshell organizations seem to be concerned about also what they're trying to solve
So how worried should an organization be I feel like right now when you buy some of these connect
Two devices
Your elevator company is like a let's do elevators as a service and you're like yeah that sounds great
Or maybe someone comes in with a connected lighting pack
Are companies aware that their broadening their attack
That is a terrific question
Because I can throw that in many cases
Surprisingly enough no they don't the reason is that
Traditionally
Things like
Office spaces
Building automation
System seems like that
They don't really go through any type of IP
Think about TVs in the hallway
For instance of a building for a company
Normally the people who install that are third-party contractors
The facilities group are the one that can track them in the first place
It's not really
A process that goes through the general it procurement process
Now not just that
You mentioned two different things that happen a lot and I'll focus on the elevator one because it's an interesting
The reason is that
It's just a cost reduction
Basically
The company that sells the elevators wants to go to
Support them remotely so they don't have to send
Ignition every time there's a problem
A very good thing
Up until the point you realize
That elevator needs to be connected
Somehow
To the internet
And usually that somehow is through
Other companies infrastructure basically the network
Alba company
Spell that presents an interesting dilemma
Because on the one hand
It security at that point
If they suddenly realize that that's happening
Can come and say there's no way I'm connecting an elevator in my building to my network to the internet
At that point
The company would come and say
But they give us a 20% discount for doing this so of course we're doing
I think that it security are increasingly facing these types of issues where the mission of the business
Something around the way the business works
Is demanding
The more and more of these things you put in
Digital transformation is creating
My conference
Screeding
Supply chains that have dinner connected devices between the
They're creating building automation systems like connected elevators that service all but really
All of these
Are creating a mounting resurfaced where the security is put in a position where
They don't want want to be the one to say no they want to be the ones who say
How to do it
Correctly
How to integrate all these things without a proper solution
That makes no sense so then the solution for them is
Please do not say by yourself
Putting aside for a second
Armistead the solution
It really comes down to the same principles that
Always guide
Security When approaching these types of problem
It's around disability
Monitoring analytics about proactive
Disability means they have to be aware of all the
Things we have to be aware of what connected to network
There are multiple ways to go about this
And a lot of companies are trying out different strategies
But the point is that the first step
Is for security to realize that there is nothing that's really outside of their scope
Responsibility
In five years ago
Cecil's
Expected to protect IP cameras
Allan Block metabolism in a lot of other things happening
And it's the same with everything else
And it starts with visibility
Being able to
Count for every device that you have
Also means being able to account for the risk surface that they create
Basically all those folks
Got hit by one guy or not text you
The device of the godhead were essentially unmanaged devices
Every device that has endpoints
I would have thought something like that
But the problem is that if you have even one device
Tucked away in some closet somewhere or sometimes even
Buried inside a wall because 10 years ago there was a server running Windows XP
All these devices it's an app that you have
Just one device and it to take down an entire facility so the visibility
Being able to
Account for all these things is key
Elmo 2nd pieces
General Lee
Airport hygiene
Around device is being able to implement policy
No matter how you do it
You do it automatically if you do it
Manually
Policies are really important
Like I said
Connectivity is the main thing
The Relief Society
The main aspect of what makes them
Markdown quote on quote
And so limiting
Connectivity intelligently
Is really really the most
Important part in policing
And also of course with reducing risk
Go back to your question I would say that
Getting a good handle
And a good comprehensive handle it that at all the assets
The organization
Is
The first step it's
So I would say Primary in that
Such a basic step
That all the rest after that
Wolf logo directly from what you find out
And trust me organizations find out
All kinds of
Anything from connecting treadmill
All the way to door controllers are running Windows
From 20 years ago
There's all kinds of ants
Interesting stuff
Connectnetwork these days
Let's break down some of the crazier things you've seen
We'll have a little fun here
What have you seen running on
That you're like oh that's connected and surprise
Wow all kinds of things
First of all
The treadmill part is really interesting I mean most companies don't even consider the fact there is such a thing of a connected treadmill
That happens more often.
I assume these are in company gyms
Yeah sometimes it's company gym
Sometimes by the way it's things that employees are departments bought for themselves
I just connected
So not always is at the
Play Gym specifically where that but yeah that would be one of them
I think that there's a wide variety of gaming consoles and things like that
Peopleconnect
Again
Things that depending on your point of view it might seem
Trivial and it might be very slow
Surprisingly surprised to find just how many they have
Connected
Smart assistant
Seems like you know Amazon Echo and Google home
Some things like that
Absolutely all over the place
Digital microscopes
You wouldn't
Never in a million years think run Windows
Not only are these types of things connected to network
In some cases they can even be
Patient zero in spreading things like wannacry for instance or kind of other types of ransomware
And by the way you name one example before I think a lot of organizations don't realize just how much of your building automation
Just how many
Things like
Door controllers or lighting fixtures or
All kinds of other things are connected their Network
And just for the heck of it all to say that's a lot of companies don't realize that these kind of emergency call stations like
You know how you have them
Can always sometimes these defibrillators but kind of emergency nurse call station
These types of things are also network-connected
No one even knows
Definitely interesting things that come up
When you do kind of a discovery like that
Okay I like that
And let's talk one of the things
Been talking about recently on the show is this idea of connected medical device
Connected medicine
And and
I worry a lot about this because I feel like hospitals
It security is not their strong suit
People's lives
Hopefully their strong suit
So
What are you seeing in the medical world because they are really embracing connectivity in ways that
Figure very helpful
But are also
Little bit scary
First of all
Hospitals have gone through quite the transformation
Over the past 2 years
From being an install being
Very very obviously
Patience
Saving oriented
The problem is this
That exact orientation also made them Target
They're increasingly the target
Cyber attacks that are meant to Cripple their operations
So where once
Hospitals mostly have to worry about stealing of patient
Information
Something like that
Today they're handling a much tougher situation
What happens
Someone
Takes over your MRI machine
It cost you
Quite a bit
And takes it offline
Most hospitals is a really a really tough one
I mean
They need that device
Deceit lies they need it back
What is it
Statistics show that if you pay ransom for ransomware
You're going to get hit again
It kind of makes sense in a cynical way but it's just the way the world works
So increasing over the past two years
More and more hospitals
Realize
But they have to get a handle on what's going on with their medical devices
They have to get a handle on everything
Carmen
And I have to do it quickly
So your point
Understanding
Network-connected medical devices understanding their weaknesses
Standing what they should or should not be doing it being able to lock everything down
Is a very very
Big thing
Large Hospital
Today and I would answer that
That's some of the problems that they face is that a lot of the medical devices that they have kind of the earlier points
Are running really old
Standard Opera
Sothink Windows XP
Sync Windows 7
Which is going to be end of life
These are things that
Are hard for that because
Medical devices
Given everything that they know true
Application
All the different certifications of these devices went through
Names of the hospitals also camp
Securecrt traditional
Monitor
Take a look what they're doing so they're in a very very
Christine
Let's spin
2 second with chatting about maybe what we see happening
Types of device
I would say that
Beyond the general sense of these are problems
I can tell you from our own
So we've seen anything from MRI machines that were taken over and connected to command and control servers in Russia
All the way to ransomware spreading across Hospital networks in general
Even one
Fairly elaborate case where
Client hospital was faced with a situation
Where infusion pump connected to a live patient
Have malware running on it but it wasn't
In the scenario where you can't disconnected because there's a person connected to it
So they have to have a nurse
Sit next to me all night and make sure that device is still operational.
Shutting down not doing anything weird and
That's a situation that I think that's most
Hospital that's kind of a doomsday scenario reaching that point
Kill Point around kind of what to do about all this
So the answer is that you have to take
The very design of these devices into account when you're approaching the problem
All these devices
At the end of the day the risk surface that they pose
Is
So connectivity is exactly
A lot of these devices
We're not designed
Security in my car not too much security
There's a lot of
Things like open ports and Communications a lot of things that can be abused
And what I say is that
That very connectivity
Is exactly what any solutions that tries to solve this problem
Have to look at
I hope that that has
All right we'll do dear thank you so much for coming on the show.
Thank you very much.
That's it for this week thanks so much for listening and remember if you
You like more iot news sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot. Com