Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast
This is your house
Stacey Higginbotham and your co-host
Kevin tofel
And we have an amazing show for you
Are you today
This is episode 202 of the iot
T podcast and we're going to be talking about
Lowe's Iris shutting down
We've got acquisition
Galore to talk about talking about lifx
Wig wag and
Neo
You may not know
All of this company is but
You probably know their acquires
We have the New York Times did an editorial
Consent really talking about that as it relates to iot devices book here in Norco
The EU is
Recalling children's
SmartWatches that leak location data
And
The
UK
Which may not be
Be part of the EU
Any longer is spending 70 billion
On iot
Security Plus
Some new skills for the Google
Assistant
Bad news
For iot
Security again
And
We're going to hear from a new Advertiser this week called urbanex
+ Denise Howell Whois
An attorney in Newport Beach California came on the show to talk about
All the crazy
Ramifications of having connect
Get devices especially
In Criminal
Hand symbol
Proceedings
You're going to hear this and understand what rights do you have in
Most likely what rights do
You don't have
So let's get
To it
With a message from
Our sponsor
This week sponsor is Western dish
Western Digital builds Data Solutions that enable the world to solve its biggest challenge
On your phone
In your car
Brought your home and across cities
Everywhere data lives where there to drive the Innovation necessary for the best results
Today and tomorrow
Turn devices to systems and solutions
Our end-to-end infrastructure creates the right conditions for data
To realize its potential
Learn more at data makes possible
Dot-com
That's data
Makes possible.com
Okay
Hey Kevin
Before we get started on the show I should tell everybody
I've had a couple
Emails lately at people trying to
Play or show on their Google assistants or the
Echo device
The reason you can't get it
Because we are actually the internet
Of things podcast
So if
If you would like to hear it you just have to say Madam a play The Internet of Things podcast
And I will a
China what's the step
Okay
Let's talk about
Lowe's
Shut
Sing Down
Kevin this makes me so sad I remember all the way back in the
Mike 2012
Getting excited about Lowe's Iris and getting my own and
Setting it up and being
Kind of missed
Because it had a subscription fee to do a lot of the really cool stuff
This was in the era of Staples connect
And SmartThings launching
And
I can't remember if wink was on the scene yet or not
The good news is there's no subscription fee anymore
Cast
There's no Iris
So
At the end of last year they said that they were looking for a buyer
The time I really doubted that they
They could find one
Because it's a weird platformer
You'd have to support all the users
It's a dedicated system so it's not
It didn't seem like something
Anyone else would be excited
Basically
Right
Got to be a challenge to make money if you're a buyer of this
Do you know
Like you said support people turn a profit and so on so forth and yeah it's not like we didn't know this was coming cuz you
And we sat on the show couple months ago they're looking for a buyer we got a lot of questions about Lowe's Iris you always it's
Still going to be viable and so on and so forth
At this point
March 31st it is shutting down the platform
But
We see this happen all the time
Probably less now as the market is maturing
But this is probably the best possible way something like this could shut down for its customers because
Cause
People can continue to use the service through March 31st
You're not going to be charged
After
January 31st can I still get like two free months and you never prorated refunds actually going out to come
Customer switch
I'm very surprised by
Yeah you're going to get
If you're registered Iris
You'll get this email and if you
Click through in the link to the email you can actually
Register for a prepaid Visa card
So
You're going to get a Visa card
4 in
I guess in one of the Articles someone who had Iris said that they got about a hundred bucks for their Hub and 140 for their feet
Video camera
Which was about what he paid for it
Damso
That's
Has been shut down school it's a pretty rapid shutdown usually you
Get a little longer lead-time sometimes
You don't get rebates
Remember when Nest bought
Resolved and they were just like
We're going to shut this down in 6
Whatever was like what I paid $300 for this thing
And then finally nested
Come back and offer some rebates
So
Sad
It's doing well by its users by doing this
It's a bigger picture
Let's talk about what this means for the Smart Home
Because while Lowe's is doing this
Ikea is actually
Doubling down
With more products
Text and their CEO
Getting up on stage and talking about
Like launching have a kitchen as a service worker
Going to have you know
Furniture as a service
In this kind of
Rent not to own just
Rent to rent
Concept in
Products because of the connectivity
Being able to enable it so
I find it interesting that Lowe's is like
No
Ikea's like
Yeah
I'm surprised that
Ikea in a sentence going after this space but they are different from those because
They are selling
Furniture
They are selling the insides of your home where is
Louis
Who sells the components for the inside of your home building materials and so on yes they do sell appliances and other things but
It is a different type of store so I see this as a better
It for Ikea I'm not saying they're going to be successful I certainly hope AR
But
I mean based on the data that they have it must assume make it be successful here and I could see why they may think that we'll have to see
If that's actual reality though
Yes and I will also say I talked to some of the people who participated in those Iris over the years
In one of the complaints they had was
The companies would
Add connectivity to their products for the Lowe's Iris system but they wouldn't do it in a thoughtful way and what happened was they were
Doing it primarily to get
Promotion at Lowe's
The Branding so
Customers didn't always have an awesome experience or sometimes
Connectivity didn't enable anything that
Made sense
That's important
So
It is
We'll see
Yeah I still go to
You know my Hardware I was at Lowe's the other day about anymore
So
Yeah they'll continue to sell smart home devices it's just you know the iris
Brand and service is going away if you do want to get that Redemption don't go to your store for that it's all done
Online however Lowe's does say in the letter that they sent out to people
That you can return any Irish items purchased within the last 90 days
That are not connected to the Irish platform via the normal return policy so you may be able to get
Money back that way as well
Happy thought by this now and then maybe later I'll put it on the platform
Alright so
Said who's there
But maybe not unexpected
This feels like
As the markets mature and we're seeing a closing down of kind of the early days and speaking of that
Took a bunch of
So let's start with lifx
Lifx was just acquired
Bye buddy home
Which is based in Australia
Lifx was actually
Create an in Australia
We have the founders on the podcast like
2014 or so
Crazy thing
And
Ghetto
Typical thing on a colored light bulbs
Come along way they did a deal with Qualcomm
Licensing IP thing
Free wifi
Chips for light bulbs basic
And now
About my buddy
Which is an iot platform in Australia that does energy monitoring and management which is not something I
I actually associate
Lifx at all
And neither do I and that's the funny thing the intent is to use the lifx products to gain more
Energy monitoring data
But
Did you have to buy lifx for that kind of
Scratch my head over that
This may be a four stack
Position
I mean
If you look at where we are in the bar
Market we're seeing a lot of companies there like oh it's time
You got to reach scale
True
So
The purchase price is 51 million
Dollars
I feel like lifx probably if they were
Amazing what do better than that but they actually are the number two
Tender in the
Is it the colored smart light bulbs space in smart bulbs that's what they say behind
Philips which is no longer really Phillips
What is Philips Hue but
Company that actually owns the Philips hue light bulbs is
Childe signify
Just in case you guys were
Not confused
So now do we know if we're going to see
You know life X products continuing to be for sale here in the states
I would expect so
Even though nobody is
Mainly in Australia
Base platform
I mean I think that would be kind of silly to spend turkey 1 million and then
Really limit your sales
I haven't really said but
I
Can imagine that lifx goes away from everywhere but Australia
Wechat another acquisition
And things will go away
Wig wag
Which
Is a sensor company based in Austin
They started out making a very generic sensor and then pivoted to making an industrial
Or an Enterprise iot platform they have been acquired by our
The chip design firm
This looks like
A straight-up
It feels like cuz arm has such a big presence in Austin it feels like somebody's friend was like yeah sure
I'm sure they're slicks
Already happening here but wigwag
Their platform
Will be closing on May
And arm did send some refunds to
To the backers
Wig wag
Kickstarter
Wayback
So
I miss that Kickstarter
You did so I remember really well be
Because we were
Oh man we were in the middle of a cloud
Prince in when they launched
There
Kickstarter it was
Awesome it was like this generic sensor that was going to do
Everything and I mean
I wanted it
Like right then and there and it wasn't like
2013 that have
It was the sort of thing that I guess when we thought the
Home automation Market
Would be more creative and fun
You could actually like
Create all these cool rules and I thought people would want to buy
It was
It had humidity vibration
Temperature all the stuff and I
I thought you know it's a great thing that you
Put a lock on your washing machine when it stopped moving
It'd be like oh you're watching stunts
It was basically
And then later on they pivoted to be more enterprise-focused
And critic 8-way device and then sensors there but
So goodbye
Wee bag
Hopefully arm is taking maybe some of your interface I don't know really
What are there getting you
Maybe it's okay
There was no
Pricing associate
Okay
And then finally
Control4 which is a
Professional home automation
Can system
Everly Candles Company
Yes Charlie Candles there is
His company but
Head of
Amazon smart home stuff
Castform anime
She went over there last year
So they bought a company called Neo
Animatrix
Nothing
Device that
Control your television
Controlled
Your lace it worked and it was a really beautiful life
Ticket launch to the city of
Maybe it was CES I've seen it for the last
A couple years ago
Those shows
In
It's fancy it's nice it's pretty I mean it's kind of like a
Display on it and very simple buttons
Tapped into their database of like a gazillion product
60000 devices
Yeah
And basically when I talked to Charlie briefly about
Bastille this is
Their whole thing is at
At the Smart Home is too complex for
DIY hours most people are not going to want to
Integrate all this
Weather so they're trying to bring in
Pieces that they think are attractive
And useful and easy-to-use so
Their dealer Network
Can come in and do it for people and then people still have
Like more options to
. so that's
Video hear you book The interesting thing
Current Neo customers they're going to get support
For all services
For another 24 months
They're not going to sell the Neo anymore
They're not buying it for the remote with Avaya I guess for the smarts the SDK the database
Okay so
All of these acquisitions
Big picture you guys we talked about this we've talked about this for the last year-and-a-half
There are a lot of iot platform place I got funded in 2013
They're all going away
They couldn't
Reach scale
And bus
Yeah I'm getting some soon I mean it's not like they had bad technology cetera but
They can't do it alone obviously
Right
And I mean that's not surprising
A lot of these companies got a lot of their money and started right after Google paid 3 point
2 billion dollars for nest
Crazy rate in everyone's like
Oh my God I got to get it
Smart Homes
End
That was the high right there
And it was way high I still don't think it was the best
Purchase price value
But you know
Nest is still around still doing well they're integrating it better into things
I think they're making
Lemonade out of their lives
Okay let's talk about
Let's talk about privacy in
Data security and all that
Get stuffed
That we love so much
Here at the show this weekend the New York Times did an article on
Send
And
Practice of doing these Longview Les and you basically say
Yeah yeah I agree
And thinking NASA
Reasonable way to do a contract between a user in
Adidas
And they're longer than I thought I always thought that you was were long but it was interesting to see you right in the beginning of the story
Reading Amazon's terms and conditions alone out loud takes approximately 9 hours
Yes
Yeah what's up
Maybe if you read it
To yourself it takes less but it is a long time and I'll tell you I read
Read all of these like a whole day's worth of effort
Yeah
In
It mean when you read them
You're also
There's only one option
You click yes if you want to use it
If you have to
Suzuki
Close to you
So
It feels like
It is like
It is a very uneven Exchange
Especially
In my opinion
I already paid you money
To buy this device
And the functionality
And you're paying that money before you even know what the terms of service are
So there's been some ideas here we talk to people in the show who
Suggested like when you put a device in your Amazon cart
You get a
Little
How to play
Do you know Apple or Google does with their
Permissions when you download an app
You can something like that
It says this shares data with 3rd power
You consent to that
And then you have to read those
Before you can actually
Buy the product
Which I think is
Not a bad idea
It's a very good start
I don't know if we're ever going
See that but
So that's one way to do that
So the New York Times essay
I bring this up because this is something we've talked
Talked about for like two or three years we we've talked about the lack of any meaningful
Concentra
Can you sign these things
And the lack of recourse for
Consumers when they realize what they've given up
You can always bring things back without paying lyca restocking
Eeyore
You know
Sometimes you just
Can bring it back at all and
That feels unfair
And I'm glad the New York Times has talked about this cuz the New York Times is
As it were the paper of record so when they start talking about things
Things actually happen
Which
I wish we had that power Kevin
We do not but they did point out some of the things we have talked about before obviously gdpr
Over in
The Hue enemy California
Law
Yes
This is definitely something that
People are thinking more about with
The Wider ass face
Books candles
Some of the Privacy conversations with apples trying to bring up and of course
CPR
So the solution here
I don't know there's efforts by
I told you about that particular idea about looking at data
Before
You put something in your cart there's also public knowledge released a paper last week about creating assets
Security Shield
This is more about security and not as much about privacy
But the idea is there encouraging the government to
Create a program call
Call the security Shield that is kind of like
The epa's
Energy star
And so if you're not familiar with that the energy star program
Is federally there's a law written
It talks about what standards things need to meet
Achieve this stick
Basically
And
Public knowledge is power
Paper is all about how to create such a program for iot device secure
So that would be useful right
Absolutely
So yes
Maybe that way
Will happen I'm sure.
Let's talk about
Let's talk about another security
Challenge this is actually in the EU
How much GDP are so there is a recall of children's smart watches that are leaking location data which
Nobody wants
Now this is the safe
Kid one made by a German company called Enochs group
It is not for sale in the UK or the us but
Apparently in Iceland
They found out that the mobile app
That works with the watch
Has unencrypted Communications to the server so there is unauthenticated access to the data so you can get
My location history of a child wearing a Swatch phone number serial number Etc
Yeah so it was basically I think they call it a wrap it alert as part of the rules and laws over there too
Recall this thing and that's exactly what's happening
It's pretty power
Forcing a product recall is
That's not a thing to be taken
Yeah I totally agree
I don't want to see this is overkill this is okay this is a problem that needs to be resolved but even if
It's just the mobile app that
Has the unencrypted data why couldn't they just put an app update out that
Encrypted data
Probably because they couldn't Insure One because it's the EU
But to maybe they couldn't insure people
Downloaded the patch
Maybe the watch was too small that Hardware on the inside was too small to like
Take the patch and then
Reboot I don't know
From a technical standpoint if it's connecting to a back-end server and it's the data go into that server they could shut the service off until people
Updated
Not the watch that it's updated Sac City app
According to this story so it may be just a send a message I don't know like we're not going to
Tolerate this kind of
We're Not Gonna Take It
No
Oh I'm singing it must be a good day
Speaking of encryption
And let's take a moment to say here's the basic rule you should encrypt
Your data on your servers
You should encrypt your data
Find the app
And you should encrypt
The data on the device
And then
Whenever that data is
Traveling
Play the app and then
Device between
Cloud
The phone in the cloud
You should also encrypt
There that should just be the way it is in yes encryption is a
Pain there's a little bit of overhead there some costs associated with
But if you want to secure iot
It's not Job 1
Not having hard-coded password
Unsurprisingly child
But
Sparkle table Stakes it still tablesteaks absolutely
So
This reason
To a report about
Unlocking encryption on some popular iot devices
Yeah this is a test data from researchers at Brazil's Federal University of
Pernambuco which I may have
Totally
That up but that's okay and University of Michigan which I got that right
They took it.
The Wolverines
Alcohol during sex
Tom Brady
Whatever
The report took a look at 32 smartphone apps used to configure
Incontrol 96 Audi
Top selling WiFi Bluetooth devices sold on Amazon so that's a pretty good
Testbed async
Unfortunately
Lee found out
31% of the apps have no encryption at all
And another 19% had hard-coded encryption keys so you could
Perhaps reverse-engineer the encryption bad bad bad
Kind of jumped out of me because of the companies and products named here
They
Created some proof-of-concept attacks based on their findings
Anime basically break
To hack around with
Tp-link
The lifx app
Belkin WeMo and broadlink e-control app
So granted a lot of these tax you have to be on the same Wi-Fi network and so on that's kind of a given
In cases but that doesn't make it
Acceptable so well
They also shared that
Tp-link
They have the same hard-coded encryption key for all of the devices of a given product
Yeah yeah they even showed the code I mean I can see the Java code and I actually can understand it thanks my Java class
I have the seating number for the hashing and encryption and
I could
Probably figure out what the encryption key is based on that but actually so could probably anybody was the time at 4
Yeah and Kevin hasn't spent that much time and effort
So
Not on that note this is not yet
So this is not that hard so what is this mean for you guys
People who have these
Cuz I have to pee
Dlink switches in my house I have WeMo
Are you stopping
Actually
This month we're giving away a WeMo dimmer switch
Encryption not included
So in some cases it's a design
So WeMo doesn't
Encryption they don't do encryption between the device in the app is part of making it easier for users
They say
Now I know
One of their former
Security folks
The leftover
For this so this is something that
Did they've chosen to do even though they know
So
You might say okay
We talked about risk profiles and
Previous podcast but you might say hey do I have a high enough risk profile that I should really worried about this or are the devices that are
Into these Outlets
Could I really cause
Problems
You know what is it
Is an air purifier or is it a
Curling iron
Thermostat
I mean I don't know why you wouldn't talk it in obviously but I'm just thinking
Portable heater
So you don't think about what you got plugged into these device
Two might want to hack
How easy it is
Getting on your Wi-Fi network is not
Super trivial unless you
And out your
Wi-Fi network like candy
Which some people do
I always recommend guest Network for everybody
Especially your kids friend
Man today is chock-full of
Security tips for
Yeah I would also recommend
Choosing devices Worthy
Apps have two-factor Authentication
To log into those app
That way people cannot log into an app
As you
Easley anyway
And control your devices if they were to gain access to mosto
Yeah for example if I was on Kevin's Wi-Fi network
Etihad WeMo devices
Because I have WeMo devices in my house and I'm running the Apple
I just open my WeMo app in his house if I'm on his Network and start controlling
His devices
Yeah I'll be back
And we Moto's
That's not a choice if I understand
7 on the flip side the report did it's not all doom and gloom
Reported point out that Google's Nest thermostat app is a good example of how to do security right
Which I know that also supports two-factor authentication and all the configuration is secure with SLT
Last of the cloud or via Wi-Fi with wpso
There are right ways to do that are examples of this
Kind of should be a standard but that's a whole another issue that we sort of touched upon earlier
Yeah in Google I will say Google does a lot of stuff behind the scenes on the security
Not allowed to talk about some of the things I hate
I do but they're very good
The Nest devices are
Are very good
So very comfortable when they see flaws or when
People bring things up
They actually took
Communicate with
Users they update tp-link has had a couple hacks and they have not updated a lot of stuff
So they're cheap though
And that's what
People seem to be buying
So it's not the downside of
This is that security does cost money and it costs convenience and
People
I don't know I don't actually have to factor enabled on my Nest even though I think it's a great thing to have
Know any chance I can't I do and then I have a
Google Titan security key for
All those accounts you can use a benefit Decatur app there's lots of ways. You can use SMS messaging
Would be my least favorite option at that's not as secure as other options
Alright will see you now we know that I am terrible at
And I wish that the MyQ
The Chamberlain MyQ also
So has 2Pac
Application which this is the year of us calling
42 Factor
On all iot device
So get used to it
You're not using it maybe I should come to your house and try and control your nest
Read on that
Okay
Speaking of Google
We got some news on assistant
Google Assistant
Chanel
Figure into
Interpreter which announced at CES
I was super excited about it
And then I had like right when I got home from CVS I had a foreign exchange student my house from Spain
We totally could have used it
But it wasn't out yet
So what
Yeah there's always at the CES demo that Google gave and it works
Flawlessly in that demo and it wasn't kander staged it was just a regular Google home device and they had a
Conversation in English and French
Because obviously multiple languages but they showed it off it was cool it's one of those cool features that are unfortunate I'll never use
Cuz I don't really have foreign exchange students here but it is rolling out now so if you have need of it
You should see it
Anytime soon I would say
And what do you say
If you want to have a conversation in a language essay Spanish
Do you say be my Spanish interpreter or
Help me speak Spanish and it becomes a basically it is almost a port of the Google translate mobile app
Right on
We have a smart home display it'll show with both sides of the conversation
In the two languages so you can read it as well as hear it
But if you don't it would just
If you have a Google home
You just hear the translation
See it but
I can't seem to work very well
Yay and I actually
So
Not in person
But in communicating via
Email in
Text with
B
Parents of Exchange
Didn't I would actually
Translate function on
Google assist
Can I be like
I typed my thing in English no translated to Spanish.
And apparently they got the gist so we're good
He didn't use those Google pixel buds so you can probably return those things
II
Yeah those are those really Nifty
At least in theory
Headphones that you would connect to your phone and it would use the Google Translate app kind of been real time so you can hear the Translate
Someone but didn't seem to work very well
At the headsets they were.
Other Google News
Making life a little easier now you can get
Google assistant on your nest guard
And if you're like what is my Nest guard it is part of the nest security system it is bbrainz of that it's a little
Thing that you
I can wave your tag over to
Turn your alarm on and off
Basically now you can ask it things like oh
Haji do I need an umbrella today
And it will
It will help you
Yeah this is rather sneaky because I don't know that everybody knew there was a microphone in
Yashow it's an option
Temperature and it's often because
NASCAR does have an on device microphone
If you've got one
It's not enabled by default
So that's why you've got to opt-in
But it's not an always listening device if you don't want it to be
What I would love and I don't know if it works this way but
Because you're doing this as you rush out the
The door it would be awesome to set reminders for your nest guard
To be like
Do you have your gym clothes it's Thursday right
Or whatever is like reminders you need
As you walk out
Cuz I'm always walking out the door
Thanks right so
When you
Swipe that tag
And it knows you're there
Be awesome if it just shout it out
Proactively
Don't forget your gym clothes
Yeah I don't think it does that
Which it would be really cool I wonder if there's a routine available for that or someone which one
Pulling up well and maybe
I mean it software
We can always make it better
Yep so
Instead of just always ask
Asking I'd have it proactively remind me
Me about things that aren't pork
Cool alright
So that
Doesn't quite
Make for the
It's a very expensive security system but it might be worth it eventually
That is it for the new section of the show let's go to the iot podcast
Hotline
We got a winner to announce and
We have a question
About Viper
This week the iot podcast hotline is sponsored by a pharaoh
What's the fifth largest iot patent
Hopefully on the world
Afero provides a proven iot platform that doesn't risk
Ask your brand
Apparel customers have experienced as much
Percent reduction in time to Market
Nginx higher activation rate
Learn more at a pharaoh.
All right on the voice mail this week
Let's see who was our winner for the January challenge
They will get my old Google
Home
Day that would be Martin who called in last month for the January giveaway so congratulation
And if you want to be entered to win a WeMo dimmer switch
Note
We talked about
Please give us a call at 5 1/2
6 to 3
7 4
To 4
And
You will be entered
To win
That needs to happen before the end of February
It's a short
So February 28th at
Midnight Eastern
Colace
And poof
It's Magic here in
So let's go to this week's voice mail which is about
Light switches
Yay
Hey Stacy this is ad
From a little Kentucky
My iot question
Involves lighting
I have
Currently have
Plum lightpad
I was part of their Kickstarter
Purchase those seams if those are not viable any
At least what I can gather
To my internet search and
Not working as well there
The timing
Json outside lights actually is now
Working
Enough for me and some
Looking for a smart light switch to
Implement
In its place
I love the color ring around the
Plum lightpad
You know it's not a necessity
What's at the noon
Light switches as well but
Looking for other options out there maybe
CES 2019 will have to
On that front as well
Oanda
This is sad news this is another one of those companies that
We thought might get bought but didn't
Plum is
Actually in Austin company it was
Founded by the former head of Cydia
Way back in 2012 and idea was to make
An awesome light switch that controlled
Everything
I mean truly it was
Is way ahead of its time nose very pretty
But
They are no longer
It doesn't seem that they're operating
Anymore I have not gotten any emails back
Back from them
About my questions
Feels pretty grim
So
Plum light pads
They're actually ahead of their time but now we've got tons of options
Choose from
You mentioned energy monitor
And so that's throwing us for a little bit of a loop
Cuz the only energy monitoring light switch that we
Find an actual switch
Was a zigbee based 1/4
Mge
If energy monitoring is
Important to you
And that's probably what you should go with but then you've got hugs and all this other
But
You just want to really highly functional Advanced light
Then we got lots of options
You mentioned the noon those are cool because they do these pre-designed lighting things
Very pretty
I would also make a plug
For brilliance
Those do a lot of home automation
Control and they don't have a pretty LED but you can put your own
Photos on there
And that's kind of neat if you like to see pictures of
Your family are
Your favorite
Vacation spot
Lightpad they do have timer functionalities alarms Electric
Control your Sonos your nests
All kinds of stuff
A little complicated to set up
I would recommend
Professional installer
And they're expensive
But
I do a lot
If your
Less
Like your like that is too much
Idevices make
A dimmer switch
Or a on off switch
Switch usually you need to double-check
Which is which
It only works with iOS so only Apple but it is Wi-Fi so you don't need any sort of hubby
Take things
And they have that led have an LED on the device that
Might be exciting
Or you can wait
Because you are entered to win our WeMo dimmer and you
You can see how you feel about that
Yeah we look
High and low for something very similar to
The plum
Which is unique because it has an LED light ring around the switch so Shore minutes
In the dark it's really easy to find but nobody else has done that that we could see
There plenty of switches had like a little LED indicator making LED strip
But nothing around the entire
Paddle switch itself unfortunately
But there are lots
Lots of light switches so if you want to
Like I said brilliant switch
I just read about a company
Oreo Oreo switch looks really interesting I haven't tested it out
It feels like something
Do you want to test
That's all about like wellness and circadian rhythms and dimming lights in
Automation actually automatic car
Libation where it learns about the sensors in that one
Tons of sensors in there
It doesn't do the energy monitoring
So
I hate to
That leaving you empty-handed I'm almost leaving you with
Too many things
But maybe you can call us back and
Let us know what your most
Features are cuz it's a little unclear
And I think headlining today you're going to have to decide
Your top two features it's kind of like buying a new car
I must have this in this
Can I help you choose
Which car is the
All right
That is it
For this segment
Of The Internet of Things podcast
Stay tuned
For our guest
Denise Howell
She is a lawyer
Actually talking
About gdpr
What kind of data can be subpoenaed
In a case from your smart devices
We're going to be talking
Sing about actually some of the consumer rights stuff about
Returning connected devices and consent
So it's a really good interview you're going to love it stay tuned for that
And now
Let's go to a message from our sponsor
Hey everyone we are taking a break from The Internet of Things podcast for a message from our sponsor sponsor is
Urban X
And I have Micah
Koch who is managing director of urbanex
Scared to talk to us
Hi Micah how are you doing
I'm excellent hbase
Thanks for having us
Excellent so let's just get started with having you tell me a little bit about urbanaxes
Urban axes
An accelerator for startups a rematch
City Lights
The program was built by many and we run it in partnership with the Venture fund
Our goal is to work with
Early-stage technology companies
Many of them are working
In The Internet of Things
Can help them level up
What resources do companies have access to during the program
Two are companies participate in
Really immersive intensive 5 month
Program
To help accelerate their development
Perspective
The business perspective and then really prepare them for fun
They get access to
Incredible Network
2000 experts and entrepreneurs
Mentors and help guide them on there
We also helped
To provide them with a thousand hours
Hands-On
Resources
In electrical engineering
Mechanical engineering ux UI
Graphic design software development
We invest
$100,000 each
The company's flexible term
A very short amount of time
What is the relationship between urban X in BMW
/ Mini
This is a really great question our Core Business obviously at Binny's
Focused on
Offering products and service
Ability but really the future of the brand is going to extend more deeply into other areas
Including lifestyle components
And so when you think about the evolution in the automotive
Autonomous connected Electric
Shared services
We're really trying to identify new ways that we can kind of serves Urban residents
Where most of Minis
These customers are
And people who are
Smelly looking for new Solutions
Even when they're not
Within their vehicle
Is a car brand interested in improving life and say
Lenny Williams always been a quintessentially urban Brands since it was
Crisis in the late night
The company really
Collaborate
People who are living in a
Ultimately
We can help bring those who
Where can people go if they want to find out more about urbanex or even apply for your new cohort that starts in
So application
April 1st
2019 and you can apply or nominate
Your favorite startup at Urban -
Dot-com
Flash Supply
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast
This is your house Stacy Higginbotham today's guest is Denise Howell who is a technology lawyer
Newport Beach California
Are you
Hi Stacy it
It's great to be here thanks so much
I am super excited to have you because I love having lawyers on the show is long
Is there willing to go out a little little bit of a lemon talk about things sometimes lawyers they don't like to do that
Well I'll do my best
There we go I will make you say anything too crazy
Times of legal issues associated with The Internet of Things most of which
We're just going to have to find out by a lake
Doing people and watching the court so we're going to tackle it first with
What everybody is
Talking about which is
Privacy
Data protection and privacy and
I feel like we're going to get some sort of law
This year at a federal level California to pass the law
Last year that goes into effect
20/20
What do you see ahead for privacy regulation
I think I'm less optimist
Then you are that we're going to get something at the federal level this year I feel like our federal law
Tigers have
Lots and lots on their mind they've had a bill
That they could have got
That's been sitting in committee for a while that regulated
Internet
Devices that are sold to the federal government
That hasn't
Passed yet
And sitting around
For a bit
That was kind of a landlord
That was I read that long I was
Wow that is like
Brightwell
Hello government
I think you put your finger on the other problem right they don't
Necessarily
Know or have their arms around what they need to do to do more than the bare minimum
So4
This issue to be legislated on it
National level I do think that will
Actually happened
But I think what we will probably see
On the Internet of Things front is wet
I think we'll also see on
Privacy front
Is the state
Start to enact
Their own laws
Is there
Citizens are fed up
Pressuring their local lawmakers
To put something in place
At the state level and we start to get this Patchwork of
Different rags in different places that
As a practical matter everyone
One house to comply with if they're doing business in all of the states of the United States
So most of the LIE
So far have dealt with the physical security of devices
We're talking about things like
Hey
Let's not have hardcoded passwords
Let's make sure you force people to change
Passwords it's very much kind of good behavior
In a device-level
In contrast
That's what happened with Europe with gdpr as they actually did legislation
Protected
Data and I think those are kind of
Worth breaking apart
Just a little bit
Because obviously one is about
Security
Picture day like crazy how do you say legislators should
Define the problem
Privacy fence
Security with iot devices
Well I think The Regulators in the EU have swept iot devices in Ride Along
Anything else
Just they haven't made their gdpr law device-specific
So if you're
Reaching
If there
Tenants with any of your devices
Citizen how your hand
Data
Can be brought before one of their tribunals and
Find quite a bit
Approach that
Could see us lawmaker
First take Internet of Things has its own
Specific problems that I think as you
Alluded to States like California and others are trying to make sure that glaring problems like her
Coded passwords
The Tetra are dealt with
But just
Because
There are specific laws directed at the internet of things doesn't mean that those devices
Also have
To comply with data laws or the people putting those devices
Out there and then managing the data that they collect with
Okay so we probably should see
Data privacy laws and then specifically
Secure your devices lock them down
Yes
I think that's very likely
The makers of
These devices
Have to deal with both kinds
So you're not as optimistic as I am about a federal
I feel like the industry the tech industry is actually calling for this now
We're going to have so many different laws
Microsoft was talking at Davos
Last month about having
Some sort of
Global
Privacy and data regulation law
Do you think that's crazy
I don't think it's crazy at all
I'd love to see us
Move in that
Direction
Logistically difficult to get a cord
That leads to a lot
People can actually
Enforce and understand
Just like it's better to have
A federal law that
People can
Comply with and understand and
Not have to worry about
Weather things are different in Arkansas than they are in Missouri it would be
Nice rock
Concerned to have
Adequate
Consumer protection
Privacy and data protection
Rules that are easy to interpret and follow for the manufacturers of these
Spices on the other
I think that
If you can get people talking about how to bring the logistics of it about this
What's the positive staff
Talk about consumer rights with
Gadget
So right now we're just kind of figuring things out
And a lot of times what happens is I might buy a gadget or a device
Or car
Or in some cases even
House
It will come with a lot of home automation or smart stuff built in the challenges
A lot of times you don't have the chance to read the terms of service until you're actually making this purchase or until your actual
You downloaded the app and now you're agreeing to everything
So to me this seems like
A terrible way to do things especially when you're pulling so much
How much data out of it
How might we
Change that
It is a terrible way to do things
Set the gdpr tries to address
That instead of just assuming that
People
I have read and understood things
At each
Interaction where data is going to be
Be collected a separate consent is
Is required
Fine print that then
Is assumed to be applied as binding
That's sort of the place where we would
Want to get to
We're not there
As you point out
As far as the smart home devices go it is the Wild Wild West
And we're going to see a lot of
Litigation we're going to see
Other laws that haven't been
Enacted specifically.
Deal with these problems being brought in
Play
WYD
And in some cases
We have a legal framework in place you know we have tort law which is
If you recklessly
Harm somebody
In a way that is protected under the law
Then you can
Can be sued so it's a big broad Body of Lies
Deals with personal injuries it also deals with
Things like
Less tangible heart
So you can harm someone's economic
Pinterest you can harm someone's privacy
Can harm them
Emotionally
That's so
There are all kinds
Is of torts out there that
Could be brought to bear
On the internet
Thanks and I expect
If
Companies are reckless in
Misusing data
Find themselves in a PR
Boiling
Kettle of fish
Going to see a lot of
Already
Existing principles
Tort law thrown at that
And may start to rain
Some of the saint
And a lot of times these aren't terrible like one of the things I think is really difficult is it very hard to prove the harm
Having your data stolen for exam
I guess I could say
Oh my gosh
Someone broke into my security camera
And took naked pictures of me all over the internet
That feels like
I can prove harm there
I'm hoping because isn't that one of the core tenets of these sorts of lawsuits
Sure we have a right of privacy and this
Country and
If you've enabled someone to
Be held accountable
Under those kinds of principles
On the date of front I think
Proving harm comes down to
You know if someone has
Stolen your identity stolen
Money
Damage your reputation there are all kinds of ways
Demonstrating
Legal
Work someplace that prevent
People willy-nilly being able to carry out those arms against you
So I think that the legal system and the laws
We have on the books to some extent
Handle
This explosion of devices
It sure would be nice
To have
Thought given
And Analysis given
That actually address
Squirrely in head on the problems that these devices
This present
That might not
Easily dealt with under the laws we already have
Sure I'm thinking of things like have a corporate wellness program and
My manager somehow gets data about
My sleep pattern
What's under this this is not have
Today
We're not too far off given house
Some of the insurance companies are treating data from
Other medical devices
They start to make decisions about like oh hey maybe you should handle this account cuz you know it looks like you didn't
Sleep well last night was pretty easy let's
Dennis Diane for this presentation he's looking
Capable at the moment
Those kind of things feel more
Insidious that maybe just
Crashing your car into something
And that's where I think
If it comes really challenging because these are also harms that could follow you throughout your life in a way that
You may not even be aware of
Write that I love your exam
That's exactly the kind of situation where
You may not even know that decisions are being made about
Based on
Date of the people shouldn't
Maybe accidentally you would find that out
But then
How could you address it
That's a really tough one.
Some gray area that we're getting into
Okay and
This idea of
Maybe
Unknown Harms
There's also
Some very clear heart
I said I don't think
We think about when we buy these connected devices which is that they could be used against
In a court of law
A civil court or
Murdering anyone
Microphones I have all of this data in my house that
It's been collected and I'm very curious how do you think that situation
What's already evolving we've seen instances already
Where prosecutors in Murder
Actions and investigations have
Obtain data from
Relevant
Peoples
Fitbit's and Echoes and
There was a case we talked about it
A few times on this week in law that involved a murderer in
Arkansas
Where
It was actually a
Connected device on the water heater for the wall
Get the hot tub murders
Yes
And they actually track
2 a.m.
And decided that meant this person was cleaning up
Right
Strange strange things already going on
As far as
Prosecutors getting creative how they're going to build their case
Of course
That's a boon for law enforcement that they have all this
Data
Pick and choose from in trying to
Prove a case
It's not necessarily
A boon for all the litigants because
Although you're not planning to commit murder maybe you still wouldn't
Be planning to commit murder when one was
Committed
And somehow you wind up in the crosshairs
Sever prosecution
Because
Of the data that seems
To you
I might get the wrong place at the wrong time
Exactly so
We're definitely seeing
It will only get worse I mean I imagine
People running their hands in this way and
Speculated
In this way
When
Everyone be
Began to have
Computer where they were storing a lot of it
Information and certainly smartphones have been a huge part of the data
Environment
For what at least 15 years out right Supreme Court just actually it was it last year
Decided on a
Smartphone GPS case
It was
Fishing expeditions
Yeah in the Supreme Court actually seems
Issuing some very
Smart decisions about
What smart devices
So we can keep our fingers crossed that that
Trend
Continues
But the other thing you mentioned civil cases are I'm sure that people
Wondered about all the data on
Devices before there were things like smart light bulbs
Smart locks
Smart watches
Smart sleep apnea devices
So it's just
Throwing a whole lot
More data
To the ecosystem
And
The way the legal system handles that
Again this is a question of
Principles that are hundreds of years old being applied to the
Conundrums that we're facing
Today
And those principles actually
Do a pretty good job of
Trying to make sure that
We're having
Fair trials
Evidence has
To be
Credible
It has to be
Legitimate and legitimize
So if you're going to introduce something
You have to
Be able to have an expert
Come in and
Say why
The jury or the other Trier of fact
If it's just a judge
Entrust
The conclusions that are being drawn
The date of the
Put forth in court
So that's going to be true and Civil Trial or a criminal trial in order to trust
The state at its
Going to have to clear some hurdles
Being
Evidentially
Credible
Unacceptable
Before it can
Do the job and
Show somebody
Illegal act
So while I am
Concerned about being at the wrong place at the wrong time
And less concerned about you know Murder is getting
Caught up by their device
That's right that
The last concerning but when I think about civil
Trials
Nervous about like who can subpoena my Fitbit data
Like if there is
And that's just a random
In case I don't know why it would be in a lawsuit with someone
My Fitbit data
What are the basic
Rules that we should be aware of
Apps like how is that data access to has a say in
Yay or nay to it
Right so if you're a party
A lhasa
A civil lawsuit and that data is relevant
The same dispute in the last shooting that something that might have
What the judge whether it's relevant
But if you're a party and it's relevant
If it's under your control then you have to Fork it over
Often times with these
Internet of Things devices it might not be under
Control
Repository
And subpoenaed from there
And again just as if that party hat
Document
Just the fact that it's
Hard coded data doesn't
Mean that they don't have to
Turn it over if there's
A subpoena or a court order that says that they should
To help resolve this dispute
So a good question
Would be what is the data retention policy going to be for these devices
How much of the stuff is going to live on for
Perpetuity is it going to be
Various Emeril so that
Can't be
Subpoenaed in used
Company by company what they decide their policies are
Obviously
The date is very lucrative so they have some
Hold on to it
But at the
Same time do they really want to be in the business of
Having to Fork over data to feel people's
Lawsuits another dispute
Sometimes
People, knock on the door
Company and say Hey you know we'd like to see
Information they don't have a court order
They don't
Have a subpoena I would hope that most companies policies would be walk right away
People's data event
A kind and less were
Ordered two
Bye
Due legal process
But you never know unless they're under various
Data protection regulation
To decide how they're going to respond to those
Got it well in there's also an interesting wrinkle there in that there are lots of products out there in the market
Scription plans for cloud storage of data
And the consumer in some cases may not if they don't pay for that plan have access to the data
The company might still retain it
Which
I don't even want to think about that
There's one other issue that your question raised and that is I talked about it
If you're a party to lawsuit
Irrelevant
Under your control
You have to turn it over but
We talked about one way in which third parties can
Can be brought in
If the data
Resides with
The third party
What if your let's go back to your running by the murder scene with your Fitbit on
Example
What is
The prosecutors there wanted
Have the data from
Your Fitbit
Because you were a witness
And they wanted to see how it impacted you
If you saw a
A mess
And if your heart rate
Spite
Your normal running heart rate
You saw some terrible
Event take place or not maybe
Chancellors would want to say
Is witness Ram by their heart rate
Stayed the same
So
I could see how you could be brought into a dispute
Or your device could even if you have
Very little to do with it
Just happened to be that you sent in the wrong place in the
Wrong time
Yes I'm going to hope I never run by a murderer as it's happening
For so many reasons
All right
They say the Internet of Things is today
I think it's this fact that
Security researchers think that these devices
In particularly like a sieve
And again analogizing back
Early days of
Other
Devices
Tibet
Are important in our lives
The early days of
Computers
Operating systems
Windows operating systems
Also according to security researchers and demonstrably according to events that happened
Leaks like a sieve ultimately
The
Operating system manufacturers got on top of
Is that issue and
Got
Somewhat ahead of the cat and mouse game
People trying to compromise
Advice
And
Attached devices
And took care of
The public using their tools and I think that that's the
The problem that we
With the Internet of Things
Sort of
Idot phase in development where it's still
Kind of wide open
Things aren't being passed
Not only are they not being
Released in an insecure way to begin with
Even just without even being hacked
There just something that leaks data and
Sense data around in
Wasted
They shouldn't
Expect
Is unreasonable so that I think is
This problem that we're facing right now and I think it will take awhile and
Growing pains and some
Lawsuits and
Bad press
But they ultimately hopefully we will come to a point where
The product being released in the first instance
Is
As good a product is it
Canby
At that time and that it gets
Updated and past going forward
I will be hopeful with you
I just think it's going to take awhile to the economic incentives are quite there yet
So
I can't wait till Denise thanks so much for coming on the show today
Thank you so much Stacy this was a pleasure
That's it for this week
Thanks so much for listening
I remember if you'd like more iot news
Sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot, will see you next week