Hey everyone welcome to the 219 episode of The Internet of Things
Podcast
This is your house
Stacey Higginbotham and Jericho
Kevin tofel
And we have
Show that is all about you guys it is our
Biannual and semiannual how many annuals
Twice a year
Question and answer
Where you call us
Ask a couple questions or one
And we will give you the answer
In this week's show we're going to be talking about
Smart Stove
Monitoring systems
Monitoring your washer and dryer
Figuring out if someone has left you some mail
And
A little bit about my switch to Google home
So much
But first before we kick it off
IMessage
Our sponsor
This week sponsor is
Nordic
Semiconductor
Are you planning a wireless iot project and he's best-in-class performance and great Energy Efficiency
Then the nrf52 series Wireless SOC
Should be your first stop
Nordic semiconductor offers a broad selection of multi-protocol soc's to match your requirements for features
Size and cost
The NRF series range from Baseline Network processor devices to Advanced concurrent protocol devices with
Extensive peripheral
All devices are supported with the largest SDK you will find from a low-power wireless stomach
Accompanied
So if you're planning a project with Bluetooth low energy
Zigbee thread
Mercante
Check out the nrf52 series SOC family
Add
Nordic semi
Dot-com
Okay Kevin
I love doing the show
Except it's kind of hard on it
There's a lots of great questions that we get him since we only do one voicemail question.
During the regular weekly show
This lets us catch up in a sense and get back to everybody else who might have caught
I should mention that throughout this year
We have to voicemail sponsors but the show one is Schlage
Which makes
Smart locks a variety of high-quality smart locks fit
Everyone knows and loves
And a pharaoh which is an iot development platform
And you hear about them almost every other episode on the show so
You probably know about them but we do want to give a big shout-out
Since this is
All brought to you
Buy them
All right
Yay slang
Yay
Alright let's kick it off with a message
Jeremy
I believe it
Let's hear it
Hi this is Jerry from Little Rock
I'm looking for something for the educational Market
That would help induce
Students to AI
We've tinkered with chatbots and like
To incorporate this
Into working with
Skills from anime or Google home
Are you serious
These devices have
So the question is
Is this the best around
To go and if so do you have ideas on how to get this
Happier in educational Market
Perhaps the bigger question
Do you have an opinion of a better route to go to inter
AI
Thanks in advance love you show
Oh
Jeremy I like you so much for being a caring smart
Exciting teacher I wish I were in your class
Yes and it's ironic that Jeremy is asking this question because in my comp sci class at my local community
College
We ran into the same issue
Esl older students probably
We couldn't get access to the student emails
Through the Google cloud and other things we wanted to use
So I had to use my own personal
Account for all of our API calls in one
So I totally get it
And even more so because
This is really tricky if the students were the kids are under 13
Because in most cases then they can't have an account
Well they can have one but it
Tied to their
Yeah it's it's just Anna and I don't even know if that kind of account I am not going to call it a sub account
But Google has school-related
Accounts
I haven't seen
Assistant
In-home devices attached to
Nearby
Right and they would need
An account that kind of works with assistant if they want to Tinker with the apis that Google provides
This kind of stuff on Google not the only one
Amazon and Microsoft and many many other
Companies have apis Atwood
Be useful for what Jeremy's looking for
So
I hate to say it. I have a couple options
This one is to do what I asked you what I just did
I register my account for different API services
Somewhere for Google summer for lifx
Etc
To get an API
Key
And once you have the API key if you can do any kind of like coding
You can just let the students and the kids use that API key to
Access
Any
Cloud type
Air ml services
So that's one option
There are a couple of
Things out there some products one is relatively new because it
Kickstarter right now in fact it's Mike Elgan
Sun
Mike Elgan we don't know he does the used to do that
This week in Google show you talk to me for Stacy right now am I
Oh yeah I know
Mike is a smart fella
And his son is a very smart fellow too because he has a Kickstarter right now
That already met its goals already funded
It's called The Chatterbox
And it's a DIY smart speaker that
He says anyone can program
And the reason this is really
Geared towards kids
Is that
It all
Happens everything happens on the device
She don't even need any accounts
There might be some parents out there who are like I don't want my kids voice in the cloud I don't know
It's a it's a thing but it's a this is a little smart speaker sad Power by Raspberry Pi
As I got
Cute little cardboard
Teasing that the kids create what makes it look like a standing up
Robot foxy but still kind of cute
Additionally
You can
Program it
It looks like it's blocked lie to me
Which is like a dragon drop kind of
Programming language
So it's not like too complex for the kids to play with the boys services on the
So that's an option
What age range
For those kind of kids for that
Honestly I mean you can
Probably go
Could I would say down to age
It's a six or seven with supervision okay and how much is it
So this started out at $99 and all the backers
Eat that up and then went to 109 and ate that up to
So I don't see how you can order it just yet
Because
The kickstarter is over
So what I would say is Go to the
Kickstarter website
Follow along what's going on because they make us for sale
I'm sure they'll tell you where you can get at that point
Got it okay
And you said you had one other option
I do Google actually make something very similar called their Vision kit
That's the aiy projects
Start with google.com site where you can buy The Voice kid or
Nhtp you if you want but
Specifically the vision kit
I looked through there if you want to get into AI with
Computer vision
I don't see any requirement on that
That says you need a Google account
I do see it for The Voice Kids
So I believe it's like pre-configured to like use a test
Account
To access the Vision Services service
In which case
You don't need
To worry about
Tranchulas and such
Okay so you could just get this and
Unauthorised computer vision
Not traceable trackable etcetera
There we go
Okay so Jeremy hopefully some of that helps you
Hopefully
You have the budget to do some of this with your kids at
Sounds like a lot of fun
Okay
Next up we have a question from Keith
Who is just checking up on me
Thanks Keith
Let's hear it
Play Susan Kevin
Is Keith from going to Arizona
Pico question CCU
Let's begin the year you mentioned that you're going to move everything over to Google
Home versus
Using Alexa products
Anime
So kind of curious
That is going
And
Do you want to go back
I'd like to get your experience but that what you like and dislike
And if you do go back
Why you going
Keith
This is really
A sad sad
Story
I switched everything to Google
You're correct
I loved it and actually my family loves the Google smart display that we have we have two 10-inch Lenovo smart display
And then I threw
Add a Google home in a couple minutes running
I can tell you that
Everything was unplugged Within
Probably two weeks
And the reason was I had
Done the voice match
And with voice match
Which wasn't
2 strong
Couldn't recognize my voice probably half of
It did great with my husband's voice but at first he was kind of hacked off because he had to go train it
And so is this
And then
It didn't recognize my daughter at all
And get her voice match on there because she wasn't using a phone with a Google account on it
Because she was under 13 and technically can't have one
Was a whole thing
That we just did not do
So
It was awesome in theory that I could be like
Hey what's on my calendar my husband gets a call Mom and it would call his mom is opposed to my mom
But
We had to turn that off
But before we turned it off
Basically everyone in my house whenever back to madam
Because they were kind of trained to use
And we kept
The main Google home hub plugged in
And once we turned off The Voice
Recognition
Capability
People used it sometimes
But again
4 most basic
Commands
It didn't work as well
Also
When we die
Sports turn on the television
Sometimes it would be able to do it sometimes it wouldn't and then if it didn't we that say okay ask Harmony Wichita
Because we're using Logitech Harmony
Turn on the television
Then it would do it but
It was a little hit or miss
My daughter didn't like using it
Because
Google still doesn't play the same thing she wants to play with Spotify
Their Spotify integration is still a little wonky so sometimes it still plays the karaoke versions of popular songs
Instead of the actual song
Where is
Madam is like oh
You want to hear Blank Space by Taylor Swift
I got that she plays that right
Google sometimes would play an instrumental version
And you be like
Why Google
Is that really what people want to hear
That's kind of held out when
We still have
The display and we love it because it's showing photos and that's super vine Everyone likes that
And we use it to
Settled
I called my room argument there really is no supper table arguments where we're sitting down at dinner in
We're having. Like why is it this way
So we do tend to ask Google more questions
I mean I had the matinee and plug for maybe a week before my Family Feud need
Whatever like
No
This is terrible
So when you end up
And your final destination in Seattle
I assume you're going to
Put madhumeh back in everywhere
Yeah it's matinee all the way although
This is it now this will be a challenge because of the whole nest
Deprecation kind of issue
We do like the smart doorbell of choice for me is the nest
So
Its entirety have the Google display should I
You know use that display to show us who's at the door like when we're in the kitchen
It already shows us
Video from
I mean since we have it we're probably going to just use the net
Bright that makes sense
It's interesting my experience
Not that I moved or anything and
And not that Keith cares about my house
At my experience is very different and we're all Google
And
The difference by The Voice match
We don't use the voice match because if I want personal information I just use my phone for that and everybody else uses their phone for
They're not
Big into sitting around the
Kitchen table and then asking the smartest by what's next on our calendar
Cuz
They just use their phones
Just a difference in how they use it that's fine
So no voice match
And they don't really use either
Of the smart speaker
Platforms that much at all by
Comparison to me
So
They Don't Really Care as much
This is how much we use it in my house no lyric that's where you're actually
Like we're packed
By the time you guys
Hear this I'll have been in Co
But we're like the idea of living for 2 weeks out of a suitcase
We still had to keep one Amazon Echo.
Device
You guys use it for music as this do I nobody else in my house listen to music with me but you guys
You used the services that come with these devices far more than my family.
Music timers
Yeah like my husband
It is like
We have the echo in my daughter's room
So she can you set his alarm clock but every night before he goes to bed my husband's like
Anime
Set up
Yeah
I mean I'll use a voice assistant to preheat the June oven for example
That's awesome cuz you're like hands are all sticky
But my wife will
Walk out of the room go across the house
Hit the button
Walk away back into town
I'm like why you doing that
She's way healthy
I'm actually using it to Adam
Data to my Fitbit now I know how much water I drink
So I'm like
Smart
So Keith
That is how I'm going
It's pretty much variable depends on your situation
You know what I'm all in on Google so I really wish it would
Work better for us
Okay
Let's see we have got
A question from no-name
An unnamed individual coming up
But
This is a question we've gotten a couple times
Kevin's actually tried to do this
Couple different ways
So
This is all about making your washing machine smart
Let's listening
Quick question is regarding
You let my not smart washer and dryer machines
Unfortunately have plugs that do not work with normal
Outlets monitoring
So I haven't been able to just use energy
Laundry is finished
I was wondering if you guys had any others
Thank you
Yeah so we're right since we've gotten this we probably get this question like at least
Every two months
There's a lot of folks that want to know how to do this with the easiest way to do it
The thing is there's no truly easy way to do it the way I think
People would like it to work we have to kind of
There is one easy way
Easiest way to do this
Is Dubai
Connected washer
But if you don't want to buy a whole new washer dryer
And I don't blame you
Now
Yeah okay
So there's there's your thousand-dollar option
Crazy I'll do it
I found a bunch of folks that have had success
With a SmartThings multi-sensor which measures vibration
I think it measures
Noise
Vibration temperature
Open close
Humidity
Yeah but space in their focus on the vibration
Because they attach this to their washer dryer and
Paisley set up a rule that says
Set an alarm if
It's not vibrating for X number of seconds or minutes
You need to set that there an actual there's like a skill for that
Cassette that you need to make sure because I was listening cycle through
The devices may stop vibrating for maybe 30 seconds 45 seconds Munoz
Maybe cuz it's refilling water in the washer Etc
You need to understand and adjust that for you in particular washer dryer but
That's what folks have been very happy with
Considering there just isn't
A great off-the-shelf option other than
As we said buying a home
Set of appliances
You could also make your own
I wouldn't say it's easier but it's an option for people that get tinker
We can put a link in the show notes to a Raspberry Pi Appliance Monitor and does the same thing with a vibration sense
So
If you don't feel like mine when you can make your own
In that scenario though I have to buy the pie
Play the program it for like do I have to download some sort of
Absolutely I recognition Okay and then I need to have a wireless component I need to get a
Shield or a hat
Whatever Wi-Fi and the pies are almost
All them, so you don't have to add any special radio frequencies or anything like that
But as far as downloading code know your absolute right and the link we have that car to a GitHub project
So the code is already there as well as the instructions so it's not
Terribly miss you a first time user could you just download the code
That is up on GitHub
To the Pines pretty much run at
But other options that
Some people do and I don't recommend
You can actually
Make a 220-volt outlet smart
But every time I've seen that it's
You have to hardwire your
Appliance to this
Outlet
This plug
And that's not something I would at that point you might as well just go buy a new washer
Yeah you don't want to play with 200
Not so much
It's not a cool thing
Have happened in your
Okay so those are really good options
Let's pause for a moment and
Take a break
Wear weave this week sponsor
This week sponsor is
Dell Technologies
We're taking a quick break from The Internet of Things podcast
Spur message from our sponsor sponsor is Dell Technologies and I'm here with Chris Lynn
Hi Chris thanks for joining our podcast today
Can you tell us a little bit about yourself
Hi Stacy thanks for having
Digital film industry
So with your oil and gas background in data architecture and digital oilfield Solutions
Weird how have you seen oil and gas
Gas is very possible
Automation oriented
Dismiss
Four major areas of growth for it number one
Stranded
Number two is
Capturing
Data increase velocity
Number three is actually providing more analytics and applications at the edge
What area that is really exploding
Is using non typical data types like video audio and graphic Imaging to do
Real-time operations analyst
Excellent so what are some of the key areas for companies to think about if they want to deliver successful iot
Project specifically in oil
Number one
We have to remember its first
And foremost about this
How do you help the business
Be successful to increasing production
Specifically willful operation
Automation
Understand
Balsam it devices to make it better
Use with it and number three how to make
Consumers on that day that day scientist
What are you sedated and course-related back to business
Howling and users
And uses to integration and work less
And then we move differently there's three other key components
What's my connectivity
Put these things all together you
Understand how they work
Together and you can make a really good business case and you can deliver a really successful project
So I understand data-driven production is coming up in
Houston
June 11th and 12th
What can we expect to see from Dell Technologies at the show
Dallas proud to be the headline
Again for this year's
Evangelion production
At this event you'll be able to see a completely integrated demonstration showing as the cord cop capabilities
Using our technology using data
Operating company
To get that next level of efficiencies and expose production improvements and next level
Crossword
Australian basketball
Thanks Chris where can people go to learn more about Dell iot
Text repository Stacy and people want to learn more about our Solutions
They can go to the Dell Technologies. Com
Flash IMDb
Back with another question about appliances this one is from Kevin but not this Kevin different Kevin
Kevin is worried like many of us are about leaving the stove on
Let's hear what he wants to do
ICC 7
I absolutely love you Kevin from Michigan
I was wondering
You yet answer this question Locker refrigerators
Freak out about my stove
Right now I have a wyze camera pointed at it
So I can just pop up
Eric B and see if my light is on
Is there a better way that I could
Monitor whether or not I leave my stove and oven on
Thanks a lot again love the show
Alright Kevin
I'm glad you're thinking trying to take care of your family
I got a couple options for you
This is a weird space because people have built stuff for it
And
Then it didn't sell because a lot of these are very expensive
So we discovered one
Which is called Wallflower
And this is a device that will tell you that you have left your stove on it will not actually
Turn it off
Correct is just for notifications with food left it on
And the reason in this is an outlet so this is an outlet that you plug your stove into
It is
$150
It's called Wallflower Uke
You can find it at Wallflower.
And
If your home is built before 1996 you're going to need one if it's billed after you're going to need it if
But
The option is
Easy
The reason why an egg is actually to some of the things
Behind
Stoves
It's actually from a regulatory perspective turning them off
Is apparently a big deal
So everybody who's like I'm going to do this and I'm going to turn it off
They realize when they start getting through certification process that
UL process or some sort of like hey is this thing safe to eat
Put my house
The Regulators don't like them because they they don't know if it's 100% over Wi-Fi that you can like
Luther motor and something will definitely be turned off they don't feel comfort
But
That has not stopped people from trying
So
The current one and I've seen a lot of these and none of them have
But there is currently one called a nerve
Ini RV
And they are building a connected
Knob for your
Stove burner knobs
Western Gas and Electric
And what it does is you
Put these on and it has a sensor when your stove is on it will
Actually turn the knob
But
Here is the catch
They did a Kickstarter in 2017
It does not look like they've delivered on it
They were on Shark Tank
Can 2018
And just this year in February
They were part of the bsh techstars
Accelerator for the smart
What is this mean
It means that they've been promising a product for a long time
Only now do I feel like they have the backing they would need to actually
Get it done
The techstars bsh accelerator program makes me feel like
A little bit more confidence but
It's still not enough confidence that I'm like
This is really going to happen
But
You can go on their website and reserve it
And
It doesn't cost
True it will be nice to see if and when they deliver
They actually have a shipping date people know cuz I I love the idea of this
We have a gas stove
So
I'm also really would do SWAT for us
Shut off the igniters I guess but really do anything else
So this is something I would
Consider looking into or trying but
It just isn't there yet
Yeah in the starter kit for the inner earth
Is
One sensor plus one knob is a hundred in all the way up to 1 sensor and four knobs which most stoves have four
And that's 230.
That's a lot of money
So it's a lot of money for peace of mind
Yeah we are almost in the territory to spend the money on it can I get stove
Oh my gosh and now we're back to that Cheeto your old Appliance
That's our new motto
Kitchen Redo for everyone
All right moving along to a question from John
I will confess I've never thought of
This problem so
Kudos to you John
Let's hear it
Swansea Illinois
Little bit concerned about
King Auto she devices throughout my home
Lightning strikes nearby
Power surges
Half power strips or
Interruptible power supplies for my computer
How concerned should I be about my
I'll be honest I actually haven't thought of this either
And maybe I should have
Especially on my
Higher price II
Tea devices
Something like a Google home Mini
It's not like throw away money to go buy one
You're talking
Maybe 30 bucks on sale so
I wouldn't be too concerned with things like that but if you have
Spend and you have to
Pick this number
That suits your budget
For me anything
Cost me more than $50 to replace
It might be worth
Getting
Surge protection for
So
Yeah baby webcam smart fit smart speakers hubs and so on so forth
I'm actually considering this now so I'm glad John
Assets
What I would say that there's tons if you go to Amazon there are tons of surge protector choices out there
I'm going to put one out because it's relatively inexpensive for what you're trying to
Protect
Basically under 15 bucks gets you
Surge protector
That you plug in over top of an existing
Outlet
And it actually adds more Outlets as well as USB ports
But you also get surge protection by that
So we'll put a link in the shown us this one I think is 13 $14
There are Bunches of them out there so maybe look at this one and then see what the other ones the related items are
Choose the ones that look the best to you or have the
He doesn't number of outlets you want so on
But for something
Inexpensive
Can I make a wyze cam I'm not going to put a surge protector on a wyzecam
It's almost as much money to put the surge protector on it cost me for the wyzecam so
That's my thought I don't know Stacey you may have a different opinion
I was just going to see if you wanted to
Brazy
This is maybe less for your smart home stuff also there some interesting options here
Get a smart surge protector
So there are definitely connected surge protectors out there but
If your homekit fan Eve has one called the energy strip
It is
Really pretty it works with Google Assistant
The reason you might want to do
Connected
Surge
Is actually two
Set rules around like
When your smart devices are on like your smart speaker is
On or off
So you can maybe just
Not unplug it but basically
Turn it off
Completely
That might get old for the speaker some things will
Need to be reset if you turn them off for too long of a Time
But it's an interesting option
Or you if you're really worried about life
Like privacy or things like that some people are like
You can set it up so your smart camera adjust
Is totally not even getting power when you come home
So
Even if Lake
The worst case scenario where the
The company was like I am really nefarious I'm going to take over your camera and look at you
Nautica cologne
So that might be a reason to get it
Although if they really wanted to see you then they could hack your connected surge protector and then turn the camera back up at 6
There's just throwing that out there is another app
It would you put surge protectors on any of your things or says not all of your things
In some places like my office I have surge protectors already in place and things are plugged into that by default
Discussed at the outlets
The lake
In my kitchen
My smart display which is 200 my Echo Show which was another 200 I think
Those are plugged into just normal
They're GFI outlets but that's about it what about your June cuz that would not be a inexpensive trip
You know it is not plugged into surge protector but neither is my $800 coffee May
Make her so clearly I'm just not consistent and that's not smart
So it looks like John as well as you and I will be spending some money answers for Tech
Stacy
I'm just like I've got renters insurance or home insurance
Next up we've got a question that we also get
Aaron
So
And everybody else
Yeah if we were playing if we were playing Q&A Bingo this would be like the Center Square
ICC and Kevin
My name is Aaron
Viability of
Crispy Sunday have no current price coming out
Distracted
Suddenly disconnected doesn't work
Crysis 2
What you should transition to in the future or west bracket considered
Thank you and have a good day
I wish I had a better answer for you
Confer ferryman show
I sent wink
PR emails
I looked through Linkedin to see who I still do there
I sent another email to someone random that I
Was like
Third-degree connected to
I kid you not Stacy reaches out to these folks every couple weeks
And it's been going on for months it's not like
We have not tried to find out
But it's just a black hole
It is
So officially
I've got nothing
Unofficially I can tell you that the last update was
Sports
Feels like a long time ago I also haven't heard from wink yet on the deprecation of
Nest
Where is all of my other smart home devices have sent me email saying
Hey did you hear the Google
You know
Killing Nest another like
Google's not killing us quite the same way but it's still going to happen so here's what you need to do
So I feel like
I can't recommend wink anymore to pee
People if you have wink
It still works
I'm in the same boat
To be honest I kind of feel it was my go-to Hub recommendations
So long
Overtime as
Nothing has
Come to light of what's going on
I don't feel comfortable recommending it
I will save it on the Google Play Store that the
Wink folks are
Responding
2 reviews with questions as early as 3 weeks ago
So it's not like
The total black hole there are still people there they're still working the wink hubs as you said Stacy still work
I think people just like wondering where there be new products what's the lunk
Strategy is there a long term for weighing what's going on really
Don't buy it for people thinking that
It's going to be around forever but for now
It does still work if you have it
Yay
If you want another Hub option I would sell you SmartThings
Carter
I would also tell you maybe you don't need a
I know and I get angry emails.
Maybe you don't need a hug
If you're not a superpower user
Maybe Amazon or Google is
Perfectly good help for you
Okay
Let's move on to another question these are these are questions when you guys are answering them all he
Here because
We don't want you to think
But we don't listen
So this one is from Jeff
And he has a question about the mail
Let's hear it
Ice Age and Kevin Love You show
A question
Battle Wi-Fi
Mailbox alert
Back in the day
I was wondering if
Either something I can listen to that song that I have
Or something
Mailbox door has been open
After you could coverage
Mailbox WiFi
Support your answer
As you said we get this question a lot
And that's actually a good thing
Sometimes get the same question over and over because new products come out new Solutions are available
And this is a solution that I don't think we've recommended before because it's relatively new
I have to say
Jeff is like major old school with that RadioShack Melgar. I mean that is
Proprietary it's a light sensor that goes in the mailbox and
Send a chime into his house and
It is but it's against proprietary and does his question how can I connect this to Wi-Fi
The short answer is you can't
Unfortunately not easily
But we may have an alternative that's not terribly expensive
What weight should we explain why WI-Fi is proper
Play not everyone's First Choice here
Well yes we should because most mailboxes are
Probably Faraday cages was really hard to get a signal out
But the proprietary frequencies are typically in the 900 megahertz range
Which can travel better through
The Trap better through metal in walls and they also travel further
Yeah Wi-Fi is a shorter wavelength frequency at 2.4 and an even shorter at 5
Yes and what's happening is
The Spectre
Can't make it through or it can't make it as far and then the other eye thing to think about there is
A lot of them
Wi-Fi sucks a lot of
Battery power
Exactly
However
Jeff says he has good
Wi-Fi range maybe the signals
The Wi-Fi device inside of the mailbox can get through
So what we're going to recommend
Is he considered one of the new
Blink
Cameras
That runs on the battery for up to two years is still Wi-Fi
You get a one camera system and async module
Two connected to
You are network for
$80
If you put that in the place of your Milgard
And you can get a signal from it through your mailbox
You're in good shape
There's no way we can guarantee that because we don't know the distance of your mailbox is your mailbox made of
Half-inch thick metal
Cardboard I have no idea
We don't know for sure
If it will work
This is probably the best option
I've seen in awhile for
Very specific
Circumstances wherever Wi-Fi monitoring system for a mailbox
Could work
Agreed
And we also tried the wise sensors I'll just throw this out here for you because they're cheap and 40 bucks get you
What you might need
We found that the Hub could not be located more than about
3240 ft
Through a front door
So
I don't know if that's going to work
But before the show Stacy marked outside of her house with her
License and
Measure
Open and closed it several times to see how far it would go
Chick that would be ideal because again that's low power battery and so on
It might work in Jeff's case again I don't know where his
Mailbox is it might be just outside is
Front door I don't know
Down if your cameras like right by your front window or something so the wireless is a little better cuz this was
Right this is sub gigahertz so somewhere in 900 maybe 4:15 gigahertz is what the why sensors are using
So you know
Might
Work
And is cheap if you want to try it so
Those are the options I wish I had like a
2 Cool Wi-Fi photo sensor that
Would be magically able to work but
That is not an option
All right
Moving right along with another question for Wi-Fi
Stem cell
This is from Daniel let's hear it
Hey guys I just want to say I really love the show about Amazon Echo
What a year ago
Can you guys the show I guess
And I listen to every Thursday
My question is
What the best setup
For your Wi-Fi router
The safest setup
Some people say that of the land
Is the best I've heard other people say they like a guest network is the best
So I just wanted to ask
Canyon Honda
I don't have any
Zigbee or Z-Wave device
This is all my Google assist
Alexis
Cloudbase
We get this question a lot
Today's router settings networks aren't meant
Really to
Protect iot devices specifically at me never meant to protect
You from
The outside world getting in in general
Honestly you could use a guest Network
We talked about that before you can use the guest Network for all of your devices
That is an option
That's kind of locked on little bit more than say your
Standard Network
That you could look into their there certain products out there we looked into and talked about before the bitdefender Box
Is $199 at 6 behind your router
I'm supposed to help filter traffic and watch for suspicious network activity so maybe if your attitude devices are going out to someone
It might work
I guess we're not really big fans of that though because
We've never really seen detail testing
To show that it better
I've tried some of the stuff
And
It does work I just
I don't know if my life is
Yeah cuz I feel like right now I'm not
I should say that I'm not being attacked
So a part of this is you know part of your wrist Pro
I will say the nicest feature that I
I'd like to have and I think you should have it although I think it should be free personally
Is understanding
What devices are on your
And getting a notification with something
Get on your knees
So
Yeah which do you use I forgot to say gyro I have to Eero
Service
Soon I will be up in
Comcast service area and I'll try there is but like Eero does let me know it's like
This weird device has joined your dad
Cool thanks
Super weird device
Can I use Google Wi-Fi
You don't have to pay for that type of information but it's it's passive however you actually have to open the app and
See what devices are on your network
So it's not like it notifies you when something
Has joined it doesn't
Proactively tell you that there's a new device or any like that so I periodically go through that cuz sometimes I even find
Devices that we
Sold or recycled
Better still cortical attached to that we're going to clean those out
But there's nothing automatic about that notifications either
That's the one thing the other thing I would say is if I were doing this all again from scratch
And I will
I would set up
My network
And I would set up all my iot devices on that and I would also have my guest Network
And nobody but me and maybe my husband
Because I do travel
We'll get the password for the
The cornet
And everybody else including my child will be on the
And the reason I will do that is because my child is going to give out our guest Network
Password Oliver
Friends
Also because children download all kinds of weird stuff
I don't know where it's tough to but kids
Kids are like oh yeah
I totally need this
So no friends are coming over to your house when you move I got it
No no no they just get the guest Network
You know when you're buying a mesh wi-fi system make sure that it has easy Euro basically if I what I can
I just go into the app and I'm like
I said I can text you I can email you
I guess Network
Be kind of cool if I could show you a QR code on my phone and you just snap it and get on the Wi-Fi
Add that
Are you hearing me Eero
That's the other network Safeguard I would save
It's not necessarily the security products but it's just a nice best
And if anybody has
Purchased a device or a service
Help with this I would actually like to hear about the
The clothes back
We've had some people tell us what they do but
Again
They're always new Services new products coming out and it's been awhile since we've address this question
So
It could be that I have not been on the up-and-up with what's going on in this in this place
Kevin manno
All right
Our next color isn't actually a color it's someone who emails
And
Really felt uncomfortable leaving a voicemail so
Out loud
I wonder if you could help me find a solution to this scenario
I have a tablet that is always on connected to power and is showing a web page with actiontiles control
I want to be able to see the video for my ring Pro doorbell when there is motion or somebody presses the doorbell button
Or when I issue a voice command
Like
Anime
Show me the front door
Currently my tablet is not an Amazon Fire tablet but I would consider replacing it if the Fire tablet can do what I want
I know the Amazon show can display the video from The Ring
But I don't like the price of the show
Totally fair comment about the
Amazon show I'm just not a fan of that device in general
And not just cuz of the price
Baptist don't care for it even though I have some smart displays
Illusion
That's fine if you buy everything that
Amazon shows list you or whatever
That's all you
This was interesting to me because I didn't know about actiontiles which as Kira looks like as a web-based
Customizable
Bunch of tiles that would show a title for each one of your smart home devices
It's really made for SmartThings he didn't mention that I don't think it was anything else
So I'm assuming you a smart thing
Because it's web-based it works with just about any tablet or phone so you can even use an iPad
But that's not going to solve the problem
Backhero has posed to us
So
A Fire tablet I hate to say is
Probably the best at lowest cost
However
Lenovo actually makes a smart
Tab which is also an Android tablet
Comes in two sizes 8 or 10 in
And
Similar lucky Rose doing
Carol has his tablet always plugged in
This includes a speaker dock
And when you put the Smart Tab in the speaker dock
You essentially transform it into an Echo Show
And at that point you can ask
Madame A2
Show your ring or do whatever you need her to do
They start around 199 go up to 350 depending on the specs
So obviously much more expensive than your Fire HD is what you can get sometimes for 50 bucks
But if you want a decent tablet
That you can actually take out of a dog have a charge uses a tablet and then put it back in to use it as an Echo Show
It's a nice
Option
I will say
Because it's an Android tablet the native default
Assistant is Google
So when it is not.
If you ask it a question only Google is going to listen and answer
If you put it
In the dark
Then that of a will be the default so
I like this because it gives you a wider range of options if you just want a tablet that you're
It's going to show your ring doorbell
Go for the Fire HD tablet
If you want something
Is much more flexible
I consider this if your budget allows
All right
Carol hope that answers your
Thank you guys so much for calling in with all of your questions for the
Q&A episode of The Internet of Things podcast
These are brought to you by Schlage
And a pharaoh
So
Big props to our sponsors
That's right I just sang
You can find more about Schlage
@wwe
Schlage.com
And you can find more information about a pharaoh at www. Afero
Dot IO
Slash
Go big
Lots of options for you
Thank you so much for calling in
Kevin thank you for spending time answering these questions with me
My pleasure I agree thank you everybody who calls in
Yes
Cuz we learn a lot
Doing this to
Absolutely
And if you want more iot information feel free to sign up for the
Stacey on iot newsletter
@www Stacey on iot
Dot-com
That's it for this week thanks so much for listening
And remember if you'd like more iot news sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot
I will see you next week