Welcome to be
204th episode of The Internet of Things
Podcast
This is your host Stacey Higginbotham and
Jericho host
Kevin tofel and we have an amazing show for you today we're going to be talking about
App for Apple what comes out
After the iPhone
Ever pretty
Good gas and
We've got some bad news about
Ifft
Our favorite
Way to connect to services on the internet
Osram
Delighting
Company is
For sale
And we're going to talk about
New smart circuit breaker
This is Leviton
Consumer-oriented news but we may talk a little bit about it in the industrial space coast
Why the heck not
It doesn't news about another
Platform going to
2 NB iot
And Kevin has some thoughts about how Google can you
Compete against
Star Buddy Amazon
So
All this
And we'll hear from sponsor urbanex
Facts about one of their start
And
We're going to also hear from the CEO of silicon labs
Tyson Tuttle
Who is our guest this week
We talkin about
Radios and
What happens when
When giant tech companies
Keep buying
All the startups
In this
Ecosystem
Stay tuned
All of this
But now
A word from another one of our
Western Digital
Western Digital builds Data Solutions that enable the world to solve
Its biggest challenges
Safer cities
Smarter vehicle
Faster Internet of Things
So join Western Digital at embedded world
Is they showcase their open source technology roadmap
Demonstrate their industrial and Edge Solutions
And unveil the newest addition to their portfolio
Find out more at Western Digital
Dot-com
Okay
Kevin
Let's get this started with
Apple
Yay
Some exciting news that's been coming dribbling out
The last well feet look like
For a while but in the last week
Week or so we saw a couple of news announcer
It's one was that Sam
Jadallah who was actually the founder of
Be Auto Smart
I don't know if
You guys remember I definitely talk
It was a $700
Connected locks
It came out
All maybe a year
2 years ago is hugely expensive very pretty
Very substantial but Doom
And then
So he's going to work it out
Apple now in there
Home division
What also is ham
John giannandrea
Has been promoted to the execu
And
They also pushed out series voices
Jan Andreas
Come to Apple
Calls from Google
And he was in charge of some of their AI
People
Believe
Help AppleCare
Gain some ground
Because for a while
If not been awesome
Jean Andrea was
Google Drive machine learning
Now he's apples SBP
Key of machine learning and AI strategy
He reports directly to 10
Tim Cook that was a change that happened
And so basically what we're seeing is the elevation at app
Of AI and machine
To be a more critic
Which is much later than its competitors I would say
Yes so
Also
Apple just
Pull string technology
Which
Used to be a company called
Boy talk
Wispies for her
Pixar Executives whenever I think
Pixar I have
There's synergies there there
Executive back
Fourth I think Toy Story but okay
Yes okay
But
Toytalk what they did
And what pull string does is
The idea was to create a compelling narrative
A voice generated narrative
Around in a relationship
So it was designed
Orchids initially
And they were going to build basically toys
License search
Technology to Twin maker
So kids could create a relationship
Around
Barbie
Aurora Disney character toy or whatever
And they did do that
That is true
Write that hello Barbie doll is you know power bi
Clustering technology
So with all this everyone's like
Apples moving beyond the knife
Which makes sense
Here's what I think is
I think Apple
Pause moving beyond the eye
IPhone into
And there's a couple reasons I thing
One apple has said
Hookah said that health
Where will be the biggest thing
Apple has to offer Humanity
What Apple has bought a succession of companies
Give medical quality
You see it with the Apple watch
And
Since Apple was never really awesome at the
Cloud
And critic services
I think this is an area where it can take things that were a weakness and turn them into a straw
Apple's data privacy
That is basically it hurting
It's bugs into a feature that
But it's actually really good feature
And I have talked about this
So there's that ass
But there's a lot of pets showing Apple doing so cool
Eggs and I think
If you pull all of that together
When I talk to doctors
About telemedicine and
And home health monitor
Coyote
Etsy need a couple
You need reproducibility and Trust in the actual data underlying
This device
So you have to know the
This is not
Digital snake
Right you have to know this is a real
Possible benefit in this has to be proven and tested
Apple will take
We seen it already with their efforts
For the Apple watch and afib it's things like
Like that
The products have to be easy to use doctors cannot
Tell
A 60 year old
Percent
Go home
And by this connected to Bluetooth
Like it is hard
For someone to get like
A connected blood
Okay that is actually for many of our listeners
It's pretty easy to set up
That's actually not easy
Is there any product in the medical
Well has to be easy to
Use apple is wonderful
Medical technology has historically been scared
It's felt like
Analogy but if you
Apple's history
With
The iPhone and making technology approachable and you think about things like
Buying
Pull string
And some of their other
Positions
Baked make technology very warm
And friendly
In their medical devices which will make
People want to use it
I think of Apple in medical
I think it's something like I don't know if you
Remember I saw the master of none
Episode
Japanese robotic seal
Do you know what I'm talking about Kevin
I didn't say it
Sorry
The sea was called
Pero it's
Therapeutic
Baby robot
Seal for old
It was so funny because
In the show is like
What the heck is this
And then by the end
I love it
Ico
Applebee near
To do something
Not necessarily a robotic baby seal that old people
Love being able to create a product
It is imbued with technology
The people want to
Hold
Want to sleep with
Want to bring into their everyday lives
It haven't
Gather this data
Make sense of it
Forest actually invisible to the user meaning
ECG in the watch that you never see or in airpod 2
Headphones that we expect later this year to have
Health sensors and such that
You never know
Exactly so I think
And
Here's the other reason
This is a good place for
Medical technology
Not just stupid Wellness
Pieology like me and my Fitbit which I love
But that's not a sin
Right
Apple goes after
Essential
Munchies and if you think about music
Music was an essential
Technology that drove
Creation of iPod
And then
Was filtered into the eye
ITunes was a
Huge moneymaker for Apple
They recognized
What's essential in honestly the way that
I love them but
The way that voice services in the home that digital speakers are playing out
If you'll still more like a
Send something essential
So I understand why Apple
Feel like almost like
Ask the homepod out there as part of their music app
Throw that out there to make Wall Street happy
We got a digital speaker I don't care while they focus on something
This real
It is actually going to be
Healthcare is a huge industry
So I agree with everything you said but I actually want to expand the pond one early point
Where you said they were turning a weakness into a strength
Which I agree with that there's another weakness here
That they're leveraging even more
We know they're terrible at Cloud by comparison to a Google a Microsoft
A Amazon
So they can't get data
They get their data from devices and apps in their ecosystem and that's it where is others
Get data from the web which everybody uses
Apple doesn't have that
A safari a search engine that is
Huge huge gap
So what do they do they go out to their Edge devices the People by gather useful information
In your case you're making a case out of health information and I wholeheartedly agree because I have not yet found a better
Health
Wearable ecosystem then
Apple health and my Apple watch quite honestly
So
That is another
Weakness that are like unicorn
Competing with these guys in the cloud
So how do we get data at the user level
Some other way and what day do we
Specifically
And it's help
So I agree with you 100% so that's where I think
If we look at like
Hey what's Apple doing after the iPhone
I think it will be some sort of
Consumer
Oriented
Medical grade
Device
That helps
Doctors
And loved one
Take care of people in the home
Water enhancer health
And I say that because
There's every possibility that Apple could come out with its own quote unquote hearing aid with airpods wireless hearing
Maybe it's a true hearing aid or maybe it's a personal sound amplifier system which is 9 ft
Approved
And it's affordable it works its cortical magical and
They enhance somebody's life
So that's where
That's where that's at
Isaac
Feel free to argue
West Freeway alright so moving on to something
We'll see where this goes
Linden Tibbets who is the CEO and co-founder of if
I talked to him
A decade ago
About what he was trying to do here so
You step down
And
They brought in Chris
Kabardian who is most recently the CEO of monster.com
To take over the sea
So Tibbetts will stay on as if
Chief designer
Officer in
Oriana is described as a turnaround special
This isn't
Surprising
It is been really like when it started if
With
A wonderful
Vision his vision was to basically
Create
A way to interact with
With digital objects
The same way
We would interact
So
His example to me was you know if you have a coffee
Upon your
Desk
You can use it as a
You can use it as a pencil holder
You can use it as a paperweight but
In the physical world you see something and you have all these ideas for how you
Manipulate
Use it
Whose idea was to create a plateau
That allowed you to do that
Digital
So you can
Take something that was intended
Something else
Adapter to
Beach
I love
No it's a great idea and what they've done is they've gathered up all these API some of these device makers
And made it simple to you so that you want to be a programmer
Create a different program for every little thing you want to do
Do very simple trigger events and action on everything happens in the back in the cloud
I love it
I'm just wondering I was nothing anybody could see this but when you mentioned that kabardian is a turnaround specialist I had my eye
Eyebrow raise because
I just wonder
Passion
Financial standpoint
How does
If really continue on is it making its money
So if two makes
It's money from companies
Like
Apple
Amazon
More Samsung or
Whirlpool
Those companies
Can create
Supported apis basically
And they put them on the platform if charges them to
Manage that and then they can also get data about
Like what people are using
But
It's been pretty hard and like I don't know if he'll remember this but when
Chamberlain
The creator of the MyQ garage door open
Pronounce there if Channel they actually said they would charge
People a dollar
And what are the reasons was
You know it's charging them
They want people to really want to use it
People were upset but
Yeah understandably so cuz they're so used to just using it for
Free
Number to so it seems like a
Pei Wei
Kind of service
Taipei I mean the hardware makers
No
At some point what if they start pulling out in providing their own
Apps and services in so long I just worry I just don't
I love if
Business perspective I just
Question
How They Roll
Make money I just
?
Yeah well in
I think they have
A decent
Revenue strata
I just think
It's hard to get
Users in
People to pay
Pay for it and it may be a mismatch between the Venture model and what it can actually legit
So
Will also see there
So they do just raise money last year
There is 24 million yes
A little higher so gay
According to TechCrunch
Yeah this is one of those areas where I'm not going to
Wholesale freaked out like I know it's going away but
I could see you like in six months if
This guy is not gaining more traction week
I could see if
Put on the market
And it'll be
It's a great plan
A lots of come
Company so it would be interesting to see who might buy it
How that would change that mean one of the advantages of
Left is that it is not owned
Right right
If I had to place a gas and we'll talk about this whole bit more but I would say
Google would be my number one
To pick it up if it weren't for sale
There's a reason I'm saying
Spoiler alert you guys
Okay
So let's talk about somebody else that's
Osram
Which you guys
I mean I know but they are a lie
Lightning
LEDs
Yes they have the lightify play
Apartments with their platform was
This is been you know in the lightbulb world
The lightbulb world
Spin-outs
A positions
It's a tough Market
Because
LED shift suddenly
Something that you
You might buy
Multiple light bulbs per year and now you're going to replace them with LEDs and
Not buy anymore
Technology
Needs us to switch our business model
Also everyone was like services
Gnarly
So
Has confirmed that is it acquisition candidate
And
They're talking to Bain Capital and
Carlyle Group
This is really tough for letting folks
That's the story about Ozzy
Maybe it'll go the way of signify
Jennifer Phillips
Which Phillip spun out at
Light bulb
What division including the Philips Hue bulbs into a compass
Call signify
GE
It's been out there like
Lighting division
So who knows
We'll see what happens
And oh yeah
Lifx
Was just acquired by
Buddy platform
Which is a smart phone says
Crazy times for lighting
Already
Let's talk about this story
Couple weeks ago nest
Basically said hey
You can now use Google assistant on your nest secure system
And specifically The Nest guard
You have to opt-in because of your going to activate a microphone on this particular.
Weight has a microphone
What I know
So that's kind of how the world felt about this
They're like
Didn't talk about that
And
We talked about that on that beat
Regular Show and then last week we talked about it
With regards to smart televisions because we went looking for
Privacy-related
Hunt around smart televisions
And we discovered that
It was unclear if certain TVs have microphones in the mirror.
Which we thought was kind of like
Not great
List the stuff in the specs before customers even purchases are they don't want to find out afterwards
Exactly and so
Business Insider
Kudos to them
Calling them out
They sent a media request to
Google
And basically was like
How come you never told anybody that the resume
And
The response I got back was beyond device microphone was never intended to be a secret and should have been listed in the text
That was an error
Yes Bank
So
It's just like the conversation we had about Smart TVs if you're going to have microphones cameras Etc
It's all good
Upfront
Fun Center so that people know what they're buying before they buy it
Which leads me to this week's newsletter
I am going to write about what I feel like the ideal truth in labeling laws
Buffer
Iot devices
In what sort of things should be
Be covered in
A company who selling a
What sort of
Things that
Include as part of that
We've talked about some of those things but it seems like every several months end up adding something new to the list
Yeah we're like oh
Obvious but I guess it wasn't
All right and as we learn
Think so
I'm sure this will change gilfry
If you hear this before
You know the end of the day Thursday UK
Tweet at me your suggestions of things that should be in there maybe
Maybe they'll make it Millis
So let's talk about
Smart circuit breaker
Leviton has announced
At the international
Builder show a
Connected smart circuit breaker
The ties back to their device
This is
A really cool device
People are very
Excited about it
I just want to say
But this is not the first one at the
Schneider Electric india
Both big makers of those panel boxes outside your home
Both have
Is most of them
They're targeted at the industrial space
So this is at the home
In the whole Market there's actually a large number of
Products the try to do energy monitoring
For you
Either at the circuit box
Which is complex and
A pain in the butt to install or maybe at
The plug level
And some of them just clip onto wires in light
Like say that they can manage all of this stuff
Distinguish different
Devices based on their electrical signature
So
Is a rich history
But
Historically this hasn't
Yeah that there is a rich history of this but I think it's been very
It's been focused xiao-nan consumer applications and the consumer applications
Where products have
Come out for this
Have been from startup since I should I think this is probably the first
Big name that I can think of
Going after the consumer here
I think that's going to be a huge
Benefit I also think
You can't just have a smart circuit breaker be expect to
Everything go hunky-dory you need a platform that works with a Leviton has that well over the range for the product
So I got the shot
To succeed where others have not been so successful
My question is how much does it cost
Don't know yet we don't know
It'll be available in the second quarter of
So
Well presumably find out then
Historically when I have tried these devices out
I have come to
To the realization
That
They don't help
I was going to say what you really get out of it other than some cool data
So you get this awesome data and you're like
Hot diggity
And there are some Lo hang
Rate so you may see a space heater that you like
Wrap it is way cheaper to
Keep my entire house did using this energy does a space heater
So there may be things like
After you switch all your light bill
Is after you eliminate the
Space heater
You're left with things that
Yeah like they're hot
So
One of the advantages his you know what I'd like to see
Is more integration but
Between some of the
These
Companies that produce like
Meme for example which makes hot water heater
If they can make
Come up with an app that takes a
Advantage of levittown's
In a circuit
Breaker
An automatically like
Lower the temperature when it seems likely
Not be needed
There are companies that actually do
Right now
Or Whirlpool takes advantage to say
Like when I want to start
My dryer it's
Says hey by the way
We're in this kind of demand response situation don't
Yeah can you wait 30 minutes
There's some
Options but those options for lion
A lot of integration
They rely on
The idea that the consumer is
Is going to watch
Want some sort of
Demand response
I don't know if we're there yet
I agree that don't bother for there yet
I was just going to go there cuz you talk about it like at the micro-level at the macro-level this could fit in nicely with
Can we talk about 3 weeks ago about
You know the possibility of Amazon indoor Google sort of the kitty more to the
Energy utility Space by capturing all the data and suggesting the people Your Nest right now
You can save on energy because we're at
Stoller
Clips
Right right a tree cool and therefore they can spend as much in overtime and it's a bike 700
Megawatts of Power by the
Several thousand people that were
No pulled into this test
So I think it's more of a macro benefit
None of micro benefit butt
And I do think this is
Where the industry is going
I just don't know there's always the
The problem
You may have the right idea but you just have it too early
So it may be the start us were all too early in
The ecosystem is now going to come together around this but
I will say
Beecosystem does still need to come together around this for this product
Yep all right
So what's up
Ecosystem
Libelium which is what
The first iot
Companies I think I've
Ever
Dealt with
They are a European
And the
Basically started out
Like these things called
Wasp
Boats they were little Laura based
Networks it was a sensor Network for agriculture
Smart cities for whatever
And
They just announced a partnership with Ericsson that is going to
To provide
Nb-iot
Modules that will work with the light Valium
Ecosystem
So
This actually reminds me
Very much
Of kind of shift that sigfox was making around
Open sourcing its Network
Just because these are all low power wide area in it
Providers
And we're basically seeing them try.
Established Solutions
Customers we understand this let's broaden
The number of radios we support
I'll get more people in here
So
We can basically build a business
Yeah and what they're doing in there
Starting out with a developer module leaking
Purchase
NBI Ortiz you said LTE cat M and some older GPRS Network skip
Just in case
There's no nb-iot coverage so
So this is just
It's a little piece of news but I think it's indicative of kind of an opening up in the
Low-power wide area
Hbase cell
Okay
Talk about
Google
And
It's plans
Against madhumeh and I think this is why you think they might want to buy
Or they'd be likely to buy
Yes assuming if twere
Note to go on sale yes I do
Google
Jumping in there and the reason being
And I didn't even know about the X news when I have the spot
I saw some figures over at search engine land
Couple days ago
And
What is the number of
Google actions in the US versus the number of skills for matinee
And
It's insane what a difference there is
There are roughly 60000 skills format of a as of
January
Emily 4253 Google actions
That is ridiculous
I know Google is competing better in the hardware side they're selling more Google devices
Desales I would suspect reduced pricing
It doesn't matter if you can do more with the Madam a on your own and
Even though I use Google home
For more than I use
Madam a
There's a huge difference between the apps or both
And it's so easy to find skills
For your Echo
On your phone of course you can stop
That's at the discovery is
Very good
Not so with Google
I can't even find in the app where you would enable or
Look for actions because there is no way to do it that I know of I went through every menu like a fine
You have to go to
And I knew anybody from there as well
So that's a problem Discovery is just not even there
Not on the phone anyway
The other big thing is
I started working at the
Google developer blog versus the Amazon developer blogs
And there's a dedicated one
Format Ma
Refer to it many times in the show because there's always something to talk about there's always
Blueprints
Here's an easy way to create a skill
There's just a lot of
What's a hand-holding but a lot of direction for both developers and non developers to make skills
Google there's just one developer blog and I went through every
Post friend
That has to do with
Google what's this interaction
It's just not
They're not telling it enough
And they're not making it easy enough
This is classic
Google this is what Google does
They're like we have been vented some
Something amazing
We'll throw it over the wall
And if anyone wants to pick it up
You should developers will come
Yeah and that's
You cannot have best
Coolest thing
But people will not show up
They don't know about it or they can't
Even if they see it people are so busy
Developers
Normal people were all like inundated
Carnation if you don't tell us why it matters
It's not going to matter
Yeah and I'm not sure that's what I'm going to be so you can
Buy or pay the developer for Madame a skill
I don't know if you can do that with an action on Google
If you can't I don't know for sure
If you can't
What's a Development Center
Well
Yeah
Well you're on a cool voice platform but Google isn't
Google Voice platform
There was actually
Think strategy Analytics
Just put out numbers saying that
Their Q4 smart speaker
Shipment screw 95
Percent about 38
5 million units and
Amazon
Amazon was by far the winner
Yeah let me Google sketching up on the hardware side but it doesn't matter if
Now the skills they are actions aren't there or discoverable I can just limited utility people get bored with the same old same old
The functionality I think there's far more in creating new functionality just out of the
Language translation for conversations on the
Smart display
And it's fantastic
I can't keep inventing everything there
Yeah and
They have been some really cool stuff
But implementing it
That's where they fall down like
I mean I've had so many issues with
That I'm just like
I think you hit the nail on the head it's typical Google
To just say we'll just make that some people
Do that anymore
Not if they really want to get
Consumers
In this case
They're not free
Right
It's one thing to be like I will give you an awesome Gmail Prada
Free cuz he knows something people understood at the time
Whole new functionality whole new type of product and people don't know what to do with it
Including developer
Okay
I agree with you Kevin
Already
Well
We have covered a lot there's probably
There is definitely more we could cover
We're going to stop here and move to Riot
D podcast
We have this week's voicemail
From John
But
Before we go there
The iot podcast hotline
And is sponsored by
A pharaoh with the fifth largest iot patent
Portfolio in the world
Afero provides a proven iot platform
It doesn't
Affero customers have experienced as much as an
80% reduction in time-to-market and 10x higher activation
Learn more at
Arrow
Dot IO
If you want to
Be entered to win
A WeMo dimmer switch that
What's this month's price
Or you just have a question and what is the answer it
Give us a call on the
Hotline at 5 1/2
623-7424
Because we
Enter you to win that
Dimmer and
We might answer your question
So let's go to this week's voicemail from John
Hey guys this is John in upstate South Carolina
I love the show
Long time listener
I have
Issue at the house
I have a wheelchair dependent wife
Yeah and I have lots
SmartThings
We are Amazon Alexa
We have
SmartThings Hub
Winx Club
Github insteon hub
But I need a
Hammock
Something that I can program
Come around the house
She has an issue if she has a
Enable alert
Ferguson either a text or email to a
User-configurable
DIY
Suggestion
But I've had a hard time finding anything
Hope you can help
Thanks for the show
Wow John Deere home sounds like my hoe
A lot of hops
Lots of hugs
So we got options
But my favorite option
Probably the easiest one.
It's going to be from smart
Thanks and provided it stays up
Which it's gotten much better
Historically
This should be good for you
Cuz you can buy
A little you can basically do this with a zigbee or Z-Wave
What you're going to do is
You would use the smart
Apps in smart
Things
And
Under Safety and Security you're going to find
Notify me when
Blah
Click through that
Can I click button
Pick your button
First thing you want to do is
Hook your button into
Platform so it shows up
And then
This buttons only $15 so you can have these all around the house if you
Without spending a ton of money
Samsung
Samsung SmartThings
This is
In your home this is not outside your home
They do actually have a SmartThings button that's cellular powered Samsung
Sun also makes that
R outside
Thermostat something
But inside the home you can just do this it will send you a notification and or
Now
You mentioned sending it to a list
There's no function to basically send it to you
And then two minutes later sent to someone else it's
If you want
You have to create basically six rules
Phone numbers for
Same button press will then
Shootouts
Right there might be a way to it
Like if your
Enter programming it might be a way to
Create a custom notification method
Do that
Absolutely they are very open when it comes to creating your own
Device handlers and so on so that
Good if that's not something
You want to do totally understand
I have seen some scripts that people put together to do something very similar
What you're asking so it's definitely possible if you want to mess the time
They do have a call at the
Pushover
App so that would actually send notice
Vacations to Lake
Devices
If you want to go that route
You spend all day on a computer or something like that you wanted to pop up while your
Hanging out in your Chrome browsers
Right yeah pushover is an API service that will basically turn something into a
What looks like a native notification just like it when an app send you a notification on your phone instead of an email or text
It's that kind of notification were talking about so that's possible and that's very customizable again he might have to do a little bit
Programming but I looked at it
And if we're talking maybe 10 lines of code and you can probably have
Some rules apply after 2 minutes
Ping this person via a notification then this person another 2 minutes later
Gets out of The Simple Solution but it's doable
So that is our recommendation
You could also do something via a gift but we didn't like it because of latency
And reliability issues
So
That's why we went with
Plus cost wise you know
You could Poppy's buttons all over
There you go
15 bucks
A button in every room
Maybe
Multiples in every
Yay
All right
John thanks
You so much for calling us
And you are now entered to win the WeMo dimmer switch
Once again
If you guys want to be entered to win or you have a question give us a call at 5 12623
742 4
And now
Stay tuned for our guest
Tyson Tuttle who is the CEO of silicon labs
Is a chipper that does all the radios that
You know in love inside your home
And even some others you may not know about
Hey everyone we are taking a quick break from The Internet of Things podcast
Ask for a message from our sponsor
This week sponsor is urbanex
Accelerator for startups
Tackling difficult problems in today's
So we have Gabe batstone
Who is the CEO of context are
An industrial software company that's focused on transforming the future of work
True AI
So let's get this started with
Summit pretty base
How do you guys Envision transforming the future of
Work
Well the context are a little slice of
The future work is really focused on what we call Blue Collar AI
And that means
Providing technology that supports
People with warm hands on cold
Cold Steel write these are the people who make our trains roll our planes fly in our building
And imagine if we can create an environment
Any piece of Machinery equipment
About when it was made
We're going to make those jobs
More productive more safe and frankly more simulator
So contacts there is also an urban X startup
Can you tell me a little bit about why you participated in the program and what you get out of it
It was an interesting decision myself
No we are not
Young Angelina
Industrial software for a couple of decades
Michelle working with heavy weights like Lockheed Martin
Boeing and so on
And so it was a natural necessarily to go into an accelerator environment
But we found it
Collaboration
With a design Focus
Does make
You think differently worth considering
Greenpoint Brooklyn
Meet the people in the location
An association with BMW and something that seems like a no-brainer
It's a great impact on their business
Everything from
Public relations
Networking to just start ideas
We love that relationship and we're proud to be a part of that community
So by making it easier to communicate with industrial machinery
What are kind of the big challenges
You're trying to solve
What's funny the challenges change from
It seems like only a year ago that I was talking a lot about how do we deal with the end of work and there's not going to be any jobs
Iron Man vs Skynet in the workplace
And that is melted into the Global Steel shortage where now we don't have enough
Interesting
Foundational elements of
Demographic shift
Digital transformation
And I need for technology to be implemented in the workplace in a way that
Again can make people
Safer more productive and be able to do their jobs
And when you can match that altogether you start to then get solutions that not only changed companies but Industries and hopefully the entire
And where can people go to find out more
Qunar website
Hey everyone welcome back
Watch The Internet of Things podcast this is your host
Stacey Higginbotham
And today's guest
Is Tyson Tuttle
Who is the CEO of Silicon Valley
The chip company here in Austin they do
All our favorite networks on the show
Bluetooth
It's fun they also do
So Tyson
How are you doing
Good great I really appreciate you for having me on and I'm excited to talk about all the
Stuff going on in iot
Before we go on no
I know you guys don't do just radios what else do you
Well we do over half of our business now is in iot
Type of products that we do microcontrollers and wireless connectivity all the different ones that you just mentioned that we also have
Products that go into infrastructure applications like high-speed data centers and
Optical Communications and wireless infrastructure and then a whole bunch of products to go into Automotive
Silly working a lot of areas but what's really
Kind of cool is it if you think about you know where Electronics go in our lives so you know we're working on a lot of the things that are going to be these laws
Long-term trends that are going to be no kind of transform the economy in the way we live
All right
So let's talk about
Radios
Because that's where I want to kick this off cuz that's almost where everything
I feel like we're in this
Weird
Point in the Smart Home
Where
Z-Wave and zigbee feel like there
If people are less inclined to use them and people are more inclined just a Wi-Fi
Meanwhile
We see things like Bluetooth and
Even Zippy pushing into the Enterprise and somewhat the industrial
Best smart home things
Personal area networks are all moving in
Is new areas
Everywhere as always
So talk to me about
What you see with
Future of radios in
Smart home maybe Industrial
Yes I could take a look at must-start with Wi-Fi and you know what you'll see ubiquitous technology that we all have in her home
Are smartphones in our laptops and tablets and I guess televisions and other streaming media devices
That's really where at
Started and the reason for a lot of these other Technologies is because there are some
Things that Wi-Fi has the challenge
Do you have to operate off of you know very low power is in a lot of the things that we do and iot or command and control
And you know for instance a door sensor or in a window sensor or something that you throw under your sink to
Measure water in all the sorts of things they have to run off of a battery for a long time and it's going to be like to be off of a coin cell
That's not really a good application
4 Wi-Fi or you can even think about a door lock you know you don't have power in your door lock so you don't want
The batteries to give out very quickly and set up for those kinetic control applications these other Technologies in particular zigbee
Bensi Wayne worth
Leading providers of both of those
Protocols there really much more tailored to the command-and-control networks
As opposed to Wi-Fi
And another aspect of this which we can get into if they'd zigbee and Z-Wave
State interoperate with other zigbee and Z-Wave devices
And know how to talk to one another where is on
Our Wi-Fi you typically just hook up to the Internet
You're talking to the cloud but there's a robustness
Aspect about 2 so a lot of the homes
Security system
Interested are on the Z-Wave protocol or a lot of the lighting applications
Internet goes down you like for your lights
Still turn off and on in for that to all work
Together and so
Those are some of the reasons why is it being Z-Wave have
Yeah I'm taking over and then Smart Home Market in the home security Market
So you're saying zigbee and Z-Wave
Are still a big player in this
And I don't disagree with that today but even if
CES we saw
2y
WiFi locks
Launch which I thought was crazy one solar-powered and one is
Apparently highly engineered
Do not require a bun
Watch battery life so I look at this and
Kind of like
It's so much easier I'm not saying Z-Wave and zigbee lever
Go away I'm just
The Hobbit smaller slice or maybe the same slice of an ever-expanding
I mean I think that's there's room for multiple Wireless Technologies
In the whole man we can stay on the smart home for a while
We've also got Bluetooth for streaming audio we've also got Bluetooth for a lot of the kids
Similar devices that need to connect
To our smartphones but you also have their a lot of you know you have
Z-Wave devices available in lots of
Lots of different things
Is going on there and you have tons of zigbee devices that are out there you know everything
Spark plug
To accommodation devices and all of that and then you have the hubs Witcher getting created that has
Multiple Wireless
Technology on your smartphone you have LTE and
The cellular technology you have Wi-Fi you have Bluetooth for different use cases
I think that there is
Room for multiple Technologies within the home
Certainly as you look at the limitations of
Wi-Fi and we haven't really even started talking about mesh type of Technology where zigbee and Z-Wave are both messed
Technology since other devices
Talk to one another and it forms a more robust Network ways Wi-Fi is typically a
Star Network are you just talking into the Hub and they're addressing that with some of the
You no likey rower
I was going to say everybody has a mesh now
I certainly have that in my house
But that's not necessarily the way that everybody has things
So there's room for both of you look at the trends I mean you know the number of zigbee devices sold in the number of Z-Wave devices sold
Is increasing substantially every year man also has he talked about particular on those zigbee side that you know getting
The industrial applications as well as solution so that's also an interesting trend
I know that we
We haven't spoken
This much on the industrial Enterprise use cases by
Those radios
Trying to get traction and
World
What do you think
Something like Bluetooth needs to really gain adoption
In the Enterprise rental space
For one thing a lot of industrial applications and actually if you look at the
Hundreds of our Rio tea business
There are tons and tons of industrial applications unit
Factory automation Smart City applications
United listen to Smart Home in a lot of the 7-year look at retail and you look at Commercial Lighting and all of these sorts of things that again
I'm actually in the industrial space there's
An even wider variety of Wireless protocols there's the standards that we've been talking about what we actually have a
Substantial
Proprietary business
In Wireless that supports a lot of the Legacy protocols and a lot of the companies
What's the weather
Exactly where you know clear connect to her I think we have
Yeah we have over 50 Wireless protocols running on our wireless gecko platform so one of the things about our Hardware
You can run all of these different protocols on it Digby Z-Wave
Bluetooth
And the light but you can also run some of the Legacy ones in a lot of people want to run you know what Legacy protocol they want to be able to up
Date to a more modern protocol like Bluetooth or certainly Digby or even thread and a lot of times they want to have
You know where you want to connect to a device with your smartphone directly as opposed to having to go over the network and the United Pursuit
Vision North
Controls are beacons assisted wide variety of applications that people like to use in an industrial
Space and so it could be having flexibility upgradability
And also multi-protocol capability are all things that are really attractive in the industrial space so you know what I think you see
A trend towards moving towards more of the standards but also the need to remain backwards compatible with the networks that are all
Already deployed
So that's a challenge but also I think an opportunity
In the industrial area
Last week I wrote about Bluetooth
Because I think there's a lot of change happening
With that standard
It's gone from controlling
My speaker with my smart phone or headphones
And now it's just trying to be everywhere to everything.
Talk to me about where you see Bluetooth going and how that's
Yeah I mean we're definitely seeing strong demand for Bluetooth
It'll be a lie and then
The emergence of the Bluetooth mesh technology and it's in a wide range of applications you know from Smart Home
Including the voice assistant
You got residential lighting connected toys home automation devices
Controllers in a smart locks are a good example if you know where you can unlock enough indicate and pom appliances you know
Coffee makers
And robotic devices and
Proliferation of Bluetooth in a lot of bees
Differin application
And then you also see a lot going on it in the China Market we just announced
You know what xiaomi which is out of the apple of China they have been a great echo system with the vehicle system there
Selling scooters in the US but they sell thousands of different devices
In China they're working on Bluetooth matching so we've partnered with them and are one of the first companies with it
Bluetooth mesh stack that people can
Take out the
Play Weston design products for so a lot of different things going on in the Bluetooth Market
Familiar with
Because the camera the wyze camera the $20 one
I know 1.5 million if you guys have
That is actually looks just like xiaomi scammer
So there you go
All right
What are the things
To Tappan fairly recent
Italy is Amazon buy
Eero and we see a lot of
Bigger company
The smaller kind of startups that
Iot space
I don't think that's weird or anything
But I'm curious
What happens from a
Product design
Perspective and how that affects
You know your business
It's possible that all your individual customers
Consolidate under just a few customers
Which doesn't seem
Great or two maybe they've got
Better relationships
Play other chip providers in there
Lab
I think that in the case of Amazon in particular it's pretty interesting every Nero has been a great partner of ours and the 15
84 radio in there that run spread is one that we've worked on with them
And that's a great mess technology in the home and can be an enabler in a window into all the other devices and then you've got ring
You know they came in
With the home security system and that was actually Z-Wave technology and natively with Amazon they've got Ziggy technology
So I think that you know what you talk about the multiple protocols
Those all come together in that way but it's also you have the larger companies while they're going to build a lot of things
I think they're also trying to enable
A broader ecosystem of
Providers and really streamlined the interface for people in the home you know whether it's a voice interface or getting devices to
Work together or to provide the gateways into do levels of integration that any individual company might not make so I think
Actually opens up opportunity not just for us
Provide silicon into those applications but actually it will accelerate the adoption of these iot Tech
Technologies and make them more accessible
So in your position
I feel like you are
Right there where you can see what's happening and iot the big trends that we should be thinking about going forward
I know probably a year ago you and I talked about
Improving Security on the chip side for iot
I know you guys
Are doing that with some second-generation
Products
And we can talk about specifics around
So curious what else are you guys seeing and thinking about designing in
Next Generation silicon
If we're talking just about silicon
Security is a big part
And that's really getting
You know payment grade
Type of security you know like what you'd be using with a smart card or the SIM card in your smartphone but being able to get the
Daughter to costpoint
And to be able to execute that was really really low power consumption that can be appropriate for iot devices and then
Figuring out how to make that standards of security is absolutely a big part of what we're doing it's a part of our first gen but
We're doing further optimization and
Integration on the 2nd gen
Products and then
You just look at you know as you're pushing silicon technology along you know driving power consumption for longer battery life
Driving longer-range the same time increasing the
Yeah the memory in the microcontroller functionality so that you can design
You know some basically you can think about it is fairly simple
AI type of functionalities that you can do more processing
And do more intelligent looking at sensors and things like that within the same footprint of cost then
Within the same footprint
Power and so that's what's really exciting about the Next Generation silicon as well as just being able to have it work over and Eva
Broader range of applications
How do you think the world
Which change
Technology industry would need to change if we actually wanted to build
An internet of things that
Add more
Local control in maybe
A lot less data going up
Cloud
Are focuses primarily on the devices
At the very edge the sensors and no devices that we all think about is connected and we also work
At the Gateway level to make sure that they're all talking
To one another but if you talk about the limitations at the very edge
In many cases I mean if you think about the tens of billions of iot devices being deployed you're not going to run a wire
Every one of them
And so you end up with
That's substantial number of these devices with fundamental constraints on the amount of power you talked about it.
Door lock with a solar cell or something like that energy harvesting is one way but it's really hard to guarantee 100% of the
Time that that works
So you're stuck with the little coin cell battery is or things like that and you don't want to replace them very often and that's it
Fundamental you no limit as to another trade-off between the battery life
And the amount of processing that's done in so that's why we've had just a
Tremendous focus on being able to integrate more memory more processing power
You know more clever since our interfaces and ways of communicating more efficiently so that you can maximize the song
Functionality
Within
Given energy
I think at this very very edge there's a lot of innovation
Going there
And
You know as well as innovating around use cases in the partitioning of the processing that's there and at the Gateway and how much gets up to the
The clouds I think there's a huge amount of innovation I think one of the wireless protocols also kind of play into that a little bit as though
To the extent that they can become more spectrally efficient or you can drive
You no further optimization of the power consumption at the wireless level that that also opens up a little bit more opportune
30 as well but the architecture you know within the data center in the cloud has made
Huge strides but as you push that further down it starts to look a little bit different
All right will Tyson thank you so much for coming on the show today
All right I really appreciate
You taking the time to talk to us it's exciting to see what's going on out there
That's it for this week thanks so much for listening and remember if you'd like more iot news
Sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot. Com
Will see you next week