Hey everyone welcome to the 209th episode
Code of The Internet of Things podcast
Andrew
Kevin tofel
And we have an amazing show for you we are going to be talking about
Where does Siri in the homepod
Apple's new Services strategy
We're going to be talking about cyber security in the wake of a company
The mesh Wi-Fi company has a new security service and we're going to talk about
So far this Marco
Harvest their own energy Google is teaching robot with machine learning
They're not taking over the world that they might be able to better sort
Toys which is
Equally important
Real talk about ethics in AI
We got a lot of news from UPS NYPD and everybody's favorite hamburger stand
McDonald
This week's guest is Eve
Who is the head of innovation at Fort Rock and she is going to be talking to us about
Manager
For the internet of things and how we're going to get rid of
So many password prompt
It's a lot to look forward
2 +
We're going to hear from
Joe Britt the CEO of a pharaoh
On how to use data
Properly
Actual inch
All this
And more
Oasis
After word from our sponsor
This week sponsor is
Iot world
All of you are invited to iot World which is the intersection of Industries and iot in a
It's happening in Santa Clara Convention Center in Silicon Valley on May 14th
Route 7
This is the sixth anniversary of iot world and they will be over 12500 II
Beauty professionals exhibitors and startups
You can connect with strategist technologist Developers
Implementers to put iot
Actual business verticals
To learn more and register to attend
Visit iot world event
Dot-com
That's iot world event
Recording this
The lovely afternoon in Helsinki Finland which is where I am this week
I am actually learning a lot about
Scandinavia region so you're going to do about it
Probably not to show cuz I'm a little jet lag
Stacey on iot world tour
This is hits half-world to work
This week it's been like next week in Stockholm
Week after that
Back it up
Let's kick it off this week Apple had a big announcement which I didn't even really
I was like I don't really need to watch this it is probably not to be hardware-related but
Attitude in
Husky
And
Really
Wall Street
Focus on the services Market
They offered a subscription service for newspapers newsletters and
Others
Subscriptions
And
There is now an app
And don't forget Apple arcade which is there
Subscription for $10 a month to play a hundred or more games
I did forget Apple arcade how dare I
That's all right
See this is this is why we work well together
They did have some Hardware came out the week before
And none of it was home care to where I accumulated which I think what kind of
Become numb to waiting for anything new there
Yes I'm not holding my breath
New and improved
Not the way we had hoped in her so we thought there would be more sensors health-related stuff it's really just
Minor improvements in the Bluetooth connectivity in the battery life and
Addition of wireless charging
I'll take what I can
In-ear devices
I would say apple probably isn't because there are devices out there that do offer any other headphones with
In your sensors and such but
Apple doesn't typically do things until they're ready to do it so clearly they weren't
This brings us back to something they did do a long time ago being the Forefront of digital assistants
And haven't done much sense
I saw this news tonight
What is all this mean for Siri in the homepod
With all of this Services strategy that Apple Isabel
I struggle to find really anything
Siri you're coming sure you can control your Apple TV music subscription and such
My voice
That's not new
There's nothing Hunt related here so that
Another got the homepod out there they seem to have
I want to say no dependents because clearly it's there on the market still on for sale but
Nothing new is happening with the homepod
Nothing really new is happening with Siri
There
Digital assistant
Or homepod with your services right now
And that's what kind of surprised me because
Amazon for example
Has historically made Amazon is the original
Delivers products from all over the place and it is a platform that I go to to find all kinds of crazy
And it's
Steadily increasing is
Scroll trying to take a cut out of every transaction
Jeff Bezos estate
And so
Insomuch as
You know we talked about it on the show
Amazon's digital assistant
It's not yet an integral part of Amazon strategy here
Amazon does have a strategy
Invoice shopping
Isn't so far gaining a lot of ground
But I do think it
Amazon is collecting device data
And getting it
Users
Comfortable with having
Advantage more and more of their lives
It soon it will manage their shopping or it might just make shopping easier through programs like
Amazon
Which is where you have even let Amazon delivery folks into your home
If you have a certified Smart Lock
Camera
Orchestra Smart Lock
I think I agree with everything you said I think
Apple also is a middleman
Poor
Services
End
Purchases
In a different way
Mainly within its own ecosystem in a sentence
They obviously have third-party partners with absence on but they get a cut of everything
Everything you do Apple getting a cut of everything in the iOS ecosystem
And
They actually did expand beyond their ecosystem in one of their services
The Apple TV
Is coming to several
Smart TVs
So
The different way
Expand beyond their platform
We saw this with iTunes remember way back when
Finally did a Windows version of iTunes
Apple music which was originally beats music and started out on Android is obviously Apple
As well
So maybe they're just expanding to other platforms around inner
Payment
Where is something like Amazon and Google is expanding
Around
Their platform encompasses all kinds of other
Where is Apple's like new
Not going to do it
Corral
Correct
There's no real crate answer here other than
The services strategy doesn't seem to
Incorporated
Really at all
Apple is clearly not welcoming the open ecosystem that I think is necessary for this
Successful digital assistant
So I expect
Crummy experience there and double down on privacy as the reason
Yeah I think that's really good operating procedure for them right now
It was worth talking about since everyone loves Apple
I would say
Maybe not.
A fun topic
Cyber security
So this week
We got big news cyberex which is an industrial iot security startup they raised 18 million
Let it around led by Qualcomm
And even capital
Which is
In cigarettes is a company that I dealt with a lot they do a lot of reports around Industrial iot
Viruses malware bad practices all of this stuff
Business Development
It's pretty much a straight up
Investment
We expect all the expansion
What's interesting about cyber X is it has focused
Almost entirely
Industrial
Coyote and
The software monitors net
Work traffic on equipment and then
Figures out what a normal data flow looks like
When the network traffic doesn't follow that behavior is
Wait
Weird data structures soy
If your industrial centrifuge start sending out weird versions of its data
Hyperx Cloud flight
And it also looks at who's access
Which individuals are a
Accessing
The network
So it's a pretty broad array of things
Consumers
But
The reason I pulled this funding is because
We're seeing a
Huge need for this as things come online and as things that will formally not connected
So
MIT technology review actually had a really good overview
Triton
Malware
It was first discovered on Schneider all
Electric stuff
And basically attacks the safety
Systems of the programmable logic controllers
That sort of thing
Are these are the things that control the big honkin machines that run inside and
Industrial plant
And
Damn it story basically whatever I thought about Triton Triton
It's malware targets Industrial iot
I didn't think of it as
In quietness alarmist
Language in
MIT calls it the most murderous malware
Wow
Yeah
It is designed
TLC's are for health and safety
Books for physical workers in the plant and also just for making
Plant
Operate as it's supposed to
So I guess in that sense yes you could blow up a plant
Getting a ride to Safety Systems which is what am I
Yard list
It's actually
Interesting to me that
First I was like why are companies like a cyber X looking at
Industrial only
But when you explain how it monitors for deviations in data and there were traffic
Total sense that companies like this
Focus on Industrial
Oversimplify things but in the smart home you've got so many variables
People searching different websites doing different activities etcetera
In a plant
Things should be doing the same thing mostly the same all the time
Innocent little easier to
Detect
Or look for something is out of the norm I'm curious about what people will companies leaving smart home because of the wide
Variables but
It just makes sense to me now
And that's a good one
That's not the only thing you should do with industrial iot security probably should have some auditability
Around your data that sort of thing and they're definitely companies providing that
There's several layers that
Coming to play the Cyber X definitely it's always one
The other story so Heather MIT technology review
Potential for harm
Prior to this
Aluminum
Producer
Can aluminum foil
Norsk Hydro
Was struck by ransomware
We're in this ransomware actually
Shut the plant down in
Their losses this particular incident have reached
40 million US dollars
Crazy
Basically because their systems were attacked by the ranch
Swear they had to shut things down
And
They're gradually now ramp
Production
So
There's a lot of question
Cyber X will software
In this case
If it started behaving weirdly I don't know if it would catch the
Before it launched the attack basically
Suspect not only because
Ransomware is a little bit different in that
It won't take actions like in a plant in like you know make a plant grow up instead somebody
Has access to take control of the system
And can bring shut it down and say I'm not turning back on $1000000 or whatever it is
Yeah and you don't even have to attack the actual physical
Plant infrastructure
Computers Lakewood database
There's to This shows
Two different vectors of attack
Equally catastrophic
I shouldn't say
Because you know obviously
Oil refinery exploded in spew toxic gases everywhere
People that is
That's much worse than not having enough Coke cans to
But
From a company in an economic perspective
Attacks
Are things you really
So it was worth talking about just to kind of drive home how important cybersecurity
Even an industrial system
Which may not be connected to the internet
Nation states and other hackers are targeting
Comes as well
And so
It's going to get really interesting
Another security over to the Smart Home
Which makes a mesh wi-fi system
They announced their own security service
A couple weeks back it was not surprising
Because
Pretty much everybody else Comcast
Euro
Other companies I can't think of right now
I'll have these types of services and usually monitoring your network traffic
They're saying hey
Your thermostat probably should not be talking
That's weird
Shut that down
Who doesn't have one
What doesn't have parental controls
Add-on subscription type
Security service
It does have security features such as parental controls and guest networks and all
But what you're describing from plume
I don't know
The Google I've never heard Google talk about I'm sure you know I just don't know there's there's no mention of
Any over and above tech security
Here's the question
A lot of these services
Are predicated on the idea
Their services through a service provider and they're also boxes
Norton has one of his cloak
Core
These are like this and you can buy them
My question is
Do we really need
In
So far
The answer based on my eye so I got the Eero service just to see what it would look
The answer seems to be no
The things that are getting attached
Are my computers and
IPhones
B
I hope you saw not so much a part of it is because I tend to buy
Decent stuff I don't put weird
Beauty Brands in my house
I know some companies
Some of the more well-known iot companies they're actually proactively doing network monitoring
So
Me doing it as just another layer in in another saying that
I am just one person
This is all anecdotal this is not actually true data
But so far I haven't seen an attack stops that would really
Warrant
Paying for this I think the Avalon of
Okay
See that's what I think is
Missing
And your question about
Is a reason necessary I don't know the answer that question
That's probably more about personal Comfort level thing
But I just went to the Google Wi-Fi security features webpage
Firewall WPA2
Automatic updates and TLS
Communication
There's no network monitoring mentioning or anything like that
Centris
Probably do it
Civil engineering
They're pretty smart people
So in some ways I think this is
This could be two things
To get you to buy a subscription
And is falls into the need for a subscription Revenue source.
The product
Cuz they're trying to continually update these things
They're trying to add you services
Viable to
So include for example his talked about adding a subscription fee
For it
Devices
Which
So this could just be a way to legitimize charge
Charging people
Could be an N actually with
You have zero your house I think you pay what $10 a month for similar service
Yes
How is $60 for the years of $5
Yes but
I do get a blocking
I get it
VPN
Password
I probably get a pony that I haven't paid for
I have it actually picked up yet I do
You got horny and you get a pony
So
I don't know I'm not sold
I'll be real here
Nothing
I think a lot of our listeners
Just based on comments on the website and enter voicemail
They actually are concerned again I think it's a personal choice and I think it's probably
Protective than not
But I don't pay for Energy Services that's just me personally
Get off work
Go for it
I just turn my lights off
Not again
All right
Let's talk about chips
At music which is a car in California
Powered
SOC use for the
Internet of Things
Solar powered
That
You can put into an iot device and
I love all of you
It's basically the reason you basically designed a chip that could run
Bluetooth radio in a small application
Very very very low power
And idea was you could
Battery
Small TV
TurboTax
And we just run forever
And that apparently is what they have.
I wrote about them a couple months ago
High School start
6 smart for them to combine photo photovoltaic and in there
Article on demand wake up Technologies
They say I say
200 times lower power
Then other
Relating of similar Champs
Sound
And it basically the idea here is
If you're going to have a sensor
And you're going to have a billion
You cannot be changing their batteries all the time
You just got to set it and forget it
And that
What does technology could help
Let's talk about
Robot
Which of course I love to talk about so I was very interested in this
A story from earlier this week
Google AI blog
Showing off the lot
Which is exactly what it sounds like
Initially the robot did not know how to
Toss the right items into
The appropriate bin when sorting things
But using Google's AI
About ten thousand grass and throw attempts
14 hours that took of training time
They now
Show that the passing by has four C's of
Up to 85%
And
That's amazing to me because in such a short time
This arm has learned how to properly sort things into the right boxes
Certified cell phone by analyzing
Results over time
Ann supervised learning
That's what I do everyday unsupervised learning
I just think about you all these massive warehouses where we have
People going around
Turn on the picking
Of products and what not
I know they've got some robots in those warehouses and all but when you start combining
The mobility of a robot then with the self-learning of hay and I can go pick this product I know where it is
Yes ma'am
Just think about it and recycling right now
Like a huge percentage of recycling isn't sorted correctly so if we can somehow automate that so people don't have to
To do it
Cuz it's like Yaki job no one really wants it
We could actually lower the total cost of recyclables Witchwood
Presumably
Encourages to recycle more
Yay
Absolutely there's a lot of potential here
Any of the downside is that there are currently people that have jobs that do these types of things
Honest I think people could probably better spend their
Doing other things
So I love this
They should start a podcast
It's all the rage
All right
Hey
Other robots these robots are flying robot
Yes
You saw the UPS Now using drones for medical Palos
I did
Does this mean I get my new kidney deliver via drone
It wouldn't be delivered to your home
The Drone could actually deliver to the hospital if you're getting a kidney transplant
Absolutely
There are some limitations here granted this is all part of
Under the FAA as well just got approval
I should say that
Test program right now but
The drowning
Paramedical payloads up to about 5 lb
So maybe a couple kidneys on
Over distances up to about 12 and a half miles so
Specific
But lots and lots of potential in a very
Time efficient manner for something that mean when you need
Say that kidney or a heart or whatever it might be
When you see the kidney call UPS
It's a very specialized but important
I'm having impactful
Project right now
Yeah I just looked at the
Average weight of an adult human kidney is a quarter pound
Dry ice
Whatever
I don't know how to dress
Order 3 and get a discount I mean come on
Free shipping
This makes a lot of sense
Especially in
Anybody who set
Just in New York or San Francisco traffic
Literally literally
What else
Oh
Speaking of New York City
Police Department is using AI to detect
Crime
Patterns
Which
You seem very excited by this
Interesting and obits
Yeah but the New York Police Department Ashley
Said this month that they're using
Attract
Crimes and Spa
They've been doing it since late 2016 which I found
Very interesting
They call this
Modernizr is not obviously spelled correctly
Starts up things in spells incorrectly so
Nicr after the work pattern
There's some people who are rightly concerned about racial biases being reinforced
It's going to open up things to a lot of
Scrutiny
Make the world
I think we're going to see very starkly
We have
Structured our society disadvantage some people over others
And
I think when put in very black-and-white terms through
Data analysis
Will no longer be able to lie to ourselves and say that this is an individual's fault
And we'll have to start looking at culpability of us as a society
Which could be interesting or we could just shrug our shoulders
I will say even though I think I should have disclosed this making 2016
The police department is taking up
Slow approach in using us because they're not
Using it for crimes
Such as
Recent homicides
They are basically using to track petty larceny is to
Ingest data and gather analyzing and so on so
That's probably wise but
Doing the wrong thing
The measured approach
Speaking of data
McDonald's
Smitty big acquisition
Yes
McDonald's is acquiring dynamic
Which
Analyzes
Names of data
Drive-thru
UPS
A product
Based on
Weather time of day
What you ordered
Yeah it's rather smart use of external data
What happens at the drive-in
Define often
I don't know once a week
Once a month
I go there too often
Bentley and publicly minutes and that's all I'm going to say on that
Okay Kevin I would like you
Go soon
It's start documenting what you are
Offered and let's see how that changes over
I go for testing purposes
There you go see now you have a reason to
Other than
All right
Those are the stories for this week so I think it's time for
Internet of Things podcast hotline
Where we answer your question
Ciot podcast hotline is brought to you by Schlage
Traceway Friday smart locks let you create the smart home of your dreams
Learn more about Schlage Smart Home Solutions and compatibility with Amazon
Apple
Google Assistant products
What's more at Schlage
Dot-com
Coyote
Part of their sponsorship we are giving away a Schlage Smart Lock
So if you would like to be entered to win that lock
Give us a call at 5 1/2
6 to 3
742 4
With your smartphone questions
And you will be entered to win a Schlage
Connected
We must get all of your entries before the
End of March so that's March 31st at
Midnight Eastern Time
Can only ship them to the US and Canada I am so sorry everybody else but
Stop calls with your questions
We might answer
This week's question is
From Joe
Let's hear it
Hello Stacy and Kevin
This is Joe
And you may use the song the show
I recently had motorized
Z-Wave window blinds
Install
And was able to connect them to my wake up without problem
However I was disappointed
That the Amazon Echo
Discover.
I was hoping for them to be found at least that's what you heard Z-Wave device
They could be voice
Bald
To turn on off
Raise or lower the blinds
And I could find no related madam
Skill
La poblana
Manufacturers Graber
Z-Wave motor by others
Valley Football
I was wondering if you had any tips or tricks
To get the echo to recognize the Z-Wave motor
Text
Ojo I have been there
Exactly where you are now I have connected my selfie blinds to my wink home hub
And I did it in a weird way
As a zwave device and
Not only can I not connect it to Madame a
I also
Have it backwards
So instead of
Can I say open the blinds in the app
It actually closes the blinds in real life
Is apparently unknown
Law that happens to Lots
Yay
But isn't that what you're asking
You would like for it to work with Madam a
And here we have good news
Yeah the good news is you can get it working with Madam a
Will Google home if you prefer
The bad news is you can't do it with have to do it with SmartThings
So yes unfortunately
That's because the way wink
Actually sees that device just
Treats it as
It's a generic Z-Wave
And the challenges wink support
Madame only for supported
Lights
So
You can do a lighting shortcut
As long as the lights are supported in granted
Youku
Make your Z-Wave device look like a light but it still isn't
Supported by
So it won't actually work
Right and technically it doesn't quite work with SmartThings
Unless you actually change it to a dimmer switch in SmartThings there's
A device Handler that that handles this so you don't even have to change it to a dimmer switch
Install that and so on
So you can change it to a dimmer switch
Things and then it would work
That's a terrible answer because I know you have as well
Unfortunately you know it's not crazy expensive I think it's 99 bus right now
Sometimes it's even as low as 70
Right now I mean actually mine cortical SmartThings Hub cost me $10 because
I bought the USB SmartThings link
Spectacles into an Android TV
So
That made it a hub
I think that was
Especially
Because they like me
No like it was like the holidays
So they don't like me I think you're right it maybe like 30 or $40 that USB stick
I don't know their opinions on you kept sorry
For the day sorry about that
And
You know you can maybe you'll just invest in the Ikea blinds when they come out in August
Stand
That should work
With Madeline
I would replace my Hub before I replace my blind cuz I have a feeling those blinds for the motor for that probably wasn't going to
Expensive
That is true
That's why I'm still stuck with
Janky setup
Psy
All right
Well that's it for that
Time to Say Goodbye Tevin and then hear from our guest Steve Mueller
Who is the head of innovation at Fort Rock we're going to be talking about
Why you won't be entering as many passwords
In the near future
You
The first
A message from our sponsor
This week sponsor is a pharaoh
Hey everyone we are taking a quick break from this week's podcast for a message from our sponsor this week sponsor is a
Pharaoh and I have a pharaoh CEO
Jailbreak
Here to talk to us
Data and AI
So Jo you and I've been having a series of conversations including on Topix
Bank of things
Using Bluetooth low energy to create a secure payment platform
And the platform approach to iot
And this week I'd love to talk about data analytics and AI
But first
Would you remind our listeners what it is that a pharaoh does
Yeah a pharaoh provides and iot platform that simplifies how you connect anything to the internet
We can help you build business cases take you
You all the way through roll out
Mongoloid management of your entire fleet of devices
As well as data analytics
Customers tell us that a pharaoh is the best choice for into end-user experience and developer productivity
And it's also beautiful design
Really easy to use
Fast
And very very secure
SoJO there's no AI without data increasingly there's not enough data without iot
So can you explain for us the relationship between these two
Concepts
Why do we care about art
Machine learning AI ultimately gives us insights that we can use to achieve objective
But what do we have to feed a i with we have to feed it with structured data
And where does that structure data come from what comes from anywhere anything that can generate in one of the biggest problems that we have with
IRT
Is structuring the date of the right way many other iot Solutions
Allow the developer to just
Send free form data up to
The cloud the hazard with
Yes is that the developer doesn't always think through how the data should be structured to best serve
Artificial intelligence engine and without that
Planning and forethought
It's very easy
To create
A huge amount of data
But either has to be normalized before
Can be used by AI
Or in the worst-case
Just can't be used at all
So a pharaoh takes a different
Approach
How does a pharaoh
In many a i
What's the date of that you're dealing with
Comes without much contacts
Attached to it
Now she wants may be aware of the contacts
But the metadata to do
Describe it just isn't there
The best possible
What solution is to have what we call structured data
Where there's a data schema in each field is labeled and understood
From the outset
Affero guides the developer through giving
Each captured data element
That needed Kant
In this way
Data captured using a pharaoh
Is already ready to be used with AI machine learning and also used in conjunction with other structured data sources
These have been great before we go please remind us where people can go to
To get more information about it
You can always go to
Acero. IO
/ Go - big
As a great place to start
If you're a developer
Check out developer. Afero. IO
And you can check out all the resources that we have on a pharaoh. IO
Would welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest
Is Eve Baylor who is VP of innovation and emerging technology
At Fort Rock
Hi and how are you doing
I'm great thanks Davie High everybody
So
She
If you guys haven't recalled she was on the show before probably about a year ago and we talked about
Identity
And I really thought we have to solve this problem by now but
I still have so many
Passwords so
Much difficulty logging on two devices
Multiple times in a month
I'm actually getting more frustrated not less
So
We're going to talk about
Why that is and maybe some of the
Technology
That might help make it better
That sound good
Yeah yeah
Year people been working on it for maybe 15-20 years
By golly these are smart people they should be here by now
We've solved all kinds of other problems I feel like the best place to start is to break down
Infer definition
Thanks when I think about logging into things and lie, that's my identity on these devices
Nope that's Authentication
So let's tell me the difference between the two
So you know
Identity
The information that represents you that the stuff that's true
Entrusted
About you
Authentication is the active
And what the companies that want you to prove that you're you to them want to do with that information
Is
Experience
And give you a personalized experience
And they want your partner in this
Help you pay for things that help you have
An experience that is connected
It can happen
Continuously
The beginning of
Quicken YouTube about username and password
Stop music at the beginning of a session
At least
With that company that were having a digital experience
Okay let's talk about that because this was an article that
Really resonated with me
With my
I don't know 60 some-odd devices in my house and
And I am constantly being asked to
Authenticate myself to them
What is going on in this article the writer promise
Outline the problem
And then he said but guys it's going to get better cuz we have new standards
It's coming along
So explain to me
First
Why all these companies need me to like
Constantly login
Account goodlord
Yeah it is it is kind of constant cuz there's so many companies
He did mention that a sign in with Facebook button how he's never going to do it
Do that
And that enables
Companies
Multiple town
So when I login with Facebook and Google then they get all that
Data about
Where I'm going right
David that where you're going
And the companies that leverage that's fine with whoever button
They're getting data
Units of mutual benefit for Facebook on Google
And then
You get the benefit of having service
Easier sign in
Experience
I guess you could say the mutual benefit all around but there's also some privacy
Yeah I'd rather use like a password manager or maybe have
Chrome
12 Chrome keeps my
Information that I've shared
Google
Give you the choice of buying with Facebook as a button
Versus
You know creating a whole new password and you know not using
It's good to have a choice because
Puppies
And I tend to be more private
And not take that off
The author the Facebook of the Google button
So I tend not to use that because I don't want to share Facebook information with Google information
Calling again
It really is an authentication problem
Enter
And you don't want any friction and entering the Third
Enough work another solution to the problem
India password manager
People
Often times I recommended on data privacy day
When everybody I'm not a security professional
Professional
Well you know
Password managers that can help you in a reduced fraction
Okay
In that particular article this is not the solution they talk
What about coming to save us all from the charity of having eight thousand
And remembering them all
Edamame
So
New standard actually called
Web
Uth which was
Sedimented into the World Wide Web Consortium
And that is helping you too
More
Including some biometric
Indication
Fingerprint
Facial recognition
Into the browser
Which is where we have
Call me
And so
Standardization
As of last week and the browser makers have been fighting
Watershed forgetting
Stronger methods
Username password
To be supported
That's actually really good
The future of Authentication
Let's talk about this a little bit because there's things that need to happen for
People have to implement it on the browser side
End
On the
Application side or is there device side
Aspects like
What needs to happen for phyto to actually
Work for an individual or an individual's device
And then the second thing is
It's only works right now
Browser-based
And so what is that
The biggest
I would say I've been
Browser maker
Powerful
Do what they want
And
Getting browser
Change
I was going to be?
Absorb
I think that this barrier is going to fall
In the case of
Applications
NetSpend
Tazewell Virginia
And I think that we can
Master cycle of incorporating
Then we can expect
Generally what we see is that
I can't rely on
Smartphones and applications on mobile devices
I think I'll be able to take advantage
Okay so I could have
This additional at
Application even
If I'm signing in
Okay
So here's where things get
Billy fun
Not only am I asked like
Buy devices to Lake login
Things like I've let you out for your own safety which is fine I get it
So I'm logging into individual apps
But then
Another layer
Sometimes I want to link my apps together so I'm like a
Nest I want you to talk to my Amazon Echo
Intend
That goes like hey you got insert your
Nest password
And I'm like okay
Back and forth I go
So I I look at things like that is that something that
I should see get better here
I think it will get better and me article
YouTube
So
Cookies
People now know about cookies I think
Gdpr apocalypse
Yes I accept cookies in my browser
Equivalent
When it comes to anything.
Typically what apps do
The best possible experience
It has tokens
Forever
This is why things that aren't
Birthday your bank app
Can't believe me just watch
I think about my
Right I think of a token like a
The key to my house
I'm going to give it to someone and then I'm going to revoke it after a certain set
Because
You should know
That's what I thought
And you could have a vehicle
You
Could have somebody else using
Typically
Mobile devices
Anthony
Other kinds of
Connected
Smart devices
Very short life
And that's where tokens really don't want to be what I call
Naughty forever
Password list
Do
Authentication using
All kinds of things
Sky's the limit
Indication
True I would love my daughter loves to take my Fitbit
When I'm having a shower or some
Michelle Financial take it
I would love for it to be like
Hey
You're not Stacy
No I'm not looking
It doesn't have
But that's okay
This is not a highly secure
Pair device
But I see what she
But
The flip side of that is
Because I Am The Keeper of the passwords
On all of our connected home devices I'm also like
I'm basically like the person everyone calls on when
When stuff goes wrong or things get unlinked need to be reeling
And you know it's a multi-user environment and sometimes I wish that we had a way of
Authentication
You know everybody who belongs in the environment with admin rights
That is like a whole nother level of complex
I'm curious what you have
How to say about that
Absolutely
I can show you that
Small slice
The identity challenge with large
Talking about it
What is a delegate
If you think about it
What what I'm shorthanded as identity is really
Identity and access management
IT staff to manage
My house I don't
I don't know
That's exactly what I am
And exactly what
How to do
Enterprise I am contact you don't want to
Because you don't want to turn
Regular people
System administrator
In a lot of people are
Men should have to run like active Direct
That's
So what is the solution here
The concept of number of people have been working on for a long time
Identity relationship manager
It really isn't your grandfather's I am
You know
What does
How many light bulbs
Are you there
Cousin
Last time I talked to you I live in a tiny apartment
Stillhouse
I got you
Security
Delegating
Somebody
To some
Stagnant
My home
I really want to do it by 4
Function they have in my life
Function.
Having my life
The role that they have
And you know Enterprise I am we would talk about roll management
Explosion murder house
Control
So
Identity
You can actually
Keep it under control by thinking about
Other people
Glasgow
Cicadas noise
Google search
Facebook
Like I have a
Because I did something wrong
I can
You can actually do it
In
That would be automatic is part of the
Device in the app that's associated with that device or is that part of my management panel that's coming with me
Echo or my
Hub how do I get this magic
How you could do this
Benefit claims and prescription information
Data
Standard and standard
Connected and disconnected and paired and unpaired
The standard
And
Identity relationship
Enter people
Deploying
Actually they are
Example is a mandate in the UK
4 - 4
People who are
Multiple pension accounts
And pension pick up like in your 401k
So they're working
To the toy how you would aggravate
To somebody like that and we're working with
Dashboard console
So I would probably see my smart home hub people
Adopt something like this if I wanted to implement this kind of awesome automatic relationship management
Based on graph
In my home
So as a consumer the sounds awesome
Can't wait for it to be on the horizon
What hope do I have
For making my life easier in the short-term
In the short-term
Turn still
Going to be
As many accounts of people have to login to
In the very short of
Turn
I do advise people to use password manager
Some people will be
Incentivize to you
And it's up to each individual person to
Decided
Privacy
That's inside if you're willing
Official finding or not
And how you're going to manage all those accounts
But
Identity is not authentication alone
Multiple
Think about
What identity baijiu
Identity
Coming to get protection
Personalization
Implement functionality
Out of your relationship
Awesome
It's kind of like I have to share GPS information to get all these cool
You know mapping data understanding
Like automatic
Turning onto things in my house
So here
If I'm
Willing to authenticate as often as needed
I can do cool things like pay with my ring
Actually
Up to you to determine
How you have a relationship with each other and
How much it cost
Actually starting to dictate more of a relationship
It's possible for consumers to
Put in a little bit more
Instagram
Okay we'll leave
I feel
A little better
And a little bit
Powerless to start calling on some connected device companies to start implementing some
Amethyst
Technology so I can
I can ease my sign-in burden thank you so much for coming on the show
That's it for this week thanks so much for listening and remember if you'd like more iot
Sign up for my newsletter and Stacey on iot. Cam will see you next week