Hey everyone welcome to the 207th episode of
The Internet of Things podcast
This is your host Stacey Higginbotham
And your co-host
Kevin tofel
And we have a
Really packs show for you today
We're going to be talking about Charter launching some smart home management
Efforts
We got a little bit of a discussion about facial recognition
Going to talk about the latest airline crash and what it means for connected devices and software in more places
We got a bunch of news bits
Trump Google
And
We're going to be talking about
More connected appliances coming on the market
Amazon finished its Arrow acquisition
Are your data
Plus
We're going to here
From our sponsor of pharaoh
On why you need an
Iot platform
And
I am going to bring you
To South by Southwest because I hosted a panel
So I guess this week is actually lots of people
It is
Participants from that panel on the Smart Home
That was sponsored by you know me and we're going to hear from
Folks from Dallas
Tendril
Charter
LexisNexis and iRobot
Voice recorded live so you're getting here a little bit of like
Fart noises in the background because he
It South by Southwest but
It's a really awesome
Panel and
So
Before we get started
Let's hear from this week sponsor this week sponsor is Western Digital Western did
Digital builds Data Solutions that enable the world to solve its biggest challenges
Beat its newest nvme ssds the essence 6:30 and the essence
Performance endurance scalability
For next-generation workloads in the cloud and at the edge
So Step Up 2 nvme performance at westerndigital.com
For those of you who are like
What the heck is an nvme
SSD
Kevin can you tell us
I can only because I built
Gaming PC with my son last weekend and
Aside from traditional SSD which is already fast
We installed an nvme SSD
Which is super fast like
The biggest insane transfer speeds with this so this is the way of the Future 4
Fast
Data transfer on computers
Awesome so
Way of the future
You heard it here first
Let's kick this show off with
Conversation about Charter this is news I'm actually
Well originally I was excited about then
Bummed because
Charter CEO
Tom run
Rutledge said that the ISP
Cable companies
Isb
Was going to roll out a smart home management
Platform
In Austin Texas
That's where you are
Yeah
Today but they're going to roll it out in the
Fall
So
I was a little bummed about this but the story is interesting basically
Rutledge was speaking of the Deutsche Bank Media
Internet until c** comp
Big deal
And he said that Charter is developing a quote-unquote control plane to help
Customers manage the devices that connect to their
Particularly from a privacy and security stamp
This news is not surprising
We have seen
Comcast actually Focus very deeply on this both for me
Wi-Fi just making it better
Through an arrangement with
Peacock plume
And also through an arrangement with a company called Cujo it is implemented security Serv
So I think
What isps are basically doing is saying
Oh man
We have got to get up
And be responsible for Wi-Fi at home security
In customers homes
Comcast actually charges you
For this privilege
And I am very curious if Charter will see this as a new business opportunity as well
Like you said this is not surprising and I personally am not a
Cable subscriber anymore I haven't been for three years nor my big unlikes
Subscriptions
However
No Comcast XVI and now this new Charter platform and others
I probably wouldn't have a problem paying for the platform
If
It closes the security loopholes and gaps that are in a lot of beatitude products today like I would pay for that piece of mind
Tiffany if the device makers and such are not going to
Truly provide it
Then I'm okay with that
Yeah I don't think you could control all the security looks like there's a lot of
Insecure things such as
Hey
Once your password is in the cloud is it stored correctly or
My gosh
I got a weakness in some of my radio Technologies and again those hats do require physical access to the.
Zorbing near the device in most cases
It won't solve everything
Realself something
It makes it better I'm off work
Excellent
Next up
Are two stories on facial recognition that
Scare the pants off
The first is from BuzzFeed
Which published documents from the e f f
The basically showed that
The government is basically going to use facial recognition in airports
Track
American citizens as they enter the country
And use that to
Basically with four people who are
Not supposed to be
Entering the country
What they didn't do
As part of this is
They didn't set any limits on how
Airlines could use that facial recognition data
Which feels like
And they also
Didn't have any public
Comment about
Hey everybody we're going to be using facial recognition to track you when you come into the country
And didn't ask how we all felt about that as Citizens
That was not awesome
Write the next news item
On facial recognition
Was an NBC news story
It showed that many of the facial recognition algorithms that are being built right now are being built using photos
Scrape from websites without users
Consent
So IBM put out a big database
Got a year ago at
I think it was
And it was
Lauded is awesome because it had truly diverse people in it so a big problem with facial recognition is
When do you collect images from
People computer scientist had been using
A lot of images of white people so it was really
Not awesome when it came to any people of color
Or even women in some case
So IBM was like how we will fix that
And they annotated
A lot of photos what
We didn't realize they pulled those photos from
Flickr
An annotated them and then provided the database to pee
Write this is all to train the algorithm switch okay then
Makes sense to me and facial recognition is actually
Little more tricky than
Object recognition because
People
Change over time
So I get why they want to use these photos but just going out
On the web mean I don't know how many photos of Muir on the where the heck of a lot
There's more my dog that's irrelevant without my consent like that to train the models I'm not sure I'm thrilled with that
We are entering
Scary
Fairy
Deep water
Is here is an unknown area where we should be having conversation
It's not just about
How we get these images to train the data and also how we're training things have
But we're optimizing for in facial recognition is basically optimizing for accuracy
And the person
So
It's good that we recognize that these weren't accurate
Four huge swaths of the population
And try to fix that
But
It's scary to think
Your photographs might be
Used
I guess help improve this
Yay and then see it being used for something
Without people's consent like
Border control
It comes back to something you said many times and it really stuck with me
Once you give up the date at once you lose the data control
You don't know what's going to be done with it
Yeah
It might be good if I be bad
But you know we should probably talk
Absolutely
Now will move into our next big story of the week
Witches
Which is another air crash
Is 1 in
Ethiopia which was also a Boeing 737 Max this was the crash of Ethiopian Airlines flight
5 months prior we saw the crash of
Lion Air
And we have talked about this on the show but basically the issue
The we highlighted was The Lion Air crash was a result of
A sensor reporting inaccurate info
Information
And the pilots of the plane
Fighting to keep the nose of the airplane
Up when the sensor
Which was inaccurate
Information was telling it
To go down
It was actually making the plane Point down
What town in the second part of this that we found out later
Was the Des Plaines
And this
Problem was actually a result of Boeing updating the 737 with
With a software update
That changed some of the way that
Spleen function
And in the pilots
We're not perhaps
Made completely aware
So when that malfunction happened
The pilots reacted as they have been trained to do
On the non updated version
And that helped lead to the crash
And thus
We got into a conversation about
Hey
Software updates
Need training
And
How all of that
That plays out
This week in the wake of the
Latest crash
Of this jet
Many
Many countries have grounded these
Particular Airlines
The US has yet
Two grounded as of Wednesday morning
But we're also seeing a lot of
Hot takes on this where they like you don't want to drive in a self-driving car
After this and
A lot of stories that are not helpful
They're freaking out and they don't talk about the things that we need to do
When we trust more of our infrastructure
Just software and automation
We need to think about
How we instill safeguard
The hot takes are making a very high-level logical leap
Details
That comes down to management software updates
Communication of those updates
At least in the case about when are playing me for self-driving cars self-driving you wouldn't have to
Train the person so to speak
After software update
Testing
Are there so many factors no different than
Then
Any kind of
Suffer
Has to be properly tested has to be documented has to be communicated
And
VDS inherent dangers in relying upon
Sensors that could be program faulty or could fail I suppose but
To make that logical leap like hey this is a problem at all self
Driving or whatever Vehicles is just not smart
And it brings home to me the fact that
Even if we have self-driving vehicles
We're still going to have to have
People responsible
For them
Somewhere
Are in the chain so
I actually wrote about this for IEEE
After interviewing a bunch of
Connect to car makers and this was actually a big topic
This winter is CES
Is everyone acknowledging that yes there will still be people in the chain and the reason is
Sometimes software can fail sometimes computers will
Have
Weird situations that they're like
I don't know what to do here
And that's what a human operator
Take over
There always has to be in my opinion a
I take over mode that is very quickly and easily excessive
So I think the big thing to think about is
Hey
If you're updating software on something and that's actually what happened
Boeing updated the software and said
Did it was similar enough to Prior generations of the plane
The pilots didn't need to be retrained
Because that was something that would
Cost a lot of money and time
It would lead
Customers Airline customers to say yeah we're going to pass on this pretty
Eurasian boy wants to sell planes
Suicide no
You don't need
Extra training for your Pilots
And the FAA said
Alright sure
And then
Didn't get the training
And this is what happen
Fence and so there's a lot of layers here
Quick-take of
Connected devices that are
Controlled by computers are bad is not the right time
We're going there we have to go there
There are things that are too complex for
People
To handle
And I do believe self-driving cars will ultimately be safer
And as we add software
To these devices
We're going to have to establish new regulatory procedures
Recognize how much software
Change
The operational experience
And then enforce basic rules like
Yeah
Rules around testing software
Rules around training The Operators
Etcetera
Okay that was like
Hohhot
Haha take on the hot take
Which was a cooler take
So
Let's talk about smart displays because Google
Has just gone
Got nuts
Google is God nuts
Continued conversation
Are smart displays is now out for Google devices
This means what
What this means just like your smart speakers either you or Echo devices or your Google home devices
You can start a conversation with a
Google smart display and then continue it
Up until now
You would ask question like
What is the weather
But you couldn't follow up with what is the weather for tomorrow how about
Next week
Cancel. Now you can do that we tested it right before the show on my Google home hub here in the office in it
Work pretty well there's even a little in Decatur now
At the top left to show you visually that
The display is still listening for a continued conversation
Yes
Next Google story
This isn't
White
Coyote story but
It may be soon
So Google has moved its machine learning for speech recognition down to the phone
I got this this morning it was like hey
Do you watch faster speech recognition on your keyboard
Download this
It was small was actually very small
What and it's not yours
Faster
Because up until now everything would go out to the cloud Google would do its natural language processing and and send it back to you
It works offline
Yes
And that's what
Exciting so guess right now it's on the phone
Yay phones have a lot of processing power
They have a lot of storage
But
Imagine this on your smart display
Suddenly local control of things or things when there is no internet access
As long as it's not a cloud to Cloud integration
We could start seeing local control
So that would be awesome
I'm a fan
Google pixel phone
Google pixel phones there was a feature announced that last year's Google IO called Lookout
That is now available to pixel phones I have not used it on my pixel
But what Lookout is
It is a way for the phone
To provide
Information about someone's surroundings meaning somebody who is a visually impaired
So the phone could be your set of eyes R example with Lookout
And
If you're visually impaired you can hold your phone around the room and it could tell you what objects are in there dog
Speaker table
Chair
So very cool
Also
Are the accessibility friend
We've got an update
From Microsoft
Right now Microsoft has a similar product called seeing AI
And they are pushing forward with some new features
With their custom vision service
To explore photos by touch which is a really interesting so
You can
Can I have a spoken description of something on a screen if you touch the screen
They brought this to the iPad as well now so it's not just on
They've also brought this seeing AI to iPads what you did not have before so
They are pushing forward with
Accessibility things
You don't make life better
But using the cloud and sensors
That's awesome yes I actually
After I did another talk at South by Southwest
Yesterday
And afterwards somebody who worked on Google Assistant doing accessibility stuff came up and talked
And I was really excited to see the enthusiasm with which she
She didn't tell me anything that was like particularly
She obviously didn't share the
Product roadmap
But we talked very badly about the need for accessibility and it felt very much like this was an important initiative
Obviously for her personally because it's her job
But even at goo
I'm encouraged as we bring voice
And
Speakers more broadly into our home
We're also
Bringing technology to people who
May have historically had a difficult time
Yeah I think this is a
I want saying overlooked Market but I think
A lot of developers and product makers out there don't dismiss it but don't give it the attention it deserves I see a lot of opportunity
Be there I just mentioned to you Stacey before the show that my comp sci Professor reached out to me this morning saying
Hey we've got a blind student in the music program year college and
They can't use the music Boards
Programming music Boards because the button so we can see them they light up and
Green might be in a certain instrument red light mean another instrument and
So we're going to try and buy some either interface or a braille silicone keyboard overlay for this person
I never would have thought to do that
I mean there's just so many
So many opportunities in this area for four Good Hits just a bit mazes
And
In a lot of ways and this is actually philosophy at Amazon
Designing things that are accessible
Make it easier and better for
Any number of other people
So when you're doing things for the visually impaired
You're actually also helping people who are maybe older and unable to
C as well
Okay moving
Rachel all we have
An appliance store
GE Appliances has signed up
To add Wi-Fi
Capability via serrant
And
If you guys are like what is happening
Basically sierant is a company
Was actually bought by Cypress recent
Is a company that makes it easier to get devices online
What happens is
It uses what is essentially a public Wi-Fi network
Created by
Most Wi-Fi routers from isps today
Have a public setting and a
A private setting
You use the private setting
But the public setting
It can actually be used for like a cable providers Wi-Fi network
Or a company like Siri
Associate has these deals in place to use that
What it does is the connected Appliance gets on that public net
Work in the moment
You plug it in it Finds Its token in the cloud
K'Nex
And then you can connect it as a consumer if you want to
And then once you connect it you're going to do a hand over from
Public network
Your personal net
So Electrolux is done this
They were one of the first big customers
Hours for Sears
Bose has another
And now geappliances Society
The reason I'm interested in this and the reason I'm telling you about this
Is because
That public network makes it possible for your appliances to be online without you bringing
Which could worrisome people I actually think it's
Mostly a positive and the reason I say that
Is because if
GE has this always connected device in your
You can actually
When you call in and say hey
My water filter doesn't seem to be working
They can say something along the lines of
Well would you mind if I looked up Diagnostics on that device and if you opt-in
They can say okay
Look up the Diagnostics and then suddenly tell you from afar what's wrong and then send the repair person out with
With the right
Heart
Time Saver
Yeah overall I think this is a positive but I do think it's something consumers should know so you might be bringing in
Appliance that
Is connected to the internet even though you haven't connected it
I would hope that Appliance companies are not
Using data from this without
Your permission
But it is something
And I do think ultimately
It is a good feature having had devices in my home
Home appliances breakdown
I regret actually every time one of my appliances breaks down because I'm like
Smart
I could just be like
I'm sending someone out with this part to fix
Yeah even some of the
I'll call them
Little glitches in cooking with the June oven for example from time to time something has happened in the past 2 years
Going to customer support or like do you mind if we get the logs off of your machine and
You know they ask him in advance
And you either concentric or don't
But having that data has solved the problem every single time
Yeah so as long as there's transparency around the connectivity and transparency around
Opting into sharing the data
All
Or it
So I thought I'd share that with you guys cuz it's probably not something
You're thinking about
And finally
The Amazon
Deal for Eero the Wi-Fi mesh Wi-Fi company
Has been completed
And both companies
Promise promise promise pinky pinky pinky swear that they are not going to share your data
Yeah there's a really good blog post on that Euro site just reiterating
That
Amazon chairs that Euro philosophy about
Captain customer data at having customer Trust
And they say with every new product and feature reveals this is very promising to me
We will adhere to our guiding principles they do explain the three principles which are
You know you have the right to privacy
They need to be transparent with potatoes are collecting
They only collect Network diagnostic information improve performance at such
And they try to actively minimizing outdated a access
M&a to access your data they treated with the utmost security so
I mean that's a very positive thing of it
High-level high mean
But it's it should be a good people on Pacific
We can link back to it
Two years without
So that's just my cynical
I'm so sorry
But we can take this full circle
Because
Cheetah habitat about Charter and their device management Security Services Amazon's actually building this to
With 0 they are helping you
Manage Wi-Fi in your house
Kevin definitely sees it
We're going to have
Amazon devices that
Double is Wi-Fi routers and then hero also has
A security service
Basically the industry believes that we will need
Awesome WiFi
They're working on that and
Wifi based switch
Network-based
Along with a very easy way to set it all up
And I agree with you
I'm not.
So that
Concludes the news portion of our show let's move onto our
Voicemail
This week's voice mail and the iot podcast hotline is brought to you by Schlage
Legs wide variety of smart locks let you create the smart home of your dreams
Learn more about Schlage Smart Home Solutions and compatibility with
Amazon and Apple products
Siri
Google Assistant
And more at schlage.com
Slash bio
And y'all last week I said we were going to give away a Schlage and code lock
We're not we are going to give away a normal
Schlage Z-Wave
Or zigbee
Net
So please
Don't hate me
Still sending voicemails
It is a beautiful awesome lock
Honestly
I haven't even tried to encode yet and I'm still alive
Waiting to try it so I can see if it
Really last
Very long.
So
To enter to win this
Particular lock give us a call in the iot podcast hotline at 5 1/2
742 4
And you will automatically be
Be entered to win
We will
Close this drawing out at 31st of March at midnight Eastern
So get your voicemail in before that
And maybe we will answer it on the show
And this week's voicemail is
Kyle
Hey guys
You can place on the show at a question about
Outdoor cameras Arlo wireless camera
The eye
Put outside for my patio and I install outdoor outlet just for it I'd like to be able to switch it on and off
Can I get you a smart
Switch to my SmartThings Hub so I can hard reset
Stopping to get a lighter
We'll have a hard time finding
A Z-Wave plug that will stay inside like a waterfall
Does Outlet out there and I'm trying to figure out what my best solution is
Or maybe something that since its usb-powered
Outlets like a Z-Wave USB
Thank you guys okay Kyle
I have really
One product
For you
That makes it easy it does make it easier to quit voicemail
So
I have these fabulous Z-Wave Outlet plugs and I've had them for years all around my house that using for my Halloween Christmas and any other random
Outdoor decorations
Want to use it for
They are made by Jasco
There's actually a version of this on Amazon it's got the Chasco 45 704 and it's about
$28
Which is an awesome deal
Jessica was the company that makes
The same product for both Honeywell and GE
But GE
He has their product which is the GE and Brighton
Z-Wave plus outdoor smart plug switch
That sells for 40 to 50
I Amazon
And then Honeywell also has a Honeywell Z-Wave plus outdoor on off
Like an appliance switch for $40
So
You have the same product
Couple different prices
The downside of this product is
It is not IP
Faded
It is rated for a UL standard
Because it's pul
To get that standard I have
How to pay the UL to see the whole
It is water resistant
Basically
It is not water
So
I would not plug this in
A place that
You know it's going to be
Sitting in a puddle
Immersed in rain
But I have had it outside during the winter holiday season
And every now and then I do have to reset
I have to admit my GF eyes
Click on and I have to reset those but
It's pretty good
I wonder if using that plug will
Get your over most of the hump here for a from a water-resistant standpoint but maybe some kind of
External cover over it
Derek help do the trick
I mean I keep mine on my balcony so it's covered
Anyway
I have another one outside
I'm on the wall in
Don't think that's covered
And I have it
I mean also be smart like I plug it in and it's facing down
It is very rugged
It is not a wimpy plug
So basically if water doesn't get into the outlet
You're fine
Sometimes I wrap it with Saran Wrap
Can help
They may not look
The prettiest in this is not at this is a big chunky plug
But that is really
Option we found for you and then
The only other thing we could think of
Is someone left
Voicemail a couple months back where they use an
Outdoor rated
USB charger for
Your phone
What is a skull cap
I got power pack
The power pack
Why am I blinking other name
What's basically a portable battery that you would use to charge your phone on the go but they repurposed at 4
Charging a webcams article correctly
Get up there it's similar situation
So they just
Charge that in
Brought a cord down and they just plug it right into that
Recharge it
Golang
Recharge the power pack in the
Do it as needed so that's another option for you
That might work
Good luck with your wyzecam
And
Good luck with
This particular project
Okay
I feel
Like it is time
For us to go and visit the magical bars of
Austin
We will take you
To the yonomi offices because you know me did
Have me in two Hostess panel
Where
It is South by Southwest
We are having a really in-depth conversation
About data
Privacy and what's going right and what's going wrong
With a smart home
Stay tuned for that
After a message
Sponsor. We are taking a quick break from the air
Internet of Things podcast for a message from our sponsor
This week sponsor is a pharaoh and we are back with Joe Britt the CEO of a pharaoh
Last week we talked about the work if arrow is doing with Mitsubishi
And the Pharaohs effort to create a horizontal payment
So Jo do you mind reminding our listeners what it is
As you mentioned a pharaoh provides an iot platform that
Simplifies how you connect really anything
To the internet we can help you build a business case and take you all the way through roll out and ongoing management as well as data analyst
Customers tell us that
Pharaoh is the best choice
Experience and developer productivity
A beautiful design
Easy to use
Very fast
Very very
Secure
So a lot of customers decide that
Instead of going to an outside platform they want to build their own hardware and software to connect your devices
But why should customers use a platform instead
Let me answer that from two different perspective
Well every customer and every device is different there's a lot that's in common
In iot
Overtime that commonality
Becomes better understood
Better automated
Better integrated
It's what you end up with is actually a platform
And it becomes its own product
What analogy
Is the operating system on a computer and the apps that run on it
In the early days
We didn't have a break
Didn't have compilers libraries debugger
All the modern soft
Accelerate
Development in people had to either write applications to run on the hardware Direct
Go ahead to build their own topper
Application
The same sort of thing is happening
It's more complex
Because it's
It's a different environment that the software is running
That's much more varied
Even harder to build your own
And even if you do it's really hard to keep it portable hard to keep it reliable hard.
Maintain and enhance
And it's something that you have to do from one project
To another
We really think that the time has come for it to have its own proper platform layer
And of course
We on our customers think a pharaoh is
The best iot platform out there
All right and what is the second perspective
II
Perspective
Is from going over all the questions that we need to ask
For an iot project actually starts
Let me hear the top three the first one and this is critical
Is onboarding
Can the users phone make a fast and reliable connection with the device they want to control
With a pharaoh
Simple QR code scan is all at
Next point is
Scale
Can the system scale to meet The Man Without loss of quality
Today if there'll has hundreds of thousands of
The devices in
The field and the service is designed
Descale far beyond that I'd like to share is around security is the whole process secure
Immune to Fleet scale attack
Afero provides a VPN like tunnel for your devices
Regardless of how they connect
And the list goes on but
Most customers find it very costly and time-consuming
To assemble the teams and skills necessary
To build a system
They can successfully address all of
Excellent
Please remind us where we should go to get more information about a pharaoh
Apeiro. IO
/ Go - big is
The best place to start
If you're a developer also check out developer. Of pharaoh. IO and
You might also want to take a look at all the other resources that we have on a Vera. IO
I am Stacy Higginbotham I have a show called
The Internet of Things podcast
And a newsletter called
Stacy
On iot
That's actually my website to
So that's my Shameless self
Promotion
And now
We're going to have them
Shamelessly soft
Tencent
Let's start
With
Alright how everyone
My name is Darren Hobbs I work for a company called tendril
We're on the director of product
And we work with utility companies to help their customers be a little more energy-efficient either through small behavioral nudges
Or by connecting to Smart devices in the home
Pretty good
My name is Tim Hunter I work with a gummy called Dallas
And Ellis is a company that is focused on helping more people around the world
Bmore well
In places where they live
Play and sleep
Name Sanders around corporate Venture for iRobot where the world's largest consumer robotics company
Ally makes a Roomba with an around about 27 years
My name is Dan Davis I work for a company called LexisNexis
Risk Solutions
We Supply the insurance Market with data in
Predict Predictive Analytics
I'm responsible for product strategy around connected home
Connected life and connected
Commercial
Hi my name is Mark Reimer work for a company called Charter Communications under the Spectrum brand
And I lie connected home and home security products
Awesome alright
So one of the challenges with the smart home I feel is
Everything's really expensive and a lot of us we
Don't
The mainstream consumer many of us are probably tinkering nerds who love to play with stuff
But for the normal people
It can be really hard to understand why you might want something
Disconnected and talks back to the internet
Lord only knows
So I would like to ask each of you
For a time that
Smart devices
Procedure life
Or just
Made it better
So the first thing that came to mind for me was my smart thermostat
I have an ecobee and whenever we go on vacation my husband I like to travel at we'd totally forget to program
Thermostat into away mode
Turn off at the gate every time we're opening up the app and we're setting a thermostat on vacation mode
Which keeps are kitties happy at home
But we don't use too much power either
So I've been doing this for 25 years so
There's a lot of pain I have to get past
Come up with an answer
I think that
For me
The value that I can we actually helps me
Is when it brings information that
Affects me
And specifically I mean such as about turning the light on her off lips
Methadone
Just a minor thing it's about
Maybe knowing the pollutants that are in my house
I think that is something to me this importance of an air sensor
And in technology like that they can help me be more aware
The hidden things that are going on that I don't know about
So I could shamelessly self-promote but
Was told not to do that
You right now
So I'm not going to say my Roomba
But
Exactly you're onto me
My camera is so I have two little ones at home I have a 7 month old and a three-year-old and
Last night for example I put my three-year-old down and I
Went out and took the dog for a walk and I get a notice
Application on my phone
Of movement
And as far as I knew she was
Completely asleep
Open up the app
Can I look at the camera
And she is sitting on her potty in her room
With the book
Reading it like a newspaper
Until I
Set my my wife attacks and said you should probably go in and
Take take care of
So that's a learned behavior
Yes
That's right
So I have I have two teenage boys at home
16 + 13
And if you have teenage
Boys in your house then you know that they don't know how to close
They don't know how to close garage door
And they don't know how to lock
Front doors
And so
Things that I'm sure have saved my life are
Smart garage door openers and sensors and
Certainly a Smart Lock
On the front door
Don't have the 2 a.m. oh my God is the garage door
That's a good one
First thing that comes to mind for me as my smart irrigation controller
Cuz I have an automation that says if anyone's walking around my backyard after Dark
Like 10 11 12 midnight
Turn on the water
Spray-on recorded send the video to me
So
I've yet to catch someone but I'm waiting for that day all uploaded to Twitter as soon as it happens
That's it that's the kind of automation you're like
Come on
I can't win it happens I want you to call and we'll
Will put it up on the web
Cuz I think we'd all like to
All right
What I'm noticing is
That a lot of these things
AR
They're not smart
Their automations there one off
Did they don't work together in
I think that's
Kind of been the issue that a lot of people have when we're trying to talk about this
And
Alexa Smart Home in the people who like okay yeah and then
PetSmart
I really wanted it to
Two Lakes
Assist me somehow in my life
You know I'm I'm thinking about the devices that really make a difference in my life
Those that do are super smart
And they have a i
And they're using their data for
Mybatis
So then the question I have for you guys
Cuz of the consumer that's what I want
I want my life to be
Easier
For the most part
So
Why do businesses want to sell us
That's what is
What is your goal in
Getting us to buy bezoar
Building this
Am I can start for that one
You know in the case of tendrils
We work with utility come
And so
We've been figuring out how to fine-tune the messages for consumers we know for some folks it's about being a little bit more green
That doesn't resonate with everybody it could be about
Call protect me from a high bill
Help me from being surprised but I bill before it's too late or something similar
Are you at the club
That's what you want to think about energy that much that's one of the big takeaways is you know a lot of us in this room might be energy nerds or Gadget
Nerds but that's not the general population it's
How can we make it happen behind the
So the customer gets the best outcome they're comfortable and they're happy with
Do you know using green energy or spending my son their bill but they don't have to work any harder
The device.
So
I want to address the
The question directly
What's the motivation behind people that are building products
Putting me out there
Motivation
Is they want to make money becomes
Successful in any other things
I think that the peace that they miss
And that only very few get is it really is
About the experience and experience has to be
Expression freeze pasta
You mentioned earlier you said these
The smart switches any smart lights these are these are expensive
When will you think about expense
Don't you stop at the Dollar
Think about the time it takes for that to be put in think about the prostration
When that pickle technology from company a doesn't work the way it's supposed to
Especially when you find out the product from company a doesn't work
Maybe
There's a lot of the challenges there that when we talk about the cost
A bad experience
We really
In general the industry doesn't really think about
That full-on cost
And if it's there
And I think that we need to do a better job of doing that
Sopra my motivation perspective I think the motivation should be to create relationship with customers or Everlasting
And
You got to do that by respecting the customers and their time
I think they think we change that model
Might get some
Brighten Hans I want to tweak it just a little
Are you guys
Specifically
IRobot wants to sell me
Robotic vacuums
Lawn mowers at whatever
Karina Washington
But
Why
Connect it
What is the real
Russ and end
The room has been around since 2002
So in the world of the smart home that's it
The pit of a dinosaur
And it took us a while for us to connect our products because the devalue you meet the reason to
To do so is not immediately clear
What did viking finally convinced the company to do so was it came down to Mission completion so
Having a connected product for us
Especially one with that has a vision enabled
Navigation system like the last few iterations of the Roomba
Enabled us to have
A higher Mission completion rate
Right so
Roomba is leaving the dock
It's cleaning the room the area was supposed to and it's coming back
And it's now sending a signal saying we're done
We didn't have the ability to do that.
Long time and end and it's
Because it's connected it can get itself out of certain situations and so is a higher there's a higher Mission completion rate
Great for us and that's
The ultimate goal from our perspective is its
Happiness in
Convenience for the for the cost
Yasso
My company doesn't make devices
And our customers
Are insurance companies they don't make
SmartThings
Right but
Overtime the bet in the insurance business
This is that
Your data
Is going to help your insurance company
Understand how you live in your home
In the same way that an auto telematics insurance companies are learning
How you drive in your car
And
That
In an auto telematics that has led to
Discounting
Across-the-board there's not an insurance company that
Surcharges
For your telematics
So the same thing
Is going to be made in
Home telematic
If you will near-term though
Insurance companies believe it or not
Want to
Engage
With their customers
In an interesting and different way than they ever had
So they don't really want to lead with a
The data strategy they want to lead with a
I've got a consumer that's connected to me
In a different way
What can I tell them about their home that they don't already know or what can I tell them about how they're living in their home
That might affect
How they live how they maintain their home in overtime
Are there in
So as an internet service provider we don't make her cell connected devices
But will you get the phone calls when those connected devices are hard to get on the network
Or when they're installed in places that don't have good coverage like outside of your house or in your garage or
By your circuit breaker
So what we want to do is simplify that onboarding by working with different partners and two
Different standards and make that really really easy and provide connectivity everywhere
Just sew it
What's a better consumer experience we're not going to monetize that are charged for it is just part of
A great connectivity experience
So that's really what we're
We're looking to do
All right
In one of the topics that we
Constantly here is
Data so the insurance are like hay
We can get data and then maybe
We can
Lower your premium
Yay
In an energy
Data. My energy use
Yay
And my robots example data about the layout of my home so you can avoid getting
I'm stuck in the same spot every time
So these all sound good
But it feels like
We are not there yet in for the last
I would say four or five years we've been talking about how all of this data is going to come in and
Be magical for me as a consumer but also do something amazing for your bottom line and
I just saw a survey actually that within 5 years
Certain percentage of corporate Executives and I was really high was like
70-something percent believe that data is going to be as a line item on
Their accounting sheet
It's like
Vodafone survey if you guys are looking
So
So what's holding us back from turning this
Cold hard data into Cold Hard Cash
I think
That's so I'll I'll answer as a consumer of these things
And as of
An industry professional
I think that we lack
A
Clear and compelling value proposition
I'm across most of the things that we have
The SmartThings in my house I have because they're cool
Write in
They give me something to talk to my 16 year old
TT kit about right and
I'm also I think they're going to help me at some point
But
Even still as you said we I have SmartThings but my house
It's still pretty dumb
So I think in the absence of a really clear really compelling
Value proposition it's going to be hard to realize
Of the true value of the data
Commercial
I would I would actually answer this a little differently
I would think that it's not Nestle data they wanted contacts
Xbone
And I would say that what context is a picture
And if you think about a picture any picture look at any picture you look at
Text made by Sears a pixel
And we don't have enough pixels degree pictures
When we talk about the date of this coming
Often it's a lot of repeated data over time
And it data actually dies on the line it's 99% of that data is actually useless
The moment we look at it and it and we're looking at Trend at so we may see 5 data points
Not a lot of pixels
That's just a little bit of motion of Noise Within an environment
Not only do we have to have a pixel
We're going to be able to rain some correctly to create the picture
So we got a long way to go before
The data
Nnic Longway
Enable
Way to think about
How fast things are moving
Stop that one
But
Because
We don't
Have those pixels because we don't have that context
The day that doesn't have value yet
But that's changing
There's more more things coming online
Yeah I mean I I generally agree with that but I would we do have the pixels mean a lot there's lots of
Example of the cameras
Is lots of cameras ISP cameras
Rocky cameras I'm sorry are extremely popular
They're everywhere
But but what to do with them that the context dit-dit-dit is captured in that stream
Is lost
It's right and it's so it's in his lots of things you need to know it's what's in this picture
What's going on what time of day is it
What's all the things that you need to do that we do
Naturally
Right watching my daughter and my son
Learn things right it's it's it's amazing to watch a child
And how they learn and how complex that process is
We're not there yet in terms of the technology in My Mind
To do that I do think it's coming in
Tappening
In our case
Being able to map the room yes the primary reason is to complete the mission
But now it's we can understand at least the spatial understand spatial
Context of that home
The size of that home
Even what particular rooms are
That's a layer of information that does add up to that
So I will uplift that back to you and say I agree with you
At the local level
You're solving a problem locally to the home and the humans are closest to that Kant
So they can actually fill in some gaps
That you wouldn't be able to
You can mention the word
We know when you're doing this and you're doing that and you're doing the other thing
That to me is scary
I like that Humanity's doing this we are doing this
Not necessarily that individual data
Cuz of that individual data
Has its own challenges of how it's being used because
In Europe gdpr the general data protection regulation has changed the relationship
Between the data the people have and the people who are trying to take your data from them
In California the California consumer protection act
It's a trend that's making it so that I own the day that you can't take the dative
And if you do there's some
Sarcastic
Work out well
I would agree with you
Debt from a local
Perspective but when you talk about the industry
And you guys haven't seen the bottom line at the Enterprise level
No it's a much higher view that you got to get and you got to get a lot more generalized 804
Personalization is
What makes it useful to
Consumers
And so utilities have actually been struggling with this for a long time they've been upgrading their meters
Two Smart Meters show instead of rolling the truck
Once every 30 days and taking a read They're not reading it every 15 minutes and they struggled
To prove value to the
About why it's worthwhile to roll these
Things out
And so they start with just sharing the data with
The customer says
Great I used 5 kilowatt-hours last
Tuesday between 2 and 3 p.m.
What is that
Is that good is that bad
What should I do with this information
Let the bass line but then what you have to do is personalizing
Experience for
To point out an abnormality
You're using more than similar home there we noticed an unusual P class Tuesday there might be something going on
With your air conditioning unit for example until you have to bring it that
Personal level
I'm in order to provide.
There is a trend right now
In the home space for local control in local understanding
And also not sharing your data
Beyond certain
Parties
So there's that's one trend
But at the same time there's is completely different red where we're like looks like everything I took Google and Alexa
Without
People seeming to realize that
When they do that they're actually sharing the data that they were worried about in the first
I would love for you guys to talk about
How to communicate with consumers
What's actually happening
Do we think it's even reasonable are possible or even valuable for consumers to actually own their data as it were
I'm very curious
So Stacy and I were talking about a little bit about this earlier I always come back to the example where 5 years ago
Samsung put microphones in its TVs and it CNET did a pig piece on it and it was this big uproar
Meanwhile Alexa had actually launched
A couple months ago
Before that happened
No one knew what it was yet
No one cares
Six months to a year later
They're selling while the time it will now millions of these things
And no one seems to care at all and the reason for that is because people got a basic utility out of
What's the device right
People were worried about Samsung it was less
I do think that it was over there's a microphone in my house now
The clearly people got over that when they knew they could set a timer listen to music
So
I do think that there is a certain amount of this that comes back to just what is the utility that the consumed that the customer is getting
But they're also now is it big transparency problem
Where it it could be abused it is being abused we seen it
And I think everyone has to be a little bit more transparent with the user
About that
That's a very Company by company
Right very specific we're not going to sell
Your data
You at we have a map of your home
It lives on that robot
It's not going anywhere
We met
Tell someone
There's something called the kitchen because you may want to be able to turn the lights on your kitchen with Alexa
But that's all it would know
Is that there is a kitchen
Yeah I agree I think it's all about giving consumers
And then letting them decide and if they choose that they don't want that data shared make it very easy for them to
Delete that data everywhere that it's been stored
And make it really clear is this date a live on the device or does it also live in some other system
I think I don't know if that's the full prescription of had it like label what the date is but I think
Is it local or is it cloud and then make it very easy to see it in
Delete it
So how are we doing it that today we're late scale of 1 to 10 1 being
Facebook Cambridge analytica we are
Tell Amazon or turning on your light in the following groups and
And also the color scale
I think that my answer to this is that we are very low in that scale
And I wanted to interject because I needed that
Follow up
I think I have to agree with you that it's a cost versus value relationship that were trying to evaluate but I think that
Human beings
Are are very much driven by whatever
Their needs are at the time
And
We'll see like said we we have very short memories with the guard
The different things that have
So you'll see this idea and then there's a there's a
Concept that we have
On the coast
Dick in any technology that people care about the privacy of their data
And sometimes I think that maybe that is something that we
Archie holding ourselves because we know what's under the covers
Other people are like
So what they don't want McDonald's think they got my GPS on my phone that helps me get around
Tell him make that
Relationship of the value of the cost.
I agree just to kind of blend the two
The two topics
I think you mentioned
Some of the emerging standards gdpr
We we need that
Or we need some of those principles
And we're a long ways
From where we need to be
I think
Consistently reminding consumers that you shared your data
For this reason
Is is going to be something that has to happen in it and it doesn't happen today
But I think we also have to harken back to
2D value proposition
If I share my
Fitbit data with my
Gym because they give me
50% off of my monthly fee
I don't have to be reminded of that
I get it
Right
And so what's the story
Answer your question we're not doing a good job today
We
The debate we
But I am optimistic about
I think we're technically checking the boxes just buried in terms and
Mission but nobody read yes
Yeah
And so it's about how do you
Either directly Tire
Add to Value so customers understand or just say it in plain English or show them the same data that you have access
Text you that you're sharing and
How to draw the connection
Here's what we have
Here's what we're using it for here's where you can get a chain
So there's a user experience
Add another layer
Honest
And that is
We're talking about Jada like my actual I turn this light bulb on
But let's take it up a notch to inference so let's
Now we're all talking about AI it's very exciting
Now you might say oh
When someone turns their light on
At 3 a.m.
Consistently
They probably have insomnia which is associated with
I'm going to make this up heart attack
And us there a terrible risk for
A health insurance company and then suddenly
We're looking at
In this is this is
Morris
People's fear when they start looking at me like I do not want the naked pictures of me
Turn my video camera on the web which is totally understandable you
But there's also potential for economic
Harm
Coming for this and I'm curious
What your take is on that I don't think we're there yet but
There's a real fear that we get going
Hollywood Center really good job of scaring us on the sleeves top
If you eat some of these movies I even for the last 20 years it's like
Oldest person has this terrible diseases person has been diagnosed with AIDS for example back in the
There's a movie it was one of the the
It's like
I think the movie was one of the Harrison Ford movies where he was
And idea was
That guy was being black
And I think that's where it comes to
It's not about your data
Actually being used
In the way that you intended to
It's about as being lost
Controller
Gdpr trying to help
Making sure that the people are responsible your good Steward with data
The attendance of that are you have the right to be forgotten
You can wipe anytime you want do you have the right to
Opt-out you have
You have more rights than you used to have in control of that data
And the companies that actually on that dead and now there's there's teeth in that because they can be fine
That's what was
The missing piece
Is as far as the energy goes it really does take
For some degree some negative impact
There's a lot less products out there if you've ever noticed now that you can bring up
And they have password is a default password
When you turn them on
The reason is because the industry took a shot
About two years ago from something called Mariah
That biscuit was looking at all the photos you were out there
End
Everybody said we can't be bondable anymore so we got to ship a product that actually has
Some level of security built into it so you're not
A victim as soon as you plug the darn thing internet
The clothes on that I think that the whole point of that is
The data itself
And the stewardship of that data
From when the
Either take it from you
Or you share it with them
And how that that is actually
Managed in life cycle is extremely important we don't spend enough
Time talking about that
Yeah that's right I agree I think
Take that
When we think about who owns today that which is
The recurring question that comes up
The consumer has to own it
And you know your analogy of the
3 a.m. wake up
Hits home with us because
We support the life insurance pays
And sleep is a really big indicator of
Mortality
Right and so
We have to be super responsible are guiding principles have to begin with
Value to the consumer and privacy
And of course data ownership
And
They have to know what that's being used for and it has to be in their control to change it
Do you foresee that happening where my smart home data
Starts affecting and I know you said nobody gives you surcharge
Associated with
Your data but do you see that
Helping establish new Actuarial tables
Pause and
Changing the way people pay for their life insurance based on or health insurance based on their active
Yeah I think so
So I don't support the health insurance pays that gets really itchy and
There's a thing called Head Moen
So that's it that's an independent business but
Life I think so home I think so because
You know we live in our homes in a very unique way
And
In a world where we all sort of
Hunger for cheaper insurance rates Home Auto
Life commercial what have you
If there is a compelling story
Actuarial
Story
Around how you live in your home and what that means
To the
The premium you pay
Then
I think it's going to matter
I think it's going to take time this isn't next year this might not even be 5 years from now
Right but
There is a story to tell and I think it's even broader than
Just your connected home
Your connected car is
Is actively interacting with
With your home
And with your Fitbit
And
Those are threaded together
Paint
A vivid three-dimensional picture of who you are as an insurance risk
Right but that's how we have to be thinking about this as sort of
Data and insurance vision
You're scared to death
This is it from Meijer to paper in my sink
To test smoke alarm
So I can tell you my insurer is going to be like oh no
No
I saw a compelling demonstration at CES of a company
It did something very simple
They put motion sensors
In the major areas if it one of the better in the Twin the living room all the world in motion sense
And over a period of two months
They plotted the motion
In the spaces overtime
And there's for example a very clear indication when you have an ulcer
Somebody approaching Alzheimer
Because
They're up in the middle of the night
And because they're randomly going from room to room
Something you wouldn't know without being a measure that
But you take that back around 2
The things that you're doing from from the insurance of the home because
Now you have a
A challenge to the safety of the home
Now you have a challenge to the health of the individual
It's a very real
And you can do it without invading the Privacy you don't have to have cameras focus on everything is there
You just have to intelligently
Look at the the cause and effect
Of different conditions that you want to
Who do you tell that I have all time
Haven't told anybody yet
Alright let's talk about
When we buy the stuff cuz you mentioned terms and conditions and how they're not awesome
I thought those were not your exact
What I'm saying
So
What are some ways we can do to communicate with people who are busy and who did not I mean we all know that no one's going to read this.
How they've been talked about nutrition labels for data but
What are some ideas that are percolating in your industry about how to talk to people in create these value prop
Positions and how we talk
And use about
Use your data
It could be as simple as if you have some sort of
App for email that goes out to customers
Use your smart
Tobias
You show them the data that they have
And then you give them some useful information about it some sort of inside that they wouldn't have already
That they wouldn't have gotten without this device in their home
So for example
Maybe how they use energy across the course of the day or what their average set point is and how it compares to
Dissimilar homes
And in just plain English say you know this is how we know this this is what we do with your data and here's where you can
I agree with that I think it's still in the context
Best of
Or tying it the some way to
Back to the value back to the
Ikea is an example of the things that we're doing with this
You mentioned I think you know repeating
Repeating at some Cadence in a
Relatively
Friendly kind way that this might be something that you're doing with it and just and just that just just reminding them of that
My remote might give me like an outline of my house or something
A map of my house
Yeah no absolutely right and end and I get the kitchen example that I that I mentioned right the newest Roomba
Does do that
For you and you can
It will
In the app you will see a layout of whatever space that it was clean it will then
Start a label those rooms you have the power to label those rooms
It just simple things like that
Right and we're getting there to the point where the context up well if it's
The kitchen we know that we should probably clean that more often because that's where there's more messes
Where the kids are in the kids room or the playroom or whatever it is and just those little nudges
At the same time or just building credibility
Right it's a it's really a credibility thing in the transparency
I think in addition to showing what data is being collected I think it should be required in the technical
Full specs the list
All of the data collection abilities you have so if you build a microphone in your product you have to list there's a microphone
Warren air quality sensor every sensor that collects data
I've listened to and here's the type of data it collects
Yeah we didn't we talk about this
Sephora but I think it gets did to those sort of when your
Actually making physical product
Chrissy mention this on your pocket
I'll plug your
Italy it if you're creating physical devices in the home
This has to start even if it's a software device that is software product
This has to start
It has to be a basic Foundation of basic building block
Of the concept development process in the product development process
Cuz if it's not
That is never going to happen
Regulation
You could step in but we need to be better than
As I mentioned we work with Wellness
We work at Mayo Clinic the Cleveland Clinic with a lot of medical experts and weed
Are in the commercial and unplugging
Al commercial Hospitality in the resident
Sector there's a lot of data to be gathered
So I think that the
Way to think about this is is to change the storage
Just a little bit from us
Mentality
Imagine
But I'm not just sharing my data
Imagine that there's somebody
That is an employee of mine in Henrietta off to them
What would I expect of them
Brexit to give the data and then run and go do stuff with it and then just tell me you're going to give it to me
I'm gone
Now we expect to have reports back
How that data is actually doing good
How the date is actually being used
Soaked to the point of yeah this will do this
No no
This is also doing
I think that's the big piece that's missing is
How that data is actually transforming other people's lives
There's a there's a big opportunity for that transparency to carry through the life cycle of a
I want to ask you
Again
Where are we on the spectrum of actually
Communicating this back to the
Customer
In
Creating dispositive
Feedback loop where would we have this
You're getting this out of it
I would say even in creating music.
Everyone I talked to has this great
Warm and fuzzy Vision but
Really the only thing I hear about is like how Facebook's using my stuff to like sell ads delay
Nazis are
That's pretty scary
I think that
Turd for my company we struggle because
People don't care that much about energy
Great at the end of the day like
If the lights turn on and my bills not too high
It's it's really it's like not a type of
And so
I think we do a pretty good job communicating everything that's available it's just how do you engage customers on those
As meaningful insights that we derive from the data so they understand why it matters and we're not just
Chain for Dontae
Exactly
Exactly so we work with utilities who
Have incentives to either reduce
System and overall or pull it out of certain high peak times to pray
Prevent blackouts herb
Firing up at Peak planners
Something like that so there is a massive
Impact to the world for us doing this just had to get customers to care
And make it a compelling value proposition
Searching for them
Individual a so much so that they'll opt into the program
Because usually the the feel-good message that it's good for the world isn't enough for somebody to sign
There's a sensitive data point that we all carry around with us today
That existed long before smarthome that's our credit score
And
We all I think
Hold our credit score near and dear to us
And we guard it we want to know if and when and how it's used
But we don't always know if and when and how it's used
But
It's governed in a
Very rigorous way
And I think a way that smart home data should be
And anytime your credit score is used
Bit to make a loan or an insurance transaction or
In your utility
Transaction I don't know if credit scores use
And a decision is made using that using your credit score you have to know about
The
The business that used it has to tell you that they used it you have to give consent
And then if an adverse decision was made
In the use of that
Then a letter has to go out
And you had you have the ability to
Respond to that
So there may be some lessons to be learned
From
That one datapoint that none of us want to give up
Right and
And use
Everyday
Let's
Take a trip
Back in time
And I am curious what you guys many of y'all have been in the industry for a really long time
What would you change or would you change how we're developing
Maybe it's
What would you change your how would you like to see an idealized rollout
At the smart home and like how we talk about the stuff at
Communicated
What's your I can jump in
So I think
Standard
Protocol
So that third-party apps who want to talk to all these devices have a standard integration
Mission paw
If I could go back in time that's what I would ask for
Because we integrate with
All the different thermostat
And all of them have did
Different apis
But have different levels of control
That change from time to time and it's
You know a full-time job just to keep up with all that stuff
Princess and standardization
I know
It's created opportunity
Brothers 2
Yeah I mean it and I guess the question I have is this how much of this is a wish list a true wish list right cuz I I completely agree but without
Getting into the details of
The prisoner's dilemma another
Game Theory like there's a lot of reasons why that didn't happen and
And why that also enabled us to get to where we are
Right even though it is messy and
Manassas technology
Write it it it it
It rarely ends up rolling out in a very clean
Way initially and it takes longer than you expect
But when it does arrive
It usually
Write the meaning
Progress is progress
I would say if we went back in time
To all Implement security by Design
So implement
The online security from the very beginning so we don't have all these data
I still worried that if we don't get her act together people
Will just get turned off to the whole technology
So we really need to address that
So
I think that it all starts in the education system
I think personally we jump the shark
When a company put a product in and labeled it programmable thermostat and put it in the shelves of the mass mark
Stores
That's not the value proposition of the
Consumer
So if we took the engineering guys and we force them
To learn about consumer experience and N2 understand
That's the most important thing and you need to go backwards from that
If we gave them jobs 101c Jazz 101 Smule Theory there
I think that might change
That the relationship between people and Technology
That
Today
Nanotechnology
6 way down here
Fundamentally and people
Bose speaker
We're Bridging the Gap a little bit never falling back and then I think that we just
How to divide between the
People that are making the technology
And the people that are using the
To be fair the guy that created the nest was a Steve Jobs disciple
Toni wasn't quite a disciple
Cannabis
All right everybody
Please big round of applause for us
And a big thank you to our sponsors and hosts
Thank you this is great discussion preciate everybody coming for the sand
I am sure these payments are going to hang around for a while if you want to
Interact with them
Also in terms of the
The co-host
Just wanna make sure everybody knows that
Their effects from Gentex here raise your hand if you're from Gentex
Perhaps you saw their only connect them over here which is really amazing what's a good
Example of something really useful to use
4 home control
Some of you may know resideo to the
Residential alarm
What was Honeywell
Is moving headquarters in the process of moving their headquarters to Austin
How much is awesome
Also Schlage
Is here Devin from Schlage
He is here and all the
Noemi says we call them from you know me
Raise your hands
Is a few of us here
So if you want to interact with any of these people or any of the sponsors
Bars going to be open for a while
Make yourself at home
And feel free to hang out and chat thanks again
To a really outstanding panel
Thanks
That's it for this week thanks so much for listening and remember if you'd like more iot news
Sign up for my newsletter and Stacey on iot. Cam will see you next week