Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house
Stacey Higginbotham and York
Kevin tofel
We have a jam-packed show for you today
Major test news
We've got
Really exciting sotos news
Z-Wave is opening up we got a bunch of new products because it is Eva week which means
There's going to be tons and tons of device news we're not going to get all of it
And then we also have a really in-depth an awesome interview from Chris Matthew who is
Over at Citrix
And his built
Gillian connected products
We're going to talk about what you need to know
To build and talk about
The products
So let's get it started with Kevin shall we talk about
The most exciting piece of news this week or the most
Rising
Piece of news this week
I don't know which is which but I
I think you want to talk about Nest first all right
Oh I don't know that it is
I don't I mean it is newsy
It is something that's happening I'm going to just real quick to disclose that I do work for Google I do not work with the nest e more smart home
Products
And I have no knowledge of what's going on here
I can't really comment on what's been reported and that's the news
And the news is that Nest is going to move under Google
Which is part of alphabet so Nest was their own
Alphabet company right
Yes they were a separate sub
Subsidiary
Yeah they were young we separate subsidiary but
According to Fortune
The Nest team is going to become part of Google and reporting to Hiroshi lockheimer
Who is in charge of everything Android so that's
That's kind of interesting in and of itself that it's
Going to be according to reports
Mastoid part of
Deandre ayton
Especially with all of the
Grillo
Hasbro Louis Cardinal Android
Fuchsia
There's a lots
Beti I think
And this is just personal opinion obviously
I think this should have happened from day one
I don't think it should have been a separate kind of company cuz I think that's what got it into
Trouble
Right we talked about that many times before
He was kind of autonomous and
And then because it was a separate subsidiary it had to show profits and
So it's kind of like
If Nest loses money
We probably won't know about that
Right
Swell
Okay so that's the question right now they're saying
Software
Which means the hardware division
Is still there
Somewhere
Right there still a what would they be doing without developer
Marwan fawaz
Is running nest and he's got the hardware guys and he's got all that experience with the
Cable companies
Spin selling
Those folks
Now we have
Possibly a hardware division that is stillness
Unless they just totally killed up subsidiary
It's hard to say because right now all we have are the reports of
The Developers
Moving over
So I know that there's
Probably more
Unanswered questions here that in Google hasn't officially commented at all
Break Google no comment from Google
Yeah
Irish at some people later yes or late yesterday but have not heard back from them
Cuz I probably still sleeping
So
We still don't know those things but I think what we
I hope we know
Is a Toby a more cohesive
Platform play here for
The Smart Home
As opposed to having two separate groups now
And that makes sense because what we've seen with like the Amazon Echo for example is that
Smart home plus a personal assistant
Makes sense
And Google
Under alphabet so Google has all the personal assistant uses
And intelligent
So even
Hardware to some degree because it Ayo Google announced the Google home that would it was called to make sure I get it
Right so that's that fix
Portico Amazon Echo type device with the personal assistants
Yeah I seen that says always been this separate Island
I just never understood why
Now
Initially
There was a different Vision playing out for the smart
Please watch this happen
4 Lakeshore
A really long time
The original thought was you would have these connect
Two devices and then without a standards developing we all realize that holy cow that is just crazy talk and now it seems like
Like having some sort of
Easy voice control
Probably other controls around the house 2
Makes a lot more sense
And
To really sell this to Consumers you can't just offer like
You can't just tell them hey that we're going to sell you this personal assistant that could be awesome if you buy a bunch of lightbulbs another stock you got to have it
Provide real value
Right
There's that
I don't know what this means for nest is a hardware company I don't know what it means for all the works with Nest stuff
And those Partnerships because that's
Stupid deal so
Cannon and maybe we'll only have one thread
After all this is said and done as well because do we have
Give me your threads mixed up with your weaves
Is 2 weeks
Do basically the same thing
So yes that's also a
Okay so that's the
Google
Alphabet
Nest
Saga
News I know man
3.2 billion dollars it's like the bottle reality
My goodness
But they're too
Really awesome pieces of news this week
So
Nest fine
What did I call it surprising and
I forgot
I know that you are more
Excited about this
So excited
Samantha
Is the best and or exciting news
If you're facing
If your me
Sonos
My favorite sound system
Launch today pi and it also launched a strategic partnership with the Amazon
With Amazon so
In 2017 you'll be able to
Control
Your Sonos
From your Echo
If I knew you'd be happy when I saw this news
Yes and they build some great commands like
What song is playing
Play the song
Skip to the next song so there's actually some really
Granular controls that they're building in for this which is pretty cool
So that's that in the meantime Sonos is also opening up an API so it'll work with a lot of other devices as well
This would be cooler I think if
Sonos had Mike's built into their speakers none of my Sonos is have Mike's butt
I still think it's great
Cuz I've always wanted my Sonos to
To be the voice of my home
Apus hard
I could see that change with this
New strategic partnership with Amazon
And it would not surprise me at all if he knew Sonos Hardware at some point in the near future with microphones
Antiques
She Who Shall Not Be Named voice services
Yes
No it's a good guess
Because
It makes total sense
It's kind of sad
And the other thing is Sonos now integrates with control4 Creston Lutron
In Savannah
So all of these bridges are going to let you
Control your Sonos
With some of the controllers for these products which is
Solutran could introduce
A $50 Pico remote for audio
So it's kind of like the ones they use for lighting
And shape control
It'll be used
With their soda
Play pause
So on a rainy day you can say play My Rainy Day mix and close the blinds so I don't have to see the rain today
Yes
How many people sit in the Gloom
Life is good
So I know
You're not excited but you have an event
It's just I went in a different direction
But I know there's a lot of people happy with
Saint Ignatius beso
It is exciting
So the other really exciting piece of news
Oh my God
You guys
Nazi wave
Phillips
I don't want to talk about it
A particular product
BR30 lights
It's in white
And so far you guys were like what did Stacy just say it doesn't
Make any sense these are the downlight so Philips Hue downlight
Have only been in
In color
Austin Peay basketball
And this is made me sad because my house is filled with
KFC
Can light space
And $60 bulb is crazy
So now
Phillips
White ones
And they are
They're still
I was going to say 40 bucks
Yeah I mean you could use your
Phillips
And change the color to light
Okay
Yes but why would I spend
$60 on it
Color bulb
Did not used
Because you like to play disco music and have different color lights.
That is true
That is why I didn't answer your question now the rest of the world though you're right
People would rather stay
10:40 or less
I just have white are they
I'm assuming they're tunable they are
Yeah I'm happy about that I like to in football
Yes and if you're like
Stacy $40 is
I still way too much
That's okay
Your
Let's see I've got currently running the GE light Link that are $15 they're running in my house you can also run the
Osram lightify
I think those are a 30 box
Those are running on my Philips Hue
In my house
And
So you don't actually have to go with the Philips Hue but you know if you were holding out for this because
Cuz
Give me
Then actually I haven't been holding out that
Checkpoint I was like
Yeah I got it I got to put lights in my kitchen
So yeah so I'm excited about that
Two pieces of exciting
Is my Sonos is
Going to get way more useful
And my Philips lights
In October
I can buy them
Okay now we're going to skip away from Phillips
We'll come back to it and talk about
Z-Wave
A radio
For the connected home
Is opening up
And
What this means
Is that they are going
You no longer have to
To buy access
The software the firmware for a Z-Wave radio
The Z-Wave radio is actually been a standard under the eye to you for about 4 years
And two companies
Sigma in
I was going to call at Mitsubishi but it's mitsumi
Z-Wave chips
Z-Wave radio chip
Other people haven't really
Glommed onto making them because you still had to pay
To get access to the firmware in
That the profiles to make it work
Basically
So what they done here is they open those up so no longer
To pay any money
Make a Z-Wave
Rights you have access to the code you can create your own software
Sea waves
Standards and so on so forth are free so they remove the barrier to entry which is awesome
I don't know what
Used to cost for that I can't imagine it was that expensive
Sunset Bar
It was kind of it so there's two issues the fact that there were only two chipmakers meant the prices for Z-Wave radios
People are like
I don't know if this day was going to
You know it was just
It's hard when you develop a standard
Right you got to open it up
At some point
If you open it up too fast if it's too diluted
Did nothing works if you open it
Too slow
It was a lot of people are like you know what I'm going to try zigbee Yurts dead or if you're nasty like screw it I'm going to develop
Protocol
And they did thread
So
What is Z-Wave products in my house so I'm excited because this makes it a lot easier for things like
Amazon could integrate a Z-Wave radio into the echo for example. Without
Putzing around in a way that maybe it just didn't want to do
So what's good
Z-Wave
So yes good news all around Alyssa
We have
What else do we have the
Bringing it run through
Earthquake news
Yeah well there because if he's going on there until going on today and
For several days after today so we can't cover everything cuz we don't know everything until next week but what do we know today
Well we know a couple things
We know that
Drop the kitchen scale that you bought for your wife and she never used
Stand up with Bosch and what is going to do is it's got a whole vision for the smart kitchen I'm actually going to write about
So awesome
For making hardware and focusing more on making integrated recipes
So
If you got to drop scale and you're running a drop recipe and you can import your recipes into the Drop app
What'll do as it'll read instructions like
Pre-heat your oven to 350 degrees
If you have a connected Bosch oven going forward
It'll automatically do that
That's Nifty Fifty Nifty
This is a very forward-looking
Can you play this is not something
How often do we bite
I think it's
I think it's a really compelling vision
Hope they can make it work.
Because holy cow
Okay
So that's the drop stuff
The LG
LG has a cool fridge they showed off a Tifa
It's got a big
Touch panel look
Something but it's not a touchpad
Instead
If you knock on it it turns translucent
It's pretty cool it's kind of like greyed out like a soda most matches the color of the
The fridge and then if you
Do the knock thing on it and becomes translucent now you can see inside the fridge without opening the door
I think it's kind of neat and I kind of like that better than what I've seen from Samsung with the
Basic with integrated touchscreen tablet in these things
Yeah I think
Much more
Use folded 3lc inside your fridge then to be able to check Twitter
On your fridge
And honestly this is for super high-end this is totally like a
It's kind of like my touch faucet is stiff
People I touch it and it turns on and people that are fancy
Is it that practical the faucet is actually totally
I recommend everyone
Okay
Dishwashers
Amazon Dash is teaming up with Bashi
So
The dash
Fulfillment service
You can now
You're certain
Bosch
And Siemens dishwashers will reorder dish
What are those called
The little candy looking packs that are too little dish detergent sings
So that's going to happen
Let's see
Slim tile
Tile d
Company that makes a
Bluetooth tracker
They have launched a
Really tiny tile
Because the current tile is
I don't know it's about a quarter of an inch thick
And that's just too fat to stick in your wallet
So
They launched one that is now two credit cards thick
And you could pop that puppy in your wallet
You can just makes it easier to stick on the back of a remote
If you want to get up
It was remote the couch all the time
So
That's that
And they will also replace your tires so tile has a replacement service
That
When the battery runs out after a year
You said your old Thailand you get a new tile
If you want
Instead of buying the new tile you can send your old tile in if it's up for replacement and get the new fancy or tile
Thinner and Slimmer which is awesome it is also bigger than the original tile
Yeah it's kinda like they
Tasty
Push down on the original title and stretched it out so it made it almost looks like it's a good
What's a 2-inch by 2-inch Square now just much better
Yes cuz it used to be a 1
To 5
So it is a platter
And large
30 bucks it is $30
If you send it back
If you send your old one back to
Is a temporary placement
You get to buy the new one
For $21
That's it
You can also buy
4 pack 400
Okay
About
I don't think we have time cuz we have such an amazing
Thinking of you and I want to
Stuff that we can hold off for next week
So what time
Our stuff that we're going to come for it
Is Kevin got a new wink relay
Yep installed and I'll talk about next week I got the new Kevo door lock which is a touch to unlock its
Second gen Kevo I got that
And then we got the Philips motion sensor which is what I was telling you about earlier
Not only did they announce these new lights they also put out a motion sensor
And I've been living with that
And I have some real thoughts on
So
Get ready
We're going to have a message from our sponsor
And then we're going to have Chris Matthew who is the VP of iot engineering at Citrix
Who's going to tell you
What you need to know about radios
Pros and cons of using different protocols
And the pros and cons of dip
Clouds
So dense information packed but it's
Really
Good
And I try to save my protocol
Stay tuned
Hey everybody this is Stacy breaking into this week's Internet of Things podcast with a message from our sponsor this
Sponsor is macadamia
Their professional Design Services and Internet of Things solution developer
Company
Building some really cool things
And explain how this happened we have will not
Who is president of RN Sports entertainment
To talk about a product called the fantasy scoreboard
Scoreboards
Is the next innovation
In home
Sports Entertainer
Bringing a piece of the arena or Stadium right into your very own home
With a wifi-enabled
Scoreboard for the NHL you can customize
The scoreboard in your home for your favorite team
And what it does is with the iot
We've got the in-home live update so it's
An actual scoreboard
At what the events are going on at any given Arena across North America for an NHL hockey
Taemin
How did you guys
Help them
So if you know with any connected internet product these days
You need a companion app
So we helped Tennessee scoreboard develop an app that allows you to pick your favorite team
Or if there was a team playing in a specific location that you wanted your scoreboard to show you're at that point in time cuz
Do you have friends over from a different state how you could do that
Of course we also enabled the scoreboard so that if you're playing
Choose ball or ping pong and Anna wanted to control that product entirely through voice interactions alone
That you could do that from your Amazon Echo
So will as he went to build the fantasy scoreboard what did you encounter
How to get the product
Hook up to Wi-Fi
We disassemble another product and found some technology in there with steered Us in the direction of macadamia out for narcotics
Alright so Thailand
What did you guys do to help bring
The fantasy scoreboard
So with any connected product
You need a companion application and
You know Android and iOS prevalence you need to support those platforms
Is cloud conductivity the provides a connection to the NHL servers with the game stats
So there's a connection to the Azure Cloud the connection to the electric in Cloud so that I mentioned earlier lots of moving parts
And you need to work with a partner who's
Confident in these Technologies in the way to pull them all together
And deliver a product like this to Market on time and on budget is bring together for the custom
The customer now has the ability to be able to follow their favorite team's games
On demand
And or any other NHL team that's
Playing on any given night and oddly enough
It is a global solution
I was able to control my scoreboard
Nordstrom Las Vegas
With my scoreboard being in Edmonton Alberta
Designer app
I can select games
No matter where my scoreboard is
And it will follow every game I asked at the phone
And this is what so incredible with the Internet of Things
And what that
Spies in terms of value to Consumers
It's at conductivity that ability to stay connected to devices in your home wrapped around with a + credit
User experience
Is what we're all about and what we're all their building for a client
To learn more about what we do go to www. Macadamia. Com scoreboard
Hey everyone welcome back to the internet
Podcast
This is Stacey Higginbotham and I am back with Chris Matthew
Who is director of
Iot engineering for citrus
He's also a co-founder of the Octo blue plateau
Hey Chris
Thanks for coming on the show today
KCC thanks for having me
So Chris and I go back
Wait
I'm he founded
Before I could lose active Lewis's thing called Skynet
Was all about making like
Everything talks
Everything else
And now that it's October Blue it's still about that
It's just now owned by Citrix
So this week we decided to do something kind of super
It's not super nerdy but it is a little bit
We wanted to give people who were trying to understand who are in the business of building products or maybe managing iot
Products away to think about
The tools that they have available
Because Chris has been doing this for
Courageous
Aegis
Breakdown
What you need to know that internet-of-things Prada
So
Here we
Chris
I want to build
Connected products
What should I even
How should I start what should I think about before I start
Oh my gosh
It's a really wide open
Question him we talked earlier there's so many different
Radio choices
Platform choices protocol choice
You really need to figure out what and its pros and cons
All of them
There's not a silver bullet. That's Donuts
It's heading in the industry so
Okay so if I'm thinking about this
First I've got to decide
A radio
And then maybe a messaging protocol
Maybe a cloud
How to post some place to put it
Are there other things I need to think about what I'm making
I think you've hit the big ones probably battery life
Why is another one cuz you know they all got different capabilities as far as like
How long will that device live do you like beacons are really good for living couple of years
Where is
Wi-Fi device
They're always on not so much right
So we'll talk about that in the pros and cons
We might want to say the brains of the operation so
Is this going to be doing like a hardcore
You know Intel or arm a 9 Kenneth
Brain inside or could we do with the second MCU a microcontroller
Itty bitty
That's another really good question because I'm depending on how much logic I think you want on the edge of the network with the
Depend on how much
How smart that ship needs to be in
Form factor
If you're trying to make something really really small
Now you're definitely talking
Feeling better
Microcontrollers as opposed to being like a Raspberry Pi or something a little bit
Marker bigger
Start with Lodge
Chemical radios and go messaging
Unless we get off track
Which could happen with logic
Just big rules about what's out there
Do I want to buy something like
Do I want to buy my own
Macros
Controller for Mega stmicro or something or do I want to buy a platform like
Yes if you're ever talked about building something right we're going to prototypes
New and exciting that we're going to bring the market
What I usually do they start with something really with a good ecosystem
You're like an Arduino type of a microcontroller from going that route and it's okay if it's big and clumsy with a
Fretboard Yaya prototyping
Keep that in mind
And as you get to thinking I said it works
Successes that works then you can start looking okay
There's a lot of form factor
Just like this Arduino or other
Comprable microsystem devices
And then if you really do need that intelligence
Show processing power
Maybe start with the Raspberry Pi but then again
Tell that the Danube
Shipped the pocket chip
Came out there not too long ago there's a new
Dixon Oasis
Computers are all coming to Market with all various form factors to so
I usually start big with a bigger ecosystem and then work my way Indian once you have that success
Monkey way into
Fine tuning the form factor I think
Okay so that doesn't really change how you're going to architect or anything else
Statues down the road
Not typically need some of it it does like if you get into something
I hate to say proprietary like like maybe the particle. IO
Great ship it comes in like a wife ible and 3G
Aversion what you build with that
Particular product
You will be to speak stuck with that one
Platform was Hugo something a little bit more open like an Arduino Princeton
Then you got a much bigger ecosystem
Okay
Again I know this depends on
Again
But like how should I be thinking about my radio selection
What are kind of the factors at play
I would say
Probably distance
Battery life
Skip
Baby cost
Pernoud I don't know what that's a big deal
And then
Maybe if it measures or not
All of those are very good I came in fact I can't think of another another thing you have to add to that list Wi-Fi you're going to
Pretty good range
Shell's you may be mentioned earlier but then again there's a big drain on the battery
Unless
You do it, the Amazon Dash route where it's it's basically offline
Until you press the button
K'Nex transmission goes back offline
It's a brilliant technique of seeing for giving that Wi-Fi
Distance
But also
Keeping with the battery light that's needed
Seems like the only way you're going to need to be closer
To Harbor something that
Communicating with
So that's something that
Keep in mind and then
Zigbee
There's so many different flavors if you will
That's also something else
Keep in mind that it's not
A Street Fall River protocol is
Doesn't think the industry would like
YouTube to believe
Okay and what about in an industrial setting
What about looking at
Proprietary protocols like I'm trying to think like
Lakers Hart
There's
Old school
Kind of
I want try to think
Modbus yeah
And there again
You're dealing with
There is a legacy
Legacy Center Legacy scada controllers
Yo at the time cereal was the best option
Charlotte events
Technology or those both the hardware components and sensors even so
Tell you you can you definitely need to
Fly
What's right for the environment
Sister to move it forward
Sentences accommodation
Maybe sometimes you might go
You might connect with modbus friends
Install serial device
And then you might convert it
Yeah like websocket store
UT your or something
Something a little bit more
Modern and adaptable and today's I have to suck one
Yes
So now we get into
I just have
I cannot remember it
Anymore but there was a whole set of the whole verse where I just had to
So I'm sad that are a mess
Africa calls
We talked about
Mqtt
Costco app there is XMP
PP
Amqp HTTP websockets DDS
Drawing
So how do we
How are
Give people who are not
Going to ever want to deal with that
A framework for how to say
The world of the web
I like to look at the world of the weather's taught us a lot of things about baby
Maybe the physical world like how we connect
Physical devices
Together and maybe physical devices over the web to other other devices
Tandem your HTTP yeah that was the winning protocol of the web
Websocket
Skim around
Castro said maybe a decade ago
Secreting like live bi-directional
Secure
Real-time communication so I think definitely those two are very interesting even even in the day of
Beauty and coaxial talk about 2
So I definitely don't want to Discount web Technologies or web protocols
Connecting
Seems like it I think that's a very interesting connectivity
But then there's all sorts of these other protocols at
Well they turn around 2 for some of them for a long time as well
Focused on
M2M Machining Machinery iot Communications in mqtt
That's probably that the grandfather
5 in 20 years
It stands for message queue Telemetry transport
And there's lots pros and cons with each of these as we're going to talk through but
Are we the best
Think about this protocol is
You can
Literally message a device that's offline
And when the device
He's back online
There's this concept of quality of service
Britt you can guarantee delivery of a message so in the device
Comes back online it says
It wakes up is he that I miss anything and
African said yeah you missed these three messages and now now you're all caught up
So it's that voice
Yes
So before we go
Before we go any further Chris
I got to tell people
What we're talking about here
With these protocols
Radios are just the physical way for something
Bike Share data
So
These protocols basically tell
The device's what the date is and what things are trying to do is that a fair way to talk about these I just want
How to make sure people understand
Yet most of these protocols do have like
Why refer to the transport layer and then that transports typically like the radio
Like you're right it's like
How do I get this
Text message from here to here and then what is the mess
It's look like inside of that
That's your protocol
So in this messaging layer let's break it down we got Legacy
We sat web and then we've got some of that do we have anything new yeah we do we have new things so let's start with Legacy
What's out there in the Legacy world
That
Still in use today or mites
Still be used
I think in two taquitos Reventon I mean 20 years in the running as an open
Open standard there's a lot of
New iot
Check being built on top of them
It's a very basic outside like a
Publish subscribe messaging platform
So there's other parts of the infrastructure that you need to be concerned about like a
Highly available message
Broker that knows
Mark's basically soap
What delivers a message to check that all saying okay I just delivered that to this guy he's good
I'll let you know when when I have another message
So does that require a lot of logic is part of
The message broker needs to be something that has brains inside
Yeah yeah so it's going to be something that's either going to run in the cloud or you're going to have to
Find messaging broker that small enough to fit on a Raspberry Pi 4
Incipere building
Encompassing
Platform ABC your home and your car
What other than
Should we talk about
Is Co-op
Old school
I think it's going to new school I think
Or SMTP burial School
Alphabet
You know those two are both really old so I think those are those are interesting so sleepy that one
What kind of oil Telecom background before this
That was like the
The protocol of choice for
Chat application
Teams in the day even
Even interactive voice response
Systems in Telecom systems
Managing messages
Between
Applications was a lot of DXM
Codility so very real bus
Open
Inspect
Bar security baked into it but
It's it's XML and
No one today really Developers
Anyway don't really want to write XML
Anything anymore they're all they're all
New message type format
Okay
So what we'll put that out there but
Probably not going to see it
So what about
Amqp
Am amqp
We connected aqua blue doll starts with other platforms like
Azure AWS bluemix
AT&T interaction others
Each of those platforms kind of have their preferred
Protocol to use and azure
Azra 80 is 8
So when when we
Talk to Azure that's typically the protocol we use it
It's similar to mqtt and in that it has a quality of service
But what what I've noticed is
It's a very
Daddy protocol
Skip that that also has it
Play snap your dealing with something
Very
Critical or very
State of communication are the states of the
Action is very very important
I can see that definitely benefits
About using a MCPE as a protocol they are as well
So that's when you really really really really really need to know what the message went through or if it hasn't
What state
Exactly so you might have gone through but maybe the device hasn't done anything with it yet amqp will keep tabs
It's stater in Flight State at state of action
Alright any other kind of these Legacy protocols we should think about her
Might be things to think about and cancer
But I think there's a DDS protocol we mentioned earlier is also one that I think was competing against in QT quite a bit
I still see it out there I still see it in the transportation industry
Definitely an industrial iot
From what I remember
It had an interesting approach
Using UDP instead of TCP which is also something to remember here is we talk about these protocols
I think so far all of them we've discussed it
CCP
Which means they have air handler
Built into the protocol
And it's assembling the packets on the way
And the way that they're supposed to be in the right order that that if there's
Are receiving a package
That TCP higher-level protocol
Manages hey
Resend packet number three
So I can reorder it
That's why you get the Jitter
Still sometimes like on video or something on a network
And TCP
The underlying Ark
Aventurine
That's a fair
That is fair
Yeah and then
Unity yashow
Which is coming back though I've seen
Some new file transfer protocol today
Better trying to start using UDP now with some type of him shaking over the top of it
And the reason for that is
If you take off all the
Hands shaking in the air and air correction
You can send
I don't know
What magnitude but a ton more mess
In real-time using UDP
So you got much more messages being sent to device
Which of the world of you and I were talking at lunch there.
If you're trying to control a battlebot
You don't really care if it doesn't or does not receive a package
Use what the singer receive a hundred times more packets than everyone else
More responsive with
With its weapons excetera
You definitely want to look at UDP because now you can send
Is so many more messages to device where you may not care like the the state of the hammer
Crashing down on the other battlebot use need to know
Okay we just got to keep this hammer and swing
If it misses a message
That very next messages
I was going to be
5 more degrees down
Cheap it's clean now it picks up where it left off
Got it
So now we know you're BattleBots
Yeah
GDP under don't you don't use why it don't use Wi-Fi cuz everyone else is and use UDP because you get
Four messages
That's how you
That's how you compete against me
If I have a product or a project
And I just need rap
And it's kind of an ongoing process that maybe doesn't need find granularity then UDP might be what I'ma
Yeah and I think that's for co-op
Comes in your some of the newer protocols were talking about
If you look at Co-op
Constrained application protocol
Looks like it's used case or sweet spot
Is maybe for low bandwidth Communications like maybe satellite Communications or
You don't have very large payloads very small little
Little packets of information
For lots of them
I'm Soo Co-op what I've noticed is it looks a lot like
Rest API
But it's it's
Without handshake
King without TC
Wtp
Very very fast
Short
Messages
Got it
Okay what else is in this newer kind of
Newer batch
Tutu that that that intrigued me one is all joy
They were trying to solve back then I am still are it's it's
Still very much alive protocol and project
But it was trying to
6-8 this idea where in a home environment
You might have devices that wanted
Discover other devices near them or in your in your same home and be able to message
I'm in such a way where
Earlier about mesh networks like
You really do sometimes
Want to create a very open
Discoverable message local network
On on-site in a car in a home
The downside is that
Not everything
Speaks all joints so you still need
Gateways to communicate Bridge
Other other protocols with all joints
When you need
I think one of their other
We are trying to solve
Rosen
Device
Making a
Connection out of your home
To the cloud Princeton
They were trying to broker all these
Messages in the one connection
Out of your home
And then after all
What are we working
The other one that I've been
Teen clothes
Hi Google
I think that one's
When you when you if you go to I think it's developers. Google.com weaves
When you look at how they
I look at this as maybe a modern version of all time
They looked and said okay
Let's identify how a lightbulb should
Talk how you should communicate with a light bulb
So they've tried to create this mapping
That all vendors potentially that that want to join the weaves Alliance and we project
Can basically say I'm going to make my light bulbs adapt to this
Weave
Specification
So that now I can just say
Light bulb number 6
Turn it on and turn it blue and then
Delek like we've been experimenting like
Top shoes and lifx bulbs and all these other ones that
The color blues are different
I think we've got some promise
I think if we even all join for smartphone stuff
Do you think of it as being something that might be used
Outsiders
Yeah so so
I know
With Citrix you only have to stop Flying or drones and start focusing on conference rooms
I think there's a lot of similarities
Smart home on steroids is what I look at Enterprise I
I look at it saying
Conference room
You I want to automate like
When I walk into conference room that comes to life in the meeting starts in the presentation
It's chromecasted in
They have the bridge tiles for me in the lights adjustment
But now I have to do this at
Seymour
Does rooms at talkin thousand rooms
Workspace
Yes it's I think it's it's the next
Level
Step after home home automation
And now
Hopefully you guys are finding
If
You're not
We probably already lost you
But now we're going to go into the bank account providers
I think we've covered them
I'm really sad that I can't remember my song to sing
Antioch that would have made this whole thing like
Or it
How do I decide the pros and
Deciding where to
That's another important that part of the conversation in NC
Might just
Come down to Partnerships that your company already has in place
You know if you're big
AWS
Stop
User or maybe your ear Clausen
Runs in Austin
AWS iot might just be the right the right
Iot platform for you
Because what what they done in in
I love their implementation
It basically exposed
Mqtt and websocket messaging
Slayer
To AWS
So that now you can say when it when
I receipt when this device receive the message in AWS
Now do all of these other things that aided us
Is really good at like
Run a Lambda
Serverless application or
Do something in S3 or use API Gateway to do something else
What day did I think was very strategic that basically created and iot
Front door if you will
Belt that allows
AMA iot message
To interact with anything in the AWS
Cloud
IBM bluemix
If you look at that you know Watson is is getting a lot of mindshare around cognitive
Computing and
Trying to cure cancer and all these bees really Noble interesting ideas
Lumix
Is a platform that you think they really like you
But they speak
Dilapidated
Websockets as well
And
I think if you're an IDM
Customer today
That platform certainly also has has a lot of Mary
You're a soft layer
Bloomix
IBM customer
And you're going to find
Once you get into that front door you got a lot of other
Ecosystem infrastructure there at play
Which is where
Everybody who's anybody seems
To be going this
Safety 1st a company earlier this year called Solaire
And
Very focused on on
Machine machine Communications layer and again
Tell they got asthma Analytics
As as an infrastructure play they had a gerbil
Morning
As another infrastructure clay soap
As you get more devices
Disconnected
Two afternoon again bait they really seem to like amqp
Then you can see how you can
Move the value of others Thursday
If you're streaming a lot since your data you end up platform
And you you want use Azure analytics or Azure machine learning
I think that simplifies
That's just directly connecting
Things to to that platform
And once once you're through the front door now I can route all of this
The sensor data to Azrael Dexter Azure machine learning
How important is it to
The B
All in on one platform
And I'm asking this because some people might start like
It might start their connected Journey with a product that
Is buy like
Consider using electric imp for connectivity which means they end up hosted on electric gems Cloud they're sending
Annotated there which is actually hosted on AWS
But let's say they want to pull that data into
Sing like Asher
Is that just crazy talk is that
Make an architecture fail for them
Well that's exact reason we started October
I mean we wanted to be a protocol agnostic
And then as we can
Matured the OCTA blue platform
We've connected it
To IBM bluemix
To Azure iot to AWS iot so you can now move
Messages
Scrum master
Throughout the blue to Blue Mix if you want
Or pick any any big data store of your choosing
Will Chris wonderful
But I will say that the inner ankle is so cute. It's so tough
So
I appreciate
You talking to me about this and hopefully
For those of you guys out there who are trying to understand what all might go into
Platform we just gave you a whole bunch of terms and
And thoughts for you today
Go look up orbi
Just start banding around and feeling like
You are like
I got this iot
He stuff yeah
I would encourage you listen to start small celebrate your wins build spilled something
Small and
Dad
Not small form factor but a little a little concept and then as your your comfort expands
Then come back and revisit the form factors and how you're actually going to take that to Market because
I think the imagination is the most important
Part of what you're trying to solve and if you can make
A good user experience
Yeah I think I think the rest will follow
Start with one conference
Not a thousand
Yes
All right
Chris thanks so much for coming on the podcast
Thank you Stacey for this week show thank you so much for listening and we'll see you again next week
On the Internet of Things podcast and if you don't get enough iot news for this show feel free to sign up for my news
Stacey knows things at Stacey on iot. Com