Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast
This is your host Stacey Higginbotham
Kevin tofu
This week we have so much news coming out for you we've got
Bluetooth 5 gets it
Certification
We have
A bunch of news related to Google home the Amazon Echo
I've tested some light bulbs for latency against these two things Google home is getting a new feature you're going to want to hear about
Amber to talk about how to get rid of your
Recordings
If you want to
There's also
Tons of news
With products like ge's new
Sorry to say it she who shall not be named
Light
We got a new energy monitoring device and we've got an acquisition in the wearable space
We also have
New grocery store concept from Amazon
A message from one of our sponsors Samsung
And
Our Guest this week is Peter's or to of Emerson talking about how to
Revamp your business for the industrial iot
And before we get into all of this let's go into our first
Just wait sponsor is skybell HD this is an amazing doorbell I actually review doorbell
Bells for The Wirecutter and this was my top
Hick basically if you've ever wondered who's at your front door while you're at work or when your package has arrived the skybell
Video doorbell lets you see who's at your front door from a smartphone it replaces your current doorbell and when to visit him
Presses the button it sends an alert with live video so you can see hear and speak to the person at your door
No matter if your couch or at work so if you think this is something your interest
Listed in please use coupon code iot podcast 25 at checkout 425
$5 off the purchase price guys this is a great doorbell I really like it
So if you're in the market go to www. Skybell.com and use the discount code
Good iot podcast 25
Okay Kevin
Stacy
Start off with in the certification front
Bluetooth 5 is out
What aspect this is
So Bluetooth is the
For those of you guys who
I don't know don't know it it is in your phone
It is in like
Your wearables in speakers it's basically
Really low data rate
And a really short distance Wireless
So things don't go very far
I don't really go super fast
But
That's changes
So Bluetooth 5 this spec
Has
Lots of new things the biggest things it's going to have that you guys are going to notice
Is it's going to be
Longer-range
Right now Bluetooth says that it's devices can go out to
The current Bluetooth stack goes out to about a hundred meters
I personally find it actually goes to about 20
If that
Yeah it depends on so many different things
Basically Engineers are going to have the choice of
Increasing the range
At
The risk of
Decreasing throughput
So basically the farther out it is
The slower the data
Which is an
Terrible because
You don't you might not be able to do audio but you could do notify
Applications
It's actually I think perfect for synchronizing wearables and
Getting iot notifications as you said
Because of short bursts of information they're they're not
Filled with data
So
You don't need a lot of
Truth what you just need
And then you
I love it because I have a Bluetooth ring
Talk to my phone
And it's great except for if my phone's a little too far away it no longer work
Works also good for light bulbs bluetooth light bulbs right now
If you're in your house
You know you could too far from your light bulb you can actually turn it off for the phone and then you're like
This was dumb
Borax
The range
Yay
The other thing that we should be excited about is there's going to be a little speed boost
And this will be great for things like when your syncing data or doing updates to like a wearable from your phone it'll just be a little bit
Pastor
You don't have to sit there looking to screen going sinking device
Loading
Bloating
Those things are great to know the other thing that is
Advertising rates and I kind of wish they didn't
Call it this but basically with Bluetooth beacons what happens is
They call it advertising
Pekin will send out a signal to your phone
And the phone then says
Here's a URL in the case of like Google ID Stone
Once every object have
URL
Or if you're in a store at might be like 50% off shoes cuz I'm standing near the shoes
What's going to happen here is there increasing the amount of data that can be sent by 8
Time switches
Much
Richer so instead of just being like
You're Something
Now to be like
You're Something here's a picture that something
There's a lot of data about that something
The way they're calling it advertising
Yeah but I I sort of understand why because there's been broadcasting
It's an ad obviously many can be used for ads but
They're their advertising that something is available
Write what we matter what is
Data picture a URL
So I sort of get that I just wish they'd called
Broadcasting
Then maybe people
Still probably not enough
Right right right right that's that's going to be really interesting because I think it'll
I really think there's a lot of potential
With broadcasting via Bluetooth
Especially if it's not just
Things broadcasting at your phone but your phone broadcasting out because think of all the preference data you could keep on your phone
You know you could have learned a restaurant to say
Hey I have an allergy
Like when you get in there at your table they could be like table 10 has
Nut allergy
Which is really actually kind of
Cool and interesting
We're not there yet
And actually
And say this is not there yet it is this is aspect onata not a natural product so people are going to see the speck
Introduced in Bluetooth products
They say within two to six months is the expectation so
Don't expect all these changes in your next Bluetooth device if you go out tomorrow night 1
If you go out
Next year in by when
And some of them
A lot of the speed and throughput and range things are chip
Related so a lot of things go has been floating around for a while
So some of the chip makers have
Already built
Products
Should be
Yeah I was actually just going to
Say this may not
I mean you need to buy a new device if you
If you want to take advantage Bluetooth but
You're you're going to hang that depends on the bed
Do not disturb
Alright so album
Actually I am going to assume
I assume that there will be demonstrations of this technology at CES
There are going to have
Apple Bluetooth
Whole Foods with Arena
As they often do
Experience the Bluetooth experience
The final thing that they are
Doing with Bluetooth which is worth noting
For all of you guys who are frustrated with the pairing experience
They are
Rapping over 400 known
Issues with Bluetooth into the spec
And people now have the option to
Fix them
So if you've had a device that just doesn't seem to work
Distracted
And they've wrap that in here so you can hopefully
Not have that experience
Going for it so it's also
I've done some Spectrum
Management kind of techniques in here so basically
Your Bluetooth won't interfere with your LTE
Things are going to be a little bit more efficient
In
Terms of
Set the channels they're using for sin
These are really highly technical things in
The idea behind it is basically that when you pair your going to be able to pair
Any Bluetooth device to any Bluetooth device
And it's not going to interfere with other wireless devices
Kind of the way it should be. You shouldn't have to
You got to adjust
Totally agree
So
Big big
News
From Google what hole
What's the new Google home
Connected speaker digital assistant
Is finally at
Home features
Or a
I don't know what to call it it's not a skill
It's a waiver developers disconnect
Products to Google home so now you should be able to control a wide variety
BF things
Through Google home
So
It's a developer program
Google home
Details are scant as we're recording this
But it is
Going to be one of the big missing pieces
That Google home had compared to the
Amazon Echo
And
There are lots of companies that are coming out with
Chatbots
Waste Control devices and so this should be
Actually pretty cool
I can't wait
Yeah this is good news to me because it's one of the reasons I didn't buy a Google home and back I just bought 1/4
Echo yesterday or
Just received it yesterday because of all the
Things that work with it all the services that you can use with it
I can't do that with a home so I've kind of held off
You might be purchasing a
I just might as I I didn't even this last week in my newsletter
Which guys
Stacey on iot
DACA
You should sign up for
I talked about the challenges of the voice ecosystem
Because right now we are
Is there something in this place where I'd like
Oh do I ask she who shall not be named
Or should I ask
It's funny you say that because I've seen a couple videos putting around with people have
A Google home talking to an echo talking
Go to Siri in like a loop
The talking to each other
Eric white circles are awesome
And
I have not said anything up like that beat
Because I
Don't want to annoy me
Yes
Crazy
But
I will say that it is
My poor daughter is like
Okay see you should not be named play this or do this and I'm like no.
You got a school
And she's like
Samurai
Also I spent this week testing
Various light bulbs with both the home and the echo through different platform
Because I'm Batman
That's what I do in my spare time you guys
A lot of people told me they felt the Google home with Snappy
In
I actually did not
Have that Xperia
Actually was about the same
When chewing
So
Philips Hue on both is integrated
Directly to both
In Philips Hue same
Exact
Response time
As I would Excel
What is cool with Google home is you can say
Hey hey G
Turn my living room lights pink
And that works
In your living room lights turn
What I did notice though is it doesn't recognize
The scene
So any of the scenes you say to
Google home
Didn't work
Now
The echo
Does not do colors
But it does do
See
I know
Okay so she won't seem to need to talk to this device
Message McCullers you talk to that device
This is what a wonderful future we live in
So there's
That
So that was the Philips Hue experience humble
Then I connected SmartThings
With a couple light bulbs
To the echo
Because not everybody wants
Wichita
And
3 smart things you can control osram lightify you control
Cree
And you can control lifx lights
And all of those actually worked really well in
Very quickly
Through Google home
Which is again a native support thing it's not
It's not like using if this then that or something else that would add attention rain
So you're doing Google SmartThings
Issue
Right
So that was kind of fun
You can also control SmartThings through the echo
Also
Google Assistant has supposedly done something with if this then that so it's a lot
Faster
I have yet to encounter that with
And that could be wink
We could be at going through
I'm not real sure
Cuz when I did the wink
Moonshine
Ifft
Too many moving parts
A protein which is fine
I totally expected you know
That's that's a lot of
That was kind of delighting experience of all of
I really liked
Color-changing thing on the Google home with the Hues that was kind of fun and nice
Pretty sure
There has to be weighed maybe if I named the rooms in Google after something like dinner party I
I could set some more
Definitive settings
Objects.
Cuz it would be nice to say you know like at cuz I have an echo thing
Dinner party
And that's already set but that's through.
I guess I could do it through SmartThings scenes through smart
The good old days of a physical switch and wire
Okay
Movie Ride Along that was that was that experience for those of you guys who are
Looking at that
Well actually it is very telling though it tells you that we can talk about all the stuff
For several years but
It's still maturing it's still not where it needs to be
Lots of services Latta devices lots of interfaces
Yasso
That is actually killing all right
Personal assistant in the home front
Wired had a wonderful article
These guys recording app
Can you say
You're freaked out about that probably shouldn't buy one but if you're freaked out about it and you want to delete your stuff the article which I weigh
Building 2
Offers you lovely tips
Which is nice
Indonesia
The ability to delete your
Voice recordings has been available on a lot of these services
Beginning for privacy reasons
I want people to be secure
It's kind of funny to me you buy these devices that are always listening
Or you wouldn't buy them
Obviously
And then you go and delete your recording history but you know what you just going to fill it up again
Okay hold on a second
Let's not say that at all
Okay alright.
If one were to
Have something like that
Delete that directly
You know this is how you
So
Are you really that lazy that you wouldn't type it in somewhere supposed to speaking it out
How to get away with murder
So
That's okay I'm just I'm just saying
Search delete
Hear recordings after
You delete your saved audio clips after the fact
You have to go to my activity. Google.com
Tap the three vertical dots in the myactivity titlebar
And select
Delete Act
Activity
Bye
All products
Click the all products drop down menu
Choose voice and audio and then
Now
Dismay infection of Google homes personalization features because it essentially wipes its
And that's right that's why you want to leave this on because it gets better
Weather in spring
Boys sit
Burns from your environment
You know all of these things help it
Better so
But
It's adoption
Before the echo you have to visit amazon.com
Slash
My X
Click the year devices tab
Select your Echo device and click manage voice recording
A popup message should appear and clicking delete
Will wipe out your saved
Set up instructions in the
Show notes
In case you weren't
Did you not have a pen and pencil handy to write on that day
But it's possible
And
There you go
One more little thing I just want to mention it be
Okay I'm not
Weird she who shall not be named
The Voice service
Will show you a picture
It's like a
What did you say
Credit score
It's like a quidditch goal it's a round light
Yes around lights
That stands on its side
Ion little bass and it has
People Services of
Her built-in
It just looks weird to me the price they sale will be lower in cost than
Traditional Echo
Which is $180
You know sitting on someone's bedside table and if this has the function of like the GE
Lights
You know our
That work with circadian rhythms maybe this is
Kissing a baby
And we love it
Samso
No late don't need a light
So this kind of consolidate baidu
And it sits on a WeMo switch and I can
Until.the. To shut the light off iPhone is really cool
But it looks
But my light looks like a light not a quidditch goal
Okay so we just wanted to mention that
Because
Dang it looks funny
Would be curious about y'all's opinion
All right
Big news coming from Amazon
Kevin you want to talk about this
Yes this is the reason I am finally going to make a trip out to Seattle I think just to go buy a can of tuna fish
Amazon
Go
The
Prototype store of the future was just
Announce a couple days ago
And it's
It's a very interesting concept
It reduces friction for shopping because there is no checkout line
There's only a check in line with sounds
Kind of weird
But if you think about it you check into the supermarket with Amazon go use your smartphone
You then go and grab whatever off the shelves
But you want to buy you just put it in your little
Bag
And you walk out
When you're done
What happens is
Through
They call it a I but
I'm assuming it's a lot of sensors
Cameras and so on
Whatever you buy whatever you put in your bag or your
Your card
Is automatically
Tallied up in a shopping list and
You pay for it through Amazon in the app you could receipt right if you walk out of the store
So there's no checkout at all I just
Magically Hotel mini bar fridge with
The sensors in it
Only
Grocery store
And not everything has liquor in it
Astoria
So what yeah I think this is
Awesome
I'm very curious like how much it cost per square foot
This is
You don't just
But that time is it
It's also going to be raining right now grocery store margins are at 3
3%
So this
Eliminate some of the labor cost I think kind of
Illuminates like Checkers and that sort of thing
To a certain extent I'm sure they're still good
Happy helpers
In the story to help
Define things
But
It also
Has technical cost that I'm unsure of
Wright's Auto
Who's
Affixing night I assume it's RFID labels but who's affixing those whose
Packaging cost how much did those go up
I love the idea I'm very excited as a
Consumer but I'm like Boo
How does the Shifty economics
Yeah but you know what it's an Amazon approach they don't worry so much about the
Costs in the margins and all that
You're buying a lot of their products there
Other electronics like a Kindle
As a Gateway for you to buy more things so you might be getting the devices at cost or less right
So it's it's a typical Amazon approach and what I sort of like about it is
A they want to own the customer experience which is Central to
Amazon
And
Secondly
I think they're tired of waiting
Beacons and all kinds of other Technologies
To be implemented in stores in a mish-mosh way interested to know what we're going to show you how to do it cuz we can
I need it
And I can't wait for the day that I go in and bye-bye
My kind of Cherry Garcia
And a bottle of wine when I get home Amazon
You look like you need a rom-com Stacy
How about Sleepless in Seattle
Exercise TV
So
Brave New World
Alright let's see what else do we have we have
Fitbit
Can we all mourn for a moment
Because market and reports that
Well it's part of the deal where Fitbit is buying
Pebble for
Reported 40 million dollars now this is all
Still in the rumored stage
This has not been
Satellite
But the latest news
This
Piece of news is that backers of the pebble time 2
And the
Core
I'll probably just going to get a refund instead of their device
It's sad you know how excited
Core which was
It was going to have the Amazon Echo
Services and Spotify
So I could just take this tiny little iPod Nano looking device on my
Send off
I remember
I don't think that's happening
I was so excited that I think about it everyday while walking
My dog
There's another there was another Kickstarter project actually
You know it's it is it's really sad in the sense that pebble
Not to use this as a pun though about it but I'm going to say it they can be essentially kick-started the wearables market here
Literally and figuratively
And
They've done some really nice work in the space that got some great products that aren't too expensive
And to be honest of the kind of products that aren't overly complicated to the appeal to a mass audience
But
I don't know the economics of their particular challenges but apparently they've been
Hurting for money and letting people go and
Fitbit is also another very
Popular and successful
Demon is Faison
It's especially sad because Pebble actually had in 2015 and offer for 740
$10
And this was from watchmaker
Citizen
Which
And then
In until had made a reported offer of 70 million
Right before the launch of the pebble 2
So that was that was Intel's effort
The CEO just was like nope we got it
And so
I guess he does not happen
I would hate to be a CEO
An offer like that I mean you're just like
I mean cuz you don't start a company thinking well
Play some people start companies thinking someone will just buy the
But you start a company because you were right
We all miss you got to have
Crazy confidence crazy belief
And then to say
Okay
Ocelot to you
Looking for Dennis Duffy
Dropcam to neston
Really regretted
So
They're sure
Children and negative stories always ReSound
Much more
You waited much more heavily
So
Here is that tire
Pebble news
So sorry you guys I
We can have like a little
Lots of people fans out there
Yeah okay
Chew other qwikbetz a news there is a brand new energy monitoring device is not going to be out until 2017 but
What I'm talking about it
Because I
I think it's probably the Least Complicated energy monitoring device out there
Well it's not out there
And that's why I want
That's why I won't work because this looks very simple
Works in
They bought a company called
Whisker
Laughs
And
Through this they're doing
It basically looks like a stick on thing that you stick on your circuit box
Roxanne
It starts measuring
Electricity
You spy your devices in you
The details are little late right now so in the product
Actually
Arrives I'll be very curious how they're doing that
With just like a box on the circuit breaker
Sum of the measure
This actually gets into light
Ocean noises
We'll just call it a fancy out
Has been tested
There's different ways of doing your fancy outdoor
Actually talked to hit like Mario
Curb
Those guys felt like how they're doing it
And
Yeah
Verdigre is another company that does this
Did you have something installed in your circuit
Curb yes
Actually one of them to come out
I didn't pay for it
So when I test a device
Sugar Act
I think it was $650
Pair device in your
Circuit
Foxo1 device measured
1 Circle
Can I have 3
So
Yeah that's the stuff I not cheap
And I do remember looking at these folks as I install their app
Because it works with the green button which is a initiative to get your actual energy data
From your electricity provider and
There for you match the two data points and you learn more about your energy usage so
Fortune my provider is not supported so I don't use curb
Someday Maybe
This week a device called
Plume
Launched this is plume WiFi
This is
A twist it Twist on the idea of mesh Network
Working these are tiny little pods that you stick around your home
Traditionally with a router
And things like that you Rose
Mesh networks or a traditional router you have kind of a brain
In your router that handles the routing tasks
And you have the radios
What happens with blue Ms you have the radios but the brain lives in the
Cloud
So
Each one of these pods
Is plugged into an outlet
In your home and you're supposed to have in a three-bedroom home should have six to eight plumes
And Kevin you should probably get the pricing while I
If you don't mind
Yes actually pretty expensive if I recall
But I'll get the exact
So these are
In your house and they
Adapt to how you use your Wi-Fi network so I actually installed mine but I was kind of late on my insta
So I'm not going to talk about how it's working
Because
I'm supposed to let it sit for
Take a couple days
It kind of learn a little bit more before
I start doing
Performance testing so what I can tell you
Is the install itself they have an IOS and Android app if you have the ability to install it using I
IOS do it because the Android app is pretty bare-bones
It takes about
Maybe
15 minutes in a day
It's me running around upstairs
So you basically
You plug it into your
You plug the first one into your router
Into the wall
I will say I had to find a longer
Ethernet cable
A little higher than my outlets on the ground
Problem
Once you do that it established you
Name your network
If you
Are replacing it make sure you
Get the exact same SSID
Like me
End
Your password and then you run around your house just plugging in these other things
Are the other pods
You know different rooms
Can the pods get
Discovered
Eminem and
You're done
Yeah and paws are not that expensive
If you bite me.
$69 for a single pod
3 pack is $180
And a six-pack is 300 +
$30
Probably will want
Lose people
In a home
Will probably start with the six
Like I have 7in
House and it's a
Help me come to my home bring a six pack
That's my motto
As a guest I do try
Next week I'll tell you I'll do some actual
Performance testing
Until you already the coverage is good throughout the home
I haven't noticed anything
Weird dead spots or
Any
Terrible things
So we'll see
After all of that
We have
News from Kevin
Sorry we're just going to add this right here
Pebbles
Right now it is official.
Right this very second as we speak and record pebble
I'm just reading out loud now Temple is no longer able to operate as an independent entity
We've made a tough decision to shut down the company and no longer manufactured Pebble devices
I'm going over to the update section of the
Pebble site
Temple devices will continue to work as normal no need changes to the user experience will happen at this time however Pebble Junction
Cellular service quality may be reduced in the future
There's some information on refunds for people of recently ordered as well
Sonu Kaur
Pebble time to Pebble core in Pebble time round Kickstarter Edition
So no further
You will automatically get
Refunded from you
So here's something because actually this will affect me refunds are automatic payment card the original Kickstarter pledge was placed
Packers must contact their financial institution that issued the
The card to receive
Suck
Okay
Shazam
PayPal
Never gets stolen
Russia oar
Where am I
All right so that's the sad
It kind of stinks at our first breaking news is actually sadness
That is terrible and it'll be breaking you know tomorrow
Tomorrow when you
Okay
Sad
Into podcast
Let's take a break for a message from our sponsor and then we will go to Peter's or you
Who's going to talk about
Changing your business model
After
The Internet of Things
Guys last week I was talking about the August doorbell and I mention their plan to charge users
For access to their Clips after certain amount of time
I told you the wrong time
Find the actual amount of time that you will have
Free access to your existing clips from the doorbell is one month
So that's a lot longer than what I thought
And said last week now you know
Hey everyone we are breaking into the Internet of Things podcast with a message from our sponsor
This week sponsor is Samsung and I have Abi
Who is director of product marketing
With Samsung
Arctic Cloud first off
Tell me what is
Arctic
Samsung artik Cloud is an open data exchange platform for the iot
It's a relatively new commercial iot Cloud offering from Samsung
For Enterprises
We provide Enterprises a super-fast way of connecting
Siloed devices and enabling Deluxe developer
To deliver new services and application
How are people use
ICloud
Take Healthcare and building automation
It has good patients are increasingly generating their own health data using blood pressure monitor
Pulse oximeter
Fitness trackers in salon
These devices were never designed to work together
What's the site with make it very hard
Florida Healthcare payroll provider
To build a consistent view of the patient's health
Cumberland building
It's very hard for the building manager to build a consistent view of how energy is being used
Throughout the building
When the HVAC system the lighting
System the plug load occupancy sensors
The weather feed air quality or don't talk to each other
It's breaking down the silos is where Samsung artik Cloud company
Alright and when I actually signed up for Samsung art
Which any developer can do I was surprised that the
This is not a traditional
Hey you point your device to this cloud and it takes in the data and does things with it
This is very much a connecting
Can you talk about how
Samsung artik Cloud
Is different
Then maybe some of the other things
They're out there
Svcrt cloud is very different from what you see with other iot platforms and services
On the market
Underscore artik cloud is a collection of ready-to-use
Apis and sdks that are open that are easy to use that are enterprise-grade
It when we look at other iot Solutions out there
We see the
We see us as different alarm three key dimensions
The forces we are integrated
We've integrated all the key iot Services you need
Device connectivity data collection
An aggregation device interoperability data access
Security
Into one single platform
And we expose those as API
The second is rebirth in
A number of services around interoperability the ability to connect two different clouds
The ability to manage identity permission data privacy
All that is built in out of the box
The third thing is we've kept Developers front-and-center
When we've designed and built Arctic cloud
We've made it
Extremely easy for developers to use our API SDK sore tooth
Because we know that
Developers are the ones who will actually use
Are products
And
Business news services and app
That make iot more pervasive more useful
Abby
How can I find out more
You can learn more and sign up for article out at Arctic. That's a r
Tik. Cloud
You can sign up for free tier you can start connecting devices you can connect
You still existing
Connectors that we have and connect third-party devices you can do a lot in our free tier
Hey everyone we are back with the
The Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham
And today we have with us
Peter zornio who is the chief strategy officer for
Automation Solutions at Emerson
Hey Peter how are you doing today
Hi Stacy it's a great pleasure to be with you today
I am super thrilled
Last time we talked I went to Emerson's
Guys have a nice little demo area here in Austin Texas
And we talked about
All kinds of things but mostly
Turning your products business into a Services business
On the industrial-size
Indeed we did when you walk through a number of demonstrations and we showed you some of the
The application that we are working on it exactly that area
I found an awesome to talk to you because you've been doing this a while and I'd love for you just to take the audience really quickly through
Kind of the stages of Industrial Automation because
Automated
70s
So
Where where are we and where are we going
Okay Stacy thanks I agree that very much is the case when we look at
Industrial and specifically the
The process industries that we tend to work with Industries like
Chemicals in oil and gas in Pulp
Paper and pharmaceuticals
These are industries that you know have had this idea of sensors
All over the place
Reporting on real-time data that is happening in the process
Being fat into computers and then those computers actually taking action to control those processes
That's happened now for probably a good
40 years ever since the first
Microcomputer based systems were put in place in the late 60s
Mid-seventies
Some of the fundamental principles of people talked about in iot the idea of
Sensory feeding real-time data to computers making decisions while that's that's kind of old hat for us
The new thing
Is yeah we've been doing that a long time but we've been doing it very specifically around controlling those processes
And it's historically been gone just on site
You know by instrumentation and Computing resources that are on site you know kind of very much like the
The computer that controls the engine in your car as you drive around
What's
Certainly do when the whole Industrial internet-of-things
Is a number of things number one the idea of using the internet
To take that data and also additional sensor data that you might add
And feeding that to anyone in the world or any application anywhere in the world
For analysis and decisions as to what actions to be taken
And then another big changes the tools we have available to us obviously with
Things like cloud computing and Big Data statistical analysis and
The ability to handle many different types of data other tools and Technology we have to apply to analyze that day didn't come
Come up with answers is dramatically
Differences and it's been 30 years ago
And then perhaps what I think is maybe the biggest change of all
Is this idea of the whole new business model of the connected service or the
Iot service
With that data goes to a third party
Not the customer
For analysis
And you know
Overall computational analysis together with an expert looking at the data
A coming back with
Actions coming back with this is what you need to do or this is how the problem
Should be corrected
Traditionally our customers have always done that themselves
I mean so that idea of
I really turning something that you know they did themselves
Using tools and technology that they purchased from companies like us
Into a service
Something where we actually deliver the outcome to them where we've analyzed the data
That's probably the biggest change of all I'd say in the industrial space
Man Peter you are riding my Segway is for me
Because that's my next question
You guys are trying to move into this kind of service aside and I'm
Really curious about what that
Looks like
4 Emerson
How you kind of structure
The shift
From product to service
And then I'd like to talk about
The value that the customer gets in
What they say
Cure for a company like us that's traditionally been a technology supplier we had service offerings before
The service offerings
Have been ones where we've come out
To help
Install and startup and configure our equipment
Where we've come out and help to maintain and
Baby continue to provide some lifecycle value out of it
But we've never been the operator
Of the equipment right we always provided the equipment to end users
Who did the final operation and use the data coming from it to
Can make analysis site
I used a very simple analogy that you know we're always
The guys that you know sold and serviced your lawn mowers for you and
You went out mold your lawn
Now we're lawn mower service
Will tell you hey if you like is a turnkey Manor
Will put this equipment in will take the data will analyze it and will even
In some cases take action for you in addition to just providing you
With information
That's a big business model shift
For you know traditionally
Technology or product supplier company like ourselves
Let's break that down a little
So when making this shift
You don't do it all at once
Crossroad whole portfolio
How do you
Target and start
A process like
One of the first things that we have done
Is we tried to identify
The applications that we know will for sure deliver business value to our customers and we've had a
A very big focus on making sure as we talked about
Industrial internet-of-things that we always start the conversation from
Here's what's in it for you Mr customer from a business value perspective
And we've also made sure to look at areas where we think customers will be comfortable
With this idea of about sourcing the function is someone like ourselves
So what does that mean
What are some of the criteria
Okay well number one
Because we're going to be asking too
Do collect data from their sites
And have it looked at by our people
Well
Most of our customers are understandably has a big concern around their intellectual property what that data might be
Medium from a privacy and intellectual property point-of-view so we start by looking at applications where we think
The data itself
Is dated at the Comfort that the customers are comfortable
Having a third party
Owner having it not all about having a 3rd party look at it analyzed
Okay
So not the secret formula
It's not the secret formula exactly next
We look for areas that we have
Great domain expertise in
Because I'm a big believer when you look at
Industrial internet-of-things when you look at
Just
You know operation Improvement in general
Really it's
All about
Domain expertise
Either in the form of
Experts
Encapsulated domain expertise in the form of algorithms or software
Or learn to Domaine expertise that you got by running big-data stuff to
Define
You know correlations
At the end of the day
This is just
Yet another deployment model
For how you
Applying and deliver
Domain expertise
2 solving a problem and improving operational performance
And I think that's true when you look at
You know other
Iot
Areas as well I mean if you look at the medical field right you know when
If you have a Fitbit and your got all this great date of being collected about your personal hell
Who would you like to have at the other end of that Fitbit while you'd like to have the world's leading expert on
You know Cardiology your you know performance
Exercising performance or whatever it may be
So
Customers are going to trust
Someone who they believe has great domain expertise in an area
For this Outsource
Service kind of model
So we will get areas where we have that domain expertise can we go to Costco
Okay so you guys are looking for when you
Service is a good business
Your customer
And something that you guys know more about than any
So now here gets the fun part
Pick something
The customer seems like they might go for something like this
Easier so hopefully
And now how do you implement something like this because
You got to think about contracts like how do you contract
When you're selling a service versus a product
In at the lifetime of this product
What it entails how you
Renegotiate
What are some of those considerations
So that permeates
Just about every aspect of how we do our business
It starts from selling
Okay so again if you're a traditional
Product or technology sales kind of organization
You know you kind of live by the
Project or the demand that a customer has created
And you go in and you try to differentiate your technology or product
Compared to the other guys
Here
It's more of a demand creation model
You have to go to a customer and be able to sell them
On the business case in the value of of what you're providing
You have to in some cases
Be willing to move to morva outcome-based Performance contract do you have to
Not just say hey I'm going to show you a product but actually be willing
To stand behind what the results for the outcome may be
Of the particular service that you're delivering
You get into lots of aspects around
The data itself
Where the data is stored is the data connected to
Securely security of course has a big D
Concern sometimes what we've done in that particular area
Is we've partnered with Microsoft because
You know
Data storage and rules around who owns data vary tremendously across the globe
There has been a lot of focus on that just brought from cloud computing overall so we'd rather just
Partner with somebody
Who can address at least that aspect of it very directly and has a lot of experience in that
So generally where we land there is the data always belongs to the customer
But any knowledge
That we gain from working with that data
That knowledge that application if you will belongs to us
You have to dress contractually what you're going to do if the customer
Is done with the service and you know wants to cancel it for whatever reason and says hey I want to have all my data back
You have to agree who in your organization is going to have access to that data and for what purposes are going to have it
Let's talk about pricing
Because this is a big
Issue I mean going from selling a physical product
Presumably you sell once
To selling a recurring Revenue stream
Recurring service not only is it a different type of sales cycle
But it's also a different way of
Accounting for it
Pricing app
So how do you guys
How did you think about pricing
When you were sitting price
So you
Generally always want to work from the value delivered back so you want to look at
What would this particular service
Do for a customer what would it cost them
If they didn't have it what are you saving them
If they
Didn't have it
What do you potentially
What kind of down time or maintenance
Expanse would they have to be spending themselves if they didn't have this service
And then work
Into
You know what a good price would be that looks like it's an equitable sharing
Are the benefits that you're delivering to the customer and as you can imagine
There's always a lot of back and forth with a customer on
Assumptions you're making about what might happen
Versus assumptions that they might have about what
What happened with or without
How to service
So right now you guys are not selling like you are not having to deal with
Like I sell you a valve
As part of a service without actually
Selling someone the physical valve
What we are
So we are dealing in some cases where
We sell just the service and Princeton star steam trap monitoring service is a good example of that
So we're not in the steam trap
Business per se
But we know a lot about steam traps because we
Make specific sensors
That go on steam traps
And have built-in
Algorithms built-in analytics inside of them
That are capable of identifying the acoustic signature that tells you what's happening with that particular string trap
So in that case we actually go out and we sell a specific service
Where we would go in and put the sensors on your steam traps
Bring them back to our
Pervasive sensing Center where we
Analyze what's going on
And then we
Tell you which Team traps are failed are likely to fail and which ones to go out and do work on or we can even go and do a
Good for you
Are cell so there's an example where we actually are selling
Just the service
On equipment that
We don't manufacture
And in that case
Talking about you know transforming from selling products to selling services
That's an interesting financial application for
Just because
There we may go in and install all the equipment to run that service
Well that's Capital Equipment that you know we're going to carry on our books for a prescribed length
The charm of that of that sales contract
And that's a very different kind of financial business model for us where were
You know Manufacturing Company we're used to looking at things like
Cost of goods sold and inventory and include things like that we try to keep our capital costlow
Here's a case where in order to get a
A recurring annuity kind of service
We're actually going to have to take on some additional
Capital that we hold on our books in order to
Enable Unity service
And what's interesting here
Is
This isn't a crazy model that got if I think about cloud computing right now
You know
Basically Amazon took all the capital expenditures and
Google and Microsoft
To turn
Computing power into objects for
Now if I take this though to Industrial manufacturer
That doesn't feel
A sensor or a valve is in a fungible resource like
Computer is
Basically a virtualized server
So that gets into some kind of just basic economics of
Can we see
Hey can you guys financially do this
For everything
For what things I don't
And then
Can this really have the type of impact that like cloud computing
Yeah I think that's a great analogy I think what's interesting when you think about cloud computing also
Is that those companies
Truck capability you know Computing horsepower
But they were not the providers of right other companies were the providers of that at the time
You know whether it was
Is Dell or HP or whoever it was that was in the server business right
But then they became the one that was the service provider of it
Okay
Nnr case
You know where they the Capital Equipment provider it's not
Possible just as you said that's a great
Distinction
To relocate that right that valve that steam trap that whatever piece of process
Office equipment
Have to be physically there
At the plant
But the
Uptime of it and they making sure that it's available on demand
Perform
The job that is supposed to perform
You know that's the service that we would be offering going forward and extended to it
Ultimate end
You could see it
Yes being turned into something like what we never even sell you a valve in the first place
We saw you valve uptime right course that's the example that's used a lot with like aircraft engine
It's right that you moved from buying an aircraft engine
Do you move it you move to stress by the hour or whatever maybe
Recall
I don't see that happening with with everything because
You know
Not every capital expenditure is a
Is is giant hand in marriage that sort of I think
Model being built around it
But for sure
The idea that the maintenance of the uptime and the availability of that of that asset being
Being there when it's called upon
I can see a lot of things moving that model
Cuz it really boils down to
What are the things that the
End-users the manufacturers
Want to spend their precious time and resources
On
Keeping going and where do they View
Are there domain expertise and what are they better at
Let's get into the concept of security
Because we talked about this a lot on the show
A lot of the most recent discussion is been around
Consumer and smart home and
Mirai botnet and all those kind of fun things
But it is kind of a crazy place to think about
Bad security practices
So I would love to get a sense from you
How your customers are
This
First of all they absolutely Dulce security as a very important thing we've run a number of
Daddies are just questionnaires with our customers
As well as looked at a number of ones that other people done the industrial space
And you know what usually number 1 and number 2 and
Switches in order sometime around Industrial iot
Is what's the business case
And then the other one is always security
Obviously in the industrial space
It doesn't help
The term iot is used broadly
Whether we're talking about industrial iot or home iot
Or iot in cities or
You know smart instrumented people it's all called iot
And then they read in the news
Statue at A candle wiped out
The internet on the eastern half of the United States cuz
Your internet enabled Barbie doll and home thermostat
You know had very poor Security in the first place
So that
Sort of Cassidy a shadow over into the industrial space
But in reality what happens in the industrial space
Is you are dealing
With very professional it organizations that have been working in the security area
Since computers have been around and certainly with a greater emphasis in the last 10 or 15 years
There's no way
They're going to put in
Iot infrastructures and iot connected devices
Without going through every aspect of what the
Security is an insuring
That the security is
Up to Snuff it is what it needs to be they are very highly concerned about that
Okay and in fact
When you look at the stuff that we provide you know to enable iot like RR wireless sensor for
Polio
The networks that we design our design with
High levels of encryption built in from day one
Key management and you can't even turn it off
So you couldn't even get into
Kind of the scenario that we see in the consumer iot world
It's all right
Will Peter thank you so much I feel
Gosh smarter about iot and Industrial internet
Okstate she's been a real pleasure
Well that's it for this week's show thank you so much for listening and we'll see you again next
This week on the Internet of Things podcast and if you don't get enough iot news for this show field
Free to sign up for my newsletter Stacy knows things
Stacey on iot. Com