Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast I'm your host
Stacey Higginbotham and this is your co-host
Kevin tofel
And this week we have got
Gobs and gobs of news for you including the fact that Kevin is psychic
A preview of CES
And
A review of a
$3,000 coffee maker
And let's see
SIM lighting Products
But I am really excited about
So let's get with the show
Kevin you want to start out with your psychic prediction that has since come true
I do not want to say I told you so but
You know I won't it's funny because my kids always say I'm from the future I was
Predict things and then
How many personal things you can get most of them right at some point.
I might remember when it was but I could have sworn I said
I don't want any more of these smart home hubs hanging off my routers
We got only screens in the house all these TVs why not just
Put the Smart Home
Hugs in the TVs
Guess what
Samsung is going to do that in 2016
They are integrating smart hubs right into their
4K TVs that are 1080p
If there s UHD TV so it sounds to me like it's all 4K TVs not 1080p is but
Doesn't matter I want one I'm super excited by this and we need to talk about what it means we found some tidbits
After the announcement earlier today
Tidbits and we should say this is a very specific hub
It is
Samsung
Hug which we all know and love
Incall
The SmartThings Hub
Alright so
Let's go with tidbit that was tidbit number one
This is the SmartThings Hub you can
So
It's actually the SmartThings software and to get this inside your television
What must you do
Will you have to buy a 2016 television personal
Second of all this is kind of interesting
Samsung is going to offer a
Free USB adapter
It's called the SmartThings extend and
Before the show station I were not sure what that was going to be or how much was going to cost we've just said it's free so now we know it's free
Interesting way it's going to add the ability to Monitor and control zigbee and Z-Wave devices from your TV
So what's inside the TV radio wise does not include zigbee and Z-Wave
But
You had this little USB dongle and 212 to the compatible TV that is
And you'll be able to
Work with zigbee and Z-Wave devices
Yay
That's if you if you care about that so
In a lot of ways zigbee and Z-Wave are going to be kind of the Legacy Smart Home
Radios
Even even though
Smart things guys will say
But
So the TV will have the Wi-Fi
And I bet it has Bluetooth to
Oh I thought I would would not doubt at 1 for one second
So yeah cuz the V2 of the SmartThings Hub has
Z-Wave zigbee
Wi-Fi Bluetooth
And I believe it has a spot
Or has a dongle break
Unplugging
Cellular
So
With all of that
Applaud the sin and you got the SmartThings soft
And what were unclear on right now is if it's running tizen which is the operating system
Samsung uses on it
TVs
And we're trying to figure out if
The current generation of
SmartThings
Hubs runs ties
Because way back when it was
Announce
Lafayette
It wasn't an ounce
Is it like the SmartThings Hub was
Running tights
They wanted to move to
That's that's my educated guess is that the current SmartThings Hub does not run on tizen
You can call it Legacy software from
When before SmartThings was bought by Samsung
You and I are at the big gay
Iot keynote sing last year at CVS where Samsung was on stage and Tyson was going to save the world
Can let all our devices talk to each other my guess is that
Samsung spent 2015
Getting that ready
And
I know the TVs are on tizen
I also know that
I'm expecting that tizen version 3.0 the next version of tizen will be out
Next month
After CS is what I'm hearing but that wouldn't preclude a CES announcement obviously so
I'm thinking
The new
Call the new SmartThings platform for better word is going to be tizen-based
Right so tizen hopefully 300
Will soon come out
And we'll see that
Running
Auntie Dee's and
So
Exciting
Will get
For people like Kevin who hate hugs
You will soon have to buy only this
Samsung
S UHD what is the used
Ultra that that's why I'm picking it up
Yeah that's why I'm thinking it's
That's why I'm thinking it's going to be the 4K TVs actually Can Shed a little more light on that just now as I'm re-reading what they put out today
Let me say this out loud for Dragon celebrities
Because actually have two things here
We're excited to announce that all 26
2016 Samsung Smart TVs will be compatible with SmartThings
So that's one thing that smart TVs can be 1080p 720p whatever
And all s UHD TVs which is the 4K set
Will have iot Hub technology so the TV can become the heart of your smartphone
A slightly different
Oh okay so it sounds like for one of them they will be the Hub and the other one was sounds like it will be
Become integrator because
Comparto
Got it
That is so true
2 related answers with their TVs and iot
Okay and it sounds like
You probably will then be able to
Control or organizers
Smart home on your TV
The Samsung
S UHD application will allow you to trigger different SmartThings
Teens
You can also get notifications on that sucker when important thing
Things happen
2nd Annual connected cameras right on your TV
Control your canoe
Devices for me
Fancy
So the forecast Wednesday when they get
If your SmartThings
If you're not a smart thing
Okay
Let's take a moment here and just Lament The fact
Did the sounds really great
But
It also sucks
Here is why
Tell me why
Because
We and I have seen this I have seen this dream come to fruition
In labs
With all join
And other Open Standards
223 years ago
Where all of this was happening
And things were whizzing around my house through invisible radio waves and software
Open Standards
Years ago
It it's not coming
Troop
But there's a difference there's a difference here
I agree with you that the Open Standards and and SmartThings it's all very similar to All Join
What all joints didn't have and what Samsung does have is it also owns the hardware side of things
Right we'll see in this gets into this can get into
If we want to talk about
Is
Why
Why this is fundamentally broken
So
Thing 1
Yes I got some data heading into CES
From
Let's see this is
Parks Associates is saying that 43% of people next year
43%
People in the US will buy a smart device
In the next year
I want to tell all those people
No Doubt
Different kind of counter to our show
I usually don't do that
So because
You are about to set yourself up what was happening right now is everybody is creating these.
Please lock and standards that we've talked about we talked about for three years we talked about it last episode with friends a few
And
We're about to talk about it now because this is very much on my mind
Going into CS where we're about to see a lot of other walled Gardens
Being built
So
With Samsung what they're doing is I know that last year at CES
They got to her
Their CEO got up and
Did this wonderful everything must be open presentation and
I'm sure he still feels that way
But that is not what's being built right here this is very much a hay
I got a Samsung TV that's going to work with tizen
And a hug that also will it possibly eventually run tizen
And everything
What happened on this TV
And
It is very frustrating for me
Soap
6 best rating for everybody it's it's one of the biggest challenges that
Smart Homes in iot devices really have them in your right way I'm not going to rehash it cuz we talked about this
I don't say every episode but darn it comes up on off alot how
There are just too many
Competing call them standards if you will that competing efforts by different companies in groups
Companies in
And Kickstarter projects and so on that
Want to
Give you the solution but
If they're not going to play nice with others if there is a lock-in
2 to a large degree still on next it's frustrating as all get-out
So there's an interesting perspective out there and I want to draw your attention to it audience
I'll put it in the show notes but Bruce scheiner
Read about it over the Atlantic
And he'd kind of drawers
He talks about this he talks about in relation to Hugh he talks about in relation to John Deere's
Tractors where they're trying to send
On the software associated with this and Keurigs coe's on their their pots and dram
And he blames the Digital Millennium Copyright Act which I thought was really crazy
So
Whose theory is
Is that
And I'll just I'll just read part of his his theory here
Stop competitors just reverse engineering the proprietary standard and making compatible peripherals
For example another Coffee manufacturer put in Keurig codes on their own pods
These companies rely on a 1998 law called the Digital Millennium Copyright Act
The dcma
Originally passed
Prevent people from pirating music and movies
Well it hasn't done a lot of good in that regard
Is anyone who
Uses BitTorrent can attest
It has done a lot in Hibbets
Security and compatibility research
Specifically the dmca inclusion anti-circumvention provision
Which prohibits companies from circumventing
Quote technological protection measures
Effectively control access to copyrighted works
That means it's illegal for someone to create a hue compatible light bulb without Philips permission
A K-Cup compatible coffee Pod without Keurig
Orange HP compatible
Printer cartridge
Without
Hp's
And this explains why I still prefer using my Amazon Echo in the wink hub
Because neither one of those folks are trying to create their own walled-garden nearly as much as anybody else
So yeah so his his thought as he writes of the Atlantic is that all of these things are inhibiting
This is kind of
Cert this inability to circumvent
Proprietary
Code is
Why we don't see why we can't have nice things on the Internet of Things
This is why we can't have
Interoperability
Is a problem
And it seems like it's getting worst some degree
Because we're
Because we have
More products
Entering the market
And then we also see that we want them to connect
There are enough products out there that are starting to be on the market
Connect to other products
That we have
Oh
Will see this connected
Like here's a great example
Sample thermos makes it connected water bottle that connects to a Fitbit
And you're like
Hey cool there's a connected water bottle that measures my hydration
Connect my Fitbit
But I don't have a Fitbit I have a jaw bone why does my jaw bone
And you're like
And if you me you you email VPR at
Why doesn't this connect to my job on there like all we haven't talked to them
You're like
Guys
Get on it
When it be just so much easier is
If they didn't have to actually do this
Text negotiation yes
I'm as everybody here
Who listens to the show is probably like yesterday that you said this already
Okay
So I just wanted to drive you to it or dry your attention to it because I thought
You know this was an interesting perspective we don't hear
A lot about Digital Millennium Copyright Act
So it's like that
That made me think
I don't know what the
Entirely Act
I'm sure I'm going to bring it up with people as I go to CVS and talk to them
So
Will find out
And if you're thinking about buying a
Connected
Device a smart home device in the next year
Please
Choose Wisely
Choose
Wisely that's probably the best thing to choose a product that is friendly and plays well with others
Although I would have said you because he plays Wells
With others and then they did the friends of hue program although they did
Walk it back
So they quickly they quickly backtracked on on that I know we talked about it last week but for those who missed it
Third-party bulbs
Or no longer going to be working with
The Hue bridge and about a day
After hearing people complain about it
To said that we are going to change that back to the way it was sort of
Yeah
Speaking of Phillips
They only say a coffee maker brand
Which I may or may not be pronouncing correctly because
Because I live on the internet and I only read things
Sako is there coffee maker brand and
They have launched in the US
A
Connected coffee maker
And this is a connected coffee maker that is a super automatic coffee maker
Which is the time that grinds the beans
It has like a
Brew unit that
Does everything from grinding the beans still like
Pretty the pressure in the
Pumping out of fool
Fancy cup of espresso or
Got the milk frother
Macchiato
Chino whatever you want
Does everything all you have to do is like
Clean it once
It's amazing
I own one
I really love it
Mine is not as fancy as this one this is a
The MSRP is 4000
The dollars
Yeah I know
Williams-Sonoma has it
What is on sale for $2,500 Before Christmas normally is $3,000
So this is fancy it is the
Grand
Arista Avanti
It's sold in Germany now coming to the US
Phillip send it to me to try
And it was
A lot of fun
And it's
Connect it
Say that she's talking about the coffee just going on in my nose and
Happy Meal
I know that doesn't taste as good
The Bluetooth does not
Okay it has Bluetooth
It has an app
It has
It has some form of
Intelligence
I'm going to say the Bluetooth felt more like a gimmick
Than anything
One because it didn't connect
Anything else
If Phillips wants to make it connect to other things it could be maybe better
Like maybe if it wants to connect to my jaw bone to be like most aces up
Turn on the coffee machine
Although this thing heats up in a matter of like
Less than a minute
So
I don't really need it to like
I mean it's not like a huge weight for coffee
Still be nice to like connected to if this then that and set up a trigger on the echo.and
Same can you make me a cup of coffee and by the time you get downstairs
Ready that's true I would also like to be my echo Jeeves
Because that would be amazing
Cousin Augustine Cheves
Make me a cup of coffee
All right while I'm dreaming
So yes if all that happens
That would be
But that doesn't happen the best thing about it the Bluetooth is that it gives you access to the app
And the app does make it easier
Then that it has a
It hasn't LED touch screen
And
There's a lot of buttons you can press there's like
I think 16 total drinks you can make
So
There is a kind of a lot to do on the touch-screen although you can do it
All from the
Touch screen
That's fine
Doing it from the app is a little bit easier
But
If you can't find your phone
You're kind of like
If you're like myself and don't always have your phone on you
You may kind of be like
You gotta do not want to run back upstairs and
I like the app cuz it's got pretty little pictures of all the drinks so if you're not sure what it's called you can just do it by sight if that's the one
Yes Andrew is Daffy drinks
From the app you can be like
Oh this needs to be much stronger or I need more milk or I need less milk or I need less coffee any more coffee
Yeah I did this
It's very much fun
So
So but it also feels kind of like
Do I need the Bluetooth
Yeah
Maybe not but let me did you know if they sell egg
Similar non-bluetooth Edition like you have you
They do and I'm curious what the price differences
I don't know
Do you think I would know
But I don't know
You can like
The thing is that they come out with new models all the time
Yeah no like you could probably buy last year's model
Very similar features for like
Much less
So
Where you could buy like a giraffe or a
DeLonghi
We're getting into it we're getting into clock
But
If you're if you really want
Today's high-end really amazing connected coffee maker
The coffee on this
Is consistent
It makes it has a nice
Crema Crema
The little the little foamy stuff on top of your espresso is nice
I will say that the flat white was not good
So
The flat white not gray
Cappuccino
Good the latte
People ask me if they wanted me to test it with almond milk
Soy milk
Skim milk
So I did those
It's Frost all of them
It didn't do as good as the job as it did with whole milk
I don't drink those milks normally so they all tasted pretty bad to me
Because I just don't drink them
Whole milk or nothing for me
Kind of nice but it still tastes too kind of watery like an almond milk
Short
So what if you like almond milk it tasted
Like toasted almond
Belk in the drink so
I'm going to stick with my Nespresso
So the coffee was consistent I felt like if you had good beans
You probably could do it
I have a friend who has the Jura A9
Like I will make coffee amazingly well kind of fancy coffee maker
If you came over any tested it and
We found some that we like
We found that
Some that we're kind of watery
But you can actually dial
Up your bean Grimes and all that kind of stuff you can customize like just about everything on this thing so I feel like it
You spent a lot of time on it
You probably could have cheese like
Greatness
Except
That is that
No I wish I wish you would had like some kind of Wi-Fi access so I could like make you a cup of coffee on the show
Mm
I felt like Wi-Fi would really do Oaks
Okay my to ask for this Woody Wi-Fi access
And then a little weight sensor
At the bottom
Iowa caucus
Yes you can see if there was a cup there because
We even with Bluetooth access
Like I couldn't always tell if I wanted to make a cup of coffee and I couldn't see the coffee maker if there is if I couldn't remember if I put
Put a cup there or not
Except for if there's a cut there
And I was like
I had to get up before I made another
Oh the shame
Theogony
Moving a couch in the bed
But you be you be then burning calories doing so and that's what apparently a lot of people are doing this holidays
Because they bought
Surprisingly fitbit's
Yeah it was like the top app in the in the App Store
So the conclusion was that everyone has fitbit's and everyone loves them
And they all got them for Christmas
And not shot way up
And ye everyone got tickets for the holidays
Everybody should be tracking their steps
Still have my job
Had a lot of server trouble leading into the holiday
Which
You know was a pig
No one's talking about this
Except on the jaw bone like
Jawbone support Twitter
Account but you know if you got a job own and it's been slow to upload
Know that they have been having some real issues
And they're really not copping to it
Except they're they're like
Some server trouble it should be fixed now but mine is still actually uploading kind of slowly
So and apparently other people are still having
Trouble so
Now you know but this brings me to CES that was a really long convoluted segue
CES
Where
Fitness
Trackers
Are going to be a thing but not the thing
We're going to keep it pretty General because I'm actually going to be at the show
Next week
So all I'll be bringing you all kinds of crazy things that I have seen
I'm including
News and things from the show but
Big trends
AR
Cars
Probably cars
I'm sticking with cars lot of traffic
Yeah I think I think intelligent self autonomous type cars you can talk a lot about the technology there and over
Volkswagen is
I wanted a keynote one of the big Keynotes there
Robots that they've always had a little robot section and it's growing every year there
Intel makes sense
Intel CEO Brian
Brian Kang
Kevin and Stacy who talked about people whose names they cannot pronounce
And products whose names they cannot print
That should be the name of our show
Alright so Brian K from Intel's going to be there I expect a lot on Intel's wearable strategy
I'm in iot strategy
As well as
I need you're going to see more of the smart home stuff you know the whole enter the homework tomorrow kind of
We saw a lot of that last year
And the year before in the year before but last year was really the year of iot
This year yes I got tons of products I'm going to see lots of stuff I got so my inbox
Just bursting at the seams with crazy products
But
I'm telling you
Cars
Cars cars cars
Also a lot of
What is it a lot of
I think I'm just see a lot of Smart Home Products from larger vendors
The last year I saw a lot of Smart Home Products from light
Newer kind of companies
I'm getting a lot of invites from Big established companies with
Products
Yeah and I can't say too much because I don't want to like now
Outland Marcos
What's better with the tricky part of December going into city as we have some information ahead of time and we can
You know we can't really give that away but
I think you're you're spot-on I don't think
I don't think those smaller smart-home players are going to be gone or missing I think they're just going to get lost in all the noise
Canasa because you're right the bigger companies an hour
Moving into the space as it continues to grow
Unless you remember last year homekit
What is the big thing
This year
Man
Homekit is nowhere on the horizon and we're still waiting for a
Just so people are where we're still waiting for a lot of homekit profiles
We haven't seen a video like profile yet on homekit all we've got right now
AR
Kind of some sensors
We've got the
We have door locks we don't even have door lock
I can't think of any
I know that
A few of the hubs now work with homekit in stands newest Hub does
Outlets
And we've got lights
Space it's a very limited selection though at this point
And that's because we still don't have
Homekit works with profile
Rights we have a profile for each product
Comes out on the mark
And we're still waiting for a video
I think we're still waiting for
Door lock
Do we have the homekit door lock
If we don't
Then we're still waiting, I don't think so
I lie to you
The Schlage
Touch sense door lock
August has a homekit door lock to that's out on the Moor
Yes they do
So we have it or not profile it's still just seems like
It's still talk about him or talk about homekit then actual
Products and platforms and here's your whole solution make life easy that's kind of what was promised and
It's just not here yet
It's a Walled Garden that's still being built
Pretty pretty lame water garden
Who loves Gardens
It's just a while there's nothing interesting in there you don't want to live there yet
All right
And in terms of new device categories
I'm not seeing a lot
But
There is one
Product category I am really excited about it's not a product
Categories of product
I was going to tell you about it because it's so freaking exciting and then we should probably in the show cuz we have talked a lot
All right
Just company
Cut stack lighting
I interviewed them
A couple like before before this version of the iot podcast
And I've got a review unit coming
End
When it's here we're going to talk about it in Greater depth
But
It is a light
That is
Responsive in this is actually really interesting Trend we're going to keep following
It's
Instead of calling them smart because they feel like the
Turn smart has been to so bastardize
Over there,
Responsive and idea is these lights have a motion sensor an ambient light sensor
And a
Occupancy sensor
I'm not sure
And what happens is when you walk in
They
Turn on
And if it needed if there is not enough light in the room and they also turn on in regard in Black release
Listen to the circadian rhythms of the day
So
Their white lights
Politico
Brighter in the morning and
Turn yellow room dimmer towards the evening
And so the idea is they
Turn on
When they're needed
And when someone's in the room
When you leave
Turn off
So
And you do nothing
And then they also will
Work with other systems
Is the plan
So they will act as
An occupancy sensor for your neck
Or other
Thermostat
Overtime
And they will work through if this then that
So why am I really pumped
About these and I'm going to get
Towards sometime after CES I'm going to get the first so they come and be our 30s right now
And there are a hundred and fifty-four
Hub and to BR30
And it's 60 bucks for each additional bulb
I know they're very expensive there Q expensive
That's okay then just starting out with a new product I mean you know until you can scale up and bring your prices down today
Crosstown I did that
I'm not
I'm not going to write them off because of that
And see how they work
Yeah. I'm at the exactly cuz I'm kind of excited
Occupancy
Without
Relying on a phone
Kind of exciting
Right
Is it said it's semi presents
Semi presents but they report back like if there's a person in there
Without needing the phone
So so in a sense I can provide presents information to other devices such as your nasty as you said
In particular
Great
I'm but I'm I'm still kind of stone
Because you know man
And left
That is that is the product I'm really excited about
And that is kind of some thoughts about CEs
And we will
Now let you guys go I have a cool guest for you
His name is Rodger pills
Kiss the chief Innovation officer at Pitney Bowes
What is the mailing
Company
Which you guys are like what
It's crazy but
He's part of a
He's actually
Contributed to a report on
Venture industrial switches
A new model of venture-capital at Big Fortune 500 companies
For The Internet of Things
So for all of you guys out there who are like
How am I going to get in with a big company is
Startup or
I'm a venture capitalist and how am I going to get my startups in a big companies
And I don't know how can innovate Around The Internet of Things
This is for you
If you are playing Joe who is like
I'm just connecting my house
This may not be for you unless you were like really excited about mail
And then you can listen to it because we talked about
Pranking
Printing machines
Stop
There you go stay tuned and thanks for listening
Hi everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast and today's guest is Rodger pills who is the chief innovation
Russian officer
At Pitney Bowes
Hi Roger how are you doing today
I'm great how are you
I'm awesome
So thanks for coming on the podcast today
We are
Excited to have you
I am
Talking to you because I picked up a survey for the industrial internet
Consortium all about
This concept of a new wave of investment in iot startups
And basically
It was about
Venture industrialist
It's about a new type of venture capitalist
Coming in
Kind of investing in
Startups I'm going to talk about that but first
I want you to talk to me about what you do
Pitney Bowes
My role as Chief Innovation officer
And also lead our Innovation initiative has been our technology alliances
Okay and when I take a pic nebo's I think
You're going to hate me for this I think Direct Mail
But I know you guys do so much more than that so
You want to give us like that.
Maybe even ten thousand foot view of
What else you guys do
Absolutely
Nelly operations and
Technology products
2/3 + SMD and Enterprises
3 billion dollars
Billion dollars of business in software and e-commerce services that grew 20% last year
Over the last decade the company
How about you
B company with very strong book physical
And digital assets
Tyler Converse
So
What kind of challenges do you guys
Like so getting to this kind of venture industrialist
Concept
Which I don't know if we're
We're on board with yet but
Canada
Stadia was
You're going to need
A special form of strategic investor
To invest in the industrial internet
And I'd be curious from your take
Not not just about this but
What are you guys looking for when you're looking for
Startups or
Companies to work with
In the internet
Sure we have a certain set as an objective that we're trying to accomplish and
We look for partners
In the industry that will
Filter in gas we believe we have applied technology that's needed to cry to sleep
Customers
Video of expertise about the Technologies but then also
I got the use of Internet
Obscene
Technologies to transform business operation to transform service
Driven are partnering approach
Journey that we have done so far has occluded to serve our large
Enterprise business
And that was the partnership with
GE where we were looking to a big company in that case
That's provide a form and a set of application services that would help us
That we're also
I'm working with a VC back
West Coast water company
To provide
Network
Connectivity and security
4in internet-of-things initiative we have for our
Business
If it's a smaller if you keep a company that has the capability to work
Certainly not for you to work with them especially if their identity
And can help us
Okay and so
That that's kind of awesome because you got both ends of the spectrum
And
What I took from this kind of
Report
A couple things one is this idea that
Working with clients
Like your side
Clients like
Yourself
Midea is the venture capitalist
May not be super successful investing here
Is because they don't have the domain expert
Expertise
Industrial clients
Like yourself require
And at the exits here may not be huge so maybe they should leave it tonight corporate development officer
And I don't know do you
Do you have an opinion on
I think it matters by the component of Internet of Things
Technologies are activities in
I think we would think of it as a value chain
Subsistence
Technology
That's required from a security networking employee to extract
Data from machine
I can't believe that
Could be a relatively horizontal technology that could be applied to a broad brush
Total addressable Market
There is
Networking in cloud-based
Big Data
Collection ingestion and analytics capabilities
And I'd argue that that later as well
Could be applied to a broad total addressable Market
In the top layer which is
The set of applications that are created to help
Crazy business outcomes that the Industrial company
And that maybe something that has a more limited total addressable Market
And it's probably more nuanced to the needs of unlike ourselves or particular subset.
What about this idea
The big
Fortune 500 companies out there
They just don't want to
Work with starter
I feel like in reading this report
There was a lot of openness
What's in there
2 startups because
There's so much Innovation coming from
The start of
System that a lot of these companies
Is feel like they can't
Afford to miss out on
And I thought that was kind of an optimistic way of
Exciting
Equally optimistic in there
We do work with quite a few venture-capital back companies that we we may not
Work with startups that we perceive
Have a significant amount
Business risk associated with
I rely on them to
I'll be around if we using
But
The reason we liked working with Venture capital-backed companies that maybe Yer
B round C round type
Venture Capital companies is just as he say it can typically be
A cutting-edge technology and I'll help us transform where we're going off of Transformer product roadmap
Accelerated a year to sister that feeling
It's been a great marriage
A customer that we have that they don't
And she'll channels and indirect channels that we have and they don't
So it's a very symbiotic relationship that sits work very well and in many
Avicii. Companies as partners
Also consumer Technologies in in we
Actually really love to have them as customers of ours cuz they drive
Requirements
I think intelligently and accelerates the capabilities of our own products
Oh I like that I bet
Are they demanding customers they're like
Hey why can't I venmo you buy page
My payments
They're incredibly demanding or not
Quite a few humbling meeting
With the
It's so expensive and tastic and and what we try to do is work with
I've clients at BC back companies as clients usually perceived as having
Requirements that you need be
A year or two ahead of the rest of the clients we serve and sodas demanding and
Don't they look it up you say why aren't you doing a PhD in
We actually like it because the active AT&T
Looking at it for the rest of the clients that you can sleep there
So I have to ask because this site I feel like it's probably part of your job
How do you think
The Internet of Things is going
How to change Pitney Bowes in the next year
And then in the next
3 years
This is one of our most important initiatives that the company
We have
A set of 552 foundational Technologies as we describe them that we believe
Poppy
Tri Core competencies to transforming Who We Are
Are corporate strategy and vision is to
Leopard 2 combination of physical assets and digital assets
The power Converse
And naturally know
Internet the internet saying it's right at that cross section of physical and digital
It's perfectly aligned with the key we are and how we're going to
Stop by Viper
First inner core traditional male business both for SMB and
Score
Large Enterprises will we are
Well on your way with initiatives
Connect
I all of our machines Express reviews and for Enterprises
To collect
At 2
Storage in a cloud-based
Dictator
Platform
And to provide set of value-added application New Jersey Solutions
Traditional mailing business
Really transforming it
Did digital into a new setting
Halsey
Thermostat
In either homes or or Office Buildings with transform
Buy Nest into a digital devices connected to the internet
In the closet is providing new diet
BHS
Utilities used to date
Will I have to stop these machines are these machines
Put addresses in postage like
Thinking machines ER
But what machines are they
Yes. Still in the SMB area
Over a million customers that have
Machines are in their offices that do put postage on
Envelopes that we have a set of
Capabilities that allow us to collect and you were already providing this like report
Not too well over a hundred thousand of our customers
Are growing
I significantly
And Internet of Things
To applied additional capabilities such as
Ink subscription services
Which is already happening and in other types of off the Craftsmen such as printers
I need franking machines
Look like a fax machines are or printers but they are actually
Revolving credit cards in Disguise and we
Actually
7 billion dollar transaction
And I deserve an additional set of financial services
Start Internet of Things capabilities I will facilitate
Large Enterprises
It's the other end of the spectrum and the machines we provide
Largest telecommunication companies in the world
Actually it's big
Shuffle cards
Sleep with large Machines of ours that are
Large locations that that look a lot like plants or factories
And we have one large egg for example producing 800 million
Statements forticlient every single year
Should be
Define vim
And the need to get everything right all the time is
Amanda
And we've got machines that produce over 20000
Call letters
An hour and so
Part of our Industrial
Is the extraction of data from these machine
And ensuring that the machines are always and we prevent any unplanned downtime
And then lastly capacity planning and job scheduling can be done around
Build your own computer
In the last play Replay in
It's really important to Pitney Bowes with worry
A key technology provider to IRT implementation
Stranger things
Most exciting Casas is election earlier that were
A leader and let's go location and television
The application of geospatial Analytics
How to solve business problems
And with the Advent of iot
Need to look at itdata through the lens
Location
And get pixel Analytics
It's become mission-critical
Mobile operator
Global leaders
To I wanted to
Understand
Quality of their Network
In all of their
Self-operated
You wanted to do so not just buy that can you hear me now
Commercial but actually based on real transmission
Foreman
So it was an Internet of Things implementation the date is coming from
Tens of Millions
Cell phone data collected in Big Data
Aeducan Plantation and it's our location intelligence that is
Just a chalet analyzing billions of the beta Squad
Mobile operator knows really anything that's in your network
I know where the market to sell
After the third and final Pizza
Coyotes impact company closes
That's actually leveraging our strength Ram location intelligence
And data management and healthy
Companies like I asked you to drive their business.
Those are all really interesting use case
Actually I'm a very different
So I can't wait I would love to hear more but we are out of time
And
I appreciate you coming on the show to talk about this actually
I kind of want to go see one of the
The big giant
Posters
Postage generation machines in one of the big Banks
Absolutely
Sound exciting a factory tour everybody let's go
Thank you for coming on the show this week