Hey everyone Welcome to The Intern
Turn out of things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham
And this is our special CS edition of the podcast it is sponsored
Machineq
A Comcast company
So this past week Kevin and I were at CES that is
The Consumer Electronic Show
Weighs about a hundred and eighty thousand other people in Las Vegas
This your show the attendance
Seemed
Much
Much less than in previous years
Usually there's a lot more bottlenecks a lot more bodies on the show floor
Really
Both Kevin and I were kind of amazed that we could just walk around without much interference at all
I don't know what to make of that except for
Possibly might be a rocky 2019
We cover the news in some of our prior podcast but every year I'd like to bring out the show that we record at sea
CSN we asked attendees their thoughts in a little bit about why they are here
In this episode as I said is brought to you by machineq
Machine key with a Comcast company focused on iot in the global Enterprise B2B Market
Their iot platform includes best-in-class Lora based Gateway Hardware
Enterprise-grade management Cloud software
MSecure Wireless connectivity to help you easily create your own dedicated iot Network
This enables you to speed up Innovation and reduce time-to-market
You can learn more at www. Machineq
Dot-com
So this year was actually the first year at CES for one of my interviewees
This was Mike nefkens who is the CEO of the newly-created
Resideo company
Resideo was created when Honeywell split out its consumer-facing businesses from its industrial commercial
Videomix thermostat that provides Home Security
It also makes the part sounds like inside your water heater HVAC
System
So Mike and I chatted about the changes happening in the Smart Home
PS plus March
I feel like a lot of things
We're like
Finally getting to where we
I've been saying we would be
Would you guys actually very curious
Where you're going to sell
A lot going on in the smartphone market in what you said about incremental is right you know over the last 10 years people
Beverly adopted one single product at a time no one wakes up one day and said today I'm going to make my home smart
Now finally seeing companies that are
You know they have the platform
Act ability in the homes be able to now bring a lot of this together to really give you a smart home experience
Entertainment
And Beyond some of the basics
Pro Channel or a channel has finally caught up please be froze for typically screwdrivers and Ham
And they Now understand basic networking
Make sure that these connected
Business model is going to look like both for you and for the dealers and service providers
Yes
Writer of call
We're hoping for sets at our products
So we can actually sell the product to the dealer as well as happy as our software
And other services I will actually charge a monthly fee or annual fee or whatever for certain services
A long time like nobody thinks about their water heater until it goes out
Replace every 3 years
So actually starts with technology into those things how are you changing
I think about warranties communicating with the customer hell on the supper last or even how you build it
Two or three weeks before it's going to go down if there's something wrong it will start to consume more energy or it will start to leave
Control unit connected an alert to yourself
Tractor
And what it means that you have to have a contractor's somebody
Signs your home
You know everybody every person
Has a general physician
Pro
Invisalign
What should the positions have with Lake Fitbit data or heart rate monitoring data because they don't
I don't actually want to be on the hook if something goes wrong
I'm serious about against liability
Let's say your water heater explodes and maybe our contractor missed that memo I don't know
We've done with combustion units where you have natural gas coming in with a flame so that's what we're here for and that's where
The contractor can team up with us and you know we'll make sure that these units are secure their safe
I will stand behind how they work
Another first timer at the show was Procter & Gamble
The company started building connected Tech back in 2015
And at this show they were showing off connected toothbrushes skincare products and a connected error
Freshener I spoke with
Thanh ha who is an R&D director for air care products
A P&G
About what they've learned selling connected devices to mainstream
Consumers
And what connectivity offers PNG
Cheese business
Okay I imagine all of you guys have heard of proctoring
Hair care products the last time I checked
Error
Freshener kind of system that was so long ago
And now this is her first year at CES So Tan
Why are you guys here
We have
So since you talked to his last we have developed
Autonomy technology
That really addresses consumer tension
So for example the product that mites
Team is here with this called
And what we learn from the
Fire Trine CSM
Home
Product
Technology
Self-control
Consumer
Because it was what space in terms of the
It didn't solve the biggest consumer tension
That people have
With continuous air
Air freshening products
Which is
Starts too strong
Goes through a period that's just right and then gets too weak
So with that in mind
What's the right
Consistency
They want the exact same thing
Burien
So after going through over 30 different
A-Z technology
Deliver this
Consistency
Disconnectivity
It possible for you to use
The thermal inkjet
So we could have done it without conductivity
What what kind of activity does
Control example in our test
What we learn
Is over 95% of those
They love to schedule
That's what connectivity allows additional control
Is the delivery system that allows
Precision delivery
Connectivity allows that last layer of the control that the
People are sick
AIC schedule it through conductivity through the app
They're getting up getting ready for work or school
A few hours in the evening
Coralista after dinner
I'm home from work
Store hours on the weekend
And so that's what kind of activity allows and is amazing with the consumer
You guys have been experimenting with
What have you learned about making your products connected to the mainstream audience
Yeah I helped solve a problem
There's a quadruped probably smaller
That's kind of cool I'll buy it but for the mainstream I think it's like it's kind of help
Either
Make the task easier
Or improve experience like the app
To be in scheduling with area
I think that's what we've learned
And so as we look at all the different technology
The question we ask is how is this technology helped me implement
Technology
Really help solve it
No problem
In disconnectivity open up new avenues in the R&D Department
Oh hey choirs
Work experience
It what it does is it allows
Another layer of control
And so
The most obvious one in this Bay Area cases instead of running 24/7
Or having some
We determine what the schedule is
The product
If people can tell us what they like what they don't like and you know that you probably know with your other podcasts
Your people are very very open to providing feedback until that connectivity
Is actually a direct conduit to sub
Zoomer so we get a lot of input that way to
How are you guys
Bedding technology and everything
I feel like Technologies just going to become like
Right it's not going to be something that we
We think about her so how do we get there faster
Because I think
Consumer Brands actually
How we do that is with product like area
Artists like the Gillette heated razor the Opti
Is new technology always comes out of
Price premium
Right so I think the
State to rush out there and try to implement
But just from an affordability and
No problem
But will be like for a POTUS like area
That required
Technology to solve
Adding conductivity
This will be a natural way to
More available in more home
As a steel drive there the cost will go down
Alright thank you so much time
Building a connected air freshener or adding connectivity to your operations can be hard
So let's turn to our show sponsor machine q and its CEO Alex Crum
To talk about how Enterprises
Even those who may not attend CES can adopt the iot without a lot of fuss
Alex Banks
So how is machineq helping the Enterprise adopt iot
Applications fast
Enterprises are actively piloting many low-power iot devices today unfortunately
Many aren't stealing fast enough because they look the scale lacrosse
Particular vertical application
Infrastructure which becomes difficult to manage
Have devices
Digital air
Gateway as well we offer a centralized
Best in Class
Lora Gateway
Couple of software to manage those gateways and software to manage
Multiple types of devices
Rather than taking multiple Court
On routers and switches in your factory or in your store
Machineq Gateway and Gateway management tools
Companies and partners issue lights
Where can I go to find out more about machines
Can you can go to machineq. Com to learn more about our products and services
Chewy.com
I like the CEO of resideo or P&G this wasn't
Colors first time
That was last year
However the maker of fixtures
Toilets
Tubbs was the talk of this year show with its
Madam a enabled
Toilet
That's right
Part of some of the collections they put
The Amazon Echo
Into a toilet
So you can talk to it
I asked Jonathan Bradley a Kohler
Why
Closer decided to make that decision
And how
Okay color was the star of CES
But there's actually real value
Spill my spaghetti
What's the weather like
Yasso Kohler 145 year old Ran
The meeting design innovation in the bathroom space
You already know that
80% of consumers bring a smart device into a tablet or phone into the bathroom
And we already know that 13% are using voice to do some
Where did China give him that experience more elegantly in more Integrated Health Providers use cases
Next products
Why do I
Especially because you got it embedded in the mirror
Which is also
Yasso the choice
Right so
Go ahead and better than Amazon Alexa we know that every morning you start in the bathroom
Information download weatherby's what's my schedule like for today what's the weather help me decide what to wear or fiction
Play music
And it also Alexis
Oh my gosh sitting on the toilet and telling madam
Weird
I'm sure there are people out there
Let's talk about
The overall it cuz you got a bathtub you have the sink mirror and you have the toilet
You have a shower
Yeah so what's great about car companies offer the full port
Polylok products
Bathroom for consumers weatherbeeta shower the tub the toilet
Vanity mirror
Entire collection so we can help curate that portfolio products for you in build that smart
To walk me through my
Kohler smart. I have just woken up
Just woke up
Ray's lighting
You could have it energized the most bright setting in the morning to help you wake up
Get ready and start your day
Then once you're energized for the morning right now have Alexa start your morning routine so your shower can turn on your lights
Your lab write setting
After your shower your coffee pot start all that can be automated while you're still in the bathroom finishing up today
Okay and right now I have a Google home mini in my bathroom and I use it to listen to podcast while I shower
It's fine
Okay so these are products that I plan to buy
As you add technology to them does that shorten their lifespan
So we understand these are fixtures in your bathroom
Created over the updates for all these products between voices going to be around for some time once these products be updated
And how did you guys do this did you hire
What is the process because
Embedded boards in like software development that does not feel like
Maybe your class of expertise
Yeah so a couple ways talk about that so we've actually technology products for over a decade
Add intelligent toilet if you have Smart bathtub to ever hydrotherapy we've been doing this for some time
This is an axe progression in a mixed bag of how our products work
We've also got a partner with the right vendors to make this ecosystem to Microsoft azure
Is our our partners Rockside environment
Done that was right for making the products right and then the infrastructure right together so it's been a partnership
Another big Trend in both a bathroom and outside of it was aging-in-place
We're all very concerned about the demographic shift to more seniors and not enough
People to take care of them
Beer in the US or in Japan where this has been happen
Sing for a while
So we saw a lot of robots who could help care for the elderly
A lot of fall detection sensors and tons of wearables
Even companies in the smart
Home we're trying to find ways to build
Non-intrusive sensor send to device
Help keep an eye on grandma or Grandpa
Neil Mitchell of
Leo
Explains why his company pivoted from a smart night light
2 a device that helps
Keep track of people inside there
Alright Sunil
I remember Leo launching a couple years back
Listen for
Seem to gain a lot of traction
We're here now at CVS and you pivoted can you tell me a little about what you're doing now
Incorporate a bunch of senses
Jamaican impression
I can find your cell phone real food making its activity away
Intelligent
Independent Living parents
So in addition to
Okay
Grandma grandma may want to know that
Form I can have these in different houses then we're all on the same
Personal best
Cell phone
What sensors are inside then
This is a Resurgence of radar you guys were seeing and everywhere which is kind of a neat thing to do and is typically More Fry
Privacy-focused
Service plan now at this night light used to be like $99
What are you charging for it now
Maybe one of the bedroom one of the living room on The Fosters
It's grandma gets up in middle of night
And once again it's time to hear from our sponsor machineq
Let's go to Alex
Alex Winter that we saw last year is that companies are looking for
Specific vertical Solutions
They need a lot of help and expertise
In building out there iot infrastructure
How can machineq helpthe
We can help you in two different ways we work of hundreds of Vertical Sleeve providers
Who has deep
Sector expertise by building their own devices navigation layers and if you happen to need a mouse
Water detection device
Wedding
System
It happens to be more aware we have a whole slew of things
And we can help match those particular Solutions with your needs
We don't have an existing partner today
We can even build and help design
Particular device that you need
Internally
Eventioneers web designers
We can prototype and commercialize that
For your particular request
Alex
Where can I go to find out more about how machineq can help me with
Particle iot
Applications
The best place to find information of the machines.com
All of the sensors in Connected devices in the world matter very little if you can't send the data around the home or two
The cloud
So for the rest of the show we're going to focus on the network connectivity Trends we saw at sea
Faster WiFi
Lower-powered Wi-Fi
Bluetooth mesh and
The return of that. Which is a wireless interoperability standard
Rings
Thread and Wifi together
Are all in the same
So first up
Let's talk to Brian Bedrosian
VP of marketing at Cypress semiconductor
About Bluetooth mesh and wife
Okay so one of the big topics here is PS is as always
Smart Home
Wireless standards Etc so Bluetooth Alliance is
Really making a big deal about with mesh
And they're also adding profiles for various Smart Home
Home devices
And I'd love to get your opinion on
How this is actually going to play out
Profiles on top of a radio
Feel like an effort
It might lead interoperability problem
I think you have the Bluetooth Sig has been great about
Creating interoperable profiles
For audio and
Mouse and keyboard for years
They've done it better than anybody else
If you look at the whole wearables
Market
Fitness Inc
Distinguish Bluetooth is
Technology
You know growing across new segments
Big Moose horn
Okay
And are you excited you see that people are getting really adopted for the smart home or is it going to be you know maybe the more
Traditional technology
Are we really believe that Bluetooth will begin to expand more on the Smart Home
Wi-Fi horses of the home internet
And this is the factor standard for home networking
Who is this is the most compatible technology
Stand Together there and every smartphone in
How was the consumers used
Control their home
So we really see the combination of Bluetooth and Wi-Fi evolving to really be
The center of the home network
You think we'll see Bluetooth power sensors
Baidu Bluetooth
Energy is really brought together a whole new
Realm of ultra-low-power products
Coupled with high-power Tran
And with mask
Completing the Bluetooth profile
We can connect every device together feeding back in
To the home control
Okay so Cypress is a chip vendor and you guys bought broadcom
Wi-Fi
Some Trends you're seeing in Wi-Fi I know here
So far I've seen a lot of
Wifi powered device
Superpower
Hungry
People just don't want to do a tub so I'm very curious what are you
We're seeing two different direction
Jensen WiFi right now
We'll announce our Wi-Fi 6
Technology the latest generation of
11 a.m.
Gigabit-speed Wireless
Tomorrow for automotive entertainment
Power wife
And there are a couple
Companies that are now
Prodigy
With our new 2018
Ammeter wire
Best products
Better delivering power
Consumption profiles very close to what Bluetooth was
A couple years ago
So battery operated Wi-Fi is
Is here
Wait a second
All right
Is this a new Wi-Fi standard like Halo or something weird like that or is this just low-power Wi-Fi 6
This is just low power Wi-Fi fantastic architectures 802 11ac friendly
And works in any home network
Talk about this in battery life on this kind of sensor like or is it for sensors or something like that or we flipped
More for like cameras or that kind of
Yeah right now the low-power Wi-Fi is really for things more like cameras
Portable music
Things like battery operated
Thermostat
But we'll see one more Evolution pasta
I'll take it into the sun
Hbase as well
That'll be what time frame
12 to 24 months
Going to hold you to that Brian
I will deliver
As you can probably tell I have my doubts about those Wi-Fi sensors happening anytime soon
But I did see some Bluetooth sensors when I visited with Kevin Tate of rigado
We talked about sensors sales and who's buying
We've been talking a lot about Bluetooth here at CVS and I finally found what I was looking for
And this is a big deal for me because
I love sometimes I think there's a lot of power in them
And I
It's more accessible technology
So let's talk about what
To get to this point
Where we have
Sure
A lot of commercial applications
Required
Divisive
Where are you need a device that can do the sensing connect via Bluetooth and then get
2 something
I like it that way
I can translate
Bluetooth profile information
Into something like
Mqtt
What was required
Was
Getting that pipeline
Standard
So that companies could not have to build every step
So a lot of what we've done in the
Gateway's make that
Ble
Bluetooth low energy
To mqtt translation
Very easy
So in particular
Wide variety
Anything that's
Bluetooth 4.2 or Bluetooth 5
Appliance can talk to her Gateway
You can talk to it
What is a beacon
Impaired mode
We can even control those devices
Are Gateway and all that can be pushed seamlessly
Go to the cloud it's a little wacky though because people
Hairball blockage
I am curious it does that change
Huge difference when you move into a commercial environment
Verses relying on
A personal foul
And extremely good
Connecting to wireless devices
Running secure applications
Connecting to the cloud so in a lot of ways the infrastructure required to collect sensor data
Restaurants or hospital or a smart office
Looks a lot like a phone
You doing the same thing
Connect devices running applications and pushing data to the cloud
Is short of a someone stapling their phone to to the ceiling of every room
You need an infrastructure that's a little bit different to do that
Still secure
Still scalable but one that can run multiple applications collect data from lots of different types of sensors
Get it where it needs to go
To your point I think the fact that Bluetooth especially
Started with the
Means that the landscape of the infrastructure that
Companies like Regatta recruiting now
Mirrors a lot of the way you used to do it
Okay and what are the big seems that
It's a nasty yes payments just a
We're all trying to. Biote and fighting it's really hard theme
Is this idea of I will package everything up to you
A bunch of whatever
And then give you the date
We seen this with companies like my devices machine
Damn it right now is a sponsor this pretty
Tequila episode
And
You guys are talking about this
Why is this happening and
What are the ramifications
Locations of that
Has a couple of interesting reasons that's happened in and then things that unlocks what is
A lot of iot
He is still in
Pilot prototype
And so companies
What's a company says
I'd love to have temperature and location data
About all these Assets in my warehouse
How to get that date up to the card and see what I can do with it
If it takes them
6 to 9 months to get to the part we actually have the data
Quote see what they can do with it
Then
Tremendously
Right and so being able to me like that
Here's a package that allows you to get the data you wanted
RN
Even and afternoon
Write to the part where you're assessing the business value your testing out the ROI
Figuring out
What it would mean to to invest in a large-scale solution I think that
That unlocks
A lot of power
Was frankly held up by iot industry from a pilot
And who is buying
These types of solutions is it
The guy who in the hospital is trying to keep the drugs what's happening
The answer can be all of the above
One of them
One of the
Areas of focus for us your rigato
Is we are trying to get that data
To a solution provider a systems integrator or an Inn customer
Ultimately needs to be able to
Aircloud
Are there a lot of solutions out there
I would seem more like a stovepipe solution
That you up if you use their sensors
Thundercloud
You can
Take that taser
The customers at work with Elgato
Get the data directly to their own
Cloud
Infrastructure that gives
Ultimately
Datastream
Becomes the point of intersection
Empire last interview I try to figure out what happened to thread and why this is the third year that we're hearing about
Gdb in thread coming together
Sadat.
I still haven't seen any products on the market touting thread or..
So Daniel mineta
Co-founder of mmb networks and a member of the zigbee board of directors
Explains why
What are the new things happening
The idea is
Thread
Which is yet another wireless
Call over things like
Wi-Fi
And this is actually
The second-year we've heard about that. At CVS
So I'm curious
Why we're hearing the six
Been talking about..
ICS
And I think
Because we have to keep in mind while Beast
Bodies Leipzig
Years ago
What we announced
Distance
Interoperability
Reliably
Mosto
The date
Animal that's running
Networks that aren't too sticky
Like bread and other
Fred was
The first one that
Guichos
Last year we announced that
Actually
He had me but I think had a name for it
2 years ago last year
Was..
That
What the Fred group
We had reached on
An early version of
Released
We invited people
Come and join
To look at the Spectre
Start working with it we had devices
Operable on this Earth
And now at CVS
Pronouncing
Despective
The 100 status
Completed spec
Developer
Start working on will that work
Going to change
Also important
Especially
Is that
And not only that but we work
The Fred group
Work that.
Available on
To ensure that there is
One is not
More assertive
Haitian houses
You both in one
1 check
One process
Certified on
Ghost bread
Why is it
Consumers should I care about
Because
City of Moore
So what does it mean for
Sweating over the past couple of years the smart home has kind of been a wild west
Home and
What do they know it or not the way they've been
Connecting them is by
Creating account for that device
Connecting it to that bend
Answers cloud service
The knot vendors Cloud Server
Stocks today
Amazon Cloud
The Google Cloud
What's that mean
Communicate from there
Administrative work
The first
One or two
Two or three devices or maybe the first
3 months out of the box
Fall apart a little bit
Scale
Can you have 30 devices
And they're all talk
Controller weather
Alexa
30 different
Cloud what you're going to get is the
This thing where every so I
Doesn't work
Frustrating
We kind of have a tolerance for that on our smartphones I'll find the app crash I'll restart it
We have no tolerance for that
When are lights
Turn off alerts
Bendaroos
Realizing that
The only way to
Especially to the large population
Arnot Tech
Tolerance for
Is not working proper
You need to have sex
Echoes
Who's in my house
Why do I still
I care about this
Maybe a joke
It's almost similar to
Think about
This time in the iot
The internet is here
AOL
Or MSN
And you kind of had to stick
Nose
You had friends on those networks great
If they weren't
Dairy success
Start the internet
Write that
Innovative
Figure out what people actually
Turbo
Emailing that works
But eventually
You did want to talk to
Internet not just what one of those ecosys
And that's kind of where we are in the smart
Major company
Are probably still going to be
Mayberry in Port
Very important
Controller
But they shouldn't
The ones Define
What you can and
Go out and get
New application
The new devices
Just work without having to like log them
Indifferent
Circular counter
Illicitly
One particular
What makes my home just work
I would be very excited
Will say
Okay y'all that concludes the special CES edition of The Internet of Things podcast
Sponsored by machine to a Comcast
To find out more about machineq
Is iot platform
It's Gateway Hardware and it's enterprise-grade
Cloud management software
Visit
Www. Machineq
Dot-com
I'd like to thank Alex Cora Matt machine key
And everyone else at machineq for supporting our CES Show
And I'd also like to thank all of you guys listening to it
We'll see you Thursday with our regularly scheduled show and in the meantime
Enjoy those gadgets