Are you awake
Northern listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
Daytime Jad abumrad and Robert krulwich
Greenbridge
Jordan 13
You got to see this
You got to see the store they're going to bring him to go see liquor store on right hand side
Do make you go make a left that's Bowers actually about receipt and this
Bowers
Is reporter lots of knots Okay so
Three or four years ago I taking the bus down to Delaware and I
Satanist
Crappy hotel and then woke up
Super early like 5 a.m. still dark out to hop in his cap
You got me really excited let me tell you I just started working
Radiolab this is like my first first time I didn't send out to like to just go out and get paid
Can anybody lives on that be so glad it's over
Awesome
And the whole reason
Why I was headed down to this beach with to record myself
Communing with
Horseshoe crab
Have you ever held one looks as if I've never had one in my hands I would love to hold one in my hand
Why are you so very far away right now it's fine
Down to that Beach
Because a few weeks
Earlier alright everybody say something
Hello hello hello Robert my head
Should have fallen into this Rabbit Hole hello we'd spoken with a guy named Alexis Madrigal
Who is a staff writer at the Atlantic how did you get on to horseshoe crabs where did that start do
Late at night I was reading through the site where all these crazy press releases are published called Eureka alert
Dot-com
And I happen to see this really tiny study
Which had the on promising name
Sublethal behavioral and physiological effects of the biomedical bleeding process on the American horseshoe
Crab
Limulus polyphemus
And I thought this is going to be my big story this and then I went and I did
Did that thing that we do now you know horseshoe crab and then Google Images they're on the
Screen going to Alexis he saw
These pictures of a bunch of
Horseshoe crabs
Kind of propped up on these metal racks
And they were all kind of
Tied in place
They are on the row and they all
Had these thin little plastic tubes coming out of their shells
All them and underneath them are what look like kind of a 2 liter bottle
And
There's blue blood in it
Blue
Baby blue blood
And the strain blood
It turned out to be the least interesting part of the story like that sound level like it just the visual that draws you in
Because inside their strange blood
The horseshoe crabs have a kind of superpower
It's one that is help them survive hundreds of millions of years at the Earth is changed
As other species have come and gone and
Challenge has been saving their butt
What is in Saving hours
For decades
Nearly all of modern medicine would not be possible
Without this
Special little thing in their blood
But
You might all be about to change
Oh wow oh what are you doing over there
Is really cool is it like has a
Prom
The sex prom Every Spring I was no we should do we should all go together
It's it's it's in June and it's on the first moon of June Lexus you want to go
I do want to go
Let's go
Which is where I come in test test test test test
Right cuz it ain't being that Robert and Alexis and I actually couldn't go and that it was like okay then send it send
The new guy you know
No I mean at the time it was like you were just Milling around the office
And you look like maybe you needed it Adventure
So we like hey do you want to go see these crabs like to see the sex run
Yeah yeah yeah
So anyways so I go and then when I got there it was
Still pretty early like maybe six 7 in the morning it was
Little bit rainy
But
When you walked
Down the beach it was just littered and in probably
Thousands of horseshoe crab
Yeah there's no way that
We just we get a visual like what does a horseshoe crab look like
Like a semicircle and then there's kind of like this French Shield apart and then there's that
Hill and a catcher's mitt
So there were these hordes of
Scotland catcher's mitts
Got laying around and they improve really slowly
The Eliza may be knocked upside down by the waves
And you could see their soft underbelly that these 10
Lobster like legs
And then walking around them
Wer
A bunch of people
Many of them were from a big pharmaceutical company which will make sense
A second but my guide for this morning on the beach was a guy named
Glen Glen Cove short hair while wearing socks in sand
And I'm the founder and director of the ecologically research and development group
I think I saw that you were the Airforce I was
Controller
And the first time I saw her she cries was in 1969 when I was stationed at Dover Air Force Base
Being a young guy coming down to the beach
Looking for something that might be going on and that's all horseshoe crabs it was until many years later that I
Kind of looped around into this thing but that was the first time I saw the
Certain kind of weirdly fell in love with them
And I became really they're like Champion you're not all that attractive
She been around in a while I find them quite beautiful
Glenn now leads is
You know Educational Tours of horseshoe crabs are especially at this time of the year
And he walked me up and down the beach
Painstakingly explaining to me the rules of the you know what the sex problem
The larger ones
At one point he pointed out two crabs that were stuck together
Attached to that female
That's his gal now locked to one another
Duck
Tie-down
Which makes it harder for them to write themselves
Right now is surf is rough enough
Off where they were
There's a good chance
Would flip them over
And they be okay
But because he's
Hanging in there
The likelihood of that hat
Becomes more remote
But he'll die with her
Seems like a blockbuster Ronin
I had to go back to remember
Burt Lancaster on the beach and I forget what movie that was
The ways
You're crashing over and that was symbolic of the romance
They were both
Open bathing suits
Do you know embrace
Sing one another
Nobody
So we we've got to go to an animal world version
No. Going on
Glenn's romantic I just painted this
Sex orgy as a beautiful
Flowering like a meeting season like
Spring in nature kind of a beautiful thing
But I'm really really quickly was like
What are those know that's gross
The reality of it was kind of horrified
There be like
Isles of crabs trying to have sex with each other Big Dreams of them all
All hooked together
And it would be like going in the wrong direction all the time like
You'd see like one crab in the middle like a female like a bigger one
Call stripping and then three or four males like all trying to mate with this one crowd at the same time
Heading when you look even closer
It turned out the female crab was dead
Like this weird like
Necrophiliac
For some of crabs
It was it was pretty
Raunchy actually
My glasses are getting old
But while I was standing watching all this
You know hurly-burly of crab sex
I was struck by what I think is one of the central questions of the story
Migas
It's almost impossible not to notice that
Oh yeah
A lot of these horseshoe crabs are really banged up
Oh yeah I goes right through like chunks of their shells are missing their eyes are missing
Some of them damn hole that you can see their legs underneath and they're all just fine they just have
I'm all these kind of crazy
What would seem to be fatal injury is but they're all just kind of walking around like it's no big deal
Just consider it on the species level so it like like yours a creature that has lasted hundreds of Millions
Games of years it outlasted the dinosaurs and the asteroid that killed them it outlasted freezing ocean
And it's so far has survived the Industrial Age of human
And you look at in your like
How
What's a secret
And it turns out the part of the answer to that
Has to do with that
Baby blue blood
This is Alexis Madrigal again so our blood is red because
Hemoglobin is rich in iron right and their blood is blue because it's rich in Copper so their molecule that carries
Oxygen for them is called
Hemocyanin but would really interesting about this blood is this chemical system
A slowing down bacteria
So say your horseshoe crab and in your blood there's a little bit of bacteria
Maybe got through the crack in your shell anyway
In your blood are these
Shout for the me besides he's oval cells that are turn on patrol in the bloodstream and when they
Counter kind of bacteria the amoebocytes
Oval cells excrete this substance called coagulation which does exactly what it sounds like
Area around where the intruders are just like
Turns into this like jelly stuff that bacteria that snuck in
Trapped in a bowl of Jell-O
Wow
And a crack in the shell
Amoebocytes
Till that off too
What does it do with a gel that is a poop it out or something
Then at dinner can actually attack the cells once they've been slow down
So it it blobs The Invader and then that's it and then some other
Defense Defenders coming in and take it out take it out
Superpower fighting its tiny battles in the bodies of you rather plain-looking creatures
Touch one of these guys before
First time how does it feel is the reason why people from pharmaceutical companies were on the beach that day
Lithia whole life then you have no idea
Playing out for literally millions of years
One day humans started to catch on to this
End
One human in particular.
To explain we're going to leave the horseshoe crab just for a minute and talk a little bit about
Injectable drugs
That scientist innovator James Cooper
Any relation to James Fenimore Cooper of like the last of Mohicans
He was named after James Fenimore Cooper and his son is also named James Fenimore Cooper
This James Fenimore Cooper told us that while it was
Total Miracle when injectable drugs like
Morphine came onto the scene
It was also
A bit of a night
Mare because they didn't know about bacteria
Occasionally the fluids they were injecting would become contaminated or so does that inject this materials that patients
Get infections and develop terrible fevers or even die
They can be incredibly dangerous to us and so to make sure these drugs were free of bacteria that cause fevers
They didn't just you know try it on a person and see if they died
They checked it
Autorabit
And they would have liked
Like racks and racks of rabbits
Like 24 rabbits in Iraq
They are restrained even that Loosely mean like a pilgrim being punished in the Town Square exactly right
Take a little sample of the thing they wanted to inject into a person and then they would inject that into the rabbit
Ear
And if there's certain kinds of bacteria present
The rabbits will get a fever
The temperature will go up and the way they measure their temperature was with these the electric thermometer
Letters up their bum
So if the rabbits temperature goes up we know we shouldn't put this drug inside a person
But if there's no temperature Spike
This solution is safe to inject into man or woman or children or really anyone so that's how crude it was
Cast wasn't
Really that reliable either because rabbits are like pretty sensitive so even if sometimes don't like seeing new person and will gets
Scared then they'll just have a fever because of that
So is really it was not a great test not great for us
Especially not great for the Rapids
After they would go through a few Testament even after only one
Aegis
They killed them
Enter rabbit Hall of Famer
James Fenimore Cooper my joke is that I love to talk to rabbits because they're all ears
Any way back in the late 60s
Cooper was a grad student at Johns Hopkins University
The end one day one of his professors came up to him in the in the hall or whatever kind of jokingly maybe someone seriously
Is Cooper if you want to get out of this
Institution with your degree
You're going to need to find a way to test for pyrogens
By something other than the rabbit basically
Find a better way that was sort of a joke although I think he meant some of it
Lucky for Cooper around the same time this other Professor does University dr. Levin
I just come out with a paper on horseshoe crab blood could theoretically
He used to test for bacteria in
People
Hearing doctor 11% about it doctor Cooper sat back in his chair and was like
What does second what if we use the horseshoe crab blood
To test our drug
Would it be possible to enter take this test and adapted to test drug price
All of those Rapids
So they got together made the test work
And as soon as we made that publication in 71
In the pharmaceutical industry jumped right on it and so this
Particular
Chemical substances coagula gin in the horseshoe crab blood actually became
A major part
Of the way that we test
Things that we're going to inject into our body
And every hospital as you walk down the
The Carter you look in a room that's an IV bag hanging surgical instruments on a tray injectables
For pain
Infections your dad pacemaker cancer chemotherapy your grandma's new hit your kids
EpiPen immunization shots
All of these things have been tested with this
Material that this tactic were able to do using the time of gold that we
Extract from horseshoe crabs
450 million year old speech
Yeah but in order to
To do all of that in order to actually you know
Keep our medicine safe
They actually have to go out every year and
And drain horseshoe crab blood seriously
Best keep doing this out every year
Crabs every year they drain their blood and then they go put them back out into the ocean like a like a
Like a like a horseshoe crab blood drive
The whole bunch of companies that do this industry is worth
Tens of millions of dollars
I really really wanted to see this all in action but I wanted to go to one of these
Facilities
After the break a lot of in a very special guest
Will do just that
They will infiltrate
So to speak
One of these leading facilities and Witness
The baby blue blood drive
First hand
That's coming up
This is Katie from Big Sky Montana
Radiolab
Supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloan at www. Sloan. Org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here I'm a producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help this summer I'm hosting
And I request for those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
We're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments
Williams
Basically I want to hear about this
I kid you know did something
It just means you lean back and say whoa
How do they do that
Maybe it was the moment that our kids you've been reading to 4 month started reading
Back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons and you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed they're writing music in the margin of their geometry
We're interested in the
Specific moments where
Kid does something super smart but doesn't have anything to do with the test
If you have a story
Go to radiolab.org
Flash brilliance
Record a short audio message
And that's where you're at. Org / brilliance
Thank you so much
Is Radiolab we're back
With lots of Nasser reporting on
Horseshoe crabs
The scientist who love them or at least love there
Very valuable blood
Maybe them too but mostly black
And therein lies the rub
I think four or five companies that go outside horseshoe crabs and then
Extract their blood
And wanted to see what what is it look like
So I sent out a few emails
And then I was emailing these companies for like 3 years the nobody ever return my emails
I don't know why maybe they didn't want
Bad press or I don't need anyone bleeding that year or whatever
And so I basically given up on the story
Begin this year
These folks at one of the company's culture
Charles River Laboratories ever like hey why don't you just come down to Charleston South Carolina
And watch what we do here
So I went
And along with me I brought
How's it going you guys
Shine the horseshoe crab signal on the moon
And I come running
Miller is a former Radiolab staff or ecstasy is the first
Radiolab staff member besides myself
And Ellen and she is a co-creator of NPR's invisibilia
How did you get in on this
I weirdly have had affection for these creatures my whole life I like grew up with them there's some of my first memories would do
Do you remember seeing I remember seeing what I thought was a crab I was like
Probably
Three or four on the beach with my parents in Cape Cod where we've gone my whole life and
And I just remember walking on the beach
And seeing this like massive crab
In Hawaii third of the size of my body basically
And remember kind of jumping back and my dad's angle
Pick it up poke at it you know interact and so I kind of turned it over and I saw this
The closet I got scared
And then he you know he showed me it wasn't alive it was a malt
And
Explain what a mole was that there had been a crab in there
Laid out and now was the
This perfectly intact
Skin of what it used to be
And
Your Wonder like where is it now and what's it doing now and do I ever leave a self Baha'i don't know is just little and I thought it was
We brought it back to our Port remember that I sat on her porch for years
And like
Dogwoods Nevada
Where
Are we go
Ever since then it's just been a like mild poetic fascination
To build buildings
Alulu did you have a feeling about this business of any sort before you and visited that there's a part of me that would that
Wondered like oh I totally love these creatures this Big Bad Company Justin
Splitting it for their blood
You know I went with a little
Skepticism
Thanks. Let me know an eyebrow down and scratched
Just in this kind of understated nondescript
Office Parkland there's like people in capri pants and sandals from the outside it looks like every other one
Story brick building
No but then when you go on the inside of your hit with this like I can smell it a wash of a smell of
Crab
Hey
Wow.
Now how would you
Describe that smell
Panda
Crab myth
It's a high-ceiling brightly-lit room with
Industrial sinks along one wall shiny metal operating trays on wheels
Sent no matter where we were standing we just sort of managed to beat like exactly
Do you need us out of the way in the way of all these busy people rushing around
Lab coats to wear a hairnet
Pushing around these big gray bins on Wheels I'm inside each bin
AR
The horseshoe crabs
Twisting and turning a little
Waving their tails all heat on top of each other about 20 per bin
So
We have are crabs coming in from
That's Brad parashar guide there two parts to the blood donation
We start by washing the animals scrub the shell
What you speak are living animals
Smooth shells are passed person-to-person rinsed and Shining
For crab your hair
World
Yeah
Monster wash
The rack of lamb
It's time for the bleeding
16 crabs
Will Dover
Crabs are taken out of their Benz folded in half that their tails are kind of underneath a new put on these racks
Wither strap down with a bungee cord to hold them in place
And then there were wheeled into this tent
Which is like a
Clean room Zone
Dislike
I got these sort of like plastic curtains all around
Are we can't go in okay and he didn't let us go in there because as regular bacteria carrying humans
You dirty enter the super super clean right in when we did we saw that
In a crab's body right at that hinge there's like a little opening and the needle goes in there
Any news from that needle that is blood like
Brazilian
Yeah kind of sci-fi
Sky blue
Blackwood slowly dripping into the glass bottle
Are low clouds are going but they just kind of look
Like they're sitting there and they're draining them about a third of their blood
What is your emotional sense of this scene
You like it was
Kind of this
Feeling some sort of like what we're doing here is
Weird
And
Kind of
Vampire
I don't believe it's like we're sucking their blood
So
It was a little creepy
When
So lots of flakes
I feel like when we were in there
There's like
So many we were in the factory dozens and dozens of boxes filled each would like
10 huge crabs
And we
We are in the yeah I not processing Zone
And before we went and saw the blood
This like maybe sound cheesy but it was actually
Found Anna keep thinking about it
This there was this moment okay so here we okay what are we looking
Can I tell when one of the guys in the factory
I pulled out from these dentist
Big female horseshoe crab
Oh yeah
Baidu
And he's just sort of holding her by the shell
The tail is really coming right at me here
Her claws are going up and or tails kind of
Waving around
Writes a lot of hair
Exactly and so take these calls
And he like
Turn her over so she's upside down
And then he took his hand and just let her go
I was kind of grabbed his hand
They're sort of pinching my hands here but
It doesn't hurt that much power to him they're just using that the store to grab the food
Can I try
Can I get a little pain
And so I just
Kind of slowly
Stuck my hand out toward her claws
Are clouds like
Engulfed my hand
Fairy
Classy
It wasn't a Scrabble you kind of like
Foreign
Attach the all the claws class
In unison
Really tight
It's actually kind of
I thought I am being like this horseshoe crab is
Holding my hand
Timmy and of course this is just silly projecting so I'm saying that
But like it felt like
And it wasn't
But it felt like a communication like I'm in this
Enemies
People are doing weird things that I want to be back in the city and I'm upside down and I'm about to go into like
What have a think you know one of those like shower heads
Braids all up in my undersides and then off to be bungee cord and
Green like
It was almost it wasn't like it was in pain but I had this almost like
Primal creature to creature
Help me
Yeah like I mean
Part of me felt that too
But
Me on the other hand
Did you get to go home
So the same fisherman
That bring the craps to us
Deliver them back to the
And released their set free
Straight back to the wall
And how many crabs did they do this to every year
About 500 thousand
Horseshoe crabs every year
Do the crabs to get blood and then released him and didn't they just swim away fine or some of them
After the bleeding there's a small percentage like I think
The conservative estimates around like 10%
But that might be a higher estimate or
Am I get lost
15% like 15% so if you're talkin about 500,000
Crabs
Divide every year that that that means about
Horseshoe crabs are dying because of bleeding every year
You know they actually is in that original paper that I looked at again Alexis Madrigal they were actually
See that a lot of the the crabs don't have
Like
Blood crabs and non-blood crabs like have slightly different movement patterns and that's because you know maybe one of them is
Missing 30% of its blood
But I needed to
I needed to double-check on that until they did
See that the blood animals
Appear more lethargic they move
You know
Marsala
And like imagine if imagine if you had to go like Harvest deer
And then believe them of 30% of their blood and then you'd like leave them back out in the forest like there's something about that hands so yeah
It seems very medieval
Is there any hope
I'm getting out of this whole vampire relationship we have with the horseshoe crabs
Well
Perhaps
And let me tell you a brief story
About a bird
Smallest bird
Cinnamon in color
With a long bill it's called a redneck
Incredible thing about red knots is of all the birds in the world
The Red Knot makes one of the longest migration
Nearly 10000 miles
Tickle from the very southern tip of South America
All the way up to northern northern
Handed up into the Arctic Circle where they lay their eggs
And the whole journey
Takes about 5 months
And what happens is thousands of these red. Birds will take off from South America to fly like 4000 miles
Brazil stopped at 4 just like a couple days rest up eat some food
And then the thousands of them take the skies again and they fly top along the eastern coast of South America over
The Atlantic Ocean before they get to their final messing grounds they make one more stop one pivotal
Russo rest stop
In
The Delaware Bay
Yeah
Dried up
Now when I was in Delaware there weren't like a
Kind of birds that are but basically these birds when they make this journey they rely on horse
Because
I don't know if you've noticed
Missing all the eggs
They need to eat millions of horseshoe crab eggs to complete their migration
And this is the thing it's weirdly these birds
That might actually free the horseshoe crabs
From us
Yeah yep
And to explain I got in touch with this guy my name is j Bolden a biology
In the global quality Laboratories at Eli Lilly and Company
So Eli Lilly and Company
Huge pharmaceutical company that makes
You know cancer drugs
Antidepressants
A lot of insulin and things like that and real quick people
Are at the core of our commitment Manufacturing
Here's a message from executive the driving force behind our innovation
Radiolab is brought to you by
Anyway
One of the things that companies been helping innovate is horseshoe crab blood a synthetic version of horseshoe crab blood
Yeah so you know G
The problem is there needs to be a supply of horseshoe crab
You know climate change is real
I could have some supply chain consequences which isn't good
And it was actually all the way back in 1997
Some researchers
Out of the University of Singapore cloned
Just factor C protein
The essential Factor see protein in horseshoe crab blood that goes
Blue blue blue blue
Around the bad bacteria and now we can make
The protein of Interest
Instead of getting it directly from horseshoe crabs
So why are we already using that
Will Jay explain that there's a whole bunch of different reasons but one of the big ones was that you already had an industry
Tri built on horseshoe crab blood and so there is no real immediate incentive
To change
Which is actually
How we get back to
The cumin curcumin good friends
The Buzz
So turns out people like these birds a lot like actually way more than horseshoe crab
But
Since the birds eat the horseshoe crab eggs their feet is kind of entwined so like the horseshoe crab is not doing
Well then the birds not going to do well and so why don't I just go around to all the birds
Conservationists to use some of their political power and contacts and it's only now that we're starting to come up
Pain
A new dawn
Good afternoon everyone and welcome here is a great place to be today
2018 J was standing on a stage along with some conservationists
Do Nancy Eli Lilly would be one of the first companies to use synthetic horseshoe crab
The big headline news here
Is it the pharmaceutical industry can actually
Replace probably up to 90%
Abusive horseshoe crab blood without incurring any major regulatory change
Which means these horseshoe crabs can finally be freed of their servitude and bondage to mankind
Can get back to doing
What is going on
What they love
Well
But here's the weird thing and I think like
If the synthetic comes through and we get it perfect and it works and we never have to drain another horseshoe crab then they just because
Come these weird kind of sea spiders again
And I
I could be
A really bad thing for them
Yeah
Exactly this is actually something that Alexis Madrigal talks about 2 because most of the other things that these horseshoe crabs have
Ever been used for in the history of their encounter with humans as resulted in the death of like large numbers of them
Because before we ever valued them for their blood thing one we turn them into a breathalyzer
Ketchum boil them and grind them and then just stick them in the soil as a way of
Promoting plant growth
Or Thing 2
We catch him
Cut them up and use them to like as bait
To catch more valuable species like a particular kind of snails
Okay so I have right here in front of me this comes from the Atlantic states marine fisheries Commission
Which their number save that you know
As of the late 90s
There were nearly 3 million horseshoe crabs being killed every year for commercial fishing
3 million wow
But more recently we put restrictions on how many horseshoe crabs can be used for commercial fishing for bait
It's even like him a lot of seats at
Slime to go to a beach and just take a
You know a bunch of horseshoe crabs like in New Jersey if you take a horseshoe crab you could get fined
$1,000
The thing that I've always wanted to keep in mind of this is like
If you're going to have to be in a hook up to some economic system which most animals in our world are
You kind of want to be hooked up to one that that's super high value
And that doesn't kill you
Is it a fear is if like if the synthetic works and we no longer need horseshoe crabs for their Precious Blood then we just go back
Back to chopping them up putting them in the ground and using them for bait because they live where we live they live along
Populist
Sure
And
That right there for the taking
You know they're not
Prepared for our murderer simple
Unlock this
Nice to meet you
Thanks for having us here
Glad to
And there was this moment where everything just kind of
Lyft for me
You know like where I realized that
As cruel and kind of grizzly as the
Draining of the blood
Themes
I actually may be the best
Thing for these creatures
Like our
Selfishness
Maybe protecting them
This is our very last stop on our trip down to South Carolina and we met this fisherman named Jerry Galt
Who is employed to collect
Horseshoe crabs for the company
What peaceful little
Swear in this Forest
Yeah I know this
This feels like the most secluded place
With Jerry walking around this little pond
I worthy exactly wrong.
What's known as the holding Pond where they put the crabs before they go off to the facility
And while we were down there. There
Jerry likes
Poop some water out of the pond
Best bottled water
Then he held the bottle up to our faces
In the movie
All of them
Every
Wow there's so many of them
How many yeah they do
100000 eggs
How to season
Wow
The size of a like a really round grain of rice
Pearled couscous
Are they were they laying the eggs
Here or or or did you
Where you lay their eggs Longshore
Disbelief
Yeah I'll literally right here
Oh wow
I feel like we heard a tiny bit about but what's the what's the story of
How you went
From where your family went from
Being
Kind of seafood
Being a fisherman too
To doing this kind of
Crazy different
Well
We're just a bunch of Fishman of ADD
A cherry told us
The gist of it is back when his dad was doing Seafood fishing
His dad was catching a lot of horseshoe crab selling them off for bait and then one day this guy just showed up at his house Suit and Tie
Dad did if you would quit selling them for bait
You know you make a deal for me you would buy them
Buying for more money
To Jerry's dad said
We've been doing it ever since
But I got something I want you guys to know as a fisherman
I'm proud to be part of it that's fine it'll be
I want to say is the most
Noble thing I do
Because I get to touch every one of you guys because it's used for
Making sure medication is
It's a forest
And
Can't say that about
Soft shell crabs are
Agrupar he live
Touch it again
ITouch
You
Indirectly
Indirectly I'm touching all of us here
Because we're all part of it
So it's pretty neat thing
If you had to describe your
Feelings
For the crabs
For the horseshoe crabs
How do you
Feel about that
Well
I have a lot of respect for him
And
I almost feel like it's some
Divine Design
Horseshoe crab is
No
I've seen him
Fishing Forum you know their new since then
And Naseem on the side with important to
Human Society
In
I just drives me back the idea that is
It was
Divine Design and they been around 400 million years it took him this
Took us this long to figure it out I guess
Any curiosity where did that
Without leave the two of you
For me I mean Jerry's of the fishermen he's
He's totally right like we we just
Figured this out these crabs are being Clark kenting us
This whole time they they have this hard one superpower that they probably had since
You know before like three branches on our evolutionary tree and
An an in evolutionary terms like
Are the winners words that we're chops
We're baby Chomp
And they're just like
There is
Something
Miraculous
Inside them and end in a certain way
It's easy to stand next to them and feel almost small
We're not unlike an asteroid or just another thing they're probably going to
Interlock we are a blip
To them
And yet
We're dangerous live
An n in a weird way like
People the people we met down here the people doing this
Work this Blood harvesting work
In a wake to represent
The best way to treat the crabs
Exactly treat him like eggs
There are these rules in place to make sure that the horseshoe crabs are only picked up by hand and you can't pick them up by the tail
Cuz you can injure the
The muscle
Until we keep them covered when we transport them
They're also on a time clock
We've got to get him back as quick as possible they have to be back to the ocean within 24 hours
When they get to the lab
Give it a manicure pedicure each one gets scrubbed clean by hand
Bring it back and let it go
And he showed us how he returns them to the water and he like
He built this freaking
Waterslide to do it more gently
No now we
Pick him up
Sedimentary slide
In the water take some time to the river
Before we used to
Pick him up and toss
And we've got away from tossing them
Is amazing
I got to slide on my dog 204 Long
Water slide
Where they rehydrate on their way to the river
That's the mail
We just interrupted his
Embrace
Game
It's cuddling
This piece was reported by lots of Nasser with help from down
Ammiano marchetti and of course Miller and was produced by Annie McEwen and Matt kielty
With help from Liza Yeager thanks to lakia Windish and everyone at Lanza's global endotoxins
Testing Summit Mike Kendrick and Brad Floyd of the South Carolina Department of Natural Resources also tomorrow
Eli Lilly and of course Kate Contreras John dubchak
And the rest of the team Charles River
It's listening
Message press 2
Start of Meth
Hey it's Alexa
This is Lulu area
Radiolab
What created by dad
Riding is produced by
Gordon wheeler
Is our managing director
Include xiamen Adler back of wrestler
Stephen Cabral Bethel hockey
Tracy hun
Cell phone on Twitter
Melissa O'Donnell
Webster
Michelle Harris
Beautiful
Woodworking radio grid that get in the house
And this message
With no text message with no no
A measurement ruler
Hello hello pretty good
The phone
She'll be there high
So
Word on the street is you have a story
To read
I do I do have a story I think my levels are okay
I have a really weird
Horseshoe crab
Deep dive
So you have to pretend you have to like really Channel me
Speaking like
A kind of Jersey do you like I pictured that this voice
Is like a
Jersey
Kind of Tony Soprano voice
But like go there I will I will be translated
Into that boys
In my head
So it's called
Me and Jane
There's nothing finer than the feel of Jane suckling algae for my back
If that sounds gross
Just imagine how it would feel for a moment
Find horseshoe crab like Jane
Climbing up onto your shell
Nibbling and scraping around to remove this past week
Failures and setbacks and scabs
A glittering Cascade of fun suctioning
All over your shell
Footsies
Should say when her work was complete
My turn
Sorry I must have brought this is a pregnancy curse but there might be some breaths you're going to take out I'm so tired even
Denigrate
What fees should say when her work was complete my turn
And I'd climb back up onto her back
Two around a bit
Pop a few Barnacles off but
I never really did that great of a job
For two reasons
I am a bit late
After years of being a bit lazy and allowing my Jane's shell to becoming crested and salt scabs algae barnacle
More than a few muscles
I've come to find it all quite
The whole stinking mess is a topographical record of our
When I say this to Jane she rolls all 9 of her eyes but I mean it
That patch of black algae on harappa Malik Ridge
That appear the night last spring when we spawned under a new moon
Which is of course
No moon at all
That white gunk
Near her tail
From a nap in the mud
The actual remnant of a cuddle
Or those Barnacles on her backside
I know the very day they latched on
It was on a trip up to Maine to see the tide pools
Jenna been scared of going scared of black bears or humans are yada yada yada I cut in and told her those were just miss
Perpetuated by fearful crabs with too much goddamn time on their hands
Life Is For Living I told her as I thrust her into the Gulf Stream and boy what a time we had
We soaked in tidepools we lay out in the sun Jane picking away at my back while I walked her through my idea for a star
Schnabel
The particles must have suction onto her somewhere between the
Boyhood stargazing scene
Spooky starfish star residence
And the seagull attack scene
Even if I hadn't been too exhausted from My Fit of inspiration to work on her Barnacles at night I doubt I would have been able to pry them
I'm off
As they prove the next morning hunter that glaring Mane son
There are as hard as
Oh well
Without these spots I fear I'd forget
The life will become a wash
I whisper these kinds of things to Jane when she seems a shame of her little green beard
Or when she sluggish from her kelp
Tails pulling in the tide
These stains and scabs are the
Circulars of Arc
Experience I tell her
There are memories
Need physical
A record forged in desiccating sichting
I mean
It's not that I don't appreciate a smoother shell when I see one
Jefferson
Wife
For example it is hard not to notice her swimming by
Rochelle turgid with the strain
Perfection
And if you happen to be on Shore when she comes up for air
Watch out
It is almost like an optical illusion water on water
Pump of liquid emerging from it
Self
What I'd give to reach out with the tiny hairs in my most
Private of spots my nephew basis and run them along her shell
But still
You couldn't pay me to trade places with Jeff
Well I'm off on a fish carcass Bender with the guys are having a quiet morning to myself going mollusk hunting
Jefferson is at home in that same damn ditch
Tending to his wife
All day long
Pics and Buffs
Scrapes and scrubs washing away her every residue
She won't even tolerate a bit of salt buildup
It was a simpler existence
It's with my Jane
My Old Barnacle gal
More free
Lately though
I have to admit I've been feeling restless
We're not fighting at all
We're still very much able to make each other laugh
But
I feel so big
Things within me are becoming uneasy
I mentioned something along the lines of this to Jane about a week ago
But she assured me it was nothing
Just physical
Time to molt
But the moon proved her wrong
The brightening Moon and The Descent of thousands of new horseshoe crabs on the Cove it's the spawn of
Horse the upcoming spawn must be was triggering this uneasiness in my gut
Because while the first part is lovely
There is nothing like the feel of your pedipalp out in the ocean holding onto the edge of Jane's shell with your grippers
10000 other crabs clacking so hard around you it's sometimes induces a c Steam
What happens afterwards is
Unsettling
Something strange comes over everybody
Jefferson is no longer high-strung Jefferson
His wife no longer a prima donna Frank
He's always been kind of weird and lonely
Themes
Okay
Everybody is lifted from their selves
Or rather ourselves seem to lift from our bodies and leave us
We become one
Without our peculiarities at Giant
10000 Claude being
As we fall asleep at night
Thousands of us thinking into the cool mud all at once
Kind of communal dream takes place
And we awake United
We share food
Take turns guarding the eggs
Drop our suspicions of one another
We are an efficient machine of a species
Without the drag of the individual
I think there could be a book in this
A sort of anti hardening in fetus
Promise of the commons
Imagine a completely selfless species what good we could do how quickly we could rise
But
Alas
Curse of us creatures unable to change a thing about ourselves since the dinosaurs
We can never get this elevated
State to last any longer than a couple of weeks
It ends instantaneously with the hatch
Once we've watched as Tiny versions of us
Smaller than clams with little button tails
Disappear into the surf
The collective conscious being acidic a
Ourselves float back down into our shells and we feel that familiar itch again of loneliness
A selfie
Confined irrevocably
To its own body
That's when we become assholes again and dick heads
And self-serious know-it-alls
And so my hunch
I tell Jane is that this strange
Gurgling in my gut
It's some kind of
Quantum vertigo
Yeah that's it
Quantum vertigo myself longing to be set free Into The Ether where it can
Leap and spin and do whatever it is self do up there
And dastardly old me
This collection of hard shell and claws
Desperate
To keep it inside
But no
Jane was right
It was just time to molt
Ha she said after she heard The Telltale
Rumble from underneath my presuma
Poor old grabs thinking he's the next
Political theorist
Stirring with ideas
When really it was just a case of
Skeletal indigestion
I went there with my tail
Shut up
She was about to respond
Eric Lottery burp came out instead
I said
Mutual
Mutual molting
Genocide
Splendid
As we ready ourselves for the process
There's not much you can do but stand there and take it
I realized something
What timing I said to Jane will have fresh bodies just in time for the spawn pristine
Shell
I thought you liked my in crustaceans
Said Jane
Staring out at the sea
I do I got
My darling of course I do
It was right around then that she started to split
Her head started craning forward and iWatch
Nauseated and thrilled as a bigger
Wetter version of her began sliding out
It took hours
This arduous process of slipping out of yourself
But when she finally emerged she was a sight to behold
Like Jane
But gleaming and massive
I better go she said
I know I whispered
The soft and jelly like new Jane would need to find a secluded place to hide as her cell hardened
Shall I find you in our spot
Sure she said
I began to slowly
Carefully
Step away
I lay down next to her old body in the sand
It was almost like laying with her any old day
That trustee Silence of her listening
But with her shell completely empty now
That familiar pattern of barnacles
Took on a frightening weight
Something about them made me feel very worried
They can tell you what
Eventually I too found myself splitting
It wasn't the easiest of mold so I'll spare you the Gory details but let's just say the old me didn't want to let the new me through
And it made its reluctance known with a deep gash down my back
But at last I emerged
Bloodied and gelatinous
I went to some bushes nearby
There I waited as my back began to harden
Through the brambles I had a good view of our old shells
Lying side-by-side in the sand
Two little humps in front of the sea
I gave that ass for hours
Is the moon split across
The sky
There was me
The old me
A shiny little Dome reflecting the moon's journey in miniature
There was Jane
The old Jane
A body so carpeted and weeds and Stone
That she reflected
Only us
A week into legs
Human ones
Switching by my brambles
The rubber pads on it
Feet make horrible squeaking noises
I Get Low
Blackhawk for a moment and then run over to the old Jane in the old me
The creature a little one for human Yanks old me by the tail and brings me up
Tithead
IWatch is it said he's my private Underside
Then turns me over and places me back down
Thank God right where I have been in the sand
It runs its strange hand along my smooth shell
It turns to examine old Jane
Her sweet fuzz
Are barnacles
Ilife
Rochelle cracks
Under the rubber pad of its
Butt crack
Into a thousand pieces
Little bastard heirs to pick old me up again
And all I can do is watch for my brambles as it runs away with me
And it runs away with my past self
Dragging it ruthlessly
Down the shore
The spawn has come and gone
I looked everywhere for Jane
Waiting by our spot calling her name into the clacking shells
Nothing
Now
I spend most evenings underwater with
Frank
Weird Frank
Awaiting her return
The fish won't stop nibbling at my molting wound
I can feel flat worms burrowing into my back
Ask Frank to help me clean it but he spits muscles and tells me I've got to be kidding
Michelle is growing itchy with Grit
I don't know if it's and or Barnacles are what
This afternoon
I simply stood before the undertow and called her name into its haunting screams
Jane
Tells me to shut up about my starfish novel
Everyone does a coming-of-age starfish novel he says I mean write the damn thing if you want
Please stop talking about it
As I sit with him
Algae sprouting on my lip
I rethink the value of a self
Screw the promise of the collective I think sometimes oneself can be a pretty good thing
Self like a Jane
For instance
I keep getting hit with shards of grid that
Instead of bouncing off my shell now get caught in my kelp
Tangles
I feel sluggish
Unwieldy
In constant pain
I think I'm past selves
That smooth old me
What is a self anyway
What endures
With the solo thing of question and my body now long gone
Is it even continuous
I have the distinct
Sense
The Jane would tell me this is magical thinking
That the old me is off somewhere on the mainland near that little human creature
I can picture that clean old Shell of mine drying out near some flower pots
Being occasionally sniffed out by an idiotic canine with a sloppy tongue
Yes I'm sure of it
They're Jane with scrunch up all 9 of her eyes and say of course you're sure of it you're making it up
The old me is preserved in pristine form on the mainland
Well the smashed shards of my sweet old Jane
Encrusted in the very stuff of our love
Disintegrate into the sea
Perhaps it's little bits of her
That are sticking to me now
Where's my horseshoe crabs
Oh that's great
That's really nice
You're really nice to listen to while I know
Good I'm glad that's lovely
I I didn't
Heading home