Are you awake
Northern listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
And NPR
It's time now to practice some very useful phrases
I'll say them first you repeat
Remembering together
This is Radiolab today
Translation
It's time
Do begin will have eight experiments in Translation transcreation number one
The best poem was by my mother
Buca califia people remember
Now you try
Hello
Hi there
Hi. Doug this episode was inspired by a guy named Doug
Professor of cognitive science Indiana University Bloomington
You may know him as the guy who wrote Godel Escher Bach
Which is a hugely influential book
Is there in circles
Republican
9 but we actually got interested in him
Pink star producer Lynn Levy
Because of an obsession of his which predates the
16 I was 16 the Year 1961 I was taking a French literature
Glass in one day
I came across this poem
A tiny little bow
It kind of sat right in the middle of the page
Like a long
Thin sausage vertical three
Syllables
Caroline it was super skinny and 28 lines long and long and it was delightful it was very
Very cute and funny I fell in love with the poem immediately and memorize did I Still Know It by hard to Palm is basic
Play Get Well cards written by the sky climb on Monroe who was a poet in the early fifteen hundreds
The court
Of
Queen
This Queen's daughter
Seven or eight in
She got sick flu or something in this poem was supposed to cheer her up and very sweet
Could you say it in French it looks as hearitfirst okay it's called
Dumb ways that invalid to a
Sick demoiselle
So to speak
Mexican lady young lady
Mananas download bonjour
Gettys on Kool-Aid
Please move live atop of the concept of Eternal Jaclyn Alderwood Mall
Vasca Yonder Tobuscus okusan laundry put Emoji coffee to you
City of Tacoma.
Drifted want something done filet mignon
Oh my God you must have gotten so many chicks when you were supposed to go that was exactly
The opposite I was I was
I wish
Okay so you read the poem files it away deep in the corner of his mind fast forward about 20 years he publishes his first book
He becomes very popular in the publisher decides to have a transom
Enter the number of languages including French
In that process which took years it put me into the frame of mind of thinking what kinds of crazy things going to
Happen when you translate crazy text
And
All of a sudden one day that poem
Popped into his mind I said there is a challenge
Let's try to do this
And when you say challenge like what was it what is it what is the challenge
Okay what I meant was
He says you got this if you just focus on the
This guy talking to a younger girl saying hello my dear I'm sorry you're sick being sick is like prison
I cannot wish you to open your doors get out to the world clean all of them all
Get out of bed eat some Jam so you don't look so pale
Units are like get better here's to your good health
YouTube want something then let me know
But just saying those words in English
Misses the hole
Spirit of the
The
Tone the lightheartedness
And and
Recipe for dog it also ignores The Palms Forum it's wonderfully
Catchy
Little sausage shape on the page the fact that the lines
Rhyme you know aabbccdd and all the first line
Is identical to the last line I mean Young
Disorder has the feel of a palindrome it has the poet's name in the middle of the poem that mound of them all
Did I say three syllables per line
28 lines long so all of those things added up to a set of constraints you might say on me
So Doug sat down and got
Got to work and quickly became
Embroil
In the question of like how do you translate this
Coming along the way
Even began to make a little grids of possibilities for different lines of the poem
For example
Voske on data boost
Like this line the basically says don't wallow in bed
I had a lot of possibilities and I'll just read you the
Little diagonal display here instead of spurting blood in bed instead of burping in you
Your bed instead of bursting out in benstead of lurking
Senior instead of hurtling out of instead of hurting their
Instead of squirming
Slurping sloppy head of burning up in bed instead of turning blue in
On and on and I came up with
You want me to read my purse translation please
My sweet dear I sent you all the best
Your for stressed is like jail
So don't feel very long just gets
Strong go outside take a ride
Do it quick
Stay not sick
Band your ache for my sake
Buttered bread while in bed makes a mess so unless you would choose that
Bad news I suggest that you'd best soon arise
So your eyes will not glaze
Douglas praise help
Be near
My sweet
Deer
Tell Claymores now Douglas became Douglas and I
Became Bread's buttered bread jam and jelly
They are words
But the words
Represent Concepts in the concept have a kind of a halo around them I mean when you
Talk about jelly you're implicitly
Talking about bread and things that you spread it on oh I just think you'd like to stick their fingers in jelly
No bread needed
Okay okay fair enough
Feeling like you hadn't quite nailed it Doug sent the poem to one of the guys at
Translated his
First book into French
A guy named oddly enough
Bob French
I said hey Bob and you do it
And
Bob said well I'll give it a try
First friend let me send my embrace
Quit this place
It's dark halls and dank walls
Insoft still
Regain health
Grass and flea off with me Clement who calls
Very different in tone
And really quite marvelous
He got the
Masonry at the gym
Clements name in the middle but at the same time it didn't have the lightness
The tone is much more ancient
Wish you could argue well it's an ancient poem but
Text us dinner there's a bigger problem was 30 lines long so
Extra-long
And what he ate was a
Sacrosanct number no no no no no
28 lines that rhymed wonderfully and the essence of his poem was
A form rather than
AR
Then I message that is the message was Getwell
Which is pretty simple but Doug would argue no it was the Forum
That's what made the thing funny and Charming until the question for him was
Who could get the field but nail the four
To make a long story short
He ended up sending a poem out to like 60 people doctoral students who my sweet I am free
One regard
Otis hard dear recluse colleagues friends
Chickadee I decree of find a
He's got his wife to do one Dart away from your case
Engage in Brave flight
So you might flee the croup it was all bird-themed hope you swoop into ham apple jam and French bread
Running around from town to town saying hey
I got Obama anybody want to buy some Haley then if I am a person of binges this began a bin
Some might say
And that b**** ended up becoming a 700-page book
Filled with translations of this poem best one now
This is Ben. Right right now this is not the best one
Stop it ok Google okay okay this is also one of his butt like a 20th wahneta
Petite gal so sweet
Hug from dog
Some dumb bug dragged you down Zach that friend
Feel the Earth bug zappers
From The Scourge you'll emerge in a Trice
Sound advice from a ham
Ducks
Clem
So smashed blue
Come
Come you who lived the two sheets as true
Sweet let's chew
Make your heart palpitate Clem's mandate
Sure hope God cures your bod head to feet
Should have got used your bod
Although not the best
I do want to get to my mother's translate have here is my mother's
This was somehow
I'm going to have to look it up
Pure water
Facebook is wrong complicated
This one from his mommy says came along years after he started
Anything that might be the winner
Hi to its Getwell hospital prison in prison tell
Get well for yourself
Clements orders in a nutshell
Go pig out
Open wide your mouth keep those sweetmeats going south
Unless you're hell you'll turn pale
Loose poo la la. Wiggles your tail
God restores that helped you my little flower
I noticed that she doesn't
Begin the poem
And in the palm of the same line she doesn't have 28 lines just maybe about 16 lines
She doesn't pay any attention to syllable count my first reaction was
Mom come on
I didn't pay any attention to the Forum
And I did what I wanted to do this is my feeling and I was just leaving that's what I did
Actually you know I have to say
It has stood the test
The time it has some kind of pizzazz that no other one ever
But if she respect the forms you didn't do the syllable she didn't rhyme with the way it supposed to rhyme she didn't give you 28 lines
Have that track
Is that a translation then or is that just a
What are standard flowers bloom
As I got more and more deeply into this poem
My Philosophy
Started to become
Chairman Mao's
Statement let 100 flowers bloom
Another words you can look at it from so many angles and each new angle in riches
It is and makes it more fun but you can't read a hundred versions of every poem that you want to read okay
Okay I agree are you right I guess make me question though that the Rules of Engagement and what are no rules
There no rules it's all in
Formal okay but there is Jim in one of the translations and ham in the other
And they're like they're
Factually different
Food substances shouldn't be negotiable
I mean does a fact about the poem is that it was written by somebody in French
It's not in French anymore the mission
What was what
Was
He said
Not
What do we make of what he's saying what are the flavors of what he's saying what are the variance of what he say when is that like isn't the expectations
That you as a translator
AR
Giving
Me him
Like it is this man is lost
The time and now it's suddenly I get to experience him
What is a hundred flowers are blooming that's somehow feels like I'm not getting him at all obviously you're getting to the question of what
What is translation and can it be done my my feeling is that
Even though these translations that we've heard are all very different
They all
Show something about claim on my ho
Ducks basic point is it like
Any person
Kind of universe
They're too big
Comprehend in their entirety
So any translation of
It's only going to get you at
Tiny
Piece of that pie
Refraction
I'm in luck we have one photograph of Frederic Chopin
Photograph
In that picture he survived
Scowling
What did Frederic Chopin really look like
What was his smile like
You know you look at a photograph of Chopin and you say all this is what Chopin look like well no
Chopin look like many things
Even the very day that that photograph was taken
He had
Thousands of different Expressions on his face but then what about a year earlier or 10 years earlier I mean knowing soap
Open is a very complex thing it's not one thing
Millions of different things that are united
By analogy
Into
Something that we refer to as one thing
We should say we looked into it in there are actually two pictures of Chopin
But he's kind of scallion
No smiles
Go to McDonald Cafe
Otoko no miss you
Mumu
Go to McDonald gospel
Yeah yeah yeah
Lesson number two
Are you just talking or are you doing
Tupac Shakur kids
Wichita Zoo
Now you try
Number two
I hear I hear the sound of a telephone
Hello
Habari za asubuhi
A story from Greg Warner Greg is a NPR's eastafro
Corresponding
You are what what time is it where you are
It's love
It's evening is based in Nairobi
Embarrassing cuz I just told you good morning
In Swahili
But I forgot to say good evening so oh
Okay so Greg we were just a booty call
Article for the great website
Call transom. Org
About
Being foreign reporter and working with translators and all the mishaps
You know when you have to go from one lime
Switch to another
There's actually a really good example that I didn't use them
He's about
Failure to communicate
I can tell you that story
So
So there's this word and you wouldn't think of it is untranslatable but
It's the word serious
And
When seriously seriously
Crio
In my experience when you hear this word serious in East Africa or
Bothell
Or Stern
It actually
Almost never has something to do with
Your mood
But serious tends to me
Is
Are you just
Talking to me or you Siri
SRU
Doing some
And usually doing is like
Some kind of
Transaction usually
AIA Financial
I've been asked by
How many East African officials are you going to be serious with me
And
It obviously means are you going to
Can you bribe
Usually I pretend to misunderstand at the key moment I said yes I'm a very serious
International journalist
Send
But the story that I want to tell you it
To place a couple months ago
I'm really pleased to be back in Africa secretary Kerry
Addis Ababa Ethiopia and
Enormous energy
Just a few days before Kerry's visit nine journalists had been arrested under this relatively recent anteater
Tarzan law that basically says
Any criticism of the government is illegal
I had a serious a very productive meetings this morning with my foreign minister counterparts and
Secretary Kerry was giving this press conference
I shared my concerns about the
Young Ethiopian bloggers that I met last year
Not now felt like a
Who
With Ava Spears
I've been in prison
And I firmly believe that
Set the work of journalist whether it's print journalists or in the internet
Media Vatican
It makes societies
Stronger he said all the things you do to expect him to say said we believe they're free speech and open dialogue important to the app
Country pop
But we remain committed to our partnership with Ethiopia
Yes, it was also wrapped up in a lot of praise
And I'd be delighted to answer a few questions
Cuz I'm not sure how that's even do that
Adventure Time For questions
He took some vetted questions from the Ethiopian journalists two more from the traveling press and to carry
I know he was very impatient
We left the party music you know what we're just going to try something different we're going to
Calling an Ethiopian journalist
Cherry Point
Is one guy
In the second row
Young guy in his 20s boyish face wearing a mustache
I may have invited the hardest question of the day now
But Minecraft
Paradise
Okay so leave me
Yuan
Raise doubles agents of national Foot Locker
Who is a blogger
Andy's friends
When does guys like well
Every time a journalist is arrested the US gives a statement about this but you seem so out of
This keeps happening
Repeating
Very much
So then he asked
Question
Is it leap service or are you seriously
Concerning Hobbits
Zerorez
Is this lip service or are you seriously concerned
At this point everybody they're all looking at this journalist to
Obviously it's take considerable personal rest in a place like Ethiopia in a crowd of journalists including state-run
TV stations guys on camera asking this extremely sensitive question about the arrested journalist
We really we demand
Say genuine safronia
And Terry looks at him
Like
You've got to be kidding
When I stand up in public and I and I and I say something
I try to be serious about it and I think the fact that I'm doing that is Siri
And when I raised
Him by name in my,
I carry sounds to me like he's sort of
Insulted by the question and
So remember serious the word serious in East Africa to be translated very much his are you doing
Something preferably financial transaction right and so what this journalist is saying is
Are you just talkin about this or are you doing something
Maybe threatening Ethiopia with withdrawing a tour with drug support and Carrie says I am very
Seriously talking about we have previously called for the release
These individuals in
That is the policy of our government
And it's a serious bottle
Thank you all very very much
And it seemed to me maybe you know
You can judge me
But it seemed like he was almost like
Look I'm like the most serious politician that's out there I mean I lost the presidential race in 2004 in Paris
Because I was being too serious by the American public
Like what are you accusing me of not being
Serious
We put in a number of requests
Speak to John Kerry or someone in the state department but they
You think he was aware of the misunderstanding who carry
This fellow
Can you pronounce a name for me
My name is anania sori
He's a young guy in his twenties season independent journalist
And
I was like you know when you listen what happened there and I kind of felt like this
Guide me
I'm standing here I'm not joking I'm serious
African Stacy series
They say no are you going to not just speak are you going to do
Are you going to take
Sanctions movie
What is Ethiopia
Do you feel that that question put you at risk
Maybe who knows that is a job description
Doing good journalism in Ethiopia
Thanks so much
Stinky Pinky
I'll give you a call
Give me a call
That conversation was about five months ago
Did you know what his fate at all I mean he found out whether did he suffer for this question in anyway
No but I have his phone number so I can give him a call and
Hi honey it's it's Gregory Gregory Warner
Go green Cody how are you
I reached him by Skype
He told me that actually after that press conference he did get
Strange calls to his home and some Facebook messages from people you didn't know telling him that
He better rethink what he said
The lineup
With the government priority
From the government
It's hard to tell it has been reported that this
Ethiopian anti-terrorism task force will waive social media attacks by
Getting people to send messages on its behalf
Were they threatening
Yes I'm okay
You know you sell team gender
Thunderstruck Old English
Wings and Things
And it might come Monday
The newspaper founded got shut down
Publishing one issue
And he was planning for a while to
Weed in Nairobi
Leave his wife and kid behind and then maybe return grab them apply for asylum in the United States
You know my mother and my
Underground building
Uuh Washington
Okay
Washington
Like a lot of
Ethiopian sea
Actually got some relatives in the in the states
Did they hear that you asked the question to John Kerry
Yeah yeah yeah yeah that exact what did your mom say
She said please don't do that
It might be you know targeting you
Hinckley Grand Casino
Yeah
Not that like that
Lance on Snapchat
Radiolab will continue in a moment
Message
Hello this is dog
Books to read
Radiolab is supported in part by the National Science Foundation and the
Foundations of public understanding of Science and Technology
Information about www.slha.org
See and distributed by NPR. Org
Chris carried on the translation in radio stories
I got me
Thinking about Sunday stories
Okie doke
And this message
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
This summer
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
About what we're calling tiny moments of brilliance
Basically I want to hear about those times when I kids you know did something
It just means you lean back and say wow how did they do that maybe it was the moment that a kid
Did you been reading to 4 month started reading back
To you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lesson
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of their musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed they're writing music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the
Epic moments where
Kid does something super smart but doesn't have anything to do with the test
If you have a story
T-shirt with us
Go to radiolab.org
Brilliance
Record a short audio message for us
And that's radiolab.org brilliant
Thank you so much
I'm jad abumrad this Radiolab today
8 experiments in Translate
Restroom number 3
Brake hold its shell shocked
Du Bourget
Discover the shield truck
Now you try
This one Rodrick Roatan.
Wheeler talk to
Gopnik about George
What is George Carlin mentioned biggest Carlin It's a Wonderful sort of folk philosopher of language, the comedian
And this next thing this next thing is about the English language
About little Expressions we use we get we all say in the little sayings and expressions that we use all the time
Is one of his great subject
He didn't even have a high school education you know so it was not something that he
Got from
Cooling
And one of godnicks favorite Carlin racing I really like this one too is about how Carlin hated
Euphemism I don't like words or hide the truth I don't like words that conceal reality I don't like euphemism
American English is loaded with euphemisms
Because Americans have a lot of trouble dealing with reality
A car that was wonderful about things like that what about book called
All the way
And we brought in these
Senior citizen
The reason we use you for so I just been through
My father-in-law died
4 months ago
And we went through the same horrible business that we all go through in a
Intensive care Ward where the doctors and nurse practitioners
Have a language that they've been taught
We just want your father to be comfortable
He's Gravely ill
Greatly I mean she's dying right and we wanted to be comfortable means can we give him enough drug so the hill
Pass out before he dies in song
It's certainly true that
Euphemism
Can be a repellent thing but
No one is full
What were mocking is
The absurdity of the effort to disguise something that you cannot disguise but Carlin's real point was that
Did like dolls are reactions
Do it actually has like I have a negative effect
He has this whole bed it's about shell shock
PTSD in the first World War
That condition was called
Shell shocked
They used to call it shell shock
Not simple
Honest
Direct language
Cool syllables
Shell shocked
And then it became battle fatigue battle fatigue
Porsche
Takes a little longer to say
Doesn't seem to hurt as much
And then after became battle fatigue
Then it became operational exhaustion
Paver up to eight syllables now
Television post-traumatic shock disorder
Still 8 syllables
PTSD post-traumatic
Stress disorder
The pain is completely buried under jargon
This was the Orwell notion that you could erase sensitivities if you blend it out the words
So
If you stop saying oh yeah we just tortured the guy if you say some
Phrase interrogation or enhanced interrogation that makes a big difference
PTSD we are not having the appropriate reaction to it emits shell-shocked I'll bet you if we have still been
Calling a shell shocked
Some of those Vietnam veterans might have gotten the attention they needed at the time I'll text you that
Now you putting your finger on the this is where the
The rubber meets the road
Does the use of euphemism
Does that really Rob us of some understand
Adam gopnik surprisingly says
The truth is just the opposite
We actually have more of an apparatus to help people with PTSD
Then they did in 1915 to help guys with shell shock
The reason the word gets more abstract is being exactly because you have a much more complicated an abstract system of
Support it's not because I think that's the reason it's called PTSD is because it's a more complex and
What that Evolution says
The initial thing was all these guys are being driven crazy cuz the shelter exploding all around me
The Western Front
Gopnik says the thinking was you know it was temporary the shell goes off loads in a moment they have a moment of shock and
They need a moment of rest and then they can go back in
But I World War II we're thinking
That's not quite right not just shells exploding right
It's the whole experience of battle
It's all the shooting in the death
BB guns battle fatigue you trying to generalize
Trying to make it richer as a kind of it also becomes fatigued versus shock there's less violin
Right because it because you're looking at guys who may not exhibit the symptoms of shock necessarily but
Overtime it becomes impossible
For them to go on is a wonderful film from World War II called let there be light
These are the casualties of the sky
Cumberland mine
Men who are damaged
Emotional
About guys with what they were then calling
Battle fatigue in the reason they were
Calling it that was because you didn't necessarily see it
Right away
Ben around Vietnam he says we realized you don't just see this on the battlefield you see it with guys who aren't necessarily directly
Involved in battle until the question became what's the source of it it's you say well it's nervous exhaustion say the human
Nervous system can only
Take it for so long and then everybody's nervous system shuts down
What's the term operational exhaustion
The guys aren't cowards and they're behaving the way all human beings
And then
You get more concerned about them and you say
The real problem isn't there just their experience on the battlefield
The problem isn't that there in a constant state
Of
Disorder because it lingers on long after
You think it's over you can't just get these guys into a hospital for six months and think they're going to be better they are permanent
Let you have post-traumatic shock
And then once you have a
Who has PTSD
Is Justin
It's perfectly possible
That the language of euphemism grows and becomes more abstract
As act as people actually are becoming more empathetic
To the people who suffer from
Suorin do you buy a man he's too he's basically turned crown on his head
Chinese made these blender and blender words
Enrichment
That I have any my only move would be to hit play on Carlin
Poor people used to live in slums
Now the economically disadvantaged occupied substandard housing in the inner cities
I'm very broke
Dead broke
They don't have a negative cash flow position
I'm broke
Lesson number four
Imagine a lot of Coca-Cola like bubbles on your tongue
450 Sherri Coca-Cola.
Now you try
Pretty good
This is Emily
Some of you may remember that a couple years ago we did a story about Emily wear
She been hit by truck
Going into a coma and then her boyfriend at the time Allen
I had brought her back
My writing on her hand
She's writing her name
Almost
All the stories we've ever done I think this one has gotten the most
And when we left that story
Emily had
Emerge from the comment again to recover
But she was blind
Totally blind right yeah
Like no light any good nothing coming in now
Needless to say was a very big at you
I just
I know I just had to develop my own ways to
Navigate
Throughout the world end
Just myself and I
And being a visual artist
She had to develop new ways to draw pad
Tryon
And if you draw the Crayons hard enough you can
Feel the wax
On the paper
Yeah then one day in the summer of 2012
She gets a call
From the lighthouse
School in New York
City Lighthouse school yeah it says School for the Blind
Her mom had to found out that they were trying out this
Brand new technology
I think they were doing the study for the FDA experimental
Long story short Emily shows up the lighthouse school one day and walks into the
This room in a guy named ed
Gives her this thing
He described it I mean is it a big
No it's not it's just like
A regular pair of sunglasses
Though they were a little heavier than your normal sunglasses
Is right on the front
The bridge of the nose
Was a little
Camera
Going forward
And then attack
The sunglasses was a little wire
It ran out of the camera and down to this little square piece of metal is made out of titanium
And it's just like
The size of a postage
A little bit thicker
L6
Pizza titanium was filled with
Thousands of Electro
And what was going to happen is that the
Camera was going to convert images into
Patterns of electricity
Beyond that little square
So we told her to take a little square on your town right on the center of your tongue
And close your mouth
So
A put it on and they turn it on
And it was like it started to tickle
Imagine a lot of
Coca-Cola like a lot of bubbles
On your town and always late
Prickly prickly feeling the idea behind
Science writer Sam Keen author of the tale of the dueling neurosurgeons is it we actually see with our brain not our
Or I might seem like our eyes are doing the singing in our ears during the hearing and
Fingers and thumb touching but that's not how it works
Each of our senses send signals into the brain as electricity little blips on nerves
And is the brain then converts those little blips into what you perceive as a sight or sound or smell no obviously
Someone was blind the retina is not sending those signals anymore
But
What is there is another way
To get
Signals for light and dark in color
Into all of our brains there lots and lots of Pathways going from every part of the brain to every other
Other part of the brain
Normally your brain isn't using those pass
Is even though they exist
It's like there's a road there but it's shut down
Traffic cam
But
What if you could open up some of those rats he's just let me sit with it on for an hour
Our two hours we just swivel her head around and feel the patterns on her tongue
Young change and every time I looked around he say
Oh that's a chair
Bassador
That's me
That's your mom
Like this for a while at shoulder a ball and it's
Square plastic banana
And nothing's really happening for
Except for that prickly feelings on your tongue
Then there was this moment I'd had this
Really long styrofoam Broad
And he
Plastic
In front of me he moved it
Up and down in front of my face
And I was like oh my God what was that
Suddenly she says you just
Thought I was like oh my God
It just happened
I don't know what it look like
So in my mind's eye looks like
A long way
Skinny
Stick
You see the texture of the sticker
No
I couldn't see texture I couldn't see
In three dimensions it was very flat
It is kind of like
That kids
Toy Lite-Brite
So imagine like a black screen and
Little tiny white dots
All arranged in a line
To Emily was allowed to keep the brainport device for about a year-and-a-half and during that time
Lite-Brite resolution of a did get better
Has your brain learn to
Speak tongue
It was awesome
When I saw the p
And one of the things that really struck me in our conversation was I asked you about
This video
Her mom had sent me showing her
Wearing the device in walking down the
You told me that usually what you know now that she's blind when she's walking
Down the streets of New York City
Especially Uptown where the streets are
A lot wider
She said people see her and her white cane and walk a really wide circle around
So
Isaiah
Yeah I hardly ever notice other people walking around me it feels like
I'm just
Walking alone
I can always hear the traffic
And the sound of traffic
But
Not if he
People
What you says when you put the device on input that was sent to Iran
Tongue
The sidewalk
Camelot
I thought it was amazing like I didn't know this many people were on the street at the say
Same time as me and now they're all they're all there again
Almost like a painting
Really soft lashes
Everything is really soft like
Soft
Roshes
Ink that can move their is walking and I can see them
Legs moving and I can see them
They're gay
But I couldn't see them clearly like I couldn't see
Defeater tour
Whether they were wearing a shirt or short circuit
Gas repairs I just like
See their Shadows
And
Every now and then I See the Light casted on them
I've mentioned smell like underwater
Pictures
Squishy jellyfish like
Yeah
Yeah like lighting up
Yeah like that
And that for Emily is
What it's like to translate the city
With your tongue
New York City becomes is
Hazy sea of
Walking fish
Make their way along in the sunshine
Lesson number five
I feel like we're Futures are going to crash today
What are the best roasts
Now you try
Next up producer Tim Howard so when I heard about this story with
Emily and the Brain Port I immediately called up this guy
Page on which my foot is it this one
You might remember him I'm David Eagleman I'm a neuroscientist at Baylor College of Medicine called him up because I can
Crosses thing that he's working on
That
Is sort of like the next
Generation
Of crazy
It called the vest which stands for the variable extrasensory
Sensory transducer
And it's it's a vest that you wear underneath the clothing in this vest has 24 Motors on it
Little vibratory Motors just like the ones in your cell phone
And the best
Connect to your phone so we pick up sound
Time Warner Cable calling
Valuable
Through a cell phone
And the cell phone does all the computational work to then convert that sound
Into patterns of vibration on the vest and you feel
Buzzing all over torso different Motors running at different amplitudes
It actually changes every 20 milliseconds so it's a moving pattern and it might seem impossible
That you could actually extract something useful about what's being said
When David brings death volunteers into the lab and have them do a particular training on the vest
He said that over the course of 12 Days people get really good
At word recognition
Somehow they begin to intuitively recognize
This means high for blue or chair if you tried to concentrate on it and
Figure out
How each motor Translate
Some part of that sound
You would never figure it out
But the good news is
You don't have to do it consciously
The brain
Is a special Aesthetics
Directing
Statistical information
And because of rain is so good at this kind of translation says David what he really wants
Do
Is used as best
To create new senses
So what if you fed in stock market data
Converted that into the busing who did you develop in the media
Perceptual experience
Of the economic movements of the planets
And would you without having any conscious awareness of how or why you're feeling a certain way could you have
Having intuition like you kind of feel like oil Futures are going to
Crash today
You wouldn't be
Analyzing all this information you would just
Feel like we're also working on feeding in
You are seeing a
From minutes
Real time weather data from the let's say 200 miles
Around you
Question is
Would you end up having an intuition Peekskill
That's better
Then what the weatherman can tell you on the news
Or
This one what if we took
500000 tweets per second
Cast it through some natural language processing disorder
A higher level summary of what's going on and pump all that information through the best would you develop a sense
What's happening on the planet where you suddenly say
I feel like something just
Happened in Nairobi
And oh I think the
Canadians have Justina finalized their election of something in it
I don't know what this will be like yet but there's no reason to expect any limit on on what the brain will be able
Able to develop
An immediate perceptual experience about
More experiments in translation
In a moment
Is Darlene calling from
Kampala Uganda
Rachel app is supported in part by the National Science Foundation
And by the Alfred p
Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and
Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloane @www.
Does org
Radiolab
Experimental translation
Russian number 6
Thank you very much interpreter 3940
Bank of Albuquerque.
Now you try
Furniture protector you really do get a spectrum of life
Nathalie Kelley
You know you get
A little taste of all these different things aren't there happening in the world
It really opens your eyes
She wrote a book called found in Translation in years ago a small town in the Midwest
Is just remember going to work with my dad
And it was a janitor and my dad said you know he actually speaks another language
Another language
On top of English
And she says
She remembers her seven-year-old brain being like wow there's a whole nother language Beyond
Learn fast forward many many years Natalie goes to college and she just started learning languages Spanish
Please Arabic German Italian whatever I could get my hands on
Connector to The Wider world but what it actually led to
At least initially
It's very strange job called telephone interpreting
This is how I never actually thought
To think about
Until now the basically when anyone calls a business and there's a language barrier
The operator can call switchboard and Patchen someone like Natalie for them
Natalie like a lot of these telephone interpreters work remotely
Which man should be in her house alone in a room and every few minutes
Hello this is interpreter 3940 how may I help you
She get a call
And it could be anything
One minute you're interpreting for could be a celebrity whose booking at hotel or restaurant in
Spain then you're interpreting for a court hearing and then you're interpreting for Hospital
I was
Well let me put it this way
I got a call
You never know where the calls going to come from
And I heard that it was a 911 call and most of these calls are actually not real emergencies
But I knew
Immediately something was different
The dispatcher was connected
And I heard
This woman whispering
On the other side of the phone
She said
Muhammad Ali
Mybama
He's going to kill me
Oh my God
The dispatcher said
Where is he
And she said
Astana casa
Yeah he's in the house
And the dispatcher said and where are you
Tabacalera,
What's that mean
Under the bed
Does he have a gun
Daytona pistola
Where is he now
In the hallway
What's he doing
He's opening the door
And then
Click
Really
Yeah there is just a click
That's it
Yeah
You better get me about that is like
Like if you got into it
The connection then
What weird place to end up in real life
You by yourself in your room and then suddenly you're dropping in the middle of the most intense moment in a person's life but then ripped out
Before you can know who the person was
About to happen to them
And then you're back in your room again
That happens and then the phone rings again and then your pillows is interpreted reinforcer how may I help you
And you're back to it and you're interpreting you know something is literally within a minute after that phone
Call ends and the next person is probably coming to buy trading stamps
In in in
Spanish words
Yeah
Can imagine
What it was like be like that
Skip and jump like
Lesson number 7
He got down and dirty so I got down and dirty to
Target baskets
Now you try cases this next story is next translation story
Mystery
This next story actually
You should say it contains a lot of obscenities a lot of obscenities coming up a lot of strong graphic
Language
If it's not something you're into or if you got kids around
I would advise you to skip forward by 9 1/2 minutes
Are you still here this one comes from our executive producer Eleanor
So you should start the story ellenhorn The Show
Nick nuciforo who helped us arranged
Tour for Radiolab
So he invited me to come to Ball 2014
The Oddball Comedy Festival and when we got there either
Bike
Huge crowds
Tens of thousands of people kind of ground like 14,000 people
We sat down
Anna state of New Jersey
The roastmaster general Jeff Ross
Giza insults
Comedian he gets up you the MC for the night
And he sticks the show off
How the hell are you Jersey
Yeah
How you doing sir
He starts taking folks out of the crowd what's your name
Rob I Loved You On To Catch a Predator
Look at these two chicks how you doing lady
You look very cute two fives make a ten
And then
It looks to his left
And high
There's a lady doing
Sign language over there he sees the sign language
Can I come over there
She looks like she's in her 50s
Brunette glasses wearing tank top
What's your name
Kim
Give it up for Kim
Stadium
Clapping for him
This is wild Kim
And then he says
So anyway I was jerking off the other day
Pandan
Clear the air
Seeing this
Deescalate then I stuck my thumb in my nose just since I had a booger in there
And I decided to stick my pinky in my own
Makes it look like she's sticking your hand in her butt
Crowd Goes Wild tonight Kim
Soca Frost takes it even further
And afterwards I'm going to get out my vibrator with a hand crank
I give it to you old school style vibrator
Sex squeezing my morning
For like a half an hour
And it felt so good she is having to like
I'm troubled by how funny that says I love you Kim
Well
Yeah
Cuz here's the thing
Halfway through the show
I noticed that Kim wasn't there anymore
Chicken translate for Sarah Silverman Shin translate for someone else
So
It made me wonder
What did I see there what was going on
Jeff Ross was clearly using her
Was Kim okay with
What's that
So I found a list of all the sign language translators in the state of New Jersey
I'm good how are you I found her okay my name is Kim Van Cleef and I'm a certified American sign
Language interpreter
And we're here in Ocean Grove New Jersey
Kim lives part of the year at end she has her entire life
In a religious community on the beach
And it's Ruthie comedy I'm doing religious
Sign language
Interpreting services and the choir and there's this venue nearby that does
Big stadiums
There's any deaf
Ticket buyers
Venues required
By law to provide
PNC called me I do all their concert all the musical concerts which I I've been doing for years
Goo Goo Dolls James Tower whatever
But I always can prep for them I get this setlist I go to lyrics.com I always
You know cuz a lot of times I don't know the Goo Goo Dolls not like Frank Sinatra and
You know hip-hop
What he asked me to do
You come in like
That I didn't know what was coming at me I had no idea who any of these
Course I went to know any of the comedian eventually I asked her about the whole Jeff Ross thing
Basically having you harass yourself
And
I am most curious to sort of
Find you and follow up and just find out like
How's that
Self
Well and she says the moment Jeff Ross
Start getting raunchy
She had a choice
Business register's in sign language
Yeah you can be formal you can be casual
Or you can be intimate
And you can pick sides from all of those Regice
Like take for example the word
Now that the light
Way to do it with two maybe
Spell it
So f
Uck
Or the regular gesture you could do this
Tear you giving us the finger
Two middle fingers
You know there's quite a few
Getting started and then there's this one that actually shows people doing the action
Two fingers on each hand and
There's that you know this
Play which is even more graphic arms out
Pelvic thrust is receiving the physical
So she had a lot options
But with Jeff Ross
She figured that what was necessary
But this kind of intimate
Graphic tone he was down and dirty down and dirty
You didn't have any discomfort with any of that
Arnetta having such a good time I really I really was enjoying it
You asked
Never occurred to me
She was there for one
Girl
1 Def
So there's fourteen thousand people there
But one ticket buyer
I was deaf and ask for sign language
Just one yeah
Young girls that with their mom
But you know where this client was
Yeah oh yeah she was
In that position on the stage because she was
Near where the client
Inside the whole time she's
Sign into words
The client and see her reaction can you just
Scribe
What your client
What's doing
She was like oh so I figured your hand over your eyes
She said the client when it was like a whole body cramps and I think she thought she was getting a lot of attention
The client was mortified
An intermission
My client
Find back to her
We're going to take off and go home now
So I'm like
Has a Kim left because the client left
Yeah we did you manage to talk to this girl at the email there I got the venue to call her
But she hasn't gotten
I'm suddenly feeling bad for this
Does Similac she got a raw deal
Would you get if you had been her
Have you been Kim would you have
You think
Just enjoy yourself a little less
It's been a little less graphic and been a little
Less
Playing with the comedian
I think I would have dialed it down
Knowing me oh my God yeah
You would have dialed it down he's a good man Jasmine translator
A terrible translator me this is one girl in a crowd of 14,000
Then in the transit Reserve
Her not the 40,000
She came to a comedy but it it was there in any way in which Kim had an obligation
To represent the
The client
Can I see the middle between us I think that's
And I think the correct question I think it's a fair question I mean she's not just their represent Jeff Jeff on
No she's there too to be
Mutual representative of people know
Why do a comedy show she's in the show she's translating the show from the state
Person that's what Kim said and if they're yelling
And screaming
Your signs are bigger your faces
Exaggerated you know I made it clear to the tone that he was
Projecting
But after that
Do you feel bad at all did you do feel like you've lost sight of her and you started translating for the whole crowd
I feel like you went Behind Enemy Lines at all
She just said no she was deaf I would have done this
The same thing
Doing my job yes
Cuz that's what a translator.
A translator is
Making what is happening up there available to me
Not creating a middle C
I guess you could argue that if she had made the choice to fingerspell
So that she protected the girl you could see that from her perspective as I was saying that because she's not giving her the full experience
Weird because in her making the equal
Experience and her doing that
She makes an X
Experience with docker
Wow
Other
Camden tell me
She could have taken it
Pressure intimate
Oh no I did not
No
I did not go there
I didn't casual
Badcock
The song deeper 3D pictures about
Disney chocolate Auntie boots
Lesson number 8
How does it make the ribosomes without a ribosome to make the ribosomes
Motivate Barre bedroom
Now you try
Do you guys mind if in the remaining few minutes
We going on an RNA fishing exposition
What's your situation
OKC recently we sat down with a reporter and
And science writer
Carl Zimmer to talk about
RNA
We were talking about something else in RNA chemo
Cuz here's why ever since we started doing the show Robert got
His
Got his
I got a little in system for
All right I was like what do you want to do and you're like what I do or Nana's like
But is there a story in your garden
That if you understood what RNA does you'd realize that translation is
Profoundly important to our existence that's why I said
As I alright fine let's just try it
So we were talking with Carl Zimmer we brought it up now unfortunately I think this is a day when you were out of town
I think you're at your son was getting married
And I was doing like taking work for me
Okay alright
So the definition of translation in biology
Taking a sequence
In DNA
And using the genetic code
Translated
Into protein
Right and the discovery
Of this was
Maybe even more exciting
Then
The discovery of the double helix
It was bigger than the Watson and Crick
Yeah well
At least equivalent
So here's a quick story so what happened was okay to Justice at the table here we all know the DNA is a thing
And that when you're born you get half your DNA from Mom half
Dad
The Francis Crick and James Watson
Figured out
The structure of DNA the basically
The recipe of DNA your recipe
Is comprised of
The four bases
Is in a long string
See
Angie that's it
Pictures of Ramsey like we humans were more than DNA we are these
Fleshy
Peeing piles of muscle and bone and all of that
All the stuff stuff of us comes from proteins
We have a hundred thousand different proteins in our body
Different kinds of proteins to the question was
How does all that get generated account of the
4 simple bass has become the amino acids
Hundreds of thousands of proteins that make
Us
Us how do you make the translation
People were thinking of this as just this
Incredibly complicated problem that might
Never be solved
And
The first person really think seriously about this was not a geneticist
Does cosmetologist make George camo
Gamo just said wait a minute
This isn't that complicated
This is just cryptography
This is a code 4
Demi Lovato
I know the DNA
Is contains four bases A T C and G
They somehow create hundreds of thousands of proteins so I just need to
Think of a clever way of
You know creating a little code machine where you put in the DNA
And then out comes the protein. What what simple code could I do to do that
And just sitting there no experiments no nothing just thinking
This guy came out decides I think that
Are cells read our genes three bases at a time
Like instead of 80
CG
AC, thought maybe it's ATA ccg
TCA
In other words whatever it was it was reading the DNA in the cell maybe it was reading it in triples
Not pair cuz if you have sets of three rather than two game of figured
Possibilities and that might put you on the path to making all those hundreds of thousands of proteins
Now this is just a guess but surely after the double helix Duo Watson Crick and a group of other
Other scientists
Work it all out
They they figured out how you get them
Physically get from DNA into
Proteins
You're so works
Inside the cell
The DNA sitting there all coiled up the set of molecules come along attached to it
Unzip it and it got a copy of it
This copy is now made of RNA which is like DNA very similar still in a basic sort of four letter format
On the move cuz it pedals over to the
Big old factory in the cell called the ribosome
This crazy floppy convulsive Collective of molecules
What's the RNA copy is inside this big Factory another kind of RNA
Comes over and begins to
Read my sister eat at I'm like okay ATA well that must be cool
GGC well that's going to be and it begins to create this chain of amino acids
King of proteins and eventually the ribosome will take this chain and
Ejected out
So that they can go grab oxygen or
Cut up your food or make your hair or the
The cartilage
In your ear your teeth
The neurons that carry the thoughts you think whatever
What does disp
Place the
Quote author
Of you
Cuz I I mean I remember growing up thinking no DNA is my sort of like manual my blueprint or something all of me is in there and
System Outlet opens and then out pops me
But you're saying that there is this
Sting that is reading these three base pairs
Forming any of a
100000 proteins
Suddenly I'm thinking that's where the game is nuts not the DNA but in the thing at 3 Midday and
Well yeah I mean DNA is just a totally meaningless molecule just flopping around
Unless
There is a way of
Reading it
Doesn't the build that they're they're the reader of the DNA come from the DNA
Trip to that's just weird
CW app so you have jeans for
The parts of the ribosome
At this point a producer Tim Howard and Stern wheeler
It's like a book
That
Birth its own reader
That's that will read the book not exactly though because that does you you are certain
Putting DNA pain
That pedal store
Sequential it is it's it's it's first
Indiana House DNA
What you're saying is it in the order of events you begin with DNA and then after that
Get the ribosomes
Events of what
Of you
Okay but but you got to bear in mind that you
I don't know how far back you want to go with you where do we start with you
Do you want to start
Jazz the fertilized egg
Well hello
Sure yeah okay
Chad the fertilized egg has DNA
Annie's ribosomes
House of the Breeders already present
When a cell divides
Two new copies of DNA go into
Each new cell but they also divided up all the ribosomes
From the original cell
So they're taking the factories with
So you the DNA is never without
The code
Okay so it's like Moses
With the tablet
Together
Regular is a Noah can I just have never thought of it that way so I might need to think about
What makes the ribosomes then
Is it come from the DNA I thought you just said that
Yes it is how does it make the ribosome without a
Directions on to help it make the ribosomes
Wait
Translator
DNA code to the ribosomes how do you
Make the ribosome without a
Ribosome to translate
The code to make the rabbits
You couldn't wait a second
I'm so confused right now to take the DNA and the ribosome
Partnership
All the way back
Do billions of years
Zeze
Parts of the system
Evolve and became dependent.
Are there very early in his
Fat girl says a lot of biologists think
The life
Started out
As just
RNA
No DNA
And so you would basically have
Little little organisms that would
Have these little kind of Proto genes made of RNA
Eventually
These RNA molecules started to connect
Amino acids
To make a little building blocks
The proteins
So you're saying that
People generally think RNA came first
That is one of a couple leading
Okay
So it's possible that darnay came first
Then DNA
Somehow it suddenly I'm thinking we shouldn't talk about RNA all the all along
Twilight
I mean just in general RNA has been incredibly
Neglected
The Bible instead of in the beginning was the word should have been in the beginning was
The person reading the word
In the beginning was the code
Did you guys feel the earthquake just now
I really know there was there was some kind of vibration happening
And in my head too because I was thinking but I finally get it now like I get it
Christina got sold to us as like this is the first step in understanding The Mystery of Life
But somehow it doesn't feel like that anymore
Suddenly like RNA the ribosome
That's where the real Myst
II
I like the way you thinking
And so Jen discovers that we are all
Translation
Is the truth
The Deep Secret
Who invited you in
If I said I told you so you wouldn't be able
Translate
And no
Let's say goodbye
GTA V Buy
Now you try
Naked naked
My Little Pony
Sanction
Goody goody
Doesn't make any sense cuz all the syllables are totally of
Okay good
Black heroic translation from the Korean of orally go is by Margaret
Glass piece of thank you
Fiesta
Sing Old MacDonald in Bambara what's the Malaysian language
McCarthy who did our Italian version of
Yankee Doodle Dandy lyrics
German I've Been Working on the Railroad
Azza Khalil who did the Arabic
Amazing Grace and she's the mom of our intern
Of course our Puppeteer from our apocalyptical show Myron do so did our Russian version of You Are My Sunshine
Journal Walia during the Hindi version of
Three Blind Mice on that with the piano and musical interpretation on everything John
Dryden
If you go to our website radiolab.org you can hear
A Proto version of
Radiolab
Spanish
Which we like your
Yep I'm Jared Berkowitz
Start of message
Hi this is David Eagleman hello this is Carl Zimmer
Radiolab is produced by Jad abumrad includes ellenhorn Soren wheeler
Tim Howard Rena Ferrell Molly Webster Melissa O'Donnell Dylan Keith Amy York
Andy Mills
Kelsey Padgett and Matt Kelty withheld from Adrian walk cream ABDO and clear canister
Special thanks to Nancy Updike Larry Kaplan
Suzanne Franks and everyone at language line
And this message
It's the show's over
It definitely Julio
We said goodbye
Too late anyway this is now we're not even here
No this is this is
This is for the people who
Adventure into
Hideous Derek
Territory because
We have
Delete ask
Lister's tutu
To send the end
Can still tell us what you think about
That's a bad mother
Jose Nunez
Holiday for the bedroom
Of a bird