Are you awake
Northern listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
And NPR
Hey I'm Jared
This is Radiolab and a couple of days ago as in like
We we were on stage at the Brooklyn Academy of Music the big opera house they're really beautiful theater and it was full
Thousand people we were part of something close radiolovefest
Radial effects is a big public radio broadcasting radio loving thing
That WNYC station here puts on basic it's a parade of all these amazing public radio shows in pot
Guess we open the Fest
It was called radiolovefest
We figured we would use the opportunity to
Basically talked about the community of people around Radiolab that we love
The Producers the musicians
Featuring amazing acts like
So percussion Hoosier hearing
A lot of stuff happened and we told our story today we're just on this podcast we're going to play two stories for you
Ghost stories about
Love
About heart
The last one wish you were here
Is a is an exclusive interview with Oliver Sacks
Paisley
Give me a kind of valedictory interview
Pretty wonderful
We decided
How to do literally
I look at a heart
This comes to my producer Molly Webster it was scored live by
So percussion
Which is Eric Chou Beach Josh Quillen Jason treuting and Adam zielinski and some people in the audience in theater on inside a pretty
Be strong reaction to what you are about to hear
And we are not
So sure that that may not also be the case if you
You just listening
So if you are driving or operating Machinery maybe this isn't the best piece to listen to cuz it can get a little
Intense which will talk about little bit afterwards
In the meantime here is
Producer Molly Webster
So this is a story about a friend's summer Ash we used to work together
And I think it's fair to say that
Summer has a
Complicated relationship with her heart
You know my heart was not beating
For 3 hours
This is a really crazy.
I was
Technically
Hart dead
I don't know
So couple of things to know about summer
She's like Wicked
Smart she's an astrophysicist
Cheese has a lot of Big Y
Propulsion center of gravity and moment of inertia
X and Y
Remember that original like radial keratotomy
Like no I don't even know what that
Where it is
The other thing to know is she's in
Engineer writes she loves like
Take things
Depart
You sort of like
Poke around
Rewire
Ratchet
And so the thing to know is when she found out she had to go
Get heart surgery she made sure there was someone in the operating room
With a camera
Of my open chest
And the valve
And when things were
Haircuts and when things are being sown in
Completely as a scientist
I want to know what's happening
I want to know why I want to know what you're doing I want to know what's going on around me
Start a backup in
Explain
Summer
Was just
The following up on like a heart diagnosis
Happened about
18 years earlier
And so she had been diagnosed with a murmur
Which is basically
Funny sound in ear
Your heart
And that's in between the thumb thumb
Dlanter this was just
The follow-up
Sure nothing
And so she goes to
Did the doctor
They run a few tests
They sent her on her way and
A few weeks later
It's an email
Don't panic
But I think you should see a heart surgeon
It turns out the situation with her
Carhartt hatching
Her aorta which is
Like the largest
Artery coming out of
Her heart it was
Larger than
Then it should have been
It's supposed to be about
2 cm in diameter and in summer
Yeah what does that mean for your body
So that's the thing
It's asymptomatic
It's not actively harming you but it's
Threat to your life
Because if it rupture it's your main blood vessel and if it goes
You bleed out internally so fast
No ER can help you her doctor says go find a heart surgeon and in the meantime
Are contact Sports
Summer is like a live in New York
Like living in New York is a contact sport people crashing you all the time
Six months later summer find yourself on the operating table they actually
I think I'm not sure the exact order of operations
But they open her sternum from the bottom all the way up to the top
And then they just said
You pull back a rib cage so they can get at her
They put some sort of
Fluid on it that
Stop that from
And they actually started just inject that fluid into the heart
And that short-circuits
So your heart actually
Stops
And then
A hook you up
A bypass
A heart-lung bypass
And one of the things that does is it
Drains the heart of all its blood so it's like flat like a pancake and you can see picture
Pictures of all of this on her blog you can even see pictures true you can even see pictures of
The surgeon cutting 4in out of her aorta and replacing it with
The synthetic to
And the entire time Summers heart is
Just Lim
In quiet
8 hours later
She wakes up
What do you remember
About your first conversation
With your doctors
Oh I don't remember my first conversation much
But I do vividly remember my first thought
Part of my friends
This
Just mind-altering
Pain
Oh my God 8 hours ago I felt
So much better than this can we just go back to that now like Joe
You know everything pulls on your torso
And so when your sternum pain
Cut open and then reconnected
Everything that pulls on that hurts you can't move anything
Or List anything
It hurt to talk
It even hurt to breathe
But literally from
Day one
They make you stand up
And start
Waukee
Really I was like she was like we're going to get you to send child
And that's just too
That's just too
Basically just got to get the heart going again
You know just get it healing
But here's the thing
When it came back
It came back
With a vengeance
3 Fairhill recovery went really well about 2 months in she's in car
Rehab the pain is fading
She's thinking about sending her mother home her mom at
Staying with her for a while
And then one day she's in cardiac rehab
On the elliptical
And so I remember stopping
And I had
This white T-shirt
That would
Literally
Fluttering
With my heart
Like it was blowing in high winds or something
You mean that
You could see it
Yeah even though the physical therapist there could see it
Will it rain
Give me give me like you would look down and you'll see the thing
Your heart beating
Through your chest wall
Pushing you
Shirt off
Well
Because I'm a lady
There is a gap here so like that
Sort of there's a space for that vibration
So to speak
But then she goes home and it was still half a
Like just sitting on a couch not even working out she's like woah my heart is strong it just fell
So strong that I heard of me was like as it seems like
So one day
A few months after surgery she goes to Upstate New York
He's visiting some family friends and she's hanging out with their daughter Julia
She walked in in
We're sending in
My room
They're just chatting
And it's suddenly Julia's eyes get really wide
Feeling there's a oh my God I just I just heard it
She could hear Summers heart
Out loud
2 feet away from
In the room
And I was like okay this is happening
So I guess in typical summer fashion
And she's kind of like let's engineer this if a friend of mine can hear it with her ear what could a studio pickup
She grabs a radio producer friend
Studio and he sticks
A mic about 6in
In front of her chest
And this is what they recorded
This is not a stethoscope this is what it's
Sounds like if you were standing a quiet room next to Summer God that's strong what does that feel
You like it just feels as if my entire rib cage
Age my clavicle my sternum my whole chest cavity is acting like an amp
It is sort of transmitting the vibrations of each heartbeat in fizz
Physically in my body to feel each heartbeat
It feels like somebody has a rubber mallet and it's banging on the inside of my sternum
It is very staccato
When she goes back to the doctor she's like dude my heart
So he sort of just did some like listening and some feeling haha you know what his reaction to was like
So we run some tests and he's like listen your blood pressure is fine
All of your stats are fine
So
I guess I did a really good job Yay good for you but okay I guess I have a strong heart
Yeah a strong heart but I don't want to feel this all the time the doctor was like what
Probably just that there is scar tissue on your sternum
And it's transmitting the vibration
And his back goes away the sea
Fade he said
Sometimes 6 to 9 months
This is when
Maybe the scar tissue
Heels more spins out
Does she's like all right so I can get to that
That's no problem
Sushi sorta just settled in and treated it like a sign
Lego party
If I went to
A restaurant
Where they had like tables for two
But they weren't like this
Sturdiest of tables
If we had water glass
Houses on them and I
Hive
Leaned on the table
Water glass
Looks like Jurassic Park like my heartbeat would be like the
Footsteps of the tired
Yeah so that was like my parties
If you had six months of elation party trick and then
Yeah and then it stopped being a party
Yeah
What happened
And I'm not really sure like
You know incident wise I think for me it was just time passing
Cuz that 9-month Mark
Just came and went
He was still there
And when she asks her doctor he has no idea why
12 months
Still there
15 months
And she says it just started getting really annoying distracting
The funny thing was the more active I was
Then the less aware of it I was
She says when she was at her office trying to be still be still
To either be writing something writing emails
Planning lectures
That's what it would be like
Really loud that's when it would become the most dominant thing like I couldn't go to
Work because it just kept drawing my focus
And when it did it would just feel her with anxiety it was sort of this like
Automatic response and I'll try and explain if it's basically like when you get scared it goes into your
Brain and then the signal goes down into your body do you step on a snake and your brain is like oh my God it's a state-run body
And then your heart
In summers case it was just the opposite there's no snake but her heart was pounding their brain
Would be like oh why is my heart pounding oh my God is there snakes there must be a snake run buddy run
Workout
My brain keeps thinking something must be wrong because we're having we're already doing this
So something must be wrong so I guess something's wrong so let's freak out she was caught in this feedback loop and then
And she was like rightly so edgy and Prime that any emotion on top of that like even if it was
Happiness is just too much oh my gosh it would keep me awake
I would get into hearing the Rhythm feeling the Rhythm
You sort of with the expectation of just next one
Fun
Fun fun
Next one next one next one next one
Next one next one next one
Next
With Every Beat our hearts are just literally tapping out time and
Actually thought about this and there was this idea that was proposed like a right before the dawn episode of Modern hearts
Surgery that we each get 1 billion beats In Our Lifetime and then that's it
And most of us don't notice them going by but in summers case you can't not notice it that I'm aware of it all
It's never not there it's never not noticeable
That beat and it's just like this constant awareness of the future that summer is
Endlessly meditating on my heart takes over and I can't do the things that I want to do and
Not knowing if that's going to last forever or if it's going to end suddenly or
Going to Peter out but not knowing gets me
So she stopped going out as much
She stopped returning phone calls except for like a few close group of friends the worst times we're just
Curled up in bed
And just
Is crying
I really want
Yell at my heart shut up
Stop would you really talk to her
Well I mean I've never had conversations
But I would be like
But it wouldn't
And as time went on
Like the constant pounding
Just became unbearable she describes it as like this alien creature
Is like trying to claw its way out the bottom of my neck
But there was this one moment
Right in the middle of all of this
She had her 2-year check up post-surgery
And for that they had to take up
A picture of her heart
So I schedule my
Two-year appointment and to look at heart they do and
Which is basically a you know like the ultrasound
Like that you got for the pregnant
Yeah it's like a little a little while and then you get the Jelly
We basically go all over
Your upper
You know the area around your heart
I from all different angles
So what ended up happening is I'm lying on my
Left side and I'm facing the wall in the
Technicians by me
And the technician is sort of like reaching around her waving the wand
Her heart
And the monitor for the echocardiogram is
Find summer so she can't see it but
She's wearing eyeglass
So you know how you can sometimes like see a reflection
Peripherally on glasses
Something behind you
Like if you were in a somewhat darker room there was a window like you totally Caesars
So the rooms a little bit darkened
Somers lying there on her side
And she sees the reflection of a
Screen
Oh my glasses
And it catches our eye because
If it's moving
Then I realize what it is that I'm
I'm seeing
A tiny reflection of her heartbeat
And I have this
Moment
I have this moment where I'm like
Oh my gosh
You're my talking to my heart in my head going
We had you're working hard
Like you're trying your hardest you're doing the best that you can
I'm doing the best that I can you're in there and you're working and you are working for me
We are on the same team
And I just totally like I just silently sir
Crying
What do you think
Bird that on like what was it about
Seeing it
There's just something about physically seeing it
Pump
And but feeling it at the same time like knowing that I'm seeing what's happening inside me
That somehow just like
Flicked this understanding into place
She said there was something about seeing it in real-time like a feeling this thing in her chest
Just pulsing in rhythm with what was happening on the screen and then suddenly just
It didn't seem separate from her anymore and all those worries about the future and what was going to happen and was
Going to go away. Stopped no
You are just beating
And that thing is me
It was sort of a sort of like this moment of
Of recognition of its
Purpose and its work and
And sort of this
It's kind of like that whole idea of when you feel like you see somebody
Not just physically like you see who they are
You see what they are but you see who they are
You had that like I felt like ice
CU heart
Like I said
See what you're doing
See what your purpose is
I see you on the one hand what she sees like with her
Engineers brain Izzo
Realization that eventually led to modern medicine right like the minute we took the soul out of the heart
Touch it to cut it open a stitch it up to start fixing things and now we have life spans if I some s
Estimates are 2.5 billion beats on the other hand
When you hear someone's heartbeat your parents or your child
Is an entire lifetime it's a it's a history of Beats it's a series of
Beats yet to come and thinking about
Summer asked us if we wanted to try and listen to her
Can we try that just see if you want to just move the microwave
I'll Stand Up
So she stood up from her chair
How to put a chest
Right in front of the mic and then we all do
Just got really quiet
Oh my God
Oh my god wow it just makes me really emotional everytime I hear it it makes my eyes well with
It's really amazing
Guess I still got it
Good job
Hugo
So give it up for Radiolab producer Molly Webster
And giving up your self protection
That one we said earlier that a lot of people in the audience had strong reactions
You're so I don't know if you could do the same but like when we were doing that story I should definitely seem like something's going on out there
Cuz we were on state I couldn't answer their 20 something going on in the oven is something going on stage but I didn't really know
It was we were in the middle of it
Walk off stage
And the first thing we hear is that
Numerous people had fainted even vomited during that piece we were like
What
Seriously I did not see it coming we really really scared
And I thought oh my God I might get my killing people like it was just like
Are they old
Maybe I can handle it
I just was and then I kind of
Weirdly mortified terrified but if we figured out that no one was hurt
We were like we got
We're like
Would you start putting out my start making some calls to me like what
We make it that I didn't know you thought you was a show is over and we all go home days after
Listen to podcast
The damn thing right with the Swift understand this in the I sound that is completely right
The first person we called was a psychiatrist
Rachel Yehuda
Mount Sinai School of Medicine Department of psychiatry
How was he born
Mitre have any 5 or 6 people out of 2200
Somewhere between 5
And
We don't have a clear number just yet. What might have caused this
Just like a guess
So my best guess about that would be that they have activated their parasympathetic nerves
System
In response to hearing the heartbeat
You just explain our autonomic nervous system is divided into a bunch of different parts you've got your sympathetic nervous system disorder
Fireflight right
Sweat turns on when you're
Scared then you got your parasympathetic nervous system which
Is sort of the opposite
Rather than getting you ready to fight or run
It makes you calm
Dr. Yehuda says it in certain people that parasympathetic response
Kenexa kind of go overboard and their blood pressure can drop
Quickly too quickly
And they end up painting the most common
Give me a list for this to happen in
In real life is
Fainting at the sight of blood
Some people just do that and it's
Not that comment about you
4% of the population
Have is kind of a
And we don't exactly know why it happens there is
Summit Canyon de TI Dia of fainting when you see blood
Is it an Adaptive evolutionary response
That you know maybe back in the day when we were being chased by Predators it would have been a good idea to faint or dead
Nahel skip you
He wants live meet and you're dead meat to eat that
I already.
Another
A theory is an alternate evolutionary what is it
If your blood pressure drops like it does when you faint that kind of protects you a little bit because
You'll have less blood in your arms and legs
So if your arms legs get bitten by a lion say then you're less likely to bleed out
There's nothing juicy to suck on
If your blood is I'm not in your
Winger your limb
Yeah who knows these are just stories but
Going back to the two or 4% thing we got to thinking
2 to 4% of our audience at night
Would be
What we decide Molly was it would be 44 to 88
44 288c 2200
So we put out some emails look at the incident reports
And I think now we have identified
I need us we've heard of maybe 10 or 11
1011 it but I think
It based on some of the stories are coming in that the number might actually be much higher
Example it just manifested itself physically in a way that I
Could not have imagined
I would be the case
This is Maria chaveco
Actually works down the street from us
For the company that makes Latino USA
I was sitting in the front
Against one of the walls but not right at the wall
She says she was listening to the story everything was fine at first but then
She does as the beat kept going
She began to worry
What if it never stops what if someone never gets away from it
And then the drama and got more intense and it was
Pono
Oh no and it was definitely the sense of being trapped that the thing that was giving her life
Which was absolutely necessary was also the thing that was
Tormenting
She says that she was thinking about that
She just kind of got
Short of breath
I looked at my husband
Put my hands up like
Like I got to go
And he looked me he was like are you are right and I was like
I shook my head
And
And I and then I had to talk in my brain like okay
This is an intimate radio moment
You are right in the front area if you get up
6 people have to get up with you what are you doing you're ruining this for everybody
Just Breathe
And it'll be fine and then the deeper I tried to breathe the more anxious I sort of got
And I have this fantasy of like
Standing up and doing like a ruler
But I was like that's
Suck it up
And so
I thought I'm having trouble breathing just thinking about it I don't put no no no no I'm fine I'm fine
That's what my hunches
There might be a lot more than 10 because
Maybe a lot of people just pushed
Through and didn't get up at 6
Still felt weird case one of the most interesting things we bumped into is that doctor you told us it's
It's very pause
At the fainting in the woods penis
Really
In what sense
Well
If you hear somebody's heart
Beading
And you're aware that that's what you're hearing it might arouse of tremendous connection within you
Of hearing the very source of their life
Yeah I became her
I did I just I was there with her and
Will it be a lot to take in and you feel a little faint or emotional I just identified
So much with somebody being
Trapped in their own body I thought she couldn't escape
It was beating in my chest
The drums I felt were beating in my chest and in my
Crazy fantasy you know maybe they were beating at the same Rhythm one of the people that you emailed after the live show said that
He felt like his
Heart was
Trying to match her beat
And he couldn't catch his breath I don't know I haven't I don't know it's never happened to me before
Highest Indian if you ever want to hear someone's heart beat again and she said oh yeah
In fact she said she's going to listen to the story as soon as it was podcast
Which is now
Is that she's got all these questions like what
The Acoustics of the space
What's fact
Issues with so many people or
Videos of volume
It's pretty loud and will I feel the same when I hear it
You know with my headphones on or you know while I'm driving
Will I have that feeling so I had already decided that I was definitely going to listen to
Will let you know what
Toyota brakes when it's so percussion you provided all the music so far
They just released an album called music for wood and strings written by Bryce dessner of the national this is what you're hearing
It's kind of an amazing piece
If you want to check it out go to so percussion.com will also linked to
It from radiolab.org
This is Charlie from Brooke
Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloan
Www.slha.org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help this summer I'm hosting
And I request for those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
We're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments
Brilliance basically I want to hear about those times when a kid you know did something
It just means you lean back and say wow how did they do that maybe it was the moment that a kid
You've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the musical score in math class
Is there ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the
Specific moments where a kid does something super smart but it doesn't have anything to do with the test
If you have a story please share it with us
Go to radiolab.org Brilliance and record a short audio message for us
And that's where you live. Org / brilliance
Thank you so much
Hey I'm Jared I'm run I'm Robert krulwich Radiolab
And we're back
Now going to take you
Live on stage
Academy Music
Miss next door you'll hear some references to some pictures which obviously won't be able
We'll see but we've got them for you at Radiolab.
We want to finish the night with a salute to a guy who's been on our program and part of our family pretty much from the beginning
I have known him
Morgan 35 years
Early I'm going to Radiolab started I asked him if he'd help us out and send us a few story ideas he didn't send us a few he sent us
Bushel Tales of chemistry in medicine hallucinations music people so many extra
Ordinary people that he knew
Founder help
Cuz I just doesn't run out
Dr. Oliver Sacks
Neurologist taco
Is a guy who notices
Everything is deeply interested in
Everything that happens around him into him and tonight we're bringing it back on tape
But alas maybe his final offering Frost as many of you know
Dr. Sachs recently was diagnosed with liver cancer
And you wrote about this in the New York Times he said he plans to spend the time that he has
Laugh
Writing
Be with friends not doing interviews but he did agree to share his thoughts
Exclusively with
Tonight
Are you Galaxy
Cuz he's one of our family
So as I've done for decades now I went over his house in Manhattan with my Mike and I sent
I just need to know what just
A month-and-a-half ago you were fine
And then
I see beginning of the year I was fine
On the 3rd of January I feel Sandoval queer
And I tossed some dark urine
I thought I said little girl bladder attack
Didn't pay that much attention
But thought I better get things checked
And then
Vxrail
Is expected only to show a couple of gallstones
Chode
FAFSA
And my liver
Alumadock
How to say he didn't know what his will and I would
Need further tests
I
I knew what they were
I said it's
He's right the doctors eventually confirmed
A cancer that has been found in his eye 9 years ago had spread to his liver
Were you
Peyton
Or
Relieve orcas
Sore
But you know I am
I think my first feeling was one of
Overwhelming sad
They're also
Strings
I will see
And I will do
One or two people listen to me in
Consoling me
But f*** it it's not like we all die
It's like you have four months
Has that has your property is your prognosis at this moment cuz I know you had an
Well if it gets revised it depends of course on how is the cancer response to treatment sand
Or how quickly it spreads
This is so far
The metastasis from my eye only in my liver
I told they love live
I love liver as well and I'm one of the magical things I did was going to have liver and onions
Sudoku
I'm thinking bad liver looks better than mine far away
This is what he's like instead of being frightened by the thing is trying to kill him he's thinking about loving liver and liver lovers
Looking for connections and one really doesn't stop
He just notices it case in point
A few months ago his doctor said to him We're going to run out a line
Up your liver and ineffective going to straight shave off or start some of the cancer cells first on one side than the other
Go to see if I can give you a little more time
But they warned him
How's the metastasis
Guy
They put on farias contestant Kevin
Send me exhaust you text your system badly
At one point shortly after the procedure
I started talking a little strangely
And I'm as I was talking I was inviting
You'll be the first person to see this
So he showed me a notebook where song it
To you
In just a moment you can see this sort of
Writing there on the left it's all he's writing a book actually children's book about the elementary table
But as he was writing if you if you look to the next page
If you can see that it gets a little bit
Wobbly the letters and then
And then there was some
Crossing out there
Yes I see them then why the dramatic lie
The Whiting
Change it
It actually scares a large
Slash across it and then you get seems a little incoherent at the palace
Okay pure
Atlanta's delirium
Krypton made
All this happened to the course of 10 minutes
I'm writing at a constant speed I know pretty much how fast I write
And so I can time this out I can figure out exactly how long it took me to slip into delirium out of
Of this delirium
Animal Medical West
I think this was a lovely illustration
How to put in a timeline of delirium
Coming like that
Unusual
You don't seem too worried at all when things become incoherent
You're not showing it to me as if interested
I was crazy here for a little bit
The truth is Oliver is fascinated by what goes on in the human mind no matter how strange he gets up there
I went time when he was a young resident in California driving his bike and by the way I I should show you what he look like
Take back then when he was
Driving his bike is I think it's him
In New York
Kind of
You know
In the sixties he was also a champion weightlifter they called him doctor Squad
And in this picture that you show you here
That's him raising six
100 lb
In order to win a trophy like this is that he was a champ and and you can see more pictures like these that cuz we have signed copy
Copies of Oliver's Newman we're out for sale in the lobby
Pretty good book too by the way
In any case at this time
The 1960s in addition to being
Muscled out however was a serious recreational drug taker
And because he's Oliver he was extremely curious about his high as no matter how weird they were
1 time for example you took
20 pills that he shouldn't have
And then to my surprise
How does a spider on the wall
Set hello
Have a voice like that she's also
Famous mathematician
It cost me a wild a technical question as to whether Russell had exploded
Frege's paradox
And we had this
Conversation
Cuz you you trust your perception
Okay many years later when I mentioned this to an entomologist
Cornell
Philosophical spider
Inotes
Taking it all in talking spiders whatever
The generosity of his curiosity becomes profoundly moving and transformative when he's tree
Treating his patients I want to tell onestar here really quickly do to demonstrate what I mean
I never once had a patient when he called mrs. OC
She was
An old woman she was 88 years old living in a nursing home
And one night she was awake and Jarred awake by a loud
I wish
It was a song
And she thought about somebody left the radio on but when she looked
3D when the room is on your roommate
Soundasleep which was odd because the song was really loud
The doors after that
There's another song
And then another song
Which Associates may be my roommate can't hear the songs because the songs are are coming to the fillings in my teeth I've heard that spot
But no her doctor told her this is something in your head you need to see
A neurologist
Which led her to dr. Sachs
That when he met mrs. OC he she could barely hear him the song sung by the female boys were coming and coming she was
Frightened and justifiably worried that she was going crazy but Oliver said no no I'm going to do some tests
And when he was done
He said he found a slight stroke or condition that triggered musical epilepsy 87 production of music
Picking her brain
Normal doctor might say okay we got the diagnosis and he thought that the songs would probably faint it will pass are they worth
But Oliver did not stop
He doesn't stop
He kept talking to her
She told him she was born in Ireland in the 1890s her father died before she was born her mother when she was
Only five she was sent to America
For the Love of beading
Make a note
She had no conscious memory
The first five years of her life
New memories
It's black
We asked her about the songs
What are they like
MS Associated well I think they're lullabies
Can you sing them for me
She did
And then after checking them not sure who I'll ever figured out that these songs what happened to be popular
Irish ballads
From the 1890s where mrs. OC was a little baby
And I gave him an idea
What he does next isn't science
It isn't in any traditional way medicine
He just told her the story
And it goes like
You don't have nobody remembers anything that happens to you when you're one or two or three
Well there was a theory wants not honored much today but it's sad that those earliest memories
Get locked away deep in our brains in a special safe
The weekend never open
So let's suppose mrs. OC
But you are struck by some crazy chance
Open the lock that none of us can break
And release those first memories
In you
Just for a little while
Show that The Voice you're listening to
The homeboy
Maybe that is in the radio boy
Let's play
It's your mother's voice
Pets your missing mother
Until with the ripe old age of 88 you finally get to be back in your mother's arms
You get to be a baby again
Images of the Seas thought about that
Okay it's
Sort of fit
I'm an old woman
Old people's home
But I feel I'm a child in Ireland
I feel my mother's arms I see
Ikea voicing
United
Clinton's wrong
Shortly thereafter the songs began to fade the pauses widen
Mrs. OC he's been so frightened by this music in her head was now
Sorry to see the songs go
But it was Oliver
Who noticed how those songs that touched her
Who noticed that the songs might become a comfort to her because that's what he does
He listens closely
He can hear another person's heart
And this is really the
Profound puzzles for me
About Oliver
Because reading the new what a biography you see that while he was so full of heart as a doctor in his own life
In relationships the really matter
It turns out he didn't get a whole lot of affection
He was for a long time a lonely guy I'd say he was
Very lonely
And he's talking about that now for the first time
Let me talk about love for a minute
In this book you tell the story of your of your very first love
A fella by the name of Richard
Selleck
Can you tell me what
What happened with him
Yeah she was a load Scala
A poet
Unhandsome
Beautiful
Beyond belief
Anais
Fell for him
Although I didn't
Say anything
Because I was some
Very haunted by my mother
Accusations
What is your mother
Well
The Google couple of years back then my father
How to open a conversation I was about to go to office
And I saw the Father song
Conversation
Any setup
You don't seem to have many girlfriends
And I said
No
Wishing the conversation would stop
He said I'm
Something wrong with girls on my I said know that
That's fine
Pepsi prefer boys
And I said well
Yes I do
I said I've never done nothing
But I do
I knew that then
I knew that
Probably since I was 12
And I said
Don't tell Mama
She will be able to take
But my
Father
Did tell my mother in the night
And the next morning she came down with him
I somehow want to say that face of Comber
Enraged me
And my other thing said
Joanne abomination
I wish you would never been born
And then she has something to shut up
And said nothing for 3 days
And
The match was never mentioned the game and highlights
Anthem
2 years later I found myself
The first time in my life
Falling in Love
This was the gun guy Richard
Holler at the time was in college
It was a very positive feeling why didn't know whether it was one which I did Express
But I did
Say so with my heart my mouth
And Richard
Clipped me by the shoulders and he said I know
He said but I'm not that way
But I love you in my own way
And
I was glad I have said that imply versus being received in such a warm February
I thought you might be friends for the rest of our
Lives
But then one day he came into me since he didn't bother by finding
Alarm
In his groin and he was worried
Could I have a look at it
And I looked at it and I felt it
And it was hard and tethered
I turned out to be a
Tiki malignant
Form of lymphedema
Sarcoma
Anthem
He never spoke to me again often
I don't know whether
Since I gained the first to recognize the ominous
Import
Harbinger of death
Messenger of death
Whatever
But you you were left with the
With that silence
Yep
Few years later
Allergy medicine man they mellings younger the Sailor
He liked Oliver he was into weightlifting they became close friends
And they began living together
I adored him and was in love with him and unloved
Physical contact
I need workout need Russell and ride motorcycles kind of tightly in
You never talked about what might or might not be happening between them but one day
They were together and Alder was giving Mel a back massage with smell.off and asked him to do
I love doing that
And Oliver says sometimes he get a little
You know
Excited and gave no indication it was okay
But but but one day things went a bit too far
And I got swatted
I went over the bridge just before the Big Bang
Metal immediate resource
Don't happen
How to shower
Adam said I
I can't stay with you anymore
And then I found that
Very
Cool and upset
That made me feel
I don't want to have anything to do with
People
I must have fallen in love
Kenosha lights with anyone
Again
And he didn't share his life with anyone for a long long
In fact
He told me a story about something that happened
Maybe 8 years ago
I and I was just joining the faculty
Columbiana
I was having this one
An interview
And fun park
The interviewer said to me she said I have something other private Law School
Would you like macejka
Fuel system too lean
Can I said no
Pb2
Or my affairs
And I did say
Thinking she was going to ask me about
I said I haven't had any sex
35 Euros
I bet that's what she was going to ask me my Social Security
Tell the truth is Oliver didn't do anything about it because
He didn't think he could I be chosen Richard lost Richard
Chosen mail lost mail
What's the point he was thinking and then
Find Uno's waiting her why these things happen to people
But a man came along who for the first time
Chose
Oliver
I admit bilious I need the number of people because I've been changed
A manuscript
The book and then
An intimacy grew between us
I don't think I quite realized how deep it
Pause button with a particular episode
In Christmas
All Pro 9
Meineke
Kmart
And in his suit
Serious
Way she has a serious calf of leg
She said I
I have conceived a deep love for you
I have conceived
I got a few extra words I have conceived
Tumblr forgot
Okay was he scared to say I love you
You know she likes the English language
Camping food
More cautiously and yet most lonely
I think that's a beautiful way of putting it
And then I realized
At that moment with his
Saying that
But I had conceived
A deep love
And I
Good God it happened again
And I'm in my 77th year
Arlington
And what next and things
Basically have gone
Happily ever since
And surprisingly guiltlessly
Because then again I'm not dealing with or what I'm dealing with a food
I'm dealing with an individual
I'm not dealing with a.m.
With a condition defined by medicine
Hello
So Oliver still doesn't know how much time he has left for the moment as you can hear
His mind is totally in pacu still riding he has two books in addition to the one you find in the lobby
Beat that is writing in the children's book
Bunch of New Yorkers stories in last few months and a New York Review of Books story
He's got energy to spare so I want to do one last thing for we close
And this comes from yet another conversation I had with him it's a story I know Oliver wood Heat
Because he's not a capital I religious
Buddy is somebody
Who definitely Embraces mystery and for a long time
He's been mystified by a color called
Indigo
Which Newton had inserted
Between blue and violet
I know no two people seem to agree is to what
Indigo was like
And
So I
Hilltop sort of chemical LaunchPad
Meaning took a lot of
Face at Fenton
General Ross
Vincent asset
Analytical cannabis
And when I was fishing tee
Stoned I said I want to see
Indigo
No
Reply
Does This Feeling by giant paintbrush
Therapeutic huge
Trembling pear-shaped blog
Of what I instantly realized
Was pure indigo
Are on the white wall in front of bed
It has had a wonderful luminosity
And in particular I am a religious person
I thought
This is the color of Heaven
And I lived with it and ecstasy
Suppli recipe
He says he had one more moment like that this time no drugs
He was in a museum staring at an Egyptian artifact he sees this
Read and color back again
Just repeat
I was given tantalizing
Of of radian ineffable Beauty and then again it banished
And that was 19
And I've never seen him to go soon
But who knows you know
Someday I like the thing
Dr. sacks make it to see that color
Again
That was the remarkable Sarah lipstate also calls herself no Valor that was
Her own composition
Special thanks also
To Josh Ferguson and keep scratching
Mounted this whole show with no time
Extraordinary
Yeah and certainly a huge huge huge thanks to Alan horn
Carry the load on this thing man
Mickey Capper Advocate Edgar and Cohen and not just wants to Rota everybody at the especially
Call Barbara Wolstein test James and all the folks at so percussion Eric chubby Jason trading at
Production manager.
Thanks also to wnyc's recording engineers
Edward Haver George Wellington and Noriko akube and thanks also to Eva.
I'm jealous I'm Robert Kovac
Thanks for listening