Are you awake
Radio WNYC
Anjana barad this is Radiolab a couple years ago we did a show
About 8
Crazy
Cold War CIA operation
And a little
Trick
Did the CIA invented
To say something without
Saying anything at all
And it just felt like
This one survived with the moment you know with the Mueller report coming out and all the redactions and
Intelligence and counterintelligence
Russia
Another story just going to resonate with us again
Ulcer feels like a throwback to an earlier simpler time
So we just going to play at this week
Hey I'm Jared I'm running today on the podcast
Back a little bit
We have a cloak and dagger Maritime Adventure in secrecy and truth from
Reporter Julia Barton
Just maybe first you can start off just by introducing yourself
Yes of a story for me begins with this guy
Yeah my name is Jeff Larson I'm the data editor at propublica
Outfit and Jeff does a lot of their
Reporting someone in a case
It was
Summer of 2013 you know that big story about how the NSA monitoring millions of Verizon customers
That just came out just watching the story like all of us are end
Then the thought occurred to him
She's are monitoring all of these people pay
Does that include me
So he goes over to the nsa's website
He was surprised to find it right there on the site
File a Privacy Act
For your metadata
They have live online for right there
Service that they offer to everybody
Until I went ahead and did that yourself you're requesting you say what do you what do you know about who I called
Who I heard from yes exact
What were you expecting
The best-case scenario would be just a you know a page of
All of the communications actually to my wife my wife's a Verizon customer and I'm an AT&T customer so I'll
All my phone calls to my wife
I didn't think that I would ever get
Any response back
So he hit submit expecting nothing to happen
It was actually really really
Quick I think it was on the order of
10 or 12 days
You know we came to my home
Address sort of a manila envelope
You know my wife
Call me immediately when she picked up the mail and said hey
You know you got it you got a letter from the National Security Agency and there was
Complete panic in Irvine
So now she's looking in the cabinet
Chris Paul
Beeping out exactly how many open up the letter could you read it
Yeah I have actually have it up right now
The letter said
We cannot acknowledge
The existence or non-existence of
Such metadata or call detail records
Pertaining to the telephone numbers you
Exactly
What does one know when one hears that
I don't know I mean when your Porter and you hear that
It's sort of that you put you in this weird place so Jeff takes the letter into work
Next day and he shows it to a colleague been doing a lot of reporting on drone strikes
Guantanamo and he's like
What the hell is this
Does it mean something and she said that was a glomer respond
How do you spell how do you say is it's how do you spell globe
Glomar
Glomar is a
GL
M a r
Bloom
What did you think
Just of the word
I thought it was I thought it was some lawyer
And Kumar who had argued successfully argued the case
Because it sounds like a bit of legalese
I didn't know the fascinating story behind it
So why start looking into it
And right away found this nutty story involving a nuke
A claw billionaire some manganese
And this classic tension between Secrets being really
Necessary
And really harmful
Sneaking
But to get there you have to
Start with this guy
Okay start out by
Getting your name and how we should identify you know my name is David Sharpe
That's my real name
During the mission my name was David Schultz
So in late 60s David was working at the CIA he's been there for a while and he got called on to
This new thing
Called project azorian I started the program in 1969
Here's what you need to know
In the late 60s the US and the USSR were playing this high-stakes
Chess game with their nuclear submarine
Cruising around international waters and there was a lot of harassment than went on getting on each other's territory
In fact in January 9th
Create a US naval ship
Captured after leaving
Pan and everyone was worried that the Soviets had her code book
And there was an interest in getting even
Well 2 months later
In March of 1968
A Soviet sub called the k-129
Just
Vonage
We don't know exactly why it sunk
There's all kinds of
Conspiracy theories about what might have happened it just sank to the bottom of the ocean
And once the Soviets
Sentara search Cruise out
Trying to locate it
And failed
We came in and
Somehow through our sensor technology or
Whatever reason your conspiracy theory of Choice by tell you
We found the boat
So then the thought was
If we could get inside that thing
Such a bonanza
There was a lot to be learned
Whether it would be the code books the cryptographic equipment for and it's the big one
Missiles it had it had nuclear missiles on the chief of
Naval operations it really wanted to see if we couldn't recover that submarine the whole thing
Problem was at the subway three miles below the surface of the ocean and the pressures at that depth according to David
A roughly 7500 pounds per square inch
14 million pounds
No big one so their solution is to get
A room full of top-secret Engineers together and just start spitballing ideas
Like what if we just went down there to attach Rockets to it blast the target up to the surface
How do we catch it when it comes out what if we okay we could we can
You put these pontoon or gas filled bags and Float the target up except that we can't get the gas
In there because of the pressure must have been amazing meeting or you could say anything
You could say that
So in the end they settled on
Claw
Idea was to build this
Gargantuan eight fingers
Claw and
And a boat
And then you would
Put the claw in the boat
Wring it out
On the high seas
And then you would lower the claw
3 Mile Long piece of
Pipe string
And then like one of those
Carnival games you know where you you have to grab the toy by remote control you would position the cloth over the sub
And exactly so
And then you would
Yankees
Off the bottom of the ocean
Pull it back into the boat
Gatewood open on the bottom of the boat
In the claw and the submarine would come into a chamber
And you would have it
I'm totally not making it up
The CIA made it up
Is it just sounds weird but they did it they got the money they got the approval from the president but they still needed to cover story
So they called up
Billionaire
And they asked him or probably is people do you guys think you could just
Pretend to have a sudden interest in manganese mining from the bottom of the ocean
Because Howard Hughes was a known inventor it wasn't Howard Hughes
Living in isolation in Las Vegas is fingernails growing inches long and being pretty bizarre
You know I don't know if he was living in Las Vegas but the rest of that I think is probably pretty accurate
Anyway so the end up building this massive ship glomar Explorer the ship was called glomar
That's where the word comes from
Yeah it was built by this company called Global Marine
Global Marine glomar and
They get the boat out there
They lower the claw
Clawson MI
Bottom of the ocean where the sub is
Anco headlights and cameras on it
So they could see what was happening
Do you remember when you first
Saw it
It was a very badly mangled hole
And we could see it very well
Big actually could watch as the
Claw wrap its massive claw hand around the sub and begin to pull it back up
14000 ft
12000 feet above 9000 feet from the surface
We were beginning to feel some cautious optimism that we might just pull this thing off after all
Then
I felt so just a little a little bump in the ship
And we went to the control center
And everything look normal
On the television screens
But then it suddenly occurred to the
Operators
That these television images had not been refreshed in other words they were television images taken
Maybe 15 minutes ago
And when they refresh those images and got the real time
Picture of what was going on
It showed that we lost
We lost most of the submarine
Basically
The part of the sub with nukes
With the missiles
Maybe with the code books
And all the stuff they wanted
That part broke off
And
Years of work
Millions of dollars
Just slowly sank to the bottom of the ocean did your heart go
Yeah yeah it did it did it was it was
Tinsley
Emotional
And yet they find anything we still don't really know
They've never actually disclosed what they found in that piece from David's description it sounds like they didn't
Get a lot but
There's a whole reason I'm telling you this
It's because
Not long after that
Bike intense
Moment
Disappointment
The story starts
The break-in the Press
Turtles are starting to
Call up the CIA they're asking all these intense questions they're onto it
And the CIA
Figure out what to say
And what not to say
Jets it's a dilemma
There's no question about that
Which brings us to Walt
Walt Logan
Which is
Just to be clear not your actual name
What's a pseudonym
So in 1975 Walt was a lawyer at the
CIA that time I was leaving associate general counsel
And as a story with breaking and all these journalists were asking questions
It became his job
To develop
The response
Simple
Except not so simple
Yes there's a diplomatic element of what's going on in here that isn't swab
And that is that you have the Soviet Union and the United States
At odds
And the problem was
We didn't want the Soviets
To know either what we had found out
Or what we hadn't found out
Either way would have been bad
If we said that we didn't recover any information on Soviet missile
Which was the truth then that would tell the Soviets that they don't have to worry about the security
Regarding their Warriors
David says we wanted them to worry
This is a cold war we might as well make them think we found something
On the other hand if we said
That we did
Recover information on the missiles
But we're not going to tell you that would be lying
And they couldn't do that
We don't governments lie all the time why can they lie because this is 1974
This is the year of Watergate this is the year that
Congress breaks the entire Federal Security apparatus over the coals
This is also the year they revisit something called the Freedom of Information Act
Boya
Actually Floyd been around for a while but that's when for you finally got some teeth
Place has anybody any American should be able to ask the government for documents and the government has to respond
It has to
For cover that information
Help
Are you put it this way
Well it's not a huge fan of this Loft investment
Time
Resources
And to willy-nilly give it over to somebody who writes a letter to the agency is is
The wall season the cia's job is to keep secrets
In keeping secrets
Keeps America
In fact every CIA employee is legally bound to protect something called intelligence sources and methods
It's not an option it's a law
Hence his
So very well
Under the foil all the public has a right to know on the other hand
He has a legal obligation
To not tell the classic tension of our times exactly
What have to say something
He has to be truthful when he says it
But he also
Cannot reveal anything
And people's agency have been trying to figure this out for months
Is why they brought in
And how long did it
KQ2
Come up with this kind of response
I would say probably a half an hour
Well
That half an hour of work
Tortured journalist
And lawyers for almost four decades
Is we came up with
The glomar response was basically the following
We can neither confirm
Nor deny
The existence of the information request
But
Hypothetically
If such data were to exist the subject matter would be classified as could not be disclosed
Very straightforward
I think about that that's that addresses what we were you were just trying to
Put your finger on
You can't
Confirm it
Which would be giving up Secrets nor deny it
Which would be a lie if it was classified you couldn't be revealed anyway
Suckers as you can imagine
People who file these foia requests when they got a response like that
They were like that's not going to stand
You are the sucker
They fought it in court and the fight went on
4 years knock-down-drag-out but eventually
The government wins
Judge rules in their favor well the judge agreed to their logic that sometimes
Revealing even
Existence of documents
Endangered Nash
Social Security
Kind of response
Bloated to the point where now you here actors like Will Smith using it confirm
Nor deny or Pixar characters using it Hollywood publicist
Confirm nor deny the rumor ex-congressman Anthony Weiner
Konditor confirm
Norton
Become this total
Boilerplate phrase of our time
Swiss Viagra
How do you
Confirm or deny that Conan
But
But on a more serious note
Since that initial glomar response in 1975
More more government agencies have begun to use it surprisingly and not the obvious ones
We found some from the
Department Commerce
Department of the Treasury Department of energy before then
Centers for Disease Control that this thing has legs
And it makes you wonder
Why does this thing have legs
Why now
It is weird like this
That guy that Republican guy
You started with
Jeff Larson
It's all he's asking is what do you know about who I
Call Andy on the answer is expecting to get it's like
You know you call your wife
Why would they glow Mart that well they told him in that letter that if they
Confirm or deny the existence or non-existence
Of those records
It would help
Are at the average
Stories of United
I just I just so that I can sympathize with the United States of America for a moment
Why would that be right
I gave they said you called your wife on Monday at 3 Thursday at 4:30 she called you back at 6
6/15 what would an enemy than learn
I guess that they they would learn
They have records of me calling my wife
Sodium statutory reason why I've read
You're sort of foias are denied with a glow my request
Is that if you say someone is under surveillance by acknowledging record
Or you say they're not under surveillance by
Acknowledging no records
Either way it's outlines
The Contour of the
The program is a tiny crack
Through which people can
Set of puncture the wall and
Get information about the larger program so you just given us the government's position that makes perfect sense to me
Let me look at the thief or to come up and say to me I'm a cop
Are you investigating me if I say yes but he can
Can hide if I say no then you go rob another bank or the other robbers will know that I missed a really good bank robber and I'm
I'm terrible at
In anyway I seem like
I feel suddenly dangerously exposed
I don't know it's all very very confusing and you could wrap your brain around it and never get to sleep for the rest of your life
She thought about it
And by the way there is a we should say a very good
Argument against that argument
That transparency is a good thing
If you have an agency that doesn't have any sort of constraints on it or doesn't have the
Proper oversight
8 / steps
That argument from NPR special correspondent
Dina temple-raston when we come back from the break
Hi my name is Josh and I'm coming from Harlem New York
Radiolab
Supported apart by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloan at www.slha.org
Thanks
I'm Jad abumrad this is Radiolab okay we're back with our story from Julia Barton
About the glomar response where government agencies refused to either confirm or deny
Something in response to a freedom of information requests
And ask Julie was supporting this piece
Robert and I called up NPR special correspondent Dina temple-raston
Just a sound her out
Cassia
Covered counter-terrorism for NPR for years and so she been glomar Don drones she's been blowing hard on
Harris investigations I've never actually heard it
As being glomar
I have to say that she told us something interesting that this
Whole non-denial denial state of
Weirdness
Has created some very unique situations for her as a reporter
Seance
Flanagan Monday
She sits down
Rights of foia requests about the Drone program which will get
Glomar
Then on Tuesday
The government will turn around
Organize a meeting for reporters
About the Drone program a story about a drone target is out and it seems
Incorrect
To the White House
In in a big enough way that they feel they need
Correct the record
So they will often conduct
A conference call
On background with a number of reporters from a number of different organizations
And basically say to those reporters
Okay here are the following people who are talking to
To you but you are not allowed to say
Who they are
And they're going to put this in context
And you can quote them as and they usually set the ground rules in a senior Administration official
Administration officials familiar with
It's a program or something like that
And what then happens is they get to correct the record without
Officially
Confirming that something is going on
There's an interesting thing about the White House in government that
That they believe that they still have deniability if
High-ranking official
Who is unnamed
Says something is go
And as soon as a name is attached
Then the information in their view fundamentally change
It suddenly becomes
Concrete
And actually that's
Kind of what happened with the project azorian that
Glomar Mission from the 70s
Even now the only reason that we know half of what we know about this whole thing
Is because
Some historians we're really dogged with airfoil requests
And they found out about this whole series of
Internal CIA newsletters and in one of those newsletters
There was a
An article with the title that
Clue the man of this
Glomar mission
Before that
Pacific article
Yeah when they have a name of an article than they can for you that and then it's really hard for them to say
No documents exist because they have the actual title of it when it gets specific
Yes
So the CIA released this article but
I mean by now
Decades of past
And
That's what
People now say about the glomar response is that it's just a delaying
Because Congress and
I talk to this one guy Jamil Jaffer he's Deputy legal director of the ACLU and then get Clomid all the time
We've come to expect them now unfortunately you know I mean when they get a glomar
They don't get upset they just think okay
Well we got another two years in court that's what I means it means it means you have two years of litigation before you even get to the point of
Arguing over whether the government has a right to withholding
What was what's happening with his two years
Well
They're trying to strategize so if they really want to know about a program
And I really want to get those document
They will look for any sort of mention
Of those documents by public officials in the same agency
So
Say you have a pen
And you love this
But you don't want anyone to know about it someone asks you if it exists and you say
Say hell no
Confirm or deny right and then you had a party
And you just mentioned in passing you can't help
Lovethispic
Check out this
Right well I was nearby
Now I take it to a judge
And if they look
He's talking about this pen at a party he's bragging about it
He can't refuse.
Confirm or deny its existence anymore so they're looking for cracks in the glomar
Yeah over this two years yeah and it's this
Really expensive legal strategy that most people can't even get to
Only big outfits like the ACLU can even challenge them and their government May ultimately lose it all
These cases but it will lose at a time when the public debate will have moved on to something else
And that's one of the real Danger series
Next Step
By the time the truth finally comes out
We don't actually care anymore it's ancient history
Not for everyone
Bill the divers
Who are specially trained glomar Mission the original plumber mission
Second David Sharp says
After they were able to
Pool that last
Fragment of the sub out of the water
They were able ultimately to look at
Side and where there people in there
There were
There were three crew members that were
Basically
Hole
And recognizable
And there were major parts of another three crewmembers but
They were
They were given the full
Full respect
That I think the Soviet navy would have
Conferred upon their own people
Under those conditions
The problem was we were keeping the whole thing Secret
And that allow the Soviet government
To do the same thing
They probably didn't want the embarrassment of acknowledging that they lost this really important submarine
They also didn't want to derail arms talks that we were having with them
And for a bunch of other reasons they just
Pretended it never
Happened
But they had to say something to the families of
The sailors
Who died on that submarine
3 / 3
There's a widow of
Second in command on the k-129 her name is
Irina is Ravenna
And while ago
She was interviewed on Russia
Television
She showing the death certificate for her husband
And then she reads it
All translated
Cuz I can
3D tattoos
Death certificate
Cause of death
Presumed dead
What did that
This new guy meet you let your skirt
Horrible inhumane
I don't know
Who is the author
Wanted to know for 30 years who is the author of this horrible inhumane document it would save him
This is what we've been living with for 30 years
Eric kossoff
Death presumed dead on the
Doesn't even make any sense and that that's cruel
In this context it's cruelty
That's what she say
Give me an answer that says nothing
Can be worse than just
Silence
Big thanks to reporter Julia Barton there is much more glomar information on our website radiolab.org
This is Danny from Miami
Radiolab was created by Jed abendroth
And is produced by Soren wheeler
Dylan Keith is our director of sound design
Susan lechtenberg is our executive producer
Our staff includes
Simon Adler
Becca Bressler Rachel Cusick
David Gable Bethel have tea
Tracy hunt
Matt kielty
Robert krulwich
Annie McEwen
Naats of nasir
Melissa O'Donnell
Sarakari
Arianne wack
Pat Walters
And Molly Webster
Would help
From Shima Olie
Audrey Quinn
Anil Denisha
Are fact checker
Is Michelle Harris