Are you awake
Northern listening to Radiolab
Radiolab
From WNYC
And NPR
Hey I'm jad abumrad Radiolab
We're talking about
I don't think they'll ever be another space
Actually next podcast
Full hour about stories and grow out of particular thing
Projects for today we have a preview yes or no
So that's the place
This is the place the story about a thing
Lives inside a Steel Vault
Inside this huge Laboratory
At wits University in Johannesburg South Africa
Real estate Professor their doctor Bernards FL to pull it out and show it to a reporter
Patricia Hume
And this is the original
This is it
We have a driver
In front of us here
I mean
I had to listen up when I get this fish every time I
Take this out
The reason it Gibson gooseflesh
Goosebumps is because
This object seems to completely up and two basic questions about
You know human history
Amazing
Where Do We Begin
And when we began who was trying to take us out
Producer Andy Mills takes
Break
With thunder and vigor and gust
Yes I'd like to ask us
Alright it's one of those discoveries
That almost didn't happen
And here to help me tell you the story okay I'm Professor Lee Berger
Is late I am a research professor
At the University of witwatersrand in Johannesburg in an acre
Explorer in Residence at the National Geographic
And explorer-in-residence that's a weird title it seems like you didn't you should be one or the other
Oxymoron is yeah we said that our Story begins back in the 1920s in South Africa at a place call
Call Tong Tong
It's tea and Yugi is the proper lane in Suwanee
The Western way of saying his tongue
It's a a desert area on the
Southern edge of the Kalahari escarpment
Typical picture of Africa
Roxbury about trees running gazelles and
Back in the 1920s
The place was crawling with Europeans
Blasting away with with with dynamite
Drilling with big steam girls and
Huge explosion would take place in one day these miners
They're blowing their way through bit of this Hillside and
As The Rock Falls away
And Smoke Clears they realize that they've opened up this
Cate Blanchett cave
And inside of that cake
They found dozens of these
Strange looking Rock
Almost like animals
What are the miners
He takes those bones given to a geologist geologist
Box them up and send them to this Australian guy who's living in Johannesburg
Named
Raymond.
And that's probably the first miracle in the story
Raymond Dart
Was it neuroanatomy
Comparative neuron
When the only ones in the world this was a guy who knew his fossils
When does box arrived who's actually wearing at 3
He's going to be best man at a wedding in fact later that afternoon but he's like
That can wait
He reached into the box
Shuffle through some Antelope skull was full of baboon skull monkey skulls
Until he got to this one
Note to your me
If this would have just looked like a big chunk of limestone
But Raymond are immediately realized
He had something special and he started
He actually went and got his wife knitting needles
And started
Scratching away at this rock much to his wife discussed
He then spent the next several months
Delicately chipping away at the Limestone until the rock literally
Top free
And there he stared
Into
Perfect
Little
Fix you can see here the face is quite flat and inhumanly
What was the face of a child a human child humans have a larger brain
According to doctors that felt this child's brain was smaller than a human child
It was closer to the size of a chimpanzee
So it had features of the human it had a brain more like a chimpanzees
Stranger still
Start to remember study the sort of thing he looked at the foramen magnum
Hole in the base of your skull for your spine goes in for creatures that walk on four legs
That hole is generally towards
The back of the skull
So they can look forward but here
The holes on the bottom
Which suggested to him that
This creature
Walked upright
It was not a monkey
Wasn't an app as we know it
Today it was certainly not a modern human being this was something in between
If you were walking across a broken Woodland
Queer little conch shell might have lived
You would have seen
Person off in the distance
As you approach though you begin to see that something was wrong with the proportion arms are probably in the long
Longer legs a little bit shorter
And as you step closer you see the little phone shows body would have been covered in this thick hair
More like an ape then then we have but it'd be like Noah ever seen because it would be standing there
In very much the way you would be standing staring at
Onto
So if it is a little bit human a little bit
Kind of in the middle it seems that he did he feel like this was
The quote Missing Link
We don't use that term because Evolution doesn't happen that way there's certainly dark today
He even back wrote a book called adventures with the missing
And right after he discovered the skull he sent
The paper off at amazing speed to journal Nature
Published in February
1925 e. This was going to revolutionize ever
But he was wholeheartedly
Rejected
By the great scientific community
Of your
Batiri
First we already knew that humans didn't evolve in half
Yeah Africa was backwards
That was the belief
Says Chris Stringer on a research leader in human Origins at the Natural History Museum in London
Back in the early 20th century people of the time felt that if you can you can see
Who is wonderful kyva painted many thousands of years ago they prefer to think that you are or Asia one more
Would like to send to Savannah Origins
Inextricable
Second
Scientist already found a skull that they believe belong to the quote-unquote
Missing Link
What's something cool piltdown man
It was this
Ancient
Man
Fossil thing that they found in a golf
Course in England so in their mind that was the right place
And also improved them then you've got this very large Brain and a brain case that looks
Really quite like a more than human one
Which made sense to them
You know clearly European ancestors
Would have had big brain
Because they're European
I'm in the Tomb individual at a smooth brain
Primitive look right
So dark
He spent
The next
Plus years
Arguing with people
This is our ancestor
And getting nowhere
Until
In the late 1920s other fossil started showing up and showing up South Africa Kenya Ethiopia
Fossils they were from roughly the same era as the filter
Their brains are teeth or bone structures they were all totally different
So this was very weird I mean
How do you explain that for decades
Nothing else not till that man turns out from anywhere in the world
Soaps in forensic experts at the London Museum of Natural History they decide
I started looking material under microscopes right off the bat
They found it
One of the teeth clearly showed
The marks of a metal Fallout
The deed has been filed down to look flat
No it down was a fraud
The fake forgery hoax in the hucksters were never caught they will questions in the house is a pond
About the competence of the Natural History Museum that it deletes expert shipping food through this time
This wasn't even a very good fake like for Tricare
The Jawbone of an orangutan they took some Motrin human skull pieces they then stain
Bat material
Doc Brown so eat the same, like stone tools
And all this time
Right there in front of them
Was the poncho
It is estimated Inspirion estimate of being around 2 million 2.2 million years old
Which still today is the oldest
Not
Quite yet human fossil that we have
This this would be
Probably
The greatest
One of the greatest
Ever been argued to be the most important
Single fossil ever discovered in the history of humankind surgery
It brought to the full
That Humanity originate
In Africa
But every human on earth
Is an African
Will of African origin
Butts butts
More than just
Where
We came from which I think it's totally cool
Super interesting weekend we can look at the skull and we can see things
About
You know what life was like
For this
Like little version of us
That lived so long ago you were looking
The teeth
It was eating
Was it eating like what we eat surprisingly similar
Tortoise
So yeah it wasn't it wasn't like
Hugely differ
From what we eat
But I think
The most exciting thing
Vatican telescope
You know not just about what our life
Was like
But
What was
Lurking in the shadows
Waiting
To take us out
You can tell that from this
Diamond Vista school is it
Kind of at the center of this murder
Who killed the tongue shop
At the time when when when Raymond dark
Made that Discovery he had this sort of
Gut feeling that this Taung Child was killed by one of its own
You know cuz this is like 19-24 we were between two Wars War
One hitter
Record the horrible destruction that was actually a medic in that war and he walked away convinced
Humans were were inherently
Evil creatures that were inherently violent and that we are probably a lot worse in the past
In fact the opening of 2001 A Space Odyssey
Where you see the monkeys
Beating each other with the bones was based on Raymond darts theories of the violet
Origin
On the continent of Africa
So that was darts like pets
Siri that maybe tongaat Club down by his brother or his name
But
That ignores one big
In that Limestone mine where the tongs go was found there were also all these others
Boone schools monkey skulls and roses like little collection of Bones
More like what you would expect
Defined in a predator set
Donut
Datong
Like creature but maybe
Cat
Big cat
At least a large mammalian Predator then because that's perfectly acceptable
We're tough
They're tough
It's okay to be killed by something mean and vicious
That became the new Theory
Because
What else do humans have to fear
Write what now here's where I think maybe you come into the story for some reason when you arrive
Many many many years later
This idea
The cat did it
Seems to disturb
I was addicted to that story is anyone else I've been brought up on it through my anthropology classes every every
Book I ever read said that
But
One day in in 1990
For he bumps into a completely new idea Eureka moment
Is there I was
At Gladys field
An excavation site in South Africa Lee and his team we're doing what they do digging for fossils I just finish Excavating
Haitian Almighty mid left and I was sitting there watching the Sun
And I looked up on the hillside
There was a troop of vervet monkeys are small gray monkey
Never coming down to Ford's down the hill
It also sent her an alarm call
I looked up in the sky
And there came
Huge eagle
The Monkees
Scatter is Eagle swooped around the edge of
And as it came down around the edge of the hill I realized you
The Trap
Because coming around the other agent Hill
Was that Eagles make
Edit
Zoomed in
And whack one of those large monkeys
Right in front
And everything went silent
The other Eagle landed this Eagle sitting on top of a now-dead monkey
Eagle staring at me
I'm stranded it probably would
My mouth open looks at me for a moment
And then leaps off the edge of this cliff
Cliff with the dead monkey
And flies away with
Is it down
And I had no idea
So I got into my car
I chase the direction it went I knew it was going I knew but he's Black Eagle Nest where they were up on a cliff face
I crawled up under crossing the river crawled up under the
The nest and there was
Pilot
Shoot
Hyraxes little antelope
Baboon skull
Baby baboon skull
Almost every one of the bones there
These amazing
Markson
Keyhole shaped Cuts where the Eagles have
Driven their talents into the skull
These big eagles can have
Killing talented 5 6 7 in long if you can imagine that
I got in my car back to the lab in joburg
He wakes up in the drawer that contains those
Skulls and bones that were found
With the taung child skull
And
Zach
C Mart
Kimberly
There's even like
A little Mark on the tongue child skull itself
A year later 1995 he and a colleague they publish a paper
Burdett blamed Eagles
The death of The Gong Show
And it was received
Like
Smelly wet blanket
Why why why why would they not say oh of course
Because
It was entrenched ID
Lee says maybe subconsciously
They felt they
Like our ancestors are being demoted again that is the
You know we were not the masters of our universe
Because
Cats just
Steel tougher than Birds
I don't know but according to leave the big cat scientist were let you know it's been published it's been published delivered
For 40 years Sweden gun
Into a debate in the in the
Colored pages of
The journal Nature
Under load lifting capacity of birds of prey on whether or not birds-of-prey could lift something Islam
Large is the taung child
And these debate
They went on for
Ears
He couldn't convince people
We need something more until one night about 9 at night
Years later his home scene in my little study
He was reading an academic paper about eagles and how eagles sometimes when they kill little mammals
They'll reach into their eye sockets
And pluck out their eyes to get it the nice juicy brain on the inside
And in the paper it was a really beautiful image
What's beautiful to me
People who study dead things
Beautiful image of skull of a primate
With the interior socket
Eyes
With these Jagged marks
These very particular scratch marks
On the underside of the eye socket
And I was staring at these images and
I went
Oh my goodness or something to that effect I got in my car
Drove down to the lab open up the safe
Hold on
Turn the face over
And there they were
On the base of the inside of the eye socket where these Jagged Richard Marx
That you had to have done
By reaching into the orb
The exact
Same
Mark you can see little little exclamation mark
Cummins
No one had noticed
In Imagine I'm sitting in the middle of this Anatomy Department in the middle of the night
In a vault containing million-year-old fossil a Magic Moment
It's so now you know
A little bit about how this creature lived and how it died
I mean Beyond solving the murder mystery what does that tell you
First to say solving the murder mysteries kind of cool
There's nothing wrong with just doing that
Have you ever thought
Why when you're standing out on a
Playground
Or standing out in open field
And a shadow passes over you
Do you know that feeling that occurred whether it be from an airplane or whatever
First you get that tingly feeling on the back of your neck and then you
Yank your head up you ever wondered why you do that
You do that
Because the little Tong child died two and a half million years ago
Because he didn't look up quick enough
Producer animals
What did you say
One very important thing to say is actually didn't experiment with the story we hooked up with some people at MakerBot
It's a very nice folks
The field museum in Chicago
And we had 3D scans made of the taung child skull next to holding on right now
Mine's purple Instinct replicas of the
Taung child skull menu
The Ridges you can feel the scratches in the eyes if you could listen to the store YouTube
While holding the tongue child in your hair well that's exactly the reason we did this
We have partnered with a museum
World Museum
That's spelled with forums two in the front two in the back Museum
It's this tiny little Elevator Shaft size place
Here in Manhattan where they display all these sort of like Oddities you know like little
Objects from Saddam Hussein's Palace
I have a
Cool toys that were banned from Saudi Arabia right
And they will also be displaying error
3d replica of the taung skull
So if you go there
Can I see hold the skull you dial in a little number and you can hear part of the Peace
Is to listen to the story while holding this
Not only that if you have a 3D printer of your own
And you go to radiolab.org you can download a scanner 3D scan of the tongue skull
You can put your own
Thanks again to MakerBot and to shoot digital for helping
How to make that happen
Preston Levy for conceiving of the whole idea go to our website radiolab.org I'm Jedi boom wrought iron
Thanks for listening
Hi this is Lisa back calling from Fort Worth Texas
Radiolab supported in part by the National Science Foundation
And by the alpha
Poppy slime Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloan @www. Sloan.
This is Cliff Friedman calling from the University of Miami in Coral Gables Florida
Radiolab is supported by Squarespace
The only one platform dedicated to providing a simple way to create a website portfolio or online store for business
The personal use
Squarespace
Knights Templar
What's a dragon drop tools
Create professional website
Users create sites that are mobile ready
Including 24/7
Support domain names and
E-commerce all on the same platform
Free trial
Squarespace.com Radiolab