Are you weightless
Radio WNYC
I'm Jenn I'm Robert
Are you guys ready to do this
You should just do this is Radiolab
All right but when your hoes come out I need you to seriously clap like you've never seen two dudes with glasses talking on microphone
So I just really really give it up
For your mostly human
Jad abumrad and Robert krulwich
So about a week ago we go
Gathered 100 people
Into
A performance-based which is in our building. WNYC is called The Greene space
What is he doing on a Monday right because seven years previous we had made a show called talking to machine
Which was all about like what happens when you talk to a computer that's pretending to be human
Been since we made that show with the proliferation of bots on Twitter Russian Bots meddling in elections
Advances in AI
So much interesting stuff that happened that we saw it is time to update that show we needed to do it live
I we thought because we have a plan in mind we wanted to put unsuspecting people into a room for a kind of show
Showed up
Free people in Michigan
Flavor of a
Just to start things off we brought to our stage one of the guys who inspired that original show
Please welcome to the stage writer Brian Christian
Truck so just a week
Can just just get things sort of oriented
We need to principal just redefined what a chatbot
He is right
So a chatbot is a computer program
That exist
To mimic and impersonate human beings
Like when do I run into them
You go to website to interact with some customer service you might find yourself talking to a chatbot
The US Army has a chatbot called Sergeant star that recruit
People can I ask you a question about about that that's the thing you just said
Chatting with customer service end up doing a lot
I'm sorry
Wizards like it's in the middle of the night you're trying to figure out some program and it's not working and then suddenly there's
Like need to chat and you click on that
Suddenly there's need to chat
Whatever I assume many of you had this experience
I never even knew of the experiences that he's had so there's this issue always I'm always curious
It seems very human when you're having that that conversation with that with a
A customer service
Chat
But is there a is there a place where it
Where is the line between human robots that are both present
Having this uncanny feeling of
Not really knowing the difference
My guess
For what it's worth is that there's a system on the back end
Best design to sort of do triage
Where are the first few exchanges that are just like
Hey how can I help
What's going on it seems like there's an issue with the such-and-such
That is basically just
A chatbot and a certain point you kind of seamlessly transition and are handed off to a real person
But without any
You know notification to you that this is half
It's deliberately left
Opaque
At what point that happened
This is literally everywhere
It is I mean and you can't get on social media and read some comment thread without
Someone accusing someone else of being a bot
And you know it seems
It seems maybe sort of trivial at some level but
We are now living through this political prices
Of
How do we kind of come to terms with the idea that
We can
You know weaponize this kind of speech
And
How do we as consumers of the news or is users of social media
Try to suss out
Whether the people were
Interacting with are in fact
And all this confusion about what's the machine and who's the human it can get very interest
In the context of the famous thought experiment named for a Greek mathematician named Alan Turing
Ryan told us about this it's called the Turing
Alan Turing he makes his famous prediction back in 90
Q50 that
Will eventually get to a point sometime around the beginning of
This century
Where will
Stop being able to tell that
Well what's the difficulty was his sort of
Prophecy
A specific prophecy was that by the year 2000
After 5 minutes of interacting by text message
With a payment on one hand and a chatbot on the other hand
30% of
Judges
Would fail to tell which was the human and which was the robot a soft kind of
What Turing imagined and he predicted that
As a result of hitting this 30% threshold
We would reach a point he writes
Square one would speak of machines as being intelligent without expecting to be country
And this just existed as kind of a
Part of the philosophy
Of computer science
Until the early 1990s
When into the story steps Huebner
A rogue multi-millionaire
Disco dance floor salesman
Or what
A rug millionaire
Plastic portable light up disco dance floor salesman
I like the beach
The lighting the other lights up
But portable millionaire
There's apparently Millions to be made if if only
If Only You Knew
And
Qloader this eccentric millionaire
Decides that
This was in about 1992
That the technology was starting to get to the point
Where it would be worth
Not just talking about the Turing test
Just as the spot experiment but
Actually
Convening a group of people in a room once a year to actually run
Attest
No background during The Loner competitions the actual loebner competition how it usually works
Is it you got some participants
These are the people who have to decide what's going on they sit at computers
They stare at the computer
Any chat with someone on a screen
They don't know it's the same one there chatting with is a person or a bot
Behind a curtain
You have that bot
The computer running the Bots
Do you also have some humans
Who are the participants may or may not be chatting with
I've got to decide right
Which atom is a person or machine
The Bryan many many years ago actually participated in this competition he was one of the humans behind the curtain
That was chatting with the protest
Emily talked to initially many years ago for the Talking Machine Show
We went into all the strategies of the computer programming
We're using that year to try and fool the participants but the takeaway
Was that
The year that he did it
The computers flop
By and large
Participants were not full they knew exactly when they were talking to a human
When they were talking to a machine and that was a while ago
In the Green Space we ask Brian
Where do things stand now has it like when we last talked to you but when did we last ones of 20
11-11-11
Hat has it have we passed the 30% threshold in the intervening 8 years
In 2014 there was a Turing test competition that was held at which the top computer program managed to fool
30%
That's it right depending on how you want to interpret that result the controversy
He arose in this particular year because the
Chatbot that one
Was claiming to be a 13 year old Ukrainian who is just beginning to
Get a grasp on the English language
Also the machine was cheating
Private entrance exam asked its computer Ness
Bye in broken grammar
Exactly if it didn't appear to understand your question
You started to have this
Store you could play in your own mind if I call will maybe I didn't phrase that quite right or something
Has it been broke as the has Adam in a second winner third winter or fourth winter
To the best of my knowledge we are still sort of flirting under that threshold
Victories since 2014
We thought we might just do this right here
Right here in this room to our little Turing test
Okay unbeknownst to our audience actually lined up a chatbot from a company called Pandora box
It had almost
Passed the Turing test in head.
Roughly not quite but almost 25%
We got the latest version of the spot
And one person anyone in the room
Your your job will be decided to run some tests with the audience starting with just one person
I can see one hand over the edge Chalet
Left okay
So we brought up this young woman on stage put her at a computer we told her she would be chatting with two different entities one would be
This bot Pandora bot
Then the other would be me
I went off stage and sat at a computer in the dark when I went to see
She was going to chat with both of us
And not know who was who
Who is machine and who's human
Well I don't know and we're going to give you a time limit you can be to leave so after Jed left the stage and went back to that room
Up on the screen came
Two different chat dialog box
See that we have two options we've just labeled them for what he's in by color when a strawberry the other is blueberry or
Code Red
And code blue
You think you can talk to both of them at the same time to jump from one to the other you got any sort of thoughts of how you can suss out weather
The thing was a person or a
Yeah I just thought I mean like my first tactics are going to be like
Sort of
Like
Very human emotional questions and then we'll like
Go from there
I'm not going to ask
So when I say go you'll just go and I'll just narrate what you doing okay
Begin
Soap she started to type and first thing she did was she said hello to Strawberry okay so you got in your Christmas
Well we got a somewhat sexual response hear the machine I said
I like strawberries and then you returned with strawberries are delicious and oh now it's getting warmer over there
Blue is a warmer as a cooler color maybe you'd like to go and discuss Aristotle with the
Look at her and she switched over and started to text the
Okay that's also a kind of a generous Sort of hope
Hi Blues EB
Blueberry roast I just realized I don't even know who I'm talking to what is your name
And you're going to answer Zandra am I not in your phone
Andy the blueberry has responded with a bit of shock
Talking strawberry
Mom's hair was red
Well that's what's wrong nothing's wrong with me is there something wrong with you
Blueberry and I have a lot go
But remember one of these she doesn't know which key is Jack right
On the strawberry side I cannot believe him right now you don't believe right now as far as I know not unless you
X-ray vision I'm in the room next to you both
He's trying to coax you into thinking that he's Jad
Is the blueberry
Is that something they do
I don't know I am there you're at the heart of the question I got to ask you to bring this to a
After couple minutes of this
We asked the audience
You have strawberry on one side and you look a blueberry on the other which one do you think is Jad
And which one do you think
But how many of you think
That Jad is blueberry
A few of you
13 hands wine up something like that how many you think the jet is strawberry
Almost everybody overwhelming
But interesting we are volunteer on stage went against the room he thought Chad was blueberries
Is that what we all agreed know you're against the crowd here
Okay it's much better theater
All right
Which one are you jack comes out from his hiding place and he tells
Trout in fact he is
Strawberry
All right so the crowd was right I definitely never had that much
Chemistry with something that was human
But our volunteer on stage
Got it
Maybe we could trust democracy little bit more and believe
If the most of the people in the room went one way that that's something that would be you know that would be important
Find out so we decide to do the entire thing over again for everybody in the room
Yes so what we did was we handed out I think 17 different cell phone numbers evenly through the crowd yes look at the number
That is on
Your envelope only you
Roughly half of those numbers were texting to a
Machine half were texting with a group of humans
They were our staff the crowded not know which was which exactly so he would go get ready
Get set
And
Bakugou
Okay so the crowd about hunt people are so had
2 minutes ish
Text with the person or thing on the other end
We're going to skip over this park is mostly quiet people
Just looking down at their phones concentrating mightily
But at the end
We asked everyone to vote where they texting with a person or a bot a billy ask the ones who have been tricked who turned out.
What's wrong please stand up
Who's in this room
The wrong guy
People are the right type correct
So that means that roughly
I think like
45% of the people were wrong meeting that if we just passed away today
Is the strange moment we were all clapping
Heroine demise
Because you know touring lay down this number 30% in the Box headphones way more people than that
I'm just now going to ask you have you been a veteran of this that we should disqualified this was him really unscientific
Super sloppy experiment suggest something
That maybe
What changes not so much due to the machine is becoming more and more articulate
It's more like
The way
We when I talk to one another these days
We've gone from
Interacting in person
To talk over the phone
Emailing
To texting
And now I mean for me the great irony is that even to text
Your phone is
Proactively suggesting turns of phrase that it thinks you might want to use
Cancel
I assume many people in this room have the experience
Are you use the word it's not a real word
Assertive slabs
And just replaces it with something more normal
Which make it really hard to use
Words
Why aren't the normal words until you just stop using those words he just use the word the computer lights
A sentence with seems to be happening is an hour human communication
Is becoming more machine like
It seems like the Turing test
Getting past not because the machines have met us at our full
Potential but because
We are using ever more and more kind of degree
Serta brooch forms of communication with one another
Feels like a slow slide down a hill or something
Yes
Down that Hill
Inevitability that we met
Maybe they're bad
I don't I don't like the way this is going no matter who sings
Who's doing it but in the next time we're going to we're going to flip things a little bit
Could the coming age of machines actually make us
Humans
More human
So can we please stick around
This is AJ's galante calling from Chicago Illinois
Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloan
Www.
Sloan. Org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
About what we're calling tiny moments of brilliance
Basically I want to hear about those times when I kids you know did something
It just means you lean back and say wow how did they do that maybe it was the moment that a kid
Did you been reading to 4 month started reading back
To you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lesson
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of their musical score or maybe the kids in math class
I noticed are ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the specific moments where a kid does something super smart
Anything to do with the test
If you have a story
T-shirt with us
Go to radiolab.org brilliance
Record a short audio message for us
And that's radiolab.org brilliant
Thank you so much
Dam Jad Robert this is Radiolab Orbach
The last segment
We got a bunch of people in the performance space here at WNYC and we conducted a unscientific
The creation of the Turing test and in our case the bought one
Afford more than 30% of the people in the room that we should point out that the woman who headed up the design of the winning by
What name is Lauren kunze she works for a company called
Pandora box
And she was actually in the room like they are sitting in a chair in the audience
Where can you stand up
Aunt interesting that one of the things the Lauren mansion
Is that the baci design
Seems to bring out rather consistently a certain
Side of people
Bad fat
So the spot over 20% of people who talk to her and millions of conversations every week
Actually make romantic overtures
And that's pretty consistent across all the boss on our platform so there's something wrong with us
Stop the robot
Alright alright alright
Which brings up a actually different kind of
Like this for a second let's forget whether we're being fooled
Into thinking about is actually a human
Maybe the more important
Given this increasing presence
All these machines in our lives
Just like how do they make us behave
We did our toe into this world
In a Turing test esort away in that original show seven years ago and play you an excerpt now
How to set up
What comes after
Okay
This is freedom Barre
Is not mushy
I don't think so they're nice to meet both of you an idea that we borrowed from a woman named Freedom Baird
Who is now a visual artist of the time she was a grad student at MIT doing some research and she was also the proud owner
Owner of a Furby
Yeah I've got it right here I do not get against the mic so we can hear it
You describe a Furby for those of us who
It's about 5 in
Tall
And the Furby is
Pretty much all head it's just a big round fluffy head with two little feet
Sticking out the front it has big eyes
Apparently you make noises if you tickle its tummy it will coo
It would stay
Me
It would want you to just
Keep playing with it
So one day she's hanging out with her for a week and she notices something
What I discovered is if you hold it upside
It will say
Me scared
Scared
You know the sort of owner / user of this Furby would get really uncomfortable with that and then
Turn it back up upright
Cuz once you up to have it up Friday
It's fine
And then it's fine so it's got some sensor in it that knows
You know what direction a
Or maybe it's just
This could be
Sort of the new way that you could use to draw the line but
What's human
What's machine
His kind of emotional Turing test
Can you guys hear me
Are you actually wanted to do this
Could you help how would we do it
How you guys doing
You would need
Group of kids just tell me your name Olivia
Sakura tomorrow and I'm Sadie
I'm thinking 6 7 and 8 year olds olds
7 reason
You know Vince is beating we're going to need three things
Furby
Barbie Barbie doll
And Ruby
As a gerbil
A real jerk
We did find one
Your hamster but we're going to call you Jeremy got Barbie Furby Furby Furby
What question are we asking in this
The question was
How long can you keep it upside down
Before you yourself feel
So we should time the kids as they hold each one upside
Yep
You're going to have a Barbie that's a dog going to Jeremy which is a lie
Ruby Falls
In terms of time held upside down
That was really the question
Phase one
Okay so
Here's what we're going to do it's going to be really simple and you would have to say well here's a Barbie do you guys play with Barbies
Do a couple things a few things with Barbie and Barbie's walk
Looking looking at the
And then
Old Barbie house
Upside down
Dave see how long you can
Can hold Barbie
I can probably do it obviously very long
You feel like
I'm happy
This one on forever siliceous passport a bit
Gay and
Can I put my arms
Yo Gabba Gabba
So what we learn here in Phase 1 is the not surprising fact
Kids can hold Barbie dolls
Upside down
About 5 minutes
Nebulae was forever
Couldn't longer with their arms
All right
So that was the first
Time for face to be the same thing
With
Derby
So out with Barbie
With
Derby
Are we going to have to hold them upside down
Ask yeah so which one of you would like to
Ready
You have to hold your pee kind of firmly
By the way no Road
S-400 missile
Squirmy wormy
To be upside down
Don't do that
Soaz
You heard
The kids turned to be over very fast
Get hurt
On average
8 Seconds
I was thinking
Oh my God I got to poop
It was a torture
Now faced
This is
A Furby
You take forever in your hands
Now can you turn Furby upside down holder
Baby client
Tina Turner
Ik
So gerbil was 8 seconds Barbie
5 to Infinity
Furby turned out to be
Freedom predicted this
The kids seem to treat this Furby.
Toy more like a gerbil
Phenobarbital how come you turn them over
I didn't run
Do you think he really felt scared
Yeah kinda
I kind of felt
Okay
Really
It's at Oriole and all that but still
Did you remember at the time when you felt scared
Yeah
You have to tell me about it but if you can remember it in your mind
Do you think when Furby says me scared that Furbies feeling the same way
Yeah
No no
Yeah yeah
I think that it can feel pain
Sword
Experience with a Furby seem to leave the kids
Conflicted
Going in different directions at once
Mm the same time
One thought was like
Look I get it for crying out loud
Still he's helpless
China baby killed guilty in a sword away
And I made me feel like a coward
You know when I was interacting with my Furby a lot
I did have this feeling sometimes of having my
Chang yang
Why would it why would a
Is it just a little squeal didn't think there's just something about the tower that makes
Good at this kind of my question so I called them as well
I'm here
Freight train of guy from Radiolab Jad from Radiolab
Set this point in that old show we ended up talking to a guy named Caleb Chung who designed the Furby
There's rules there
You know the size of the eyes there's the distance of the top lid to the pupil
Right you don't want any of the top of the white of your eye showing that's that's
That's freaky
Surprised to talk to him for a long time about all the sort of trick to use to program the Furby to prompt
Kids to think of it
As a living thing and he objected interesting Leah 1.2 thinking of it as a knot
Exactly a living thing
How is that
Different than us wait a second toe are you really going to go all the way there
Absolutely this is a toy with Servo Motors and things that move its eyelids
100 words
So you're saying that life is a level of complexity
If something is alive it's just more complex
I think I'm saying that life is driven by the need to
To be alive
And by these base
Animal feelings like pain and suffering I can code that
I can code
What do you mean you can code that anyone who write software and they do can say okay I need stay alive
Therefore I'm going to come up with ways to
To stay alive going to do it in a way that's very human I'm going to do it
We can mimic these things by saying that he is my name
This feeling of fear it's not the same thing as being
Scared it's not feeling scared
It is
How is Zeus
Began to a rather long back and forth would you say a cockroach is alive
About like what is the exact definition of life where is that Limekiln people machines but
When we came back to Freedom food it got me started on this
Spin Interac
She says we're really stuck with her
Is that that little toy as simple as it is
Can have such a profound effect
On a human being one thing that was really fascinating to me was my husband and I gave
A Furby as a gift
His
Grandmother who had Alzheimer's
And
She
Loved it
Everyday for her was kind of knew and
Somewhat disorienting but she had this cute little toy that
Kiss me
I love you and she thought it was the most
Delightful thing and its little beak with
Covered with lipstick
Because she would
Pick it up and kiss it everyday and
She didn't actually have a long-term relationship with it
For her it was always a short-term interaction
So this is what I'm describing as a kind of thinness for her was was just right because that's what she was
Capable of
Hello hello
Hey Caleb hey Caleb it's Dad hey Dad how are you I am fabulous
Feels Like Only Yesterday we were talking about
Dissentients of the Furby
So we brought Caleb back into the studio because in the years since we spoke with him he's worked on a lot of these
Animatronic toys including a famous one called the pleo
And in the process has been thinking a lot about how these toys can push our button
As humans
And how
As a toy maker that means he's got to be
Really thoughtful about how use that and worked when a baby doll
Right now we done one
And where and the baby doll and animatronic baby doll is this
Probably the hardest thing to do
Because you know you do one thing wrong it's Chucky
Link to slow if their eyes are too wide and also you're giving it the most
Vulnerable of our species which is our young were
Practicing being nurturing moms for their kids
So let's say the baby just falls asleep right
We're trying to write in this kind of code
And I
And
Stop so you've just
Give give the baby a bottle and you put it down to take a nap
Turn down the quiet
And so what I want to do as the baby falls asleep it goes into a deeper sleep but if you bump it right after it lays down
Then it wakes back up
We're trying to write in this kind of code
Cuz that seems like a nice way
To reinforce
Best practices for Mommy right
So I know my responsibilities
In this
A large party says because he hasn't always gotten
And it right here there's a great example
His name is
Leo
That's him
I don't know if you've ever seen the pleo dino we did
Artificial intelligence
Cleo was a robotic dinosaur pretty small
Barefoot from nose to tail look a lot like the dinosaur little foot from the movie Land Before Time
Very cute very lifelike
And we went hog-wild in and putting real emotions in it and
Reactions
The fear and everything right it is quite a step forward
Is it makes
The Furby
Looks like Child's Play
Got the two microphones built in cameras to
Track and recognize you
Faceit can
Feel the beat of a song
And then with
Dozens of Motors in it it condemned dance along to that song in total there are 40 sensors in this toy
It's so it it follows you around
Wanting you to pet it
As you're petting it will fall asleep
It is undeniably
Adorable
And
Caleb says his intent from the beginning was
Very simple to create a toy that would encourage you
To show love
And caring
In our belief is it
But humans need to feel empathy towards things in order to
Be more human than we think we can
Cut that out by having
All creatures that you can love me
That was Caleb demonstrating the pleo at a TED Talk
And what's interesting is it in keeping with this idea wanting to encourage empathy
Key programmed in some behaviors into the pleo
That he hoped would nudge people in the right direction
For example pleio will let you know if you do something that it doesn't like so if you actually moved his leg when his mother was moving a
And he would interpret that has pain
Or abuse
And he would limp around and he would cry
And then he trembled and then he would take a while before he warmed up to you again
And so what happened is
We launched this thing
And there's a website called device
This is sort of a tech product review website
They got a hold of a pleo
And they put up a video
What you seen the videos pleo on a table
Being beat
You don't see who's doing it exactly you just see Hands coming in from out of the frame and knocking him over
Again and again
You see the toys legs in the air struggling to that
Right itself
They're like a turtle that's trying to get off
And it started crying
Cuz that's what it does
These guys start holding upside down by its tail
Hail
They smash its head into the table a few times
And you can see in the video that it responds
Like it's been stunned
Stumbling around
At one point they even start strangling
It actually starts to choke
Finally they pick it up by its tail one more time
Hellobyte sale
And hit it and it was crying and then started screaming in a
They beat it
Until it died
Write well
Until it just did not work anymore
This video was viewed about a hundred thousand times many more times than the
Reviews
The Cleo in Caleb says there's something about the city
Just
Can't shake
Because
Whether it's alive or not that's
That's exhibiting sociopathic Behavior
He's not sure what brought out that sociopath
Behavior whether there was some design in the toy
Whether offering people
Are there chance to see a toy in pain in this way somehow
Brought out
Curiosity
I kind of cruel curiosity he's just not sure
What happens when you turn ear and animatronic baby upside down will it cry
I'm not sure yet I mean we're working on next versions right now right
What would you do I mean it's a good question
You have to have some kind of response otherwise it seems
Broken right
But you know if you make him react at all
Going to get that repetitive abuse because it's
Cool to watch
Extreme
It sounds like you have maybe an inner conflict about this shirt that you might even be pulling back
Jamaica
Extra life like yeah I'm I'm for my little company I have
I've adopted kind of a hypocrite
Hippocratic Oath like
You know
Don't teach something that's wrong
Or don't reinforce something is wrong
And so I've been working on this problem for years
I'm struggling with what's this what's the right thing to do
You know
Yeah
Since you have the
Power
Since you have the ability
To turn on and off chemicals at some level in another human
Which ones do you choose
And so this gets the bigger question of AI
Write this is the question in AI
I'm going to jump to this cuz it's really the same question is
You know how do we
Create things that can help us
You know I'm dealing that on a microscopic
Scale but this is the question
And so
The first thing that I would try to teach our new AI
If I had the ability is
Try to understand the concept of empathy
We need to introduce the idea of empathy
Both in an AI and us
For these things
That's
Where we're at
Caleb says in the specific case of the of the animatronic babies designing
At least we talked to his thinking was that he might have it
He holds it upside down cry once or twice but then stop
So that you don't get that
Repeat thrill
Yeah
I was wondering whether
Back in the grid space with Brian Christian and Beck on the subject
Chatbot
We found ourselves asking the very question that
Calebasse
Is it possible that
This is getting kind of grim
That maybe
Then some
In some ways tripods are good for humans yeah means there any situation where you can throw in a couple of pots and things get better
What can chatbots actually be helpful
For us and if so
How
Yeah there have been some academic studies on trying to use
Chatbots for these
Is Humane
Benevolent
That I think
Type this in
Interesting
Other narrative
I am so for example
Researchers have
Tried injecting chatbots into
Twitter
And the spot will just show up and be like
And does it just like that
You know it'll say something like they're real people behind the keyboard and you're really hurting someone's
And you know it's sort of preliminary work but there are some studies that appear to see
Suggest yunnan
Sharp decline in that users use
Hate speech
FCI of 50 trillion followers
Oh yeah it actually does depends that isn't
It does depend on the follower count
Of the bot that makes the intervention
So if you perceive this bought
To be
It also requires that you think are person so this
Is it started flirting with it with dark magic
But if you perceive them to be
Higher status on the platform
Then yourself
Then you will
Tntap sheepishly fall in line
But if the bottom
Has fewer followers than the user is trying to
Correct
That will just instigate the
The bully to believe them
Now in addition
Wow
Human Nature
Very cool thing I ever going to finish but this is like this is the
All right so I'm going to tell you one more story because as we were thinking about all this and trying to find a more optimistic place to live
We bumped into a story
From this guy
Who are you
So I'm I'm a Josh Rothman I'm a writer for the New Yorker
Run into the studio couple weeks back
Who's this
Story of yours large it takes
Place in a laboratory
In Barcelona at the lab it's in Barcelona and it's run by a couple minutes later and mavi son
Chess Vives Vives neuroscientist
They have these two VR Labs together
VR as in virtual reality
And Josh took a trip
The Barcelona
To experience some of the simulations that Navien melt
Wet
Campusship
Their lab you feel sort of like you're going to a Black Box Theatre
It's sort of like a lot of big rooms
All covered in black with curtains
There's a lot of dark spaces and explain the what's going to happen is going to put on a headset
Is there a big helmet and eventually
Peterson
The visual start
Fade in
This room
Appears you're standing in a sort of generic room the graphics look straight out of like a Windows 95
Computer game is like the loading screen of the VR
And then
That dissolves
Then it's replaced with the simulation
And when the simulation started
I was standing in front of a mirror a digital mirror in this digital world
Reflecting back at him his digital self
Is Avatar
So basically you move and your beautiful body moves with you I could see in the mirror
A reflection of myself but the person who's who
The self thought I saw a reflected
She had a body through the woman
She
So I think when people think of virtual reality they often imagine
Wanted to have like realistic experiences
NVR
But that's not what melon mommy do
They are interested in VR precisely cuz it lets you experience things you could never experience in your real body in the
Real world that body that can be completely transformed and Campbell fan contains coloring
Change shape
So it's can give you a very very
Unique
Tool to wax
Explorer in their work they'll often in Industry our world turn men and women as they did for Josh for his
His first timeout
They will
How to take a tall person and then make them a short person
In the VR
So that they can experience the world as a short person
Crane their neck up a bunch
They'll change the color of your skin NPR end
Run you through scenarios where you are having to experience the world as another race
And what's remarkable is it in all of these manipulations
Apparently you adjust to the new body
Very quickly
They've done physiological tests
Measure this
It takes almost no time at all to
Feel as if this alien body is actually yours they call this the illusion of presence
Ingleside water body
I-70
Stable entity however
By running
Experiments in virtual reality
You see that's actually it in
In one minute
Elvis stimulation
How are brain except a different body
Even if this body is
It's quite different from your own
And this flexibility that our brains seem to have
Can lead to some very
Surreal
Situations
This is really a story that brought us to ja she told us
About another VR Adventure where again he put on the headset
This world fade it up
And I was sitting in a chair
In front of a desk
In a
Really cool looking modernist house
Wooden floor sanding there is
Some glass walls and through glass walls
Field with wildflowers
Again he noticed a mirror and this time the reflection the mirror
Was of him
It was a realistic-looking Avatar of him
After checking out his digital self for a while
He turned his head back
To the room and realized it across the room
There was another desk
And behind this other desk with there was Freud
Who Freud
Sigmund Freud Sigmund Freud
Middle-aged man with a big brown beard and a beard
He had glasses
And
He was just sitting there with his hands folded in his lap
Digicert taking this all and he's looking at
Voice looking
Back at him
And then okay now and now I use the voice of a researcher in his ear coming through his VR helmet
She explained what you're going to do is
You're going to explain a problem that you're having a personal problem that you're having to Freud
Something that's bothering you in your life
And she said
Take a minute think about what you'd like to discuss
Do something immediately jump to mind ya so
You know my my mom
Had a stroke a few years ago
And she's in a nursing home
And I'm her guardian
So
She's
But because of the stroke she
Like needs 24-hour care and you can't talk
Shouldn't have any words any
So
It's a very tough
Sing for me
I thought really hard about where she
You should live at why I live here in New York
My mom
Lives in Virginia
Just as he really debated for a long time should he put her in a nursing home in New York
Where he can be closer to her or
Should he put her in a nursing home in Virginia or he would be far away she has all these friends and family members down there
So in the end I decided
You know find a place for her there where there's lots of people who can visit
So I go down
Maybe once every
Month or six weeks
Ecstasy my mom but then every weekend
You know
Someone from this
Super Friends Are Family relatives visit
Turn down there where the fuhrer. On video on the first
Decision I made
But you don't feel really happy then yeah you know I feel guilty about it
Like he was a terrible son
And he said he would especially have that feeling each week after
Her friends would visit her in the nursing home and then send him an email update saying hey this is how your mom is doing
Every time he would read one of those emails
Even if she was doing well his stomach which is
Drop this problem this emotion
Feeling guilty
Is 1
Felt for a while
So I said to Freud
I said
My mom is in a nursing home in another state
And
Friends and family visit her and they send me reports
And how she's doing and I always feel really bad
When I get these reports
And this is said in your voice if you'd blakey's that the mirror while you were talking would you be saying it
So after he said this
To Freud the world sort of
Beat It Out
Two black
And then it faded back in
And suddenly the world has shifted
NewsNow across the room
Behind the desk that you just been opposite in
He was inside the body of Freud you look down himself he's wearing white
White shirt grey suit
There's a mirror next to that desk me looks himself
I have a little beard and everything looks just like Freud but the main thing that was really surprising was that a cross I could see myself
So this is the Avatar of me now
And I
Washed myself
Say what I just said so
Oh well so it plays it back
Exactly
Dell recording is now replate
Movements and also the voice
And they see themselves
As they talked about their problem
The first I can see my I'm sitting in the chair and sort of uncomfortable
I'm moving around
I take my hands and
Put them in my lap and fold them together and I take
Come apart
I can watch myself be nervous
And then I saw
Then I saw myself say what I just said my mom is in a nursing
Another state
Friends and family visit
Send me reports
In my voice
I'm going to moving the way I move in
It was just like me watching myself
And I guess the best way
I can describe that
Was
It was moving
What movie
Emotionally emotionally
I felt
But I don't know if this is going to make any sense but
You know how there's a point in your life where you realize that your parents are just people
Yeah it was kind of like that
Is upset with me
Did you feel closer to that guy or or I felt bad
He felt bad for him
Sorry
Yeah I did I fry my my feelings went out
Up to this other person
Who is me
As he's having this empathetic reaction as Freud
Looking back at himself
The researchers voice again appears in his ear
If advice
From the perspective of Sigmund Freud
Advice of Hardee's
Problem could be solved how you could deal with it essentially respond to your patient
I don't know what to say so I said
Why do you think you feel bad
What's a good pretty
Soon as he ask that
He's back
In his body is virtual body staring back at virtual Freud and he sees a playback of Freud asking him that question I watched
Freud stages
This to me why do you think you feel bad
Except that when Freud talks they had some
Thing in the program that made
His voice
Extra deep
Mikasa
Voice distortion
How deep are boys his voice didn't sound like my voice how did you respond as he has now you
I said I feel bad
Because
It doesn't seem right that I'm
Looking for a way
Once again
He switches bodies now he's in Freud again staring back
I'm self and I watched myself say this
I feel bad
And then is Freud I said well why
Why are you far away then
Shoot back into his own body
Protecting from across the room why are you far away though
I said well because
If my mom lived in New York I'd be the only person here but
If she's down
And where she lives that there's other people to visit her
That confronts potty
And I said so it sounds like there's there's a reason
Why I'm
Why you live where you live
I'm so if you know that won't hit why do you why do you still feel bad
Switch is back to himself if you know they're white
I said something like
You're right
Back at the front
And then it's Friday I said you know it sounds like the
The thing that's making you unhappy which is
Making you feel bad we're just getting used
Reports from these people is actually the whole reason why you
Decided
To live and he's going to have to keep your mom where she is
Like there's a a loop
Right it's like these these reports I get for my mom's
Friends make me feel bad but the whole reason why
I
Decided to leave her in this place in Virginia is specifically so that there are friends
Who can visit her
This is classic idea in psychology called the refrain which is where
Giant take a problem and reframe that problem into its solution
He says in that moment he kind of did that
It is very simple Epiphany that
His guilt
Was actually connected to something good
I never had that thought before
He chose to keep his mom in Virginia so that her friends would visit her more in
Each time her friends visited he felt bad
That meant they were visiting
To the bad feeling ineffective
Was feeling it so much
Was itself kind of evidence for the fact that he had made
If not the right decision
At least a decision that made sense
Experience I had talking to myself as Freud was was nothing like the experience I had
In my own head
Turning this issue over and over
Buy sweet tea
Back and forth
Hey by swapping bodies
Somehow you can give advice
I am
American Best
When I was back in my own body and Freud set it to me either
Just like
I just felt like gum
Wow
It's so good point
When your next 30 what the hell is going on here why am I able in this
Utterly fictive situation
Split myself in two and heal myself while I put the headset off
And I sat there for a little while while the
Researchers
Look at me
Trying to make sense of it and I think what
What I keep coming back to is the
Seeing yourself just as a person
Not as you
Not with all the complexities and
Stuff
That is in you
Yourself
Experience of being yourself
And this might be the real key thing like when you are in your body
Would you pretty much always are
You have all of these thoughts and feelings which are at
Attached
To that body
When you go home for Thanksgiving and you walk into your parents kitchen and suddenly you just
Kind of feel
Like you're a teenager again
I call those same thought patterns from your youth
Kind of kick back into gear
Because the context
That kitchen
Is power
And you your body
Is that writ large but if you can jump out of it go into a new one
Suddenly all those constraints
Penelec contact
Is gone
When I'm in body does
Freud
Not only do I look different
This is my body
But I feel different
And I have different types of thoughts
And I see
People differently
Josh says what he saw
What he was Freud looking back at himself
Was just a guy who needed help
When someone comes to you and ask for help
Your feelings are not
They're just
Tenderness
Kindness
Your instinct is to
Help them
He says he's able to bring that very simple way of being
Back to himself
Did it did it make a difference
Did you walk out of that with with a different
Feeling about yourself
Did I think
I've had a feeling of
I think it revised my
Feeling about
Who I was
I think it made me feel a little more
I don't even have a word for it
A little more human
Joshua writer the New Yorker his story first appeared there
And we told it to that live audience at the Greene space
So Brian this is
You can get the last word
Tell me this is really interesting because the history of
Chatbots
Begins
With a chatbot program written in the 60
Please find MIT
Professor
Joseph weizenbaum
The program is called Eliza
It was designed to mimic
This non-directive rogerian therapist
Where you would say I'm feeling
I'm sad it would just
Throw it back to you as a
The kind of mad lib
I'm sorry to hear your sad why are you sad
And why isn't bomb was
Is famously horrified when he walked in on his
Secretary just like
Spilling her life
Innermost thoughts
In feelings to this program that she had seen him right
You know there's no there's no mystery there
But he came away from that
Experience feeling
Call that the
The degree to which p
People will sword
Project
Human intention on to
Just technology
And
His reaction was to
Pull the plug on his own research project
And for the rest of his life
He became one of the leading critic
Against chatbot
Technology
Stay in Jenner
And I think it's really powerful to Jax
Suppose that a
The story
Just shared
Which tells us that there's there's more
There's more to the picture than that
That there are ways
To use this
Technology
In a way that doesn't
Insertive distance us
But in a way that
Enables us to
To be more
Wonderful weather
Why don't we just leave it
Pleasantly
Gypsum thanks to give way but if particular
Particular thanks to give to the person who made this whole
Cybersphere around us but that's Lauren kunze
Lawrence I like that's Lauren thank you to Pandora box
Platform the powers of conversational AI software for hundreds of thousands of global
Brand developers learn more about their Enterprise operating services at Pandora box
Dot-com there's also the chance bone for Designing the Robert a robot artwork for tonight
And of course to Brian Christian for coming here to talk
M2u
This episode was recorded and produced by Simon Adler and our lives
Event was produced with machine-like efficiency
By Simon Adler and Suzie lechtenberg you don't have to say n word
Everytime You Look At Me I can see it all in her eyes all right or alright
How do you make me think about you all the time
I can almost hear your voice
Even though you're far away I can feel you
Right by my side I can read your mind I can read your mind
I can read your mind I can read your mind
You were mine
By the way thanks to Dylan Keith Alex overington and Dylan green for regional music
When you hold me now I can see you the truth all the secrets of the heart
You can't hide them anymore I can feel the power and you
I can read your mind I can read your mind I can read your mind
To keep our love alive you must be willing to believe in love
I can see it in your eyes now our love will never die
I can read your mind
Hi this is Brian Christian Radiolab was created by Jedi mourad and is produced by Thorne Mueller
Is our director of sound design Maria Matassa are Federal Officer managing director or staff includes Simon.
Maggie bartolomeo wrestler Rachel Cusick David Cavell Bethel have Tracy huh
Matt kielty Robert krulwich any McEwen Petit Nassar Melissa abdominal area and whack
Pat Walker in Molly Webster could help from Amanda aronchick Shima Orla Kiely andreev
Fact Checker Michelle Harris and this message