Are you awake
Northern listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
Okay ready 3-2-1 hey time Jedi been wrought iron rubber College this is Radiolab
And this is part two of our attempt to answer some listener questions that are piled up over the years
Gathering digital dust in our inbox
Come from kind of close to home
Starting us off this round is a question ask her
Who has developed
Quite a reputation here at Radiolab
Scott little
I'm just a normal dude man Scott spoke to our producer a lot of Nasser
Send us a lot of questions that got her attention they don't they don't stop I can't slow this brand on it
I truly do not even remember like writing why is the moon
We seriously not translated any animal language is yet is there a reason coconuts look a lot like she pansy
He had just a coincidence
Zeroed in on one of Scott's questions that at first seemed kind of simple but it got really
Ibig
When a space shuttle goes into space
How do they make sure it doesn't hit any satellite
Is it chest radar
Is there some kind of complicated cyst in the tracks all of them in and since we talked it's kind of looking at the bow
About that she know about like how many satellites are Acts
The up there
What are we even calling space junkins
And has this affected anything
Yeah
You know it's just like it it goes from like kind of informational to like
Almost like this sort of Doom and Gloom real fast like
There's so much junk up there like it's going to be impossible to leave the Earth's atmosphere pretty soon
And I don't know I just it just kind of
I'll be curious to see what what
Who's who's in charge of all this that's what I want to know
Okay is everybody there
Willing to talk to you about space surveillance
Yes I'm here
So I couldn't actually find anyone who is literally in charge of space
But I did find what I think is pretty much the next best thing on the commander of the 18th space control
I think your title has got to be the coolest title of anyone I've ever interviewed
The commander of the 18th space control Squadron
Amazing
Okay so so let's start from the top when the space shuttle goes in the space how do they make sure it doesn't hit any satellites
We keep track of wood called the space catalog of all the man-made stuff
Surrounding Us in outer space
A little over 23,000 objects whenever there's a launch anything mad or unmanned
We'll track it again
Disgusting things in catalog and will make sure that it doesn't hit anything on the way out
Up there and then
If there is a chance of an actual Collision they send out an alert
The notifications we create are called conjunction data messages
Send several thousand of those everyday
Thousands we have a more refined what we call emergency criteria
Between 6 and 10 of those per day
What
That's a good that's a lot but when you consider retracting 23,000 objects
But on top of those 23000 object
It turns out there's there's even more stuff out there
But she says it's basically just
Too small to be able to track
We think that they're probably more like a half a million close to half-a-million on
What's you have like almost none of them
It sounds like that but just remember that some of those
Frost 500,000 objects are very very tiny pieces of debris
Yeah what are we talkin about
But the paint so there's no way you can track like
Half a million flexor pain that feels like
Stop feels like impossible
Metal window
That was hit by a flock of pain
And the kind of damage that it can do moving and tell me what kind of
Speed what what
Yeah what would I see if I saw that picture
Several layers of the shuttle window and they determined that it was from a Fleck of paint
I'm just you know what tiny flag
So you got almost half a million pieces of the
Itty bitty space junk
Keeping our fingers crossed
And
Monitoring the situation
I'm so we can react to it if something happened
Okay
What's up when I when I called this listener he's like
She's a little bit
Paranoid
I think it's called the
The Kessler
Syndrome that what it is
The castle
That's what it is
NASA scientist got this thing named after him
Bernese like we might get to a point where we have so much stuff in space
That like
Something will collide with
Wait like two satellites will collide and that Collision will cause so much debris but it will basically be like this
Giant thing we're just like things are just exploding around the earth for like years and years and years.
Some sort of locust plague
Space Jam
Swarmed with a locust plague of space junk
And that it'll be impossible to leave the Earth's atmosphere anytime soon
What would you say to Scott
This is Steve
We have
We have a job to
Attractive object
A question like that
Is this kind of out of our realm of responsibility
And just let me ask another question then tell me
If you can answer it that's fine too
Which isn't he also brought up something called the keslow effect
Do you know about that or have you heard of that before
Which is which is the idea that
There's a possibility that two satellites will collide and then milk
Create debris and an idol
Make a domino effect and cause all kinds of other
Collisions and then it'll be
Ahold giant debris field
I'm sure we've heard of it the Kepler effect
Okcastle are sorry about that
And is that something you worry about or no
Hello
Hello hello
I guess it is a concern
Her butt
The members of the Squadron do such a great job tracking everything that's up there that we would hope that that wouldn't happen
I thought nothing nothing but the answer I was hoping for started this whole thing
Thinking that
Scott Speer was like kind of crazy but then after that conversation I started
Yeah researching it for real and I
Online I found this video of Kessler himself there was a general attitude
The space was a big sky that you can put anything in it that you wanted and not fill it up to the problem that you quickly running
He basically says exactly the way we operate in space all this results in exponentially
Free until all objects are reduced to a cloud of orbiting fragments that are capable of destroying any
Spacecraft the 10th operate anywhere within that cloud
Which would mean no satellites
The weather satellites no GPS satellites and then
In the future if things go really badly
You know we just be
Stuck here
Forever
Andeavor
On Earth
Our next question comes from the sky in Brooklyn and he is
That would be fine
5 years old
And I interviewed him
Dad are going to go in my kitchen
Who r u t g
And I'm your son
Okay tell me your question
The question is
What's Earth color
Why is the earth called Earth
I don't know why
Give any guesses
Just came up with the name
The Earth came up with its own name
I think
Should I find out and then tell you
Yes
My first stop was a guy named Peter Peter Barry
Isotope geochemistry I work at the
The University of Oxford
My research
Am I right that you have some kind of loose affiliation with NASA is that is that not right
In a sense that I mean I do a little bit of
Planetary work I've worked
Lunar samples
In the past but you work on lunar samples
Yes I've actually done some
Isotope work on
It's actually one of the few people on the planet who
Held the Moon
In his hand
So here's my question I think it's pretty simple but maybe there's a
The story there I don't know
Question comes from
Tej via me his dad
Why is the earth called the Earth
Well that's that's a really in
Question the Earth is actually so this is
And it's in
In Old Saxon
Derive from
English dramatic
Roots in German
Earth is sad
Erda
I believe the guy die
German
And of course all these
All these words are originally drive from
A mother language
An endo your
Working mother length
What it means in German and what it means and all those old languages
Actually just means
Soil or
Ground
All the other
Planets all visible
Have these really
Awesome name
They're all named after Roman god
I mean you have
Mercury
The move really quickly around the Sun
So it got its name from the Roman messenger god then you have
Venus
Does this Bright Beautiful or blowing in the sky
So we named it after the goddess of love
Of course Mars
Which was fiery and red
And so we named after the God of War
Earth is the only
Planet which is it named after
A Roman god
He clearly has
This much different
Etymology
Peter ultimately referred me to another guy.
Classify the game please
I speak and yeah this is Gabriel Berry
To the price of indo-europeans probably were sure
Proto proto-indo-european
Yes so it's so basically that what Gabriel Berry told me is that you could
You could trace all this whole thing the word or back to this
Group of people who lived in a day
This is like way before JC way before
For the Greeks or the Romans
The proto-indo-european
Lived in
Especially what's now Eastern Europe
Cities already people from
Steps
Russia
Don't know a lot about them
We know they moved around a lot
People couldn't for whatever reason settle down at some point maybe about
5000 years ago
From the steppes
Eastern Europe
Russia
Swept into Europe
It seems I drive
Chariot
Imma came on horseback
Make huge wave unsettled away from
Button down too
Northern India
Imagine This
This wave of people on Horseback spreading
All over Europe in an India and
Speaking this language they would ultimately Branch out into English and German and French and Hindi and Portuguese and
400 some odd language
Spread across Europe
Crosstown
India
Underground
Daughter's day started to slow down
Settle down
And that's when they start spending a lot of time
Looking down at the dirt
We have lots of words for founding
Plow
Or as in the world that would become Earth
Evidence that early point adjustment dirt
And presumably adjustment like
Vistaril
But this specific
Little
Piece of dirt
Right here
Then I'm plowing
It's somewhere along the way
That word
Herta
Became the word for Alder
The whole ball of dirt
Basically the word that starts Benji
It comes
Same word
Beautiful then
And also
Quite often
We have no idea when that
Switch
Happened
Exactly
May we know within a
P2000
Whenever it was
That strikes me as a pretty important moment for us people
Can I ask some questions
When did you discover the Earth was a planet
Don't know really what did you discover do you remember when you when you learned
If the Earth was a ball
When
Nice to you don't remember to you
Baidu
Now you don't
Yes I do
Little nest
Little
Coordinate age
That moment for him happened to daycare
This place called little Nest Brooklyn
Vanessa
It was a day when his teacher Vanessa
Had them do this little
Project
She said we were going to make up
Our own
Pushing her
On what
What is that mean
That means
And make
Two eyes
Awesome legs and tomorrow
IC
They're basically making this Earth pop
And he says after they did that
You were sitting on the rug
That way you have your best ideas you sitting on this little rainbow colored rug that they have hold Nazareth puppet
I was thinking
I was singing of the Earth
Lights Round
Smooth
Round
And it's a
Cipriani
By the time we get from the Proto Indo Europeans to the ancient Greeks and Romans
Couple thousand years
You begin to see the concept of Earth rising up
It goes from a simple word that means dirt or soil
To Mother Earth
The goddess
So it went in the opposite direction of the other planets
It started as lowly dirty thing beneath our feet and then became divine
When I told Sage this answer he was disappointed
You sexy hoping that the Earth was named
Buy an alien
Daddy night-night another question
Sun-maid
How is the sun made
Give me like how how did the Sun
Become the son and that's another good question
Do you ever look at someone and wonder what is going on inside their head
What does he know that I mean
BFFs best friends forever what is BFF best friends
Are you ready
Does Dunkin Donuts have it maybe no no no like you like here in America they have people coming in that I think somebody comes with
To the truck what do you do with it what you have done it before how did I do that I don't even understand
Tell Simon
Door in here
Next Step black please
568b
Thank you thank you the Adler family
As a user Simon Tyler and his dad
So a couple weeks back
I'm just heading out of town now
I asked my old man my dad to record himself going on a drive
All good road trips deserve, coffee and being approved
Individual but I am I decided that a drive-through at McDonald's would be the appropriate
He and my mom live in Northwestern Wisconsin in a small Lil
Little city town called auclair
Going to drive
Country Roads
In specifically what would I ask him to do was to go drive on the county highways just outside of town
Passing
Farm field areas there are very few cars on the road that I'm on
The reason I asked him to do this was because for as long as I can remember
He's had this nagging
Question
A question that he bombard me with every time I'm home off times when were talking
On the phone he'll bring it up by 9
Can you hear me yeah that's the dinner table over email I mean I've heard about this at least
600 *
What does Mom think about all this I've never asked her
She just rolls her eyes
Yeah
Yeah so what happened
So do you want me to tell you why why I'm recording or do you want me to I knew we would get
So you can tell me now I thought maybe it was going to be like that I had
Figure out
Let me let me just prompt you with this and see it see how well you take the bait here
Do you know the question I'm talking about and could you just
Tell me what that question is
That
Question is
Well let me back up an example is this
A person will be riding a road bike
Down a lonely Country Road
Two other people
Will be walking their dog on the side of
10 days
Semi-trailer truck
Will then be coming down that road
Okay so we've got three different actors here
And nobody else for miles and miles and
And there is not at you having
The biker hasn't seen another car
Or pedestrian
4 miles on this road
But what will happen is
All
Three of those actors will come together
At the exact same point in the exact same time
Creating a dangerous situation first of all
But then it's just
And then it diffuses
And you could sit on that stretch of road for six more years
Cannot find that app
And the key thing here my dad says is
Kia Tim Adler
When is this sort of thing
Give me a lot all the time
I would say it happens
Once every two weeks
Upcoming we have the possibility of an event
On the day I sent him to record himself
After 10 or 15 minutes of not seeing a single other car on the road
Cam'ron this band there's a manure wagon
Being driven by a tractor
Right down the road and yes
We are here at all happens
The manure wagon is going down the road
Attractor has just pulled out on the road and now I'm passing by
And all three happened at the event
Same place it just happened
What is your
Question then is it why does that happen or is it a question is
Why
Does this happen to me
Does it seem to happen to others as well
Okay
Take it to the bottom of this we called her man who he thought might just have been
I'm by Professor MSU Professor David Spiegel
Does that mean you've been knighted
Yeah yeah yeah
You're a knight you're the you're the first night I've ever spoken to
Time to stop
The probability of me talking to her
Professor sir David is a statistician repartido
When I ran my old man questioned by his response
People contact me and they get very anxious
Because they feel it something's going on in their lives but making things happen all the time they're getting signs from the environment
Random
Synchronous
That was the time that call Young invented
For this. It isn't entirely
Vine 2
Through space and time
Carl Gustav you know the famed psychoanalyst of the 20th century
Dreams or visions of the future
Behind night shut that we didn't
County recognized
But did Drive these things to have
Something beyond the normal rules of
Physics and kites rationality
So he really believes
Dental for
I think he just
Wasn't very good statistician
Because
Sir David says when you start to look at the events in our lives in terms of their probability every single event.
Unbelievably unlikely and unpredictable
Soak the crucial thing that measures it for the surprising
Is the unlikeness of it occurring
At some point over a reasonable period
And just I don't know I'm trying to make this as concrete as possible so
Good luck so if you're driving down the street
Yeah that has I don't know
3 cars
10 MI
NJ bikers / 10 MI
Yeah yeah likely is it that over the course of those 10 miles you're going to intersect at the way that he does
The likelihood of that happening any
Particular 10 miles ready to take Chlorella
Is very loud
It's a surprising event
But if your father drives a lot
The likelihood of it happening over
I didn't make a week
2 weeks
Suleiman
Is very high
David says think of it this way
Let's say my dad would consider one of these intersections to be a meaningful coincidence
Synchronous event
If a semi truck in a biker pass him
Within five seconds of each other
Now
If in 1 hour of driving my dad sees say
15 cars
5 biker
The map tells you that the likelihood of one of each or both
The car in the bike passing him in the same 5 Second window
Is about 1 in 7,000
But
Think of how many of those 5 Second Windows there are in any given week or month
In fact think of each of these 5 Second Windows as like
One spin of a roulette wheel
Giant roulette wheel with
7000 different numbers that you could bet the ball would land. But
This is Keith
When my dad's driving it's not like he only gets one spin of the wheel for one chance to see
See one of these synchronous events
Instead it's like every 5 seconds he gets to try again
Given that he drives like 3 hours a week
When you do the math
What you end up with is a 31% chance
A-Team experiencing Mis in any given week
Meaning if he's looking for it
He should definitely expect to see one of these
At least once a
So you have to
Not look at just the Avenger not just
The particular thing your father exist
You have to think all the time
For those things because it didn't
You know you got to think of all the stuff you're not singing
How are you
Pretty good fish
Quite the fish if you'd like its Third cast
Call my dad back
To break the news to
All right you want the answer
Yes
So
We can explain it to him from the history of Yuan to the fact that he's really just got to pay attention to all the times these coincidences
Aren't happening
Right and when you look at it from that angle it's
Statistically to be expected
There
I understand
It's a little hard to swallow
I'm a Little More Union than most
It it does make sense
From a statistical analysis
But why does it
Happening to me
So these things do happen to some people
Because your friend so sick right now. It doesn't happen to people who are very sensitive
Underwear and then notice their environment they're pretty mindful people that happens to
I was just what I'm saying is this is a real admirable
Your characteristics
Well there's no question this makes my day when I've heard that I've been
Raised by a knight
Elias highness that someday we should go out for a cup of tea
Not to bring it down though
He he told his praise on you I would love to meet you I'm sure he's wonderful but I would
I think I would say that
He's not very special
You didn't really have
Tell me that
Sorry sorry
Now that's okay that I'm going to just listen to the first time
Alright okay enjoy the rest of the day of the week thanks I love you and I'll talk to you
Tell Mama give her a call and hopefully tomorrow morning
I love you too
NPR news and classical
89.3
Green Bay
I want to ask you one question
I just relax
We're not in Kansas anymore
Where do I go
You know where you are
Where am I
Hi this is Jacob calling
Tufts University in Medford Mass
Radiolab
Supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan
Enhancing public understanding
Science and technology in the mall
More information about Sloan
Www.
Sloan.
I listen to Radiolab so much that I actually
Part memorized
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
And I request
For those of you who
Who spend a lot of time with kids parents
Aunts and uncles
Teachers looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments
Brilliant
Basically I want to hear about this
When a kid you know did something
It just means you lean back and say
How do they do that
Maybe it was the moment that I
A kid you've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of their musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class
Are ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the
Epic moments where
A kid does something super smart
It doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story
Go to radiolab.org
Flash brilliance
Mrecorder short
Audio message
And that's radiolab.org
Flash Brewing
Thank you so much
Jad Robert Radiolab we are back
With more questions okay so mixed up Yeah by name is Evan Becker we're going to go to Boston with Eva
Becker and here is his question
Boston-area still in box
In today
Kind of relevant today
The question is is something of a snowboard
Snowboarding for 20 plus years or so
Friends and I OST
Usually go up
Uibe
New Hampshire Vermont in New England area
Yeah and you know a mini years back on one of these group trips they took
And I
Recently opened a
Don't you mean course
And by the way that tiny
That's a producer Tracy hunt
And then another friend jumped in and said I bet you I can get that up to like a hundred miles an hour easily from the top of the mountain
No way
You couldn't even do that in purpose
Addition
And from this small little
Disagreement
From there and I was in 2004
Going on for more than a decade and over these 10 years going back and forth in the back and forth on this question
Everything is Friends gradually focused in on the rules
What's up
An event
They came on this very specific wording
So the question is
In perfect condition
Within the Earth's atmosphere and I was in the back
Can you read
100 miles per hour going down a mountain
I'm
And everyday
Like an inner tube
It's the same thing that you get if you went to a local hardware store
Nothing fancy nothing
Andover the engineer
And still to this day some of Evans friends are like yeah we can break a hundred miles an hour we can
It happened he says no
Cannot do that
But I think it can happen
I think you can happen
That is Destin Sandlin host
Of an extremely popular YouTube channel called
Important smartereveryday cuz he is very smart on his channel but Destiny does
Is he proposes
So you probably observed that cats
Almost always land on their feet
Questions
Today's question
Is why
Questions a lot like Evans Wiki then proceeds to answer
GGG
I think that's in your also an actual rocket scientist
I've only I've only said that one time my mom corrected me very quickly she's what
They know
I'm what's called a flight test engineer so we test missiles and helicopters and stuff like that
How do you say one thing before we start
I feel like before we jump to the answering part of this
Conversate
I want to appreciate what was the question
I'm wondering is there some like physical
Are there some physical reasons why a hundred would be really hard to do
In an inner tube down a hill
So this is what I thought about when I first heard the quest
So if you think about going down a hill
There's two things that are slowing you down
The first one is the friction with the snow
In the second one is the era's
Which progestin all boils down to something to eat
Drag
1/2 times the density of the air coefficient of drag
So this started as a really simple question in my mind
NSI started
Gaming out how to
How to do this without killing the person the more I thought about it the more I realized it can get very very calm
Yeah I can I can show you all those equations
But I can't work them out on the back of neck
Mostly because
Math is hard
Still he did tell us that he could he was pretty confident that he could get this
Tube to go down more than a hundred miles an hour.
Yes I'm saying that it can happen
Are we sure that somebody hasn't done this
And posted like their GoPro video on YouTube
Well I guinness world record
Oh gravity
Powered snow
Well what is it what what's the what's the world record
Okay so at this moment Destin's wife Tara Sandlin
She's in the studio cuz she's with him on vacation in New York and she's been looking at her iPhone
Epi Guinness World Records website
Gravity powered snow sled
134 km per hour
3.5 under
Remedy power questioning everything about what I believe
A sled is meant for velocity of two business values faster
Omani miles an hour
Would you slow here so so here's the deal
I'm different than most people I I'm not going to die in this Foxhole
It's clear that I'm wrong
I would go with this this is what I would do
The real thing that the tube
Causes of problem in my mind is
All the friction on the
On the mountain
Right so I mean
Within the balance of the question because he
He went to all these Great Links to Define what we could do and what we couldn't
He did not
Tell us what slope the mountain had to be on
And so what we're going to do is work and go to the worst possible Mountain imaginable witches
Straight down
A cliff basically
Okay are we all on the party line
And so with the help of producer Tracy
Evan
And in Destin
Can you hear me
Do you want to Devin the questionnaire to hear what how death is going to work.
This thing out good we're all together
To break the ice with answers are
Yeah so this is ultimately a question about terminal velocity
Rewrite
In theory
If we were to
Go straight down
Like
Out of an airplane
We would go as fast as we can
Can ever go because the only thing contributing to the
The terminal blocks
See that point
Would be dry
No friction
I don't know you what would you do
Except the answer if I'm able to go a hundred miles per hour straight down out of an airplane
For example
Would you say that it is pause
Maybe you even if our
Yeah even if our Hill is only
1 degree
Off of in a straight down towards the Earth that still counts as a
Alright
Yeah I guess so
Yeah as long as it's going downhill in the Earth
Yeah
Yeah I want to call I got a buddy named Paul here in Alabama he owns a place called
Skydive Alabama
I go to church within the same all the time
And I think he became so distant like I don't know like
Seaway call him from your phone or something is that what you
What you think going to try to do
So
Paul reset Her Go
What's up man are you ready for me to merge you
Alright Paul you there
Hi Paul how's it going and we have Evan who had those who had this crazy question about snow tubing
Okay
When's the whole inner tube thing in a toaster
Suspend Pollak we want to know if you could jump out of a plane go straight
Could you break a hundred miles per hour barrier
Is that safe can you do a test like that
Yeah it is totally possible I've done it
What weight
You done it with an inner tube
Absolutely.
Closest two different occasions he in a bunch of friend jumped out of an airplane
Carrying an inflatable flotation device in one hand
I watch a little computer to track their speed on the other side it how fast did you go
In both cases it was over a hundred
Really
The same it's as if it's as if he has a virtual Mountain
He jumped off the question specifically said on the mountain that these guys have been arguing about this for a decade
We're going to come back to them and be like noon or just drop out of an airplane
True or false and that's where you go to law school you and stuff like that what did you read the question I am now
I hereby recusing myself from this whole affair
Do we have we have we have ceased
You truly in good faith answer the question and furthermore we get the guy on the phone
Phone and we Hoodwink him into accepting a renegotiated contract.
I am I would not be a party to this
Hangzhou
Tell us where we're going next eat so the next one is
From our producer Annie McEwen hello
Any
Dad
So what are we going to be talking about to question you bring us
Okay so this one is a little bit different
Because it didn't come in from a question came in the form of a very tantalizing email
From a fellow named iron Hendricks
Iron Henry
From Amsterdam high iron
Yes it's me and he's basically said ham iron I'm an artist and it just want you already left to know that me and my friend
We are building a building and island of fat
And Island
Yeah I know a couple of all the things to build an island out of wife at
I'm just fascinated by it I just like thinking about it that made you start
Looking at fat in a curious way what was the moment
A friend of mine and Mike Thompson and we are in a train
Going to Amsterdam
Are you feeling fat or what what what
We're weird guys
Great joke about things like this like the chips
Ray Wise or something and then we started talking about how in the English newspapers that has been this news
Stories about pepper
Stop birds that are under the ground in the sewers of London just like wreaking havoc
And there was one
It's actually in the Oxford dictionary since 2015 is sick an actual word
How fat burgundy Iceberg look like
Well I mean like a sort of Imagine Iceberg I guess but this one's floating on the water
In the tunnels Underground in London
And is made entirely of
That and a little while ago Hernandez friend Michael actually got to go down into the store to check out these fatbergs
And it was an amazing experience through it with these waiter hip waders on
Pushing bits and pieces of fat side
Drains for the trampoline
Gooey stuff inside of the sewer
Where is you have is that a picture of it of a fatberg
Oh my god wow yeah so it's so it's like this like clumpy lumpy Mass
Girbaud jeans
Fat stuff
Gray and brown and it's filled with all the sewer stuff when I'm sleeping
Fungus grows on it completely block
The Old Brick tunnel
Underground so this is like this is like based on the things people have eaten there so much fat in people's dies here and such in the sewer
People throwing fat away like taking bacon grease thrown down the sink cooking fat down the sink
Yeah and in September of this year in London they found a fatberg in the sewers that weighed as much as 11 double decker bus
That's how much fat
Shut up in one place oh my God
Engine is at the Thames water
The Civil War Oregon
When's the giant fat blob plugging London
Describing the news
Spectacle lake monster monster
But I mean I felt like
Maybe fat
Is it a monster
Maybe it's just like
This this giant thing in the world that's
It's trying to express itself
Young States
Appreciation
I make up 20% of your body that
He wasn't he's celebrating fat and so he said that
If as an artist you're trying to explore water you don't just drink it out of a glass
Rock Your Body
Appreciate
What's that experience it in all these different ways
Check engine
We just want to have this
And is that where he came up with the majestical idea of building a fat Island
Citibank
Spot off The Wharf in Amsterdam and right there in the ocean water
He's building this little
Floating blob of fat waste materials
Sometimes you're just buying it
Right now it's like 15 feet across and it's just like they're hanging out
Alive movie
Always changing
We give ourselves
Maybe another half year or a year and then it should be finished interview
Haha actually how big do you hoped
To get it can you think of
At like it's a big as a truck
Or a blue whale over
Oh my God that would be amazing just of course my dreams are like the my dream is that I won't be able to
The end of it
But that's not really realistic I suppose I mean
The size of two or three trucks would be amazing already and then you have a real thing I mean it's probably be able to stand on it
It's something I would like to be able
It'll be pretty good then. Then you can really sexy college at Island summer
Definitely
Yeah I know it's strange but
But I know that I love it
I know the time when I'm there I I really love that little
Thing that is there in the water
If we were that uses as part of the show I need you to give me some kind of
Question that I can try and answer about that and it sounds like you are are doing a lot of questioning
I would really like to know when it was like
I'm very very very curious about
The relation
Okay or even when did set start because we know when certain species of animals started
More or less when the universe was created right
When was the first set
Okay
This is something that I would love to know
When was the
The first five
Fat
It turns out that the
Very very first
Version of fat
Has been around for
Pretty long time
Before Big Bang
The actor star form in exploded then you can start forming
Okay so this is
Is aqueous geochemist
Tom McCollum in my pajamas
Teamweek
I told Tom told me that the earliest earliest version of fat
Was a harbin
Oxygen compound
Arias Arias
Hydrogen carbonate
So first
Eat Hydra
And hydrogen comes along with the big bang
So we get there really early
Then we have to wait for
Start a forum starting at Old assorted Diana
Explode
And then you get carbon and
And that carbon and oxygen along with the hydrogen is now a certainty
Swirling around in this Interstellar space
Dust stuff
And when those three things
Come together
They start to make these
These shapes
So you have like a chain of carbons linked together
And each one of those carbon has equal height
James Bond
Carbon hydrogen chain
And then at one end is the what's call the carboxyl group
Carbon hydrogen and oxygen
Yeah so I like to think of it kind of like a flower
The stem of the flower is hydrogen carbon
The Petals of the flower contains ox
As well as carbon and hydrogen
And there's fat
And it's little
Flower likes
Long before the earth existed
Floating around in space
Savannah Sun and the Moon and the Earth
In the planet
Indy car source
And on the surface of the Earth
After it's cooled
You got fatty acid
Now we don't know exactly how they got there whether they formed on the Earth itself or came from like
Meteorite smacking in the Earth
But the important thing is that fatty acids are there
And there's also a lot of water
Water is important because
That's the thing about these little fatty acids is that never a hydrophobic into the molecule
So hydrophobic means
Scared of water
It is a first quarter
So are fatty acid flowers the oxygen end the the flower end
And so if there's water dispenser like and so all these flowers form
Desi can imagine it like a bouquet that is so full that it is a
Sphere
Show all the flowers on the outside cuz they'll of water and all the stems on the inside they're hiding from the water
The all the fat flowers
Join together
Because it allows the
Water heating parts
The Hyatt
And the water and loving parts
Beyond the surface
But this is all like longpre life
This is life has no idea what it is yet
Life hasn't even thought about
Coming on the scene
But there is a theory
That is one of many theories out there
But there's an idea that when these little fat flower bubbles for Minnesota
Primordial sea
They're kind of taking a little hair pulled the fluid
Rounding them inside with
Whatever your fluid
Going to get trapped inside there
So on the inside they've got
Some things
Some visitors
And the theory goes that maybe one of the things around in the sea that end up getting pulled inside one of those fat bubble
With a little floaty bits of genetic material
Like it with a little bit of RNA
And then
For the first
Time ever
Instead of random bits of RNA floating around in a CPC
You have
A cell
For the first time you have an inside
You have
A you separate from
The soup around you
So
The Fat Ball
Bandirue threesome from outer space and Levy landing gear and maybe Hood cool
The first container that made life possible
That's right
I don't think there is any way to really have anything like we call a living being without having
A membrane
Separated from this round
That is really important
Propounding
What is
Is without father would be no us there we beheld we we are we are we are built in houses effect
So that means when you get your soap bar out of the shower you should give it some respect
Is so fat yeah I think so
Traditional sopes
You don't know everything.
But I think I'm actually excited for I'm to hear this because I feel like
I mean what can convey all the way that the beginning of Life
Can hear me
I wonder what he'll say
So I called on again
And this time
Just had a conference
I have to go to this conference
I didn't know what was coach Webb because
Colts coach
But you're everything is covered in fat
Taking over my life and I just have to deal with it
Anyway
So I wanted to tell you what my sign just told me about
The earliest
Spermicide
Can I tell you okay
Think of a way to put this succinctly
I told them everything I learn
Barrier between us
And the rest of the
So that makes it makes
Yeah
Yeah and it could be that these Lee be like early early fatty acids
Are the sting
That make life as we know it
Possible
Exodus
I suspected it
Why
Yes
How'd it go
Intuition I guess
It's beautiful
This is how it's supposed to be this is what I've always dreamt of
Pittsburgh stocks
Generate
Jessamine Lovelace
Nice that's when I tell you that I don't know that's right
This is what
This is why I live
A lot of people to think for this these two episodes this is actually a real group effort but one particular props
Stupid Easter Tracy hunt in that kill t-shirt
Spearheading the whole thing to Bethel and to Bethel hopday for a huge production assist
It should you have a question
It's burning in your brain
We know exactly at Radiolab wnyc.org
I'd like to get them for you
He does particularly like it when you stand on the sidewalk just outside his window sick
I told because I'm on the fifth floor you have
Have to be very tall
Or in a tree
Okay we say goodbye I'm I'm chat album thank you for listening and
Requesting
Yes
Questing
Dirty question
What is this mean your ass I've been wondering all day too. Let's get to our question
What do they do that
I want to be
What's the question
Why
To play the message press 2
Wisconsin Radiolab was created by Jack
And is produced by Soren wheeler
Dylan Keith is our director of sound design Maliah Mathis our Padilla is our managing director
Simon Adler backup Loeffler
Rachel puzic
David Gable
Bethel hop
Tracy hunt
Matt kielty
Robert Horowitz
Annie McEwen Latif Nasser
Melissa O'Donnell
Aryan whack
Pat Walters and Molly Webster
With help from
Amanda aronchick
Emma movie
David Fox
Cigar fatalii easy Wang
Katie Ferguson
Our fact-checker is Michelle Harris
And this message