Are you awake
Northern listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
Hey I'm Jared I'm rubber, which is Radiolab and today
We're going to hit the phones
Hello
Starting with this guy
Mark Morrison
Hey Mark this is Jed calling from Radiolab
Got ahold of him at his home in Olympia Washington
Houston traffic
All right maybe we should just jump in and you should just tell me the story
I was DJing a wedding
Out in Lacey
Next town over
It was a hot
Like
Late spring time
Feeling like summer kind of day
And
A little rented
Facility that had like Windows on all sides and all the sudden the power starts flickering
And it starts
Raining
Really hard
Okay
Ben
Free
Are falling over
Wendy's
Disgusting
And if the sky turns
Tonight
Well
Like 3:30 in the after
So Mark takes off goes back home
Hang out with the new baby
And
We open up the curtain
Turn off all the lights and we're just kind of marveling
Insane power of the
Storm is happening
My wife
It is sitting on the couch my two year old
Watching
Charlie Brown or something on
IPad
And then all of a sudden
Thursday
Snap like the sound of a whip crack
Or like
Like a two-by-four be
Snapped in half
And about
Whitney Houston
2 feet in
Front of my face
Right next to my mother-in-law and the baby
There
A little
Beer
Of light
White light
Just a little or
Size of like maybe an orange or a grapefruit
Blurry edges around it
Floating in mid-air
Is bright is like the sun
They're like the bright it lit up
The entire room
Wow
We all
Everybody in the room in unity
And Marx says this
Sun orbs
Covered in front of his face
Muah muah muah baby a second when all the sudden
Who's gone
Yeah
That's some X-Files that right there
None of us had
Any idea what the heck happened
What did you go around the room be like
Did you guys see that did you see that
Everybody thought everybody thought
My mother-in-law thought that I had like taken
Cadillac firework
Throwing it up in the air
What did you
Do
I didn't do anything
So what I did was
I started trying to Google it and there is
Piano
Imagine trying to Google that you're not going to find anything
Type into Google
Fear of light floating
Indoors
I didn't get very far
But I just wanted to get to the bottom of it
And so what Mark did
Is he setting of the computer any typed up this email
Basically saying like what the hell is this
And then he
Sent that email
Into the void
Which would be at
Gmail inbox
You know it's sat around for a while because we tend to get these kinds of questions
A lot
Are there more stars in the universe or grains of sand on earth
A lot a lot is it clean a minivan sticker V Apple why do some birds walk and other top kind of fish here why are horses
Especially good things with a traffic jam random questions like
I don't poop questions why is different animal species act differently what happens when you flush a toilet
They just sorta pile-up we should have put them in this bucket year and then feel guilty about not answering them
And over the years while they keep coming so the bucket gets Fuller
And Fuller
+ 4
It's okay okay
Let's just dump the bucket app
Until we're going to try and answer some of these questions today
Beginning with the question about
The orbit can I speak to Martin please
Peter tok them
University of Florida
Thank is it still good time to chat
It is about the only time because I'm going to go to dinner in about 10 minutes
How long we going to talk
Well
So I told Martin the story thunderstorm boom glowing or poof gone
Ya basic questions you like what is that
Well that observation is not uncommon and it's
Call Jenna Lee called ball lightning
Ball light
That's what it's called
An accordion Martin ball lightning
Is timeless
Describe exactly the same thing
19th century and 18th century that used to commonly
Come down the chimney
Come out the fireplace
Bow Wow
Analysis Martin we are living in an electronic world and so these balls of lightning
I'm Donovan telephone in airplanes they happen in submarines
Actually that's been reported
Lightning strikes outside an airplane and Eyeball comes to the windshield and floats down the whole plane
If I'm in that plane I'm thinking right
Where your depends anytime you got electrical stuff going on you can make a ball of fire like that
So do we know anything about what causes
What it is exactly is it just another form of lightning that somehow manages to wall itself up and hang around
Martin is actually one of the few people who has studied
Ball lightning in the lab exe got funded by DARPA
Trying to figure out how it works
Wasn't quite able to
He says what's likely happening is it
When a bolt of lightning strikes might hit something
Boil water tree
Substance
It's lit up and somehow phone to self into a sphere like a balloon there a bubble or something
Like if you imagine
Lightning hit some dust
Shocks the Dust
Changes chemistry
So that form some kind of
Spiracles
Scaffolding
In the lightning
Sticks to the scaffolding or something
Maybe that's what's happening
You can't prove it there's some Theory which indicates that that might happen
But if you go in the laboratory
You trying to make it
You can't make it
So can't prove it
And
If you get a book on ball lightning or you get my book and look at the chapter on ball lightning
You'll see probably a list of 50 different theories of people of come up with
All the way up
Black holes and then discontinuities and time space and
Things that are just
Completely
Almost out of this world
So they remain a mystery
But
Well observed history
And other people don't have any good math for how lightning get started in a cloud
Really I didn't know that we don't know what how lightning can get started
Shouldn't be able to
It shouldn't really be based on what the math says there's not enough money
Saint Cloud
So you're saying understood
Almost nothing is understood
Floundering around
Distance
Do you find yourself thinking about ball lightning and then suddenly just tiptoeing into an existential crisis
How little we know of the world
So I make my living as trying to uncover a little bit little more bits by little more bits but
Yo there's lots of it at 9
Mixed up producer Tracy hunt
Goes on a field trip
Justin the very Hallowed Ground
The New York Public Library
The New York
Public Library
What is floryday
Right here in the grand hall is a beautiful chandeliers all over the place is gorgeous
Collinwood field
Millions of books
In every field of human endeavor
Row upon row upon row of shelves
Close to fifty centuries of human thinking
Millions of visitors like Tracy would walk through these hallowed Halls
Question questions fueled by curiosity the desire for truth or knowledge for wisdom people trying to unravel
The mysteries of
The universe
I came here to ask him a question about catnip
Cabinet
Yes catnip why why why can't I
So we actually got like
500 questions from our listeners
So I thought it might be good idea to take some of them to the library
So I met up with this woman
She walk me into this office
There's about like I don't know
All people sitting at their death
Imanage ask my DL and I've been in this department for about 5 years
Smione
Nypl it's 917 ask nypl and putting phone number out there
And if you call them
And you ask him a question
It's their job to answer
Yes and so we are
Like a call center so article day
Starts with questions
And I get a typical day honey
150 to 200 and resumes telling me that most of the questions they get it will the weather be like this weekend.
Boring pay my library card expired or I wonder when you
Spock you know also they they get some weird ones
Ichthammol
Yeah
So I got a list right here and in the past they've gotten things like
What kind of apple did eat is it proper to go alone to Reno to get a divorce statistics on the lifespan of the abandoned woman
Elicense in India what is the natural enemy of the book telling me how to be a mistress of Ceremonies at a musical or what does it mean when you dream
Elephant
Advanced robot
Biltrite
I was maybe a little dismissive
Ford fuel pump
I mean all the questions
Of course you're very important
We welcome all questions
Play this by the way is Bernard Bernard and Marsha Bean has been working for asking my plc's about
2001 answer the question he did answer my catnip question which is large feline species like tigers and lions
Lions have the same reaction to catnip
As domestic cats
Yes I cats like catnip apparently tigers at least that I had all these questions so actually had them
Take one that they thought was super interesting which one did you pick
Tooth answer
Having me get the exact wording
So
Yeah so here we go could you play a meaningful game of frisbee on the surf
Pics of Mars
End
Yeah that was a good one and I think the word that makes it like just
Really shine is
Meaningful
So
The first thing he does you want to get me kind of doing some
Some searching you know again back-of-the-envelope kind of stuff here
A little disappointed that you didn't bust out any like books
I'm just looking up frisbee aerodynamic
She literally just turned a frisbee behavior on Earth
The spin of the Frisbee of course the lift
Drag
But he looks all that stuff up
Assume that like aerodynamics on Mars
On Mars
Bear youth in the air there are so
Fitting lifting thing that you begin
Frisbee
Not have the same sort of
Hovering effect that a frisbee does here on Earth and it probably would be more like just
Throwing up
Ball it would just go
Ten feet away 15 feet away I don't think that that's that counts as a meaningful game of frisbee
People throw it back and forth but leaving.
You're playing frisbee
On Mars
I mean it's just that should be inherently meaningful
In a growing up I remember seeing
A rebroadcast
Of
You know like the astronauts on the moon
Playing golf
And I'm sure that they were not playing like
You know PGA
Gall
They were just you know amateur Duffer's but
They were golfing on the moon
I mean to me that's
Pretty good pretty impressive the venue
Kind of
Makes the whole Endeavor meaningful I think in it and its way
Thanks to producer treatment
I asked you did ask them my dragons question
Well then turn next up
Tracy Honda
And Dragons
Hey this is Christina Tracy High
Just saying hey
This question is from Christina hard quiz
I'm a native of Novato at Northern California
And I was born and raised here
Love this place
And you and what was your question to his if you remember what it was roughly
Came across this
Article about
These creatures
Called ohms
That I guess we're being you know washed out of
These caves in Eastern Europe what are they called
These sort of like go online
Cave-dwelling amphibians there totally White
Skin is translucent very like otherworldly
The article touched on the idea that
Ya folklore
Thought that you
Little Creatures were actually like
Dragon babies being twist
Shout of
Of these caves where where these huge dragons live
Spell
I started digging into it a little bit and of course you can only find so much on the internet but there was this idea of drag
Being assertive like a universal myth
Across
You know different disparate cultures and
Christina started to wonder why it seemed that
So many cultures all over the world I'll have Miss
About dragon
What is it about like humans
About cause them to believe in these like huge
Scary fire breathing animals
Set true that yeah.
Sort out you had the northern European dragon that we're all familiar with then there's the Chinese
Dragon which is a little different that doesn't have wings doesn't breathe fire
Then there's other Dragon looking for two things the Nana Bolognese
Pool in southern Africa. There is the Amar associated with the Incan Empire yeah I think there's no doubt that
We have fabulous awesome
Creatures like
Dragons
In almost every culture
In the world
So this is Adrienne mayor research scholar in the classic
6 Department
Stanford
And I'm most interested in is what sorts of things
Found in nature
Might have led pre-scientific
People
To believe that dragons or
Monsters are there fantastic
The creatures really existed at least in the past or even maybe in
Present
Adrian actually got a book called the first fossil Hunters
That lays out the theory that a lot of these stories were actually based on
People finding old
Dino fossils and Bone fossil bones
Are teeth or claws
Footprints embedded in stone
So they see a set of old bones that they couldn't explain with any modern features
So the creature they go to is this
Dragons
Sheep thing
Yes
But I do want to
Queen Elsa
We can never know for certain which comes first.
Observations of
Mystery is traces of
Of unknown animals or the stories of dragons we don't know which comes first she said it could be that the story about the Dragon
Ken was already there and then when they found some bones they just sort of apply those bones to the dragon f
If the dragon came before the bones where did it come from
There's another theory
Some Scholars have said they're like
Monsters of the ear they arise from
Ancient Memories
A very real predator
That were face
By our ancestors basically
Dragons are composite of the Seas creatures that used to eat us and in Huntington kill us like crocodiles
Saber tooth tigers and lions have bears
Gigantic
Serpent snakes pythons Honda Raptors
They can take like this scaly skin of the crocodile the claws of the saber-tooth tiger in the seaport
He put the wing of the Raptors put them all together is all the old Terrors rolled into one like
Boom together
Attack in to all those fears that are ready
Cranberry inside
I'm going to go for that one
Yeah like that that works that that feels like an answer
Scary that could be very destructive
What's kind of magical in in Game of Thrones
The intimate scenes
Wholesale
Hard and bring you closer to these creatures that should be in a burning your face off
That she just used this whole Dragon thing to talk to
This lady at game from Game of Thrones
Her name is Paula Fairfield and she makes all the dragon noises for Game of Thrones
Oh she makes the dragons what did you ask her I guess it was
What did you want to know
Well I wanted to know I like I wanted to know like how does she make
These
Sounds and it was really interesting cuz you know we're talking a little bit about you know how dragons are composite creatures
And she basically uses Composites to make these noises
Absolutely take some places from
Birds
Ricci Chriqui bird sounds
In fact
Different kinds of reptilian recordings and stuff and key is it always scary animals
Dragon that sheet you know which of the Dragon said she's trying to actually create a performance Ford I have
Sounds I might choose simply by
Certain personality traits that I might want
Push forward
So in the case of drocon
So on the show there's the nearest
Dragon Queen and she has three dragons
And one of them is named Rogan
And she named
That dragon
After
Khal Drogo
Heard
Hot late husband
So
Drogon is like her lover
He kind of has like a very affectionate
Central relationship with her
He's whistling at her all the time he's looking at her butt and going oh baby
And so in order to kind of push for this sort of like
Dragon sexual tension I guess
She uses the sounds of
Two giant tortoises
Animating
Tortoises
It sound like
Well
And I'm out to play it
Wow
The grown of the mail actually became
With some working and you know just meant and stuff became I'm the source
The basis for
Drogon spur with her
Volaris
We need to respond
My people need me
The funny thing about the Pervert Rogan was watching people watch it and giggling when they heard it but not really knowing why
That's me and it's big
Because it had
That ass instead that kind of sensual sexual Essence at / so yeah
All all kinds of things and
You know I also use
Dragonfly wings
Make that kind of funny flutter of the
Thorin sets
Since moving like especially on the end of his tail this year
As you move through there was like a chitter
And that was like dragonfly wings
Dragonfly wings
Yeah
I I was wondering if you ever had a question about dragons that you would like to have answered
You don't know it says Cheerios
Because I think the thing that differentiates
It's the dragons
Preachers and makes them
Slightly I play
Is the fire thing
Where did the idea
That's a good question where did that come from
Well there many theories about
That actually I took that question back to a dreamer
The one that I like
Is connected
To the devastating weapon called Greek Fire which was this unquenchable fire can't be put out by water
Infected Burns and water
And so it was a Naval Weapon
And I believe that Scholars have found that
Some of the nozzles for lasting Greek fire
4 shaped like dragon
So that the boat look like it had a dragon on board breathing fire at the enemy ships
So cool
They had dragons that breathe fire
I would make it back to to Northern Europe
That's the best theory I've heard
It's interesting
So it's like it's a drag it is a composite of all the things
Features of scared us
Now we're part of that composite I technology
That big dick
Is built becomes part of the creature that frightens us
Text Tracy
You're welcome
Who is
What is
Anything coming to mind
Say something
Gray
What's a fedora
Should have known Matt
You should have known that all right we're going to take a break
This is Marni Campbell from the beautiful Banks of Lake Washington in Seattle Washington
Radiolab
Supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of
Science and Technology
She in the modern world
More information about
Sloan at
Ryu. Sloan
. org
I hate everybody
I'm a producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents
Aunts and uncles teachers we're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments
Brilliant
Basically I want to hear about this
When a kid you know did something
It just means you lean back and say
Well
Maybe it was the moment that
A kid you've been reading to 4 months
Started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of their musical score
Or maybe the kids in math
Music in the margin of their geometry
We're interested in the
Specific moments where
Kid does something super smart
It doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story
Go to radiolab.org
Flash brilliance
Record short audio message
Again that's radiolab.org
Flash Brewing
Thank you so much
Jad Robert Radiolab we are back
With more questions
Next one comes from
Producer Rachel Cusack
So this question comes from Liam hamburger from Denver Colorado
I was browsing memes on my Instagram feed
The picture was trying to go to sleep
And the caption was her he's probably thinking about other girls and then
What do you say wonder what
Yeah so he said I wonder if I've ever bought milk from the same cow twice
So if I go to the store I bought a gallon of milk and then I go back maybe a week later I got another gallon of milk
What are the odds that the same towel is in both of those gallons of milk
I would say
The answer is almost
Certainly
100%
Start Benjamin he's a math professor Harvey Mudd College
Claremont California
And I'm also a nap emoji
And how is he so sure that it's 100% according to Benjamin it all comes down to
And dare I say
Calculator
So take a farm like Dale's here
My name is Dale
Pine Hollow Dairy Dale has about a thousand cows
And 22 time you cows walk into a milking parlor they lineup it looks like a wishbone all day all night
And they get hooked up with these black rubber hoses are your here and there is a guy putting them
Machine on a cow and he hits the
Button that turns on the vacuum and then
Out of there others
Into the big hose along the bottom of the floor
Run to the house
And it's meeting up with all the milk from all the other cows
Domenico's
From that room into another room or get cool down
Very cool down it goes into this rocket ship looking thing outside called a milk Silo where all the milk from Del's Farm
Image of hanging out together
Until it's full
Sending out
Over 8000 gallons of milk today on a
Tractor trailer
Amazon picks up milk and it stops at another Farm in another Farm in another Farm until
The truck is full
Full list of the processing plant
And once the processing plant all that milk is just mixed around even more with milk from all the cows Muresan
And I still have my
My back-of-the-envelope that have the
Calculation here here's with my something there are about 90000
Drops of milk
In a gallon
I don't know a hundred thousand
Contributing
Tempura chicken processing plant
A drop of milk
From anyone tile getting into any particular gallon but probably the case
Gallon of milk
Contains
Most of those cows
Contributing nothing in one drop of milk you could probably have a bunch of different milk molecules from a bunch of different
And so one glass of milk
Might have
Maybe hundreds of thousands of different
County Public Schools
In my glass
Wow
I'm going back to the original question Arts argument is that
When you're drinking a glass of milk there's like so many different bits of milk from so many different cows
Then it's probably the case
Two glasses
Look now. You're almost certain to
A cow that was rapped
So you're bound to run into at least a little bit of one of those hundred thousand cows
Again there's no point being that every glass of milk
Thousands and thousands of different cows
Contributing to it a little bit of 10000 cows in every class in every glass of milk
I love that I don't know that I know it's great it's like you're enjoying the collective efforts of this entire species
Oh no I think it should be the product of one or two cows when you can picture in your head and maybe pat on the nose
Thank you you could say
Yeah I know I'm with both of you I feel like
It weirds me out but I also think it's kind of cool at the same time what happens if you drink a glass of milk
In New York
Get on a plane flight to Atlanta
Then have another glass of milk are you getting the same 10,000 in each class or are they different 10,000
Answer that question and it seems like no one really wants
To pay to ship milk that far
And so basically it done processing plant might be in a whole different group
If you really want to figure out exactly which plant your milk is coming from you can go to where is my milk from.com
Yeah and
You input a little code on the top of your carton
And see how often that number comes up again each processing plant has its own code
Show many stores
Thank you just a big thanks to Dairy Farmer jail Mattoon over at Pine Hollow Dairy
Oh yeah
Glass or two for lunch and a glass or two for dinner probably two glasses each each meal if I don't
Drink milk I don't feel good
Like if I go away on vacation
Gypsy milk
Garden Center Apartments Middleton
Now brown cow
A married couple hello is this Marie
Does Matt kielty come from real life how are you
I have you on speaker phone and back is right here how's it going
So Zach Murray it was years ago actually they sent us an email
But what I think is like one of the most confounding perplexing mysterious devices
He can find inside anybody's home peso the microwave
I guess I guess what I'm wondering is
1 why were you microwaving peppers in too deep
GMM of this happen
What happened
Petzl quick scene setup Portland Maine
The kitchen
Brown dinner time cooking tomato sauce
Shortcut for something
And I said oh. Don't put those in the microwave
And I was just like
You're crazy
Hogwash
Mom put some peppers in the microwave in a spark
My first thought was that he was wrong that's what I thought I bet your memory was like there must have been a piece of metal in them
Nike wavys don't remember that and that's what was barking up cuz special I wouldn't do that
Nothing until
We have the ability to find this out
And I approve that's wrong
So that was like five years ago in the past so we decided we would actually do
Our own experiment
The present
To get to the bottom of this
Do green peppers
Spark in the microwave first thing first I shouldn't bottom microwave
How's it going fifty bucks
Alright alright baby
And carried it like
8 blocks back to work
Also bought a bunch of groceries because we're going to do more than just a Peppers test and 4 reasons
I'd rather not get into a decided not to start with the peppers
Baby carrots
Producer in McEwen
Until
Cats
Okay
And as the great Ronco says of infomercial Fame
Set it
And forget
This little yellow spot just shot out from one of her slaves
That was crazy
Vaal Spark
Weather
Those tiny spark
Okay next
Disregard to locate to get the kale boom boom boom
Delicioso how do you smoke
Ready
Said it
Why was electricity coming out of the blueberry
Grapist
Pepito strip strip petitis
Creepy meaning
Anytime cook
Jumbo Franks
Turkey Franks
Siri said it
Red and green
Bell peppers green was crazy pepper
Parasect record
See who needs fireworks when you got it
Yeah cuz I don't want it yet is it going to look like who's on fire
Play Bad
Take a break
What did you say to Maria after the
Peppers
Spark in microwave
I think I would I don't know I was totally speechless
So pepper spark in microwave that was settled but
The debate about my understanding of how microwaves work
Why
Maybe it's just that ever have a lot of moisture in it
Zach maybe it's you put the pepper in microwave all that water get
Skin act as like Tinder and that lights on fire quickly
And I think that the green one
Taste a little bit
Little bit of metal in there that Sparky
Is your next step to
Find the appropriate scientist oh yeah I'm definitely going to try it
Put this case to bed
Yeah just give us one moment
So ended up tracking down this woman is Caroline Caroline
Okay
Carolina Ross
Summer professor in the department of Materials Science and Engineering in MIT and experience
Microwave a donut with some
With roast potatoes
Yeah I've seen Sparks most potatoes
Alright so yeah
So Astrid in the case of
The peppers
Potatoes or
Are the grapes like all the different food that we tried
Like what happens in a microwave
The food just relay
So they got some pieces of paper in the microwave
Press start
Like what
What happened
Okay
So that was a
Gadgets in the microwave oven that produces the microwaves it's called a magnet phone and it's an interesting
Thing in itself
Okay quicksand it's basically like this hunk of metal that makes microwaves but Kailyn told me it's really cool thing which is
If she's be used in World War 4 radar that was in the forties and then
In 1945 there was an engineer Raytheon who was working on these devices
And he found that some candy ball he had in his pocket got hot
Like this Cooks food until then SLI magnetron got thrown inside of a mailbox
Indus was born
The microwave so it's an interesting thing in itself but
It produces a beam of microwaves and they
Bounce Around inside the microwave oven moving at the speed of light
What is pounding
Into the pepper
Like shooting independent episode
And these microwaves
They are the right kind of frequency to cause the molecules in food to oscillate back and forth
You put the pepper in that so
The purpose of lots of water inlet Esquivel the things as well
And
Those molecules stops absorbing the microwaves and bouncing back and forth and
Hitting each other and heating up
And then that fit gets even home satin even horse app
Eventually
It could burst into flames
But that is not
What we're seeing
With our pepperoni
It's not no because
Is Caroline
Find me a flame is very different
I got a spark
So one thing to keep in mind just that some
The pepper is fairly conductive it's go to all this water and that we know that water can conduct electricity
Computer has a lot of salt dissolved in it
Minerals things like that in that sense it's a little bit like a piece of metal metal as we know so
Microwave energy Roswell as we all know
Yes
30 Gatti's pizza pepperoni microwave in there
Another thing is the microwave like the wave itself it has an electric field
Which house lights back and forth high frequency
Shoot in a piece of paper what happened is
Is electricity starts
Switching back and forth to Pepper on flowing
You can get quite big concert Electric
Yield around the food and that's electric field bills off enough enough and eventually it's big enough to
Close the app
To Glow
Around the food
Actually electricity coursing through
The air like a fluorescent light bulb
You can start to see these glowing balls of gas
Floating
Text you the air turning into plasma
Now back in the center the microwave
RR little bit
Pepper Wethersfield
Electrical current switching back and forth through those bits
Peppa and
If you have sharp corners
Tiny microscopic little points
Electricity electricity are concentrated at those Shopko nose like a lightning rod
NFL Corners electricity
Bill
Build
Until
You got some mini lightning bolts
McAllen said everything in the microwave disorder
Calm down
Until the electric field builds up again and it doesn't roll over letting loose these mini lightning bolts
Does a very Dynamic process you've got things being honest you've got things recombining
You've got charged flowing you've got light being emitted
Things get hot
There's a big current flowing over that tiny fraction of a second
Lots of quantum physics in there
And then we hear a little thing
And then
With them
Then we're done
Nice job to do
How you doing
Okay
Call Zach Murray told everything I learned about there's parking pepper and that even though both of them didn't have you text Siri like sack was right
Waters important part of Marie was onto something with this metal thing
It feels like it's almost like a little bit of like a marriage
Start pardon the pun between both your idea is that
What is what is happening inside this
Black Box
So yeah
We have some some of the elements there
Yeah
It said it's about it
There was one
Thing that I ask all these questions
We are getting in
There was like this tiny little pattern of of married couples spending us in
There was one couple that was like
They're arguing about
The nutritional value of microwaving a potato another very
Long email about how they've been debating about how we perceive
Color
Actually had a similar to
Yes it does
Oh yeah
Sort of like
Tone that I thought was
Lean and you thought was brown gray
Yeah we have that couch for like
Between different houses in different
Probably like 5 or 6 years and maybe 7 years 10 years
And I
And I was yeah I always thought it was gray and still do but apparently you and your sister thought it was Green
You like them together for years and you never realized
You're saying something completely different
You don't have a green couch
Producer Matt kielty
All right so that's just a few of the questions you asked us which we tried to answer
But that's just the first part of our effort we have another whole sequence of questions and answers coming up so
If your question hasn't been answered yet
Never know the next batch never there now question it's coming very
Very soon
Why do humans have two feet
The facts
Do the little
Headphone string
Where do we go from here
That works like I have no idea
For kids
Why
Who knows
To hear the message again press 2
Start of message
Hey this is Marie Muller calling from Portland Maine
Laura Mueller and Calvin Mueller in the background
Video lab was created by God album Rod and is produced by Soren wheeler
Dylan Keith is our director of sound design arrested 90 * 58 is our managing director or staff include
Simon Adler Becca Bressler Rachel Cusick David devil
Spell Happy kasie hunt
Not guilty Robert Coley
Netty McEwen the chief Master
Melissa O'Donnell
Aryan black
Pat Walker
Molly Webster
Help from
Linda Ronstadt
David Backes
Agar fatali
Babywearing and Katie Ferguson
Fact Checker is Michelle Harris
Next radio app
And this message