Okay before we get going today just a quick prompt
So we're putting together a show of questions
Questions that listeners have asked us over the years we tend to get a lot of questions if you want me like why why doesn't the big cloud
Their fall down and it's full of water right that various kinds of questions and so we're collecting all these questions that we're going to do a show where we're trying to
Answer as many as we can
So if you have a question
It doesn't matter how dumb or how sophistic any kind of question email us at questions at Radiolab
. org
Again that's questions
Radiolab.org you can also text us the word questions at 701 - 01
Why do I always have more wire hangers in my closet
And never enough socks that might be one that we would
At least read
Okay let's get on with the show
Weight units
Radiolab
Radio WNYC
Hello I'm Jah diving wrought iron Robert krulwich Radiolab and today we have a story from a long time
Time contributor of ours
I was up to something new with these days are Gregory Warner
Yes if you listen to this program you know his work because he's been on our show so many times about us
Stories from upstate New York about faith healers things 12 years ago then sore from Afghanistan
Mammoth quote Afghan Elvis a couple stories from Kenya one from Ethiopia
And exported acute alcoholism
Buy some quack in Moscow
In other words he's like all over the place he is a foreign correspondent for National Public Radio
And recently NPR
Decided to give him his own
Podcast
It's called rough translation it's killer
But we're going to just begin today with sampling one of his new pieces
It again takes us to A peculiar place with an improbable
Results
Is Gregoire
The six months before Muhammad went to prison with the best six months of his life
Atlanta this great job managing a Pepsi Plant
Any country love on his first date
We went to Smoke Restaurant in Seattle
Where we live
My name is Esteban
20 years old
Tell her to State Bank
That we were talking to you
Thailand Casino
True Spanish ion
We want to get married
That's it love at first sight
Yeah in a sentence yet
So struck by her gender she was smart
Connect about everything from the future of their country
To the music they like
Whatever images the word Somalia calls to mind
The Somalia where Muhammad lived was in a cultural Renaissance
This is 1981 it was under communist rule
The Dictator
What's the dictator but he was also a big fan of Somali culture and music
Music was sexully big part of how Muhammad courted Isfahan he made her mixtapes
This was the 80s
Juicing or did she say
Oh she's a bit the singer
A few months after Muhammad and his mom got married
Muhammad got a phone call from the director of local public Hospital
Donations from the community she was desperate for donations
Forbidding
That music-loving dictator his name was Siad Barre a
He cut off supplies to the hospital
In retaliation for an independence movement in the region
The doctor's been calling all his friends and Secret
Directions you know people can we raise the money discreetly ourselves
But Muhammad wanted to go big or suppose maybe I want to share my happiness
What do you mean by share your happiness
Unicorn tribute
Customer other people who are less fortunate than us
Muhammad was in that stage of new love when you just kind of think the world is full of good feeling and if everybody knew it was going
Going on they would do the right thing
Any take this bold and pretty risky move
He writes
A letter from kinda nice letter about Hospital conditions conditions
Especially implying that the dictator is not doing right by us and we got to step up ourselves
Couple weeks later Muhammad and his pain heard a knock on their door in the middle of the night
The Arsenal why don't want anything like that
It's just that we need to take him
You see that
My wife
Remember
Fluff
Esoteric
Muhammad is accused of treason
And sentenced to life in solitary confinement
Since way
And this is where the story really begins
Muhammad cell is Tiny maybe 6ft by 6ft
Concrete walls
Hole in the floor for toilet
And a window high up that lets in just a little bit of light
Better.
Cockroach
Come from the toilet
Cockroaches cockroaches in the light of the world
Puts you
Instruments with
Defi
Sweet
On their feet would be excrement from the toilet
After cockroaches come from rats
The mice
Mosquitoes
Alarm supply Mesquite
Like an engine jet engine
But even worse than that sound
Is buzzing in his own mind
Because in this present there is one rule to strictly forbidden
What's your name
He's forbidden to speak the other inmates
Forward and backward
Back pacing back and forth
And this is a tiny place to
Go back and forth from this
So that three short steps forward three shirts as backwards Resources phone
So that is his life now
Until one day
He hears a knock
On the wall
Knock knock
Becomes
Words
Another time
In another place
All happy families are alike
Each unhappy family
I'm happy it's only
This is rough translation the show from NPR
At Gregory there
Vegas
Hey we should do you want to just tell us what rough translation is so I've been making a podcast this year
The idea is that
In every episode we follow a conversation we're having in the United States
KIRO that's playing out
In a different place when episode we might
Hear about how fake news is playing out in Ukraine which is been getting fake news for longer and higher doses than any
Sing America sing imagine
We're hearing about a Transit happening more now we're Chinese women are hiring American surrogates to have their babies
Tim
Basically every episode we try to do the same thing just sort of see
Something we have a see what the other folks yeah
Which is not like what we saying
I'm guessing this one we have a guy locked away in a Somali prison should we
Just get play and see what happens
8 months into Muhammad's prison sentence
Then he's in a Cell that's always
He's alone
Not quite
Peddler
So many different types of ancestors
China
Was like watching a film
Facebook
3D
To look around for food
383 t-shirt
When are you
Houston time
It's another with
Able
Have loved to go
See you at that Hill there
The horse the Whitley wood stain
But I couldn't go see for sale
Concrete
And then
One evening when the guard is at the other end of the line of cells just out of earshot
The guy in the cell next to Muhammad
Whispers
So what the door saying Glenn ABC
To the one playing ABC Photo
Learn ABC through the body remembers
End end does that make any sense to Muhammad them on zero says
Are you looking at the road between us
But then
But then he knocks on the wall
Piccadilly's
And when Muhammad leaned over to the wall
I could hear the sound
Shark
So you have a sharp sound and a kind of
Adult sound
Windows to sounds
Immediately clicks this is the alphabet
Oh so the guy singing learn this code is code so you can understand them
Penny stocks
See
Person alphabet
And then
And what would he want with the first sentence that you heard
Which means peace in Somali
It means how are you
I could be that way.
Hosts Today Show
Navigating anything else
Antonio Mohamed Canal spend most of the day tapping back and forth
The talk with the guy in the next cell about
Politics
Share a childhood memory
But at night
When you can't sleep
He turns against the concrete
And then again
And again
I'm Only Sleeping few review
Half an hour away cover half an hour wake up from a nightmare
Sweaty and in a panic are you awake
I can't sleep I need to talk
I'd like to sleep when I'm falling asleep
Sitting in my heart
Face
Sofas
So I was thinking those space that
This is
Texas Methodist
What is the smell of death
Muhammad had a lot
The fearful thoughts in that prison cell
Especially about his wife
I cannot imagine how how she is
Coaster news from from the world
About cycling
Skip difficult to imagine where she is
Even with a Sheetz alive
Then there's a meaner thought as well
Government was encouraging
Wipes
To divorce their husbands
The government was saying you should divorce
Statesville haunted prison
Even some chefs friend
Planet Fitness Astoria
Divorce in Somali Society in Islam is usually the husband's exclusive right
But there are the quranic verses that can allow a wife to choose to divorce her husband if the husband absent for some time
It shakes loyal to the dictator use those verses
Pressure the wise
A political prisoner
Question number Speedway
Forced from their wives
I was thinking sometimes District
She was only 20 years old
They'd only been married for 3 months
And he was sentenced to life you synced
She's probably enjoying herself
She's living her life
I am in this place
At first it's just a little twinge of resentment
Then the feeling comes back
Stronger
Sharper
You think
She should be visiting
But wait
Cheikh Anta
Nobody can visit Spruce and nobody can get in touch
How do you still you blame her for not getting
In touch with you
And and what do you think about her in those moments when you're blaming her for not to
Visiting
Pretty far from Love
Chipotle Target Optical of time
Every time that Muhammad is tapped one of these dark thoughts on to the wall
Someone was listening
Someone on the other side of the wall
Was a doctor
Dr. Adam nebeker
Gallstone in May
Athens prison
Is the doctors listening fees Taps on the wall
He's also diagnosing them
Acute anxiety
You was telling me the symptoms
Through the wall
I should tell you that doctor adhan and Muhammad we're actually friends
Before present
The doctor with the director of the public hospital going to call them up and ask them for donation
You did not ask Muhammad to write that letter
Complaining about the hospital conditions
Cuz there was no press Allowed no newspapers
No Free Press
And that's the moment the government decided that
They should do something about us
But if the doctor blame Mohammed for writing the letter that got them both thrown in prison
He didn't show it every time that Muhammad. Whatever the hour the doctor would not back
You still have these nightmares
So he jumps
It has a nice man and that he knocks on the wall again
Do I have to wake up
And then I can start conversation in a show.
Fall asleep again just like a baby
Tibetan making you fall asleep
If dr. Allen seems fairly unsentimental about some of the more dramatic aspects of Muhammad's life
It's partly that these two men are such different personalities
Will Muhammad describe that nighttime arrested the moment of shock and Terror
Dr. Adam seems to have met the same secret police with a bag
Packed and ready for prison
Bag of clothes
Lots and lots of books
Books is the best
Befriending in a prison
But then when you go to
The Prisoner was taken away the back room
Assume
Tell me about the day you learn the language
Bellaire the Nook
Well
It was the most exciting day in your life
It was the most exciting and we couldn't sleep
Way to go me ask this this knocking this is something that they are they all were doing there was a particular line of 8
Prisoners of these eight prisoners it was a particular guy in the in the middle there who
At once heard of Morse code
And
Just lying there in prison one day thought hey what if I ended the language and we can talk also this was actually a home
SpongeBob he did not know Morse code he just knew of
And the guards couldn't hear that that was something that was their own
Right let me know literally they could this was kind of the magic of it they could be just
Tapping on the wall they could be having a whole conversation and the guard would have no idea what they were
Say
We started practicing in the whole day and all night
And if there's a joke
And somebody loves
Everybody stop smoking on the wall
And asking that's red what's that joke about
And the dead guy
Stop
Sending the message the joke
And it goes from 1 to take an hour to send it tiny joke from one cell
The next South the neck
There were eight of them in this prison
Cuz they don't know that we're knocking on the wall because they can't hear
I'm the one that she is all laughing they just said all this girl
These guys are also losing their
Sanity
Meanwhile on the other side of the wall Muhammad really was worried that his mind was slipping
I was frightened of going
Twisted Canadian my mind
When I commit suicide without knowing
Without
Wangjing
Is it almost like
The fear of going crazy with make me crazy
Imagine people who are Christian
Imagine that maybe
Going crazy with supporting
Norton
Sawyer
Try to understand why the doctor on his side of the wall
And I was trying to come selenium
And explain to him to the wall
He's not going to go mad and that he's not going to die
But
You can cancel person through a wall
Months go by
Been a whole year
Finally it's
2 years of their prison sentence
And something happens
Doctor addend is summoned to the office of the warden
To get a change of clothes
The room was empty and there was a bench
The Oscar to sit on the bench and then he asked
He asked one of Augusta Grand Prix your bank
The whole bag with all your clothes or books ever
And that hit you up or are you open that bag and then he tells you to choose
Something new to wear
And you don't choose anything else
He says don't use anything else
Not this was a relationship. Just getting his first change of clothes since he arrived in prison
To choose your next t-shirt the doctor turns to the warden he lets him right in the eye
Can I have one book question that's wrong
Him and I
Did not expect that he would agree to give me so I was just
I just tried you and he said yes you can choose one of your books
So then I started thinking of the all the biggest spook I can take with me a few minutes later the doctor he is walking
Back to his cell with the fattest book in his bag under his arm you can picture and fantasizing about just getting to lie down and read
Read that when he returns to his self there's that sound
At the wall took her to me the thought that what anti-free this before infinity War
And distract the negative thoughts
Miwa Muhammad on his side of the wall
Here's the new set of taps
Haven't pooped
Abu can I read it to you
Chapter by chapter
Anakin
I like rain
Anna Karenina
The famous novel by Leo Tolstoy
Published in 1878 the English translation that they're using
Is 800 pages
350000 words
Nearly 2 million letters
Each letter
Set of TAPS for the doctor prepares
So
Just stop
I took
Piece of my
Bed sheets
Hayabusa.
I don't like
She's prepping for a medical procedure
Wrapping the sheet around his wrist and knuckle
Cuz it'll be like that
So then I started knocking
And he started listening
All happy families are alike
Each unhappy family is unhappy in its own way
Everything was in confusion in the oblonsky house the wife had discovered that the husband
The effect
Did those TAPS in that book had on Muhammad's mind
Is active brake
It is Michael Burrows from Portland Oregon
Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Lansing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloan at www. Sloan. Org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help this summer I'm hosting
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
About what we're calling tiny moments of Brilliance basically I want to hear about this
Did something
It just means you lean back and say wow how did they do that maybe it was the moment that I can
Kids you've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons and you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed are ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the specific moments where a kid does something super smart
Anything to do with the test if you have a story please share it with us
Go to radiolab.org brilliance
Record a short audio message for us
And that's where you're at. Org / brilliance
Thank you so much
Okay we're back this is Radiolab
And we now return to the tail
Told by Gregory Warner from his new podcast rough translation
The day that the novel Anna Karenina and did their lives
Marked a new phase for Muhammad and the doctor
Each morning dr. Adam wood
Carefully wrap his hands
And open the novel
Muhammad on his side of the wall
But listen
When he was dressed
Stepan arkadyevitch
Sprinkles
Wassabi Production
Broadway Storage me
Pocketbook matches and watch
But it's double chain and seals
And
Checking out his handkerchief
Feeling himself Queen fragrant
Healthy and physically at ease
Spite of his unhappiness
He walks with a slight swing on each leg into the dining room
Coffee with
If it's been awhile since you cracked open on a creditor
Here's what you need to know
Anna is Noble woman in nineteenth-century Russian she's married to a man much older than herself
She goes to a ball in a black velvet dress line with lace and falls in love with Soldier
Count France
Rich boy careless love Muhammad immediately hates him
And I was hating anything in uniform actually
Wedding first season
American filter
Right he's in the military and you were in a military prison
If you really didn't like ROTC
So anyway the soldier vronsky
Steals on his heart he gets her pregnant even though she still married to the other guy and then on a mix
The choice that really changes everything
Because instead of having a secret affair
Like all the others in her social set
She makes her love Papa
She leaves her husband
And
Society the Russian nobility
Cut Her Off
The isolator
Trotskyism answer
Pretty much able to go on with life
But Anna's realizing how alone she is
She's staying in a room wondering what Bronski is up to when he's not with her
Just the same as Muhammad was
Wondering what his wife was doing
Outside the Prison Walls
Muhammad read me this one sentence from the book beloved her
Sorry
If we David had he would understand all the difficulty of her situation
Are you prescribed from it
If you loved her
He would rescue her from her situation
San Jacinto
Is traps
Spy
Reviews about women and maybe desire
But you were trapped
Buy real wolves
It didn't matter how different their lives seemed
On the outside
Inside
She was suffering all the time
He felt
Exact Lagana
He also was jealous crazily jealous and also hating himself for being jealous
And all the sudden he meets this fictional character who is suffering
In exactly the same way
And is suffering
Is driving her into a state that Muhammad most feared for himself
Going
The second alien my man
When I go to commit suicide without knowing without
Wangjing
Cessna 750 pages into the book
And 2 months have passed since the doctor first started tapping the book letter by letter
Anna and vronsky are now living in Moscow and it's summer so it's hot and suffocating
And on this particular day Bronski is off visiting his mom which
Anna hates because she thinks she's trying to set him up with a young princess
An honest in the State of Mind where
Chipotle thinks that she's a burden to front ski and she
Pixie be better off without her
But also she wants him to suffer her absence the way
She's suffering
It's in the state that on a bunch of walking down a train platform
The train is hurtling down the track and this thought possesses her
She knew what she had to do
What are rapid lightning. She went down the steps that led from the tank to the rails and stocks
Quite near the approaching train
And he's thinking about what she's about to do
Shady tribe
Except for her
But he realizes his tears are not just from one of my wife
He's remembering Islam
His wife is she suffering
The bouqs one that brought me back to
Think about that a lot
And he finds himself asking a question that in two years in prison he's not asked himself before
Did I do well
Those few months we were together
Had he been a good husband
Military time
Instead of thinking
She's left him
And also hating himself for thinking that she's left him
He's thinking why did he take himself away from her
I writing that stupid newsletter
In a different way
That letter that got them all thrown in prison if you could have talked to them
Putting himself in his wife's shoes like that
It kind of took him out of his own misery
He could think about like
Pizza Pit West
And then me
Cuz I was wondering presumptuous
And outside with
It goes from self-pity
The pity for her
I think that's related to the books tell stories they actually famous for that that's like his magic crazy Talent
Can you say more about that magic crazy Talent cuz like
When I was
I told elif batuman about Muhammad story
Heard her reading Tolstoy passages for us
She's also a writer novelist yourself and totally obsessed with on a credit I like it alot
When I told her about Muhammad's experience
She had this idea
About why that book in particular might have helped Muhammad
Make this mental leap from
Hating his wife
Imagining everything through her eyes
Customer gives a lot of weight to to all of the characters like even suggest like a newlywed young girl you spend a lot of time in her thoughts
And there's like a scene where she's trying to
Eat a mushroom on a plate and it keeps slipping from under her for
Time Juventus. Disobedient
Slippery Mushroom in hair
I shaking delays
Full retard
Show lights
It's a book that takes the subjectivity of young women seriously
And not just young women everyone that servants and I'm the dog there's a hunting scene in this that's dumb
Actually goes to the perspective of the dog
And and everything just seems so true you read that near like that's definitely what that dog was thinking
And so she says the experience of reading Tolstoy is the experience of being constantly confronted with how differently the
The same thing can look from us
Slightly different perspective like he's just he never gets bored of showing that and in the book the characters themselves
Judge each other and then are able to expand that and to see each other a little bit more generously that's what elephants do
That tell stories book
Gave to Muhammad
Tiffany's cat
Didactic definition definition
In a place like
Like that person
People become very selfish you think everybody has forgotten about me
At the beginning.
And nobody cares about me like that
What do you think about other people's situation than you
You understand it's helping me
Senpai help me
Even sleep better
Tolstoy actually had one more role to play
Muhammad's wife
8 years after his arrest
Somali political winds shifted and
The dictator was trying to appease his enemies
Muhammad and the others were suddenly released
He discovered his region of Somalia was flattened by Civil War
But it also discovered something else
His wife is mine
She was still as what
She is not giving up on him
And she had suffered in his absence
Working at the State Bank
She's been pressured by your boss to divorce
The traitor Muhammad
When she refused she was relocated
And by the time Muhammad was released
You're living in a refugee camp
In Germany she couldn't even make it back to Somalia to see him
So I waited another day that was
Another
See about 10 months
Go to see each other
Finally they figure out a way that they can reunite in a neighboring country
And though it's been almost
A decade since they seen each other
You recognized her immediately from a disc
And if they drew closer
Is Van opens her arms to
Give her husband a hug
And he reaches out
And all that he could do in that moment
Is shake her hand
Do I not feel as I felt even even prison I was feeling so much in love with her
And yet when we met
She was like a
You know something like that
Well
I mean
I will
Asking myself
Why do you not
Ice in love with her
This was a moment
That we found really
Interesting and
As we were talking about it with Greg Studio
Greg said it was really In This Moment
This. Of Dow is overcome by a momentary doubt
Of the possibility
Setting up
That new life
Dreamed of on the way
That the book came back to Muhammad
Again
Except this time you didn't think of the main character and he thought of a different character in the book A guy by the name of
This is a character who is
I also love also has
Like strong emotions
And like Muhammad in that one moment with his wife
Levin spends the entire book
RAC by doubts
But everything and eternal dissatisfaction with yourself
Man attempts to improve and failures
And then Eternal X
Location of the heart
And standing there with his wife
Is weirded out by his own lack of
Feeling
Muhammad had two thoughts like oh
I'm like leaven In This Moment
And
What happens to 11 at the end
And what's really cool about Levin's conclusively of the book is he finally just decides like I'm not going to worry about how weird my feeling
But she doesn't
Actually come he doesn't make himself whole
As he wants to be he wants to the whole book he wants to be
Fully in love with Kitty and not just with his heart but with his mind soul and want to be a good Christian and everything has
It sort of makes sense
But you know but he's just a complicated sort of
Guy in and got many
Different feeling for the end of the book it kind of feels like
You know
I'm going to stop
Just
Thinking obsessively about how awkward I am in this situation
And I'm just going to
Dealer supposed to
I'm going to be the dad
I'm going to be the husband
And Muhammad thought to himself
Like maybe I need to do that too because
Who knows where I'm at right now I was in a Cell for 8 years
In the prison
In a way you wouldn't be living
You're still
Inside yourself you have no.
You have to open
Minifigures Lego
Opening back up
It's probably going to take some time
And some work we have to learn to love each other again
And daddy says
What they did
Aeropostale had a lot to do with it
You think Tolstoy helps you fall in love again
I mean I mean
Meaning of love you know it wasn't so easy
Love again
This man has
Inexperience and she was living God real life
Difficult for people to
Brother to live with someone who has been
Is solitary confinement for so long
I was protopage got to leave it at that particular time
And you're saying that knowing
That you are hard to live with knowing it
Yes made it easier for us to
Talk to each other to
Live
Plant live with each other
Because you knew that if your heart was not
Quite working yet
I should be that moment for life book
Hey one last thing
There is someone else to give credit to here besides the Great
Russian author every detail the Tolstoy wrote into that book
Every perspective shift that helped Muhammad Escape his prison cell
All the sentences had to be
Tapped Out
On a concrete wall
My friend I could imagine him getting tired
Suicide weapon
Direction to dr. Adnan Syed Muhammad was his last patient
After their release he was just too out of practice to return to medicine and after prison the doctor did try to read
The novel Anna Karenina again
I went to the pusherman
What a treasury that penetrated too many bad memories
But he knew someone could use it somebody of journalist
And I took that book to him and I told him that the best thing about prison
Things you can have in a prison is a book
Greg Warner
Thank you guys
Going to check out more episodes of rough translation will link you to it at radiolab.org or you can go to npr.org
Slash rough translation
This episode of rough translation was edited by Marion McEwen and was produced by Jess Jiang thank
Thank you to Elizabeth senja spackman who introduced Greg to dr. Adan She interviewed dr. Adan at the hargeisa in
International book fair in Somaliland the rough translation team had editorial help from Jacob Goldstein Noah King Nick Fountain Roberts
Smith Brian Lupo Kowski and Sana krasikov LF Batman is the author of the possessed
Adventures with Russian books in the people who read them her new novel is the idiot
Play music by John Ellis more music from Blue. Sessions and are Dylan Keith ruins music as well
All right well we should go I'm Jedi home run I remembered for wish and thank you very much for listening
This is Susanna calling from Sunny Beirut in Lebanon
And It produced by Soren wheeler Dylan Keith is our director sound design our staff includes Simon Adler
Rachel Cusick David Tracy hunt Matt kielty Robert krulwich
Melissa O'Donnell Ariane whack and Molly Webster with help from Amanda around chick
Katie Ferguson our fact-checker is Michelle Harris