Is Jad Radiolab so
We're at the here is a show we originally released
About
Six seven years ago we decided to revisit a trees
Mind
Style started off
I'll say more about it
Are you weightless
Listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
Okay ready alright let's open the show today
Test test on a sunny street corner
New Jersey where are we now we are on Washington Street which is the main thoroughfare in Hoboken
It's a nice day in Hoboken people are out and about after work
Name is John Horgan I'm a science journalist he's also a teacher
And John is out today with our producer Lulu Miller
Doing
What do you often does wishes to go up to someone he doesn't know
Only take a minute at moment and I can give you
Will humans ever stop fighting Wars once and for all
No
Because of
Greed
And one UPS
To explain John's been asking this question
Will humans ever stop fighting wars
What's 4 years
These are him this question
Snapchat about war get something really Bass
Do we feel we can change
Who We Are
Any kind of popped out of his mouth was 2003
In a friend asked him to give a talk at a church just a few days after the first invasion of Iraq
So here I was in this
Church and I remember the mood was very somber
I was determined to try to make people
Feel that okay
This is a setback but still
You got to believe that this is possible and I try to list all the reasons
Hennessy was making his case and getting worked up
You look at the 60 or so people were there in the audience is that all right
How many of you here believe that war
Will and someday
And I think one or two people raise their hand at a 60
And John thought way
This is really Who You Are
And so that's actually when I started
Reading as much as I can about all these things and dug up some surveys from the 1980s
Sounds about 20 years ago
People were asking this question
You think war will ever end taking surveys
A snowman that they were not the most scientific
But like the results
Seem to indicate
That we used to be optimistic
Back in the 80s only one and three
Got that work
Is a minority
Where is today
Will Youmans ever stop fighting Wars once and for all if you take that question to the streets of Hoboken
You'll find love about nine out of 10 people
Saying yeah I think so
Never know
Might be called up John again recently to ask
Have the results change cuz he has
Kept on doing a survey and he said no
6 years later it's
Still roughly eight or nine out of ten people say no we'll never stop fighting
Same results
Depressingly
The worst part
Is it when he asked the next
Why do you think
Invariably he gets
Something like I think there is a human nature is to for greed and to always want more it's just
Human Nature
And I don't think we're ever going to learn why do you say that I just think that it's too ingrained in our human nature
So
So we want to challenge that last day
Too ingrained in our human nature that was handed down to us
From our primate ancestors violence meme
Who knows
Question is
How ingrained is that
Well yeah
Me if you think that we have inherited something yet what can we do about it we Stocker can we change
Phoenix Wright choices
So he's got for you this hour or three stories where choice
Individual choice
Challenges destiny
Maybe
I'm Jared I'm right by Robert krulwich this is Radiolab
Stick around
Here's the thing
Did not mean the present
This show was
Are usually inspired by an anecdote that I'd read about the New York Times is Guy Martin bunzl
Was telling a story
When he was 18 it was 1966 I believe you sitting on a plane and a guy next to him
Sad looks
The stewardess and then says
Not another negro stewardess
Something like that
Sky Martin buns over by the way the classroom
He says
Thinking back on it
That was an interesting thing
Because
Had that guy on the plane said that a few years earlier would have been like
Commonplace
Had he said it a few years later
It would have been intolerable the right then
It was neither
It was things were shifting
And he said
You know it was like this guy was shouting through an open window Between Worlds
That was his praise
Open window Between Worlds
Totally lodged in my head
And I've been thinking about that phrase a lot
This feeling that maybe the ground is Shifting beneath our feet not quite sure
And that's actually what brought us back to the show that feeling
Is each of the stories in this
Show
Kind of suggests that
Window Between Worlds
So what we going to do is as a redo the show after a couple of stores are going to check in real quick
Whether we feel like we passed
Through this window into a new world or whether we're still
Stuck in the Middle
You just you just heard Lulu Miller
I briefly in art and that last few minutes
She at the time with our producer now of course she is
Become Superstar host of invisibilia
Damn
To the show began with
A familiar voice
Remember this guy Roberts
Sapolsky
Robert sapolsky
We've had on the show couple times he's a neuroscientist spends most of the year at Stamper unilab
Rat scientist doing the real biology in the lab
In the Summers
How am I going to spend time in East Africa in the Serengeti studying while Bevins there
Why you but it was you working now
Season 2 this is interested in studying stress
Effects stress has on the body and turns out baboons
Are perfect
Source of data
Because
They're always under
You know the one thing we know about baboons on forever
Is it a fight baboons constantly not just metaphorically but literally have been V
Textbook example of a highly aggressive male-dominated hierarchical Society
Crosby's animals hunt because they live in these aggressive troops on the Savannah parentheses
Like we humans used to invest we evolve very similar like they have a constant Baseline level of aggression
Which inevitably spills over into their social life
Which is why he's
So what's supposed to be does basically he goes into the bush
Any watches
More than they are in a whole sale today. This is covered with these field notebook
Each one containing detailed notes
Who groom who and who's not getting along with who and who's messing around with who in the bushes
He tells the following story of a particular moment in his baboon watching
Which completely
Changed his life
James how he sees the world it happened about 30 years ago
Supposed to be the young guy just out of grad school
Settings first troop might
My first Baton Rouge
True. We love these rare animals I was very
Connected with
The most ways a pretty average group or basic
Baboon Troop
The females were highly affiliated with each other
They had a very stable ranking system the males meanwhile
Highly aggressive dumping on each other cuz that's just what males do
Right
Okay mid-80s
A big boom in tourism in Kenya of Wonders for the economy lot Sanu lodges lot to Lodge expansions
And there happened to be the next territory over the tourist Lodge in this one particular Lodge
She says he's gotten really big
Really fast
And during the time the lodge greatly expanded their garbage dumped me they stated they just dug a hole out behind the
A large when you stay a tractor came out
With the leftovers and dumped it there
So we're talking about here if you can easily imagine is he big steaming pile of
Trash half-eaten Food baking in the Sun
Smell wafting in the breeze
From miles and miles and into the nostrils of baboons everywhere
So
It was not long before a troop of baboons
Possible
When your boss covered the garbage and just order cheating on it
I hear there are eating leftover
Desert Sun
Chicken whatever is done
Dumb full of
Food must be to a baboon like
Like wandering into
Manna in the wilderness
So this troop almost immediately shifted their entire Behavior
2 they just slept in the trees above the garbage dump and instead of getting up at 6 in the morning to start forging
Are they would waddle down around
2 minutes of mine and the tractor would show up at 9 and dump the food and they would have
20 minutes of sheer Frenzy
And then they go back to sort of being couch potatoes
And this is how it went for a while
So they're over there
Living off of garbage
And
Somehow some of the males in my troop figure this out
Ismael's think
We got to get in on this
We got to go over there
And take their food what emerged was each morning a bunch of males would run a kilometer or so
The garbage dump in fight their way in
So every morning there be a showdown
I'm basically yeah they would come back with canine slashes and stuff like that and fat but also have
Drumsticks
Cakes
Hamburgers
This ritual
Accessible C1 on for year and then
You years into it
I got word that there were a couple of baboons in this garbage dump Troop
That looked awful and something was wrong with him these guys from Elijah called him and said hey you better get down here and look at this and
When you got there
What he saw
Was horrible animals with rotting hands walking on their elbows
So
Trying to figure out what this is about get veterinarians involved when we finally figure out is tuberculosis
Infected meat have been thrown in the dump and then eaten by the baboons
And this is really bad news
Because well tuberculosis in people
Is it really slow moving disease he be kills non-human primates in weeks
And it's a nightmare of a disease
For them in just a short time
The garbage dump Troop
Was completely decimate
Not to mention the tough guys in sapolsky
The ones that have gone to the dump every morning
They got two of the same kind of rotting hands and they all died
That must have been really
Kind of tragic
Not
Good. For me
These were my animals
Grown up with these guys
But yeah while sapolsky was heartbroke
Now that half
The alpha male
Super Dad
He didn't notice
Strange things start to happen
Change is harder than well grooming spiked and I sit on a branch and I take
Please out of here
Be as well either usually when a female Grooms of a male the male is never received
But suddenly they were
Even weirder you saw a adult male sitting in contact with each other and grooming each other
It helped how rare that is
Be like it from something in the middle of round 5 of a heavyweight bout
Mike Tyson just decided to stop boxing and Evander Holyfield hair
If you were babbling all legit it would have been less shocking if these guys had wings
Door were photosynthetic or something up to then I've seen like 30 seconds of male male grooming the corset
15 years but at the time supposed to be kind of wrote it off this is just some freak event wasn't going to last
Sookie actually stop studying
Non natural event removing half the study subjects
Scientist became less interesting to you know that was the rationale it was just too painful to go on walks
These guys
So I moved to the other end of the reserve
Like 40 miles away and started with a new troop there are an for 6 years I would not go anywhere near the corner of the power
Park is I just
Be there
Fast forward
6 years
We come to the MoMA
That really change things
Strand really flipped him into a different way
And it happened
Kind of bags
It's about 6 years later out there
For the first time with
Who was destined to become my wife and
Decided I wanted a kind of show her where
I am grown-up what part of the part I'm going to go to the old haunt yeah basically she went there
And the truth was there and they were acting pretty much the same as before lots of grooming not so much fighting isn't that
Nice and they're still like this great Remnant true
Just pointing out all the different baboons are there
Steven
Whoever
And then it
Hixson
Houston or whatever
There was only one male left
We've been there at the time of the TB outbreak
One meal
Stick with me for just one second and you will go
The thing about male baboons
Christian artists
Hands around puberty
The Mills get a little ants
I get itchy
They're bored and they just pick up and leave
So in a troop any of the adult males grew up someplace else which meant these new guys at work
We're coming into
Sapolsky Stroup
Coming in from the outside from the old world order jerky real dog-eat-dog world out there
What's he got to figure these new mails are coming in
Withhold expectations that they're going to have to kick ass
To be respected which would mean
This whole Kumbaya
Situation should
Evaporate
The moment these guys show up
But it didn't
It's stuck
Oh my God
The new guys are learning we don't do stuff like that here
You guys are learning a new way will that means the old way the violent way
Isn't the only way
This this lured me was one of those moments
Will be one of the three or four that sign for once in my life
The key question was how do these guys unlearn their entire
Fire childhood culture of aggression blah blah and somehow learned we don't do
Stuff like that around here
Wow
Well what will how do they unlearn something that was supposedly built in oh
Midas Moline
But but here's
Sapolsky
Ears
And this is really going may have to do
With that
Precarious moment when the new guy comes
Now normally what happens in this order status quo
Is it the new guy arrives and it's
That really bad
It's awful
Can you look at them and eat just identify with
Like freshman year of college or something
They're completely peripheral every male whose higher-ranking dumps on them
Baboon is completely ignored by the lady who just sit there
Somebody groom him my God I went to sophomore year until
Somebody groom him come on
Why don't they
Cuz they did some adult male would have attacked them hopetown ladies hang back while he's out there biting and
Incline and trying to scratch his way and we've got here
Is a cycle that is a good tip for a long long time
But if you make one small change just remove the alpha male take him out of the equation
Suddenly the females are more relaxed and more likely to take a social gamble of reaching out to some
Somebody new the key thing is the females
Early enough everything's different remarkable in your typical true
3 months on the average before the first female rooms in this true
6 days
Can I out 6 days a week
Compared to 3 month
Yeah and a world in which from day one as an adolescent male you're treated better
Something about the aggressiveness melts away
The thing though is Jabba.
Before we get too carried away would you have to ask
The question just how permanent is
Change is
As nice as it is so I explain this whole story that you just told
To a professor at Harvard named Richard wrangham
Brother innov-is hear music evolutionary biologist
Annie's chips
Particularly
But you have to know okay you heard the story about the baboons
What do you think
You'll know it's a nice example of the
Potential for some change
Actually we should put on resume
Let you know lots of balloons have been started across town
And this sort of example is never been found in a natural
Context
But I just happened to put a garbage dump
Text to have humans provide food the
Leads to
Several mail.
That means that I could imagine going on a helicopter all over Africa shooting all the alpha males
I've been giving all the ladies at
A chance to
Create a different baboon culture and me when I guess I'm wondering is do you think
An absurd situation like that the baboonery might change it
Its essential nature
I don't think it'll change it to sensual nature I can see that that can be
A cultural influence
That may lost a little bit of time
But the larger info
Clearly is the session of
A genes that produce a particular kind of brain
A baboon is basically a baboon until you get some kind of
Genetic China
That is
Something good
Supposed to
So Professor running
A genetic change
To make sure that this is really real permanent and here's the thing
I know this constitutes a genetic change but it has been 20
Years
Real yes
20 years in sapolsky original baboon troop is
Still
Operating in this
Even though dozens of new mail
Elsa come and go
Any idea
Something that was
Miso
Unchanged
Could change
And change quickly
And then State change
As a result of something so
Arie and undefinable is culture will that
It's caused Robert sapolsky
Dare I say it
Absolutely understand
Something that I Do by
By Nature
No not at all if you think this syllable
Decided
To send it to Foreign Affairs magazine
The magazine read by a lot of politicians
Still
They went for it
And so we had to ask him after it was published
Did anyone
Write you back
No basically not
I basically heard nothing from anyone now
Yes big yawning silence
III
I'm sure George Bush and Cheney
Rita teach evening and tremble at his implication
No basically as far as I can tell it was a huge waste of time for me to write it
Well we're at it
My mother didn't even
Alright so
7 years
Past as we've mentioned and so we say
Decided that it was only right for us.
The catch up with rabbits
Hello hello
You know we're trying to close a window here to
Increasing noise
We found him in a very odd place
Actually a for a Baboons
Play this in the library of the middle school with
A bunch of kids outside
How did that happen cuz wife now directs the musical theater Productions
So
Somehow I'm playing piano is rehearsal pianist at this
School with the musical
We are doing Oliver this year
Really
I just had nothing to do with me or queso
Anyway so
I told Robert that we talked to Richard wrangham reminded him
Ryan says no no baboons are hardwired to be a certain way in
And circumstances never going to change them in
Yep
He and I are
This isn't the first time we've
Disagreed
And I think we probably had a we shall see sort of finish
So what what have we seen since you guys talked about what's been happening yeah what's been happening as well they were
A few possibilities
There's
One scenario where
It could have turned into exactly what was
Being predicted there which was that the
Troopers go back to you
Being a
Typical highly aggressive baboon Troop
The other possibility is the one that I was always like
Dreaming of
Which is
So you're a
Kid who's grown up in that
True band you
Grown up on the Communists are and
Along Comes puberty and it's time for you to
To pick up and you move to a different route
And what happens when the kids who grew up in this baboon culture
Switch to other Troop
Not supposed to eat miss it if just one baboon from the nice if you went off to join the menes Heap
Probably get his ass kicked but he thinks
How did you get to nice
Balloons together
Make a little bit of a team
Arabic language
Critical mass of niceness
I just might
Red
And turn all the other guys nice
In principle this
Like great unique
Pacific culture in these baboons
Could be transmissible
Who in Siri
Okay well don't leave us hanging I got what
Has happy
Okay so what actually happened is pretty
Damn Grimm
Did they did they go back to being mean
In substance is really worse than that number how this whole thing begins because there's a troop next to sapolsky
I may be eating garbage
In a garbage dump
Eventually sapolsky
But now the garbage dump is open and available
They went over there and began looking at the tourist Lodge
And just living off of garbage now they just
With the garbage
And essentially
Stopped functioning as a coherent truth
So this question will they all become nice baboons eventually or will they all revert back to
To being mean baboon
That. Totally trumped by
The garbage
There was so much food.
Need for these baboons
Hakeem so free and so available that the natural business of baboonery
Just broke down
Lot of males around that being killed by game Park Rangers there because
As per usual with a sort of thing they got dangerous to the humans
There because
They got to habituate
The humans
So lots of males were killed
The rest of the troupe is
Defragment it so
I never
Got to find out what
What happened in the long run
Cuz the garbage got in the way again
Yep
Exactly that's simulator I've seen you at
What's the troubling thing here for me is that how you know there was
Traditional baboon culture which was
Violin hierarchy
Call there was this
Hint of a hope
Have a different
Baboon culture which was
Grooming and happiness
And we had a question about which one of those two would spread or
Last
But the truth is they ran into some junk food and then they have no culture
Exactly what I had to say it that sounds depressingly like America
Yeah
Unders
Bunches of them still there I'm sure as we speak actually not as we speak but
10 hours from now to philby
Waddling / 2
Get some leftovers they're probably not missing the culture that they had but
Yeah those were my guys
I had my last season out there for years ago and haven't been back since
To quote a
We would do anything
For you any
Where is daffodil
So you just so you know
View all I will
Okay
Oh God
Just managed to get that stupid song out of my head rehearsal earlier today thanks a lot
Aware
My name is Julie Rogers and I'm calling from a nice walk on the streets of Oakland
Radiolab supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation enhancing public understanding of science
Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloan at www.starone.org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
We're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments
Brilliance
Basically I want to hear about this
Times when a kid you know did something
It just means you lean back and say
Well
How did they do that
Maybe it was the moment that I
Kids started reading back
Do you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lesson
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of their musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed they're writing music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the small specific moments where a kid does something super smart
It doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story
T-shirt
Go to radiolab.org
Brilliance
And record a short Audiomack
And that's where you live. Org / brilliance
Thank you so much
Hey I'm Jared Broadway rubber chromatids Radiolab topic today
Choice and human destiny
With a way we are is that the way we're going to stay
A very nicely but here in the last section we were talking about a baboon and their propensity to Sirius
Maybe or maybe not we don't
Really no
Blitz which R8 will go to Oregonian or just a rare subset of human being
Set up we were thinking a lot about
Small groups
On the show
Yeah cuz that's what we are we are small group primates
The phrase sometimes used to describe humans
And it's a phrase
Carry some negative connotation
As involved in these small groups that we are predisposed to be small-minded no
Small is not always a bad thing
I tell you story now this
The small groups
Story it's just as a warning
Contains graphic
But
We hope you'll stick with it cuz it's a really cool story takes place in a small town
You can dial the wrong number and still have a conversation
So tell me where we are in end
Downtown Silverton
Essentially our downtown is not changed since the
Late 40s early 50s
But we'll get to that this is Stu Rasmussen either main character
A little while back still gave myself and producer Aaron Scott
A tour movie theater on the corner of the old hardware store on this corner
This builder of his favorite place on Earth
Silverton Oregon Roots about 40 miles from Portland
Top 40 years for Portland actually you know it's the town I grew up in
My image for what I want silver going to be no I rode my bicycle down the street and came to the hardware store tea
How are you and wave all the time it's a small town everybody knows me
Ifrit
Stu
This time would never change
You would stay frozen in that quaint
Norman Rockwell candy-coated image
I'm his boy had the weird thing though
Is it that image in his head
Would probably never have included a guy likes
At least do as he is now
Is it is a show about change here is a story
Funny pretty radical bit change
You wouldn't expect
Speaking of which can you describe where we are and what we're looking at
What were standing in front of the Palace Theater on the corner of Oakland Water Street Has Gone With the Wind theaters with a Big Mac
Marquis in the bulb lights
And everything built in 1935 and in continuous operation ever since
Staples out some keys and opened it up
He suggested that we do the interview here in the town's only theater even smells like a Gilded Age
Theater at 1 p.m. still smelled like popcorn from the previous night
And was filled with nothing
200 Mt read
Velvet seats in a small town theater
Beautiful
Lights off
Okay see you later okay thank you
Best seats in the house right in the middle
Pretend We're watching a movie of your life
Hilarious adult movie
Hardly
So the movie of Stew begins
In 1975
He said theater just like that seminal moment in my life
Who's won The Rocky Horror Picture Show came out stew is in the projects
That's a Java changing the rails and at some point
During one of the musical numbers
Glances at the screen and
It was like
What was what was the oh here was this movie
With a guy
In Drag
On screen
Sweet Transvestite
Transexual Transylvania
What's a word that I've never heard
I watch that again and again
Fast forward 10 years to now owns the theater just like his dad before him
He's an upstanding member of the town
Silverton city council then on the library board
Then
He starts to
Transform everyone will tell you
It began with an a
I think I probably started having my nails done in 94-95
And started out with very masculine nails without polishing
Square and then
Slowly grew them out that I went into what I considered a masculine nail color of blue
Gradually
Start to paint them red
Acrylic tips
Got longer and longer this was the first test
The community
How are you
Cuz I would be at the theater taking tickets
Be dressed as usual and plaid shirt jeans and boots and would come out
For their ticket
What in the hell are those
You can't miss any know you had a lost fingernail long-time Silvertown in
I had to give him my ticket to sell though she 17 and he ripped it and like his nails like
Went down the palm of my hand and just gave me the chills nails were the first thing
El Palmar veterinarian
And city council
Born and raised turn silver
Hoquiam definitely talk
But it happened so gradually to something you hear again and again it happened
Graduate
First it was
The nails and
And then
At some point in time he changed the focus of the movie theater and was really making a game attempt to get new release
Lisa's
Frequently you know when there was a theme kind of movie
He would get in the costume my name is Ken Ham
Former mayor of that sort
And very often the costume would be female attire Step 2
Upstairs very careful transition coordinator when we spoke with four years
After the nails he would
Quote promote that week's movie
By dressing up for one of the new Star Wars movies was out and it wasn't a coincidence you've dressed as Queen
Family Dollar
I love you
There was a movie called that My Big Fat Greek Wedding
Also a lifelong silvertone Ian
The complete with the veil. Of course got everybody
Will put it together with
Is it on the web
She's a registered nurse sexuality
Transgender or any of those things I think we thought it was just dressing up to go along with his with his movies
There was
Clearly a let's go by the movie theater tonight cuz we've got to know what
Stu's wearing you pursue this was just the beginning of something he was
He wasn't just Clowning Around when did your
Ginger complexities begin
Probably 14 or 15
I think I was a shy young man
And interfacing with girls my mother was a bit
Strange on on that in the
Girls were evil and they would
No girl was good enough for her son and
Data data.
That's how we did it all
Not until I was out of high school
Two girls were kind of scary it sounds all girls are scary
Yeah
Well everybody else went on dates
He says he would
Build computers
Scratch
And even today
Is basement you'll find an entire electrical shop my God fun stuff
RF generator Spectrum analyzer logic analyzer
Who said the best that he can
Explain himself
Genuine
Just say that when he looks in the mirror he likes himself better
Distressed
To the woman I don't know how to describe it
I can understand it I mean some people like to dress up and look like a cowboy or
Lumberjack whatever
What's your mental image of yourself that you look in the mirror and you like
Set after Nails after a
Dozens of episodes of social example cross-dressing took the next step
Begin to perform some experiments like he would go to The LumberYard
Just to get some stuff to nails or something all the while he would be wearing a padded bra under his flannel shirt
Just to see what would happen to this tree was like a test it was like a calculated test
To absolute age if it was possible
If I could survive
With breast
So when he was 52 he drove into Portland visited
The doctor put him to sleep
The doctors made two small incisions one under each breast about an inch and a half or 2in
Long and they pulled back the skin on each side slit in an uninflated balloon and then pump it up with water until
The skin was stretched to the point that
Was almost transparent
That sounds very painful
Was it
Well
I was asleep at the time
But when he woke up
He was a different man
Because he now had several pounds of new stuff
Hanging off his chest
Who is singing at that moment
I was thinking
What have I
Done
There's no going back I can remember being in
Mac's Place downtown at a table and
He was coming across the street with his breath
Prominently showing and it was the first time any of us realized that he had actually had surgery
And when lady was going
Look like any other lady was going to look across the street and oh my God
Look it's to my God what is he doing
There was a buzz around the situation when he walked by and then return
Ensue
Yes
Basically this is Victorious age
Stew's longtime girlfriend
Living together for 36 years
Be walking in our local Goodwill in would be a few miles away from each other and
I would hear
Like he had changed
Somehow
It's just trying to
Fulfill that body image he's got in his head
West York
Body image
Mate
As I've been difficult
No
No I'm sorry it if you if you want to get kinky about it
A man with
Chronicle
Okay
Did the
Was there ever any
Concern
There was for me not so much force to I think
Partly because he didn't hear as many Whispers as I felt I did
But
I was concerned for the theater business
Not without reason
A lot of kids in the town stop coming to the theater cuz their parents wouldn't let him take his health to go ahead and
Wasn't long before pickup trucks full of teenage boys with drive-by the theater yelling slurs
Well yeah I guess
I guess
Fagedes
Fleur I guess so you get to this point in the
Sped up movie narrative UPS to this point right here we're even
Though he took it so slowly
So careful
It's still
Easy to imagine things turning ugly I don't know what was that movie about the boy that was Beno draw
Dragon Beat to Death because he was gay in a small town in the midwest you know what a voice.
According to Linda Webb silverton's not so different from Laramie Wyoming where Matthew Shepard lived it's a small town
Very traditional very conservative
To expect the worst but here's the surprise
And the whole reason we came here so rude
Monday January
The worst did not happen
It was no redneck rebellion in fact the opposite happened
Something historic
I
High on January 5th 2009 the town of Silverton elected stew
Mayor of the city of Silverton Marion County Oregon congratulations
Silverton has a length of a nation's first openly transgender mayor directions first openly
Transgender man
Transgender in heels
Speaking of the sound of
Stew's 4 inch heels pounding on linoleum
Is he goes to city council meeting
O'Hara
Couldn't be better how are you
Nicole Wallace
You know
City elitist or whatever but I met her in a plunging v-neck sweater and a black mini skirt
Not what you would expect
A tiny Conservative Republican town
So we want to know
Your why did this happen
Co-producer Aaron Scott and I walked around town for a couple days
And we interviewed dozens of people including
Guy named Ken Hector
Beat out from there
He's a Conservative Republican definitely not one of those big fans
It was just a difference in philosophy about
I don't want to sound pretentious but you know as a mayor I think they're certain extra
Haitians
About professionalism of that
You should exhibit
He would come in
Where at
Appetite
Cleaning copper
Cleavage down to here
You're almost point of your belly button
Come on you know when you're at the council meeting show some dignity here and just
Dress
In the appropriate attire for the occasion
Can even try to get the city council to impose a dress code
But when we asked him you know are you surprised
The town has
Embraced
And even got so far to elect a mayor
He said
No news of Rarity in that you know there's a lot of people in this town
Extremely religious
Very conservative people
Word a stranger
Who came into town suddenly I'm sure the support and perception might have been different but you're talking about a Native Son
Who grew up
He said
Who runs the only theater in town so he's out there every weekend standing out from the Palace Theater
Taking tickets to everybody knows
Back in the day we used to be the Cable Guy
Play home is still the guy you call here
Your computer so it might sound strange to you but it's
And that is when it hit me
Actually
Under the right circumstances
Small town could be like the most
Progressive place on Earth
And it's exactly because everyone's all up in your grill
You are forced to know people
Like stew
Oh my goodness
I grew up with stew
Amy I remember when stool is like an altar boy at the church as my brother
This is Susie team
Retired teacher his parents and my parents
Like a lot of folks and silver 10 she is known stew for so long and so many different contexts
But you can't do that New York thing with him where you like you see someone on the sidewalk and you size them up instantly and thinking
Now after he's way too complicated
Note to her he's do the Altar Boys do the computer geek
City councilman sue the mayor or just
Do whatever
Go on about your business at the people we talked to
Effects of the same folks who said
Yes just do
You are still not happy about the
The situation no I mean
I don't think God's a crossdresser
The other felt it was morally wrong
As in the case of this Menace
Genesis 1
27 says so God created man in his own image
In the a.m. or some folks like Linda Webb husband John
Just felt like he takes it way too far right there it's in your face
He dresses kind of like a streetwalker
You feel that that's confrontational baidu
The most of the people who had objections it was a little more nuanced
It went something like this
Well I buy personally did not vote for him for mayor because I didn't feel it was
Good idea to
Have someone
That look
Like that representing us but on the other hand
He is a good man and he's got this town at heart
Another rights according to John but really isn't stew
Where the town
It's the outside
All those people out there who are going to hear about
And then judged
Which is what makes November 25th 2008
Such an interesting day
Stupid just been elected mayor
Squeaked It Out by about 400 votes
But he hadn't yet been sworn in
When a group of Christian extremist from Kansas showed up and down and started marching up and down Main Street
Yelling at the
And at one point that you can unfrozen American flag put it on the ground
And stepped on it
Just to show how expensive it sounds good
Cuz they
Will not by any means warn him about to send this taking him to hell
So unpleasant and then bringing up signs that say things like God hates over tank God hate
It's your man. Hates f*** your pastor is a hore
The opposite sex from the town decided to start a counter protest
Stood
Across the street from these people by and large
Just a few guys
No earlier someone it suggests all the guys out to dress up as girls and all the girls I did dress up these guys and gassy Davidson
Said his initial reaction was
Yeah right
Very was
Address
He said that at first he in the two or three other guys who had on women's clothing
Felt a little weird
But then
People just started coming and was just amazed
Amazing of a couple of hundred people I mean men dress like women who dress like men some of the people that I sat down there
What's surprising
Because I had labeled them in my head as conservative people drive by
People signs got love sort of God loves to with costumes the town
Really lie about your gut getting bigger and bigger thinking that moment
Understand you were standing off to the side just watching
What's going through your mind
Yeah well honestly I tried to discourage people from even giving them the time of day saying
Don't give him any attention
I couldn't
Get that.
They were so angry
They they came out
200 people
Minute dresses
Grandmother's babies
It's just amazing
That was the town that wasn't me
Sorry I guess
Emotional
That must have been a turning point for you
The biggest one
Frost Aaron Scott who did a huge chunk of the reporting for that piece and co-produced it with me
We'll be right back
Okay so that story with we did that about
7 years ago
The world is different
Like what
Regards to transgender
The language we use
Change it back then we said transgendered
And now we would
Transgender
But with Caitlyn Jenner in the news and all the stuff we
Stadt
Wondered like
How have things changed for stew in these left
6-7 years
So hello
We decided to send producer reporter Erin Scott
Back to Silver
Sit down with Stu EyeMasters partner Victoria
Just to catch up
I mean it's been 7 years
Since I will be going on seven years six years
Since we were in the store the first time
Going on in your world
Well since the election that's
So the first thing you told me was that he got re-elected after 2 years and then he was re-elected again
And then
Actress
6 years of marriage
You know out of the game hello you
I have truly enjoying my vacation
I need to tell me the back when the story first aired things did get
Kinda nutty
Well you know it's probably the most unusual phone call we've ever received Victoria net worth
Sitting at home the phone rang and it was a fellow
From New York City who said I was bicycling in on Manhattan
Listening to the original Radio Lab piece
And
He thought it would be really fun to do my life story as a musical
But I know it's a big deal
Any dip
That fella was Andrew Russell he put on a big production up in Seattle it got standing ovation
The most
Surreal and bizarre
Experience in my life sitting in an auditorium with 400 strangers watching as
In song and dance
My life goes by
You can call me
And she can call me
Can call me
You can call me
Can call me she went
So there is this musical which seemed to do pretty well and then
A movie producer called them up and said that
You wanted to options to his wife for a movie
And now Victoria says those Whispers that they used to get
Those have turned into people wanting
Autograph
We're stopping them in the shoe store and saying you stew
Are true that beer can I get a picture with you
What's sure
Really
What's the big deal
But one of the most interesting things for me was that a lot of that attention was at the beginning
These states two sides
You know he's transgender issues him
Grown in in the national news
The ad on TV shows
Deuces the
Back in Silverton
Cities transgender
Becoming pretty much passe
So
Here we are
You says it's just kind of routine now
For him and everyone else
Except he did say there's this one thing
Every time the story are their rears which it does from time to time
When it when it goes
The phone starts ringing a week
Tell where it's from he says he gets these calls from people who are struggling with their own gender issues
We're trying to figure out how to come out to their family
And people actually call your home phone usually anonymously they won't identify themselves necessarily because they're still
He'll either closeted or not really ready to come out there saying
Thank you so much for being yourself
And for telling your story to other so that I can
You know I can validate my life from that thank you
Does that ever get old
No
For somebody who was in the position that I wasn't made the change and then to have other people
Either following along or
Emulating in one way or another
Is very gratifying because it validates my life and it says why you weren't a complete waste of time
A lot more than a lot of people get
Special thanks to producer Eddie McEwen for helping us and all the update
Hey this is Tracy
Changsha Hunan China
The lab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology
Party in the modern world
More information about slowing
Www. Sloan
Are we about to do thoughts
Okay
Hey I'm driving right by Robert krulwich Radiolab and today we're talking about
Change really what what looks like
So you remember back to the booze when we started this
Program
The question were asking then was Will those baboons
If they do enough Generations will they create a new color lipstick looks.
What's up let's hope we don't know whole milk and the town that uses a mayor is that town expanding the sense of
Possibility or stop lower blood pressure
Now let's get really serious there are indeed
Changes that deuce
Stick
We're going to examine a rather startling example of it right now
But you do that we need an evolutionary biologist and we found one at Duke University
Yeah hello who's this that's Brian hair
And the first thing Brian your did was tell me about another guy
I have was a very famous geneticist in Russia
He was alive during World War II and doing genetic
Lights work but after World War II
He was a little spot of trouble
But what you do well because he was a real darwinian he believed in evolution and genetics
But thinking about Evolution like a darwinian evolution is does
That was not popular in Stalin's Russia is popular the word or was that a death sentence it was a distance
So
The writing was on the wall
Any new that he should probably take the Trans-Siberian railroad
From Moscow quickly
Quickly
And he went to
Nova De Beers
And the way that Dimitri blab decided to hide his continued in
Starting darwinian Evolution was
He would begin a fox
Farm where he would make
Fur coats
So what is Mr Bean live actually doing what
Dr. balaya was actually interest
Was to understand
How does domestication happen
That's a question that's a dumb question or select them question in all because you just going to bring that note I think about a wild ant
It is impulsive
It is aggressive it growl
What is it a wolf or you're playing a wolf that I've got there
This is
A domesticated
The nature the animal has completely changed here and if you want to learn something about the nature of a creature how it can change
Domesticate animals are wonderful place to start
Supplier
He decided why did I just
Experimental domesticate semana
And his cover was that he was going to make better for a cup
When was the 1959
Kiss a Sputnik was up Russians were feeling good and he was making fur coats so to speak
So to speak began one of the most
Exciting experiments in biology
Things with Demetri but life does he goes to a bunch of fox Pharmacy to look at I want to buy
A bunch
Foxes and he says we'll all I got to do is take this group of foxes and break him in the shoe
And one group
I'm not going to change them in any way
Okay so it's like a controller
So when we was just normal Fox normal
But the other line
I'm going to decide who is going to be allowed to breed
And who is
Unfortunately
It going to be a haircut
Some of the factors get to have
Puppy foxes
Of their own and some foxes become
So what are you doing
Marvelously
You go or what
Roach in
Where the fox
Beautiful baby
Author of a juvenile
The experimenter would stay
Stand say a foot away
And we just try to touch
The fox
Hi
Run Fox Run
If the fox would make
This kind of sound
And sort of cower in the corner like
Most boxing
Would do
What is that what the sound is the sound a Fox Makes
So what happens if I make that sound
They did not breathe at Fox in the Next Generation board put it another way
Pretty much
That's just wrong but now
Every so often like maybe one out of every 20 foxes there would be a fox
It would not
Would not
It wasn't afraid then
Then they would
Shoes that fart
Read in the Next Generation
Let me get this over and over again
Generation after generation they would breed the nice boxes together get rid of a bad foxes breed the neck
Except get rid of a bad foxes read the next set next set next set neck
Next
What happened in the end eventually if they had foxes that were attracted to humans no job how long do you think
It would take to get boxes
For being wild ferocious animals
Tubing animals to would lick your face after this kind of like a how many year Exterminating
Reading Eggs
A long long time I mean I would garlic
Like how many years how many years how many
Well it took wolves like thousands of years income dogs
Diamond almond long time well here's this here's the thing
10 years ago
Don't tell me to shut up
Crazy what was
Exciting and surprising
Was that
The same foxes they actually show a whole Suite of changes that he did not select for on Purp
I like what do you mean physical change
These foxes as they became more gentle
For some unaccountable reason
Their ears
Instead of pointing straight up
Flip over that's right it was a big accident that they now have floppy ears the tail
Now they have curly tails
They have multi colored coats that are no longer just grape tips of their paws
Color the teeth
Get smaller and their bones became very thin their bones got the yes
What happens to the skull and the face is it actually becomes more feminine
Dead Sea
I don't know what to make of that
And it's not over this experiment has been going on at 7:50 years 45000 foxes
Later who is read about this is that I got to see this for myself so he went to a
Xenoverse 2 beerus
Just to check it out I did I took the Trans-Siberian railroad which you know
2 days of looking at green grass
And there's like one species of tree
And I think there was a butterfly that was kind of pretty
I was at birch trees you look at Bridge Street and mother Bridge Street and Liberty Street and pretty much
You got it you got it
So I show up and they had
Thousands
A foxes
Giant buildings that are probably you know as long as a football for
Full of
Just rows and rows
Of fox
And when you see them they actually wag their tail they whine like a puppy dog
They're cute and cuddly and they love people and they don't bite
Sounds perfect
Except
For the one thing I forgot to tell you
Is that when they're yapping
Beside the sea
They cannot help but pee for joy
Makes sense to me that they're getting nicer
Is there breeding them to get nice
Why is all this other stuff happening with their to their body
What's going on
Well you know
The unsatisfactory answer that problem
Nobody really
Knows why
Why am I in this is to synchronize
Sync
Evolutionary biologist at the University of st. Andrews in sky
And he has
Inotia
This is just a hypothesis
Here's what he told me
Did you guys go back to when a fox has a very very little
Inside its mother's womb very very very early embryo
Like two months
How to become a fox
Who can survive in the world this d'olimpio need
Strong
Pastor gropher you defer
Bone strong I don't need to go all these things that you
Need as an adult
All of them come from the same fountain
The population of cells in an embryo
Wow I didn't know that
Called mural
When the fox grows in the south
Sir goony's epic migrations these guys are like
Pioneers
Moving throughout the body and blazing Trails some of them go out into the skin some of them
Happened to the cartilage of the Fox's beard
All these different issues tell big parts of the nervous system
Major parts of the brain and the adrenal glands
What's a real man that's the most important one for our
The adrenal gland
I'm sad
When
To be afraid
If you against a well that's something that makes
Whatever that sounds like it's the one that makes that sound when your breeding
Hear out of an animal
Maybe what you doing
Is your slowing down
The migrations of these cells
They don't deliver the fear
If you don't deliver all the other things that they use
What you're focusing on what you as the experimenter doing
I want the guys who's adrenal glands
That might have the function of making the animal more team but what you're doing is a by-product
The bat is selecting for guys who don't get as many of those cells into their ears and don't get as many of
So if you get some of the cells you need
How to make your ears
Pyramids
Straight but not quite enough
And your ear will go up to a certain point
I think the sales are going to complete the deal the rest of your ear
Flops over
Really you haven't come is that why dogs have little sloppy joe
Slow down to the point where they don't
Finish the job they were still there are literally arrested the argument is that
When you select against aggression in animals
You're changing the time in the rate of development such that
The experimental foxes are actually
Frozen as juveniles
They actually never really grow up
So then to domesticate a fox
Just like to domesticate a wolf and you can talk what you doing
Is you making permanent puppies
Peter Pan kind of things
So if we wanted to apply the store to us
And we wanted to say breed a gentler
Bleeker human being
We should just
Kill the football players is that the idea
Like with the foxes you just eliminate the meeting with the same thing happened to us
Really
Remember to eat professionally interview.
I was back a Richard wrangham vividly
Movie think about humans obviously we're getting are just super specs
But he says if you choose to
Go back if we go back
Just 30000 50000 years
And you look at the collection of
Goals
The early versions of Ostrom way back
I think you see some interest
Like changes
If you look at a domesticated animal
They have smaller teeth
That want to dance
And in humans we've been getting smaller teeth
Over
The last few tens of thousands of years
Like the Box we've been getting more gracile bones that means to say that
Particular length of limbo and it becomes a little bit narrower
Just like the
So it is tempting to think
That
The same kind of process
What's been going on in humans as a pink eye going into my
Animals which is that
There's meaning
Selection
In favor of
Kinder gentler human
Wait a second. Who's doing the selecting in the case of the foxes
Mitsubishi LF shot you if you were
Too aggressive
Who's selecting the who's domesticating the humans
Is that it was the
A growing tendency for
Hunter-gatherer ancestors
Settle down
In the
Instable
You mean like summer camps
Sing songs about communities but if you are in a very small family group
Well then it pays to be big and strong and mean because of you are the biggest guy and you meet a smaller guy and he's got some potato you
Grab him eat his potatoes beat him up and then move on to the next till you never have to see him again
But let's say
It is time passes Human Society grows on
We might have 30 or 40 people
That way you can build bigger fires and you can catch more bunnies and you can defend against enemies
But in this world if you beat everybody up
You may not survive that when pitted against anybody else
One on one
The big strong pink eye is a win-win big strong mean doesn't
And we see this in summer
When you can start to form coalition
When you can start that multiple in
She say a mean guy stop it
What you can't take on
Both of us or all three of us or our whole group
Go away we're going to deal with this guy
Maybe they deal with him by shouting and Darna ostracizing him or even capital punishment
Richard wrangham theory is
Who they can't have kids to spread their genes because they have the unfortunate condition of being dead then we've essentially bread
The more aggressive genes or
We have
Domestic
What we're really talking about groups versus individuals
And $0.07 I think we're really talking
Beginning of society
Rule of law
In the way that we think of
And this pressure
Be a little more gentle
Going to be a little bit more quiet
It hasn't gone away
If anything we're being select
To work together more
Took took
Be able to tolerate being packed in even tighter
What you put 20 chips on a Jet Plane
And try to send them across the Atlantic
Let me tell you that only one or two
We do this all the time we take it for granted
Is human beings.
Big groups of people can get along with one another I do think that is reasonable
Imagine that humans have a future of
Increasing
Self domestication what I sent you proposing
Is it as the Earth gets more crowded all the creatures on Earth are these dissension could you have to start learning to live with each other to the Marcos
Bumping into each other
The winners will be the domesticated wild everyone will get more empathetic to each other because that's the only way you survive
Let me get gentler
And gently and gentler tool am literally lie down
With lion
You said it Beauty
But I do believe it
Well we may have to go through water through ups and downs before we get there
And of course to something
Select the alarming about the fact that one possible mechanism by which domestication is Happy than humans
This through
Literally EX
Execution of
The more aggressive types
But in the long-term
Sure
Let's hope that
All of us become
More
Floppy ears
Moe's Lafayette
Exactly
We start working together album
Show me your teeth smile
Exist
The way we ended all video
Thorn wheeler Michael Raphael
Hornet moving
I need a ride
Imma take a bath and Elsa Chang special thanks to
Brian Harris father
Aaron Scott
Dr Anna Kournikova Dr Arena 5
Encrypt meaning