Are you awake
Listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
Hugo hi I'm Roberto which this is Radiolab it today with me is Simon Adler that to me
He's a reporter and producer here and he's got us a tail I do it's an American Tail and a kind of Timely
I think about you describe it. I think it's one of those classic Us Versus Them tails
Go back to maybe tonight
Versus Ice storage unit because I in fact it takes place
Right in America's Heartland
Where in the Heartland Nebraska
Seneca Nebraska
This tiny little town in Central West
Nebraska
Okay
It's near the town of Mullen Nebraska what you got
You know obviously also don't know this is Matthew Hanson
He is a reporter with the with the Omaha World-Herald and a couple months back you got in touch with us because
The story about this town right so
I I got an email from a woman who lives a couple miles outside of town she's really upset cuz back in 2014
The town was
Split in half
And in fact there was a group of people in the town who were circulating a petition
Petition
That would end the town
We circulate a petition to end the town do you want to be in town anymore
Right by law if you have
Enough signatures on a petition
You can get things on the ballot and the question that ended up on the ballot was should Seneca
Cease to exist
And it's split that a group of people to try to end their own town
It got us thinking about
Let's put that seem to be the selection right now and it occurred to us that maybe just maybe this tiny little town in
In the middle of Nebraska might have something to say about the rest of us
Let's back up there
When when did
All is well in Seneca until what
It started with the horses
Actually let me sit back there a lot of horses in Seneca
Most people in Seneca ride horses
Imini on them
But there were these six particular horses
Right in the middle of town
And
You know that the split
Sort of started
Right there so I got so curious about what went down in Seneca
That I flew to Denver one two three four five five and a half hours into the Sandhills of West
Central Nebraska. Let's see if we can get anything on the radio here rolling sand dune
Carpeting grass at the ranch catalog is another Ranch what's this Wednesday and smack dab in the middle of the Sandhills
Is Seneca after many hours and many miles we
We are here okay
So why
Cathy's Rolling Hills that are green. With these yellow flowers
Junction 86a Seneca okay with that kind of an old big red sign that says welcome
Seneca with a big
Okay and get there it looks like
Starting to drive through town a picture postcard
Small town from yesteryear found by railroad tracks
Direct got the railroad I'm taking a
I mean really pretty to my right
An abandoned house
To my left
Another boarded-up house
Another street with absolutely nothing on it no gas station all boarded up another rundown house
It says no trespassing
And just really tiny I think one into the other is
One eighth of a mile
And we're done
So there you go
At 30 miles per hour it takes
10 seconds
Okay turning around in
Wow okay
The house to the left here has a giant
Bored over one of the windows and spray-painted on it is
Sandy H is a big fat liar
Interesting
And so on
I ended up just walking through this Tiny Town of Seneca you're like knocking on every door guide I think I may have knocked on every single door
And of course I ended up talking to some folks wanted in the town others wanted to save it and and
Sprouts
She told her notes to me were
Come down hill
First house
Is nice
That's not me
Burnt up yard
I don't know if this is it
How are you this morning
This morning and now you're here in New York
City and how do you do it very good to meet you everyone told me I can't let you into my house
I don't have any other way.
And you want to plug in
No I'm good I am all set here all
Good tell me who else you're going to talk to
Larry Isen
Okay well
Jacquees
Okay
I'm the sanest
The person you're going to talk to today
You know that's what
The terrible thing to say
I'm sorry about the cigarettes
I want to get into more contemporary things are real quicker to set the stage
When did Seneca pop up on the map
Well
All I know is when I was a little kid it was a booming town
But I mean that great dances and wonderful bands
Send beer
And there was no place else
To go I mean Seneca used to be
Really
Find
But okay
Celebrity tell you the story
Some people had come and they bought a house in Seneca
Okay this would have been fine except the MLB this animal
Nobody knows these people
And there is a big fuss about them and their abuse of these animals
So sure these animals are being abused
I was under the impression that this was all about horses in her front yard is that true they had horses
They have six horses in their backyard
That's the yard
6 horses in the size of one car garage
Exactly
Get you what you remember the first time you saw the horses Here song
Yeah both at the same time Larry Isen
Former member of the Town board
I mean it's pretty hard to miss when you drink it down the street when there's
Six blocks to the town
You know that's it's easy to hear about face
You'll be on the list also tomorrow I really am I going to be in the probably all have
I'll have five phone calls by the time I get there
How did you decide that you were going to take this up as a cause as a member of the
Because of the complaints that were called to my house
What are you going to do about the horses
Is there they're up to their knees and excrement what are you going to do about
And so you pass an ordinance or yeah
And what what did the ordinance say
I don't remember it was two pages but but in any case it
Stipulated
Certain amount of square footage
Cohorst
As well as shelter
Well
That was
Part of it
The thing about Seneca has
There's always a war in Seneca
Again
Judith Brown
Okay
6 horses in the front yard where the most concrete thing
But
Larry Isom
And the bachelor going to go see
They have always wanted us to look more like
Cute little
Colorado tourist town
Where we talking like beautification like
Yes he wanted to create rules
To create growth
And I think they wanted to
To keep us lower class people in line
And so
They were out here
Telling us what to do
And they'll tell you things about me to the 60s
In New York you did lived in a calm you
Herb thyme and Brenda brain down
The satanic at 3
Lake Isom again
Nancy Ahmed wife
And here Jackie severe
So we don't want to defend we don't want to bicker though we don't want to open that up
The ordinances were were necessary because of the situation that we were presented with
There was no elitism
They weren't on that board to dictate to anybody on this town
They need to cover nuts for the horses.
Where you started and then
You had people that was trying to
Say you're not going to tell me
And if you look around a little town you'll see the ones that take pride in what they have
I'm sorry
So
The town was split into
I mean we could have liked each other
But we've had nothing but constant
Constance
Fighting
Hello okay she won't hurt you
Millie also wanted to save the town after last name not be used
This is excited
I mean I've heard so much about you and
I have to ask where did you hear about
Me from who avoid this is small town
I mean it just
All over
The telephones Are Ringing with my name
Okay I got to be nice right you're recording all this recording you don't have to be nice that you can
I'll be honest I have no use for those people
I didn't want them to take our time
How long have you lived inside
Oh
Guys about 30
37 years
And how many people live here
Right in town maybe
I don't know if even 22
End
We get talked about alot
I made Wichita
Put down a lot
Give me just a minute
Hi honey I
Do you have anything you want me to ask
Okay
I've been playing phone tag all day long they did people making fun of Seneca
They make fun of Seneca
Quite a bit
The outside
You know I'm like
Oh Seneca doesn't have anything what are you still doing here
And
It's not like it used to be
I mean years and years ago this just be at the neatest little town yet everyone live in
And then it just I don't know it just went
Downhill
I mean that
That's the only way you can say it
Cindy Hansen
Wanted save the town
Unofficial Town distorted
Started smacking
73 I believe it was
Stop being a division point
So the trains no longer stopped here
So that did away with the three hotels the 24-hour cafe
The man that had Filling Station pulled out in front of a semi at Mullen that ended that business
His brother had the shoe shop
And he died of a heart attack sitting there working on his shoes
The lady that had the variety store
Tripped on a kitten and broke her hip that close that and
Remind me to print
Anyhow
Seneca really start dying
Presley
Get away from there
What's so I guess I'm here because I'm trying to talk to as many people as I can
I understand what happened with the whole voting corporate
Again
Sabre Milly it started out that there was
6 horses
They were up in mud up to their probably belly
And I think
One of them had to be put down because it was
Kicked this is how close they were
Together anyway I mean I'm an animal lover
I wanted something done about it
7-Eleven
Instead so
We had a meeting
The board tried to tell him that's not sanitary we did this
Scusset you know we going to get the horses gone that's the purpose of the the ordinate but it was not just
Judith Brown and they wanted to get rid of all the horses all the cattle all the chickens that is
Ridiculous
Chappie chicken
But do you want your chickens do they run around town people are so afraid that their animals were going to be taken away
And then
Eventually
The board members forbid people to have animals
That was the gist of it
And so more and more and more the count.
There's a group of people here in a group of people here nobody gets along nobody on the
Town board with speak to anybody at which course then that just mad I just yell at him louder
Certain people that I just give hand gesture
I said things like my dog doesn't want to be friends with your dog it was awful
Terry bison
Can I have appointment to your time to talk and the town
Got ugly they started taking pictures of people's places and put it on Facebook and say how they
I didn't clean up their property and just public shaming people this was the same Seneca people that were posting
Supposedly you know there were aggressive comments that we did have the sheriff come up did anyone tell you
Are you that it was just out of control I mean Xanax you know I took a lot of
It was a very unhappy
Time and so finally people started going around with a petition
To get the onion corporation on the ballot we thought we will just unincorporate
Corporate unincorporate unincorporated our village
There are agitators in every group
Okay that's me that seems kind of like the nuclear option here right like we're just going to blow the whole thing up
Oh yes absolutely
I think that
Sense of shared community
Was just slowly dissolving
Year-by-year
Again Matthew Henson of the Omaha World-Herald
And it didn't have it had probably to do with what was happening Seneca but I also believe that I had to do was happen in the United States
Sort of the idea that
Winning the argument
It is more important
Then
The much harder job
Of coming together and say okay we disagree on this
Let's find
A
A solution to our
I'm having a little trouble finding out what about the hot like how close is this
The sense in the town was certainly that this thing was just a dead heat really split right down the middle
Backflips
It's all right
When you come back from break
Seneca goes to the voting booth
Andesite
This is Kim eslinger calling from Bismarck North Dakota Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan
Foundation enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world more information about
About Sloan at www. Sloan. Org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
About what we're calling tiny moments childhood Brilliance basically I want to hear about those times when a kid
So did something
It just means you read back and say whoa how did they do that maybe it was the moment that a kid
Did you been reading to 4 month started reading back
Do you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons and you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed they're writing music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the specific moments where a kid does something super smart
Have anything to do with the test if you have a story
T-shirt with us
Go to radiolab.org brilliance
Record short audio message for us
And that's radiolab.org / brilliance
Thank you so much
Hello hello
My name is Simon
I think I sent you a letter of a week
Even even for 5 minutes
I don't want to you'll probably talk to the haters but I'm done
Let the line dog's leg okay thank you so much all right
Bye goodbye
That was that was Jacqueline licking
Who is the woman who circulated the petition
And she I just refuse to
I'm rubber collection I'm signing this is Radiolab and Simon other is with me just before the break you were saying
I'm in the town
God awful trouble trouble
Happy town was so upset with the town in the government and the people of the town
That they were circulating a petition
That would end the town itself
I mean I got where they were upset
But I certainly don't get the idea that the solution is 2
In this place that is existed since 1888 this again is not to Hansen reporter for the Omaha World-Herald
And it bugged me
And why why did that bother you because I'm from a small town
I could imagine it
Happening to my town
A&i I can also empathize with a frustration
Of the people who wanted to keep it a town I mean you have to meet
Sandy Hanson
Will you show me a cup of your favorite artifacts you got here
Who operates a museum of Seneca history
Display says you cannot go to her Museum and not say wait a second
This place has the value
This one I wish could talk what we got baseball jerseys here with the
The Seneca baseball team
I got the uniform
Even the song one pair of pants don't have the caps
Backcountry
This is the newspaper cutouts 1860 these are pictures of family
Lived here advertisements of people of the area
Seneca Centennial hat
And people just send you some part of the concern here that history will be
Forgotten
It is
Because
Been a town 420 cm
So
What is it what does it mean to be a town
What does it mean it means Neighbors coming together
For the good of each other
When my husband died
He died in Texas
Eyebrows by Asia packet
Find I'm just
Having a graveside service out there at Cemetery
Well the time people wouldn't hear that
They had a big meal prepared my yard was mowed
The water was turned on everything was ready to go
And
It became a fool
Service
What is Edgefield
Felt like home
Like the way you're supposed to feel you know
Warm and wanted
You see they're talking about something that used to be
Again to the brown who wanted to end the town
They wanted to preserve it the way it was
And I agree that used to be a lot of fun
But that's true of any Town up and down this Railroad
If they're trying to
Preserve it then what are you trying to do
You're just accepting that we're going downhill here
No I'm accepting that
I myself
Do any better than this for myself as an aging woman
I've only lived here twenty years
But I'm from here
My mom my dad my cousins are all
Strong all over
Eclc
And this grass
You know
Anyway
I guess what I'm saying this to me it's
Heaven
Like I don't care
About my house
Falling down
I'm 70 years old and I'm going to finish up my Arts
Supplies and died at the respectable age of 96
And I do have enough art supplies
Didn't put enough for years
Could do that
Was that the nerve that was being touched your bad because you want to live this way yes
These people saying we can be proud of our town we can
Make it hustle and bustle
So they're saying nothing you're saying
No we can be proud of
Just the way it is now
Yeah
Say
Okay so how
When did you first hear about
The petition going around
Car wash
Again Millie from the safe Seneca side
I think the same day it was going around I heard about it
And how how did you feel in that mode
It was horrible it really was it was just
It was more than frustrating it was
Just like somebody punches you in the gut
She lets all the air you know it's just
It's the sad
Mostly it just seemed like if we could get rid of this unbelievable piece
Bureaucracy
We could just live here
So finally the incorporation it got on the ballot
At the regular election where you do the Senators and all that
We had a special ballot for Seneca where we voted for the town and would it or would it not be a name
Incorporate
What did you feel when
I don't remember feeling anything except I've got to get in there and vote
Dim if you don't mind just telling me how you about it
Oh I voted to the unincorporated
I voted to keep the Town Incorporated incorporate I voted to keep the town
And then she said okay that's the last Seneca Valley
Shoe designer shoes
Kevin Jackie severe
Sabre
Because I don't think I've ever had anybody explain this to me yet
Can you explain the night of the election and what what actually happened
Well you know we have internet access so we were watching the election results
On the internet to see how it came out
Who is we are there were I don't remember the four or five of us six of us maybe I'm not sure who all was there
What's the weather would you like refreshing the page over and over again how did that
No we knew about what time they'll be on you know we gave him an hour or so and we logged on and
Song
We saw that
The Village was unincorporated
It was by one vote
It was 15 to 16 we lost our town
Sandy Hanson again
What was that
I can't stay at Public Radio
What was lost the day after they decided to abolish the town
Sheriff come down with him I don't know what they thought we were going to
Shoot him off with guns or what
But the sheriff came down they took the greater they took the tractor took our snow plow
And
We no longer have our Street Maintenance our lights
Maybe your identity
I don't know
We never had much here but we didn't ask for much
I mean
We lost
Sunny kobe taken off the map
And if it isn't on the map where they can look it up
Mayberry nor nobody even knows it's there
Why I cried but I mean it hurt
Janet Jackson again
People are moving away from ready to go
We're all ready to leave
We don't have anybody there's been nobody move here since
Nobody
It sounds like you're saying the future is gone
I wouldn't say it's gone but I would say it's very very limited in unlikely
Yes I am famotidine incorporate
Again Terry Hartman
I love this town
And I think the people who voted to unincorporated
Are the people who wanted to keep things the way they were
We didn't want to change
I know everything has to
To change but
But I didn't know what else
To stop the fighting
You know this is my hometown to
I don't know how to explain it is
It just got so ugly and out of hand and
Some of the members of the village board for just crazy
But the town board
Was just three members
Millie
They have to do
Really what
The majority of the time once
To do
Otherwise we can get rid of them
Do you believe in the Democracy of Senate
I believe in democracy
Does that make me thin idiot
I mean I live in Hope
You know
It just it really
Felt like
Seneca had lost something essential
When were talking about basic American democracy
Again Matthew Hanson of the Omaha World-Herald
And it worried me to see that in part because I could feel that
And still feel bad happening
On a national level
Dick the kind of
Just completely black
Conversation
Around
Shared
Values or
Compromise
I've got a smoke more
Drink more
And one last time
Okay
Judith Brown
So
Can I tell you what I want to hear
Maybe the strongest argument for
Keeping Seneca
But town on the books
Is that then there was some sort of framework
To force those two
Communities within the town
To be together and to think together
And with that now gone
There is now no communication no compromise
None of those people had anything to do with us before accepted
Continually criticized
We were
So
We couldn't compromise with
These people they were not rational
All rationality was gone by then
And what's going to happen with this next election
What America is full of diverse opinions and it has managed to work and I guess if we take what happened
Here
And if we apply that model to the rest of the United States
Like it's not a town then what
We have the county we have the state
And the little town without those hateful people in it
Is really quite lovely
But it's not a townhouse
I don't know why you think that
Officially right
But it is a tell
Here we are
I'm going to leave here until I die and so is Rose
Inherent Elsa woman lands in
So you would say that even though on the book Seneca no longer
Exist
Seneca still exist
And we're still two tribes
2 tribes of turkeys that's how I usually put it
It'll never get along
This story was produced and reported by Simon Adler special thanks to Ryan Scott
On slide guitar
Michael Schulman trumpet
Chase coupon engineering help
Special
Thanks also to Matthew Hansen reporter at
Spell Mahalo World-Herald the Omaha World-Herald
Okay we'll be back next time
Go to the next message
Press X message
3 Omaha World-Herald
Radiolab is proof by Jad appenrod Dylan Keith is our director of sound designs for an wheeler senior editor Jimmy York
Workers are senior producer
Are. Include Simon Adler Brenda Pharrell
David gebel Matt kielty Robert krulwich Annie McEwen Latif Nasser Melissa O'Donnell
Aryan whack and Molly Webster
Hotel from Niagara fatality Phoebe Wang
Katie Ferguson Alexandria Lee Young W Harry Fortuna
Entropy of Berlin
Are fact-checkers are Eva Dasher and Michelle Harris
And this message