Are you awake
Listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
Peter Piper picked a peck of
Culpepper's
2 1
Jad Robert Radiolab and now we're going to do part two of our border patrol chief
Okay with reporter a lot of Nasser of Heroes podcast we had part one of the series with which we called hole in the
Offense
But I'm I'm excited to tell you now the rest of the story I feel like I've been holding out on you
And now
Are to hold the line
So
So let's do first
The previously on I think
To the previously on is
.
We had so it was
December 1st 1992
You have these Mexican American High School kids from this
Poor neighborhoods High School Bowie High School in El Paso
Right on the border
They
Do the Border Patrol
Who is Jason is harassing them who's hassling them
Because of
Really the color of their skin
And they went they win this amazing improbable victory
To get the Border Patrol
Stop
So that's where we are now
Right
And
Things are about to take some unexpected
Midterms
We're looking at the early 1990s the lawsuit was filed 1992
And right after that lawsuit
According to Tim Duncan sociologist actually turn it on.
This whole movie story
Right after the Bowie Victory the border patrol Chief in El Paso Del music AIDS
Obviously an old school throwback we're not accomplishing 100% of our nation
He's out
Music Gates's replace
And they're bringing a new chief piss my name is sylvester daysland
Silvestre Reyes
Been a veteran of the US border for 26 and a half years and he has a very different style
Great spot here yeah
This is one of
My wife and I's favorite place what do you want me to
Silvestre Reyes
Mexican restaurant on the outskirts of El Paso
Big guy broad shoulders, looks like gay
Like a retired football player
But who is now a gram
Merry Christmas
Coffee with cream
Very kind face
For a guy who revolutionized how we deal with the Border you and you grew up here
We're sitting
Here but a mile from where I was born
Our farm was
Northwest of here
We are
We grew cotton
Okay alfalfa
Watermelon some onions I'm the oldest of 10
Six brothers and four sisters
He says that his brothers and sisters did I'll work on the farm along with a bunch of undocumented workers who
Came in
From Juarez back then we had party line phone
So somebody would say
Roberto's coming today
But they didn't know what time or where
So whenever that happened
I was
Test2
Citadel
Two and a half ton truck
And he would watch the road
And I would blow the horn
At the first sign of what we would refer to his La Migra
To alert the workers
Jesse calls at the greatest
Irony of his life because
Fast forward
To college I got drafted into the army
He gets drafted to go to Vietnam spent 13 months in Vietnam
That was a helicopter crew chief
I came back from Vietnam
I was scheduled to go back
But what happened in
1968 was
My dad
My second brother
Was on his way to Vietnam
And
So
My
Dad was on his way to the airport
And he had an automobile accident
And got killed
So
I was the oldest
In the family
So
They let me out
To take care of the family
I'm so
Raise needed a job being a veteran any federal exam they opened up for you
So he starts taking these federal job exam
The post office
Bureau of Prisons Customs border
Patrol I mean just any test that I could cuz I have to make a living
And the very first place to call him back
Border patrol
Yeah that was what was available
Again Tim done so he becomes the kind of Pioneer in the board of choice one of the early
Hispanic agents when there were very few the job
Was tough cuz they didn't welcome you with open arms cuz your name is Reyes and not Smith or Jones
But I kind of enjoyed the challenge
He said he was dead set do everything twice as good and have
Pine and eventually he moved from being an agent into management and he works as well through management I was a first-line supervisor
Kaiser through the ranks
Second line supervisor
Tata towel
Academy and he eventually becomes the first Hispanic sector chief
Which means
In charge me
Huge swath of the Border in Texas
So then come
1993 you are
Sector Chief and your sign back here
I was moved here in late June
And
In early July I decided to
Assess the situation
And the situation
In El Paso
Did not
Look good
No
Looks like there was a mess
So one of the first things Ria's discovers is that the border between the US and Mexico apaso is in a state of
Chaos chaos we were averaging about 10 thousand illegal entry
Add a add a unprecedented numbers Bend for trolling have enough people to get them all so people were telling me
That agents are pretty much running cycle through the city
Liberalism questioning everybody stopping people asking for their immigration status
And they're doing this despite the fact that they just got sued by these high school kids for doing essentially the same thing and just lost tooth is still
Hanging over the patrol deal with that there was a huge deal it was making a chaotic
Which is worse and rias is on top of all of this there was a movement
When I got here to push the Border Patrol
Moved 25 miles out of the city
Two kind of creative borderless Zone around the city to unite El Paso and Juarez
Who's coming the spirit of NAFTA opening up NAFTA is good for us because it will cut the tariffs on trade between the United States and
Mexico the North American Free Trade Agreement NAFTA is going to open the border for the flows of goods and capital
But not people
And there's a little bit for people to
So they felt
That the border patrol is an invading Army they're the problem instead of the solution
ESO what he finds it that they're really unpopular and and that's just
Half the reason you're unpopular there's a whole bunch of other people that hate him for a whole different reason
Really yeah you when he got there he went on this listening walking tour of the neighborhoods along
On the Border there's there's whole neighborhoods there
But you are WETA
Barrio I want those neighborhoods and I talked to them
End
They thought the Border Patrol was a disaster
But instead of saying that the Border Patrol was over reaching that they were doing too much they felt
That the border patrol had failed him
Had let them down
And the people that lived on those neighborhoods they felt like they were under siege
We have been broken rice
3 *
Illegal immigrants
A little girl scared
People complain about burglaries about loitering people selling their Fruit Stand
Knocking on doors asking for money
Didn't like have to
Do it vendors all the time or people begging and didn't like having stuff stolen off their backyard garden hose a lawn chair
The phone off their clothes line gone
Overnight
These people living right on the border wanted was more border
Patrol to stop what they perceive to be
You know migrant petty crime
Aunt Susie he's really getting it from both sides
Yeah it's like a whole City's coming out
We were
With one foot on a banana peel
Of getting driven out of town
That's why I had to change
And I didn't have a lot of time to do the
Okay
Sung so what does he do
Well he had an idea
A pretty radical idea
I knew
There would be political pressure there would be public outcry
So you take this idea around to a bunch of
High level
The mayor of Juarez
The mayor of El Paso people at the Mexican consul in El Paso are going to in Juarez
The Sheraton
Chief of police of Juarez in El Paso
Annie's going to each one of them and basically saying
Look
If
We're able to correct
If I can quell the chaos
Would they support the Border
And they said yes
Okay so here's what I find so fast
It's September of 93
And while Reyes is hatching his plan at the same time at the El Paso Civic Center
Honest one particular weekend
The United El Paso people are having this big convention
Talking about how we can try and create this borderless
Community Resources local officials and Civic leaders are hammering out their proposals and everything
Presenting to the audience
That same weekend
Silvestre Reyes
Rolls out
His plan
He wanted this to be a surprise
So we launched the operation at midnight
Since September 18th 1993 Saturday night
Reyes gathers all of his border patrol agent for Border Patrol
From all over the sector
And I breathe every single shift
Allegiance
Myself
I told him what was at stake
I told him that if this thing didn't work
They're going to run us out of town
My initial reaction was well this is going to be interesting
Retired border patrol agent David Hamm was there with his anti drug smuggling
And he said after the briefing we drove up the Border Highway on the Mexican side
And we got to downtown water sitting in the library about sunrise
And so he and his agents are waiting right at the Rio Grande
And the sun came up
Any severe
At the border
She just saw all the wall border patrol
A wall of Agents along the river
Hard yards Park
Each one in their trucks
Light green trucks
There helicopters buzzing
Lowell along the river there were floodlights every worth of the agents could be out there on the clock 24 hours a day
Basically what race
Done is he created a human
Wall on the border at the river.
It stretched for like
When my
And I had told my guys
We're in this for the Long Haul
What race was doing
This is his plan
Was to essentially change our strategy On the Border
How we police the border from a strategy of
Apprehension of letting migrants come in and running around chasing them sending them back
To one of deterrence
And called it operation blockade operation blockade
Day one on Sunday morning like they always did
Hundreds of Mexican migrants tenders construction workers housekeepers
Waiting to cross into El Paso for work
But now they were confronted with the Berlin Wall On the Border
On the line
Where they would have to wait him out
Waiting to see when the border patrol agents will pack up and leave
By the time night falls the migrants they just turn and go home and figure okay I guess we'll just
Come back in the morning they came back Monday
We were still there
And that's
When to start
Spaghet
Chaos
D2
Summit Amy Jacobson is standing by live under the paso del Norte bridge where the incident occurred
Mexican took to the main bridge that connects El Paso and Juarez
Close the paso del Norte bridge and confronted border patrol
They blockaded traffic
Skirmishes One agent was struck in the face with a rock blood and bandages still litter the area
Time there was screaming going on so racist how many races are there are all these headlines
The newspaper there are better ways to do this
Basically saying this new strategy is wrong operation blockade is nothing more than an attempt
To divide the community
Race is the mayor of El Paso who he preached about the operation is denying ever knowing about it would call them when they said mayor
Chief
I just didn't know what to do how many children are going hungry because their parents cannot come to El Paso
The local Bishop came out in
Supper Club is winter
If a blockade continues
And this is only date
Two of the blockade by Friday 3
Drawing of around 200 occupy the password
Things continued to get worse day for more protests
Day 5 6 7 at the end of the week
People were starting to get really desperate
But a remarkable thing happened that I didn't plant
The banners on private property around 2 shows
Support for operation blog
The support for the border patrol just
Skyrocket
List
Support enforcing the laws that felt like they were under siege and the bowhead failed him
They came out with these huge banners of we support our border patrol
The tide ribbons on their cars that came out with
Donuts and coffee
For the border patrol agents who were on the line it was like all of a sudden there was just sort of
Flip people locally on love
Across
Racial and ethnic lines
A movie store
Bella cosmetology
Because overtime what happened during this blockade was two things
Brian is one of the most popular reasons he's El pasoans are in favor of operation blockade
Prime goes down
Now it's hard to tell whether this is actually
Because of the blockade
But there's a reduction in petty crime some like 15%
That's the bottom line
And the second thing and this is way more surprising was it from Mexican Americans
Could being harassed by the border patrol presence in their neighborhood
They start to notice that is a ghost
The agents were gone right right it completely clear them out because now they were all down on the border
So there's this you know this
Tidal wave of support like
Virtually everybody locally in El Paso both sides
Are really happy with what he's doing you seem to solve the problem in one Fell Swoop
What was the reaction of Bowie High School
The
Principal called me
Paul strelzin
What's his name he's passed away
He called me
And he said
Chief I hope you
I hope you
Thought this out because
You are you have given us
Our campus
But
Right in the midst of all of this
Silvestre Reyes
Gets a phone call
Phone call
From Washington DC
Saying you got to stop this
I'll tell you all about that phone call
And what falls out of that call
Hi this is Adam McBride from Laporte color
Radiolab
Supported in part by the alpha
P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloan @www
Got Sloan. Org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here I'm a producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
And I request
For those of you who
Who spend a lot of time with kids parents
Aunts and uncles teachers we're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments
Brilliant
Basically I want to hear about those times when I did something
It just means you lean back and say
Maybe it was the moment that I
A kid you've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of their musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class
Stay Ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the
Epic moments where
A kid does something super smart
It doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story
T-shirt with
Go to radiolab.org
Flash brilliance
Mrecorder short
Audio message
Again that's radiolab.org
Slash brilliant
Thank you so much
This next part of the episode contains
Some moments that are very graphic
The depict death and I'm pretty
Put away
If you're squeamish
Are you listening kids
I may be drunk
Chad Robert Radiolab
Two part two of our border Trilogy from reporter lots of Nasser
When we left the story Silvestre Reyes had put into place operation blockade which was then renamed operation Hold the Line
And everyone in El Paso
Seem happy
Very happy
Yeah but people in Washington DC or not
The Clinton Administration they're about to have this vote on NAFTA other talking about free trade
And then this guy this little guy no pasta oh he's
Created a blockade and looking like a little closer than I thought and the last thing the
Ministration needs is
Any controversy over the
Until right in the middle of operation blockade
Reyes gets a phone call from his
Boss's boss's boss
Pilgrimage endocrino
No Janet we know who is the Attorney General
Big lady like her
I'm in even back then when she was
Hammering away at me I'd like to
And she wanted to talk to me
And Chee
Started
Using talking points
Play it was a wrong thing
Political consequences International ramifications
He has this sense okay I'm
I'm about I'm about to be fired but he said to her
Madam attorney general with all due respect
Do me
One favor
I said
Come and visit
El Paso just come and visit El Paso
I said because you are
Making the statement
With all due respect without knowing
The difference that it's made
In El Paso
Please come to us
She
Silence
But she says
I will be there Tuesday
So Janet Reno fly to El Paso Reyes sets up a bunch of meetings for her and I told her I said look I'm not going to be there
Cuz I want you to hear it
Unfiltered and your dad me being there
As he tells it Channel real sat down for all these meetings with all these local businesspeople and she was so blown away
By what she heard how
Happy everyone was with the situation that you put aside the fact that Mexico has been put aside NAFTA
She came back and
Chi
You shook my hand
Very impressive
What you've done here is amazing
What people are telling me is incredible
I mean she went on and on she says I'm going back and I'm going to tell
The president
That he needs to hear
You talk about
The president of the United States
We should just change her entire view after after one visit.
What he says and apparently she was barely there for a day
What
I wish we could get Janet Reno take on this but unfortunately she died in 2006
Teen but
Her change of heart actually makes a certain kind of sense mean there was a real
A very important political element to all of this
Text Doris meissner
She was at the time the head of the immigration Naturalization Service basically Janet Reno's number 2 when
When it came to the Border
And she says but at that moment the Janet Reno
In Texas touring El Paso the Clinton administration had a big problem on his hands
About a thousand miles west Californians are open arms
About the illegal immigration that is coming into California 40% of the babies born on Medicaid
In California today are born of illegal immigrants
We are going to take back California you had this wave
An initiative like Proposition 187
Problem by denying services to illegal immigrants
Super hard line measure passed by a wide margin
The Clinton Administration was definitely paying attention
California is California a largest Electoral College fries in November's presidential election
California being a red state from 1968 all the way to 1992 Clinton was
The guy who broke the cycle and if he was going to get reelected California had to continue to vote
For the Clinton administration
So one of the things that might have changed Janet Reno's mind or more importantly your boss
Bill Clinton's mind
Was that they saw in El Paso
A potential solution to the California problem if they could make illegal immigration weigh less visible as rate
Also
Maybe they could hold the steak
I'm pleased to be here today
Ains
Commissioner Doris meissner
February 7 1995
He rode mine
Chief Sylvester
Psoriasis of the El Paso border
Chrome
We have just come from a meeting
With press
Which time he signed a president
Miranda
Directing RH
To move forward
With new edition
Regain control of our borders
And better enforce our immigration laws
This is the first
National border patrol strategy
I spend a great deal of time on it things had not been done that way before
And it was a it was a fundamental change in strategy
According to Doris meissner and she really was the architect of the strategy
The idea was to
Take what Reyes was doing which was very clarifying and steal it up there were basically
Play 4
Major
Crossing quarters
Along the Southwest border
Each of those four spots that were going to amass border patrol agents
On the Border not
Behind the Border not in the city where they piss off the locals
But directly on the border
Concentrate resources
Starting of course in California
AR
Strategy was to start in San Diego because that was
The highest Crossing Court
Maybe 45 to 50% of the crossings
Across the entire Southwest border
We're happening in the San Diego sector
We start in San Diego with operation GateKeeper
Then move to I believe Arizona and I'm just trying to think of what we name. Ever
Operation safeguard
Exactly and then the fourth was southtex
All of a sudden now
In 1994 the Border Patrol
Publishes this
Was called the
The Strategic plan is also known as prevention through deterrence this is Jason De Leon again the Anthropologist who started us off
This whole series
Did they write in his policy document
We know the Border cut across a whole bunch of very difficult environments
If we disrupt traditional Crossing places Urban ports of Entry
And we push people toward these extreme environments
They will have to cross rushing Rivers
Mountainous terrain places that where you can freeze to death or you can die of
Dehydration
But the extreme environment
Will slow people movement
Will make them easier to catch
And we'll also perhaps
Stop them from coming
Another word
After Reyes
It became our national strategy to push people away from urban areas
And you say
The desert
As a kind of natural deterrent thinking was the that would be a natural geographic
You know of
Allied that would
Take care of
The rest
Now one of the things
Of course that we learn
Is that
That that didn't hold
Because in the nineties the Mexican economy was struggling so people still need a jobs in that on the American side Farm
So people still cross
Crossing to the cities
They were crossing through the desert
No one was watching
Five men stumbled out of the mountain pass
So sunstruck
They didn't know their own names
Justlikenew Reyes books The Devil's Highway
Going to remember where they come from
Had forgotten how long
And so that's why
In the late 90s
You see the number of people dying in the Sonoran Desert overnight
Start to Skyrocket you go from 5 to 10 Bodies 2
The hundreds
By 2002 or so the numbers in Arizona or upper end $150
4 year a couple years after that it goes over 200
Those are the official border patrol numbers
That they report based on the number of bodies
Found
But after Jason had that experience finding an arm in the desert and not being able to locate the rest of the body he started
You do wonder whether those numbers
Were accurate
How many more people
Might be dying out there
Who are never found
Never count
Yeah
Which for json at least
You became a scientific way
But what happens to bodies in the Dead
How fast
Do they decompose and what ends up happening is
I just kind of Hit the library
Scout literature
You know his body Farms where we do this Tennessee Texas
Jason Thomas one paper that suggested that when bodies are decomposing in the desert heat in the dryness drastically slowed that
Down this idea that the debtors going to conserve
Nobody is going to
Mummifying that people will be at the forever according to that paper could take up to six months for a body to decompose to the Bone
When will you be able to see the bone
But the remains in that
Study were collected in a bunch of different areas under
Different condition sometimes even indoors no one have done it kind of in situ in the deserts beheading literally no
No scientific data on that at all
So I started getting really interested in
Is there a way to
Do some science around me
He eventually wrote in an assistant named
Kate hall Hall and I'm a physical anthropologist
What's a physical anthropologist
A physical Anthropologist is someone at who
Studies
At least 30 human bones and I try and infer what someone's life and death was like from skeletal remains
Ions
Jason pretty much came up to me and told me that
He's been thinking about getting some pigs
Pics
Pigs have long been at the common proxy for human bodies Buena for Crime Scene stuff like
They shoot them they bury them
And you know that you're using
Police different report of decomposition experiments
So
Jason and Kate and the research team had down to Arizona
University of Arizona has a meet laboratory at that deals with live animals so we called up
Jerome
DIA
Euthanizer
And he came out
In this big truck
He comes out with these animals to pigs
150 lb
Alive Jerome shoots the pigs in the head right in front of them
And then Kate and Jason we got shoes and socks
Thruster pigs
Bra panties jeans t-shirts and clothes at migrants
Because they wanted to recreate the conditions exactly
And then he took these dress dead pigs
Out into the desert arivaca Arizona
It's like another planet it's like nowhere else I have ever been on Earth
It's hot
And saying it's hot doesn't
Really do it justice
So get together in this big field
And we had one when pigs
Under a tree in lightshade we are trying to replicate like
If someone weighs
Tired and needed to take a rest somewhere
Lying in their groups and they would say well we didn't leave the person behind but we had to go they were dead so they would cover their body with rock
Fox in hopes of protecting them from animals
Three places to pigs
One in the shade one under rocks
And they set up a series of motion sensing
Cameras all around the perimeter of
The area
To watch
Both pigs
These are the kinds of cameras that turn on if something moves we set up the cameras under a very very hot sun
And remember based on what Jason and read the prevailing idea was that bodies in the desert dome decompose until
Six months in around nine months in amount would make the likelihood that they'd be found
Higher
Which might suggest that the official numbers are Act
Regardless the Assumption wise
That these bodies would be laying around for a while
But
Pretty quick
Something moves
And triggers the camera
So this is footage of the pig that was in the shade and on the cameras you see
Pig just under a tree lying on its side
Wearing his little white shoes it has
Jingdong
Bloated
But it intact
And then
Later that night camera comes on against night vision
You can see the pig again
And then
See this vulture
A few feet away from the pig
Kind of looking at it kind of checking it out
Just
Standing there
And then
After a couple of hours
Camera comes back on
Another eight vultures
On top of this pic
And staring
A few hours later they go and they make a hole in the back of the neck
Kind of like kind of right behind the ear and they're trying to connect the brain and then
Turn off the shirt they eventually ripped the jeans off
By noon is a 50 there are
Hordes of vultures
Attack
The abdomen
Richtofen the stomach and then you see
Intestines being pulled out and then you have two vultures come in front of the camera and they're playing tug-of-war with the
Seize intestines and
They start to take apart
The limbs will actually like carry them away they will carry linzess like
Convenient packages of meat
They can eat later
27 they dragged what was left of the body about 20 m
Upper Hill
And within 9 days they had picked
Picked it clean
Everything's been pulled apart
Anxious
Scattered all over the place
After 9 days
There's hardly anything left nine days
Yeah so they thought it might take 9 months
And now it's down to nine days and and that was the pig in the shade the pig in the Little Rock Cut The Bad Pig
Went way fast
Yeah that was within 24 hours for Ultra 2 started feeding
I just got in underneath the rocks and ripped it up because we felt we had really forgotten that
The rocks
Conduct heat
So it literally Cooks the body and speeds up the
This process
It will completely defied
Expectation
This wasn't all you're expecting at all vultures the only scavengers that you were known as
Not the only scavengers so we saw some Ravens to must have dogs
So this town of arivaca where we working a lot of people dying nearby and they have these
You know kind of ranch dogs that are pretty wide-ranging
And people have I'd heard stories of people singing on my. Came home with a
With a piece of human bone
But these animals
We're in or on our property eating these pigs
I'm just now thinking it from the point of view of the dog owner on like this dog comes in and gets on the couch like
That's the same tongue that might have been
Knowing on a human arm exactly
And after the vultures and crows and dogs that have their way with these pigs Jason K told us that the desert started working in small
Mahler invisible
Waze
I have never seen this before like we used to flies and some Beatles but
Consuming parts of
Long bones are chipping off pieces of bone
I'm carrying them off to this ant hole a meter away
Not there
For for long enough note and they will completely disappear this is an environment in which people can become really easily
Just erase
Well there is something about when you when you were describing
The first moment when the vault is really sort of
Taryn to the body
I haven't by found myself going to recoil and trying to protect my abdomen I still have
That reaction
There's something just
So
Overwhelmingly human about this
You can't not take
Personally
What can we talk about the
The numbers for second
Because if
Bodies
Are decomposing and disappearing
This fast
Does border patrol numbers
Start to look sick
Suspiciously
Low
Do you have any sense based on
The speed of decomposition
How many people
We might be missing you know it just
It just depends I mean on the phone when people die
At what time of year that I mean if you live in a better way to do is if you compare the number of missing persons reports
With the numbers of recovered bodies
There's a discrepancy of
These are missing persons reports
From America and missing persons reports are filed in the US by families already here
Or or
Trump sending countries but thousands of missing persons reports
More than the natural recovered bodies
Thousands a year how to go missing a year during the process
Obviously missing persons reports don't equate to deaths in the desert
But pretty much everyone I talk to including some retired border patrol agents
Agree that the official number is
When it comes
To the actual number of deaths
Nobody knows for sure
Depending on who you ask the real number could be anywhere from
Twice to 10 times the official count
And if you think about the fact that that has been happening
Years
Then what that
High School history teacher one cyber Coronado told us at the end of our last episode
That sounds so crazy
Because of us
Fences were built
Because the fences were built
Maybe 10000
People have died in the day
There's no way to verify that number
Or any number
But the potential scale of it
Kind of forces you to ask
Who is responsible
Some of these people I talked to said that the
Mexican government needs to do more to stop people going into these areas
Others blame the Smugglers who bring people over
Some people have said that the migrants themselves
Vdara Spa
They knew they were making this decision to come if they die it's on them
The other obvious question is
What About Us
Yeah
And what's clear you know json is
Bad
US policy makers one exactly
Play clueless about this
There were points where people were saying things like
If we do this if we funnel them towards Addison or desert of Arizona at we funnel them towards the port of Backwoods of Texas
People are going to get hurt people are going to die
But if enough people died perhaps that will be
The deterrent then that they'll stop coming
Is that written down
It is oh my God I said death equals two turns there's a chart that eyesight in the book and this is one of the one of the moment
Where I was
When I was doing the kind of archival research that just
Just shocked me where there was a point with someone written this policy document
Alanine one of the follow-up reports by the government accountability office
Some numbercruncher or some policymakers sitting at a computer and DC
Making an Excel chart
Work they're putting out different metrics to measure the effectiveness of this policy and one of the metrics is
An increase in in in migrant death
There was a recognition that if death goes up it means that this policy is working
I ended up finding the document Jason was referring to it's a report from the government accountability office
And it also mentioned said in other areas death might also
Go down
I wanted to talk to Doris meissner about
Cottage cheese remember the former ins commissioner that help take the Sylvester Rhea's Hold the Line strategy Nash
And actually read part of the report
Yes
And then there was this kind of one appendix
Sin it is 5 and it's indicators for measuring the effectiveness
Of the strategy
Tradutor illegal entry
Along the Southwest borders and one of the indicators was death
Deaths of aliens attempting entry
And basically what it says is that
Is recording at that
If the Attorney General strategy
Successful deaths may increase
As enforcement in urban areas vs Aliens 2
To attempt mountain or desert
Crossings in FL
Text saying that
If the strategy
It if it just increase in these
Treacherous areas
That's a sign that the strategy is working
Think I recall
Reading that because it's so
What makes you gasp when you have to really think about
What the
All of the implications of all these things are
When you know this is one of those
Paradoxes of
How is it that you go about doing work like
It's absolutely
We're
Ferb so many reasons that there needs to be border security
But I think it is
Fair to say
That
The idea that we had at the time and the thinking that we put into place at the time
Was too simple
What was much more difficult to take into account it has been the tenacity
Of people
Coming to the United States
Wanted to come to the United States
And the length
To which people will go
In order to do that
What that there's another way to read this means the
The appendix five the sooner the thing that that has you in your words
You said you know could make you gas
With that sort of says
And one way to read that is that we took
Problem that was very visible
And we push it to places we can't see it anymore
And
We did that with full knowledge
Did that
That people dying means we're doing the right thing
Tatume appendix V begs the question mean what responsibilities do we
Have
For this
It doesn't quite feel like this is something that we can just shrug and say we didn't know this is going to happen
It feels like we knew damn well this
What's going to happen
You know when you asked
The question what is our responsibility and when you say our
I think
And I take that to mean what is our responsibility as a nation
The answer at the time and the answer still is
That
The enforcement will do everything that I can to
Prevent
People from Crossing in dangerous areas
But that
Cannot include
No longer
Doing enforcement across the bar
Nudura says that you know once they started to realize these numbers it's spiked and if people were going through these areas they started doing
In a lot of public awareness campaigns information campaigns warning people about the dangers of
The desert
Devoted to safety on the Mexican side of the created a whole new search-and-rescue unit cell
There were
All kinds of efforts
To address it
But I will be absolutely Frank with you
The idea of abandoning any kind of strengthening border enforcement
Because of that consequence
Was not a serious
I would not appoint a serious
Discussion
And the policy never really changed
Substantiv wait there was a later report that came out from the government accountability office
That basically said you look you've done all these safety measures but the death in the desert are
Still going up
Doris meissner was no longer head of the ins-and-outs
Point but after reaching out to a whole bunch of people who wrote that report and
And the people received it
And peering
Nothing back frankly
I finally got in touch with the commissioner of Customs and Border Protection under President Bush at
The time Ralph Basham
Now retired and he told me he remembered reading that report
He said that you thought about those deaths all the time everyday
But in the end she said it was just politically infeasible to back off the enforcement
At the major Crossing Point
Sort of getting a border patrol to really control dangerous areas like
The desert
And in the end the US government didn't make any substantive changes in response to the rising desk
And I guess you could
Read that as a lack of political will or indifference
But Jason actually argues that
We were giving a
Blessing to the system that was killing all these people because
It kept his problem just
Swept under the rug
Yeah
Are you saying that
The US
Government
Whatever portion of it is responsible for this policy
Is knowingly
Killing people
I would say it's knowingly putting people In Harm's Way
And I know that there is a high likelihood
That
Bob certain percent of people are going to die
It happened I was like they're having nature do the do their dirty work that's kind of what you
Feel like it's absolutely I mean I would say 100% that nature is an agent of
Border patrol
It's at this kind of unsung hero of the border patrol either not on the payroll but they do all this work
The environment beats up on migrants
And then those who don't make it
It just cleans up the mess as well
I'm in nobody has to be accountable for this because it just disappears
We asked Customs and Border Protection which oversees border patrol 2
Comment whether they had tried to
To change their strategy to avoid migrants
And they decline to answer
I wonder if I wonder if you feel somehow ambivalent about it like
Obviously there are trade-offs for everything every every
You plan has unintended consequences
But but this now this has happened and and these deaths
Are also happening
I wonder how you feel about it if you feel somehow I am busy
I feel deeply ambivalent about it I feel deeply
Sorry about it I am very conflicted about it
I also know
That
Migration is by its very nature
Incredibly dangerous Enterprise but you know when it's illegal immigration
People coming up in a well before they ever get to the US border
People coming up
Through Mexico through very dangerous areas where
They are robbed and kidnapped and extorted I mean there are awful Terrible Things That Go On
In this quest for a better life
What I wish
Is that
We would be able as a country
Support immigration policies into a fact that it actually allow for people to come here legally
Kumar economy is asking for
In terms of the jobs that exist in the country
This
System that we've been involved with for now
Decades
Allowing illegal immigration to occur in sizable numbers
Having work for people in this country
Is indefensible
And the enforcement agencies are caught in between that they're required
Create border security and yet there are these
Terrible
Cost
Those terrible cost
Would not be there
If we as a country and as a political system
Would come to grips
With the issue that is right in front of our eyes
And that we simply won't come together politically to answer
We are a nation of immigrants
We are a country that believes in the rule of law
We
Can't wait is indefensible
In light of that history
And those values
To have a loud
This kind of an illegal immigration picture
To go on in the way that it has for all these many years
Wooden wall I mean this is going to sound misses an intentionally knife question but
If what you're saying is that that
That
We need to save lives
Weather how we feel about
The issue of immigration
Is it a wall more humane
Given what you just told us
Well the walls not going to do anything
I mean we know that
Yeah I spend a lot of time now most of my time is not then with Smugglers
Who loved the idea of a wall
Cuz they're like man I can charge twice as much for this for my services
Even though
It's really not going to be that much harder
Cuz people dig underneath it they crawl over it they fly over at they take a boat around it I mean
The wall itself is never going to
It's never going to be at
Deterrent
And on top of that I actually I didn't even know this
When we talked to Jason
But if you listen to the things that President Trump has said about the wall since coming into office
2000 miles
Because of nature because of mountains and rivers and lots of he would end up just being
Even stronger version of this policy
And you have a river a river
I need an even stronger funnel interviews very places that are killing people
And erasing any evidence
Of their death
This episode of our border Trilogy was reported by lots of Master with Tracy hunt
And was produced by Matt kielty with Bethel habte and
Third installment of a Trilogy where things get a lot more personal
Is coming up in the next podcast stay tuned for that
Big things to Jason Deli on Whose book is called the land of open Graves
And 2 Timothy Dunn who's written a lot about this including book blockading The Border and human rights
Special thanks to Oscar Cervantes Jose Romero Erica King Joe Reyes
And the rest of the agents that we met from US border patrol in El Paso and to David ham and Liz and the rest of the staff at the border
Patrol History Museum Veronica Reyes and two former El Paso mayor Larry Francis retired
Border patrol sector Chief Ron Sanders and Robin Reineke at Colibri Center for human rights
I'm Jared
Hi this is Rebecca Jordan calling from Dacula Georgia Radiolab was created by Jad appenrod and is produced
Warren Miller
Don't keep is our director sound design
Maria madisar Padilla is a managing director
Our staff includes Simon Adler Maggie bartolomeo
Becca Bressler Rachel Cusick David gebel Bethel Hoppity Tracy hunt Realty
Robert krulwich Annie McEwen lack of Nasser Melissa O'Donnell Aryan whack
Pat Walters and Molly vibes
With help from Amanda erotic Shima only I and Jake
Arlo
Are fact-checker is Michelle Harris