Are you awake
Listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
EDM
Revolt there is no she Liam
Yes he is pronoun and element stop writing the most noble gas
If there was she Liam
I'll find
Why
Lie
She might be
Ungettable rod
I'm Roberto which is its Radiolab today
Elements I carried your oxygen
And you walked beside me through the lobby commenting on the decor
When you need it to stop for breath
Your hand
Wren light
Unsteady
By the ocean of breath
Twice
I remember
I carried your oxygen
He was heavy
Oblique alloy
Steel
This hour is a collaboration with poets like the ones you hurting while you're more of
Musicians supporters of course the periodic table
Speaking of which
A producer
Storm wheeler
Who's sodium spark brain conceived this entire show
He will lead us off so this one starts with the story I heard from Jamie Lowe
She's a rider in Brooklyn
And at the heart of this story is this particular 24-hour. In Jamie's life that
She is
Venezia
Publish to set it up for one second so what are we about to watch
I'm not actually exactly sure where it's
Starts
But we're about to watch
I think the night but
Before Valentine's Day
Walker
Through the tape
Go for a urine control there was a space bar
Springer video starts
Night time Jamie
And her friend Mike he's one filming there outside his apartment in Brooklyn in the cameras pointed
A bunch of high school students who were just
Walking by
Joy City Hotel
So you want to be an actress weigh
I love acting
Hell yeah really
That's so cool
Yeah that is my enemy dell'arte cell phone
What's month
It is nor hand or foot nor are North Face
Are any of the laundromat
I'm somehow am I gagging them on to recite it
Tamest you're perfect
Toshio's without that title
Aroma. They name and for the name which is no part of the
Take all my stuff and screaming
Baby's all right
Eventually turns to Jamie she's sitting on the stoop
Huge curly hair wide eyes and she starts to sing
The kids are song
What does
You don't come again
I was pretty convinced that I was like I agree
Singer and rapper
She likes
Producing a lot in never
It was fun to watch people react
She made people
Play Happy wherever she went
Flea markets and she would talk to people and she would pull the spark out of
It just felt like New York love tricks
Text Mike Ryan
Guy holding the camera healing that Jamie just
3 weeks earlier not long after moving your
And they pretty much instantly became friends
She was
Show
Positive
Recology
Talking to little kids on a stoop
But then that next 4-5 hours
It was pretty defining
Taken 2
Lakes Apartment
You're just
Walking around
In a bra and open dress
Sparkly red bra
And plus
Big bag
Plastic bag on the
Stomach
Belly dancing
You might have to show their eyes book
Okay we go
That's worried about
4 hours
PetSmart
Boy
Good morning
Stalin
Sade 2001
That's
Kumquats and avocados are kumquats for
My grandpa
Kumquat
Three or four days ago and
Best breakfast by cutting board
I'm kind of Power Bars
Rainbow from
In the present I gave you tighten cup of wine that we're going to drink
And
A cup of wine of course it's 7:40 in the morning
Just keep pumping
I'm tired of
Keyport Mike
Today weather
What's going to happen today
Today
Contact MTV
Debate Club
10 Fidel Castro
List of
It has to be about them
Give me about any
Jon Tester
Were you were you meaning that literally that you were going to go on MTV and debate Gore V bush
And then
That is exactly what I had in
I thought it was make
It seemed harmless
It just didn't occur to me that what I was seeing with somebody who
Had deviated substantially from who they wanted to be
Jesus Christ
Eventually might got up had to go to work Jamie took off for a while and then later that day she showed up at his office
The first everything seemed sort of fine but
Within 20 minutes she said hey
Tell you what
Can we go to the roof really fast
What
And that immediately
Say okay over pants
Floral wrap around skirt we are now going to the roof
Are you ready to be blown up in pink
You can hear his
Done like the day has been insane this is at the end of that day
Snowy
7th Avenue rooftop
What it what is it what is it
Piece of yarn
Pastor Mike Patrick Ryan
What are you
Canada work
At 5:20
On top of the world
The World Trade Center by one Mario
Yeah tonight
At that point he was like
Done
We're done
Yeah
That's when it hit me that
There is no way
Did any of this reflects what she would actually want
I don't know if delusional is a kind word here and if it's not
Apologize but
If she's delusional enough
To think that we should get married
Is she delusional enough to think she can fly
Will she be distraught when I say no
Know and we'll see
Would you jump
It's my Lord the camera
And I said
I'm afraid of heights and I want to go downstairs immediately
And I felt for the first time
Fear
And I called for I believe they called her mother first
Dalian
And I just said
My name is Mike I'm a friend of Jamie's
And
I think she may be going through something
And I don't know what I'm dealing
I'm in over my head
When Mike called
I just got on a red eye
That night
Text Leanne Lantos
Jamie's mom it was my job to get her
To go back to her therapist
So that we could
Could get some medication in her
For the end of episode was not entirely surprised that it happened once before
Jamie was
High school at that time she was not sleeping at night spinning around the room talking.
Non-Stop
About how she had to save Central America
I'm just asking
Bring up first episode Jamie ended up at a place called The Neuropsychiatric Institute at UCLA
And she ended up being treated by this guy
Dr. mark deantonio
Psychiatrist
She was in a very
Acute manic psychotic state
I remember being served
Tackled by
Nurses that actually take my meds because I refuse
Still we didn't know if we would ever see our Jamie again
You know that was
That was the scariest part
Everyone around me I think was really really worried
That I wouldn't
Come back
But you did come back and it's what brought her back
That
Is actually the reason
Not so interested in the story
Shortly after she was admitted
Dr. deantonio told Jamie's parents he know what this is and we know how to treat it he said she's a classic
A case of
Of bipolar is no question
And
Did the drug of choice
Is lithium
Which
It's not even a drug but just
This
Salt and Heat
Explain to us
You know that she would need to take three tablets of lithium
3 tablet
What's this song
And it could bring her back when it work
Just remarkable
Memories of like what it was like
To come back like that
What you were thinking or what it felt like
As really hard
To describe as a little bit of like
Slow realization of
I was like
Oh that was a weird thing that I
I did a week ago
Why did I do
The first time she was actually lucid and coming back
To herself again
The first words out of her mouth were
Mom it's not me
And I just
That just killed me
Within a few weeks it was like
The incident never happened so bizarre I mean I felt like he was this thing that's a
Fault that I get to just take three of a day and and that was it
Only normal dose side effects no issues she went off to college and just like flourish
It was great things were good for a long time
And then after about six years she said you have been on this pill for six years I've had no problems
I'd like to go off at why don't we try to go off gradually then about a month after she was totally off lifting
In Mike's apartment
Up all night you were so tired just a minute ago
Have you told me I had to leave but now I'm still here aren't I
Totally manic episode all over
Cuz I am
Whatever
One of the things that kind of makes lithium
That affected
Lithium has so spooky and you hear this from a lot of people that have taken lithium
How to treat bipolar
Is it selfish
Is so
Simple
Lithium is
If a single atom
This is
Story collider podcast
He's had some personal experience with psychiatric
Chinese written about
That to me was fascinating that did a single
Adam
Can change
What we think of who we are
I mean it's not even
Number three the third element in the table
What are the simplest atom
Lights with 3 protons 4 neutrons 3 electrons
That's a pretty simple didn't matter it doesn't get much it really is
Is it never struck me when I was on Lex
Cipro or Wellbutrin together when they put me on you know if you look at them
They look like what you expect a pharmaceutical drug to look like
Ring of carbon atoms and some other things stuck on the bed and they they look like
Big complex molecules in I'm complex my brains complex
To take this complicated thing to change
And then you're confronted with
Justice Adam
He was found by accident that it works
It's not complicated to make us
Assault that you did
Still out
And yet it has the
Profound
The other thing I know about lithium.
Redis
Profound language
Is that
You're not just saying
My Mind my personality is being changed by an atom
It's Been Changed by an atom that was created directly in the Big Bang itself
See how this atom formed in the Big Bang
Goes through whatever it does
Winding path to come onto the Earth
Gets dug up
Turn into a pill given to
Someone
And that changes
Their effect in the world and that to me is just it's this
Profound reminder that
The forces that shape everything in the universe are the same as the forces that are shaping
Who we are and what we do
And what her identity
It's possible that these forces
Shape not just the people with bipolar disorder but
All of us
End up talking to a clinical psychiatrist annafellows who
Told me about these studies
Huge epidemiologic studies biggest one I think was in Japan owners in Austria when was in Greece famous
When in Texas
In which they look
At communities that different levels of lithium
Lithium in the water supply and we're talking about
Tiny
Titanium
Micrograms
Thousands of
The amount in a milligram
If you think of like a pill of lithium what were talking about amounts like 10,000
I guess the amount
We're dealing with here
And these studies found by and large in in towns that had a
Tiny bit more lithium in the wall
Suicide rates were lower
In some cases as much as
30% study which is
Astonishing also shows
The towns that have
The highest lithium level
Have
Lower felonies theft
Rape
And these are
Reputable publisher
Studies
No peace studies
Only showing of correlations but there does Italy
Seem to be
Some kind of connection
How's it doing do they know why
Works in the brain after they know what it does
Essentially
No
Still kind of a mystery
One of them but here's mark dantonio
We know that bipolar disorder involves a defect
Certain part of
It's an area of the brain that has to do with controlling mood
So believe it out there neurons in the brain that
Keep your mood even
These neurons that do their job by a sort of passing electricity back
4th and that electricity is carried by sodium
So the whole system is pretty much based on sodium
Lithium is very similar to sodium so if you have lithium in the Brandon Ron's will use that music
Send lithium ion
Here's what's interesting
Lithium Werks
Just like sodium but not as well lithium is similar nothing properties
That it can be
An imposter
But whatever does it just doesn't work
That's the key
So then this area of the brain
The defective area of the brain that makes these moods flip
On and off so
Intensely
Doesn't work as well and that stops a bipolar episode
That's so interesting that maybe it's sluggishness is what makes it
Yep
Although he says that same trip where can be a sort of sodium and posture
But slower
That can
Also causes
Slight Tremors in your hand you can have nausea
I'm taking affect the kidneys
The balance of sodium your body is regulated
Parsley to the kidneys and somehow lithium
Replacing it
Canby
Toxic to the kidney
Which actually brings us back to Jamie
After that episode
New York with Mike
In the video she went back on lithium and again she was fine fact for the last
16 years she's been
Completely
Normal
But then a couple months ago I went to a new primary physician mostly cuz I'm lazy and I didn't want to go to the Upper West Side
Side to see my other doctor and this doctor basically
Took my blood
Pressure and was like you're going to die
You need to go to the ER for kidney stone
Or failing and so she suddenly had to make this
Choice that I could turn over
Stay on lithium and
You know
Go to dialysis and get a transplant
Or that I had
And that now would be when I
What switch that I had enough function
You have you are in the middle of that decision now you feel like or do you feel like it
I think I'm going to switch I think I made that decision it's just that every psychiatrist
Stand New York leaves for August
Because I don't know why but they all disappear for August
All of August and mine said
You should probably wait
Just wait until I come back
But I
Feel like I have a good
Group of people around me I have
A solid job
It's terrifying.
Accord
Mania
But I also feel like there are a lot of effective drugs
And that one of them
Is going to work
Olympia Schoology
Depakote sounds like
God
Zac Brown right you're on Depakote
Ashley was in the middle of that decision Jamie did
One last
She actually took a trip to Bolivia
Which is where much of the world's lithium comes
Place you can go and
Literally see
Massive
Salt Flats
Just covered in mounds of love
I just wanted to
Experience am I wanted
To be near them
So I
When
It just looks like a hallucination it looks like somebody could not have conceived of this landscape
You know you have red legs
Send your flocks of flamingos and
Dislike
Long salty expanse
That goes on
Ever like it's just
You
Jessye Norman
Do you go up to a pile and
Put your hand on it
You stand on it and you jump off the pile and lady I was
Makings kind of lithium angels
And it was awesome
I know I have to go off of it but I really am
I mean gratitude is like not even the word
Feel like this thing
Allows me to be me
It doesn't Define me but it
Allows
Hino
Functionality and that
Sounds kind of wonky but it's like
Everyday
I get to work
And it's because of that like everything
You know I'm just
I'm grateful to it for its service I feel like it's done
Done a lot for for me
It worked so hard to get to me too
From The Big Bang to now
Pretty certain weather
A sword is made of elements
Do not have lithium which we should say
Only some of which was made in the Big Bang
Some of it was
Also made me super no one will have one of those coming up
Special thanks to Ben Lilly
Anne Harrington Kay Redfield Jamison seaflo and of course Jamie Lowe
James working on a book about her experiences with bipolar it will be called
Grand Illusions
This is a song from the band Sylvan Esso
We played them the last story in progress
And they wrote a song about it
It's not me talking to
Compassion
Another Nova on the way
It's not melee weapons
That was Sylvan Esso with Jamie song
You want to talk Bang
Hydrogen was there at 0 hundred hours in
The coke colored velodrome of dark matter
Gases chicken gases and infinitum
Chartreuse
Deafening birth
The cosmos cartwheeling
Yellow green purple
Blue-black in the Spear of night
First I was a
Star
Then a stain of water
Then
Kindergarten
These poems by the way come from two events that we held in New York City
We went to a emotive fruition which is a wonderful activation run by Thomas Dooley
Who is himself a poet he's summoned poets more on the metropolitan area for two nights they came to the Bell House in Brooklyn
Botanic lab in Manhattan and so far we have heard hydrogen by cerasoli read by Ramsey faragallah
Healing by Christina Quintana read by joniece abbott-pratt and I carried your oxygen
Upon by David Mclaughlin Road by Sam Breslin Wright
So next
I'm going to be three claps
I don't know if you need that
Just-in-case mechanic
Okay so a while back we ended up talking to a guy named Eric Mueller who makes a YouTube channel called veritasium
Super popular channel guide
Science and engineering week because he's making a documentary about uranium
And we got to talkin about what happens when you take two protons or neutrons and you just
Putting together
It's it's absolutely not
And that led to this really interesting conversation about
The beginning of all that
I feel like a little bit of back story is worth saying here
One really important thing to know
Is that combining nuclei
Gives you energy
He says when you slam two particles together they get squished
And in the squishing they lose a little Mass
That
Mask gets admitted
As energy
This is equals mc squared
That's what's happening in the Sun
So the sun is taking protein
Individual protons
And smashing them together combined
And that gives you energy
The energy of the Sun
They're lost mask
Is the sunlight
That we basket
It was math
I have never thought of
Light as
Former math that's what a star does he says it smashes little Adams
Like hydrogen together to make bigger atoms
Like helium and then big rats
Like carvana
Looks like oxygen and every little Collision
It's doing
Generate some energy
Which keeps the star going stars live
By this process of sticking nuclei together
Going from smaller nuclei
Making bigger nuclei the heavier the star the more the Smashing and bashing they can do in their core
A bigger and bigger nuclei
Inform but there are limits
6 million years ago there was a star
Giant star
Way to get nurse
It was just an Adams
The combining taking hydrogen atoms and making helium taking helium atoms in
Making carbon making oxygen and as its National is nuclei together it's releasing energy
Bigger and bigger and bigger
There comes a point
We're sticking nuclei together
No longer gives you energy
And that point is element number 26
Iron once you've formed iron
If you're a star
That's the end of life as you know it
Is iron iron is incredibly stable one of the most stable
Nuclei in the universe
Its protons are tightly packed in there until you can't
Force
Any more energy out of which means you have a core which is no longer
Going to give you energy you can't cook up anything higher than than the iron
What happened to the star does it just become a big hunk what happens
Everything starts to collapse gravity takes over
By the fact that there's all this energy
Going out
To the Dead iron-core starts
Pulling everything back in and if this point all of that stuff which is headed inwards aluminum oxygen carbon magnesia
Silicone starts rubbing against each other and it starts getting real hot
And reel dance
All of a sudden
You get
The supernova
That was the most pathetic Supernova explosion
So even though we know there are no sounds in space for the purposes of your enjoyment
We present to you
This Supernova here's the beauty of it
Here's the beauty of the supernova
In the ridiculous excesses of energy that are there in the supernova
Explosion the biggest in the universe there is so much energy
Is you for these nuclei
Which
Would not form
Under any other conditions
You know Iron is carbon to form germanium silicon hits oxygen to form
Titanium you start to get all of these bigger elements
Including like gold including the gold
In your wedding ring
Extreme ridiculous excess of energy to form
Is done
And what are you left with your left with a giant field of debris
Carbon and oxygen
Silicon
Helium
Clump together due to gravity
Together is our sun
Mostly hydrogen and helium in it
It's like 99% of all the mass in our solar system
And then the other trunks other bits and pieces start to come together as well
Outside
How you get the Earth
And all of us
This is where we got you so you're saying this is the birth of everything past iron
Exactly
Exactly but I think I can get it for the very first time
Post Supernova like in the in the middle of cycle
Supposed to whenever you have lots of the whole periodic table herlings
Through space
You really do
You can find Eric Mueller most days on his YouTube channel
Veritasium is documentary uranium twisting the dragons tail will soon appear on
PBS it has already
Pyridium
Kid on PBS in for some crazy reason
It passed me by
Coming up
A story that will make you wished
The Cold War wasn't
Not me not me I'm I'm happy it's over
This is Hester Fuller calling from the Northeast Kingdom of Vermont
Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloan at www.slha.org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
And I've requests
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
We're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments
Childhood brilliance
Basically I want to hear about those times when I kid you know did something
It just means you lean back and say whoa
Maybe it was the moment that our kids you've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed they're ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the specific moments where a kid does something super smart
Have anything to do with the test
If you have a story with us
Go to radiolab.org brilliance
Record short audio message
Message press
Again that's radiolab.org / brilliance
Thank you so much
Next Step
Producer Molly Webster +
Carmen Wright
K12 lunch
So
Science
With my sister's I just always go hashtag science
Cuz they get really sick of me trying to teach the kids science lesson
#science it okay so
One of the biggest mysteries in
Biology
How old am I
That
It doesn't seem like
Well I mean like obviously I'm
Molly Webster who's 32 years old who has lived
You know
232 birthdays I guess but this is a question of like
We know that some cells in our body regenerate
And so it's like
How old are those cells like how old is my heart right now
I like how old my eyeball or how old is my nose
The northwest
Corner of my kidney
It's just like you know if I'm 3 years old now I'm 33 years old do the cells in the 32-year
World are they the same as earn even the same as the one when I was three that
The question that's one of the questions in the same if they're not the same
Because if you understand that then you might be able to look like
Salve injuries help people heal faster or fix diseases where cells are
You don't messed up
Like psoriasis or anemia or ALS or something
Like that but also it just seems so cool to be able to be like oh that's
Chunk of my heart
Is from 1997
My heart is from 1983
At the party of Robert I would want to meet the original Roberts
Is there anybody who's been here since 1947 I'd love to just say hello
And if you just join me in 2015 well that's nice I mean night
One of the questions I've had for a long time is is there a way that we
Can try to date cell
Until the like we can't really send anything into the body because that can be toxic
So
Answer for a long time have been no
And then 2002's
This little idea pop
Stop
And it's something called the bomb pulse
Bomb by OMB and impulse
Pul SE
To explain
Forties and fifties we all know this we round way
Testicle out of atomic bomb
The first test with 1945 Trinity test New Mexico a few weeks later
Atomic bomb was dropped on Hiroshima and Nagasaki
World War II comes to an end the rest of the world just tries to catch up to the US
The Russians
Then after the Russians British
French bull Cold War basically just continues to unspool
All in all over 400
Atomic test
Schwinn off above ground between 19
1945 and 1963
Just imagine
If only one atom bomb would be dropped on an American city
Thousands of persons would be killed instantly
Gnosis sucky time
Well hashtag Zion
There's one good thing
Potentially one good thing
Popped out
And that is an answer to the question of how old are we
That somehow came out of the bomb test
Yeah
Hello how
Let me explain
Do it so with every one of those detonations
When atomic bomb goes off it would shoot a whole bunch of stuff up into the app
All these like radioactive elements like
Bcmud
Tony and all these things
Process that explosion shoots up a bunch of neutrons and then Neutron will crash into nitrogen
Floating in our atmosphere
And create
C14
Do very special type of carbon it has to
The particles in it
Now is all that
Bad radioactive stuff starts
Falling out of the atmosphere back to
The ground c14 doesn't fall out of the sky
I just heard a
Floats there
And what happened is overtime the wind currents
Carried c14 from these test site
And just spread it all over the planet
And the c14
Which is just totally like normal carbon
Not harmful
It is bonds with oxygen and it gets
Sucked up into plants
And then animals eat the plants
And then we eat the animals or we the plan
And then suddenly the c-14 is in US
So we all have like a little bit of the atomic age in US
Maybe I was even born in 1963 so
Why would it be in me that is
Cool thing because it hangs out in the air for a long time so it's
Is actually still up there
What does have anything to do with dating anything
Yes I'm about to tell you that
Hey you there
Yes I am
I'm principal called
I'm a senior scientist at Lawrence Livermore National Lab
Professor of stem cell research
At The karolinska Institute has become nearly 2,000 Jonas is staring down this question of like how do I date
And a certain point he gets
Together with Bruce
Because he comes up with this idea which is just l
Maybe we just look up there there's some groups in Europe is one in particular that's been measuring the atmos
Disappear every two weeks since the late 1950s images
Bruce says what the scientist have done is they've taken all of these measurements and they put them into one chart so you can see the
The amount of c-14 in the atmosphere over
So we we have this basically basically a calendar and I could I could send you a picture so you can see what
See what the graph looks like to see a picture
According to Jonas
Consadole in 1950
Define with all the bomb test
Victor siburian
Increase
A lot of carbon-14
Very dramatic increase that's why they call it a pulse
And that increase was all the way up to 1963 when
Historic events in the US the UK and Soviet Union agree to stop exploding atomic bombs
Of an atom Test Ban
After.
Fragile
Decline
You know they're just measuring it all the way down so they can just say oh like here's where it was in 1980
Here's where it was in 1990
Mm
This right here is the coolest part because
The amount of c-14 in the atmosphere
Any given moment
Is directly reflected in our cells
It's right so if there's like that much
C14 in the atmosphere in September 1972
And that is going to be mirrored in cells that were born in September 1972
So it is like this
Totally perfect
Birthday
We can see approximately how long have they been there for 10 years or 20 years or 30 years
It's like once this idea got out
Everlook scientists all over the world were like oh yeah
There's been a new invention
It didn't take long to see
This might be something cool to do
It came about because they made a big atomic bomb
So just to give you a quick sense of some of the work
It came out of this I spoke to one scientist I'm Christy sporting and I work
Karolinska Institute in Stockholm she was working with Jonas and they figured out how to use c14
In brain
I mean first of all the basic question was
Can adult humans make new neurons
She says that for like a hundred years so Dogma had always been that the neurons football movies are the ones who died with
The problem was she had no way to investigate this
Said she couldn't use it in humans
Even if they were dead humans
Until she figured out a technique where she could like extract brain cells
To see how much do you
14 was in there
Yeah exactly
It turns out the next best thing to Human
Is a horse
Because horses
Khalifa Court cemitas decade
So every second Tuesday
I would go out to the local abattoir
Bulova slaughterhouse
An hour away
And
I mean I was a vegetarian surrounded by caucus
And I would
Bring the horse's head out to
And I had to figure out how to get the brain out of its head
Wait what
You actually had to like
Cut open the skull and get to the brain yourself I'm in the second time I went I took my boyfriend with me
It's like I can't do this
Physically
They actually had a circular saw
And actually discovered that to the skull
The barn
Across the top the noise of the horse
Is quite thin so that was a much easier access
Point
Christ discussion did you ever see your research going that way
Xidan
Not at all
But what she saw when she finally moved her research from Horseheads
Humans
Was
Turn over
Which I'm quite Redbox levels of new neurons in adulthood
I think once you notice is team show that this
Work
Scientist got excited
And people started today thing
And not just cells
So
Pantages
The bassline ages we knew before
Was that the skin was like 14 days old
Working for Deloitte
Surface level of your gut
Skin on your gut I guess was 5 days
5 days even shorter than skin
Does that's like the surface of the intestine the surface
Yeah that's like
Embassy 14 the the deeper muscle apart of the intestine
The averages
18.1 years
15.1 years old big difference between skin 9 years old
That sells was another one that they did
10 years old
Yeah
Interesting why would a fat cell need to
10 years
Cuz it's perverted George.
They don't know
Do they know that like what would be one of the oldest part of us
Your your cortex which is like the
The part of your brain that does
Like abstract thinking
Or your voluntary movements
That's as old as you are
Really
If you want to know one of the
The oldest parts of
The oldest cell is probably in
Your pinky part of your brain
Cortical neuron
Will that fit
If I think of myself
As the stories I tell my
When you get Alzheimer's and you lose
Your stories and you lose your mind like people
But the interesting thing though is the hippocampus is where you keep all your memories
And they saw that your hippocampus
Does
Make a bunch of new
Neurons in the hippocampus
That's Jonas recent again
Jets approximately 1400 new hippocampal neurons
Per day
Really
Yeah and then each of those neurons will live like 20 maybe 30 years
So does that mean that the part of Robert's brain where he keeps
Stories he tells himself that part
Is being made new every 20 or 30 years yeah
Strange thing I like your oldest stories
Could be stored
In baby little neurons
He's weird
I remember going to
The Kyoto
And it's like
The oldest most
Temple
In Kyoto
It has
Exactly the form that it had
Spell hundreds
If years ago
But when you walk in
Though
The walls in the
Floors and
The roofing live Benrus
Stewart they can restore toxic over
And over again
Cuz in Japan what they call old
Is the Forum
Go to
Athens
And you go up to the
The Parthenon
They're you're standing in the very top
Pericles
The same
Same materials
So I can
In Greece they believe
That the original stuff is the
Is what you preserve and in Japan they don't
I think it's just the form
I was thinking of this thing you're doing is sort of a little bit like that like I was thinking I'm much more Greek than I am Japanese
Cuz I want to know like what my original cells are fit where they are in me but my question is messing me up more basic
Tickets like why does
Part of Me guitar
Reborn in
The other part to me don't like why not all of me
If all of you is being reborn you just
Crumble into dust
It's interesting because they don't know they said the next
They said basically
This question of how old is a cell they said no one was asking everyone wondered this but no one was asking this question cuz they never
Tools to ask
So now they're just starting to ask those questions
The problem
This bump also we've been
Dependent on in the last decade
To start answering all these questions
It going away
Really every day a little more that c14
Get sucked out of the air
So how much time do we have left teen years
It's gone by 2030
Give or take
So we need to get questions on Sat now
Because we really are working against the clock for many things we want to look at
I talked to his Alzheimer's researcher who is trying to figure out life
The chronology of the disease like when certain
Like pathologies form in the brain he was come just like I just wish I had a little more time
And when I think about this
Like I think about this on the subway this morning like I was looking around and I was thinking
Yeah I'm on the L train it's a bunch of like
30 year old kids or something and I was like these they're all reading or something drinking there
Expensive latte
Like these people are
So far away
From thinking about
Cold War
Atomic bombs or anything like that
And they're all walking around just like this
Secret signal from
Atomic. Inside of them and then that little signal is like banging out like now
Knowledge about their shoulder in their elbow and their liver in the westside of the liver in the east side of their flavor in like different parts of
The heart and the fact that it's now going away
And how like
Someone born in
You just made me really boring
And like they're not going to have any insight into who they are sort of makes
Inclined to very peacefully want to
No no no no
Why do you forget all the poisons that it that is not a benign event in Sturtevant
Experimental picker-upper that is
Extra
Stuff in the air dream what about
Only Young Thug play telephone
With One Sweep of power known by God
Producer Molly Webster
And special thanks to Henry druid
And Mark Levin Happy Valentine's Day magnesium
I go blind watching you burn magnesium
Iodine is cute
Sublimates
And yes I'll put lithium in water to watch
Kid Scoot About but my heart
Belongs to you
Magnesia
The hotwife laying the abandoned the slowness of you becoming your own fuse
Mercury is beautiful
But it's you Maggie
The way you burn for me
The way you leave nothing of yourself behind
We are flying over Greenland
Your elbow is too close to mine on the airplane armrest
Down there they are X
Excavating uranium from beneath the arctic ice and selling indiscriminately
Go from here
I can only see the white
Device sheet
Glacier Top Mountain
This is an island a fishing rig
Colourful houses
Cod and catfish
Stew in tomato cream
Once I thought every isotope in me
Is Radio app
I make the people who love me sick
This is a teenage way of thinking
But you have
Uncovered
A glowing
Spark
In the pristine
Frozen place
With Amy
That was uranium from poet Emily Hockaday read by Johnny sabat Pratt
Before that
Happy Valentine's Day magnesium by Jason Schneiderman performed by Sam Breslin Wright
Feeling right yeah
Coming up we're going to get into an elevator push the button and go down
All the way down
My Mother Does Colwich Chad Nicklaus have
Hi this is Pilar Castro from Bogota Colombia
Remind me to put it in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology
In the modern world
More information about Sloan at
Www
That's long
Hey I'm Jared I'm Rhonda and Robert Ulrich is Radiolab in today
Elements
Quit doing it with hydrogen and oxygen and nitrogen
Anaya TV Emporium into Layman's volume satirist Town lyrics
Okay so we have this periodic table of elements which is a list of the simplest
It's a matter that we know of
And it's so theoretically everything that we see
Everything we are is made of the stuff that is in that table
Blessed with beauty
Of the periodic table that it describes everything
45 years ago a scientist was studying
The motion of the Galaxy
Beautiful layer
Spirals better calculations did not
Plain why the galaxies were holding together and
Take a note this got to be some stuff
Why can't see around the galaxies that explain why they move the way they do
What is that stuff
Whatever it is
It's not interacting with the matter of our world
Hardly at all
Otherwise we'd see
Indeed why we call it.
Dark matter is a dominant
Massive component in the universe
Experimental physicist Rick Gates Co
Did the the stuff you and I made off the United States conventional protons
Is the Flotsam and Jetsam of the matter well if it sits cost on a sea of dark matter
We're talking about in terms of the total composition of the universe you win
The stuff we made over four and a half percent
The other 95.5% is this stuff the Dark Matter dark energy which theoretically
Around if you cup your hands you if you have a dark matter particle in your hand the problem of the challenge
Is that it is so weakly interacting that
It will pass straight for you and in fact will pass straight through the bed and will
I have very little probability ventrac
What if you get one of these little bastards in Iraq
Then
Forget the periodic table then you would meet the most fundamental element of them all city of lead historic
We're going to tell you about an experiment now this desire experiment and we send our producers and emails and Damiano marchetti
Check it out
Getting is this post it is happening in
South Dakota in the Black Hills in this little town called lead
And I've not seen this many trees
Set alarm
Incredibly beautiful picturesque little town but right near the town as you Crest over this hill
That's it
You'll see this mountain that looks like it's just been
Corn open
No we we pulled over and we walked over to the edge of this thing
And it was like tearing down into an ancient volcano that's not what I thought it would look like
In this town
There is one of the deepest man-made hole
I'm planning
That's where the experiment is
And it's there because
Way down deep in that hole
It's demonstrable
The quietest place in the universe
That is Kent Myers he's a writer
Don't make sense in second eroding article in Harper's magazine recently that is all about this experiment
And this whole
I was interested in the idea of these Frontiers at the
Where are you from
Frontier the movie Fargo
Jamaican says that this story
It starts off way back in the old west Hardy run to Wild rugged 1874 General
Custer and crew Custer comes out looking for this
Gold and finds it
Gold on the mountains and the rivers and in the dark.
Far below the surface of the Earth just like that 10,000 people within 2 years or just invading
Illegally invading the Black Hills which were of the great Sioux reservation and by 1901 the miners blast
1500 feet down by 1927 3500 feet down by 1975
2000 feet deep
To put that into perspective
If that's what's up mile and a half
Is a mile and a half
Imagine 6 empire state buildings going
Straight down and gold is that valuable that you could put
That kind of effort and energy isn't that astonishing
But what happened is that eventually the price of gold
Drop to the point where the size of the mine
What's the unsustainable mining 8000 feet down
Nina forever
What you go down your price increases your cost increase
You got a holic further you got to air condition the mine
You got to pump out the groundwater you have to run electrical lines down there you
And so in 2001
126 years of being an operation
The mine shut down
Metacritic ghost town I mean did the fear that we were just going to have the whole
The whole economy of this
Part of the country is going to fall apart
Barbie
As this was happening
We saw
An opportunity that these physicists realize that this was an opportunity
I don't like how I do physicists do
Are mental physicists do they love holes
Dwarves
This is where we get to that idea of quiet this experiment needs a kind of quiet
That you cannot find on the surface of the Earth
When you and I are sitting on the surface of the Earth when are acutely aware of it but we are being
Hit by cosmic rays at a rate that I think really rather amazes people
If you simply hold your hand out
Three or four times a second
Cosmic ray is going through your off hand and it's going right through it and that's every second
Say what you want your body is literally bathed in thousands of these every second
We are just being bombarded with
Add in
Ricky schedule
Talks about it like being in the middle of a
What's the stadium during the Super Bowl
And
This is is there everybody in this
Arena's clap
Now just imagine that in the middle of all this chaos there is one person
Leaning over to their friend
And Whispering a secret
Dark matter is like
The whisper
It'll be lost in the noise we have
The cut out all this noise
In order to even come close to hearing
And
It turns out putting a Mite of rock between you and the lapis's is taking you
A lot of the way that
Yes the greats now
Listen to this mine through these massive iron doors
Down these
Long underground tunnels
Into a room where we met this guy and who are you
Mike Stone Age grew up in Lead South Dakota I'm the
4th generation that's been
Hanging around homestake mine
Mike works at the mine so does his dad both my grandfathers were homestake veterans
Let's get that Mike went to school with and his dad went to school with they work in the mines and my grandmother's
Father on my desk
It was awesome
But now
Now he works in room where he basically
Equip scientist with other safety gear and stuff
David's Tea
Boots and a respirator
KicksOnFire you want to be able to breathe
What you want to hear
And eventually
If I'm in this old steel service elevator
Little farther
Subcage the 41
Laura Southgate
And then we just start rocketing downward
Ascending
At a thousand feet are ears pop
Wet muddy smell sort of walked up and asked we're dropping
All that noise is getting slowly filtered out
We're able to
Literally use the rock to absorb these cosmic ray particles after.
Donut shops
Hello
Thank you
And we step out
This is a caveman
It looks like
Kate it's got
A dome-like ceiling and walls that are just
Carved Rock what is that sound
That's the sound of rain coming through
A whole lot of Rock
Because it's not raining outside
It's not raining
In the world
It's just groundwater
It's costing over $1000000 a year
Just to run the pump
The drain
That why does that give you some $2000000
Yeah yeah
But Rick says
Down here
Like this is the least amount of radiation that we will ever experience in
It is quite dramatic it's about 3 million
Less
Cosmic rays
So when you hold your hand out
Let someone every few months
January
Coming for you and now
March
But that isn't that isn't the end of the story
Step inside here the very first step when she even have a nice day turns out that even if you cut out all the Rays coming from the outside
Side
Are there still Rays coming off of
You & I we carry a certain amount of uranium and thorium
Are these radioactive elements in
So
Okay
So what we're going to do is you're going to take your coverall saw Robin barland made us change clothes
Do you know
Yeah
Scumbag stuff
Oh the microphone
Okay
And then bring Texas into the Labyrinth experiment happens
If this all white room
What is huge tank metal
Tank contains 70000 gallons of high purity
Water and was directly inside at home we can without fear of disrupting experiment
Experiment actually happens inside this
Bang the outside of it
Steel container
The whole idea is that this water like she still trout even more radius
That makes it very quiet
Not quite
And so inside that tank of water
April even smaller tank
The element xenon about a third of a ton of liquid Xenon
Where do we find Xenon on the periodic table where it what is his seat on this number 54
It's over on the right hand side so that we have this
Imperial
Named
Set of elements week-old a noble element mean they're just too good for everybody else they interact
Hardly at all
That's right you really struggle to make Xenon interact with with any other atoms
Which is just another way of saying that inside of this tank of xenon which is inside of the tank
Water witch
Down in one of the biggest holes ever dug by man
It is really really really really
It's the monster
The quietest place in the universe
When you can't preview you don't know that it is because there could be somewhere some quieter place but as far as we know it
The center of Des Lux detector is the
The quietest place
We human beings now
And what's supposed to happen inside the super quiet Xenon
Space City idea
So you have here is that this
Cloud of xenon
It's just
Waiting
And the thought is that when a dark matter particle
That's like zooming around all the time when that zooms through this see.
Because it is so quiet in there
Because there is nothing else happening in there
That dark matter particle even though it's not supposed to interact with anything from our world
That particle
If it disturbs
Is it nudges in any way any of the atoms of the Xenon
Will notice it
Not tiny little disturbance
Whatever happened
Fences
You can think of that moment
Is the universe whispering
The Whisperer in human nature
The Whisper is a point where we really
We really want to speak
Intently
Do I single person we whisper
When when
And we whisper
Funerals we whisper in the presence of
Awesome things in nature we
We
Use of the voice that drops down
Town and drop starter only goes into the ear it's intended for it's it's Isaiah
Is call you know he's lying on his mad and he hears the whisper because he knows that for me alone
That calls for me alone and that's that's that sense
Get this experiment gives to me is it here the universe has been shouting and shouting
Scientific knowledge out of the shop out of the Clapping out of the cheers and now liver
At in the 21st century is
We're going down to what's it saying in the whisper and those Whispers Goku
Clear back to conception they go clear back to birth if we understand
These Whispers
Were very close to understanding
Gestation
And end
I got carried away there but we love Italy
Yeah
Okay and did you get to hear
The
Whisper see the disturbance whatever it is
Did you meet the dark matter
Well how can I give this to you lightly so this is confession time I've I've
Been looking for.
Yes
And so far we have yet to see a convincing
Satta
Interaction
Stop mattering
That's getting that nothing
It all nothing but Rick hasn't given up hope
I mean he's heard never gives up hope he says maybe we just need to build a bigger more sensitive to text
That's exactly what we're doing
Instead of their current one
Which has the third of it
We are now designing and building a detector
Cuz it's going to be 10 top
Says even there
Who knows the uncertainty we have to deal with his is is at least a factor of 10 million
Antoine TV the other pretty disappointing thing is that when you're in this room
Like in the room with
The Lux detector
Supposed to be the quietest place in the universe
Loud it's crazy loud
There's sounds that I can only describe is
Robot
Dying
Was there any moment that was quiet
Like YT quiet like deep quiet
Philly quiet
Well
Sort of after we went Deluxe
I have some time to kill and they took us into the wrong part of the Mind where these to mine for gold and they just
Walked us through these old tunnels
And you're you're walking through the black and all you hear is like the sound
Catching the wind speed suck down
The silence it's it's not like it's not like the science of like
Show the street is really quiet outside of my bedroom it's got like an energy to its like
It's kind of like when you're running and when you stop running and
Absence of your exertion to refills you it's like that moment where the absence of the noise sort of becomes
Palpable and that's for me
The moment not standing in the laboratory for me that moment with moment right now I am standing at the center
A busy not I don't think I ever ever have felt that
Producer Damiano marchetti and Annie Mills almost a year and it's been
Poodle pleasure he's moving on but we wish him
Would you like to wish him I wish him quiet with the good kind of quiet
Anaconda has energy
You know the won't won't won't my second thank you.
Original music this hour from one tricks point never Sylvan Esso Kevin drum can Camden and DJI
Loss with Matt kapustin to Connie Walter and to the folks at the Sanford underground research facility for letting us visit them
And stay and stay
90 leaves
Yeah
Which is what we're about to do I'm chat up and run by Robert krulwich thanks for listening
Message
2 News
I want to do this because I think all these peoples names are awesome I mean tell me you don't agree
Album Rock includes Brenna Farrell ellenhorn David Gable
Monster House
Who are these people
Like a crime-fighting team you know
Nadler Kathy to Molly McBride Jacobson and Alexandra Lee yeah
Dasher schellinger
Anyway thank you so much for having me on the show and
You might just want to go check that out
Real miniature
And this message