Eggs job before we get started on the podcast
Two things
First the MailChimp challenge with a little while back
We did
You guys did it
Media West if a certain number of you who became
Sustaining members MailChimp
Pigeon with money
It happened
We're super great
Thank you
We did it
Hey number 2
I want Elena that toward the end of this podcast
About to happen
Wait wait haven't been setup yet
You guys want to hang out until the
The Alice Echo
Why why do we have to be at the end
Can we just be up top
But that was the deal we talk this is my Rosa Parks moment and you know why we can say that is
Because we are
You're putting me in a box here at the end of this podcast
Come back and introduce you guys listening to two very funny people you just heard Phoebe Robinson Jessica Williams they're starting to pod
C Studios
2 Dope Queens
It's awesome
We'll talk about it
I see you got to hang out
Yeah yeah
Are you awake
Listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
Jad and Robert Radiolab
I'm going to just tell you the store
Just very briefly I'm going to tell you the story of three
Enormous mister
Pistou but you know very well and one of which I bet you've never heard of ever
Okay
Mystery number one
This is the one I know where the one I don't see the one you know
So about
4 billion years ago
The Earth is one
Huge mostly ocean of lifeless chemical
And then for some reason we have never really been able to understand lifeless chemicals suddenly
Per diem
Opposed
Can you get
Life hello yes I was just arrived.
Lake Macbride map
Nick Lane I'm a professor of evolutionary biochemistry
University College in London Nick is the main guy in the story I'm about to die
But just to continue this setup
If you're number one where does lice come from
Next
Mystery number 3
To make it morning
Think what about the two who is going to be the subject of the story and more important the middle one is the Deep
I'm surprised because you've never heard of it so I thought I would skip over to
To remind you how familiar you are with one-in-three holler at fine go to 3 and then come back at 2
Drake
Conscious
For some reason
For some reason one animal on the planet and only one that we could always seems to spring into this
Very elaborate sense
Of self-awareness we don't know why it happened you don't know how it happened
It just did it right
I'm familiar with 1-2-3 if you are not here is number two that's the one that keeps Nick up at night because
Does a kind of a gap a black hole with everything important in biology happened
We have very little insight into
What what it was
Black hole in biology
If you want to know what it is this black hole
Do you know you do
Mystery number
They were a little bit past 1 move away before 3
4 billion years ago we got life is just floating around
Blue specks in the ocean
Are very simple cell
Probably pretty much like code of a bacterium as we know them today this is very small. If you're looking at the
Period at the end of a sentence a is it about that size or smaller
A couple of
Thousands of a millimeter long
So tiny tiny things
They all look the same in this size and shape and they don't seem to be doing anything very interesting
They were having babies and they were using energy
But if you look inside one of these
Things
Not much going on
Is race replays often described as a bag of chemicals there they're not complex they're not
Complex simple simple as can be
And it goes on like this for millions of years and then
What ready to building is also
2 billion year
If not longer
You just have tiny tiny some
Chinese symbol bobbing bobber
Babysitting
Something in the way
Poppin Poppin Poppin Poppin nothing nothing nothing nothing wrong with it
Three good reason there is
You should know there is no rule which says life has to get bigger
We could have stayed
Infinitely small
100 billion years
Really yes really but then said something
As they say about 2 billion years ago all of a sudden practically overnight
A new kind of Life shows
And it's huge
At least first one
The actual volume when our around about ten thousand times bigger massive increase in size
Like we just jump from specs
The battleships and inside these things
Massive pieces of complex machinery
Becomes bigger
Bigger and more complex It ultimately
Leads to
Jellyfish
Giant redwood trees beluga whales
Beluga caviar wishes baby whale
Nevermind cherry trees hurdles Library tarantulas elephant
Paradise
Here's your second mystery
How did life for such an enormously long time safe
So simple
So dull and so tiny and then
You got these big life-forms
What happened
And why did it not
Happen for such a long time
Well I are you going to enlighten me with such as to answer is yes but I want you to remind you this is a few
When making a hypothesis
Who knows really exactly what happened during we're never going to get whenever going to find life
Found footage
That moment right
We can we can only imagine if we can only use the evidence we've got now
That is it young I'm a science writer at the Atlantic
It's the guy who introduced me to Nick Carlson X work and
Experiential here's the important thing to
I'm not doing those two billion years when nothing much happened but life didn't get it
It it's that life
Couldn't get caught
There is
A barrier there is an energetic
Canyon
But simple cells
Find themselves
What
It means that it's a huge deal
Should try to get thinking about what it takes to get bigger
Six-figure cell wall
Fix my Surface
More openings let things in which they got more power in my moving parts and then to make the whole thing fit and work together you got to have
A bigger design planets or DNA so you're going to need more DNA
And all that DNA needs to be copied
You're going to need some DNA copy I need to read the information that's encoded within it
Do you need to use that information to build proteins and some Builders I'm about lost but this is
Especially costly
So you don't get bigger
Free every new Step takes extra energy
Just like if you were going to you know if you're going to increase the size of your company by a thousand times if you're going to have a
A thousand times more employees
You're going to need to pay them all
Where you going to get the money
I mean you and I we might be able to go to a bank
Little thing you don't have any place to
How do you get bigger
I mean can't you just eat
More food than you normally eat
So that you get more energy so that slowly over time to get bigger
I mean by you could do that
But suppose you don't have to
Stomach to absorb
You make a stomach somehow
The stomach
You got to eat more food to build
Eat more food you can have the stomach when you can't really have the stomach let you eat the food you can't eat the food what you have.
You just stuck in a hole kind of a catch-22
Yeah you're sucking what what could cause a young and energetic
And climb over the walls of that Canyon and to start
Experimenting with complex
You need something improbable
You need something very special
So special and so improbable that according to this Theory over the course of all of our planets has
That has only happened successfully
Once
What what happened
But here's the thing
His life
Bopping along it's boring boring
Boring way everything is
Very tiny
Very simple and then one day
Two single celled
Creatures
Start to drift
Gorgeous women.
One of them is an archaean little Bob and one of them is a bacterium
Under The Blob
They they belong to the two great houses of simple things in with the montagues and capulets
Solve 2 billion BC
These two little cells start to get near each other slowly
It was he sell One Soul the other one has to offer Nick imagines that I don't know maybe the little one was
Expelling some kind of chemical that lets a is some hydrogen gas just for the sake of an argument
That's what he wants and maybe the big one spits out
The nitrogen which is what the little one wants Olathe
China come together they smuggle
Totally ordinary thing happens all the time with c
But in this case
Stop smuggling gets closer and closer until somehow
Those who sells meat
And
They much
They just squish together how they merge
You know membranes fuse cell walls don't always full maybe the big one it had a hole in its walls
Fell through hole I don't really know what the mechanism is
But we do know if
The point is somehow this little guy jumps into the bacterium
Find itself inside the arcade
That's the first thing I
Guy gets inside another look
Like I tell you this is this is this is extremely rare
Cells don't get inside other cells when they do get inside of the cells for the most part
Doesn't work out
Because if you're this little guy on the inside now you're trapped you can't get the things you want to eat it's cut off
From the outside world and chances are it will die
Which is what happens you know 99.999% of the
Not this time
If it's a swallower is capable of of bringing in that outside world and feeding it
Food and feeding it to it
Swallow if you like then then it will work
Maybe that's what happened to your sister maybe the big sale had some kind of mutation that allowed it to keep
Eating the little salad spinner
Eliza Doolittle sell survive
And thrives
Because the second thing that happens here
Is a little cell in the inside
Struct device
Excel with two cells inside it maybe then. I was inside it
Which if you're a big cell
Normally not a great
Situation you find yourself with
We guessed inside you imagine having a house party and the gas won't go away
The cost of producing more guests
I was going to be a ride is going to be a mother or something
The point is his neck when you get to this point it really shouldn't work
But somehow
It did
But not only did one cell get eaten
Will Survive even rear
And then divided without creating a right even rarer but then somehow this big sale finds ways over and over
Taking care of moles
Do new houseguest
Amerileather they're all stages of that life cycle you got some old folk in there and you got some babies in that or not how you going
Going to do it while you probably need to
I put in the Maternity Ward first of all to look after the baby's let's
Yeah that's that's that's putting some kind of clinic for for end-of-life for the for the foot today for the geriatrics
Sauna
This big Sal is able to construct all this new Machinery inside itself
To keep this extraordinarily various group of houseguests
Happy
Why
Why would it bother I mean like what is the
What is the cell get in return and youth you said
Said it didn't have enough energy to build itself bigger so how is it even doing this
Well now you're getting to the real number of the store
The key here says Nick is those little house guests are living now in the Big South
They're not ordinary house
Very very specific kind of bacteria that we now call mitochondria
And if you look at the descendants of those little guys who live in us right now they have
An amazingly strong
Electrical charge
Let's order
Radiates
Across the membrane
On their outside
An electrical charge
Is
At least it's the tiny it's a hundred and fifty million
But if you shrink yourself down to
The size of a molecule
I'm feel the strength of the electric field right next to. Membrane is it exactly
230 million volts per meter which is equivalent to a bolt of lightning
This is what the big show gets back cuz it's return gift
Lightning
And it's this new electricity that gets it
It helps it find all these new adventures in construction project
Now they can
Support
Enormously large adenine so you can have
Bad bacteria may have one or two copies of a gene you cannot have
20 or 30 maybe 50 there's no penalty for doing 7 what I want that gives you as a kind of a redundancy that allows
Different genes to do slightly different job so to diverge to
No you do call the scope to experiment to try things out
So you have one group going off to become algae and plants in another group becoming animals in another group becoming the funky and
The Descendants did
So well
They've taken over the world
And they all came from that
One single
Coming together and that one you knew yes it comes down to one merger between two cells
That made one cell
And then everything comes from
Yume redwood tree of the hummingbird
Fungus
He's about to be growing in a pond
Every type of light that we can see with our Naked Eyes
And many that we caught
I'm coming from that single cell
And what does spawns says Nick is is this is how we get the great tree of life that we see all around us
Hector
Eons and eons of sameness
Send me to get this Many-Splendored Thing That is nature
It starts right here but we're looking at
Is truly the Second Genesis
Play okay hold on a second hold on
How do we know any of this actually happen
All that that all of the life that we can see comes from one cell how would we possibly know that
Well starting with us
If you if you go in and look at the genetic material inside ourselves
About half of all dreams
Little bit less than half
We find them in bacteria or archaea
Mixes you can see very clearly that the original DNA of those two cells
Two cells are merged into one
They're inside us
Stupid ass that sequence in the structure has remained
Kind of almost intact
The two billion years and just the structure of yourselves alone provides an important clue if you look at the cells of old
All those things if you look it but take one of your cells
And one cell from that fungus so from the spruce so from the whale
Unless you were
Unless you are next Messi been trained in this
It would be very hard
To tell the difference
Between those
In other words all of ourselves
Lacrosse animal
Plants
Something like those original
Very very similar they will have that nucleus that's internal skeleton they would have mitochondria those are the
Lightning bolt
Descendants of that first of all.
They got swallowed you know we have
40 trillion cells on each of those has got less a on average mm mitochondria so that they know that
A tremendous number of mitochondria in one human being
On the giant redwood tree has a lot more than that
And so does the worm I'm so
From that point of view just
Biomass we are about 40%
Mitochondria
So just from biomass
They are possibly the single most
Prolific
Life-form that ever existed
Okay you got me
I do like this
I mean it is also like
You know it's a little bit like
It's a pretty certain we learn who chimed in as we were working on this
Remember our guy what was
His name from the floppy ears
Kind of witch
Is that Richard Richard
Consists of
Finding energy
He had that thing about he wrote a book is all a long time ago but it was all about actually talk to him at the time human and such
Pictures of going along doing their thing and they're eating
Draw leaves in the forest same way that chimps do now but then once they learn to cook once you start cooking
Does a terrific advantage
Cooking would break things down and then once
Then you don't have to break things down inside you which means that you're putting less
Energy into your food but getting more out of it. Increases the amount of energy that you can get from your food by 25
3040 50% maybe more
Mysterious but that
That is when we got smart
Because we were in again an energy Canyon
Where was just
Given what was around you and how much work it took to break it down to the parts you need you couldn't do much until you light a fire
Fire underneath it
And and you like a lightning bolt
And you break it down so that you don't have to do that work cuz now the fires doing that work when you put it in your tummy and you get all the goods
Would have to work
And now
Now you have time
An energy to make a brain
They can think about
That is when
The genus homo
Humans
In the first
Full flowering
All the sense of that word
Image
Wow that's a
To the energy Canyon sleeping
Theory might actually
Touch on mystery number 3 to the conscience one
Cooking is an act of intentional I mean it you know when you decide to light the fire and
Put the meat then you're doing something that you and
Intend to do
To me is when you go back
To the original
Pairing
Just pure xidan
I meant so much
Blood flow from something
Incompletely cosmically ask
Occidental
That's that's
Really really
That merger and the
Harmonious continuance of that merger
Was so breathtakingly improbable
Only once today
Nick says it only happened once
2 billion years
And there's no evidence to suggest that it is
Happenstance
So there is no
Trajectory
Two Worlds
Necessary complex life or university
Pregnant with the idea reverse there's nothing about the way that he pollution has worked
On Earth
Just suggested
Complex life is
Uninhabitable out
And if this hadn't happened with the Earth just be still rich with with little
I don't know life ones that are smaller than the
The grain of rice that's
All we'd ever got
I think that's a I did does that mean that you have to have this incident
On planet xandar
And Planet zantar 36
That's really interesting right I think when we think about
Finding the prospect of finding alien life
If we think
The universe the universe is so vast
That we cannot be alone. That must be life on other way
I think what this
Tells us is that
We will probably find life elsewhere but it will probably be microbes
It was in a did the offensive
The odds of finding
Something
Like the aliens that you would you expect right so do what they'll do Finding Your Star Wars Cantina
All significant
Gilda finding like a bacterium somebody probably
Reasonable
You might find life but maybe it's going to be
Boring
We could leave it right there
But you know you probably won't get killed by the Monte Vista.
That's a good thing that's
Nicholas book on the series called the vital question
Special thanks to Eric Steinberg
It's worked on this podcast and two Richard wrangham whose book is Catching Fire at youngest forthcoming book is
I contain multitudes
You can find all these references
Our website
Radiolab.org
Yes this is what this
To County mates
After the break
Which
Stick around
Hi this is Sharon
From sunrise
Florida radiolabs support
In part by the Alfred P Sloan
Enhancing public understanding
Science and Technology
In the modern world
More information about Sloan
. Sloane. Org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here I'm a producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
About what we're calling tiny moments
Brilliance
Basically I want to hear about this
Times when a kid you know did something
It just means you lean back and say whoa how did they do that
Maybe it was the moment that I
Kids you've been reading to 4 month started reading back
Do you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lesson
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed are ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the specific moments where a kid does something super smart but doesn't
Have anything to do with the test
If you have a story
T-shirt with us
Go to radiolab.org
Brilliance
Record short audio message for us
Fan that's radiolab.org / brilliance
Thank you so much
Just a heads up I Spy
Chica and a breve
So I just say things like
Totes
And Mike
Early twin
I'll just go with it I'd like I know what you're saying
Get here as promised at the top of the show I want to introduce you to a new project that comes from
Two very funny people
My name is Phoebe Robinson
And I am
Michael Fassbender
Future Baby Mama
My name is Jessica Williams and I plan to be the maid of honor and Phoebe and Michael
Oh yeah
You're okay with that mean literally just put myself in your steak what obviously you're in the wedding
Jessica Williams and Phoebe Robinson art
2 people who are obsessed with Michael Fassbender I don't even think he's that hot
Now that's so
Commercial and they are both Comedians and writers Phoebe his work for MTV and Comedy Central
Jessica Williams you might know from The Daily Show where she decorrespondent
And two of them 15 dup to make a podcast
Called Stadium today it's called 2 Dope queens and my bet is it if you like Radiolab you will also like the five cat
Where can I buy old wine
4 second
There's nothing else for you to be
SoDo
People still use the word Delta
All it takes is like to black people to make something
Yeah that's the rule we came and we walk down the
Streets around we had our shoes on
As long as it's two black people doing it
Hello Kris Kross when they did the the genes it was just going to put them there.
How did you guys meet
We met
Almost two years ago I was doing a background on a
Black hair in the military peace
For The Daily Show
Stories Jessica is doing the segment DB
Part of the segment one thing leads to another Vice Jessica to co-host
Comedy think she was doing like a live thing
And she says the moment they got up there on stage murdered
Homicide first-degree murder murder movie
This feels really good
We should do this more often
And so we're like always
You know like I like my
We start dating like hell yeah
Who got a movie or like
Oh yeah we're going to the mat
And what
Just keep seeing how things going to end
The date and then after a while it's it a morph into something that is
Are baby we made a baby we made it baby
My favorite read customer service thing is never in my
My life
2 Dope Queens is a live comedy show that happens at Union Hall here in Brooklyn gently what happens is Phoebe
Me and Jessica that get up on stage and just kind of Rift
I think if you're in the audience we really want
I feel like you're hanging
Hang out with us to the get up there this year to go back and forth for a while then we have
Some of our favorite friends or stand up
Comment
That's in between
Yeah yeah
I wanted to share this thing that my girlfriend and I have been doing
Like this comedian that Phoebe and I both love and him Gary gulman
We we role play
Like the other night we're playing Secretary of Housing and Urban Development
But here's the here's the twist she was Secretary of Housing and Urban Development I was deputy secretary of Housing and Urban Development
All the stores that stores that status thing she was my boss and I
I didn't feel she was pushing her agenda hard enough how is he
Then we come to Washington to make friends
Attempt to make changes
Then we have people like Michelle buteau and who's really funny and she does stuff a Comedy Central a lot of places
Clip of comedian Michelle
Obito
Telling story about how she met this guy and I was like oh my God this is the one like we're going to move in together we're going to live by the mall
And he came to visit me in New York one time about the cell phones while on the bed and they were exactly alike and it rang and I picked it up
And this girl was on the other hand she goes
Is Eric there
And I go who this
And she go who it is
If I go
Who dis
This went on for a real long time
Cuz we knew who this was
Casey said the next to the Naomi
Yes but who is Naomi
Who is Naomi
Paragon
She's a younger woman that she
Is practically an old lady like all she wants to do is she says in her stand-up is like sit at home with a blanket in
Play with her cats as you can imagine I love to watch procedurals
Halibut okay
I love--my Criminal Minds is my number one I do like classic Law and Order but I do prefer a special victim
You know
Yes I just love it I love it I love it
It's it's amazing how every episode
Is MBA the white women in Peril you know it's like a white woman's in Peril that's how we get people to care you know
It's just nonsense
If there's one thing that we should be taking away is it like
White ladies okay Megan
Peceras
Becky's okay
You guys have got to stop
What's a jogging at dawn and dusk
Stop
I hate to do Jesse Jackson but if the light as well you should not go are you following me
Are you following me if you're jogging at those hours you got two options
Okay
You're either going to find a dead body
Call my dad bar
You always like to have women represented
Doing stand-up or storytelling on our show we met
Episode and people different orientation
Is people of color like it
Really really fun
And I hope that like if you come to see the show or even if you stay
They'll see that we really love
I just want a hilarious
And I think we
Really did deliver on
Yeah
Phoebe Robinson and Jessica Williams from the brand-new WNYC Studios podcasts
2 Dope Queens
Definitely check it out
Go to iTunes or wherever you get your podcast from and check them out two dope Queens
Thank you
Jad abumrad
Radiolab
Produced by
Directory sign design
Chanyeol
Simoniz products around
Melissa
Ariane what
Molly Webster
With help from
Alexandra Leigh hunt Alexandria VA
Stephanie X
Michael Owen
EBay
Michelle Harris