Northern listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
So before we get started I had to
A couple questions for
Yeah please find a way so I talked to a lot of pee
People who use
Temperature
Contact there's a lot of
People
Just don't have faith in Media
Consideration
Rihanna
XY control
I got a couple questions for you
Cuesta way
Why now
Why do we want to do the story now
Yeah well
It's a it's a
Abby Abby discount story
Olivia
We did we were it was unknown to us until right
Fitness feels a little newsie of the moment
This is Robert by the way
So we have Robert we
Jad Jad
Yes
Yeah we should I guess
Do you have any other questions I'm sure we can wait we can table though
So what is the Ingo
What what do you want
The Story 2
We never know that
Okay
Hey I'm Jared I'm Robert krulwich Radiolab today
Today we're going to tell you the story of a guy
Is it a guy named Ryan wash he's part of the movement of people who've taken this
Established corner of the academic world
And Eve
Is Avery shaped it reframed it
Into something even weirder and more different
Weirder
No way I'm not weird bad.
Interesting
And debate lingo that's a link
That's a link usually when you run a criticism the link is the
The thing that they've done
Oh okay
What can I can I can I put a lesson
Can I connect let's go to Bentley
Okay so the world that were talking about witches
The center of this
Obviously debate
Yes high school debate and College.
Now I have an elevated the base but from the outside it always seemed like this
Hyper-competitive
Brainsport accordion briefcase where they have all these
Miles in there with all the research and they go to these tournaments
And they argue about some topic back and forth and back and forth and back and forth
Note the interesting thing about the bay I didn't know this
Beforehand is it the people who do this
Stop & Go on to become
Hugely powerful people you don't Supreme Court judges
President
Leading thinkers Scholars Titans of Industry the farm team of the big folks for tomorrow so Lee Iacocca from Christ
He was a debater Margaret Thatcher Ted Cruz Karl Rove Hillary Clinton Oprah Winfrey Richard Nixon
Malcolm X they all were debaters
Today
This is Ryan
Story Ryan washes
Story of debate
Actually
Ryan Street debating
Yeah yes
And the story comes from reporter Abigail
Killed before we get going so let you know there is
Strong language in the story
Profane words
Skip it if you need to
Otherwise
Is it biblical for jumping right now
I would love to know Ryan like
What was your life like
Before you
Wherever on Adams
Well Kansas City Missouri in the city
Public school you know
99% black students
I was actually tricked into debating
I really had
When was it when it when was this so we're talking about
Oh well
Mm I'm sorry I'm old
2005 when were you born
If you send your old 1990
But yeah
I ended up getting tricked into the bay
I'm almost definitely a more of an observant person which is why I like to play the game of chess
Because
You know how people move their pieces the time
Listen to move their pieces all gifts
You know something
Fairy tales
And so I was tricked into the babe
By playing chess
And I ended up winning the school chess tournament that we had and
This little short German redhead lady
Name Jane Reinhardt
I came to
Chess practice I ended up being present
Temperatures practice one day and put me in the hallway on
I understand you you know you were chess champion and that's a really good thing and we had this debate program and I thank you
I'd be really good at it
You know anybody who can critically think a chance to critically think
Yeah yeah I don't even know what to say was
No no
Fat
So over this
Next year she kept on telling me it's just like I thought I told you to join the pain I thought I told you to join today and I was like
I thought I told you know
I can spot a debater at
20 pesos
Okay you think I'm playing so 1 Monday I came to school she handed me a p
Piece of paper it was a revised schedule she had my schedule changed
To where I had the bait first
Sour
Here you are
A lot of eye debater
I just come and kind of days
My schedule got changed
Okay that's fine
That was first day of classes Ryan's learning the basics of
And in this kind of debate that he's doing school policy debate
There's two teams and two people in need
Usually the debate is about some kind of national policy
Like
The United States government should increase
Economic engagement in
One team at the beginning of the debate is randomly assigned to be affirmative
And that means they're supporting
.
Who sang yes the United States federal government
Should do that
Here's why
The other team is the negative
And they're arguing against
Different
Both of those ice maker
The judge decides
Who made the better record
I mean I get him up debating
Almost daewon
We ended up having mock debates in class like Pepsi verse
Cisco can you know
Family Guy versus
The Simpsons
But that sucks it wasn't very fun it made us learn how to do impact
Impacted
Analysis
So for instance
Let's say you're debating apple versus orange
If I say the rinds
If apples are necessary for the fertilizer
Produce Orange
Just so you must go for apples
Impact of choosing apples over oranges
You have to be able to compare the two and make art
The traditional stand for
Is rain started learning all this impact analysis Holman's model of argumentation
Started the Depo Palace logo if you really well
Yeah he did
Tournament is one of those activities that afford you the possibility of traveling places
Where I grew up and went
The school I mean students didn't leave like a 40 block radius for their entire life
If you're in control and activate
And everybody's listening to you
And
I think it's
It's important to feel that way even if it's only an a
60 90 minute debate
Ryan needed those win
He needed
I was enjoying
That affirmation
The thing that helped me out was that
My first
Tournament
Was
Anime canvas in eternal
Debate Kansas City is urban debate league
And so we were debating other kids from the same neighborhood
What's the difference
Schools
And so that environment
Of debate was
To me very different like yeah we wanted
Knights win
But there was a lot more, ratterree in the debate
And so to me by the time I went to my first national
I was very much
But once I went to that national tournament for
First timeout
Okay I don't know
National Tournament
You're up against what I call name brands
Predominantly private schools and so we were really excited about that but I will dress clothes on
Bakugan the bus started kicking a little bit just by going to the Bay tournament got off the bus went inside
And then
We went to the cafe
Syria
And when we open the door to walk
.
The room
Pilot
I mean when I tell you the talk
Wingstop literally
300 other Plus student
Stopped and stared at us because a bus
The Blockheads
MAA like watch
That's the whole time
At least that's how I feel
You know but
We walked over to our table
Look like
Do not worry about them
Pull out your things
Get warm.
And so
Got our stuff pulled out
Starting to practice
They started
Yeah whether they were Whispering about the bait stuff for about us I don't know I wasn't in there
I can definitely explain to you what that felt like
It was real
And making things even more awkward and more uncomfortable
The ball is that when the debate actually got going and this is particularly true at the national level
This
Is wet debate
It sounds like
What is it
Sped up
This is what do they sound like today
What the goal of speed-reading are spreading if you Willis to get more arguments
And apparently and this is like
Digression
This kind of thing actually started in like a 19
60th and the students are actually the ones
Uber driving
What are things that makes debate such an interesting intellectual game is that it's much more of a bottom
Up driven activities in a top-down
Activity director of debate at the University
Arkansas
In the case of speed
We evolve the situation where
One team decided Well I'm going to
Presente Target
The other team
Talk slower and Aaliyah
You didn't answer two of these argument
So
You lost a debate because you didn't answer those really well we need to answer all eight of those arguments
Has gone way too far
It's not as if you didn't know how to do that
That's the way I've debated I did try to
But he says
Somewhere around the first national tournament
Just kind of stopped making
Like the fast-talking
The fact that
Yadada babies super you know highfalutin topic
I felt as if
I could never take any of
The stuff that I learned
Intubate
And take it back to 33
Askew what
Where I live
And this isn't just you need to ride
I mean what you say at the stage in debate is that a lot of kids like especially Inner City
Kids from public schools black students
You know they just start to drop out of debate at a certain point
Ryan
Brian didn't do that
Now something big is going to happen
Somebody's going to say
No what happened was it stay at a student from University Academy and she was a senior
Her name was marshawna
And she went
She came over and asked around heart
She needed a partner there was about to be this tournament called
Casey Casey
FeFe
TLC tournament
The big high school debate tournament and marchioness
Who's older than Ryan but
She needed a heart
So
Changing Rinehart and Jane said well
So met with marchon eyewear
What's the first day before
The tournament happen
And I pulled her into this room and I had Oprah had
Three boxes of Evan
You know and I was ready to go with me
The topic was whether the US
Increase participation in
National service programs
Peace Corps
Armed services
And I'm like all this is the stuff that I've been working on that shoulder the learning serve America stuff I had this
Find Peace Corps affirmative that I hadn't wrote yet
Statistics on them
You know and she was like
Yeah and so she hadn't made this expando and was just like okay
Take this folder
Go home
Study it but I got home and I open this
Expand Ln
With all of this
It was full of things and I stayed up literally
All night
Studying
File
I mean it was not a lot of evidence there was not a lot of pre written out answers to arguments there wasn't a lot of that
There was some things that were there was Ralph Ellison I am
And invisible
There was a clip from Ralph elephant you know Invisible Man in there there was
Lithium desert Twisted line
Maya Angelou poem in there
But still like that
There was some original stuff that she wrote
And I'm like I
I didn't get it
But she was kind of told me you know let her
And I'll drive the ship
You just ride along
Okay
So
Next day we get to the first debate I still was very unclear when we arrived at the tournament
Just was going on
Get to the classroom and standing
Other side of the room
Are there two of them
Are they white kids mostly yeah they were white guys in
Suits with Republicans
If you want to know if you wanted images
The other team there affirmative
So big
And they're like
Service programs
Broad
SI she gets up to give this speech in that starts with this like
4 minute long piece of spoken word
Speech kind of about her personal experiences to be this way of speaking
Was very
Passionately Force
It made people.
They stop writing they stopped talking
In the middle of this riff
Marshawna laid out this Ark
That the style of debate
Did they engaged in that fast pace
Form of debate
Was exclusionary because it demotivated minority
Students from participating
And not only that like it also creates this
Resorts in Bali
Because if you're going to start
Debating with
Ton of argument
Help researching those arguments so you pay people and you paid coaches help you make those arguments and that's clearly favors
Rich and affluent schools
And beyond that
Marshawn argued
Even the language itself setup a norm of what counts
Intelligent
Authoritative
For instance like men's voice to be held up over women black people to always seem angry and rude
I'm going to just being passionate as if they don't
I feeling you know it was a criticism of the auctioneer style of debate it was a criticism of the insular lingo up
Debate over the criticism
Of the way in which debates were decided socially and politically as a
Opposed argumentative
So
I was like I was like okay I can use it with you
No I wasn't shocked I was like I was like I was like damn ever the greatest
Slaps like we was at the poetry slam but I was sitting to myself thinking like
Am I going to extend this like when it got to be his turn
What's left for him to say I don't know what more what other words
Back at you
And so it wasn't until the second person from this team got up and he started
Speak and he was like
You know
Debating about to say this Brave this is a this is disrespect
Go to the state of debate and he turned to her it was a
This moment he turned to her
I he said it like from
So
You should go down the hall because
That's where portrait poses help visit academic
Debate
What
And he basically his argument was that what we were doing was
We will we were having one
Talent show
I was just like
I get it
I can maybe it was a study and I had done all night but everything kicked in that moment what happened came into the room
Like I get everything that she was trying to say what
She was saying about the structure of debate because I had felt those things before I just didn't know how to articulate them
What's it like I get
Did I can
What's it like
Commissioner get what she saying like the bay
And let's just say we definitely went on to
You won this match
Yeah we won the debate because
Let me just explain what happened in the
Judges
In this kind of situation have a choice
Price Rite
Like they can hear the arguments that Ryan and Marsha on arm
Making and they can think of
Really about the piece
Peace Corps or about armed services
Is so
You lose
Or they can do what the judge in the state
They can say all right
Topic has kind of ship
But let's look at what we haven't
Let's look at the argument
Ryan marshawna saying.
The structure of debate is
Racist
And then you've got the other team not really responding in any kind of like
Counter argument attempt way
Ryan in this debate what does is he
Key points of thought he points it when this other team says leave the room and he says Hey like
What they just did
Cruzar
That we are
Excluded from
And the judge agreed
Oh so you use you use his sort of you use his you don't belong here as
A kind of
As a as an article about our evidence in
Came for a lot from what happen
In the debate
Fascinating let me just take that guy site like so that you're changing the whole
Really gets going there's no racism hegemony like I'm a racist
Going to be what is he supposed to do like
Wingstop
The first off
Diesel stop
I mean I mean you don't have to say you're right this ain't nobody going to want to admit that they're racist
But you can definitely
Admit that you've been gation races Praxis or you can have a debate about whether or not that was erased
There's a healthy debate to be
We had about that button
What he said was that you all do not belong here
Leave the room
Like if you walk in and you say what you just said
And you say it forcibly in eloquent
I hate you're changing the rules here you're breaking things down to leave the room and then in the leave the room they'll even so
Kohl's open to this counter
Talk to you give
Like it's still it's still
I just mean that you'd wear a vest and so this is a thing there
Very few rules
To the Bay
But there is
Kinds of norms
And depending on
You know
Community of debate
The space of debate that you're in those Norms May differ
But I only know of a few rules like there must be a winner and a loser
Time limits with an obscene that be debatable at times
There must be
An affirmative and negative
Other than that how one
Approaches debate
You know how one approach
Just the topic how one approaches themselves in their house
Position all of that stuff is
Debatable and arguably should be
What is it there's no like
Bible
Of the of debate to there's no like
Okay so they eat
Put out things like the NDT rulebooks like affirmative teams
Must be topical butt in the world of debate what does it mean to be
You know what does it mean to be on
That have to be debatable in order for the debate tonight
I'm just curious if you're really good at this I can you give me Parts me what you would have said if you were the guy
Guy cumming
After you
Before you
Well I'm one of the things that they needed to do in particular what's the phase of the debate itself shouldn't
P about the bait they were trying to say that but what they said was y'all shouldn't
I see that's interesting sick cuz cuz that's one of them up later I have sympathy for the other side is is
This weather like
I thought we talked about the Peace Corps
Like they walked into the wrong room
Or something but that was one of our argument was that how do you do debate how do you prepare
Just made them activity for hours and hours and hours
This week's opponent
Couple weeks
Arguably years are years and years
And not ever think about
Why you debate the way that you
That was what we were press
So what was the other teams react
They were really upset
Yeah they caught
Really
Yes
What do you mean no
That's
We'll be right back
Mrs. Miss Ms
Calling from her eighth grade
Tree costume
Read aloud
Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public
Meaning of Science and Technology
In the modern world
More information about phone at www.
Sloan.
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your
And I request
For those of you who spent a lot of
Timer kits
Parents aunts and uncles teachers
We're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments
Basically I want to hear about this
I kid you know did something
It just means you lean back and say
Wow
How did they do
Maybe it was the moment that I
Kids started reading back
To you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lesson
And you suddenly noticed they were doing
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed are ready music
In the margin of the geometry
We're interested in the
Epic moments where
A kid does something
Super smart
But it doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story
T-shirt
Go to radiolab.org
Brilliance
Amber Court
Short audio
Again that's radiolab.org
Flash brilliance
Thank you so much
Hey I'm Jenna Cam'ron I'm Robert krulwich Radiolab and it's back to our story again from producer Abigail keil
Which is story about
A guy named Ryan wash and about
Debate
How we debate
Yeah so
Just to kind of like
Pull back from that moment with Masha and the
Katrina all that
This kind of thing wasn't just happening in a back
Like it actually
Came from all kinds of different places all at once and one particular interesting person
He was influencing it was
George Soros
Soros Soros was fascinated by the bait that's Dr schnierow Reid Brinkley
She's a scholar and a big figure in the so-called black tube
Soros thought that debate was one of those kinds of activities that was incredibly
Important to the production of democracy
So he started funding debate programs over
Four Seasons a place is like Eastern Europe and here in the US keyboard
Pundmann
Like millions and millions and millions of dollars
To start urban debate
Program
First started with New York City 1997
Literally you know went out to all these New York high schools talk to a bunch of Administrators and Soros Justice
Pump money into
New York City to start an urban debate league
Baltimore and 2
Chicago
Detroit weather
City of Newark 23 or 24 City
So
You know if you take a step back and look at it all suddenly really within just a few years
You have all of these new black debaters
Would go through the exact same thing that Ryan went
At the regional level you can imagine get a bunch of African-American students a bunch of teachers who are supporting them in a very positive
Environment they build relationship
In friendship and so debate Feels Like Home in the
That face. First National Tournament
Culture shock
Because there is a c
Of white
And according to dr. Reid Brinkley
Influx of black Debaters into a
Primarily white space
Started to create some tension and pressure and
Not all built up and eventually resulted in something called the Louisville
Louisville project
Started its goal was to increase
I mean for participation.
I know that there's a baseball bat associated with my
Queso
Early 2000s
Down at the University of Louisville
There was a debate team or predominately african-american team
And so they were having a hard time finding
Traction
He says they were going to be
Tournaments
You know no matter what they did if they try to accommodate the more traditional style there was always something that they did wrong
The students would try to make argument
It's about race inside
Topix
But usually it didn't work
And so
At a certain point but they decided that they were done with that they were like no we are unwilling
Going to play your game in the way that you have defined it should be
P-play Debaters what they would basically do is they would show up and they would force a conversation about race
Basically saying like we're not going to talk about China or global trade
Until we deal with this this is Louisville's famous pray they said
We can't change the state
But we can change
The state of debate
So they can you end up developing this whole new methodology which is actually a throwback
To Aristotle
And in his idea yeah you need
Three things
Ethos pathos and logos
Books is like logic so you know getting research and
Scholars and evidence and things like
Pathos that's where emotion comes in so maybe a personal story or sharing something that will connect with.
And then eat those
Switch
Pinned down you can think of it like as credibility or
Is sort of like
Speaking in tune with
Like the spirit of your culture
That's where you get the introduction of the use of Hip Hop
Spoken word
Appointment
The use of what we cost
Free college
What was the reaction when this first started
They would say things to Lewisville like you know this isn't
Research this is me search
Is it black Scholars
NoDa black dollars
Airfield are not
Rio LX
That's right they would say things like hip-hop does not belong
I'm here your argument style doesn't belong here
Here in Dayton and I'm saying
Do things in really nice ways you know what I mean but there
Could be really angry
Matches at
Would you have an objection to a Prohibition as a coach
If you sit like look for the next
Lit never
And leave
You are gender your sex
Your background your family your religion behind
And stay entirely in the brain
I doubt that you would do that but I'm wondering why you wouldn't I wouldn't think that's
Black
Nothing is anti-black to everything BND gay and did you Auntie
It's right it's it's
It would be anti-black
And the reason why that's important for me is because these students don't get to leave their Blackness at
The door when they are
Write fake and pretend that they're not black
But that does not mean that everybody else is going
Pretend that they are not black
Even when they speak
What arguments they made when they open their mouth
Make an argument
People are paying a
Attention to the fact that it is
Coming out of a black body
They don't get this
Speak without race being a factor
Nobody gets too
Without race
A factor in a nation where race is a factor
So he's 16 years old and he sees marshanda do the spoken word poetry
First read more about Louisville and he's just like
Die dedicated mother a career to discussing the bay every debate every every single one and every single
Fast forward
He graduates high school isn't sure he's going to go to college I was first generation college student so I really didn't know much about the process
But then
Early August 2008
Get the message from a debate coach at a small school in Kansas
Just called Emporia State University
Ben
August 14th I was driving up to Emporia for
Soap
Brian gets there get paired up with a sophomore LaToya Williams green
Start debating together and
Over the course of a couple years
Brain starts to get recognized
He's winning speaker Awards he's
You know making it into the ground hit tournament
But
It was an uphill battle
She says the rain kept bumping into a judge's who
Weren't really into the whole three-tier approach
Yes I lost it
A lot of debate
It's before I want any
At this point he has graduated and he's debating with a freshman on the team
He's halfway into his senior year when
I had therefore
His new debate partner
Fontana School
At this point it was either find somebody to the Bay with or I'm going to be career with over
And so what happened
Is Ryan is also close to one of my best friend's who's one of my contemporaries Rashad
Evans who was then a coach Chad West
Connecticut University
And
Basically Rashad hat
What is bombshell idea
One day they called Ryan up and they were like
What if you partnered up with this guy from Rutgers
Elijah Smith
And the reason particular which I thought this was
Does a good idea first Elijah is with an astoundingly good debater he just had excellent
The old and traditional
But the other reason was
That
Both Ryan and Elijah were queer black man
The thinking was that you got two guys kind of standing at the intersection of
Tulak marginalized
And if they're going to try to make an argument about feeling excluded and invisible in the debate World well
They can own that argument
Better than almost anyone
So
I called him
When I'd it was 9:30
Do you want to come to bed with me this is a lot
I can't really answer this right now and I was like I understand
I'm asking you to come move to Kansas for a semester or what have you and Lee in Newark
Newark New Jersey
He called me back the next morning and it was like 8 a.m. my time he was like I've already applied
And so the next couple weeks he was down in Emporia
Elijah not debated for tournaments together first tournament matches
Lost four
I was very upset I was heartbroken because I was a senior and I was like I don't really do to 4
But it's fine you know it's okay and dr. Reid Brinkley was actually at that tournament and she said that
Ryan and Elijah debate was a hot mess
They just didn't have any chemistry there was nothing
Persuasive about a nothing
Popped about it no I didn't really speak to the judges
She remembers a time when Ryan came over to her apartment to talk to her and
And he was just like you know I don't know what we're doing wrong
You know he hit you know he just didn't know why things weren't clicking what's not working I don't know what happen
The three of them were all talking and Rashad
Ryan really looks up to Rashad because
Rashad is also a queer black guy but
He's also like a really really great debater and it was Rashad who said you're not being a
The queer black man
Right you're being a debater
And so Richard would say things like you need to push it out you know what I mean you need to you know
Sometimes sometimes you need to duck walk on them you know I mean sometimes you're going to have to do you know if he's playing
Be black you always be black and
We're in the spaces so rather than attempting to
High parts of yourself
Instead you should be fully you
Ryan with this and his head went back to Elijah
And within a few weeks
Things started to click who are just like here is what our roles are this is what you do
This is what I do I would start the debate
Expected rain in the choir if you will
Elijah who did the middle speech
Logic counter-arguments things like that he was better at the game of
Brian said they went from practicing ethos pathos logos to being it
Methodology
MN
In their second tournament they made it to the finals and they lost in a close decision but
The third tournament was actually a national tournament called Cita
Cross examination debate Association
It's kind of
Call Beth people's tournament
I was able to give her pretty good
2ar and we ended up squeaking little
And then there 4th tournament
Their final tournament together
But actually
That's the whole reason we're telling the story
NDT National debate tournament
That would be tournament
My decision not to go for the NDP is this marathon of a debate tournament
It's like you know March Madness or something if held every year it's last for
4 whole days and stairs
13 Rounds of debate
Fancy NDT is where
Harvard is
Northwestern
You know
Work
Masa tournament that they prepare for
That's a turn in those sorts of teams usually win
Weird
Definitely the
An all black team has never gotten past quarter finals
But this tournament
Things kick off Friday morning at 8 a.m.
Emporia versus
Idaho
And it'd be Idaho
At 11:45 a.m.
I take care of Puget Sound 415 Sago against Oklahoma
Oklahoma actually beat their butts prelim so it sound like a rod rain
And the crazy thing is that after the loss to Oklahoma
Ryan and Elijah
Going to roll
USC
They were liver Emory they beat not one but two different teams from Harvard
City Michigan State
And then on the last day they beat another team from the University of Michigan
Then they going to Wake Forest that puts them in this Emmys which is never been done before by a black team and then they're going to
Oklahoma who they beat and that
Put them into
The finals
It was
I can't everything's very surreal to me
We're in the finals of the NDT
Never happened before
We're also
Potentially about to unite the crowns and what that means is Wednesday than the NDT no team in history had ever done that
It and who were they up against
Well they were going against a team that Ryan had already faced
Like twice that year
14 time National debate champions
Northwestern University
So when is round get setup between Northwestern and Emporia
One of the things that we've described it as is
The Clash of civilizations
She says that about Northwestern because they have one of the biggest debate programs in the country
They've got an entire hive mind you know with a
Hotel war room for them to strategize in
And then
It was us this
To queer black guys
It's from Emporia Kansas
From a really small
School with not a lot of resources so it is like a David David
Goliath
Okay so let me explain the room to you on this is the biggest Rim that I had ever debated in hotel room
Did they have the debate happening and is it
Huge Ballroom Ballroom
The audience of self a segregated on the right side of the room Northwestern side it was
Packed full of beer
People and then on our side
Music like racially segregated to it was
It was it was
So just around this out
Up near the front of the room at a table where the judges which included our guys got here
And how many judges were judging the
Debate
4 men 1 woman
All of them away
And they're on one side of the stage
On the other side of the stage are the
Northwestern student wearing Northwestern Jersey open I debated at Northwestern
For 4 years
His partner a young woman named
Peyton Lee I don't know if she knew what she was like
My partner paid I was a sophomore
Where's my partner in
Ryan worth
Stop the other side where seniors that was a thing that was really getting me it was going to be my last
Debate it was Peyton off last debate
It was my last night we were seniors
This was it
How to make the Pro Bowl
It's the NFL
It's it
Their last
Debate
Everybody kind of gets up before their speeches to say like thanks
And
Bye
Is Ryan
And
It might take me a little bit
This is Peyton
Json goodbye
Can we my friend
It's been my hardest work
My most rewarding play
And it's taught me more than I could ever dream
Forgot
To all of you every part of this community
In particular
Special people in my life
Wow
It was able to lie
So the topic for the year was whether or not the United States federal government should
Increase incentives for certain forms of alternative energy sources nuclear power solar power wind or
Reduce restrictions on other forms of alternative energy
Is coal natural gas and oil
Okay so Ryan and Elijah where affirmative
So they were supposed to argue like
Something positive about the how the US government should
Solar energy production or
Strict coal usage in energy or whatever
They're not going to debate
That we had
Figured out that we want to talk about the idea of
In other words
Energy isn't the most important conversation that we need
Need to have
The conversation we need to have is whether this community
Can include people like Ryan
Like Elijah can we find home in Dubai
That's how the community feels about itself that this is a home place for a lot of heat
Right there people who grew up in the bay people who started dating when they were 12 and 13 went all the way through college
To the people that you often developed
The tightest friendships with people that
You know how some of your coolest memory is cuz you all spent the summer together going to the Bay camp those people makeup
Your family there are people who make friends in debate when they're 13 that they
Keep until they die
So rise up first and to make his argument about home
He starts talking about a movie
Have you all seen The Wiz
I have
I have not okay
So
All right real quick synopsis 19
78 film
And what
It is just like an all black cast version of The Wizard of Oz so like Michael Jackson
The Scarecrow Richard
Pryor as the Wiz
And Diana Ross
It was that movie was just like
To me you know it was the fear that Dorothy felt that the beginning of arrival
Going to Oz
An appointment is making is that like that's how he felt to
When he came into the babe when he was walking into that cafeteria
And there's a line where you say
When the Dorothy's of this world think of energy they don't think of thorium reactors but the energy required to get out of bed and navigate
The struggle
Yeah so that's like kind of
How is that how you were like tying it
Energy for US Mint what it meant to get out of bed in the morning
What it meant to thrive in the world and what you were never meant
Survive
And for Dorothy was able to reach a place of
Is there a way for me to get home where you realize that all you ever needed in the first place was yourself
Home
Sidemen
And that you have
The power all along
And that's part of what our argument was and I was part of what I was
Trying to say was that I had been in debate
For eight years that that
And I was so sick and tired of people telling me that what I had to say about the bathing what I thought of
About the bait wasn't legit
When the bank was a
Student driven activity
That I have just as much to say about this topic as you do and your claims are not any more valid than mine and my person
Bryan ended his like eight and a half minute speech
Insertive dislike hopeful appeal you know
Never give up you know we have to Ease on Down the Road
All together
Dorothy just
The fattest guy in the Bronx
Today at 1:35
Blackhawk
And then after a few minutes
Argent the sophomore from Northwestern I got up and I gave the first
Negative speech
Documents the one that they had beat us with every time called topicality which basically says the topic has
Posited a question
Should the US government alter its
Approach to energy policy
And we think that the affirmative should have to answer that
First of all I don't think the resolution is a question second of all like know where the roles has it's a
That you have to be topical butt
Our position was debate should be theoretically Fair both sides should be able to win
Argue that racism is bad
Ebates
Like we can't argue against that I'm not going to say Debaters in the home for me I love it
Who is the baker for now who's debate inclusive
For now is it actually fair if an order to win a debate you need to have like a whole research team and debate
Great camps that cost thousands of dollars to put
Participate in a topic that's democratically voted upon by all the schools of the beginning
Something about the topic should be mentioned just to give the negative
Basically
SPAC
Respect for the
Thousands of hours that my partner and I in the Northwestern debate team and other people in debate
I've spent researching energy and being prepared to talk about
The intricacies of energy policy in the United States
This went on for over an hour
It was it was a lot
Eventually Arjun and Peyton are like Focus their argument on
Their version of
The traditional version
This is how you actually changed
Not by focusing on yourself but doing research is being able to argue the affirmative side of something and
The negative side of it because people who learn those kinds of skills
They can actually go and do things
Outside of the
Like dealing convoluted globalize training
Spell global warming
So after
2 hours of this it's almost midnight
Feels
Exhausted
Yeah
But I felt it in the room that people were like we're not out of the debate
You can still win
At this point there's only one species left
And it's Ryan
I was nervous I knew it was my last speech I knew everybody in the audience was waiting on me but I like I just felt pressure
And I had maybe
Five sentences written on a piece of Yunnan
Copy paper
Like whoa
That's all I got
The audio quality of the speech is kind of terrible but
We're just going to let it play
Really answer this argument
And change our relationship to the world
Ryan says early on that piece of paper he was holding through it
Start speaking for my phone
Where what I will call the Sean.
Shantae the Sunday at the place that encapsulates your soul
In your loins
Well alright
Wendy Williams
Diana Ross and Michael Jackson
Especially when they don't have another place to go
There was portions of the speech that I don't remember giving
I was just like oh apparently I said there was a part where I must have
Shirt off
Like I don't remember that
Can I have
Pause cuz what I was I was trying to just get out of that so I mean come back
It's a kind of life provide a voice of
But as I kind of slow down to do that but
50 seconds left
I still have to answer this last thing I still have to extend a piece of evidence ocean I didn't say anything about warming
What do I do what do I do what do I do if I just look like this is reason enough to vote affirmative
Forget it
MN
I walked over and shook their hands
I gave Elijah a hug and then I walked
Got the room and went into
At that point is a judge I took a deep breath
I packed up my notes
I put headphones noise-canceling headphones on my head I found a room where there was no one else
Surrounded I could have total quiet
Think about what had been said
Scott says that he felt like the debates
What's close
Is going to be a tightrope so
I sit down and look at my notes
Irie listen to the last couple speeches that I had
Recorded several times
Wenwen Han Northwestern
Presented a lot of good research
And a lot of it he agreed with
On the other hand like
Eleanor Jenner saying if you have these
Skills and you're going to be better prepared to go tok
In front of
Congress or something
But Scott says if you just listen to like Ryan and Elijah like they sound more persuasive
Like you can't convince me that somebody who sounds like that isn't actually also prepared to do those
And Toad like
Ryan Elijah School presentation
Is actually proof that Peyton and Argent argument
Is invalid
Are the same time he thought
There have to be things that we all
Just agree on as our starting point
And if the alternative is a world in which the affirmative can come into a debate and talk about anything they want to talk about
Then the ability to make that a fair competitive environment seems a little problematic
I think Scott
Was kind of torn took me about 45 minutes to an hour to decide
Do I thought won the debate
Ryan says that when he was sitting there waiting for them
Decision to be announced
That we lost
And eventually decision
Three judges voted for Emporia into for Northwestern
Emporia
My partner Elijah jumped out
If you could have seen this room
Erupt into Joy I was in tears
Watching this historic moment happened because I've been around for so long and I've watched so many black Debaters failed
How to make it to
That pop point
I stood there and I was like oh my God
All I can say I said it like a million I was like oh my God
What sweets got in the end
He actually published like 11 page essay all about you know his decision explaining why he voted the way he did
There's a lot in there but
What are you trying to take away from it is bad
In a while
Well maybe he didn't like that
There was a
So disregard for the topic
He would have liked it a whole lot less
If Ryan and Elijah hadn't been in the room
I mean
Debate is itself is incredibly important to me debate has been the greatest
Influence
In shaping who I am as a person
And so in many ways I view
Debate as my home
And given that
It was a debate
The challenged and criticized
The activity that I have made a home for the last 4 years that pointed out
Weaknesses
It caused me to
Reflect
When's the regiment really work
I find this
China hike
It's a it's either
A segregating or an integrating event my Gavotte Mike sentence that is kind of integrate interracially
Chile World
This is a strangely warm spot
Are you saying no
When we ask Brian about how he felt about winning this tournament I I expected him to be really like
Like celebratory and
You know tell me that it changed his life
He was the first black
Student to win this tournament and
You know it seemed important
But
She didn't really go there
No
Don't seem like
I'm proud of I want you to seeing you know like why why don't you
It wasn't good
Thing for history
It was a good thing
To motivate people
I just
I just want to say
It was an important when it was significant it was powerful it was beautiful
But it was very clear to us very early on did not much head
Change by the time
We got in
Chenier Brinkley says that since Ryan's win
There's been like a backlash
Basically I'm in the next year or another black
Broke through with two black women this time and not cost
Controversy in
The state of debate
It was ruined
The same here you even had a group of
Schools like talking about breaking off
To form their own tournament where
Performance Styles wouldn't
Really be
Invited
I adding all of this just
Mix Ryan like
Not really know how to feel about
His will like
Maybe sometimes
It can just
Feel like
Yeah
It's sort of season
The series of accident
You're in
Cool were accidentally rub
Who pushes you
Pretty much
Horses you
Into something which
Suddenly
Takes you over
You turn out to be
Peculiarly good at almost Again by axe
Then you're thrown into the sequence of events where you get
Get to meet Elijah and then almost by a
Accident you become a champion and then suddenly it's over
The whole thing
Feels
Strangely
Lonely
Lonely but beautiful wonder how it feels to
Ironically this
That is the first time you have agreed with Robert
No stop
Just got to give him a hard time by first time
Huge thanks to Abigail keil for affording that piece
Abigail works for an amazing podcast called the longest shortest time
Definitely check them out
Thank you Hillary Frank for letting us borrow Abigail
This piece was produced by mr. Matthew kielty
Wilson had original music format and from Dylan key
And special thanks to twill Baker
Myra Milam John Delmore Sam our Tiffany Dillard Knox and Mary mud Darren Chief Elliott
Ihob commercial
Okay Robert krulwich thanks for listening
Start of Meth
This is Arjen Dalton from the debate story
Calling cuz I read out the
Ask for the credit though
Radiology
I don't get directions icon Realty North Virginia cuz I seen your future fast foods have a field day organic milk
Alexandra Lee Young Tracy hot definition of my collage or affection completed after the show
Looking forward to Story by