Are you awake
Northern listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
Gonads episode 3
Emily Webster
Hello hello are you still there I'm still here and this is my mother Mary Webster
But but it's another bedbugs are such a freaking pain vacuum
All the baseboards at the vacuum the floor is yet to vacuum the door jambs cuz they crawl up the walls and they're trying to get away
That sounds awful so I recently called my mom for
I guess the ketchup but also I had to work question
That's been bugging me
What's on my mind
So I asked her mom working on the story and it made me wonder what you would have named me if I was
Boy
You would have been named Daniel
Dad always like
Name
And if we ever had a boy
That's what you want
Yeah cuz he didn't want to Junior
He wanted to Daniel he wanted a little Danny
Instead he got a Judy Chrissy Peggy and Molly
Father Mike lucky father
If you had come out boy you would have been
All of us
Now we wait Daniel for a boy that's for everybody ready
Yeah well we didn't know when a boy came out as we could have
Gaming
So this is just going to sound ridiculous but I called my mom because
All the stories that we've been doing in the series
They do make you think about fate
But even if you think about the first one where they're the primordial germ cells
And they're holding on to all sorts of
Possibilities in futures
And then
Chromosome step in
No more Infinity
You're just like shunted onto
Appass
I guess I I guess it I guess asking my mom about Daniel was just like a clumsy way
Of getting back to what feels like a really pristine Moment Like a moment where
No decision
Heaven
Where you exist totally unblemish by life and choice in fate
Unless
Maybe life isn't so faithful
Case in point
David zarkower
Hello hi. I'm just going to make sure I don't like cracking people but I'll just correct you my name is is pronounce Hazard cover
Is there coover W right on my head
I pronounce it with that I like a V it's it's
Ascension polish
That's good
And you work at the University of Minnesota
What do you do there
Genetics cell biology and development
That's that seem scary
This Broad
Anyways the reason I called is Arc
Culver was because I came across the series of experiments that he did that
Just straight-up kicked me in the gonads
Okay so to begin this was
Back in the
Early 1990s is that cover was working a lab doing genetic stuff in worms and flies and
And my something
And Presto we got lucky
He and his team discovered a brand-new Gene
Dmrt1 dmrt1
I keep trying to say DRM.
Very sorry for that
Interesting
Was at the gym with in mice but also
Humans
And
In the mailman
It was expressing itself in the
Testis
Can I say it
Testicle Festival
Is that a single
Okay so yes we found this Gene and humans had it
In the testis
And the question we had was
Weather was doing something or not like you got jeans in your eyes that are making chemicals that are making your eyes
The color they are
This Gene dmrt1 is it doing
We want to know if it's involved in maybe making
Sperm or maybe just hangs around it doesn't matter doesn't do anything
You know we don't know
So do you like Alexa
Mess around with it
And see what happens
But
You can't do that experimenting humans so instead
Some adult male mice perfectly normal fertile males
Can we use
And so basically genetics
They cut the gene out
And then they take a slice of the testis and they look at it under the mat
And
I didn't look like
What we would have expected
In what they expect to see is that these are the cells that help make sperm in the testis
And normally they're kind of talk
Hall and lean
Long and skinny
But suddenly
They're different
With dmrt1 gone they have gotten smaller
Rounder
Inzer cover was like Snot something was supposed to happen
What is going on here
What are these things
Then he realized it's a
The cells are making estrogen and he was like
Oh
I think what is happening is that the cells in the testis
Turn into ovary cells
Wait what
Where's the male Mouse
Yes
So you're saying this mail Mouse now has
Ovary cells and it's testicles
Yes that's these are cells that are changing their their sex
Nothing saying can I come we just have like a
Exclamatory moment like where you where you think that's possible that happen what is you know
What do you say
Press anyway the greatest of all scientific
Exclamations is
That's weird
I'm so we had it that's weird Moana
And just to take
This weirdness like one step further
A group of scientists did similar
Experiment in adults
Female mice
Were they did like the same
Only this time they knocked out a female
Jean in the ovary
And when I went to look at it over is trying to
Kyrie organize itself into
Potestas
Wait
You sing in both cases
There's one gene it's flipping the sex
From male to female and back
Yes
1 G
One gene
How many teeth do we have in our body
I don't know like
Tens of thousands
I just wanted to
Witches
Weird concept to think of because we typically connect
XXR gonads
Two chromosomes least I do like an a
X in a y
Right girl and a boy so how could Gene step in
And reverse that cuz I thought
Genes are these
Like massive thing
When she is so tiny
Ginger tiny chromosomes are much bigger and I think the answer to that is that
When you
Get down to sex
Like what makes us one sex or the other
It's not
It doesn't work exactly like we thought I take for example the X&Y idea
Dislike
Chromosomal narrative we have a biological sex
It's a specific way of thinking about things from a certain moment
In history that we are
Actually starting to rethink
I think it's helpful to
Ceaser Tyvek
The history of how we understand
Sex in in a in a longer
So let me bring in this guy I'm David page
Biology professor at MIT
Where do we start
Oh my gosh well we're going to go so let's see we could go off the rails and any number of direct
It's your old father to be quite
Play productive but footsie
So let's go back
The 1890s
Yeah that definitely is 1890s
So
So genetics was in its infancy Mendel peas
All that was happening
And people have been
Conjuring
For millennia
Where do boys and girls
Now it came to how you look people. Mom and dad
Clearly info
Because people have realized
You know the children ended up growing up looking something like their mother and their father
Like maybe you have a chin like your dad and nose like your mom and a hair that's a little bit of both
Blending
Of mom and dad to make you
It right
But
When it came to why you where the sex you were
That
Was a mystery
Because there was no funding
You ended up being like
Either
Your mother or your father
One or the other
It must not have anything to do with
Reddit it had to be
Post
From the outside in
So people came up with all kinds of ideas for what made you
A boy or girl
The phase of the moon
At this moment
Conception cold Dark Moon definitely a girl
The state of the
The economy surprise down economy girl
Everything that was bad
Was given two women are there was what the mother ate mom's body heat
Stress all sorts of crazy things and then
We started looking
Elsewhere
But how do we inherit our character
Friend answer
Chromosome
Determine our physical appearance
And our sex
In 1923 a scientist looking down the barrel of a microscope discovered
Two new chromosome
Send X and A Y
Call the sex promo
But I just want to hit pause here okay
I came to find out for Ashley from David page that the X and Y chromosomes
Do not look like an X and Y
Like a letter so no no
No know when they first discovered them
Under the microscope they just look like these
Shaping
Clumps
Yard sale
Kidney bean
DX look bigger the white
Smaller but that's it that's so interesting because there's something about the shape of the Exon the shape of the White Witch
Read agendered
Letters that feel so yeah
Penis lights
There's like a duality or something in the acts which feels like you know ovaries in breast
After something like there is like
There is something about those letters so I was totally shocked when he was like
There's no real reason they got those letters it was totally arbiter
Anyways
When they found these chromosomes XX
Two X chromosomes
You would develop is
Gmail
Anatomic female and if you had a y chromosome
So you're XY
That's right
A boy
That was the thinking
Rodger and Susan
But then
That idea
I got more
When did you intersect with this story
The summer of 1979
Pages at MIT first year of medical
School and the
TNA Revolution
So far tonight we've been bringing you news
The world around us
Was just
Beginning
Now we have news app
Incredible World
Insider
He was involved in what he describes as like
Precursor to the Human Genome Project what would be
Human Genome Project
Working with the group of senior scientists who work envisioning
Maps of the human genome
Encyclopedia
Will know the complete set of instructions
Which made people
And we began to look back at some exceptional human individuals
Who had not been understood previously
Bat saliva test
Women
Revealed that Maria how to set up
X and Y chromosomes
Who had an X and A Y
Like most men
Women usually have a pair of x
And they're also looking at men
Penis testis chromosomes
Appear to be those
Typical of a female
XX
And 4 Page another scientist they're like oh there must be something more Happening Here than just like the
Chromosome there must be something
Deeper going on here
So we might actually be on the
Trail
Of
The secret
So scientists across the world start looking at these peoples chromis
And what we found was that
View XY females
We're actually missing
A little bit of the Y chromosome
But these XY women
A little bit of the Y
Wasn't there
Of the Y that the XY females
We're missing
Was the same bit that was present
In the XX
Meaning somehow
A little bit of the Y chromosome had gotten onto one of the exes
Abby's XX males
And so
Who is becoming
Very clear
That
This must
Fitbit that matter
And around 1990
Avenues this day scientists say they've made a major Discovery scientist
In Britain announced they'd found this one gene
On the Y chromosome
The genetic
Trigger on the Y chromosome that determines whether a baby will be a boy
Or girl
What they found is that of the 200 genes on the Y chromosome there was this one
Single Gene that acted as
The switch
The master switch the grand master switch
Which determines the child's sex
So it's not X and Y as a whole
It's one tiny piece
So
Back in the first episode
There were those primordial germ cell
Add to go on that super long journey to get to the gonads
Cathedral
And
On the journey when they got to the cathedral they were full of potential
I think it'd be anything
Female like being female that could be whatever your version of anything is
And then when they get there
There's a moment where
Fate stepped in and just
Schleich
Swept all their possibility away and said you are one thing
This is the thing you will be
This Gene is
Baked
Christian the scientist
Discovered if it shows up
Then you shoot off down the path that is
Testis
Mail
And if it doesn't show up
You shoot down the path of egg
Ovary female
And the scientist
Davis Jean a name
Sry
It is like
Sorry
Like your man sorry
So it sounds like we've gone from like crazy ideas about what makes
A boy or a girl to
Chromosomes to now like
This little Jean
Yeah but the the sry gene that you just mentioned is different than the gene that
I just heard about from
Is there a cover
Is there coover
Recovery up stack over Noah's Ark
Is a different Gene than sry but this
This is what's so crazy about dmrt1
Okay
Primordial germ
There any embryo
The waiting to become something
And then sorry
But just comes on for about a day
And then
It goes away
But once it turns on it then starts the Psych cast
Skade of
Gene Gene after Gene that all sort of
And what all of these genes do is create chemicals that send out signals that start
Forming and shaping
The test
And
As soon as the test is begins to develop
Unturned support G
Dmrt1
DeckOver stain is important for finishing the job of making a testis
Make the tattoo turn off
But dmrt1 doesn't go away at that point
It stays active
Forever
In the womb when the testis is just growing and then when you're born and through
You know childhood or teenage years adulthood like until you die
Dmrt1 is on
And if you take it away like sark overdid
The cell will actually
Change sex
Which would lead you to believe that
Dmrt1 is actually preventing a
Sal from switching sex
I called
Who is a geneticist from our first episode
Explain the
What all this means
Is that that other past the past that you did not take in the gonad Cathedral
It never went away
It's actually still there
You carry it with you always
It's just that that Gene has been shushing it
Yeah
Wait I'm repressing the other pathway my whole life
Like I think we think so
Yeah really
Yeah there's like a parallel universe male Molly yes
I think there is there's a parallel universe male male
Wait when you say this Gene has been shutting the other Molly what's that even mean
Okay so you can think of it like this
The code for that other Molly
Uncle Daniel
That code is still
In myself
And zharkova says it what does Gene does is it sort of one of the things this Gene does a sort of
Trolls and make sure that Daniel jeans don't turn on
Basically what does genes been doing it turns out as playing whack-a-mole basically just going around and being like Daniel
Daniel Nowak
And it doesn't maybe every day
It's like an election that's always being kind of
Challenged
That's where why cast
The deciding vote
And male happened
But
Does recount
Every now and then
And
15 Martie 1
Not there to say nope still mail then
You can go the other way
So now I understand why you're so
Obsessed with Daniel because it's not just an idea he's like trying to get out and it does go
Both ways like like
If you know there's sry and there's
Dmrt1
But they
I found these key jeans in ovaries that you can
On and off
Some more results
Why would our bodies be set up this way
Make you think once a decision gets made
That you just
Make that decision and be done with it
There always be the possibility of unmaking
That is a good question
I will answer that after break
But first
I'm going to call my sisters
This is Kayla Caldwell calling from Sunny Austin Texas
Radiolab presents
Gonads
Donuts is supported in part by science sandbox
Assignments Foundation initiative dedicated to engaging everyone with the process
Science
Additional support for Radiolab
Is provided by the Alfred piece
Foundation
I hate everybody Pat Walters here I'm a producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help this summer I'm hosting
And I request for those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
We're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments
Brilliance
Basically I want to hear about those times when I
I kid you know did something
It just means you read back and say whoa
Maybe it was the moment that our kids you've been reading to 4 month started reading
Back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of the musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed are ready music in the margin of their geometry
We're interested in the
Specific moments where
A kid does something super smart but doesn't have anything to do with the test
If you have a story
Go to radiolab.org brilliance
Record a short audio message
Fan that's radiolab.org / brilliance
Thank you so much
All right back to gonads
Emily Webster
Their name or hello
Okay it's Chrissy
Dude
Peggy
Hi how are you
I'm Grace
And neither my sisters Judy Chrissie and Peggy
Okay so
So I'm going to tell you guys the same
It's not even that big of a deal but it's just sort of funny
Oh okay
No no I just want to tell you about some reporting that I've been doing and then a funny thing that Mom and Dad told me
That's all I ask
Mom had an affair
No no God no
Just Chrissy this is ridiculous
The third episode is basically about how we all carry in US
Like the APA
Opposite self
That we never became
So
So I called Mom
Cuz I was like what would mail
Molly have been like like did you guys have like a name for male Molly
And they were like oh we would have called you Daniel
That was what they were supposed to call me they were so desperate to use Daniel it turns out that we were all
All supposed to be called Daniel
Reveal
It's not dinner Daniel Webster
Has Molly
Oh man are you surprised that your name would have been Daniel Webster that you would have been a Daniel
No I'll do that right
Peggy. I just know that I don't feel like
My inner Daniel Webster would have that much of a different life than I have so
I think you guys honestly not to Railroad this conversation but I think you guys want you out because
I was the one that was raised with a hoop that there was like some Daniel lingering in me isn't Daniel Webster like a famous
Sudan history yes
I took a picture of a statue of him once
Send it to dad because I was supposed to be the annual
Who is Daniel Webster
She's a boring white dude
Of course he is
We knew that part he served as senator for Massachusetts and was the under Secretary of State
Under three presidents.
I think it's just a regular irregular like old white lawyer dude
Now they're all racist
Thor ages tour
Douchebag
Sorry well
All right that's all that's all I got
I love you guys love you
Bed bug
Okay
Circuit everybody app
We have learned that we are all carrying around with us
Another path
We all have our own inner Daniel Webster's
Constantly
Whatever
So
My question for zharkova was like why would I carry this path with me if I'm always trying to like a
If I'm just turning it off
Do you have any answer
I wish I had the answer so we don't really have an answer
It could be as boring as
What doesn't really matter because normally no molecular Genesis comes in hacks out to Mirchi one or turns on foxtel to or what
I'm so
Why solve a problem you haven't created that that's
Quite possible but boring
The more
Interesting
Answer is that this is an evolutionary holdover from
From a common ancestor with fish
So this ancestor would be our great
Grandparents 16
Which means 400 million years ago a fish
Swam out of the depths of the ocean crawled onto land and took like
Squelching steps forward and boredom boredom boredom for through millions of years lock and key
Chance and fate until finally getting to
You and me
Hello hello can you hear me yes can you hear me
Bob my name is Bob Horner I'm a research Professor studies Evolution and marine biology
Santa Barbara what's your trash into the ocean
Wealthy
Hole
Idea that there is a different world under there
I'm just going to Adam Brothers. Of this
So down in the waters around the Florida Keys their swims
A remarkable fish to head wraps it is a very common coral reefs
Fish this is Marshall Phillips graduate student at North Carolina State University like Bob studies blue heads
Anyways down in the keys are some Primo spots and ice patches of reef
Group of say a dozen blue head in that group there will be
Single large brightly colored male with a blue head
And it's shiny blue green body and it has white and black stripes right behind its head
The go black white black that we very technically called the Oreo and if he's got a big Oreo well
Gmail
And then the rest of the group is essentially a harem of ladyfish
The lady in the group are little and yellow or pretty kind of swim a little slower watching out for
Birthing email starting all around
And this Harem of females will basically spend their entire lives on this one
Where they make every day with that one male the male and the female
Will Dartmouth in the water column together and then at the same time he'll release his sperm and she'll release her egg
Xfinity dark right back down and then a different female same nail go up eggs firm
And then again different female every day
Over and over
Say something happens
To this mail
Jose a predator comes along and he jumps that mail
So the alpha male
Gone
Now the question is what happens to the ladies you think it would be chaos because their whole system's been thrown out of whack but
Within
Minutes to hours
Life
Find a way
Somehow
The ladies pic
Who will be the next male have it pretty well worked out who's the largest
Each other like you don't line up or anything more than you know
But somehow they
Figure it out
Until Wednesday establish who the largest female is
She starts to change her behavior
She gets a little more friendly towards the other females just swim up to them do this little weekly dance started waving her
Pectoral fin at the ladies
Isn't really something they do as a female ever
And then as time goes on her body starts to change she will get a little bit bigger
How do you just suddenly get bigger testosterone for brain starts sending signals to produce tongue
The testosterone testosterone is is taking over and a she starts to grow
A little bit of blue starts to appear right adornos her scale start to change color then sort of spread backwards
Right at her chin and spread outwards until her head is entirely blue and then these darkstripe
Right start to form
Those will eventually become that black white black Oreo
And the other thing that starts to happen is her ovaries start to disintegrate
These are the most valuable cells in the body and now suddenly they're being
Destroyed and then they start to rebuild themselves into testes
Let's start producing sperm really rapidly
Wow
It is not
It's absolutely incredible
And then
Sex causes back new dominant male at the top of the Heap
But at first you not very good at being a male like he doesn't quite know when to Dart up and windows
Spawn stress like a teenager who doesn't know how to talk to girls but eventually
You get the hang of it and can produce baby blue heads
The cycle of
Life
Continue
Is it good Attenborough thank you
That's crazy that they just
Disintegrate their insides and then rebuild but the funny thing is if you ask Bob about this stuff
In fact
About how these little lady fish completely transform he's like
Yeah I hate to admit that but yeah it's not that shocking the shocking thing is
How many
Fishes
Change sex
It turns out
It's a lot of fishes
Nearly all the wrasses you blew had your fairies or flashers kush's
They actually look like parrots but most of the big groupers
The tiny gobies dance of fishes
Everyone asked about clownfish
Finding Nemo just that change sex
But they do it a little differently from male to female clownfish matriarchy
It's like
100 whole lot of sex changing fish
Heasley wow hundred
Skip
Here's a really crazy thing
It's not suspicious shrimp
Worms alligators if you include all of the animals in which their sex goes a different way than you would think
Mayflies lobsters
Bananas
Lizard Birds muscle snails slugs chickens
Chickens eat frogs
It's just amazing and Waylon we get to Turtles
It's a whole zoo in this conversation
So why would fish like why would
Why would any animal change sex
Well I think
Sex change
Increases your Fitness you have more young either eggs you produce or eggs that you fertilized
Then you would
As a
As a single sex
In other words
It just ensures that you can pass on your genetic material
Like a beer the fishes on the reef and the mail disappears
We are stuck
And there's no there's in your DNA goes nowhere
But if you can become a male
You can make sure that your DNA go somewhere and then like all the other fishes in your little
Kingdom go somewhere
Okay so now let me ask you the next obvious question
You told me that we come from the sea
They've got this Lexie sexy thing and the we have it to some degree Daniel lurks within you and is being active
We suppress every single day
So can we be like the fish
Yeah it does make you think of that the darkover says that ever since he did those Mouse experiments he gets
This question a lot
Yeah yeah there's some interest from a transgender community in whether this could be
Something to be helpful
But
Can't
Do it
We technically can't
Sakura says it's unethical and at this point probably even technically impossible to take that Chino
And even if we could removing a gene just won't physically reorganize us
In the way the fish do
He says that most
You might be able to produce your own natural sex hormones of the type that's more aligned with your gender identity
Oh pretty crazy to even get the body to do that
But the reason we can't actually do the full on switch
Is because
Humans
Male and female humans
Have developed
Internal reproductive
The plumbing that is
So different from each other
It would be impossible to drop of a hat
To switch
Then this this makes me confused
Miguel
Is this
Do use blanche's work from a few episodes ago as it's by potentiality that
Still is there
Latent
Being suppressed
Is that a legacy thing that is she
Just fading away or is there is it there
For a reason
It's there for reason in the fish
Is it there for a reason.
Does it serve a purpose
And therefore will be that
Always
Or
Maybe even get stronger
Yeah it's a no I ask Blanche that I don't know
I don't know I don't have a good answer for that
But it's
Do you think anyone does
Or is this like a
No I don't think anyone does
I think we're all trying to figure out why would be the case
And most people ask the same question you asked her why would this be true
And I don't know why it would be true
Even if we don't know why
Just knowing that that other path is there just below the surface
Wanting to express itself
Make you think a different way about how rigidly we Define
Ourselves
I think we like
The bin people as male or female and we both always
Put people into piles
But I think there's a tremendous amount of Middle Ground
Even when you're just talking about
You know things like the level of testosterone you're making or the level of estrogen you're making or
The shape of your genitalia or
Many other features that we we we
We've been as male or female I think there is a lot of
There's a lot of variation between the two piles
And maybe we just haven't
Appreciated the variation that exist
Naturally in our population
How are you
Looking forward to hearing from you
Call me anytime
This episode is reported by me Molly Webster and produced by Matt kielty with additional production help by Rachel Cusick
Pat Walters was our editor
Scouring mixing an original music by Alex overington and Matt kielty
The gonads theme and The Ballad of Daniel Webster
Were written performed and produced by Majel Connery and Alex overington
Special things for this episode go to Erica Todd Andrew Sinclair Robin level badge and Sarah Richardson
Thank you to composer Erik
Friedlander
For allowing us to use as work Freya was a breeze part 2
And musician Sam prekop
Whose work a geometric from his album The Republic is out on thrill jockey
I think you should sign up for the Radiolab newsletter you might think his newsletter what's the big deal everyone's got one
But in our newsletter you're going to get a bunch of Staff pick telling you about super cool things we discovered while report
According to Siri
Sign up at radiolab.org newsletter or text gonads to 701
Dash
Radiolab presents gonads is Rachel Cusick Pat Walters Jad album Rod and me Molly Webster
Phoenix time
Hi it's not you. Calling from Newcastle California
Radiolab was created by Jad appenrod and is produced by storm wheeler
Dylan key for the director of sound design
Ram at Sr Padilla is our managing director
Our staff includes
Simon Adler
Maggie bartolomeo
Back of wrestler Rachel kusick
David Cabell Bethel Halsey
Tracy hunt Matt kielty Robert
Chroma Jenny McEwan
Latif Nasser Melissa O'Donnell
Aryan whack
Pat Walters and Molly Webster
Without from
Sheena halili
Carhagg and Lisa Yeager
A fact-checker is Michelle Harris
Have a good day