Are you weightless
Radio WNYC
Hey Robert yes
I have a thing I want I would like to
Share with you and then by extension
The people out there
What would you like to share something you've been
Mulling I recently completed a miniseries in conjunction with a fil
Helmets at now out in the world called boy erased for project that we called unerased people can hear that yeah put out for
Out there in the world in the Wild on iTunes Spotify all the places
And a
Play one of the four today
Cuz I think it's it just I think this
Them as it happens here's the thing that I found Sword of Justice
About the third one I think that's our first one
Here's
A really important moment
American History X
You have to say
American cultural history
Yeah and
It almost feels like a single
Individual
Walks into one room
And says something startling to a group of very important people
Cousin accidental
Mama did he just happen to be over here talking again so by a crazy quilt
Serendipity
Enormous changes come out. That may be oversimplifying it and I'm sure there's a lot else going on deeper
Inshallah rhythms but the changes come
Almost by accident
Because someone
Mrs.
A train
Yeah yeah that's it that's a pretty good are you there you go okay
So can we play it
Yeah let's play it
This is unerased
A new podcast reveals the hidden history of conversion therapy in America on Jad abumrad this
Episode 3
Start this episode by talking about one of the great successes in psychology
If you're living with a mental health problem
It can be hard to know which way to turn
What to do to feel better
Call CBT cognitive behavioral therapy
You hear about it sometimes the news around a treatments for PTSD like suppose a soldier
Triggered by a loud sound
Well what the therapist will sometimes to do is take that same sound play it for the person
Over and over but under less and less
Stressful circumstance
Until gradually over time
The sound gets less stress
CBT focuses on goals
Focuses mostly on the present-day as things that are affecting you and your life now these kind of techniques can help
People with gambling addiction stop gambling people who smoke stop smoking it is a hugely important
Wave in Psychotherapy is often called the second way
What is the verse this is the second end
What follows is a story about one of the grand pubahs of this second wave and a grande
Awakening has he had
It kind of blew up the world
Okay maybe that's overstating it
But
Turn up the volume
Case in point this guy this is David tiesler we bumped into him digging through some archives at The Association for Behavior and cognitive
Therapy central office, only I and him were hunting around for some tapes
While they were obviously mentioned it like yeah Jerry Torres
He's trained practically everybody in the field
We have this thing called
This is River Tree and it basically
Ja
Several different
People
From whom almost every single
Temporary
Psychologist
Jerry's one of the six how many people own
There
Careers
You might call him one of the six
Cardinal Bishop
Contemporary psychology
Is Sigmund Freud
It's Gerald Gerald middle initial C
Last name davisson Davison
Professor of psychology
University of Southern California
Jerry Krupp the 1940s Orthodox Jewish also playing stickball in the streets of Boston at a time
And when the streets were pretty empty
Because of the work that was a good little boy and didn't get into trouble and no
Says he was kind of a quiet kid wasn't a particularly cheerful
Child I would say
Analytical
Watchful
Neo Jerry eventually finds himself one day working in a ham fact
That's wonderful
Can Ambien be like Hammond like a man
Well okay have a weird place for a Jewish kid to be but there he was
I had a job
In the graveyard shift that would start like that
Midnight and go until 8 a.m.
One day he is at the ham Factory or maybe on his way to the ham Factory board what was there to do so I always I was reading
Somehow I settled on
Freud's introductory lectures at Clark University
That he gave in the early 20th century
So he's reading freudenheim Factory reading Freud's lectures and something about it
Hooksett
But also horrifying this book made a profound impact on me
Unstoppable
Rent professional
Okay so this is Freud that you're hearing right now don't know what the hell you saying the only recording exist
Unconscious
Talking about the unconscious and kind of make that word out
And Jerry says the whole idea that you could like peel back the layers of a human psyche
It was absolutely
Almost voyeuristically fascinator
The same time
He says
Like some of the things Freud was saying
Weird how can Ford say
If you dream of a
Train going into a tunnel
You're really dreaming of having sex with your mother
Anyhow something about the book both
Intrigued and enraged him enough
Did he goes to Stanford and then Stony Brook
And to make a long story short
Ends up standing at
Exactly the right place
Where many streams converge to create the first real upending of Freud
The behavioral therapy Revolution
Previously it been all about dreams and the subconscious now with scientific
Experiments
You know the basic
Question
How do you get with a suffering human being
And help them
How do you make someone happier less anxious to express
Do you remove the first patient you start seeing yeah it would be it would those so-called
Yavis yunnan yavis yav is
It's it's another acronym alcohol in it
Young
I want the A stand for
Able or Interactive
The yavis patient
It's the patient's release
It is a term psychotherapies that describe the perfect young attractive verbal intelligent and successful
That's it you got it
So you know early on he says he saw a lot of people who were
Your classic garden-variety neurotics
Not afraid
Compliment creature in butt
He said that is what they used to call me
The whole reason we're telling you this story is that
In that initial batch of patients
Jerry says
He began to see
Like fairly frequently these young man walk in
They're mostly young men
Who complained that they were
Sexually attracted to other men
And they really wish they were
That's right
He says he can't remember how many exactly walked in maybe somewhere between 4 and a dozen I'm trying to think of
They were they all came
And then I supervise some cases
And the training clinic at Stony Brook they all came
Because they weren't happy
And they wanted to change they wanted you to turn them from gay to straight
Yeah
And not wanting to
Olympos my
Heterosexual values on them some would say my heterosexist values on them
I would check it out with them
Can you tell me a little bit about what your
Living situations like your social life and
Xiamen apartment off campus
By myself
In fact the film
Where I really roll played myself I wasn't acting but we did have a graduate student
Play the role of a
Troubled homosexual young man wanted to change
You'll see in that film
A pretty reasonable
Rendition have you ever previously
No
I thought of going before then
Terry says the film that he made with your hearing
Is survival composite of all the cases and Esau of this kind and what you see in the film is hems in a suit
Sitting in one chair
Couple feet away from him is a young man with big 70s hair
What's a mage
And the guy explains that he
Having trouble concentrating
Having no
Call trouble getting down to work it turned out
But he was recently prices
Buy an intensification of his long-standing attraction to men
Jerry says initially
He had no idea what to do with these case
They were anxious
Very depressed
These are folks who
The kind of people could
You know
Commit suicide
He says he felt like he just had to help that's what I was taught
That's what I was taught
And so in the film
You don't after maybe I don't know
15 minutes
Jerry says to the guy
Outline for UA
Now before we actually get in
Procedure
Just a little bit of context is necessary
I not suggest
Sexually I'm taking a lot of waste time Jerry was not the only therapist in the situation there were a lot of therapist
Is around the country trying to quote help their gay patients
Anything that we can do to prevent future Generations
From suffering this Affliction must be done
The overall approach certainly did not start with me there were other people who were doing what we
What's called behavior therapy with gays
Most of it
Was aversion therapy
Turtle file Spanish comes from your body
The odor so strong which was applying electric shocks when they saw pictures of
Same sex people
Or making them
Nauseated
With injections we vomit again and again all over everything is one of the leading of
Aversion therapist coming to Stony Brook where he's training at the time to give a lecture
The guy showed 16 mm
Films how it was done
Hooking up gay men to electrodes to their fingers of their forearms show them pictures of men naked men
Physical pain
Do it again
This bothered me just personally this had the this is Bob the idea of an intense
Ashley inflicting
Physical pain on
Other people
I just worried about it
It was cringeworthy
Interesting Lee
Jerry
Doesn't fault the researchers who administer those shocks
Pictures they were like dentist before Novocaine
2 in a pulling a tooth I'm old enough to remember
What going to the dentist was like to get a filling or getting
A tooth pulled
Before there was Novocaine
Decide to write analogy
It was your tooth hurts you need to have it pulled out you don't need to have your homosexuality pulled out of you may not think so
But if if you're gay
In the 1960s
Haunted and discriminated against
CBS News survey shows that two out of three Americans
Discomfort or fear and being told that your
An evil person that you're disgusting these people need help and so what Feldman was trying to do
Helping a eating aversion therapist who's the guy that showed
That felt he was doing the best
That he could given what was available knowledge
Yeah
Yeah that's why I don't demonize
As Jerry is sitting there in the bathroom watching this guy Feldman show this film
People being tortured
He says
He just kept thinking
She's do we have to do it this way
The people were saying
Well but it works and
That's what the literature was telling us
But I was thinking while other other ways to do it
And so what Jerry decided to do was take the basic idea of aversion therapy
And flip it
So what am I supposed to do now I'm supposed to argue well
I want you to connect to
Follow Me If You Can I don't want to say now
Nswc in the film he basically tells the patient
Baidu
Grab a copy of Playboy magazine
You go to the nurse and get a copy Playboy was what I thought of as
Source of material
Attractive
Women then he says when you get back home get yourself aroused or whatever you're cussing
Think about a man think about his body
Homosexual image
There comes a point
You know
The inevitable point
At that point of
Inevitability switch over to the female picture
Have you ever had your climax
And
My schedule was it said of shocking people into hating their Gay Thoughts he would gently encourage them to take their positive
Gay Thoughts
And map them onto a different body
I fact I think the technical term was orgasmic reorientation
And in the video apparently it's
Seems to work
In the video of Jerry checks in with him about 10 times
And the guy tells him it first
It was really hard for him to finish the deed while looking at female pictures
But then it got easier
Any easier
Until finally after about 10 of these sessions
I really feel like I'm really getting into it now
What happened was
Every time I masturbated I found now
Erin go straight through
Without any trouble you know what
Do you like you like what
I think the thing I like most is I now see some direction I feel myself
Moving
Towards something as opposed to
Not knowing which way I was
NFL
And I think that's a good feeling
Okay setting aside for a moment the question of whether this therapy actually
What
I think you can guess the answer to that
And it is not the point of the story
What happened to Nick
Is it disturbing takes on an entirely
Surprising
Inconsequential
Life of its own
And that's after the break
I'm Jenna Home Run Race on Radiolab
This is Katie from Big Sky Montana
Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloan
Www.
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help this summer I'm hosting
And I request for those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
We're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments
Williams basically I want to hear about those times when I kid you know did something
It just means you lean back and say whoa how did they do that maybe it was the moment that a kid
You've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons and you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed they're ready music in the margin of their geometry homework we're interested in
Epic moments where a kid does something super smart but doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story please share it with us
Go to radiolab.org Brilliance and record a short audio message for us
And that's where you live. Org / brilliance
Thank you so much
I'm dead I'm running Robert krulwich this is Radiolab we're listening to a story from the series the police called on her
Ray stantz get back now to the story of
Dr. Jerry Davidson and the gay cure it is 1966-67 Jerry has pioneered
This new
Kind of conversion therapy called orgasmic reorientation is made a video about it
Shortly after making this video Jerry found himself reading
The very magazine implicated in his therapy
Naturally reading it just for the articles
As they say
And
I was reading the Playboy forum
That's the section the magazine where readers write letters talk about stuff voice concerns and in the Forum
This could have been
Around 1966 or 67
They were people writing in trouble by their homosexuality
He's only found when I was in the hospital the doctor
Told me they were very futuristic
And I should try to adjust
My condition
Well
Being a card-carrying behavior therapist
I wrote a letter
Play boy crazy with me and I said
Actually there are new procedures
For helping gay men
Become less gay and comes from behavior therapy and I don't know what else are low
Well
They reprinted it
What ensued in the Playboy form over the course of many issues
Many years since I was a vigorous
Back and forth
Jerry's letter prompts series of other letters some positive some negative one in particular which calls out of her
Immersion therapy
At the cruel thing which then causes one of the world's leading aversion therapist
Guy by the name of David Barlow to jump in and defend himself
He writes
Are procedures are not torturous or the Inquisition rather methods drive from experimental Laboratories
And carefully applied to consenting human beings
To relieve suffering
That letter prompts a famous gay activist
Frank kameny to jump in with his own response
He writes
I find the August Playboy Forum letter of David H Barlow
Ben Savannah Lester death
Not only the failures of psychology and Psychiatry their approach to homosexuality
They also have the dangers of human engineering
You're so weird fact
Kennedy's letter was titled gay is good and just a few years later post on wall
That preys
Would become the slogan of the entire gay rights movie
And this is maybe the first time
That phrases used
In the pages of Playboy everyone
Raves about how Interactive
The internet is
People forget how interactive Playboy magazine was
Okay so this is a little bit of a digression
But I think it's one so worth taking that's James Peterson
I was senior staff writer /
Senior editor
Free Playboy magazine Playboy from 1973 to 2003
He sort of the institutional memory of the old Playboy
Last Man Standing
There is James reminded me
I never even knew this
Begin with
Hugh Hefner's
Intent with Playboy was just to show naked lady
Yashow philosophy
3 actually spelled out in great detail
I call it the term paper
That changed America
Hefner was an under
Graduate the first Kinsey Report on male sexuality came out
Tens of thousands of people have cooperated it was a bolt from the blue
It changed hafner's life it came out I think maybe
48 and it describes the range of male sexuality
Without judgment Kinsey describe Nails on a range of
125 from Strictly heterosexual to strictly homosexual but in the Middle where
Show me like 35% of American men had had a homosexual experience in their adolescent
So the straitjacket was
Release and what struck Hafner
The indicated for the first time statistically the great disparity
This dissonance existed between
Hyperfest
Police and Thief
The actual
Actions of society between sex laws
Versus what people were actually doing this is one good reason for
Questioning some of the old morality
And so I would have to start a Playboy along with the magazine and
Playmates
Along with all of the televised parties from the Playboy Mansion
Along with all that James says he wrote this constant stream of sa monthly installments
1s a month
For two years
Like really long essays
Some capitalism religion essays on the history of sex
Collectively became known as The Playboy philosophy
The philosophy really I think
Here's an anti puritanism
And James says behind the scenes through the Playboy Foundation we were funding court cases it Advanced cave
Hayrides abortion-rights
Birth control rights
James says the Playboy Forum was part of that whole initiative
Right after he finished that 2 years old
Chain of essays
After them created that space
In the front of the magazine
People who had
Nowhere else
Tutor
And it was in that space
Where you had some of the first
Open
Discussions of homosexuality in America
Ever and I said you know it's you look back
The sexual Revolution happened on the Newsstand
Testing
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8
Locate back to Jerry story recording of a workshop by Gerald C Davison October 6th 1972
To New York Hilton
Playboy letter episode of side Jerry continue to push his Playboy therapy and in fact he says
Monk's therapist
Technique kind of started to blow up
And in 72 he ends up getting invited to give a workshop I want to
Yearly convention
Do you some ideas and
Data and whatnot from our point of view as we have been
Working
With homosexuals skip over the actual
Specifics of that Workshop
Well I think it's clear that we have solved all the problems of things field has
Because what's more consequential
Is what happens after the pain
Jerry is a hanging out waiting for the room to clear and this young young man walks
Chubby he was a little chubby
But my age
Cherry was 33 at the time very pleasant
Very friendly lot of smiles I don't recall if he had any a beard
He came up to me
Introduced himself as a graduate student
Rutgers
He said I you know I heard your talk
I thought it was
Interesting
I'm actually give you talked myself the next day if I hang out some flyers for it
And I said
I don't mind at all of course
Decision was made
2 attack
What
We called The Gatekeepers
Of American adults
This is Charles Silverstein he was at
Young therapist in training with the flyer
Vanessa Jeri he was gay
Was part of a growing movement of activist
They were targeting people like Jerry
The behaviorist
Have a different point of view
Unlike the Freudian weirdos
Their scientists
I would say
He said the public trust at the behavior therapy
They had a lot of
What's this way over public opinion so if they could convince Jerry and his colleagues
That homosexuality was not something to eat the cured
Maybe the public would go along
The question was how do you do that
How do you make the case
This was around the time when gay activist would start
Zapping meetings where they basically go to a conference with therapist for meeting
Storm an event grab the mic and just take over
Charlie's
Sense with this Gonzo approach
Was not going to convince
The people that need a convincing
Like sharing so when he approached Jerry after that Workshop very polite
And friendly simply handed him a flyer said hey mean if you folks are doing a thing come by
Tracy just had a sense
His heart was in the right place
So we thought maybe I'll take a different project
I remember looking at the flyer
And seeing
I wish those radical gay activist all these troublemakers
Man I've been called in Mike
We haven't called a natzi
Fascist
So I remember looking at the flyer
Say to myself well there's no way I'm going to go to this
So he shoved the flower in his pocket yeah I wasn't interested went off to the next panel
The following day finally the conference
Sunday morning checked out of the hotel
And I was on my way to
Leave Penn Station to go back out
Stony Brook
He says on his way out he kept bumping into colleagues were like hey great Workshop love to Playboy therapy thing
Until we stop wechat and at one point I looked at my watch
You realized
I could not make it down to Penn Station
And I thought
How the next train doesn't leave Uno
3 hours later sending had some time to kill and for whatever reason the thought popped into his head
The kid from Rutgers with a flyer maybe I'll go
Because I pulled out the
The flyer he gave me
I hadn't thrown it away
And I found the room
Anna went to the room
And it was a madhouse
Choke the room was Electric in the sense that it was absolutely packed
Charlie and two other gay therapist run stage there may be a few hundred people in the audience of the woodlands family Incredibles 2
Fayette never heard
A gay person
I mean a baby seem gay people interrupting attention but never
Take Park
ISO in my
Hollywood imagination of this moment people are shouting they're waving no no no no
Charlie says this time he worked very hard to keep
Professional respectful
So it's at 2 it's it's
Cordial
But fierce
I was at the top of my phone
When it came time for him to speak
Charlie says he took aim
That idea hit her
People like Jerry repeat
Over
I only work with people want to change what's the
What's the big deal
That idea
Usually said that
We asked them to read the remarks
Discussion of mail
Homosexual
To suggest
The person comes voluntarily to change your sexual orientation
Is to ignore
Powerful Environmental
Stress oppression if you will that has been telling him
For years that he should change
To grow up in the family where the word homosexual was whisper
To play in the playground and hear the words faggots and queer
To go to church and Harrison
And then to college
And here of illness and finally to the counseling center
That promises
Cure
Is hardly to create an environment of freedom and voluntary choice
What brings them into the Counseling Center is guilt shame and the loneliness that comes from there
If you really wish to help them freely choose
I suggest you first desensitize them to that guilt
After that it's listening to us but not before
I don't know any more than you what would happen
But I think the choice would be more voluntary and free
And it is
Yes those are my
Do you remember how those words hurt you
How it affected me very deeply
Affected me very deeply
Jerry says he went to Penn Station
O'Charley's
Speech into the counseling
What is scale
Echoing in his mind
52058 Broadway to 517 on the train back Stony Brook
Sat there staring out the window at the scenery thinking thank you
So I was running through the whole talk
In my head
He says by the time he got to Stony Brook
He felt something change in him
I went to school the following day
I know I began
Talk to people about what
I have just heard it
The convention
And how it's got me to thinking
Jesus teaching a series of undergraduate classes at that time and he would get up in front of the classes in for the first time think
What if some of these students are
In the closet
Talking to people
Mulling things over talking to students
I began to think no
What I've been doing
Was absolutely wrong
Meanwhile his film on the Playboy therapy was still making the rounds still gaining converts
Love the film
The film have been out
4 year already
And by the time the film began to be shown
I was already
Wishing that
Wasn't being shown that I had no clue
Control over
Couple months after that convention Jerry gets nominated
As the president of the aabt the gigantic organization that had
Thrown the conference he just attended
Becomes one of the youngest president ever
The following year
He was due to give the presidential
Address
This is where things come to a head
Conference that you was held in Chicago it came at a time
A break
Forever and
Foment
He says in the days and months leading up to the conference
People on
The radical left were calling us fascists and Nazis
And they were publishing circulars were their home addresses
Someone publish your home address absolutely
We had the high was president of the association of time
Remember we all had walkie talkies
And
We hired
Plain-clothes people in Chicago Police
Because we were that afraid of violent
Set the scene when you give the speech how big is the room big big room
Big Ballroom
Mm
These are all therapists
Yeah
And how are you feeling before the speech very nervous
Terrifying
He says before the talk he'd actually met Charlie at a diner and told them about the species
Remember him saying
You know that your reputation may suffer but have to remember that in those days
If you said something positive about a homosexual
People will suspect you people may think that you're gay oh he must
Okay that's why you saying he warned me he warned me
Colleagues and my friends
I want to make plane if not perfectly clear
That I am speaking only for myself
On an ethical issue that impinges imported Leon artherapy Enterprise
Jerry began to talk by telling the audience I wish today to voice some concerns I have been wrestling with for over 3 years
That he's troubled surrounding the way Behavior therapist
And for that matter all other therapists
Heaven approaching homosexuality
Did he like a lot of the therapist in the audience
We have been approached by client
Gay men mostly
Who want their help
We made straight to us that they are troubled by their homosexual Behavior or feeling
But then he asks Silverstein's question
What is it actually mean
To help you
A Silverstein put it at the aabt convention two years ago in a discussion of male homosexuality
Let me court again
To suggest that person comes voluntarily to change his sexual orientation
Environmental stress oppression if you will
It has been telling him for years that he should change
Super All in the Family where the word homosexual
Play who did you in that speech what was la
That's quite please consider me the code from Silverstein
What drinks stain
And the loneliness that comes from their secret
Another word Silverstein's suggest that we must go back in the causal Network
And ask ourselves as determinists
What are the determinants of the client asserting to you
That he or she wants to change
Jerry that delivers the simple point which is that the problem that these people are asking us to solve
Is the problem we created
That we labeled
As a problem
And tell even if we could affect certain changes
There is still the more important question of whether we should
I believe we should not
To us now
Too many of us now
That may sound like kind of a simple easy obvious
Thing to say
Say everybody else was arguing
Is that the attempt
2 Chainz sucks
Sexual orientation
Ended in failure
That was not what
Keep that he did something
Quite different
He said
And that's me
It makes no difference
How successful the treatment is
Is is
Immoral
Charlie says he was the
First person to say that to ever say
That trying to change sexual orientation was in
Immoral things
And that's not a trivial thing
That's one of the early Tremors in a tectonic shift
Manchester view but all of science like science to that point
Concerned itself with objectivity
That was all that mattered
We stand apart from the world
And we examine it as it is
Objectively but that
From this moment for it would start to be questioned all over the place
Even in places like mental illness
You know you look at history
You see that some diseases come and go
Why would that be
People will begin to argue that even mental illnesses
Are social constructs created by the society by the people who study them
With Jerry was doing here
He was Shifting the language he was saying forget
Objectivity forgetting bulshit empiricism
Let's talk about that
Let's talk about morality
We shouldn't do this
Not because it doesn't work which it doesn't
Because it's wrong
I hope and I recommend that we continue to devote the necessary energy
To the important shower
Thank you
You right about that moment like as you were talking about how like the air
Felt in that moment you right
Friends commented afterwards that one gets that kind of Silence when everyone in a room full of 1000
People stops breathing at
At the same time
Yeah yeah
Exactly right
I remember that
I just remember
That intellect what are they going to do
When I say this
And it turned out
That what they were doing was holding their breath
Did you eventually clap
But afterwards Terry says at the reception
You walked in and it was like parting the Red Seas
Nobody wants to talk to they're all looking at me and I remember
One person I will not name him
He came over to me and shook my hand and he bent over and give me a kiss on the cheek what didn't
You like that because you said those things
Yeah and I said
I said screw you
So it took a while
Gypsum board
They did start to come around
And get on the right side of History
It's not a straight line by any means but there is a line
You can draw between Charlie's words coming out of Jerry's mouth and the epically huge decision that these psychiatric community
As a whole would make
To remove homosexuality as a mental illness from the DSM that big
Bible mental illness
Siri speech happened right at that beginning
When science was just starting to wash its hands of the whole idea of
What's interesting
I fine just as one final thought you could read this entire story as a as a sort of Prelude
Psychotherapist were basically ready to say that homosexuality was not an illness
Bible 1986
That is precisely
The time when the Christian Community
Walked in
And grab Vuitton
The scientific communities
We're accepting homosexuality and they were saying that it's not a disorder anymore
They were removing it from the DSM 3 which is why we need
To do what we're doing because Christians have to fight the battle Christians have to fight this battle homosexual sin
Because the professional counseling Community won't do it anymore
Still it was very explicit in your mind oh yeah
Did that that story
Is it storming that we eat here in the next episode of unerased which I think we might also play on Radiolab
I hope so because I all of a sudden instead of talking to data
Talking to
Jeans instead of talking to
Chemicals now you're talkin
To either God or your
Parents
Teachers or your Society or the pressures that are all around you and it gets
Greeley
Really lonely
Really really tough
This episode of Radiolab was drawn from unerased
The Untold History of conversion therapy in America that series I worked on with books feature Stitcher and lemon house
Conjunction with feature film boy erased
Special thanks go out to Shimon the eye
Ikat Aaron Michael assessor Alice Quinlan David Craig Garrard Conley and all the folks at Anonymous content
For their support of unerased
You want to hear the whole series which I hope you you will
You can find unerased in all the usual podcast places
I'm Jad abumrad Robert krulwich
Major listening and Happy Thanksgiving