Are you awake
Listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
And NPR
All right hey I'm Jared I'm Rod I Robert krulwich this is Radiolab the podcast here's a story we've been following
Comes from a friend of mine Andrews Ali
2 is
Is a great thinker and writer you would a book called resilience why things bounce back
And it's a lot about technology
Yeah but it's been a long time
For a long time in the relationship
Tween
Technology
And emotion
In
Because
Well I've thrown more than one cell phone
Into the ground
And whenever having breakfast one day and he pitched me on this idea of doing the story
About Facebook
Remember iron on a huge
No believer in doing stories about Facebook
Mystery
Wickedly interesting
Profound in its way
So he and I've been falling for a couple years
And down to this roller coaster
Events it really begins in 2011
Will let me back up for me
One of the challenges talking about Facebook
What is just
The scale
Of the thing
So you know there's there's
1.3 billion people on Earth as of March 2014
Active monthly users there's a billion people who access the site through through mobile
Devices
Just to put that in perspective there's more Facebook users than there are Catholic
That camera is real
Yeah yeah yeah
It turns out it
Is true
But they're neck-and-neck
When you have one out of every seven people on the planet in the same space
Trying to connect
Across time and geography you're bound to create problem sometimes
Again tonight the issue this time
Before we go there
We should introduce you to the guy in our story who is the problem solver
My name is Arturo Vega
And I'm a director of engineering at face
Story begins Christmas 2011
People doing what they do every holiday season they're getting back together with their families and they're going to family parties in there taking lots and
Lots of pictures
Inderal uploading them to Facebook and at the time
The number of photos that were getting uploaded what's going pretty crazy
In fact in just a few days between Christmas
And New Year's there are more images
Uploaded
The Facebook then the word of the entirety of liquid
You say more images are uploaded in a week
Two Facebook in all a flicker all time
Which created a
Situation the number of photos what's going on along with a number of photos going up
The number for Portsmouth going up
What do you mean by reports is this
Back in 2011 if you saw something on Facebook that really upset you
You
Could click a button
To report it you can tell Facebook to take it down which from their perspective
Is it really important
Mechanism
If your Facebook
You don't want certain kinds of content on your site you don't want nudity you don't want like drug use hate speech things like that
Fatso a day or so after Christmas thereabouts Facebook Engineers come back to work and they find
Waiting for them
Literally millions
Photo reports
The number of people that would be necessary to review everything I was coming in
It kind of boggled
Mine
How many people would you need it
I think at the time we were looking at it for just two years ago and I can all this has grown so much since and we're looking at like thousand
Sounds like some
Giant facility in Nevada
Filled with nothing but humans
Looking at Christmas board
We're actually joking about this but we found out later
There actually are thousands of P
Across the world
Who do this for internet
All day long
Clearly warrants
Don't show but for our purposes
Just know that when a photo is reported a human being has to look at
Tattoo right because there needs to be a judgment on the image and humans are the best at that
So Archer decided
Before we do anything
Let's just figure out what we're dealing with
And so we sat down with a team of people
We started going through the photos of people were reporting
What they found was it about 97% of these
Millionaire so photo
Reports
We're drastically
Miss calligraphist
They're sitting moms holding little babies reported for harassment
Pictures of families in matching Christmas sweaters reported for nudity
Pictures of puppies reported for hate speech
Puppies reported as hate speech
Don't like
What's going on right
So they decide to invest
Okay so step one for Facebook
Ask if you are these people
Why don't you like this photo
Why did you report this
Responses come back and the first thing they realize is
Is it almost always the person complaining about the image
Within the image they were complaining about
And it just hate the picture
Maybe they were doing a goofy dance someone snapped a photo and that why do you post that
Maybe they were at a party they got a little too drunk that you hooked up with their EX
Somebody took a picture and
That person says of you know that's a one-time thing us never happen again take it down
Arturo said they were definitely a lot of reports from people who used to be couple
Sending Dave broke up
And then they're asking to take the photos down
And the puppy what would what would be the reason for that Poppy maybe it's your ex-wife's puppy
You see it makes
She said
Take it down
So once we've begun investigating you find that there's a little bit
Relationship things that happened that are like really complicated
You're talking about stuff that's the kind of natural to try to sue
Human dramas
Plicate speech
Because
That was one of the only option
They were just picking because they needed to get to the next screen to submit the report
So we added a step
Archer and his team set it up so that when people were choosing that option
Facebook some of them would see a little box on the screen
That's sad
How does the photo make you feel
In the Box gave several choices the options where
Embarrass embarrassing that name setting bad photo and other
Where you can write in whatever you want
About the image
And it worked incredibly well I mean like 50% of people with select an emotion like
Princess embarrassing
And then 34% of people would select other
And
We read those we sit down and we're waiting the other
I'm what was the most frequent thing that people were typing in
To other it was it's embarrassed
It's embarrassed but you had embarrassing on the list I know
That's weird I know
Arturo's
Okay
Maybe we should
Just put
It's
What are the choices
As in please describe this piece of content
It's embarrassing it's a bad photo of me it makes me sad
Etc and when they brought out the choices that way
That extra words we went from 50% of people selecting an emotion to
78% people selecting an emotion
In other words
The word
It's
All by itself
Boosted the response by
8%
From 50 to 78
In Facebook land that means thousands and thousands of people and we just a sort of what could that be
It to people like full sentences
Your stinking
It's always good to mirror the way people talk
Arturo's ideas
Define conditioning is that
When you just say embarrass
There's no subject
It's silently implied
Yuan
But would you say
It's embarrassing one that shifts the sort of emotional energy to this
Photograph
And so then it's less hot and it's
Either deal with no interest
That thing is embarrassing I'm fine it's embarrassing
It is responsible for lost me
Good writer
But it still doesn't solve their basic problem because even if Facebook now knows
Why the person flag
It was embarrassing and not act
Hate speech
I still can't take it down I mean there's nothing in the policy to terms of service that says
You can't put up embarrassing photos in fact if they took it down if you violating the rights of the person who posted it
Like there's nothing we can do I'm sorry
Oh so they actually fence themselves in a little bit.
For me I always put it in
I would just be like
Go deal with it your
Yourself
Shock to the bird that's the solution
I he wouldn't put it that way but
What he needed to have happened
For the person who posted
Picture in the person who is pissed about it
To talk to each other
To work it out themselves
So are true and his teammate at week where if you said this photo was embarrassing or whatever
A new screen would pop up
I would ask if you want the front to take the photo down
If you said yes
I would like my stupid
Boyfriend to take the photo down an empty message box
Just an empty box
It's sad we think it's a good idea for you to tell the person who upset you that they upset you
Only 20% of people with type something in and send that message
They just didn't do it they just said
I'd rather you deal with this
Sartorius email
Let's take it one step further
When that message box popped up we gave people that default message that we requested
2 *
That conversation
Just get the conversation going and it's going to be the first version of the message that we did
Was like
Hey I didn't like this photo take it down
Hey I don't like that photo that's a little aggressive
But
When they started presenting people with a message box
Senate pre-written in you're almost immediately we went from
20% of people sending a message
To 50% of people sending a message
Really that's surprising expecting to see that pick up a shift
And so this music people just don't want to write
Dell sign up for pretty much anything
Not necessarily maybe it's just that
It's so easy
To shirk the responsibility of
Confronting another person
That you need every little stupid nuts YouTube
Have an effect
So they're like okay
If that works so well
Why we trust different wording
Instead of
Hey
I didn't like this photo
Take it down
Why don't we try hey Robert
I don't like this photo
Take it down
Just putting in your name
Works about 7% better than leaving it out
It means that you're 7% more likely either to get the person to do what you ask them to do take out
Turn photo to start a conversation about how to resolve your feelings
Over now measuring the effectiveness of the message so if I'm objecting will the other party pull
Pull it off the computer for just talked
Okay they also tried variations like a Robert would you please
Take it down
Please or would you mind
Take me to town. Would you please performs 4% better than would you mind
Not totally sure why but there they tried dozens of phrases like
Would you please would you mind I'm sorry to bring this up
Would you please take it down and start bring this up but would you mind taking it down and at a certain point
Andrew Nygaard true
We just wanted to see this whole process they're going
Threw up close
So we took a trip out to Facebook headquarters Menlo Park
California and somebody year ago
Just for the hubbub we met up with Arturo
Let's hang out one of these sort of like a socialist Utopia Silicon Valley campuses were
People are like in hammocks and their this volleyball happening
Did foxes running around at one point to be there on a Friday because every Friday afternoon
Arturo assembles this really big group
To review all the data
15 people crammed into a conference room
Technical folks
Dan Farrell I'm a data scientist
A lot of these guys called themselves
Trust Engineers that you trust Engineers are joined by a bunch of Outside song
Professor psychology UC Berkeley Mac Killingsworth I studied the causes and nature of
Human happiness emiliana Simon Thomas
My background is neuroscience
This is the meeting where the team is reviewing all the data about
These phrases so everybody's looking at a giant graph
Projected on the wall
You're slightly u-shaped
Curve there in that
Numbers
The hand with this photo take it down
And the hand like this photo would you please take it down
Our kind of the winter is here
That you see the person that's receiving a more direct message is higher 11% vs 4%
When is think they noticed is it anytime they use the word sorry in a phrase like a Robert
Sorry to bring this up would you please take it down. Yeah I'm sorry doesn't actually help it makes the numbers go down
Really 7 and 9
Are the some of the low points and those are the ones that say sorry
Tillich.
Don't apologize
It's like it shifts
The responsibility back to you I guess it doesn't it's just
It's just
If it's like it says it's a linguistic psychology subtle thing
But one of the things that really struck me at this meeting
Different subject
It is at the scientist in the room and they're looking at the graph taking in the numbers
A lot of them had this look on their face
Holy
I'm just stunned and humbled at the numbers that we generally get an inmate
Annies at Amelia Simon Thomas from Berkeley
My background is in neuroscience and I'm used to studies where we look at 20 people and not sufficient to say something
General about how brains work in general or Facebook like people would scoff
A sample size
That's Rob Boyle who is a project manager Facebook the magnitudes that were used to working with her in the hundreds of
The Millions
It's kind of interesting, because there's been a lot of criticism recently
Especially in social science about the sample sizes
There's there too often filled with white undergraduate college kids and how can you generalize from that
So you could tell
Some of the scientist in the room
Example Docker Keltner
Psychology
UC Berkeley
Like oh my God look at
What we can do now
Get all these different people
A different class background different countries to him this kind of work with Facebook
This could be the future of social science right here
There has never been a human Community like this
In human history
It's somewhere in the middle of all the excitement about the data and the speed at which they can now testings the bottleneck is no longer house
Fast food
How things work is coming up with the right things to
Andrew cerreto Quest
What is the statistical likelihood that I have been a guinea pig in one of your experiments
I believe a hundred percent
Any given person
It's Dan Farrell data scientist
When we look at any given person is probably currently involved in
What time different experiments
Enable
Supposed to
And different experimental things
Kind of blew me back a little
That was like
Ivan research sub
And I had no idea
Coming up
Everybody gets the idea
And the Lab Rats revolt
Stay with us
Hi there this
This is better so I was calling from London England
Relapse
Supported by the National Science
And by the Alfred p
P Sloan Foundation
And has a Republican
Understanding of science
Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloane @www.
It's not. Org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
About what we're calling tiny moments of Brilliance basically I want to hear about those times when a kid
No did something
It just means you bring back and say whoa how did they do that maybe it was the moment that I can
Kid you've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons and you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed they're ready music in the margin of their geometry homework were interested in the
Epic moments where a kid does something super smart but doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story please share it with us
Go to radiolab.org brilliance
Record a short audio message for us
Again that's radiolab.org / brilliance
Thank you so much
This is Radiolab and will pick up
The story with Andrew zolli and I sitting in a meeting at Facebook headquarters
This is about a year-and-a-half ago we had just learned
That at any given moment any given Facebook user is part
10 experiments
Once
Without
Their knowledge
And sitting there that meeting you know this was awhile ago we both were like
Did we just hear that correctly
Kind of blew me back a little
I was like
Ivan research
Subject and I had no idea
End
I had that
Moment of the
Discovery on a Friday
And literally
The next day Saturday
This is scary the world had that experience
Facebook using you and me as Lab Rats for a Facebook experiment On Emotion
Barely a day after we gotten off the plane from Facebook headquarters the kerfuffle occurred
Facebook exposed as lab rats Lab Rats
Nothing with your emotions
You may remember the story cuz for a hot second it was everywhere was all over Facebook
There was an academic paper had come out that showed that was scientist the company had intentionally manipulated you
User news feeds to study a person's emotional response
They basically tinkered with the news feeds about 700 thousand people
React if they saw more positive versus negative post and vice versa and they found an effective people saw a more positive
They would post more positive things themselves and vice versa effect
Tiny affect the results weren't really the story the real story was there Facebook
Who's messing with us
People went apoplectic
Very uncomfortable and some people went so far as to argue
Different person
Had a psychological psychiatric disorder manipulating their social world
Could cause him real hard make sure you read those terms and conditions my friend that's what that's the big takeaway
What you hear is a sense of betrayal
The I really wasn't aware that this space of mine was being
Treated me twice and I was part of your
Psychological experiments
That's Kate Crawford principal researcher at Mike's
Visiting professor at MIT strong critica Facebook throughout the
There's a power imbalance
I think when we look at the way that experiment was done it's an example of
Highly centralized power and highly opaque power at work
I don't want to see it's been a situation where we just have to blindly Trust
The platforms are looking out for us
Here I'm thinking of
I want to know your face book study actually
Back in 2010 where they did a study looking at whether they could increase
Voter turnout
Quite simple design they
They came up with
You're a little
Fox
Pop and show you what your nearest voting booth
What is an MA
Ditto in addition to that when you voted he's a button you can press it says I voted and then you'll also see the pictures of six of
Your friends
What this change
The number of people who went
And Facebook found that it did that if you saw a bunch of pictures
Have your friends
Who had voted
Can you sell those pictures on Election Day
You were then 2% more likely to click the I voted
Yourself presumably
Because you two had gone out and
Not 2% might not sound like a lot
But it was not in Tagalog and I think by the order of
340000 V
Device that they estimate they actually
Shift
These are people who wouldn't have voted and who they have said in there in paper and toilet paper
They increase the number of I said I buy
A340
Simply by saying that your neighbor has a tattoo
Yeah by your friends
My first reaction to this
Awesome it was
Okay I mean
We're at historic
I closed when it comes to
Turn out
This sounds like a good thing yes but what happens if someone's running a platform that
I really wish them this candidate is Canada's going to Lookout noches
The Mind Trust
The interest of the technology sector and I think they're
They're great candidate
Why don't we just show that get out
Message
That little system design that we have
To the people who
Clearly because we already have that political preferences
I want to come to agree with us
And the people who disagree with
They weren't get this little nugget
Now that is a prayer
Found democratic
Power that you have
Kate Spacek
Position is it when it comes to social engineering which is what this is
Companies
People using
Really
Fact when when Andrew mentioned to her
Arturo had this group and the group had a name called the trust Engineering Group
His job is to engineer
Trust
When Andrew told her that Facebook
You smacking your forehead
Hard these ideas that we could somehow
Engineer compassion
I think to some degree have a kind of
Hubris in them
Who are we to decide
Whether we can make somebody more compassion or not
How to do highlights
Couple months after a first interview we spoke to Arturo Behar
Again
Kerfuffle is dying down
We asked him about
All the Uproar
I know this is not your work
List emotions contagious
Literally like
Hours
After we got back from that meeting
That thing erupted
Do you understand the backlash
No I mean I think that
How many we
We really care about the people for you
Facebook
I don't think there's such a thing as
As
How many finishing up learned in this world
Is that
You really have
2 respect
People's response
Emotions
No matter what they are
He said the whole thing definitely
Made them text
There was a moment of concern of what it would mean to the world
I thought there was like this is this going to
Is this going to be in that
Happy Cow
Do this
Part of music
Big Al's, here is actually one
Reclaim back the word emotion
And reclaim back
The ability to do
Very thoughtful and careful experiment want to come back to work experiment
Where you want to reclaim it
From
Rimowa
Well
Suddenly like the word emotion in the word experiment on these things became really charged
Oh yeah because I almost thought that Facebook
Focus manipulator
Emotion in there
It's right in in in in in the talking about right now
All of the work that we do
Begins
With a person asking us
For help this is Arturo's
Most emphatic point he said it over and over
You know
Facebook isn't just doing this for
4fun people are asking for help they need help
Which point the one of the biggest challenges of living online just that you know offline
Can we try and engineer trust offline for at least
Read one another we do it in the super subtle ways using eye contact and facial
Expressions in posture and tone of voice all this nonverbal stuff and of course when we go online
We don't have access to any of that in the absence of that feedback
How do we
Communicate what what does communication turn into
Best thrift on this I got to say is a Louis CK on Conan
It's just this thing
It's bad
Is a scrape bit about technology and kids
Your kids are mean
And it's cuz you're trying it out
Fat
Anime see the kids face scrunch up in the doesn't feel good too
McPherson
Do that tonight that you put together start with doing the mean
When they write your
Bat
Religious cult that was fun I like that
Antioch
Back to Arturo I mean I think
How about
Like what it means to be
In the presence of a friend or a lover
And
And how are you build experiences
That facilitate that
When you cannot be physically
Together
Arturo says that's really all he's up to his just tryna nut
What tiny bit
Senator
Online sales are a little bit closer
To how they are off
And I got to say if he can do that
By engineering a couple of phrases like hey Robert would you mind etcetera etcetera will them I'm all for it
Why not take the position
That to create a company
It stands between two people who
Who are interacting
And then giving them boxes and statuses and and a little
An advertising until this is now
Doing a service this is just
This is
This is a way to win yourself into the ordinary business of social intercourse
And make money on
I know you're acting like this group of people now is going to try to
To create a vehicle
The moral equivalent of an actual conversation if it's probably not engineer above and second I don't believe
Leave that for a moment cuz they're going to just
Going figure out other ways in which to make a revenue enhancer no I don't think it's one of the other I think they're in it
For the money in fact if
They can figure this out and make
The internet universe
More inclusive
To trust
Less annoying
It could mean trillions of dollars so yeah it's the money
But still that doesn't negate the fact that we have to build the system
Right that we have to make the internet a little bit better that's fine
This idea however
That
You're going to have
How to coach people
Intervals
Subtleties
Use of the relay
Tell him you're sorry
Tell him to do so here's the formula for this
He doesn't want he did some of you you need
To repair the here are the seven ways you might repair that to do all that
It's
It's as if the Hallmark card company
Instead of living only on Mother's Day
Father's Day and birthdays just spread its wings out into the hole
First of July
I don't think that's a wonderful thing
I think you know I was like I didn't offend you
I mean yeah I keep in mind how this thing came about I mean they tried to get
People to talk to each other they gave him the blank to
Xbox One nobody used it
Right today like okay let's come up with some stock phrases that yes
Are generic
But think about the next step
After you send the message
It's saying you know Jab
I like the photo please take it down presumably then you and I get into a conversation maybe I
Explain myself I say
Oh my God I'm so sorry I didn't realize
You didn't like that
But I just thought
That was an amazing night
I just thought that was a great night I didn't realize you thought you looked
So sorry I'll take it down
School signal
Unfortunately we're having that conversation as a Next Step
How many of the birthday cards that you sent to first cousins
Have resulted in a conversation
Maybe I'll see that's the thing I'm actually not they're really the opposite of what you're saying their conversation substitute
Maybe
Maybe their conversation starters
Maybe that's the Deep experiment
Are they conversation starters or substance
I hope their conversation starters
Yeah
Cuz maybe that would be a beginning
It kind of my mind goes back
Like the beginning of the automobile age
This is how we interpret
There was a time
When automobiles were new
And you know they didn't have
Turn signals
The tools they did have like the horn
Didn't necessarily indicate
All the things that we use that indicate wasn't clear what the horn was actually there to do was it there to say hello or is it the
There to take it out of the way
And overtime
We created norms
We created roads with Lanes
We created turn signal
That
Primarily there for other people
So that we can coexist in this great
Flow without crashing into
And we still have road rage
And we still have road rage we still have places where those tools are incomplete
Text andrew selley many many many many
With me for so long and all Metro keeps who you kept bringing back into the studio to thank you very much
To Arturo in all team over there
By the way they have changed their name
It's no longer trust engineering is
The Facebook
Protecting hair team really
Weirton original music this hour from mooninite thanks to them
Props to animals for production support
And I also a Andrews Ali put together a blog post
You got to radiolab.org you can see it we can cover some really interesting research that we didn't get a chance to talk about
If you ever sent an email with little :-)
You're definitely going to want to read this
Radiolab.org I'm chatting rod