Listening to Radiolab
Radiolab WNYC
And NPR
Hey I'm Chad at 11 today
We're going to begin in a place Robert come in there
Oh my God a Place full of wonderful
Thinks it is the actual blood that Henson and Perry used to first go to the North Pole season 2 Pole
Aliens books and his Conquest to Egypt look at the antlers over there
Is the weight where I where are you by before I tell you explain something
My wife and I hate Kmart have been having an argument for roughly
What's going on at 40 years
It's always about
Things
Like objects as you know
You ever think about things you give me an autograph I can Abraham Lincoln autograph I think okay
This very piece
You don't have to write your signature in this very way
He had to be standing exactly where I'm standing
And therefore he and I share this space I've literally believe that I am standing in a room
Abraham Lincoln Shadows
Touch and Abraham Lincoln autograph
Time travel
What form of love is all those things
And I can do that without even
Blinking red
Kmart not at all
But also represented the magic of it extends to
We were really really ugly
Floor lamp from a long time ago
And every time I would say
Enough already let's go
Get rid of it
It's older than me I've had it on my life
Which makes if you don't have that at all I don't have that
So
In honor of our topic today I decided that we going to settle this argument once and for all
I took Tamar to the Explorers
Wait what's 6 + Club
Explorers deposit things that they collected everything in this building has some historical significance
That's will Roseman the executive director he gave us a tour
This is the actual Bell
From the SS Roosevelt when pairing Hanson first went to the North Pole
The chair over there
Belong to the empress Dowager of China
The last emperor's wife
Cheerleader
He points to it looks like a little desk
The empress Tarot
Picture of China satin it yeah that was her chair
Accident yesterday
She said
Nothing
I just close your eyes and imagine that you are the last Empress skinny
Hugely long line of Chinese empresses going back
Probably a thousand years
I would order them to make more comfortable
Just give it a chance
There's nothing that's going to seep into me
There isn't
I don't know man was never going to be easy at Kmart is a New York Times Reporter
Very reasonable.
Sensible
I was just a chair just the beginning I they have things in this place I was going to break her
Step by step
We'll walk this to the next
Do you snore
Where they had
Pieces of Fab
On display
Scraps of did you know early planes were made out of canvas
And these are actual pieces of those early playing
Here's the Wright brothers plane
What do you mean this is the fabric from the actual first absolutely
There was a small round piece of fabric not much larger than your fist
Buzz cut
From the wing
A beer first airplane
Sow the wind the wind
Rush over that little piece of Amber
Yeah
Very cool very interesting
Happiness is when you're standing next to the fabric that lifted into the sky for the first time in America
You don't feel
Did the top closer to a Bernardo right not even attached
What a wonderful collection how interest
That's amazing
Do I feel that no
So
I think it's something that
He's trying to pull out the big guns
I don't see how you can get bigger than what you already offered
Maybe this will
Convince you
Sports Club flag
That accompany Buzz Aldrin Neil Armstrong when they first landed on the moon in 1969
So this is one of these three things
That that piece of cloth right there on the Moon by Neil Armstrong when he first
Landed on the moon in 1969
Oh my
It was in a little glass
Box you could see is a
A royal blue
Explorers Club Factory small
Probably made of silk
Yeah I can you know what I touch the flag that was the first tiger ever
Imma David Shuman calendar
Emanation
Are you a specialist
Yes yes
Open up the cabinet
You know God it's in your hands
God dammit
Is it
Very nice
Feels like it's a Little Caesars on the moon brought there by the people who
From our planets
The first people ever to land on them
They brought this with them
Okay Utah
Well I'm done touch
Pineal
Andy Reddit
I mean I'm pretty pumped to touch it
Tamar you don't get any of this
I don't give a swoon
This is the first trip to the moon
I mean
I don't have it
I just I don't have
I got to go to work so I'm okay
Thank you so much for coming
But maybe she just open to the Future doesn't want to have to carry all that bag messenger camera
You know you are going into a swoon about a lamp that's clearly an ugly ass lamp
What's up let's be available to the new lamps of the world I'm not going to admit
Maven
Consider anything you just said except
That you're probably right about the future orientation every story that we have in this hours base
That argument you had with your wife
In story form
There's a thing
And the thing Beckett
Or not today on Radiolab
Everybody say something
Hello hello hello
Well we're talking about objects I believe yeah and I understand you guys are kicking around some ID
It is but it seems my ideas are in a bit of a different orbit than yours are maybe there's a connection
We have an orbit yet I think we've want
Okay so our first story comes from a TV producer Vin Liotta longtime TV Guide
Coup
Connected up with us because
Turns out he's making a documentary
About this very thing people's connection to objects
My interest in objects is
Things that sort of him accidentally
Gotten meaning pravin even have a little scrap of something that's gone to the moon and back it's nothing compared to
Rick Rollins
Sugar egg
Rick Rollins acrylic Rollin Rick Ross
Actually the story you want to tell us
Had three part
It's about the candy egg a box
And to treat a candy egg a box
And the tree
So this is what I would suggest as I have some clips
Short clips
And I'd like to sort of weed the clips together sort of get maybe throw it out that way rather than telling you about them
Why don't we why don't we try I see we're dealing with a storyteller
So let me just play a club is like a short clip this is just an intro to Rick
Hi
Love this box
Wow it's beautiful. The size of a shirt box
It's made out of maple very light in color it's very delicate
And he keeps his most treasured objects in it one of them is this
Great
Set a real egg
No it's
Molded
Cigarettes
Halo in a center
Light yellow
Something someone might eat
Someone might eat it I
I've not eaten it
Hi
I saved it since 1971.
Just getting to say
619 what is an Edible Egg this isn't an edible
If you kept it from 1970
It looks remarkably Good Samaritan dissolved in under the weight of time and it
And apparently it's a well it is pristine I've seen it I had a sugar egg
What is that
Only it's a half of an egg it's
Halo it's made out of sugar and you would put things like jelly beans and if you seal the edges with
Frosting and then you decorate the outside of it there must have been some reason why he
He has
Memorialized
I'm glad you mention it I just happen to have another clip 2
Day that we were to leave
I'm sorry. I didn't set it up because I'm going to have to say about Rick was when he was a kid
His family moved around a lot
There lyrics dad did a lot of work for the government so almost every year he would find himself in a totally different town and to make things worse
Worse he was very shy
Kid
Kept himself a lot for Rick friendship
But just often seemed
Impossible
But then says there was this one moment
When he was eight that they lived in Washington State
Only four-year and
He found himself in the drama because he had finally made a friend
And his friend David
Invited him to a birthday party
But it happened to be
That his birthday party was scheduled the very day
That we were to move
Again
So my father was once once again transferred this time from Washington back to Idaho and my parents are
Decided that it
I couldn't attend the birthday party because there wasn't time
So
The moving van was sitting there everybody was ready to go and I don't think I even asked my parents I don't think they know
That I left
But I took off
And I ran up the street to David's house
I I still can't picture this moment I ate his house with a brick house and he had a
Large porch that was completely empty and I know that I paused there
Even though I was
Only eight
I must have known
That our friendship really wasn't at the point where it demanded a goodbye especially
If that meant that I had to interrupt
What is birthday party but I rang the doorbell
And his mother answered the door
And
I remember seeing
Basically from her knees down
And Beyond her into the back of the house which was bright
And Loud where the party was going on
A few seconds later David showed up he and I was kind of behind her and I don't
Never seen a word
You just standing I would just Frozen and standing there completely embarrassed and not knowing why I had done this
And
I was about to leave
When
David's mom
Apparently asked him to go get something and he left
A few seconds later returned and handed me
This yellow
Sugar egg
The very same here in your box yes I
Walks back to my parents house
We were loaded into the back of
Their station wagon
And we drove from there to Idaho and I know that I held this in my hand the entire way
Did let go of it
I put it in a drawer and it has lived in various places for all these years
Why
Is it begs the question doesn't hit
You know the truth is
I knew its importance immediately and it hasn't changed I looked at this egg
And it was proof
Physical proof that I have been invited to a birthday party
And there was a hope of making a friendship
And
I held onto it because I needed that proof
That's actually very wonderful
The tree we need to we need entry of the heck I'm all about
I'm swept into the egg know I'm bring it together and I'll bring the narrative threads together a little more egg
Give me more
The tree so my parents bought a home in Idaho this is right
Left the egg incident in the Snake River Valley in Idaho it's it's very flat it's very we
Why their new backyard was a Barren landscape
Trees pine trees cherry and amongst them was a maple tree
The groove very quickly and it enveloped to house in a certain way in the breeze sound like
Suede rub together just Amplified by
It was beautiful
Live there with his family for 10 years until College I moved to Boston and Byler
Learned that my father decided that the tree was planted too close to the house and it would it would damage the foundation
And he dropped it down
It was a massacre it was it was brutal and
I was very upset
It's my mother knowing that she mailed me a package and I opened it to find that she had place
Christian it some small sprouted seedlings from the original maple tree
Backyard and plopped it in the ground behind the garage and it's arrived
And within a number of years it has grown to be a 30-foot tree
Remind me obviously of the tree that I
Had loved and lost
In Idaho
And
It became
So large unfortunately that also caught the attention of my landlord
Tragically
One night I got back from work to discover that he had chop down
The maple tree
I went out into the yard that night
And I
Salvaged these sections of the tree
Rick gave the wood to a friend of furniture maker in Gloucester Massachusetts turned it into a box
This box
One right here
Made from the maple That Grew From You know the story
Wow there's discontinuity
I find such a comfort from that
So it intern holds all these objects that have their own individual stories and their own meaning
One of them is this yellow
Sugar egg
The exit 3 in the Box
Yeah that's nice that's really nice I've been very nice you want to smack a little bit and be like
Well now you know
No not me we can put the Box in a house we made from the teeth of his dog with the thing
Thing I would say okay just keep multiplying
Oh how I wish we left it there like you can't
Really experience them unless you touch them and interact with them like that's how you
Get the essence of what's in there
But at a certain point are producers in Levy really produce this show had this great idea for an experiment that we could do
Where we would make 3D printed versions of the objects in the stories and then public exhibit where
People can come and see them while they listen to the audio or even if they have access to a 3D printer they could just print a verb
Persian wherever they are so we asked if we could scan the egg
He was game to a place that does that near him we ask him to bring his again
Technician portal
Scanner machine that takes like 360 degree images
A little bit of melted plastic and Wallah there it is
And here's what happened Rick
Drop the egg off Frisk and egg that have been cherishing for over 40 years
I had to leave it for a couple hours shortly after he does he gets a call
From the scanning technician who
Towson
Something
Here she said
The bottom line is
Yeah
The egg is broke
She said
I hope it wasn't a family heirloom
Finn met up with Rick as he was just getting back from the print shop with his bag
Egg pieces I close the stuff that the
Story didn't really even
Look too much
Oh my God
Looks like it's
In about
7 pieces
Plastic bag
Yes
Hi this is Rick
It is Rick
How are you this is Jad
Radiolab Jad Hi how are you doing I I just need to say that we are so
So so so sorry about
What happened I never had my heart
Think in that way
From any emails I've ever opened
Thank you
Thank you it was such
It was such a strange
Clash
To walk into this store that is devoted to the Future
And all these machines sitting around that are turning out
Almost magically
These new things and I on the other hand and standing there
To collect
The shards of a sugar egg that I've held onto
440 + years and
Just felt
Dullness
Kind of heavy like everything was just a little bit
Muddied
A while
It took a little while for that to wear off
And
And it did with an amazing
Clarity
When worrying I think it was two days after the egg has been broken
He says he woke up and
And idea came to me
Thought I should call Max
Sedition a
Max is the son of a friend of his who lives down the street
We do one
Tablespoons in
He's eight
Exactly the same age that I was when I got the first egg
Of Yellowstone
And so I asked him if he would help me
Recreate
Fisher Greg
Kind of
Smiled and said
YouTube
I'm in there already
Oyelowo
Going right here
Already finishing
All the one
I was
Exactly your age
Exactly
Special thanks to Vin Liotta Who provided us with much of
The tape you just heard
Rickon and will FEMA
The whole thing yeah he has doing a documentary what you guys got all that stuff about people who attach do everyday things O and A
And in terms of the
Did the egg breaking
We we actually we have we found somebody who doesn't like restoration
Free movie stuff
And we've offered
Ric to to have that person fix the egg with epoxy or whatever an offer he agreed to accept
I'm happy to say
And also interestingly enough
Myths can hear the scan that broke the Agnew
Actually
We have that scan
Is the skin skinny when she was actually running
Very moment when the egg
Broke
So we actually have
A scan of the millisecond when it fell apart
Radiolab.
Ben Liotta Radiolab
Science Foundation
Science and technology in the modern world
More information about Sloan at
Www.
Sloan.
Oregon end of message
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help this summer I'm hosting
And I request for those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
We're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments
Childhood Brilliance basically I want to hear about this
It just means you lean back and say wow how did they do that maybe it was the moment that a kid
You've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons and you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed they're writing music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the specific moments where a kid does something super smart
It doesn't have anything to do with the test if you have a story please share it with us
Go to radiolab.org brilliance
Record a short audio message for us
Again that's radiolab.org / brilliance
Thank you so much
Okay I'm Jedi boom wrought iron rubber Co which is his Radiolab Wednesday
Things I wanted to check in this is the usual Radiolab style which it means that I can basically
Schnatter on forever
Fights this is Alison gopnik she's a professor of psychology and philosophy at the University of California at Berkeley and the
The author of The philosophical baby
And the reason we call the Rob is that
Truthfully after the egg situation we Broken Egg to make this program and get food if you're just joining us
Just happened with Phil really
Crappy about it frankly but
Got us thinking about the fragility of
Of objects in for me that cult mind
And I do that I've always been thinking about
You have any father to young kids about object permanence
Which is this whole idea in child psychology that when babies are really young
When an object
Disappears from their View
They think it's gone forever
Sutherlands Topeka active you're gone forever
So I thought this would be a cool idea for us to explore about how like from the very beginning we're born with
No concept that objects that stick around but
Let me talk with Alison gopnik the first thing she told us
What's with that well it's
It's
It's a little more complicated than that
Of course
Lawrence Wright that's science until we got to a conversation and some strange directions but she began by telling us about
Some new research which shows it actually babies do have an idea that objects
Stick around
Yo if you do the experiments were you show him an object by the screen in The Matrix
Pier
Where did it go it should be there exactly
You know the well because babies look much longer at things that they don't expect it or surprising
You're saying you know
What's up
Very rarely finish that expression though
Alright so I was wrong
Here's the really surprising
Now suppose what happens is
Yellow duck goes behind the
Screen moving left right and then out the other side
Dead of the yellow duck
There's a little blue bunny
No most adults if they saw this would be like
What's up
But the babies are totally blase about that
A yellow duck goes in one side of the screen and then magically the Blue Duck appears on the other side of the screen
Until they're about a year old babies don't seem to be
Changed by that
And she suspects that the reason for that is that
The most important thing about the duck to the babies is not
That is yellow or round or duck like in any way it was
Its trajectory story what did in the past what its history is
Like this is an object that was moving left right and when it emerged from the screen
It was still an object moving left to right and there are experiments with adults that are kind of amazing
Do you sort of see the same thing
Room full of students
Divide them in half you say okay everybody on the left half
The room
Is now going to get a univ University of California at Berkeley mug
Then you say to them all right
Oh you got to have a mug how much would you sell your mug for
And then you ask
The people on the other side of the class how much would you pay to buy that mug can you get people to write it down on a piece
Will it rain at the people who actually already have them on their desk
Think that it's much more valuable than the people on the other side
They would demand much more
For their mug
Keep in mind they only spent one minute with
This mug but somehow over that minute she says the mug gets imbued with something
Some kind of
There's something and again you can see this even with children there's something about - there's something about possession about
A relationship that I have to be objects that I care about
It goes beyond just what their superficial features
That makes sense
Deeply obvious inst
I'm surprised that it was even a discovery
If I have a relationship with a thing
Like I
I'm going to see my girlfriend and the
Railroad man gives me the ticket
And it turns out to be
Fabulous date
Can I put the ticket in my pocket and I saved it to get 40 years
Anytime I want to go back
To the day that I have the great date
I just touched
The ticket
Yeah I don't have that at all don't have it at all I have a little bit but now I
I throw that
You throw it away
I throw them away
The Purge man
If some of us are more sentimental about
About objects then
Then others are and what you says
For those weirdos like you Robert
Who gets super romantic about their
Things
There might be a deep evolutionary reason for it
Now yours to take these evolutionary reasons with a grain of salt but
She says if you look at
Patterns of
Cashing for example is what it's called in biology you have like the squirrel hides his nuts the squirrels keep really
Good track of which nuts they have and what their histories are
And one possibility is that some of our
Relationship about at least physical objects
Stems from
This
The history of
History of being mammal to keep track of what we got and what we don't have
Yeah we do talk about people swirling things away is there something that's got this kind of deeper evolutionary background and
I think there is some evidence that
But it's also like a counter squirrel Instinct I mean like
There's that famous thing with observation that young male baboons when they get to a certain age
Gripped by Wanderlust and then just wander away from the truth
And which is good
Prevent inbreeding
Is actually reason to think that we all live on this kind of
Emotional bungee cord
Yeah boy in between the score on the baboon and she says it
Interesting to think about like what's going to happen to her
Bongino
Now that we're entering a world where objects are
Becoming
Just information
What will happen when we have
3D printers
That are going to be like the replicators on Star Trek
They can
Just keep producing
Replicas of
About you
Might actually mess with some of our most Basic Instinct philosophy
Great about having wonderful crazy
Thought experiment
What's the trade-in damaged
So one of them
The Swamp Man famous thought experiment
Mother got a man but here's the story of the Swamp Man matching you're standing next to swamp near you
I've been swamped a bunch of
Whatever you just standing there but that a bolt of lightning comes out of the sky
Kills another one comes out of the sky hits the swamp
Catalyzing all that chemistry in overdrive and somehow miraculously
For just a moment the reactions come together and just the right way to form
Robert
Completely identical to you Robert
A brand new you if you took
Every single molecule in the swamp man's body
It would be
Exactly like you were at this very moment so here's the question
Does swamp rabbit
Remember that date
Or does
Swamp rabbit
Care about the ticket
Your son is swamp gas Robert
Is molecule for molecule Adam4Adam
So you're saying are the memories and experiences of his life suddenly
Contained in that facsimile
That's the question
And most people's intuition is
No
Absolutely absolutely not
I'm not even hesitated why not
I believe
That my
Date and the ticket
It took me to that date
They belong to me and not to Adam
And I don't know if you ask me what's the difference between me and my Adam's I don't know
But I know it's there
Because the atoms
Have you sitting right there
Actually went on that day
Where's the atoms of swamp gas Robert
Weren't there I think you got it exactly right that it's something about the history
Robert Adams really were in that place they really were there with that
Person and
Although I could I could tell a version of the swamp gas Robert that weird
Solve this problem
Is Robert this Robert
Set lighting you just got into the swamp
Submerged himself commingled his atoms with the swamp gas Adams
How many got out when tons weigh
If then later even like years later
The swamp
I brought her
About a copy
The fact that the real Robert was there to begin with
And that the copy somehow
Hatched
I almost like a baton passing I could see that the date would be in the copy link
I think I might explain it to my
Self
With fewest shenzhen
Touch that is
My wife is very different you this to me
I one day while sitting around the office get a letter unbidden from the first man on the Moon
From the alarm
Just write something that I've written so that you do that it says
Commander Neil Armstrong
Flattering
And if you could come
In any other form but my email
I would have
Framed it I would have given it a special place of honor
But since it arrived
From the machine to my machine and then out of the machine to another machine to a flat piece of paper
I can't give it that time can't give it to
The tickets
To the date
That's weird
Why because Neil Armstrong never touched
Yeah but you and I are old Robert so maybe that stuff
When was the moment you said I thought
I wish I was
Constructing an image in my mind of Neil Armstrong at a computer touching the keyboard
And
There is an
Unbridgeable Gulf
Between
His fingers
That paper you're older
I never actually touched
I mean if you think about is touch then you're right I got to see that he's now dead or not I think if
Just touching the paper he would
He would just be a little
I don't know
Closer
Well it's a funny tension I think because
You know what
Both science and at least some philosophical and even religious Traditions tell us is that
The world is impermanent nothing in it stays
The same RR we don't stay the same our bodies don't stay the same
The people that we love in the things we love don't stay the same that's just
The truth of the matter is if there's this constant impermanence in this constant flux and some
Philosophers have argued over the years
We should just
Embrace that we would be Freer if we didn't
If we didn't
Try to hold that
Flux for a moment
I have to say my feeling about it is
Part of what makes
Everything so precious to us is exactly the fact that
We know it's going to do
Disappear we know it's impermanent we know it won't last
What we love is this thing now we love our for me the most dramatic example of this is our relationship
Schizo
We know they're going to go we know that in 20 years from now if we they treat us with affectionate contempt will be doing really well
But that doesn't
Change the fact that right now
It's this child and not any other child in the universe
Just this one and I think that's there's something really deep and profound about our human lives that
The fact that we can do both of those things will be recognizing permanents but that we
Filoli
Attachments that
That seems to me to give our life at
It's very special texture
Wow
Exactly
I could just put that whole thing you just said in the
The frame like this Bow Down
People don't about you soon my friend because the next segment
It's going to
It's going to hurt
And it is at a more wind is blowing that's all I'll say
And I'm calling right before going to bed and Des Moines Iowa Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred p
Keystone foundation enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology
More information about Saloon at www.slha.org
Life
Seems very small
As it is day today
And then you just have these moments
Open it up and do something
Much more complex and Rich
Where is it
Hey I'm Jared Radiolab today
Things are next-door involves one thing
3 people
Craig on Craig Childs
Sweetest heart
I'm a writer and traveler from Western Colorado
Reagan I'm making toy I'm an artist and a mother and an educator
Know each other
Oh yeah we're married
And finally
Dirk Dirk Von I was a street cop in the mostly Denver Craigslist unlikely best buddy
Give me the booty Bandit school together I would have just beat the crap out of him in the playground you know
Yeah we drive each other mad but in the end we can we can still scramble around just fine hard of what joined us is
Is where we were in love with with wilderness
For years they would take these trips together out into the Wilderness of Colorado or Utah no Maps
No GPS Snow Trails
No campfires
Dirk and I would go off for weeks in the desert together I think the longest trip we took was a month
Just just wondering looking for routes
Add was on one of these trips that they made a discovery
I think it's fair to say still haunts them today
Recently
Almost killed one of our producers
So we've been out for a couple of days on this particular occasion the three of them are together and there a couple days into a hike
Yeah Utah
Pink desert
But Rocky
Slick Rock
Sandstone cliffs
Canyonlands
Tell her I can do all these canyons and then we actually we split up
Reagan said she wanted to set her own camp and so she stayed in one canyon and Dirk and I popped over into the next Canyon
Never really would you just
Send it to the normal thing or you guys fighting know it's normal
We weren't fighting at all it's one of the great things about being out together
That there's an he's with that soda separating is part of the deal and I think
Reagan was looking at
Derek and me and saying you guys are
Are going to go scrambling and get weird I'm going to stay over here I don't know if that was
What part of it was just that I was at least 5 months
Pregnant and I was just starting to have a really hard time tightening my backpack so that the weight wasn't all on my shoulders
And she says while she was hiking the pregnancy hormones work
Giving her bouts of vertigo it when it was just starting to hit early
Wow in a couple of months things going to be
So she needed some alone time
She said around camp
Durkin Craig meanwhile
Scale-up is Cliff face to get to the next Canyon over
And when we get to the
Very close to the top and there's a little flat area
Balcony of rock overlooking the
The canyon below
This little ledge so we said well okay let's just sit here have some lunch break out the pipe
That's exactly
So we sit down and and
And we literally both have like the first
Lungful
When Craig decides to take his backpack off
And he leans over and I notice I'm bending over
A round object
Underneath the edge of a boulder
Back under the Shadow and you said
Hey
There's a pot under the street
And then I I dropped to my knees and looked into this Shadow and there was this beautiful
Red
Jar low and flat
Covered Maybe 700-800
Maybe a thousand years of dust
Kind of skull the sea jar with Justice
Narrow mouth on the top and it had black paint
Design around the
Around the mouth
We're talking about
Early Pueblo people cliff dwellers
People who lived out in that desert 1000 years ago
And he looked closer he could see that this particular job
It had a crack down the front of it
And that two holes drilled around the crack and then a piece of
Yucca twine have been used
Hide holes together she was precious to somebody so they might have left it there maybe it was during migration thinking they
They would return it sometime maybe they were on the Run maybe someone was hiding it from other people you don't know who
It was if it was Mahler
Gmail or what Clan or
And any of those stories but you know it was a human being in the same position that you're in right there
Doing the same thing the same gesture
You can see the hand reaching out and placing the object
You can imagine the hands and the feet and the people in the sounds that they would make
They stared at it for about an hour not really saying much
Vincent latest hits dirt
Wait a second we got to move this thing somebody else was going to find this just felt like if we can just
Just kind of luck into it what's to stop some four-wheel drive in bipedal Pillager doing the same cuz it's a
Nexus route I don't know I felt sort of protective of it cuz you know we're all over the Southwest looting dicks
Sites in that jar will be worth a lot of money tunes of thousands of dollars at least
Hands on this end so I thought well let's hide it grab his leg
The moment we touch that jar is no longer is part of that story it's now part of our store
He's a purist we we do not move this thing
Not moving protected that's covered like I wanted to build a Corral of stone around it
Camouflage that's exactly what I be looking for in fact
I wouldn't notice the
The Siege are I'd notice the Rock
Can I use somebody's hiding something
Yeah right that's looking at me going
You and your Yoda crap
Damn and he says we could give this another
700 years of life
Helmeted been there probably a thousand years or so how do you resolve said you know will come back
Tomorrow we'll just
Leave it for now
How's the you left you left in a draw
We left in a draw and we actually
Hop back over the canyon to find Reagan
Badass samurai chick
I thought y all yeah I can
I'm be able to draft Reagan over to my side is it a hike back up in that ledge yelled out for her and the next day she
Icon over to where they were I remember
Her hitching up her pants
Pregnancy style and connect
Squatting down to get in there I was your first thought when you saw it
Focus
And just being right there completely consumed in that moment
And I think it went on for a long time cuz it was like so
The truth what we should do
Oh you guys argue back and forth for at least an hour and a half and I just ignored you for most of it cuz I was just looking at the siege art I wasn't
I'm really thinking to be in the position of arbiter but I just got fed up and like that's enough you guys leave it alone
It's part of an ongoing story like
Give it up leave it alone
And so so she take some pictures and we
And we walk away
And within a year of that moment
Everything just like
When twirling
Reagan and Craig had a baby
Craigslist
Become a writer who writes a book becomes a bestseller
I quit the business and got divorced and everything changed
But even on that day
They knew
With this will be the center of things we talked about for the rest of our lives than the seed jar yeah the day we found the sea jar
Do you think it's still there
I think it's still there
I think it is
The routes pretty complicated with that particular location
I'd say 50/50
Tops
Again if only
That were the end of the
We could have done the saying where you're just like Oh The Narrative power of objects meta blah blah
It is a damn thing there
Where did someone take it
We got so curious about this so we convinced Craig Reagan and Dirk to go back now they're here
Check we sent our producer Molly Webster along for the ride
Happy campers just arrived I didn't realize when they were like give me
Each other hug the first night of camp and I was there with my recorder but like
Actually like a big moment I guess this is a reason you're tripping
Reagan had said that one of the last times now that people have kids and family one of the last times we were together
What's besieger
Yay we still have a pretty clear and today we're really really really excited to like be together
How long ago was it when they found the thing
This was 11 years ago the kids were
Reagan was 5 months pregnant and the kids she was pregnant with his Jasper
Come say hi had his 11th birthday
Close the door and come say hi
Hi Humana Molly
Dirk
There could never met their kids but the last time you said Jasper Jasper was a baby
The other thing is
I'm just going to say
Craig and Dirk are like
Brothers from another mother
Like they are like the bestest bromance
They love each other
So much
Send me to eat so we
Get there we like drop our bags we go to sleep
And I
Woke up four-wheel drove for dries I don't have to know how to cook
Out into the maysa park the cars and then we hiked a mile and a half to the edge of the Mesa
Basically the entire landscape felt like they had just put me in a bonanza set
Gnarled wharfie trees
Red red Sandy
Sandstone
They're you're on this Mesa and then it falls off into this Canyon and then there's like another Mesa
And then that falls off into a canyon there's another Mason than that and it's just this like unending landscape
We're floating up here now
Yeah
And their s*** is it just like
There's no sound card has no sounds no nothing
Internet
Off the top and across we went back to get Rig and basically our objective
Was to go somewhere into this like Canyonlands
And somehow find a a tiny little seed jar
We're to go back because I like to think of it like this is going to change things if it's if it's not there
I'm going to be so mad I like to be out in the world and just think about it to go okay there's there's a
Message are sitting there on her Boulder right now and I will be there for the longest time and it's just quiet
And I can imagine that the wind going around it and and some more sand
Building up and and it's just this really nice thought of
Isolation in perpetuity
I kind of want to hear it Echo
So we set up camp on the edge of a Mesa
And then
We all went to sleep
What's a futon
Eric Craig apparently has a flute in his bag boy
Cinnamon sweet so we we wake up like first lies today the day guys
Today's the day we go find out if if the egg is still there in the nest
A game to go down this 800 foot descent
No femurs are broken
The Anasazi were some tough
People
Big wind around this Canyon Drew saddle
Another Canyon
How long is the psych take to get out there and probably took six maybe seven hours
We're going pretty slow the kids were amazing but also slow
It was starting to like this turn to bug Dirk I think it's the way to say it
Really hot
Sun straight overhead oven going
Park the kids
Somewhere
Sure enough at the end of the 6 hour hike
Leave your pack for the big guy
Extra water and
The kids need to break
And so assertive believe them in an Alcove on the side of the canyon
Mobile scramble
Play I brought my book
Okay bye guys
In Reagan's boys you have your emergency whistles remember 3 times but no joking
Final ascent
You know we went up that Anglewood up that diagonal there I remember it really
Really clearly I'm all behind you so there's this we were slammed up against his canyonwall we needed to get over it
And the only way to do that was that there was
Boulder sort of out in front of the canyon wall and it created this
Skinny Little Chute and we had a wedge ourselves into the Chute and like
Go off at 60 ft
I'd like to get off
I had to like
Put my back against one wall at my feet against the other
Pretend to walk
And I have this moment we're before I left Dylan told me not to die for Radiolab
So I pause
And I was like
Okay don't do this for Radiolab
Never do that again
By the time we get done with the gnarly sent everyone's like
CJ's going to be there cuz no one else would do that that was really hard
Just just had just head down that been
So
Durkin Cragar like
We did that route I'm absolutely
Siege are should be around here somewhere
Temple Boulder
Looking under God like
Quarter of a mile of Canyon Phase 2 figure it out
Giant Temple
Craig thinks
Tips to the laugh
Dirk thinks it's to the right
Anything Durk
No
Familiar decided
This is it
11 years
Yeah but I just I know this is
I know it
Don't seed
Spot
Are like just going like really confused
Where's that far now
Duloxetine
I offer an hour
And it all like looks the same but everything looks the same to an untrained eye right
It's like where's Waldo land and we're trying to find
His thoughts
I finally see Craig kind of
Bar off down the canyon standing by himself
Just staring at the ground
Okay like okay
Any luck
I went down
Look at what would be
Has been are likely rata
Yeah
Which is right up through here and he points to the ground like right where we're standing
And he says
I think it's like right
Here
I think like this
Was the place
I don't want to think about this
Particular possibility
See all that stuff I just walked across
Yeah
That's all fresh
Oh series
Yeah
Play words that mean fresh
What we were standing on this pile really sharp
Rock it was just all of these Scharf
Little
Dragon knives
I'm not sure didn't look like any of the other areas we had been in
It's
Possible at the
Cliff has fallen here
And covered everything
Top of that
Cliff if you looked above us
To the top of the cliff was like so many to take in a meat cleaver to it was just like sliced off
Whole thing
Brokaw
The entire Cliff face had fallen off
And annihilated
Everything hundreds of feet in either direction it's been totally destroyed
Yeah I mean they wouldn't survive
Even the giant boulder protecting it has been wiped
Clean
It reminded me of like an iceberg
Uncapping
You see all those videos of like the front of the iceberg just all the sudden Cleaves off that's exactly what happened on this clue
That's all you're talking like 10,000 tons of rock falling here
Just
Yeah
I mean
That's not what I was thinking
Responsibility
I'm not swallowing it
Just yet
She calls and Reagan come toward us and then dirt comes wandering over
It does kind of make sense I guess
Pots been here for 700 years it does
Make sense at all
It's not looking right
I can hear it was right
I know it was here
No
No no no
My God
Craig's like leaning against the wall
Dirk was like wow man I guess
This must be it
And it was this real like
They were grappling with something and it was like
Trying to figure out like what they were grappling with
And cried just kept talking to me like not actually about The Siege our bit about the place this is where
I remember
Reagan hoisting up her pants
Pregnant
Squatting
And Derek and Me On Our Knees
Looking in on this thing for
For the longest time
You know it was very clear in my mind
The have the place itself gone
It's a damn fine
It's beautiful it's wonderful but but Jesus
This is a different kind of sadness and I wasn't quite though
Are you sad
Yeah
Yeah that's kind of sucks
Like if it was missing if somebody taking it
Tobias Adam like old screw you people
Why do you do this
This is
This is gravity
Dirts gone
Yeah
All right
Irony at all
Just let it go
Let It Go
It is like a mouse
Producer Molly Webster
Thanks I'll sue Craig Childs whose latest book is apocalyptic planet
And special shout-out to Henry Rice from a minute physics and minuteearth he has been spending time with us got towed
Really fascinated by Craig story
And
Made a little
Wonderful animation of story that you didn't hear alarm
Podcast
RadioShack
On the way
So that is Henry's animation
And you should look for that radiolab.org
Yep it'll be up soon
Radiolab.org
Is Jaden styles
Hi this is bacon
Radiolab is produced by WNYC and distributed
By NPR Radiolab is produced by dad album Rod or staff includes ellenhorn
Soren wheeler Kim Howard Webster
O'Donnell
Jenny York Andre Mills
And Kelsey Padgett
Mary Ann wacker
Not guilty Simon Adler
To Mac
Primo everyone at
Mark urbach MakerBot
The edge of the Cedars
Park Museum and Paige Phelps
Stuff that works lyrics
And goodbye annies mailbox
Hi this is Frankie I have two things to destroy today the first one is a beer stein
That I painted at one of those paint your own pottery places with my stupid ex boyfriend so stupid mug and it was a stupid really
Play some chips so here goes
Alistair more calling from Chicago Illinois
Tell me punching a wall
North Carolina sweetheart from Brooklyn New York
I made this quote what's the world puzzle there when I was in high school so it's been a long time in my room and
Better now
Maybe it's time to like it like that with that part
Fastest rap
My name is Mary and I'm going to destroy you
Picture of me and my ex-boyfriend
I am cleaning up
All the paperwork from my classes and this is sound
Me to bring them up as soon as my father's one of my father's computers and this week
It's three years since the
Instructor killed your father
So weird
Canopy with a hammer
I was talking
My name is Justin
Last year my life was like a country song
First I lost my girl
But I lost my job
And I lost my house
That my dog got killed
It was just a sound we destroying my old life
Thank you