Are you awake
Listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
Let me tell you there is nothing like the she relation of Discovery I think you know that this is the end of malaria this is the end of everything else
Mosquitoes spread wait a minute you know ticks spread Lyme disease we can probably get rid of that too I thought in the morning
Singing to the turtles in the in the parking
Pretty much and I got myself a full day of being who
And then I
But but
But
What if something goes
Wrong
I'm Jenna boom Radiolab and the guy they just heard is Kevin esvelt he's a scientist
You talkin to a producers
Soren wheeler and Molly Webster about
Crispr when she's at a technology cheese and you it's a gene editing technology
Tok can we shape
Life
Yeah we ended up doing an entire show about
And we called it a antibodies part 1 river that there was going to be a part 2
That's weird name that it's like telling someone you got them a birthday present but you haven't yet
We should just own up
Radiolab listeners we did not
Liplicious listen
Texting me know we ment to we meant to have a part 2
But you know we're doing a story
It fell apart his workout
Sucked frankly and we thought I was going to Astoria
Turn turn out to be stored at now we have what we're going to do is we're going to
Pay you what your Jill the part 2
Yeah this is the part 2 finally
Part 2 because
Crispr in the time that we did the thing till now
Has gone banana crazy everyday in the science
Action which I know we all read religious
Be there is a crisper thing I started we're going to play you the original piece
For those of you who never heard it
Justice reset the Baseline and then we're going to come back and tell you all this stuff
It happened since you
There is only explain DIY got
Got started with this
You were some kind of an affair to tell you how I was at a party
It was a it was a
Conference where they have a lot of different people with different disciplines come together
You know one of those
Are panelists
Since we're at one of those functions
And
It was a situation where like dinner hadn't yet been served and there was
A lot of booze being serious everybody was like drunk on an empty stomach
So I was standing there with some violin
What are the fun ones
The jump Palace
Night my people fairly and they they start to lose
Their s***
Like genuinely lose their s***
About this thing called
And like I've never seen signs
Excited about anything
What is crispr
Trying to explain to me what they couldn't slow down enough for me to get it
I gather that had something to do with genetics and then at one point one of the biologist tournament is like
I'll tell you what it is
I can use crispr to take a little dog
And poof make it to a big dog
Give me a chihuahua
Turn it into the size of a Great Dane and was like no you
He's like yes I can I could do it with crispr
What the hell is this thing
To sit here is you
I will get
So what happened was I came back and I immediately called science writer Carl Zimmer
Because I just figured
For this kind of thing
The car thing I got tok
Dr. Carl so I like why all the fuss
Maybe it was just the alcohol or but maybe there's something really
Happening Here
Oh there's something totally happening there I mean it's
He started
So that
You you can actually find like
The first reference
In a 1987 paper
And some Japanese scientist
They basically describe something weird
N e coli and they said we don't know what this is
Coli are bacteria inside humans and like all living things
Equalize made up of DNA and T's and C's Angie's and what happened was it the scientist
Reading a chunk of that genetic code
When
They found this really strange
Stretch of DNA
Stretch out well so basically what it was
5 identical sequences
In a row
And then they were separated by very short
Sequences in between them that were
All different from each other
The little blurb
To be like
And they look at that sound like what
But this is nothing like we've seen before repeated sequences in bacterial genomes are kind of unusual
Seems very strange some biologists felt that there must be a purpose
Among those purple sneakers Jennifer doudna University of California Berkeley cell biology
If I used to be called the dude
Sometimes it's cool in the movie she will be played by Jeff
Right meow
Xango's on scientist are single repeat Loop repeats
Everywhere
Yeah release in bacteria lots and lots of lots species of bacteria
They say okay wait a minute it's kind of cool your findings it's so often
Is this where the name Christopher comes from
The full official name is
Clustered
Regularly interspaced
Short palindromic
Repeat
My gospel
I don't know why they called it
Furniture
Sound like an app
But now
Scientist had the puzzle
If nature at this level preserve something
Intact
Here and here
And here and here and here and here
And some of these here
Creatures that have been around
Hundreds of millions of years
You figure out
Whatever this is
Doing something
But what
It doesn't take very long
Before the first big clue comes up
Fast forward
2005 now scientists have these big
Searchable database
Does DNA sequencing system scientists
Bank Willis do a search
Let's see if these repeating patterns Wiki
Finding match anything else
It's out there in the world
And
The scientist guitar
Using computers to just line up these stretches of DNA with thousands upon thousands of different species and then
Click
Discover
Did those bits of DNA
Tween the repeats
Stuck in the Middle does blurt
These
Are matching virus DNA
Like you can find viruses
With
Jeanswear
The little you know these little to the bacteria had virus inside of them
Is that what that mean that that a virus brought it
Into this
The first recognition was
This is virus DNA
Somehow all these bacteria
A little snippet the virus DNA
West Indies
Particular places
Energy now
Which is a little weird if you think about that means are totally different creatures
It would be like inside a human finding a little bit of mosquito.
How do we interpret this well
Actually there was one scientist named Eugene koonin
To look at these results and just had
Okay I guess
It's a defense
Why would you think that cuz he's a brilliant man if I went to a large
Sanitation dump
And I found a teeny bit of human hair why would I think
I wouldn't know it just like a bit human
Well you see
That metaphor might
Sort of betray your lack
Skill in microbiology like this is not a dump alright this is
Bacteria are not going to just
Let virus DNA
Get into their jeans willy-nilly
Okay remember
Viruses are the big anime
If your bacteria
Viruses make your life a nightmare
Think about in the ocean okay the
The ocean is
Full of viruses and
And
Viruses kill up to 40%
Of all of those bacteria
Everyday
And
We know that they have defenses
When Eugene koonin said was
Okay
I'm going to bet that
These bacteria
Are somehow
Grabbing pieces of DNA
From viruses
And then they're storing it
And now they have a way of recognize
Does viruses have
They come in later
Take little Polaroid shots of the enemy
Write know thy enemy
Poster
What do you called the mugshot
This is Eugene koonin
Evolutionary genomics group at the national Center for biotechnology information
He's the guy that called reference to stunk up the whole idea that maybe these bits of virus DNA inside the bacteria
Is the bacteria trying to defend itself
Both but really if I if I
If I if I could eat myself
Anythink
It was not so much kissing
Because you know
Let's get freaky
Figuring
Ouch
How the mechanism of likely to be
So can you
Walk us through
How the mechanism is likely to work
All right
What happens if
You know when the fires comes in
Excel
I just kind of
Explodes in Skyrim Lisa's naked jeans basically
If you're this bacteria these things might take over your cell so you've got to respond
UShip multiple
Weapons of Defense
If you've never seen this virus
Before using the first thing you do says Eugene is you send out these enzymes
Pack the viruses they're sort of like the ground troops
Any fights really hard
But much of the time
Vape fail and then nobody else you are here about
You're not terribly stupid
It's good fighter so very often
Virus takes over
Bacteria.
But but there is some
Nonzero probability
Did you actually survive at
If you do
Then with the bacterial do with sending some new enzymes to basically cleanup
Go out find any stray viruses.
The enemy DNA into
Beautiful smokey
And here he says it's where you get to
To the storage
Does enzymes woman take those little bits of virus and shove them into the bacteria's
Own DNA right in those little spaces
Between the repeat
Right there
So I use those
Spaces in my own
DNA as a storage facility
Yes if you'll be able to exist
You use a different memory device
Cuz here's what happened
Next time that virus shows up
Express jeans everywhere now
You are
Pair
This is where the Christmas tree really gets going
Cuz instead of sending out the ground troops were probably going to get their asses
Now you can actually send out the
Guns
What the cell does it will manufacture these special
Molecular assassin
And we'll give those assassin a copy
Of that little bit of virus DNA it hasn't storage spaces thing here take this mugshot if you see anything that matches this
Pattern killer
And these attackers do we know what they look but one of them looks like
Yep so we know what the protein looks like it it it actually looks I would describe it a little bit like a clam
Sort of Imagine Pac-Man become misshapen dandruff
Which one of these guys
What it has is
A copy of that virus DNA
It's got the mugshot that is kind of waving around
What then happens is that whenever the Pac-Man bumps into some virus DNA
It pulls apart
The DNA
Is Ipsy
Read it
It's not the right one goes on
And if that RNA has the same sequence
Then click it just locks in
And molecular blades
Come out and shop
So this is smart scissors to it's like
You're like the thing I got
All right now we're going to kill
Stack match
When scientist first discovered this whole system
They're fascinated
They were like
Still working it out
They're like
How can this happen
Cool
But then
In walks the dude
Jennifer doudna
With a crazy idea what are the crazy radical
This could be amazing
Technology
This is a tool right this is a tool that we can use to cut DNA
Where we want to cut DNA
Her basic thought was when we turn this defense
Into office
These things they seem to be really good at cutting
I need the only thing to cut the things that are on their mug
Pazzo
Maybe I could just replace what's on their mugshots instead of them going after viruses
Maybe they could go after a gene that causes
Huntington's disease are haemophilia
For example
So you got a mouse with something like
Haemophilia
This is a diseases caused by one bad G
So what you do is you take diesel surgeon to give them the mugshot for the bad Gene then you stick the surgeon with the new mugshot in a mouse
Can you set it loose
And just like this program to
It will find that Gene and
Shop
The scissors will end up
Cutting exactly
Virginia wanted
The badge is gone
Now the question is how do you put in the good G
Nitrite turns out actually going to jennifer doudna
Actually not as hard as you would think
Really yeah apparently what you do is
It's just that
Throw this new good Jean
Kind of in the neighborhood where the girl genius
Just in the general vicinity
You don't have to get super-precise and it turns out that
You know there are repair enzymes that are probably continually
Surveying and checking
For brakes
This is what happens inside the cell
Is repair Crews
Come along the sea the break
The CD good Jean just sitting there next to the break to be like all right
I'll just take it in with the pretty guy in this space he said we take advantage of a natural repair
Are pathway that cells have
They trick both the Cutters and the fish
Yeah now we're not assassinating anymore
Now we're actually
Engineering
Agon from killing to refashioning
Designing jeans doing genetic
Form of genetic engineer
30 years yes but
Not like
Genome editing technology they've been around for a long time but none of them have been as powerful as
Crispr
Best Bets
Shapiro from UC Santa Cruz she was actually one of the biologists
Should I drunkenly talk to at that thing Modern Art Museum I can't even really remember
Evening setting be so vague
Back in the day
This is just like two years ago
You have these Gina De things you would take one put in a cell and what happened before was
You would give it some instructions about where to go
And it might go there but it might go somewhere that's a kind of related to where that was
Staten Island
Ridiculous
Not only would it take left Staten Island did not find there but it would cost you a fortune and taking up 6 months of your time to get
You know it's really easy
You just give it that mugshot
And it goes I'm going to find that guy
Exactly so it seems to be pretty precise
And it's
Cheap like the old tools would set you back about five grand to use them once crispr
The 75 bucks
And here's the kicker says Carl it seems
At the moment that you can take these things out of bacteria
Stickman to almost any other creature
It still works
You can use this
Same crispr system
Can you like do it
Hornets
Vulnerable
You can do in corn corn do it in anything
I have not I'm waiting for someone to say
Crispr doesn't work in
Species X
And I have not heard of that
So basically what you have for the first time in science
Is Gene editing technology that is
Is cheap
Precise
Possible universe
And Jennifer doudna says the moment the
The full impact of
Landed on Earth
I really I literally had you know the hairs on the back of my neck rest
Just processing the fact that this thing exists
You know that you could actually
Program it
To cut DNA and
Just like this
Molecular scissors and I can just
Program and it cuts DNA wherever I want
It is amazing
Unless
Think about it
Further
Which we will do engine
I feel a cloud
Coming over there
Don't you see I see you
Over there but will be right
Hi this is Lauren from Atlanta Georgia
Radiolab
Supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation enhancing public understanding of
Science and technology in the modern world
More information about Sloan at www.slha.org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
About what we're calling tiny moments
Brilliance
Basically I want to hear about those times when I kid you know did something
It just means you lean back and say wow how did they do that
Maybe it was the moment that I
Kids you've been reading to 4 month started reading back
To you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lesson
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed they're ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the specific moments where a kid does something super smart
Have anything to do with the test
If you have a story
T-shirt with us
Go to radiolab.org
Brilliance
Record a short audio message for us
Again that's radiolab.org / brilliance
Thank you so much
Is Radiolab Jad abumrad and Robert krulwich okay so clearly the
Possibilities are there to use crispr to treat disease
Right
What if you could
Get a little more fanciful
Write like what if you can actually go back in time and resurrect long-lost
Mrs. Talk about a lot we Could reconstruct using a computer
What did genome sequence of the ancestor of all birds was
And that would have been
Kind of dinosaur
Anime could use crispr to turn the chicken into that thing
For what if you could take an elephant
And
Snip snip snip
Gradually turning
Into its long-lost relative
The woolly mammoth
Cuz they're related
But if they're there
We're right but if you know the woolly mammoth genome which they do cuz
Play Family Guy.
Crossbones
Then you could
Compare the number of differences use crispr to
Crispr out
The different parts of the elephant and put in woolly mammoth
If you can infect go backwards in Thai
Time and make changes in obviously I think you can go the other way to item mean
Humans are
Good at design word designing animals
So if
It doesn't seem to me to be
Crazy notion to imagine parents all over the
Taller children so silencing the short jeans and
Favoring topology
Getting rid of wheat
Muscles and going first
Younger ones
I don't want it on and
And I don't know where the designing stop
We sorta got into all of this with
Carl Zimmer
If
If you can
Be very very Gene specific
And you learn more and more about jeans over
Why couldn't you invent
Why couldn't you make a
You might one day get supposed to get enough to do that there's no Wing in pig lab
You know is the best you can hope for right now is a woolly mammoth lab and that's down the hall from where the
Where the
The real action is is it now there's a hall and at the end of the phone Tuesday wing it has not been built yet
It may be 20 years from now but that's what you looking at
Well yeah I think but the thing is
Well because you can't make weight
Winnie the Pooh
Just because it's her evolutionary barrier
Okay well just forget stuff like except for the joke
Okay I don't think that we need
Federal
Department
Homeland
Spring security I think we're okay there all right
But we do need
Is like
We do need to like figure out what are we going to do about
Crispr
I mean they're going to be using crispr for cancer
Going to take me to take people's immune cells out of their body
Unable to use crispr
To basically allow them to make proteins are going to be able to
Grab onto
Cancer cells
And attack their own cancer
We all have to be
What animal are you for
Georgiou
Uart Inc
You are tinkering with someone's own body
You are altering their own
Selves
Dude
Where do I
It's just I can use it with this is
Meet I don't know if it's a religious thought or just
The thought of a conservative person
I'm not screw up in the
In a test tube baby error
Now know many wonderful
Adult farmer Lita
I remember being astonished
Set
No soy
I can't I don't know where the sacred
Begins and ends
I'm not pretty
I guess what I'm instead on is I'm on
On
A hobbesian view of human beings
But there is something about
Human beings including scientist
Volume
There's a darkness and a light there
There's an Angelic side to Being Human on this
Very very
Difficult synonym
As the human beings get more and more
Create and design and
Creative
Future
That future will include
The imagination
Both light and dark
Humans
And that will be new in the world
I don't think it is new because if you go back to the start of the Scientific Revolution some like France
Does bacon with say explicitly like
Science
Is
Going to be both about learning about how the world works
And
Using that knowledge
You know this has been discovered this is been published
Everybody knows it
If you if you guys had a cocaine that we're going to all we're going to outlaw.
I'm not the same
What what are you suggesting
Cringe Lewis one two three
What is it now
I don't know
We are permitted if that's where you are
Ukraine
Shoe creams with attitude
Dial Beijing with with dragons
You're saying
You're saying oh my God
Forget to that conversation with Carl was 4 months ago
And a lot has happened
Pikachu the question that you asked
Like where does the sacred
Christian and will one of the lines that have been drawn
By Jennifer down on others was that we should not
Use the technology
Humans who haven't been born yet meaning not on sperm cells
Are egg cells because if you crispr say an embryo that is it that is a permanent change
Right that is a change to the DNA that will be passed on to their children
And their children's children and their children's children's children you can't ask
The
Person
If that's okay because you're doing it
Before they're born
Send
The real issue
Imagine making these changes
Cascade through generation after generation
You could affect the evolution of organism
And
I want to say trivial but it's you know it's fairly easy to do it
Kind of profound I feel it's really for
Profound profound but it was just an idea
That is until for the first time in history researchers in China have successfully edit the human genome and
An embryo just two months ago
It was announced that a Chinese team used a technique called crispr
In human embryos Evolution itself
The Chinese team they were not viable
You actually develop into a person so they're they're going to be discarded anyway still they can figure it out with those embryos what's the stop any
Boston ethical line
Just sort of thing could be serviced slippery slope towards
Okay
Now that the Grinch party
It's Fred and Robert didn't seem like
We called up Carl again
But we have to revisit we have to revisit because in our Armageddon conversation in which I believe I was
Extremely alarmist and You lyrics
Extremely down putting I feel that I should do a small little parade
Cubby
Remember the Alamo remember remember China
And you have to close you should just begin anytime you want like getting on your knees and saying how sorry you are going to start from there
I'm sorry so are we actually surrounded by an army of clones with soup
Super powers
Yeah but I think the Dyke has been opened I believe I'm going to quote somebody who said
Maybe a few weeks ago I think you want me because last week you can writing for naturally
I think it was maybe with somebody
Girl
Who said that the news from China and that news
Probably
The beginning of an entire New Era and I think I actually said it was a historical moment
And I and I still stand by that
Do you feel differently now than the first time
I don't feel different
Actually because
Didn't really know
Scientific
Surprise here
He says people been doing all these crispr experiments and all these different mammals
We're mammals this is bounded
In fact it may be happening more than we think
One account in the journal Nature has said that
For other Chinese labs
What are doing this kind of work
Carlyle Soto
Which she said was unsurprising to buttocks
Rising
The crisper work the Chinese team did
Didn't work very well
It works
Kind of
I mean in only a few of the cases
Did they really get
Exactly what they want
They tried using crispr in about 86 embryos and they only got to work right and maybe 28
A lot of them
Mistress made the wrong cuts
Screwed up the cells and that led them to conclude that this is a technology that's not ready
Right now for application in the humans
And
I agree
We still are in this kind of fortunate position where we can see it's dangerous
So we shouldn't
Use it
Animal human embryo
I just don't think that we're going to be able to certify find Refuge there in like 10 or 20 years and 10 or 20 years
Crispr will be
So sophisticated
The people will be able to say
I can get you
The change you want
And I can do it safely
I can guarantee you that you will have human embryos at
Have
The alteration in the
A particular Gene Yuan
So then what
Is that Jennifer doudna told us that this experiment similar experiments have been repeated in mice
With
Moore Advanced crispr system
Is it really there
There it was done with almost no air
Sometimes I feel like we're certain
Displacing all are ethical concerns
Onto
Something that hasn't happened yet
We really are concerned about
What we're doing
The human gene pool
You know it's already here
Take
As an example in vitro fertilization
About 60000 kids are born a year through IVF and
Probable that
Some of those
Parents chose what they wanted a boy or a girl and when people start doing IVF there was a huge controversy
See people said this was dangerous
Unnatural
I don't see
People
Who are unable to sleep at night because of the existence of IVF
You know I'm going to sound like I'm on Roberts out of this I mean okay so
So won't hurt
It will be alright
Are you okay so
So you guys know about all the stuff going on Iceland where they're looking
People's DNA and
Another looking for
Do these jeans and so on
And
When they're looking at these Icelandic people they found that some people
Had
A gene that
Protect them
Gets Alzheimer
Reduces our odds of getting outside
Let's imagine your doctor said
Know if you
Like for an extra $1,000
We will take these IVF embryos and we will
Use crispr
To give them the Alzheimer
Protecting
Variant
Would you like that
You want to add that to your to your procedure
Or would you like your child to
Two-Face
Teacher of of
Alzheimer's
Your choice
Teachers might here's my thing here is anything with this hole
I'm a little bit haunted by the thing you said which is
When it's not dangerous anymore
What will we
We do and I'm afraid we've already answered
It is not it's not a
Question that's open
Because if we're already doing this kind of
Stuff and who's going to say no to that
Who's going to say no to that
Yeah we've already answered the
Yeah
We may have
So that's how we ended our peace
Just now two years old
Broccoli
Roughly and the drunk biologists at Chad's cocktail party couldn't have been more pressure when you think about it
This is one of those this is one of those strange cases where like you do a story usually like we just going to leave it behind other things but
In the last
Almost 2 years
So much has happened
So we figured we need to update this thing so what we did is we asked our produce return wheeler and our producer Molly Webb
Just go out ask around make some calls and
Ellis
You know
What's been going on
41 Molly do you want to give him the big news
The Jennifer Lopez is going to do a television show based on crispr
Give me an active role in the fictional narrative of the show
She's like something old something and crispr is involved
Really yeah where you at headlines
Wow it's crossover to that extent that's the thing is that gets the sum
And I like that I was like Jennifer Lopez knows about crispr and she was like this is such a hot-button issue Where do I
That's amazing
Okay so so
Moving putting JLo aside science development have been quite a few
House right now what are those
I mean I guess I would just say that it's being used everywhere now so it's being used in crops
It's being used in medicine it's being used in basic research
It's being used hermansau and humans being used in eyeballs
Clinical trial with actually injecting a syringe full of crispr carrying viruses into your eye
Eyeball to overcome a genetic condition
What leads to blindness to this would be like with the viruses injecting the crisper the thing goes and cuts out the bad genes
Exactly just take
You know a big syringe full of viruses and just stick it in people's eyes
Yes so course when we did the update
Soren and I called Carl Zimmer
Things are moving very fast
And what kind
Thanks so
They are
Doing things that look like
Curing diseases so Carl told us about one study
Where
It seems like they cured a certain type of muscular dystrophy in mice
Cured must be cured muscular dystrophy in mice
Wow well then might not become normal nice but they get much much stronger
Then they would have been yeah so in your body you have a gene
That makes a protein that gives your muscle
Full strength but with muscular dystrophy
There's like
Typos in that Gene a mutation into that proteins not made and the result is that
Your muscles start to turn into sort of a
Fat-like substance
Has been described no power
Yeah okay so your diaphragm gets weaker and weaker your heart gets weaker so in this case they use crispr
To fix that Jean
So you get
Protein in these mice
I actually saw
At the heart get stronger or the mouse
Was able to push with more Force
I'm button until they said over weeks they just saw like strength-building up
Are they going to do that humans pretty first
Pretty First Step be at this point but yeah this is one of the first experiments to show that this approach could work
Muscular dystrophy vitamin that's not a disease
With a cure is it not until
Potentially in mice now yeah
And there are some human trials that it be there
Started or
I probably going to start soon treating cancer example people are talking about one and lung cancer
What
Sure lung cancer or no
What they want to do though is they want to
Use crispr to go into immune cells where would cut out the part of the DNA that
How to put the brake on the immune cell
And
So you're you're taking your immune cell off the leash
I can attack
Tumors
Marc Gasol
So the folks who invented this then must stand to earn a fortune
There's actually a big patent
Dispute
That's happening right now so one of the guys know this is the one thing that I have heard
About a lot of you had been checking your crispr inbox you might have seen last week
There were two teams
Jennifer doudna steam out at UC Berkeley from the West Coast team and then on the other side
Is this group of researchers at the broad Institute
Witches on East Coast
And so basically they both filed for a crispr patent so there was sort of this like
East Coast West Coast
For the last
Year
Showdown and just last week
The US patent office decided
That it would indeed go to produce is the not doubting
The not doubt the team but there are more patent super awarded
And there will probably be a peel so I don't think anyone thinks it's settled yet
So in the Civil War of
Over over crispr patents
There has been a Gettysburg
There are many more battles
What happened
Gacha
Is there is there anything else on the on the list of like What's Happening Now exciting stuff happening now
Oh yeah
Can we do favorite strike and I do kind you're my favorite and then you can do your favorite
My my favorite came from Carl
Yeah yeah they're actually trying to use it
As an alternative to antibiotics
We're headed to know what I'm saying that means
What do you say eyes like an antibiotic to me is a pill that I tell you
So what would crispr Howard crispr replace that
Well you
Your pill would have crispr in it
How how would it work you know in the same way you would take your amoxicillin or your antibiotic pill
You would actually take a pill that was filled with crispr
And then it would go out and it was fight bacteria
That is attacking your body
So you could pick out you know some super essential Gene that it has
And chop it
And that will kill the bacteria
Oh you would turn the Assassins on the bacteria exactly
So there you go
Yeah the antibiotics thing seems huge right cuz everyone's at this moment where they're like what happens with the Neck Road for bug
If you could actually just go in there and Kamikaze the DNA of like
Staff or whatever he'd be solving a lot of illness
Yeah but what's what what's your fave
Maybe the scariest to hi Kevin how are you I'm doing great how are you
Kevin esvelt
I'm at the MIT media lab
He was sort of on the early edge of thinking about crispr I meant I think of myself as an evolutionary engineer before anything
Got into biology because when he was a kid he went to the Galapagos
My parents took me there when I was
10 or so and I was just captivated
Just looking all the creatures and I thought I want to make organisms that are as beautiful as that
You actually thought I want to make organisms as beautiful as that
That's like the childhood vision and then it's so hard right
Forget it
And but now with crispr like
Almost like All Things become possible
So anyway to get to the crazy part Kevin couple years back he's working at the Harvard Medical School and one day
He's walking to work through this some the spark this
Park called the emerald necklace
In Boston
It's beautiful and there's a small river flowing through it and you have these
Ponds with turtles in whatever giesen and you know he's thinking about
Crispr and what he can do and all these
Animals that are around him
And he has this
This thought
What if
We could
Encode crispr
In the genome
What if we
Program The genome to genome editing on it
Own
Wait what what I'm I'm I'm not sure if all that what is it what is he saying well
The first
Gene drives
Maybe this is the way to think about it
Let's say that you want to tweak a mosquito
And make it so that the
Little parasite that carries malaria terrible awful malaria
Either can't get into the mosquito or can't live in it until that mosquito will no longer carry malaria that would be great that would be a great day
Think is malaria is a bad thing so you could now take crispr
I send it into the mosquito and change the gene inside the mosquito so now that mosquito either
Doesn't let malaria parasite in or kills it or whatever but basically doesn't carry it and that's great
Right but then I put it on to the wildness got us
And for itself amongst all the other mosquitoes so my mosquito has a special Gene but it's going to mate with some mom
Mosquito
And that Mom is he doesn't have the normal old Jean
And the baby's going to get my specialty but it's also going to get the normal
Gene and that means that your baby has like a 50% chance
Having your
Special training of because
Only one of those two genes gets
Sprite in the baby and then in the Next Generation the grandbaby there's only a 25% chance and you know on and
On and on
So you're exponentially losing Chris
Superpowers your chances just each generation get less and less of this Gene is going to stick around that's right because
Regardless of what we do natural selection wins in the end
Until Kevin is walking to work through the park and has his idea which is to use
Crispr to create something called
Gene Drive
I came to drop yeah
Instead of just skip the DNA and insert a gene that we want
Also insert the genes that encode the crispr system
And tell it to make that particular change
Here's how it works
You go into the mosquito and give it the new Gene that makes it resistant to malaria
And then right next to that
You put the jeans for the
Crispr system you just used to make that change a spare scissors or something
An insurance how that plays out your first mosquito has this Gene with the new change
And it also has the scissors yeah I'm going to meet some normal mosquito which has the normal
The two end up
Side by side in the baby
Now the new mosquito Gene makes the Little Caesars which go over to the normal Gene
Snip it
And turn it into itself
So now there's two copies
Of the new Gene in The Offspring without
Any human assistance
Crispr will cut
Original version
And copy over the change
That Jean does the work that I used to do in the lab
On its own inside the baby
So interesting to okay so like I set it on autopilot
So you're basically allowing the mosquito
Parent
Pass the scissors to the baby don't we send snip snip snip
And then that baby passes the scissors to the next baby up nip snap it is literally like a chain reaction yeah
So you know
From 82 grandbaby to Great grandbaby now instead of letting that Gene disappear
You're driving it into the Next Generation
That just keeps going down the line down the line down the line
This is something that spreads
Indefinitely
This Gene is going to spread like wildfire through the entire wild populations you don't change
Just one mosquito
All of those insects probably everywhere in the world
According to Kevin this is the kind of change that could given enough time
Spread across the entire
Species
So this
This idea of mosquitoes and
Watching Rampage true population of the dumbness
After we had four
Publish the idea
We tried it in East
Work on the first try
They just popped a little yeast loaded with the gene drive into a population to see if it would take over and
One week later
Yep
Kevin told us they're probably now I think it's
10 different groups who are working on Gene Drive systems yes they are doing it
And mosquitoes and in parasitic worms and in rodents
It's all happening in the lab is still they are
Trying out
You know
Dismiss method for spreading genes through a population
Yeah
I just think that sounds terrifying
Like honestly I just keep thinking of it's like oh we've we've just
Hit over a domino and then walked away and aren't watching where the rest of them are falling
I'm very glad you think that was me one full day
The reach that point
Initially I was slated
Let me tell you there is nothing like the she relation of Discovery I think you know this is the end of malaria this is the end of every
Hangouts mosquitoes spread
Wait a minute no ticks spread Lyme disease we can probably get rid of that too
I thought in the morning you're like you're singing to the turtles in the in the parking
Pretty much a full day of being
Who
And then I started thinking but but
But
What if something goes wrong
And supposed
Go back to your malaria case
Make mosquitoes malaria resistant well that seems
Pretty safe I mean malaria is a human
Pathogen
Doesn't really affect
Other animals
But what if
Say the change you make to the mosquito
Makes it slightly more toxic something to eat so
When you have to contend with those mosquitoes in
Boasting
You know it could be that all the frogs are the Fisher whatever start to die off and then that make something else die off and something else
I'll stay off
Credibly complex system and you just you just don't know or if you could be that making a mosquito malaria
Deer resistant also somehow
Makes it do better in some environment than the mosquito population blows up and then it turns out that it somehow makes it
Easier to carry some
Other disease
So
And yours are more likely to go wrong
But
How do you know we should say at this point that Kevin is
Really thinking about all the stuff he brought together a group of scientists to come up with some safeguards for this type of Reese
Research so doesn't
Escape out of the lab and and his team is only working with this version of Gene Drive the day
Pacer rigged it
So that it only lasts for certain number generations and it's her runs out of steam but
Scientist
Can perfectly well
Start playing around with something in the lab
That could affect a whole lot of other people
What happened to ask
I think what this
Technology forces us to reckon with
Is that now it's
Ffbe Reddit
We don't know for sure but
Theoretically possible for one person
Decide
To change the local
Possibly the global environment
And that
Ethically problematic race
I mean if if and when somebody uses crispr
An embryo and that embryo grows up into a person
That will be a momentous thing but if you were to Gene Drive somebody
Think about that
Can a gene Drive likes a few people in and. Tell them in
You don't have kids and someone like
And you'd be driving
Whatever Gene it is that you were engineering midterm or more people
I'm and
That's
That's different
God you know what I'm thinking about
Thing that Jennifer doudna said I think it was her in our first piece of
Like if you make a change and say an embryo like you looking to give this to me snip snip snip give this
Future child
Make it all alright
Whatever
Like you're doing that without the consent of that Unborn
Yes but if you if you know do what you guys are talking about using this Gene Drive thing
Well now your
Doing it without the consent of that unborn thing and all future generations of that unborn thing and to the consent issues
Just become like
Unfathomable
Exactly
You know I guess we're all for taller
But
All for taller
Show me and it has something to do with democracy itself like you sit there with a tool
A change in your hand and you choose it but in the act of the with his truck in
Any active choosing it for yourself this way you choose it for an uncountable number of others who do not have the
Thanks you too storm wheeler Molly Webster for the update
And the people we think the first time cuz of snakes still
The band
Many thanks to science writer Carl Zimmer many books
You can check them out at Carl Zimmer. Com radiolab.org this piece was produced by Molly Webster
Are we had original music This Hour by Eric Kowalski otherwise known as
Casino versus Japan special things to honor us with pause
Lee Mcguire Dr Blake wiedenheft
Dr. Luciano marraffini dr. John Burgess dr. Janeway she
I'm Jared I'm Robert krulwich thanks for listening
One quick note a business some of you may remember we get a show about meat allergies a little while back with the inimitable Amy
We did that together with the sporkful podcast
Preacher WNYC it turns out they've just a little follow-up with Amy she went back to get tested for her allergy one more time
And the results were not at all what you expect
So you might want to check that out at the sporkful
Dot-com
To hear the message again
Press 2
Delete at start of message
Radiolab
Ellenhorn
Not guilty in Louisiana
Melissa Donald County pageant Ariana
Molly Webster going wheeler
New York
Without from getting Lewis Kelly crime
And Damiano marchetti
Fact Checkers are you cold after
Michelle Harris
And this message