Are you weightless
Radio WNYC
It's going on tomorrow
This is gonads episode 2
Emily Webster
Oh okay my dashboard says
12 degrees outside
It's all okay so in January I went to
Erie Pennsylvania second attempt at Erie first attempt was snowed out on the New York side thank you bomb cyclone
It was like the Arctic winters of my youth are ice fishermen out on the lake
There was like some sort of Records
Setting
Snowfall in Erie that I'm
Schurz probably still melting up there
And I had landed in this in this Frozen land
To do a story about people freezing things
But not
Not things that you would expect to be frozen I don't know what you expect out of frozen this but it's not that
Tofutti cuties
Ice cream
Should I freeze my gosh
Blueberries
Fruit
But actual body parts
I like it starts at this house I'm going to we're going to the house here we are
Hi
And the people who
We're at the center of the freezing
Weirdest couple my name is an hour that's 1/2
That's the other half
I could sit right
Let's start at the beginning
That's a crazy story. I told you that right
Well 1999 I was teaching High School phys-ed it was a Friday she had just finished coaching
Volleyball and her dad called
And he said hey I'm leaving work early I'm going to go to this fish-fry I will swing by
And pick you up let's go grab some
Amateur
He goes I'll be over in about 15 minutes
It's okay
Enikos
It wouldn't hurt to look a little nice
Can you put the phone on him like you
Cuz I was literally in like a Nike outfit with my sneakers that he's Jim I just finished coaching sole I don't like and that's how I would have gone to dinner
Dinner with my dad better dad
Had ulterior motive
How old is the guy that I work with going to meet us and I'm like
You suck me up
We're driving over there at how old
56 years old at your age like how old is he
He's asleep and honestly maybe a little older than you
So they get the bar got a couple of beers
And then Skywalk sofa
Looking
List of courses we sat down at a booth
Ate dinner and by the end of dinner and he's thinking free call and sowa
One date leads to two two leads to three at that point they ditch your dad
Because he had
Stillman hanging out with him and your later things have gotten pretty Siri
We still have that policeman if I was looking at the other day
Kitchen get it on like what is a placemat is coming out just grab it to her listeners
White
Scalloped edges
Some yellow food stain Stylo mustard this placemat is from date that they
Around there one year
Which was almost 20 years ago
Texas Roadhouse
Visit Texas Roadhouse Texas Roadhouse
Roadhouse Texas Roadhouse peanuts a great peanut butter
Set a certain point three
Peanuts or whatever the conversation turns
The future
Like they were going to be together what do you want
What do you imagine and we just kind of were
You're talking about all sorts of things like kind of a little to goal-setting that we like how much
What you want to make it real casual where do you want to live
Florida would like that the climate we put the on there I think something like we want to be in Florida in 2005
They're jotting down children together to kids at least
Agreed on that Greg had already expressed at some point the family was super important to him he loves having brothers and sisters
Like we went to Christmas Eve this past Christmas and
I need the
45 people there
It was all family but it's like they don't write down that they just want to have kids they start writing down
Jack Tower
Jimmy
Tyler Joseph Joey's real names were throwing around boys names and then we had four girls Taylor
Madeline Bobbi with an i because his dad's name was Robert in the neighborhood our own names down on it
And he signed the day
I just want to say guys this doesn't seem casual
Pretty intense
Casual dinner we covered it all
Your definition of casual and mine are very different
A few months after that date
They gone one of their first big trip
To the Superbowl
In Tampa Bay
And
The morning of the Super Bowl
We are laying in the hotel room and I woke up and I felt like
She had
This feeling of a weight
On her chest
100 pound weight sitting on my chest
Like I couldn't catch my breath
Should we come back from the Super Bowl they go to the doctor doctor runs a bunch of tests
And then a week later they go back
And
They're like you want the good news or the bad news and I was like the bad news
It's not like
It's cancer
Okay
Not good
It turns out she had this
Are you big tumor
Write down her breast
Plate like where your ribcage meets like right over your heart and lungs
How big are we talking
Grapefruit size
Wow
You know you think he answering you want me to think you're dying
Are you going to die but her doctor said good news is that is Hodgkin's lymphoma
And it has a cure rate of like 95 /
She said that the doctor literally was like
Spine called it a slam dunk
But
It's still super scary any cancer scare you
Findom
At some point and he finds herself sitting down with Greg and saying
You don't have to
You didn't sign on for this like we haven't even been dating a year yet you know you're young
Hey there good-looking guy you can find another girl and you can be guaranteed like
Wicked future
You know I said run
When we got diagnosed
It's just like boom
Just like we would have to
Trust
From
Kindest Fast Track relationship and we're really having fun and join each other moving moving pretty quick
And then bam we got hit with that
So you got to do one or two things USA do I
Do I love this woman in am I ready to go on this kind of this tough Journey that's going to be had
Or am I going to get out
There's going to be one of the other right there's no gray in that Cincinnati
So
That's when I
Right
Upholsterer
Well
Okay she says yes
And so like newly-engaged that go through this cancer treatment
In about nine months later after all the treatments done she goes in for another scan
And all of the cancer
Is totally eradicated
Except for this one thumbnail size
Tumor.
Grapefruit
Tumor out of my chest to my spleen dissipated
It was still their waist smaller but it was still there right in the middle of her chest and if that point
The doctor looks scared I saw Terror in his eyes like he was he was
Was confused
Cuz he was like I gave you the normal regimen
There must be something else going on like that should be gone
Didn't know what else to do
Buttendz insurance work with a good cover that so they just decide
Screw it let's just get married right now
And so we had like this real kind of small impromptu wedding at st. Gregory's
Star immediate family brothers and sisters Mom and Dad invited
Somber
Cuz it was like
Will I be alive
Like
It's a big
What if
6 days later their New York City with a new doctor
Dr. Carol portlock Sloan-Kettering and they had spent all of their
Test results to this docker
They have their first meeting they go through another month of test
And then
She sits down
Says
Okay
I've looked over your test results
And you have stage 4
Non-Hodgkin's lymphoma
She gets very aggressive
And
It's a 70% chance you're going to die
I just remember feeling like
Kind of like with her words and how quick they were in kind of cold it was kind of like
Might not
Turn out the way we both really really wanted to
Ask the doctor how you treat this
Your says it's this super intense chemotherapy and a stem cell transplant which is
A very intense procedure and then I asked her
What can I do about my fertility and she looked at me like I had three heads you know like
My darling
Forget the fertility
You're fighting for your life
A nanny says back to her
No I want children
Like I don't think you get it
We have a plan
I put this on a placemat I signed it I'm going to beat this you might not believe it
I believe
I'm having kids
I'm having kids with Greg
And when I asked her why she was so adamant about it she just said
It was a couple of thing
One she was always really wanted to be a mom that's what I wanted I wanted to be a mom
Just Married Greg just made this promise that they could have kids together and she felt like if she
Couldn't do that she was breaking
That promise
Okay so I get through it and then
He's maybe not going to want to be with me anymore like you know like once I get healthy because
He's got dreams of himself individually like separate from mine you know even though we're married you know I mean like
Kind of like a worried that like maybe if we can't have
Have kids but like we might break up
Not really a worry
But I thought, you know as usual a there in your
Well I definitely wanted kids
You know but I wasn't
I don't know where this goes I'll be I'll be happy
And so
We are Focus my focus
I'm getting her healthy
It was interesting cuz whenever they talked about like kids
Or when there is M at that time like
Trying to get through stuff they kept
Throwing their hands kind of forever they kissed
Keep saying like
Like they were like tossing something in front of him they would make the gesture of life
Of like
I'm going to stand like throwing a ball out
Get your hand gestures are in
Interesting cuz everytime you talk about kids
You're like
Shooting your hands out away from your body like
Putting something out there in front of you that then you can like he of Yourself chords
All right
Reel it in you know you're out there
Circular things you can see it
I don't know I just felt like it was
Hope
Of
There's the gold go get it
So
Portlock is like
No I don't think you understand like
We need to get you in treatment right away like within like maybe a week
And any fertility treatment would take too long like egg freezing takes too long IVF
That would take weeks
But Annie is just like
Come on anything give me a shot
And she just paused for about 30 seconds
And then she goes
There is a doctor
Across the street at Weill Cornell
He is
A fertility specialist
She's doing a study right now
I don't know much about it but
I will make sure you have an appointment tomorrow morning
So the next morning Annie is in the doctor's office across
The street and in walks this mystery.
All right the duck is in the house
Crazy curly black hair
Me and a white lab coat on for faster
And like
I kind of like this guy don't know why I like this guy
Do you remember when you met her
Yeah and was one of the
First few patients that we did the freezing for
Oh this is our guy from a episode 1 Mr magical Donuts on Hazard a magical Oregon
Yeah
Okay we're back with the magic of the gonads we're about to re-enter the magic land
And he's also the guy that brings us to freezing
But
First a little contact
Acquired an egg and sperm and sex
And then
Some magic happened and a baby popped out
We started trying to figure out how to control that process
So what starts
The freezing of reproductive parts
Don't started with sperm 1700s they realize that
Sperm
Slow down and became really sleepy when it got cold
I don't know but that's what they saw
It wasn't until the 1950s and they actually figured out how
To freeze sperm thawed sperm
And then use that to make
A real baby
And then
It's like okay well
We figured out sperm that's like half the population
So what about
Eggs
And so they start trying to
Freeze eggs that that turns out to be a lot harder
Because eggs are so
Full of liquid
So when you try and freeze them ice crystals for a minute
Pierce's the egg
And it's at this point sort of in the 90s that act a walks into the room
He was studying
Kind of
Eggs in general and fertility
And he ends up in a lab
That is saying you know if we can't freeze eggs
Maybe what we should actually do is just freeze the ovary
Which is a totally different ballgame because an ovary is an entire organ
I'm a big
How big is
7/8 minutes the size of like a
I don't know a walnut
But yeah it's not a small task it is still a whole working
And that is actually what is
Cool about this whole thing
Because it is the Egg Factory
See if you can figure out how to freeze an ovary you can potentially freestyles
The banks
And so
When an e shows up onto the scene
This was just an idea it had never been done before
Different animals but the idea that Hansel doctors including okte had was
4 women and an e situation you know let's freeze some of your ovarian tissue and then maybe one day that technology
Will catch up
And we can do something with it
So when Annie walked in the door
How
Experimental was what you were doing
No it was a highly experimental because
She was one of the first few patients
And he comes in and
She says
There's this thing
It's ovarian freezing this is brand-new I've never successfully done this in a human
There were no pregnancies are in
He told Annie what I'm doing here is a shot in the dark and this is like the basketball shot all the way across the court at the buzzer
But unfortunately this is your only option
And then she said she was basically Life Bouquet
He explained the process the new this is what we will try to do we can take out one of your ovaries freeze it in liquid nitrogen
And then
If you survived your cancer which is big if at this point
And if you make it to the two-year Mark which is a big landmark
For cancer survivors
We can look at reimplanting it
You just hear those papers you like sign away so I can
Sign my name like
Do you remember when any of the waivers were
I just signed everything
Didn't read it just sign
Like he could have been the first sighting it's a China we're going to have babies with like your ovary over there
I did not like
I did not like to pay any attention
I just wanted a chance
Coming up she gets a chance
And things get weird
Emily Webster this is gonads on Radiolab
Stay tuned
This is Kelly powers in El Cerrito California
Radiolab presents gonads
Is supported in part by science and box assignments Foundation initiative dedicated to engaging everyone with the process
Science
Additional support for Radiolab is provided by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
I hate everybody Pat Walters here I'm a producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help this summer I'm hosting a series of Stories on the show
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
About what we're calling tiny moments childhood Brilliance basically I want to hear about this
So did something
It just means you read back and say whoa how did they do that maybe it was the moment that a kid
Did you been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons and you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed are ready music in the margin of their geometry homework were interested in
Epic moments where a kid does something super smart but it doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story please share it with us
Go to radiolab.org brilliance
Record a short audio message for us
Fan that's radiolab.org / Brilliance thank you so much
It's Molly we're back
Picking up where we left off its right after getting this
Terrible cancer diagnosis in Annie is in the OR and Doctor Octopus
Takes out one of her ovaries
What walk me to the operation what's involved
As far as surgeries go it's
It's super simple easy painless
He put you under anesthesia and then he makes
An incision in her abdomen where you go through patients bellybutton with a camera and then
Two little love
Punctures along the bikini line and we can pull the ovary out
Through that incision in the belly button
And then they drop it in a freezer this is like a 45-minute the outpatient procedure
Once it's done you just walk home yeah oh yeah
A week later
She's at Memorial Sloan-Kettering getting chemo
And the treatment is like
Saying
She goes through rounds of chemotherapy where she gets chemo all weekend in a lake the big
Ziplocs like the freezer bags like the gallon
That's what they were hanging up
Field of chemo
Thumbs up
Down one up time for another one
Time for another one
Constant in this kind of chemo they kill a lot of
Cells in your body
Good cells your bad cells your immune cells are stem cells they kill everything you're basically dead for all
Purpose of them in the blood counts are all by no doubt there's no there's nothing
Is there a whitetail red Zara playlist
From there she gets a stem cell transplant which is taking your blood out and putting stem cells back in
India is at then she would regrow her immune system hopefully without cancer
May 26th
I walked out of
Annie is
False no eyelashes no eyebrows
Skinny male stores it sucks
But according to the doctors
They were like you're good she's cancer-free
You're clear so when we got out we walk to the park
Got slice
Her people was at the greatest pizza ever
The sun is shining and horns honking and it was New York like it was like I said as I not like
Like this is life
There was
Pretty good chance that the cancer could come back
Pusheen Greg go home and
Wait
1 month goes by
That place Matt was just like
Hanging like on the fridge Rent-A-Center like
Floating there
3 months
For I would think about the cancer
Most of the day
Where would like
Is it going to go back
Where is it
Bye
Fix
A year goes by than 18 months
Still no cancer
When did you
First have the ovary reenter your mind
Well
Started to I went
May 13th of 04
You know the two-year mark
They did a pet
Pet scan blood work all that and
I was clear
And that
Jay wenzhou Lactaid
Just walked across the street
In what you remember is the last time she talked to aktay the deal was
Get to the two-year Mark if he gets the two-year Mark give me a call I have no idea where will be at with this technology
No idea if I'm going to be able to give you a baby but we'll see
Now in that interim period in those two years okte had been continuing to experiment
Working with other patients taking thought tissue and putting it back in them
What not wear YouTube
Expect
Originally we did this in the forearm
Like my under my watch like on my forearm
Correct it would just take it and stick it in the muscle
In the forearm
An ovary in the forearm
How does that even make sense
Will it make sense because this is how crazy weird
Like an ovary is
You can put it literally anywhere in the body that has good blood supply
Nginx
3 to 10 days
New blood vessel
So just it just pops on
How do you get a baby out of an ovary that's in your forearm
Oh so the idea is
That you could just
Yesterday
Lock the mature eggs
Out from just underneath the skin
And then you could combine them with a sperm in a Petri dish and just do normal IVF read makeup
Umbreon petri dish and then implant
Got you but by the time an Ewok didn't know one had done this and gotten it to work there had yet to be
A baby born from an ovarian trance
When Anna showed up though
Octavius ready
He said I'm going to take the 21 in strips
These little bits of her ovary that have been frozen
For two years so we're going to suit your own right underneath your your belly button in your stomach
Well he has he put prior to me he had put a few in a woman's rear end
No really it actually wasn't in that did that but rumor on the street is that there's no Rihanna but somewhere but he's cell
That putting it closest to where
The other ovary is and where its original spot was
Was probably the most beneficial migas
Hopefully within 2 months you'll get
Menstruation cycle and he goes and then you'll come out of menopause
Cuz remember that chemo would shut down that remaining over and put her in a full on menopause
We don't
We just got to say
Swanky does the procedure again it's super simple implants a few bits of over in the skin next to your belly button
2 months later started field first little marbles
Down around her belly button have these lumps
Describe it but like under the skin can actually like kind of grab it
Put your finger right here you could you can feel them and should you notice certain times of the month that they would be able to get images
Bigger
Eggs on the skin
It was really weird I mean I have all different sizes like sometimes less than a dime sometimes as big as a quarter
I just feel like if you rub your finger across
Almost like just a bigger version of kind of like to hit you know they have the money I'd like to Braylon the elevators
Talk to it actually measure them
The interesting measuring tape in like put like marks on and he'd like measure the circumference he like
It's good.
He says they hurt me I couldn't buckle my jeans cuz the bucket like the button on the jeans would hurt
Pressing against
Skin cuz they were sticking out you know
To Alaska
Pants are like real pretty
So about a month after the Marvel show up
They find out in New York City for a series of appointments
First
Eye cancer check-up to get a PET scan
Next day they go Seahawks
And that's when
All these interesting things beginning to happen
Andy's on the exam table for sandwiches always so uncomfortable and then all of a sudden
Autism
Oh my God
And I think I almost passed out
And I'm like
Is everything okay
He's like this
This can't happen
Dr. Hockett what is wrong
Hold on
Makeup look look and he's looking at the Monitor and doing also
I said what can't be he was
You're pregnant
What
Yeah it was just
An unbelievable moments
I was like
I'm pregnant
No looking at the right patients take a look at the chart again
Wait she's pregnant
What is that mean
I mean no one really knows what it means it means that there are eggs that are protruding out of foreskin
And yet somehow there's also an embryo in her uterus
I said
How
The old-fashioned way sweetheart
He was like no no really
How
He's like
I don't know
And then
He's like wait
I'm trying to find a heartbeat
It turns out there was no heart
It's not viable
And it
It goes on from there
They get into the car
Phone rings
It's dr. Moskowitz from Sloan
Like why is he calling us
The shoes going to drop
The cancer's back right cuz we just had a pet scan like
Literally the the day before
So she picks up the phone like everything okay
He's like your scans are
Uclear
Okay
I thought you're coming cuz I know what you thought
Izzy's I was calling to tell you that the answers back and make it back to the hospital and I was like yeah
Music note
You're cancer-free
Did you know you're pregnant
Just found out
I think you want to talk to and I said yeah
Did you know your pregnant before your the Patsy
I said
Now
The Pet Scan of killed it
He said yes
So that was
Cuz it was like
Shat
Why that is crazy whiplash
Wait can I just
You just catch up here
How did this
Like she's got marbles in her belly by
Marble Center Valley
And now you're saying that suddenly a baby appeared in her uterus
It's a long way away from her belly button
I don't get it
I don't get it likes it what did the belly button
Is it
What happened
That that's the quest
There are so many different definitely something
Happened there
And what was that something
Divine intervention
I don't know
So act a Venturi does publish to papers on this
And he raises like a lot of different ways
This could happen
In Annie says maybe the thing to remember for all these explanation
So if you think about Annie's body right now there's the one ovary that was left inside
That is now defunct
Describes
Dead over
It's been killed by the chemo
Right so you got the dead ovary Insider you've got the transplant a lower belly button in the skin
Which is very much alive full of eggs little Marvel
So
To get a pregnancy
Here's what might have happened couple different option
First
Maybe
One of these immature
Turn of egg
Sal's near belly button
Flips out of the transplanted ovarian tissue
It's into the bloodstream is transported through the bloodstream all around the body
Opposite ovary
The Dead one where
It is like this is the place I want to be
Saddles and then in there is
Matured
And then can be sucked up by the fallopian tube and made into a baby
Correct sir
Biologically speaking
It's plausible
Let's remember
Germ cells got to the ovary three long migration
Remember last episode with Great Migration The Great Migration
This will be the Great Migration * a million cuz it's going all around the body yeah
The most likely and most reasonable
That probably happened
Is
That the ovarian trance
Plant in reconnecting with the body sends out its signal is like hey hey hey hey
We got some hormones going on here
These
Hormones
Help the other ovary
Wake up
Turn back on
And then if it had any remaining egg cells that were like dormant maybe you could
Rejuvenate them or get them to mature
And then throws could become a baby
Well so either these eggs are going on a journey like no other
Or
They're waking the Dead
Yes to very reasonable option that's been both ways double banana it is so banana
That when it happened aktay just thought it was
Luck
Like maybe that over inside of the Dead one just had like one last
Stag
But
A month-and-a-half later
Pregnant
Again
In the same way
Are uterus
Yeah like
Crap
My body healed enough I could Excel
Shiva pregnant
See without intervention
And so
September 25th
Sienna and dower was born a healthy baby weighing 8lb 6oz
The first baby ever born in the US of an ovarian trance
Even though the chances of conceiving a child was Unthinkable like
1 and 5 million miracle baby
Greg Annie octech dr. Cutler poked eye little baby Sienna
Hit the road on a media blitz
She is now the mother of a bouncing baby girl the first ever to be born in the US
By using this particular
Technological breakthrough
So that happened
And then
3 years later
Pregnant
It happened again with little Greg
Same thing you'll fashioned way
And at this point they're like
We had a girl a boy there
Healthy no issues think on they felt like
We've executed
I dream of the place
No intention of having another one
Like zero
But
4 months later
Pregnant
Again three babies
Back-to-back-to-back I mean how do you become super fertile
After being in
Clinical menopause for 2 years
Does he still think there any and Greg got lucky that this was kind of a one-off
No because since Sienna was born we've had
Many more babies born from this procedure as we spend over a hundred babies
More all around the world
And it's no longer like just happening within the fertility Community I bumped it
Doctors that are experimenting using it with
Women's were going into menopause
An ovarian patch
That will inject hormones to delay menopause
Are the other place I bumped into it is in the trans Community where kids who are transitioning from
From female to male
Are opting to or their parents are choosing to freeze or ovary so they have a chat
Chance of possibly having by Logic
Kids
If they
Want to do that
So it is it is cool because you you have this feeling of like when I was
Standing in the room with Annie I kept having this like feeling of
You just feel like
Really
Close to some sort of power like maybe because it's an it it would just kind of ridiculous because I have this power to write Ivo
Ovaries but this damn being outside
The body and like like she said kind of like
Sci-fi experiment
Just like humans are Marching toward this moment of just like regulating every part of the human process
But then almost as quickly as you have that thought
You realize
13 years later
You have these kids running around
An act a still doesn't really understand
What happened
This is my
I'm Ali I don't know if anyone does are you
What are you working on
Science fair projects
What is this
I didn't even know you had this Mom
They're just now getting to the age to where we talked me to talk to him about it and we should send Sienna some of the tapes and he showed
Some of the footage from being on The Today Show before though
Cuz if you search up my name on Google
Is there still my name
This picture came up in a bunch of other ones of me as a baby
Wait what is this you guys have you have a whole magazine
Best
The world's most amazing baby
Weather 10 cute fingers and hurt and cute to us
This is Greg baby number 2
And our
Is not
Just another
Adorable newborn
She's a miracle of
And baby number three Kate
Was feeling a little overlooked
Sign the sea analysis
Magazine have Sienna
Ovarian tissue transplant you guys are number 2 and 3 in the country
NQ fingers and ten cute toes
This episode
Sodas reported by me Molly Webster and produced by Pat Walters
With original music and scoring by Dylan Keith the gonads theme is written performed and produced by Majel Connery and Al
Alex overington Radiolab presents gonads is Rachel fusek at Walters Jad abumrad and
Molly Webster
The last couple of weeks we teamed up with the website romper.com to turn some
Radiolab listener stories about trying to conceive
Into this web special
There's a lot of different perspectives you should totally check it out it's over at romper.com
Trying
Plus I was on the bustle huddle
Talking about what it's like to be 35 and whether or not there's really a reproductive cliff
Check it out at romper.com trying or wherever you get your podcast
This is iodine a queen from London
Radiolab was created by John jebaraj and is produced by Soren wheeler
Didn't he fizzled electric sound design
Maria Montes Ataxia is on managing director hasta finklea Simon Adler
Baby opossum an oppressor Rachel Cusick
David Gable athelhampton Tracy hunt
Not guilty Robert krulwich Annie McEwen Latif Nasser Melissa O'Donnell reny
Top waltzes and Molly Webster
With help from Shima ODI Carter Hart and Lisa Yaga is Michelle Harris