Hi there this is Rachel Cusick I'm a producer here at the
Show
We're going to go back to G in just a second
But first
EverQuest
Requests that only you can help me with
Did you know what it is and guys asking for money is hard I can only compare this feeling to bumping into an ex
Text with their new ridiculously good-looking partner while you're eating spaghetti you have your retainer in
And then someone asked you to recite Sally sells seashells by the seashore
It is awkward for everybody
But I am here
In your ears your listener asking for your hard-earned money
Guacamole as if I am the British guy in the magic bullet infomercial
Standing
Because I believe in what we do
So much
And I know you do too
Over the last nine months and I have been diving deep
Into the world of intelligence
IRS
Oh you got me did nearly a hundred hours of interviews
Old-school original IQ test kit
This is never been used we can put ourselves through IQ test if I were a kid I would walk away from that crying and wanting for
Burger King
Terrifying
I'm a full grown adult
And yet
Stilts
We went inside Einstein's brain across the country to share their olestra story with you and we
We have more great stories coming your way that I won't spoil for you here
And we can do any of this kind of work without the help
Listeners like you
Radiolab is listener-supported which means you make this weird wonderful show possible
And now we need your help
Radiolab podcast listener from Singapore has a challenge for our listeners
If we can get two thousand listeners to become new member is this donor will give us an additional $25,000
You can give $1 1750 to 99 the average gift is $80 and if you give that
That we have a cool Radiolab team thank you gift with your name on it but know that any amount you choose is the right
Whatever you can afford makes a huge difference each other you give goes to paying some of the best storyfinders tape cutters
Sound designers in fact Checkers in the business
These are valuable people
So will you help us
To donate go to radiolab.org donate or text Radiolab to 70101
Donate now before you get and from the whole team at Radiolab
Thank you
Did it
What's going on with the show
Are you weightless
Listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
Hate this is
I already live miniseries
I'm Pat Walters
And I'm Rachel Cusick
End at today we're going to go looking for intelligence in what made
Deam Lake
One of the more
Obvious
Okay
Do you need water
Yeah
Atwater's okay
And the story starts with this guy
Play my name is Steven Levy
Imma editor-at-large
At Wired Magazine thank you so much for coming and basically I guess
Where did this all start for you
So in 1978 I was working
4 magazine called New Jersey monthly
He was young fresh out of school
Real job in journalism
Officers were in a suburb outside Princeton New Jersey Office Park
A very Bland
Set of offices with cubicles
Yeah really Dunder Mifflin ish
Defense it was a typical boring entry level job
Until this one day we got a new attitude or you got interested
Yeah
Ecommons office
I said I want you to find
Einstein's brain
And I thought what we like
That's exciting or you would like pretty cool
I've been working on a piece about the psychology of the New Jersey driver
Write literally did a service piece about racquetball
This is better
The reason the editor assigned him
The story
Is there Benny's rumors
Going back years
That when Einstein died back in 1955
Moments after his death
Someone had literally stolen his brain
And run
Urban legend Einstein's brain is somewhere and you know that
Now that the Russians have it and
Clone Einstein
It literally said to me I want you to find Einstein
What did you know about Einstein at that point in his brain
Street with no at Einstein
Pine essential oil
This guy the funny hair relativity right whatever that was
What do you would quickly learn something to do with the atom
After a little bit of reading
Is that
In the early 20th century
Einstein pretty much rewrote the way that we thought the universe works
Einstein brilliant physicist and theoretical mathematician
She said that mass is equivalent energy equals MC square light to the atomic bomb
Devastation in time and space to bend
Let's discover black holes and like a million other things being able to last on the total
And it didn't take long before Einstein
Just became a symbol do you think you're smarter than Einstein
Einstein
So that was Steve's assignment
Find the brain of the guy
Whose name basically means
Then he said by the way this is going to be
Are cover in August
Do week 6 weeks away or something
NFL odds
How do you even begin looking for the brain of a guy that died decades ago
The richest thing
The library and
So new that Einstein lived in Princeton
Undine Princeton April 1955 so he headed over to the local public library
People archive
Microfilm
And he finds this article a couple days after Einstein die
And it's at Einstein's brain be preserved for study
And it talked about
Yeah there's going to be a study of Einstein's brain and
Yeah we are going to have a press conference
So he pulls up the next day's paper and King will be a big front-page story about this press conference
Cricket's nothing
There was no press conf
No
So many things
Okay that's 23 years ago
You have a brain study
Something's got to be public
Lake by scientist
I went through all sorts of
Scientific
Periodic
Guards
No papers
Am I really loud fart
And eventually he realizes
That little newspaper article that was literally
That was the last thing written
About Einstein's brain
But there was one clue
And that little newspaper article
A name
The name of the guy who was supposed to hold that press conference
The Never
Dr. Thomas Harvey
Who it seemed
In addition to being the guy who didn't hold that press conference
Was also the pathologist who would have done the autopsy on Einstein
So the next step on Steve search hospital and we're supposedly this Harvey
At work. And I went there I found
What's the vice president
I asked him about the phone with you
Sky dr. Thomas Harvey
Where is dr. Harvey
Hospital guy says he left you a long time ago
Venti Pike what about the brain I heard the brain got taken is it here at the hospital need to know anything I put talk to talk to Harvey
So what do you do to find Harvey
So when I was looking for a person
In 1978 there's no Google
Yeah there's no Facebook there's no LinkedIn
So and there's a lot of
Places
Bata city is in every city
Phone book
But
You been looking every phone
Yeah I eventually figured
One place I might go is the American medic
Figured this guy Harvey was a doctor maybe they have his contact info
So I called them up
I'm trying to find this
Thomas Harvey
Thomas S Harvey I know his middle name
And this very kindly woman
Look up stuff
M
Then told me there is a Thomas S Harvey
In Wichita Kansas
So he calls directory assistance in Wichita says you guys have a number for a Thomas Harvey
They said yes
Yes
Is that number listed
I said yes
Make a bee
His phone number
And I took a deep breath and dial the phone number
Back then
Someone wasn't there
It was raining in rain
Hang up
That would be at
Buddy pick up phone
And
Isaiah
Is this
Eye doctor Harvey ND
Yes and I said disaster
Dr. Harvey who worked at Princeton Hospital
In 1950
I never said
Pause
I figured
Is a yes or no question right either supposed like he was almost debating
Weather today
And finally said yes
The retrospect maybe was little The Jig Is Up
And
He said why don't know if I can help you
I said well I just like to talk to you
Well
And he was sort of
Not saying yes or no I'm coming out there to talk
So I booked a ticket for
Wichita Kansas
Department of Labor Kansas
He spends the night
And then the next morning he wakes up get the cab and goes over to Harvey's lab
Ring the bell or whatever
And dr. Harvey
Came to open the door for
What did he look like
He look like
Yeah the guy who would be your PDF
Kindly looking
Guyana
These bring a lab coat
And I remember very clearly
Yanez pocket Windows pens
They could write in three colors
Are red
Green blue
MP3 back
To the back of the
Facility of
To his
Office was basically
Eyeglass in Cuba
And with a desk
Ana chair
Michelle
Cardboard boxes
And I sat down and we talked
Now at this point Harvey hadn't admitted to anything
But Steve had a feeling
A definite feeling
Yeah you can tell he's very cautious Right Guard
Asking every way to try to figure out
Where's the brain.
A few times
Yeah where's the brain
And he really want to answer that
Pictures of it and then he should have broke down
When I guess
Yakame because he
Because I was so fun
Frustrated
Yeah I was like no pictures even
And he's like
Saga little
So he gets up
Any walks
Behind me there's really a beer cooler near me
How big is in the beer cooler nowicki
Mountain Pass weather
And goes behind me
Two were one of the cardboard box
Staples out these two jars
And in one of the jars
There are these
Pieces of
Biomass
14er
They're clearly
Brain
M
Starion
And
Thunderstruck
Movies like
A joke you know
This was amazing I mean yeah you can hear
Yeah whatever the chorus of angels singing
I'm taking this in
Ended like this
Is the brain
That changed the world
And the Sea. Brain
Was
The movie experience
I got in this glimpse
Absolutely
Of what though
Something big or something you know
Mystery
It follows Pampas precios
In this episode
We're going to try to untangle Batman
Manifestation
X15
What can the brain of one of the greatest Geniuses that Humanity has ever produced
Unfamiliar concept
Intelius
Well I'm just going to say for the record that I think that's silly
And I think that brain is a whole it is though
I do not but I am going to bring my exam
I would just like to declare my bias I don't think there is anything special about his brain
Anything not even I mean you think he was brilliant
There's something about the idea that is genius is
Tied to the physical structure of his brain that makes me
Itchy
Literally as physical sensation I have I start to itch
Yeah I think you're dismissing it too soon I think there's more to it
Then
Eustace bagge
Alright let me ask you more basic
What's the what's the fellas name again
Thomas Harvey
How did he end up with that brain to begin with
Well
You know
Dictate to answer your question this is dr. Fred Lepore he's a neurologist
Book about Einstein
It only people talk to you to answer that very question
And he says you got to go back to the winter of 1950
Einstein was living on borrowed time 76 years old
Retired living in Princeton
And get sick
Start feel this pain in his abdomen
It was almost like a gallbladder attack
Turned out to be way worse than that
Ultimately
An abdominal aortic aneurysm
Franklin who was a neurosurgeon
Surgeon at Cornell came down ready to operate
But I sign basically said look I am you know
My time is up I I will die I think he's I will die Allegan
He knew he was and that was a brave thing to say because he was in pain
Eventually in the spring of 1955
Einstein under the hospital Friday died this morning after refusing surgery
Wechat turned off would not have helped him recover from a ruptured artery
As the story goes in the early morning hours of April 18th murdered a couple of in comprehensible words
Incomprehensible to his nurse who didn't speak German
And then
In the early morning hours
Just found dead
Note on Harvey our guy was the chief pathologist at Princeton.
His job was to do autopsy
And that night
April 18th 1955
He's at home
Sleeping
And
You get the call
Yeah I think the phone call came sometime before Dawn and it was Einstein's personal
Mission
Who called him to let him know
The Einstein's son had given permission for an autopsy to be performed on his father
This is Carolyn Abraham science journalist author of
Possessing genius
The story of the bizarre Odyssey of Einstein's brain
Hardy actually died in 2007
But before he did Carolyn spend some time with him
And got his take on that day
He gets himself ready and
He remembered it was a really nice morning
A spring was in the air and your things were turning green and he was walking towards what
He realized was going to be a major opportunity in his professional life
He got to that hospital and he got to his Pathology lab and someone that morning
Had already placed Einstein on the autopsy table
She says he walked into the room
Einstein playing there
Flat on the table
Picked up a scalpel now he open the abdomen and he saw it was full of blood from the aneurysm so he establishes cause
Cause of death
Did a routine examination of the heart
Then he did something that was not in the script
He remove the top of the skull
Cut a bunch of cranial nerves
And arteries
And he took the brain out
And then you put the brain
In a jar
End
Walked out
So he literally just
Stole the brain out of
Einstein skull
Just stole it
Yeah
Which is
Pretty gross
It's not a crime
Probably history has not been kind to Thomas as Harvey
But in Tom Harvey
Estimation and he actually put it this way in our conversations once
As that he would have felt ashamed
If he didn't take it
She's not here was ashamed because here was this opportunity
To learn
Something about sort of the biological underpinnings of intelligence of Genius onofre
From arguably we are certainly one of the greatest scientific minds of the 20th century and
To not study it would have been
Negligent
Courtney Carolyn however misguided it might seem Harvey says he wasn't taking the brain from South
You taking it for
All of us
Bike for Humanity
First time
But
Best work the next day the family at this point or read on the front page of the April 19th New York
55 New York Times read that
The brain was preserved for science
And they were flabbergasted
Timeout heard of it
Yeah in the paper
Find out
Yep the family didn't know and didn't give permission the understanding although you'll find none of this in the will
But the understanding was
Einstein would be cremated and his
Ashes scattered in a secret location so that quote-unquote no one could come and worship at my bones
He was the first scientist
Become a public figure
Electra
Camden ar time
Ice cream is always very uncomfortable with
The attention that celebrity brought with
He was really afraid that people are going to start to see him as something superhuman
True science
Its power
I linked with Einsteins image
It speaks to the fact that in the twentieth century science sort of displaced religion
As
What
People put their face in
And he was going to start of its high priest
And so he didn't want his grave site
2B, shrine
That's why you wanted to be cremated as he was
On April
18th
But Harvey kept the brain
So the family went they saw the headline do they do they knock on Harvey's door and I want to say what the hell
No they found the hospital they phone Princeton hospital and they're very upset
Eventually
Hans Albert
Einstein Galveston
Get on the phone with
Tom Hardy
Now we don't know exactly what they said to each other
You probably imagined Hans Albert was
That probably be yelled at Tom Harvey
Tom Harvey apparently apologized for taking it without permission Dad finally
Harvey makes
The picture of his wife
He says you know this isn't you know the mind for all the ages we're never going to get this opportunity again and I pledged that
I will do a scholarly study made this very solemn vow
To take care of this brain to not allow it to become sort of an object of
Fascination Tom Hardy told Hans Albert he'd never let the brain become a spectacle he honor Einstein
Adjust Adidas brain
It might reveal something The Secret of human genius and creativity
You can't pass it up
And the Sun
Honda Robertson
You can study at
But only as long as it's serious science
No spec
So the next step that Harvey has
He's trying to craft a kind of a do-it-yourself
Approach to studying a famous brain even though he's a doctor
Carby's not trained in
In an in this kind of neuropathology he learned some but not to the degree that especially
What's the weather
Spends evenings taking photographs
He weighs that he measures it hit some standard textbooks different reference guides one of the really interesting things he did
Did during this. He brought this artist into
Paint a portrait of Einstein's brain
We really went when it was whole he said he just wanted to have it and he never did hang that
That painting really
One-time thing thing to do I think partly it was because he knew what Pat to happen next door and he
His estimation what he was going to do next
He's going to cut the brain into 240SX
And after that he goes across the Delaware George Washington or something to University of
Pennsylvania where there's a technician who had worked with gave her some of those jumps of rain
And she's like family
Into microscope slides
Cinema 12
Smoke Clears and I'm sorry
Untold 12 sets of at least 200 slides per set
And his job for the next few years
Is the try to take it individually to various
Neuropathologist who might be able to study this brain
So I resend that slide
Photos and samples of Einstein's brain he was trying to collaborate with experts in the field
Specialist we don't exactly know
How many photographs he gave out how many slides who he gave them to
There's a lot
Despite all the effort though there's no record of them ever getting back to him or doing anything of
Importance
From the few scientists I was able to contact at that time who received those pieces
If you were still alive
They said they didn't really know what they should be looking for
Which of course was
True
This is where Tom Harvey ran into the reality of
You know neuroscience at that time everything
As a complex beginning in our brain
At that point I just figure out
What neurons do are the communicate back and forth
Brain alone has 10000
They hadn't even scratch the surface of absurd of the understanding
A normal brain let alone trying to
Solve the mystery of genius and Einstein's brain
So years and years go by
End
Nothing
But now we wouldn't give up
He knew it was of significance he thought there was something that could be learned and he never abandon that and I think at this point
Harvey began to see himself as kind of a living time capsule
He was going to take this brain with him into the future when science
Would be equipped to study of properly
But
In the meantime
Arby's life falls apart
Affair
He got divorced
He loses his job at Princeton
Yeah he does
That is until 1978
When a young reporter from New Jersey
Knock on his door
Asking about it
Turn airplane home when did you call your editor or something on your way the first thing I did
I went straight to my
Etter's house
And he was like
Watching a basketball
We watched a little of basketball
And without saying anyway
And finally said he will
Joe find a brain
That's what you tell him that's like you would hold it for halftime virus
Was it I had to write it
We got a great image for the cover
Cuddling with my search for Einstein's brain
And then
One of the people who got the press release
This was
So in the story came out
Baby rattlesnake
And
It was in every newspaper in the country
Johnny Carson made a joke
Oh really
If you remember you about the brain
Did they really Einstein's brain
What is one of the guy to Wichita come like that
Yeah and
Dr. Harvey
Have people camped out in this lawn
Really drive everyone out
It was
You have a lot of it
The Einstein estate
Went bonkers
I mean this is exactly what they didn't want to happen
People keep calling they were cash offers for the brain
People all over the place started to write to him to volunteer to become its next
Keeper in the offer to money
So not only did Harvey
Fail to come up with any science about the brain
BFF broke that promise you made to the family
Because of all the attention
At least on the science side
His luck
Kind of changed one place to pick up the story was Science magazine
By the late 70s
Neuroscience had picked up a woman
Two new techniques
Exploring brains
Have been developed
For example we figured out there were opioid receptors in the brain
Millions of these sensory receptors and had developed a treatment for Parkinson's
Soap scientist at this point we're just slightly more equipped
And Wednesday story came out
Actually kicked off
Real research
Into Einstein's brain
Bed directly flowed from my making it
So what happened
So the first thing that happens
Is he got the call from this
Scientist names
My name is Marian diamond. Diamond
That's a good name
Brightening
Choose a professor of anatomy at Berkeley on campus
Carrying a box
She got excited coming to class
Kiewit
I never seen a human brain before freshman Anatomy lecture in front of all these
Skip by bring a hat box onto the table and open it is like a flower print half buck
Turn it up and pull out this brain cyst Mass only weighs
3 lb
And yet it has the capacity
To conceive
Other universe
A billion light years
Across
Some people call her one of the founders of modern neuroscience
Isn't that phenomenal
Alaska
The protoplasm
Do that
So she did these studies on rats
Which became very famous
Where she figured out that if you like put a rat in an enriched
Environment sowa cage with like a lot
Toys things to climb around on and lots of other rat friends to hang out with instead of just putting them in like the boring
Normal cage
What you'll find
Is that their brains
Actually
Change. More of these little cells called glial cells switch
For a long time people thought glial cells were just like
The scaffolding of the brain like neurons where the action was that throughout the thinking happened
And glial cells were just like
You know the
This dis
Studs and mortar of the
Houston that I'm holding everything
Together
But around this time when Marian Diamond was doing the studies are starting to realize that the
Glial cells
Also had neurotransmitters flowing through them
Like that they might be more important than we thought
But shortly after she publishes her rat
Studies
She
Here's about Harvey
She saw you know a little piece about it in the journal science and so she started to track down Harvey and she call
Call Tim in 1984 Harvey Center for chunks of brain
She went looking and Einstein's brain to see if there was
You know something similar to what she had been recording in her animal
Experiments and she finds that compared to the average brain
Einstein had a lot
Of glial cells
What's what's a lot
I like twice as many three times as many
What about 70% more than the control group
But what does that even mean
I don't
Really know how to describe that which is part of the problem and on top of that
After she published This research
Some other scientists race
Questions that maybe the experimental methods were invalid
Stove
Not convinced yeah me neither
So that diamond
Diamond
So after Diamond then describe Britt Anderson comes along and his whole thing he studied five other
Adult male
Dead brands
He looked at their prefrontal cortex has
And that's like where higher cognitive abilities are located so like if you're going to take a test that's the part of your brain is going to be active
Cheated and he found that compared to the other brands that he had the neurons and Einstein's brain were more
Tightly packed
To his neurons were more tightly packed
In a certain part of a
Yeah three of more neurons that part or less neurons
Same number roughly
They're just more crowded together
What is that
Say I kind of take that as like
Einstein problem-solving abilities
Could go much more quickly and efficiently
Yeah actually pretty Anderson the guy who found this
He dismisses himself and he found a difference but he also was quick to say like
We just have one of these brands
He said listen you know I
It was always going to be a
An NF1 in any experiment you kind of like the middle child of all these researchers you made like the smallest
Splash
It is through Britt Anderson
That Tom Harvey hears about Sandra Wilson in Canada and that was like the biggest splash of them all really yes
Sandra Mendelson in the fall of 1995 she ends up getting this back
A one-page fax
From a man by the name of Thomas Harvey and the back basically says hey
Heard about your research
Would you like to study the brain of Albert Einstein it almost seems like you were suspected to be a prank
Just being mad
Exactly but you know obviously she faxed back yes and so
Harvey hop in the car with the brain brains in the trunk actually
And drives North to bring to bring the brain to Canada
And the reason he was so excited to have her look at the brain what had really
Caught his attention was the fact that she had this collection of normal brains
She's been doing this long term before and after study
So years before she died. In this group together basically like they signed up they took IQ tests they did all these things while they were still alive
Live
Stream and then when they died she got to study their brains to see like
A before-and-after picture of these people's brains
Willie. Smart people so she had a mix
But the ones that she compared Einstein's brain to wear all high IQ men
So she makes this comparison
Einstein brain vs these other brains in her collection
And she write this article
Of the article
Was that he had unusual parietal lobes usual Primal low Bridal lobes of Einsteins
Brain for anatomically
Exceptional if you will
Where is the parietal lobes again
Can I wear your baseball cap is like mainly
The back or if you had animal exactly
And this area of your brain this is where all of your sensory information comes in
And because of that is also where your visual spatial awareness is located so like the way that you
You Orient yourself in the world is
Bug mostly located in that part of your brain
Like if you were to close your eyes right now and you think
Where my hands
Where are my knees
For my feet
Well you have an internal mental map that's telling you where those things are and that's your parietal lobe doing that
Anyhow
So what was different about this part of Einstein's brain is that if you imagine the brains look like a walnut which is kind of the only way.
I imagine the brain
There are like all these grooves and crevices
And there's this one Groove like a groovy groovy like a deeper crevice called the Sylvian fissure
In Einstein's brain it was shorter than the rest of ours
And apparently that's very strange when she described it to me she said it was enough to see this unique pattern in Einstein's brain
Was a striking as
Seeing a face
With
The eyebrows beneath the eyes
And Sandra Wilson proposed that maybe because this crevice was a little bit shorter
The electricity in this part of his brain could go much more quickly
How to travel around in half
I could just go
So speculative
Yes and so she was saying like the parietal lobe like this is where
His genius might be
End
If you hang about Einstein like everybody says like one of his greatest Talent is like the way that he could manipulate shapes and it mine
Find
Orient object
In his head I mean just like the idea that
SpaceTime is
Curved so he has is kind of great visuospatial
If you had to pick a part of your brain that could
Underlie mathematical abilities or visual spatial abilities
Left parietal lobe
Looking at these papers you see Thomas Harvey's name is like the co-author
He was a coop
Yeah he's like cited in the paper made my heart Happy like you made it
Especially for Sandra Wilson because he all these years have been like shepherding this forward
And when that paper came out I think
Tom Harvey felt
Then that
That his work
Was over cuz he felt at that point it did they hit
Pointed to something that was real at Ruby felt like finally
The work that he promised to do in the very beginning
Was finally done
And at that point
He actually decided to give the brain
Back
I Princeton hospital in the care of
Elliot Krause basically the pathologist who holds the same job
He did when he first took that rain in 1955
You know it
Some
It's kind of uncanny that it's back where it was
Yeah
I'm going to rain on this parade
I'm happy for mr. Harvey
But
In terms of the science
You convinced me a little bit
Comedian bit
But still kind of smells like phrenology to me
I mean it's like I'm listening to it that the experience I have is like
Sylvian fissure
And then I think to myself
Is a Sylvian fissure
I don't even know what that is like the fact that like we so clearly default to this fascination with a thing that I don't think
Can you explain it
It just kind of seemed absurd
And we know that he said that like
He didn't think he was a
Particularly special
Guy
Think he said various does lots of Courts for memories talks about saying like
I was just in the right place at the right time or I'm just say that
Really yeah you know what he's talking about his famous cousin quote about
Worrying that the packaging
Of him
Is better than the meat inside
I mean this is part of the
Method him is like and he was very humble
Is another one we talked about like
He sometimes talks about what made him special with his stubbornness
But he was really obstinate and he wouldn't let things go
That's when the only things I feel like you hear him talking about
Add some innate
Characteristic of him that made him different than other people
But didn't he never talked about being smart she never talks about
Brain
I feel like we've been swimming around it for a while
His brain
Hammer
But it is interesting that he says he he was in the right place at the right time
Which can sound kind of like humble but also maybe it's sleepy
You take it seriously maybe there's something to it
Yeah I mean it like
We've been talking about the neural connections inside
But you can also think about it a little more broadly
Like about the connections
Outsiders
Almost as if the neurons didn't stop inside his skull but like continued outward
Into the world around
Zoo
Africa
Hi this is Madeline calling from Berlin Germany
Radiolab
Supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloane at www.
How do I
We have an eviction epidemic
I'm too often we fail to grasp
What that is
But it isn't sometimes when you look at stuff on the news why is she somewhere on the pole dancing and she should be home
We're children
Any answer is
If they feel like I need to get a security deposit I'm going to go out there and make it happen I'm Brooke Gladstone
New series The Scarlet
Unmasking America's eviction crisis listen on the media. Org eviction
This is a g and we are
We are what are we what are we doing here
Where what are we doing here Pat we are back from our break
Jiu Jitsu reset I was intrigued
Buy the thing you said at the end of the last chapter that
You know there are the circuits in in his head but then what about the circus outside is that
Maybe you just got lucky
What were you thinking of when you said
Yeah I mean a lot of the obvious things that
Must be dead
Einstein was
Building on the work
Lots of other physicists
Pointer and Lorenz to have been chipping away at the same
Questions
Puzzled him
So there's that
But if you widen the lens a little boy
Let me start to think more broadly
You start to see
Something really interesting
Got a bigger
Forces that were at work on Einstein
Wings coming up
Like
Just take
Special relativity
Which most people would say it's one of his most Revolution
Share ideas
Special relativity
Special relativity proper length
Very basically is the idea that
Time is relative
And that
Time slows down
As you go fat
So if you're going a million miles an hour
10 miles an hour
I'm will literally
Slow down
Images
Seems lower it will actually be
I feel like this is the moment when
Science and Common Sense
Parted ways
It's such a weird idea
Totally
Well that idea
I came from Einstein but also kind of came from
The world around
Okay so I'm going to give you a couple of really interesting examples that we came across as we research
Okay
Number one I'm not in it at all an expert on the brain Story I mean look at some of the same things that you have but
Come from the sky
Could you introduce yourself
I'm Peter galison I'm a
Professor at Harvard University where I work on the history and philosophy
If science and Dawn
Physics and what Peter told us
Is a if you look at when Einstein came up with the idea of special relativity
Destroy the dolphin told is Einstein was working in the patent office just sitting around all by himself thinking
Take thoughts
But you look at what was actually happening at that moment
Like outside this was a transformative moment in the technological history of the world
Yeah what were what were some of the big like the hot inventions happening you looked out the window
Any central European or Western European city
You would see
New kinds of trams being installed electric motors you would see
Networks of clocks that were established UNC
I also a new devices that are being invented that could
Send signals the extension of the telegraph Network
Everything in motion everything in the chain
And
As a consequence
Time is
Has suddenly become
Atopic of immense in
Not just because the world seem to be moving faster
The first time in human history
You could be in several different time
At 1
Cuz you ran trains
So you leave Chicago at
3 p.m.
When you get to a distant City
What time is it there
Do use the time
But you started with in Chicago do you use
The time
Did you arriving at in Philadelphia
Who sets
What are the times you know before the railroad
Time was local
Every town had like its own time
Set in each town by the local jeweler who repaired and made clocks and watch
Open with the railroad you needed
Central Time in the early skirmishes over whose time would become
The time
Especially to the Showbox
It's like a million years ago it's a big big didn't like that at all
But suddenly the ability
To Traverse at a fairly high speed
Hundreds even thousands of miles
Created the demand
Think about
What time was
And how to coordinate
That was sort of the mood of the MoMA
Like just outside the window
A patent office
Where Einstein was sitting there thinking big thoughts
And what are the specific questions he was wrestling with
Was the one Peter just threw out
Like how would you coordinate two different clocks in two different cities
A lot of people the time.
We do it is you send an Alexa
Signal bike through a telegraph wire from one to the other
Calculate the amount of time it would take that signal to get from the first clock to the second clock then you take that minuscule amount of time until
Attractive from 1:00
Or at it when the clock
And then you have the same time in two places
And that's part of the problem
But then the next.
That was
What is that signal you were using was traveling at the
Speed of light
What does to clock
What if one of them was moved
Equals movie
And the light was tired of chasing it
Wouldn't it take
The light longer to get there
And wouldn't that like
Screw up your
Whole ability to
Coordinate
Why am I telling you this
Because
These kinds of questions
They sort of infiltrated Einstein
Dreams
Einstein wrote about this in his autobiography so we have a very good idea
That semantic analysis of science at the University of Illinois
She says Einstein wrote about these very particular Daydreams yet he said the P imagine himself
Be propelled through space chasing after
A light beam
And and thought
Stories of signs of biographers to Feinstein
Often agreed that it was that sort of experiment of of seeing in a what actually happens
If I pursue a light beam. Had the provided the the yard
Turn off his thoughts the theory of relativity
And explain why that light beam was such a big deal in a minute but the mean thing him and wanted to
The tell me about it what that is explained as something that just emerged
From Einstein's brain
I think it was purely an original
Idea of her
But it was not his idea at all
Printed mint
A story hero
Lead him to it
She does Einstein love science
And he said he was particularly taken
Bye-bye one author the name is
I run
Bernstein
Who wrote quite a few volumes
And Einstein says that he if he brought them with quote
Breathless attention
Infinisys the story that got Einstein thinking about chasing light beams
Was about a faster-than-light travel
And what happens if we travel faster than the speed
Safelite
The story of imagine that you could have a guy who shoots off into space
And purchased himself on a star
We looks back at Earth
Isn't the same Earth he left a different world at different
Universe
Earlier
Because as Bernstein explains when we look out at anything in space
Square knot
Being it
Exactly as it is
But rather as it was
Example when you look up
Son you're really seeing the Sun
8 minutes in the past
Because the light waves
Take time to
To reach you and because this Traveler
To travel fast
Jordan light
All you need to
Enough if
If you wanted to look at the Earth
8 minutes in the past all you needed
Go to the Sun
And if you
Jumping to further and farther a planets and stars
Then you can choose whatever time in history you want to see
Turn the story this traveler could Bounce from that first star to a planet
To another star
And another
Quotes in one point in Space the light of the scenes of the French Revolution is just coming into view
It's even farther away the invasion of The Barbarians has just become the order of the day
Alexander the Great
Conquering the world
Historical events that have long been dead for us
We'll just be coming to life
By the way
This was one of the first
Time travel stories
Inhibit
Which is crazy to think about
3000 years
Human ride
And almost nobody
That point
At imagine someone going back in time or going into the future
The stories that today are so much apart movies and culture
They all basically started
At the time Einstein was growing up
He just happened to be alive
At that time
Amanda says
They opened his mind
He said that the stories really prompted him to imagine himself
Be propelled through space
Chasing after
A light beam
And the reason that mental image was so pivotal
Who's that right around the time it popped into
Other physicists were noticing this
Weird thing
About the speed of
I'm like everything else in the known world
Light always moved at the same
No matter how fast you moving relative
And in picturing himself riding longest
Died this light
Einstein realize
The flight always moved at the
The thing speed
If light was constant
Bedtime
Must be real
Which store do you know
Eventually
Turn our understanding of the universe
Upside down
So you're saying that if
He hadn't been alive at a time when there are well roads would create a Time problems all the while there are people writing time travel fics
Ocean for the first time in history
All that had been happening he might not have thought
Thoughts that he thunk
Yeah yeah like I still think
There's something about his brain that is
Explains
Part of it
Can I buy all this other stuff
The time-travel the railroads
The stories
I would say that that adds like
Another
Corny bike
So the brain is what like 20 maybe 20 as a 12 basketball let's go to 20/20 Plus
25 Forester like
Roughly half
I don't know
I have to say that I like halfway there
Precise method where do I get to see if I can push a little bit further
Okay
Give another explanation bring it what are you up to
I got to start small okay
The first one
I spoke to the sky Alberto Martinez he's a historian of science
And he told me that one of the other things Einstein was reading that really blew his mind was
Scottish philosopher David Hume who are these pretty radical ideas including that the laws of nature kind of start
AirHeads that the fundamental concepts of science
Re-creation
Reinvention
What's of the human mind
Alberto says that those ideas
Evine sign permission to think his own crazy thought
There's a letter from 1915 in which Einstein
Write this line of thought was of great influence in my efforts very probably I wouldn't have reached
The solution without those philosophic
Legal studies
And I was gone
So much so and there's a little bit of a digression that
Just a couple of months before he was about to publish the theory of relativity
Of 1905 Einstein was supposed to meet with a group of his friends to discuss him if he was writing kind of study group
But one of the guys this game Lori Sullivan
You wanted to skip a meeting of their discussion
Betty wanted to go see
Violin
When
Einstein
And his mathematician friend
Conrad Hobby
Arrive and find that their body isn't there they are
Stop so they're still up
Set that they take out their cigars and they start smoking and smoking and smoking because they know Sullivan hate smoking
And then they take the ashes of every cigar and smear them
On his Peapod is Piccolo his his his his his table his pillow
Pillow
Totally trashed
Such was Einstein's love
Perfume
I'm going to give that like a
Okay fine but in terms of non brain exclamations of his genius
I'm about to give you my favorite
Alright here we go here
So we're going to rewind a couple years
Back for the apartment thrashing and working for the government employee
In the
Swiss patent office
Not a great job he's just a bureaucrat he calls himself
Federal.inc shiter you wanted to be a physicist so badly but no one wanted to hire him again and again
They rejected him
Yet there was one person who thought he had something special
Mileva Maric
Was Serbian
This is writer Andre and she says Malia and Einstein met in college at 8A high in Zurich
Suffolk University answer one of the few places where you could
Attend University as a woman believe it was actually the only women in their class
They're both in the same program for preparing fish
T-shirt
Science and Math teachers they become Study Buddies and pretty soon
She becomes his
Girlfriend
I longed
Terribly for a letter for my beloved witch
I can hardly grasp that will be separated for so much longer
Only now do I see
Franklin
During the early days of them as a couple or they I can I have this version of my head where it's like they were lovey-dovey but also
Speaking like they were on The Big Bang Theory it's like ridiculous
I think it was I think it was both of those
They go on these hikes in the Alps
Enjoy music
Together very romantic
Relationship
But it's also one that is very much
Search based on this
Sherrod love
They're studying physics they're reading great works in physics that I
He would skip class and then she would
Stained glass
Update
Oh she would take notes for him yet then they would like write these letters to each other about like these new ideas that he was reading about
Very curious with Kleine wolf say about
2 papers
He better pull himself together and say something reasonable this is the stuff
From which
His work on relativity is born so she becomes the first person that
You know analyzes and thinks about these things with him
He was like the first person
From what I can tell they like really engage with him as like this like weird off-the-beaten-path kind of guy
And like support that unlike love that about him
So they get married they have kids she leaves the science community
He continues to your thing not very successful
How to do it
And for a long time is drains and think much better
But then
You know them these love letters I mean they really were
A big news item
In 1986
I love letters between mileva and Einstein turned up
And there's one letter and there's one line from Einstein that kind of like rocked the world
There's a letter from 1901 in which Einstein says
How proud will I be
When we both
Together
Bring our work
On the relative motion victoriously Switzerland literally says in his power
Our work
Like our Theory
And everyone's like what they could that because she helping him on the sidelines giving him reason
Cries
The idea that
This
Iconic genius
Had had a wife who maybe was his equal
There's a couple of other letters in which Einstein again refers to our work our Theory
When you put them all together it's enough to give anyone the impression relative motion our theory that Einstein is literally saying that
Mileva was
His secret coworker
Before we get too excited about this
Baby mostly me
I need to throw in a few bag
The replies that we have from her do not engage the science
The letters in which he
Write this to her he doesn't specify what she herself did
Alberta says
When you read the letters you realize what
He believed at the time when he wrote that letter
Wasn't that special that relative motion idea they talked about in the letter.
Not relative
And something everybody knew about it at the time did Einstein have
The theory of relativity
When he's writing them and then the answer is no
We have nothing and we have multiple sources and what she says
I have nothing
So she probably wasn't his co-conspirator but she did support him at this time when everybody else was
Contradicting him and for that
I think I gave her some points
I'm going to be 15% based on what just cuz you just
Cuz it makes you feel good to give 15 or you don't
Arbitrarily I like to pick numbers out of the sky
I support V
Some percent for the
Physicist UK
Before
Fish percent
4 time and place 7%
15% maleva
Yeah that doesn't get us all the way there
I know one other person
Two stupid get like a V
Thing
Cuz when I will have an answer
And and I think I think there are many days bright green physicist
Better
At Columbia
Kiss written
So much about Einstein
About Einstein in his best-selling books
Talked about him
Television specials he has a
Play about Einstein he has written about all the ways Einstein has impacted the world
And all the ways the world
Impacted
Einstein
But surprisingly when we asked him about this
He brought it back to the brain I have to say if I was in the shoes of the
Pathologist at the time I may have
Absconded with his
His brain is well if it's a point is yeah there was the railroads and the time-travel fiction and
Confluence of so many different
Features
Who sings were around for everybody
Somehow
All of them came together
In this one brain
In a way that was different
Somewhere in the collection of atoms and molecules in the brain that would cause
Albert Einstein is the answer to why Albert Einstein was Albert Einstein
What do you think there's something innate about it like Einstein was born with some special mental equipment
Or you think it had more to do with his environment
Princess in the end it doesn't really matter
Because everything you experience
Lee Brice
Your biology
Attaches itself
MTO
When you look at a brain
You're not just looking at a structure
You are going to Brighton in some fundamental way looking at the life
That person live
Yeah every
Genius
Thought every deep
Inside every
Pattern recognized
Happened inside that Gloppy grade 3 or 4 lb
Structure that's all there is
Whatever set him apart
Brian says
Is in there
Somewhere
And if we had the capacity to lay out every single circuit
And every
Single influence
That could
Cascade through that brain if we were able to fully understand all the electrical signals and crackles
That would
Go through that brain yes I believe that we would fully understand Einstein's process and
Understand how it was that he was able to do what he did
I can't do that
Yet
Well
There's a lot of
Interest
In this concept
Structure of the brain is going to tell you something about the funk
That we're all just fed the poor who heard from earlier
Penitas
People trying
Nothing much with Einstein's brain anymore
Bonita Thrifty's hole
Loading area of Neuroscience
That's where researchers are trying to
Describe the brain at the level of detail Brian
Describe is funded to the tune of 4.5 billion told us that one guy who's doing this just about a mile from where Einstein lived
There's a
Princeton University Professor Sebastian Seung and what he does he takes
Cubic millimeter
A cubic millimeter of mouse retina
Neural tissue is not brain but it's it's neural tissue
And he slices us into these vanishingly thin sections and then he tries to trace the axons that
Dendrites of neurons the astrocytes the oligodendroglia etc etc
It can take
Months
It can take months to do a cubic millimeter
And then you got to have some kind of software that can analyze
The see if the structure can lead you to some kind of conclusion about circuitry
My cat YouTube
Quick why not definitely like if that doesn't get you to function then what what what would be what would be left
I doubt if we could map
Perfect labor
Structure of all the connections
What you're talking like me you're talking like a man
I'm a material they call me and materials because I'm saying well the left side of the brain has something to do with the right arm
And speech
That's that's called materialism
But there's another school of thought is called
Somehow
Mind consciousness
Spirit soul
Is
Separate
From the physical substrate of the brain
How would that be science though cuz isn't I mean I can imagine school of thought which allows for that but but it feels like you're
You're very quickly stepping out of science
If you go that way
Well yes
Yes okay
Probably
You know we're all brought up on this thing when you read anything in the popular press
About the brain
They'll show you functional neuroimaging
So when someone talks
The little the Broca's area the speech area on the left side of the brain
Lights up
And you got well there's your answer
That's the structure it lights up that's what's creating language
Except
When you deal with lobsters they said when we got one problem with that
It's called the hard problem
If you look at that chunk of brain that you're calling Broca's area that lights up when you talk
What exactly is happening there
How does that create
How does that create a word
Or if you're looking at the occipital lobe and you're looking at the color red
How do you create that Kweli at which is a fancy way of saying the sensation of color
We can show you where it's happening we just can't show you how
We're all looking the same thing we're saying
Somehow if we could get a better handle on the anatomy
Maybe we can explain a thought
We can explain the song
I mean forget forget
Relativity we can explain a thought
It follows Santa special.
Nativity
Is math and energy app
Define manifestation
Unfamiliar concept
This episode was reported by Rachel Cusick and me
And produced by Bethel hobday Rachel and me and Dad album Rod
Music by Alex overington
Fact-checking by Michelle Harris
Special thanks to Dustin O'Halloran Tim Houston Simon Adler and minute physics
Radiolab's G is supported in part by science sandbox
Simons Foundation initiative dedicated to engaging everyone with the process of science
I'll be back in two weeks
With episode 4
Play the message press to start of message
This is Alberto Martinez
New Boston Texas
Medialab
Was created by jab album run
NF produced by
Wayne Wheeler
Dylan
Is our director
Sound design
Do you like them burgers are accepted
Producer
Our staff includes
Simon Adler
Rachel kulick
David devil
Bethel happy
Nora Keller
Matthew King Robert krulwich
Latif Nasser
Melissa O'Donnell
Sarah Carey
Alienware
Pat Walters and Molly Webster
With help from
EK Fortuna
Ruth Samuel Imani Leonard
Tunisia
Are fact-checker is Michelle Harris
Thank you very much
And this message