Northern listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
I'm jeroboam ride by Robert krulwich Radiolab and today we have a little experiment in democracy diversity
And Division
Yeah comes to us from our reporter producer Simon Adler
Okay alright sign
Okay what you have to tell me
Couple months back I took the train down to Southern
To a little neighborhood called
Bay Ridge
Best known for his portrayal in the movie Saturday night
Fever
You weren't heading there for Disco
No
The auditorium appears to be
Showing up I was actually down there to go to this Catholic
High School
Go to the classic High School auditorium sloping down with the stage in front in like an American flag on one side of the stage and
New York State flag on the other maybe a thousand seats
And I would say half of them are filled like surprisingly there's a big turnout for this thing
You look familiar
Look familiar have you seen me before
Amanda such a handsome
And dad would not be unfair to say that
Proud as an average age of
62 the reason I was there
Come see the debate
Ways to watch the local candidates for the New York City city council
Duke it out
Who's most likely to do something for you do you think
I have no idea
I've been hurt on both sides
And that was talking to people beforehand
Weaving in and out of the other chairs
The issues that people were concerned about we're really what you would expect
Are we in this neighborhood for 5 years I've been fighting for a light
In the meantime I get aggravated we have to run for our lives when we cross the streets here
Guitar
You know
Small stuff
Taking away the $0.05
A bottle tax
When you drink a lot of Mountain Dew or something so this $0.05
It jumps up the price when I buy those 24 packs
The water
Whereabouts
Eventually the MC for the evening this woman in her 70s dressed from head to toe in
Walks out onto the
The stage
We've had a great selection here
But the candidates up
5 democrats for Republicans they sit down at their respective tables and
Okay we're ready
Get on I'm off
Gadsden
Dial
And it first
After City
City Council
I will help and make sure that those that I've Limited in, Road
Pretty dry
Will have enough
And we helped
How to take care of that
Pek
Pets
Yeah
To put them down
But then about an hour and a half into it
There's this moment where
What are your solutions for the overcrowding
One of the Republican candidates this
Guy Bob capano
Goes off on this riff
It's a matter of budgetary priority
It takes money to build schools so perhaps if we put it in
273 Sanctuary City policy
Like spending 27 million dollars
Defend those here illegally who commit felonies
Trump deportation
The Hat
And then just as it seemed
Seems like people were settling down
Democrats right
This man on the
Far right side of the auditorium
Stands up and then goes on to say
Get the Arab people
The freaking Asians out of here
Rolling right along why are you selling your house
You're letting everybody take over
OK Google
Everybody sort of sat up in their seats
And nobody was quite sure if this thing we can escalate
Shortly after he said this
One of the candidates up on stage
This tall guy like six-foot-three salt-and-pepper beard
Stood up
From behind the table and actually walked out
In front of it
And I and said
There is an elephant in the room and stop racism and discrimination in Disk Utility right here
American Pacific
So the reason I was at this debate is
Like it feels right now
Like America is just added phone throat
Certainly have divided is ivory
I just keep wondering like in this moment can one person stand for all of us
Anymore and here you got this guy
We got you just heard
Heather Elliott team
A palestinian-american
Trying to win an election in one of the most conservative and most divided neighborhoods in New York
And he's running on behalf of a group of people who currently are at the flashpoint of those two
Arab-american month
And just make things a little more complicated
Heather Elliott team
Is a Christian
The love of God and the communion of the Holy
Christian minister
Check check check
Sat down with him in his office
Sex for the first time
I am an Arab American Palestinian Christian
Lutheran Pastor in Southwest Brooklyn running for office
Arab-american Palestinian Lutheran pastor
In south west of Brooklyn
Who is running for City Council
Because I want to bring
And you
Bold
Fresh inclusive powerful voice to present our district and city council
Is that you got a nice Cadence there you that you said that
You're not being a preacher
What's a good backstory how did he end up being in Brooklyn and running for
For the sea
Christian song He was born and raised in Bethlehem on the Westbank
Christian home into a family that was
Portland middle class
Father was a carpenter and made most of his money
Carving you know those little like nativity scenes with the wooden camel and the wooden Christ he carved those
My mother was a housewife and she had my father in the factory they work
Extremely hard to provide for us a good life so it's it was amazing wonderful Simple Life
But it wasn't the complicated so I went to school grew up in the church
After High School Elliot team went into the Seminary and Bible College
And then when he was in his second year this is 1989 I was arrested
Bye-bye Israeli soldiers
I was picked up from my bed from home
At 3 in the morning
And they took me to prison
For what reason
I don't know I never been given a reason why I was arrested I never been
Convicted of anything I was picked up from my bed at 3 in the morning from my father's house and take a
Going to prison I was in a sweater confinement in in a small self he says that the Israeli soldiers
Stickley tortured him hitting me and putting me outside against the wall of the back of my head under the rain and the cold
And they kept asking me you tell us what you did wrong place what you did wrong
I said I have nothing to tell you
2 months later
He was released
With no explanation
When you got home after I get back from Kmart from prison there's a lot of people came to our house
They will save all look to see what they did to you now you have to do this to them
You don't need to come to recruit you to belong to a political party
In this case it was the Palestinian Liberation Organization which at the time was explicitly an armed resist
Distance movement that often targeted Israelis
And then they will say I would like to see what they did to you now you have to do this to them
Blessed absolutely no
This is not the way I want to live the rest of my life
You know I always wanted to
Be engaged in a place where I can bring hope I can
Help people
And the only way I can do that was it through a being become a minister
So he doubled down in his studies
Seminary with working in Palestine
And then
In the early 90s
He's at he was actually sent to start a new Lutheran Church
In Bay Ridge Brooklyn
So I came to Brooklyn 1995
I remember on the first day I was shocked
Because
Biking down Fifth Avenue if you take the whole neighborhood in we are in Bay Ridge
Which I actually did not too long ago on a bike what you notice is
On the right we have Leif Erikson Park
A nod to the
Neighborhood
Scandinavian pants
This sort of crazy mix of different kinds of people
The Bay Ridge Bakery beautiful neon sign
Looks like it hasn't changed much since the 1960s
Johnny pumps
Fireman bar firefighter bar
Can I hit record
I did record
Pirate
Skinflints Pub it's sort of like looking at a geological cross-section of the neighborhood history The Bean post Pub
Schnitzel House on the Left can see how groups of people layered themselves on top of groups of people
Making themselves part of one of the most deeply mixed neighborhoods in the country
When you get just a little bit South
It's impossible to not notice one of the latest
Trying to settle in
Popular crime furniture from Sky by car to Yemen Cafe El Sahara halal meat
Women walking around in hijab
Hookah lounge hookah nuts that
Nice
Turkish kebab
Azar
What and how large is the Arab community in the 43rd.
We don't have the exact
Because again
When The Simpsons
Department
10 years ago they told the Arab Community if you're an Arab
Chick
White
So we don't have specific numbers
But the estimate I heard her somewhere between 20 and 30
Living in southwest
That's a huge community
Yeah I mean that's only about 10% of the total population
But in a Democratic primary for city council we need only about 4,000 volts to 1
Total ya
That's it I mean the turnout is very low
And we have an open seat
So we'll have a bigger chance
Winning because we're not running against an incumbent
How what's the margin of Victory to
They can be squeakers eye mean
Justice several years back
The race was won by just
31 volt
31 yes so it would seem that if this guy can just
Despite the fact that there's never been an arab-american on city council before
It seems that if he can get out the the arab-american vote
He's got a shot what shot mean do you just told us there's a lot of Arabs there so he should
You should own insulin
Actually yes but at the same time this neighborhood is such a microcosm
I think that Islam is an evil ideology that's what I think everything that's going on
Caleb deputy director of the Arab American Association of New York
And she said if you look around the neighborhood you'll see all these sort of national level issues
Playing out on the ground like a shadow play or something
I mean you've got neighborhoods in the country right
Right next to all of these people who voted for Trump who support the travel ban
None 0 shifting National demographics were one of the last remaining New York City neighborhoods
Weather is still strong white working-class but is in the process
Being priced out gentrification is really kidding white people heart and so clearly there's going to be
Like we just got a lot of the elements of
Struggles and the anxieties that are going on a national level
So
Candidate login
1:10 a.m. with all of this in mind we still are there in search for new voters
Uteam
Along with the help with his campaign manager full of dad jokes
It's it's kind of amazing Kayla
Have you guys become like best friends
She's my mother-in-law
When you call me your mother-in-law
Cuz I love my mother-in-law set up to represent
The Arab community
I am a candidate
Going with no other candidates have guns
Before
Captain captain
Anchorage
But
Dad joke aside
It's true
She really is
Trying something that's never been tried before
And one reason that it's never been tried before is that
Is 20 some thousand arab-americans
The last 20 years
They've been hiding like for me to
It's been unnerving to take to be a district where you don't feel like people are watching out for you and your community
This is Linda sarsour
Xayah Palestinian Muslim American Community organizer born and raised in Brooklyn New York that uses bookkeeping tune
No is that not long after the 9/11 attacks
The US government in 2003
Did engage in a registration program a registry
Called en Sears National Security entry-exit registration system
Which meant that males over the age of 16 who are from these like 29 countries of origin countries that have
Had a historic
Connection to terrorism Bangladesh Pakistan Iran
Iraq Egypt
Go down the list
People from those countries that were visitors temporary workers
Non US citizens
Had to come and formally register
With the federal government
Tell me give me people
Hitting us like animals
Linda was there with some of these men providing translation services
In this
Post office like room where there are all these windows the men would be called Upon a Time photograph fingerprinted
Passport ask them general questions
And I noticed that at one point that there were some men that were being told to either leave or just go home and got some stamps in their path
Passport with future appointment
Or they were telling him to go to the 10th floor
That's when my life
Something like I got punched in the stomach like I felt really nauseous I was like what's going on here
So when I went to ask the officer she was told the 10th floor was the FBI headquarters
This wasn't just an information-gathering operation
They were planning to deport
And as this realization sunken throughout the waiting room
I can't tell you the faces that these people had
Like they didn't know what their Destiny was
And in fact about 10% of those that did go register
We're put on deportation proceedings and many of them were deported no going home no packing a bag
And I think that's where the Divide start
And Saudi Arab American population in New York
Anna Bayridge learned it was better to not show up
To not be counted
Yeah and then just a few years later the Associated Press came out with their investigative report
Press reports details how Police use informants
Police Department
Operated on
Intelligence unit
Turns out that after
The NYPD was putting large
Sections of the community
Under varying degrees
Surveillance
This is Matt apuzzo, reporter
For the New York Times based in Washington and he along with his team at the AP back in 2011 broke this story
We found out there was a unit
Call the demographics unit
Terrain of New York
Snooping around neighborhoods going to different shops all the Muslim butcher shops the cafes the
Pause nightclubs restaurants down things like they play Al Jazeera
And it's this far from my mom
Use informants known as mosque
Crawlers are moths
Swonder surveil in the Arab community in Bay Ridge who had done nothing wrong they were terrified
I mean the police were even keeping track of their kids
But which Parks do our kids
Where where we're playing soccer
Couple things worth noting here at 1 in the end the operation never turned up any terrorist
Into when those things happen none of their local Representatives
No state legislator no local elected official stood up and said this is wrong
Don't Target my constituents you know these are these people are for my district
Nothing
And
What that does is it makes you feel like the people quote
Power
Don't care about us like we were out on our own and I started realizing that there was going to have to be a moment where we
We had somebody in
In the local area
Somebody who is Arab
Stand up
And protect us
And in this is where LOL your team steps
Linda started to raise these thoughts with imams and Business Leaders whole bunch of leaders from different insta
Tatoosh and decided the first step was to run a candidate for the New York City Council the idea was start small and
Start in a place where they have a strong base
Bay Ridge
Which also happened to be Linda's
And according to her lot of the unions and a lot of the people in politics were like Linda this is your seat
You have to run for the sea so I saw it like
Unfold before my very eyes
But is calling for a total and complete shutdown
Of Muslims
Entering the United States
Pallet exchange I think Islam
Hate us
We have to look at
The politically correct and
Executive director of the new political climate
I started doing a lot of national work
Chiusano the cable news shows
Became a national figure
Really
A polarizer
Why is that well in large part because and I'm sure she would hate me saying this but
Herbrand ugly is very similar to Donald Trump
She can be very reactive
She's just going to say it like it is at a straight I'm very Brooklyn and maybe too cuz I was born and raised here but I tell it like it is
More than just telling it like it is she's the provocateur
She's tweeted some tongue-in-cheek post
About how Sharia law wouldn't be that bad
More recently she called CNN anchor Jake Tapper a member of the alt right
I mean she's brash
And clematis poster-child Linda sarsour the conservative media.
Jumped all over for it
She is taking these missteps and warping them
Is it totally unfounded
Linda sarsour she is in extremis who has gas
Goddamn country
So it just didn't feel right at the moment
I didn't want to run for the New York City Council
And so after four or five years of
Planning organizing and laying the groundwork
So that Linda sarsour could run and represent the Arab community
Lyrics suddenly this moment of
Oh God. What are we going to do
You know just by the way again is Kayla santosuosso who at the time was working with Linda
At the Arab American association
And then I remember a moment when that be Association I walked in and I said to her like I just got out of him
Meeting at father K Within
And I was like what that time I was like I think I was calling him a friendly demon remember what we was calling him but I was like
Don't you think he'd be a great person to run for Council and she likes land or hand down on the table and chairs
Michaela
I was
Just thinking about
It was like a light bulb went off
So we both like started going through our heads
Why he meets Us in the middle of that all these connections with people outside of the Arab Community he's a parent of public school students here
You work that an Orthodox Jewish hospital he's clearly Liaisons the NYPD is Lutheran he's Arab but he's
Christian is not Muslim
And they start thinking like he's going to be able to get folks that no other Arab
Oh my God he's like the most
Intersectional
He's at jogging term he's like
The person with the most complex identity that might just be
So complex it'll work
And so they reached out to me on this it listen
We want you to do this
And you know he thought about the fact that doing this it would require him to quit his job it would be
Family
But it felt again like
Here with an opportunity to
To help the people around
The people in my community
So so I think I'm not sure if
Like the end of December
Where I became like
Yes 100 /
And so
Couple months later
Announce on February 20th
This is my phone
Vista
At La Saj restaurant a local Lebanese restaurant
Heading into the microphone blowing out the speakers
Every single seat was filled
And his message to them was essentially we can look
And live in the shadow anymore
We have to be engaged we have to be involved we have to be part of the decision-making in this country we have to bring our perspective to the
Because
The fact is
Other people cannot represent us
We have to present ourselves
Play I'm really getting lucky with the parking spots
Your relationship with God
I think so
I'm pretty much right off the bat those words like us
And ourselves
They presented a series of challenges
Forefathers
The first one being a large number of Arab Americans who are
American citizens
But they are not registered and they refuse to be part of the political system in this country because they don't trust it
Like here is a community that has
Avoided government
To the nth degree for the past
Decade-and-a-half
So what does he do
Well during the month of Ramadan is the holy month or four nights a week he would show up
To the mosque
Stack of literature
I need a larger stack
Voter registration form
On the night I tagged along with him and his campaign manager Kayla
This month
It was hot
Muggy
Elliott team was dressed in his Minister garb
You know suit and collar
And as we walked into the mosque
It wasn't at all clear to me
How this was going to go
What's happening in the Middle East the world and the division and the different groups I was not sure if they were ready
Tea to support at Kendall see if an Arabic Christian to represent them
So we're standing in the back of this
Huge room
I have like Green carpet and a low low ceiling
There are like seven hundred people they are standing shoulder-to-shoulder
All praying in yunnan
Download MP3
And then
There's a break in the
Salaam alaikum
Polo bucket
I'll call you in to speak now to address the people so they know that I am here
So we sort of tiptoe through all these people
We are at the front of the Mustang
They introduce them
Hubbert Realty
Louisville mobile mechanic and he launched into the speech
New York
Basically saying you know this is our historic opportunity for the herb
Community to send their first ever
Arab-american to city council
And even with the language barrier you can hear the passion in this speech
In a response that was
Tepid
Fbat
When he was done we headed out to the front of the mosque
And
Is the service light out
Sea of 700 people come crashing out of the mosque
In
Their excitement for him is on open display
They're giving him hugs they're saying we're behind you we love you
The kids the best candidate in the field and he will represent the community
Only you can represent the community we are behind you 100%
Schedule
And that evening
12:25 in the morning
We are at
Number two
Good Luck Charlie
Each time that same energetic response everyone
People were signing
Petition to get on the ballot 39 Ogden Avenue
And registering to vote
Register template
Register him
So you you just registered to vote
Yes is my birth sign
Many of them for the first time
You're the best
Did you just register
Oh no just I'm
Only for him to just Add Water
You know me what's up brother
Ultimately everybody thinks we're insane when we say we're investing a fair amount of our resources in people who have never voted before
Foreign people are kind of like
What you doing don't do that as a waste of money
Because for many of these people the whole thing about registering and then later voting it was a foreign language
Which of them
Sometimes when he'd ask people to register to vote
They respond
We go to the give you money I understand but this is the process of other people thought that just registering to vote
With the same as voting for
September 12th
And on top of that we did see signs of that mistrust of government
You want to get the first Arab American and city council
First time for a lot of people
But still
Crazy I didn't think it would get
After going from mosque to mosque
Through all of Ramadan
5.3 months before the election we have registered opposed to 300 voters so
What do you think do you think you can get those four thousand foot from the from the Arab Community alone we are
You know
Not counting on that app that we can think about 1000 votes from therapy
With only a thousand votes
Yeah just as house but didn't you just say there were tens of thousands of arab-americans living there
So first of all if I get this correct about 250
Are American boats
Forecast
In the last couple primary
250 even getting to that one thousand number
Who is going to be
I have you left
And there's one more ring
So in Brooklyn we have about eight hundred families that attend our church the folks you might expect to be
His most Ardent supporters
Other Arab American Christians
We Are Men
Ostrich in Egypt like Sharif here Sharif Sheriff Church
I don't know yet they were really uninterested in support
Will you be voting for father father Elia team
No no no
Navigate yuan
The beginning of my campaign I tried to reach out to them for me personally
No no I don't know why is that and what what it what what's going on
Will the other be Christians in our districts are
The vast majority
Republic
Yeah I will send 95% of them already
So that's number one number two
You have the situation in Egypt where Christians are being attacked
Killed after bombing Christian churches in Egypt churches are being burned
Are these radical groups of the Dead
UC
Tensions
Swellinfo is there a level of distress
In the Christian Arab community of you because you are so
Close with the Muslim Arab Community here I mean I will give you an example
Close a friend of mine his name is Francois
So people went out to him and saying
How we cannot support him and he said why not
Why is it because he's very close
Will the Muslims and they will take advantage of him
This is the dynamic this is what's happening
So eventually they decided only going after the Arab vote wasn't the right numbers game like that's just not
At work and see what that meant was to get 3000 volt
From the Arabs in the district
Who won this election
In other words he was going to have to convince the majority white voters
That she could represent them to
Which wasn't going to be
Alright walking down 50 year as I discovered when maybe a month before the election
I went on a stroll to try to take a pulse of some of the neighborhoods of white residue
Have you lived here in Bay Ridge for a while
Call my wife
Has the neighborhood changed a lot
Foreigners
Then American
I was scary
Listen
Get so expensive
A 78 year old Irish woman
You have newcomers coming into
Art District
What do they know about
Nothing
Beijing Zoo
Not know and when I asked them about father Lu team specifically what did you know anything about it
No
I don't
And I don't care to
Honestly I've never heard of them
The one that's
It's running
Right
His Egyptian
Okay
Sumatriptan
That's how I feel
Completely turns me off
And just to be clear here
You're a Democrat
Yes
These are Democrat
If anybody asks for Donald Trump when he was running
I said hell no
But I feel
This is Alex
This is America
And I feel American person
Should be in office
Is that representative of what you heard was that street on that day yes
Clearly it's not like everyone down there has easy pay
This by no means excuses their behavior or language but I think it explains some of it that
DC rent prices going up and
Dozens of new Arab folks moving into the neighborhood every month these are not the gentrifying force though this is.
Oddly enough
The Arab immigrants and even more so the Chinese immigrants
They in some ways are
Let's talk about the issues that I hear and every issue jumping back to the debate from the top of the Peace
This is one of the Republican candidates Lee in the cave
Weather it infrastructure and transportation
One particular issue in South Brooklyn and MattyB legal home conversion
Absolute my signature
Developers or landlords are taking the single family homes
Knocking out all the walls on the ground floor in the second floor
And then putting up these these
Temporary walls
Building these very
Tiny
Cramped domicile
That they can then rent out to
10 or 15 sound
What that does
Is first of all
Incredibly unsafe
For the people living in the house
But also it's putting stress on the sewer system and streets
It causes
Classroom sizes to go up
Housing prices go up because there are just less actual single family homes on the market it's making
The neighborhood up more dense than it was ever meant to be
And so for a lot of these people who have lived in this neighborhood for a long time
I think it feels like their daily lives are being affected by these forces outside their controlling they are
Reacting emotionally to those thing
So you're fighting for
I'm fighting for the district fighting to make sure the quality of life example
Couple months before the election Elliott team was going around knocking on doors
We need to do an application form
Literature and accumulated protect Sanctuary City
No you don't have my birth is not a sanctuary City
Federal login
Thank you
UPAC
And several of the Republican candidates
You know I deeply believe that illegal immigration
Has is a big root cause of this
You're trying to harness those emotion
You come here legally get a handout public health benefits
Republican
About me I am a radical
A lift is Palestinian cleric
Presumably they're using the word Claire insinuating that you are not are not in fact Christian but you are Muslim is that the incentive
Malaysian air
I plan the trying to use
The fear of the people against my candidacy
Then the comments and needed that post it is
Just terrifying
I'm going to hang him
But for example one guy said all this one I cannot read it already but I will show it to you
He's a f****** a****** and should be treated as such
I have lived in this payment for the best 22 years and never in my life faced anything like this
And is very interesting because the attacks not only coming from Republicans but also coming from Democrats in the race
About the Democrats the donut kind of under the table
OU team claims that some of the Democrats are making the argument that
Yes he might be able to win a Democratic primary
Because he's Arab
He won't be able to win the general election
So don't waste your vote on
And Justin Brannan who's really The Establishment democratic
FrontRunner in the race is a flyers and Hazlett
This is our neighborhood our guy
So for me as a Native American who living here what that's
Supposed to mean
It is a dog whistling
A statement
Exclusion
And that I'll just say on that
As a white dude
From Wisconsin
When I see that fire I don't
See that division in
Am I just blind to it
We you have to understand the context
Cast of the neighborhood
And the context is
Everything wrong in the neighborhood is Plainville Daughter by the Chinese
You know
If the street is dirty because of these damn Arabs
You know like when I go out and say
I'm fighting for the community and say Jose is only fighting for his community
But if somebody else say the word Community it's okay it means everybody
I don't mean to push back but it seems like
It seems like you two are essentially doing the same thing to one another yeah he's saying when you say the word Community it's only about the Arab to me
And when he says our neighborhood you're saying he's just talking about the white folks
Isn't it the same thing happening about the Rex
It could be but we need to understand the background we have a president who you so much rhetoric
He came up with the Muslim ban
I'm building the wall and an attacking minorities and people of color
Our councilman and his death never took a stand on these issues and came out in support of the Arab and Muslim
Give me the deets
You have to look at the history and will it seems like maybe his opponents are
Playing up this kind of identity politics
Over and over again I saw Elliot team making it
Explicit attempt
To reach out across the boundary
Is a Republican
Cider bar
He strolled up to the table of Burly white men
How are you into started giving hug
And I mean just listen to how Brooklyn he sounds you let's hear that once more
How you doing is he behaving
Thing is been a really delicate line
Kayla santosuosso
Because we really wanted to be honest and
And not adjust too much
But while also like letting people know that this campaign wasn't just for the yard Community it was for them as well
And so the campaign was also focusing on things that
12 things that matter to everyone what what's happening
They doing a complete renovation of the station
The station
No real daily life concerns 5 months
Chaotic morning Elliott team set up a Podium right in front of the cordoned off staircase of a close Subway stay
Station railed against the MTA for doing with next to no warning at all these repair that we're really just cosmetic
Work needed at all
We think about all this
Students with a growth will think about our small business owners and master barber shops with who would be affected impacted
Proposing this station
For no reason I mean what's more unifying here in New York then complaining about the subway
And she also went after specific
Groups
Who are traditionally
I just want to say thank you so much for this opportunity to invite me to be
With you tonight
Like on this rainy Thursday night in this YWCA multi-purpose room
That felt a lot like an elementary school cafeteria
My reasoning why I'm learning Forsyth
City Council
And also to tell you
That I would be very proud to be the first one to represent
The Democratic Socialist
In City Hall who are the Democratic socialists
These are the Bernie Sanders
An important fact to know is there are lots of anti-establishment
White people in this District
This neighborhood in the presidential primary went Bernie and went Trump
Beat Hillary in this test
So you think have to put on the clothes of
Yes Brooklyn Jew above
And watching him try to do that a couple things struck me
He said that was born and raised in Bethlehem Palestine and my father actually also Carpenter
Lauren London relationship
First
How he was intentionally bringing parts of himself to the four well pushing other parts into the background
So I'm going to tell you that
We have some commonality
This together and 2nd
I don't think that's why you are here today
Right
Otherwise
How he highlighted specific policies that represented those parts
I'm selfish economic just
If free education Oregon universities I have two daughters in
College and I know how much it cost me I know that my wife and I will have to get a second job to be able to pay for them to
Go to college
So did they decide to support a partner no
Well
In fact
Bigot
Eagan Thrift by the Democratic socialists of America
Both the local and National chapters of the organization
Yes
100%
Because with that endorsement came from real support
Cafe seemed like a good conduit locally they committed hundreds of volunteers had
5200 power that allowed them to
What the neighborhood
And not on Thousand Oaks
Trying to convince people to vote
Excited about that I'm feeling good.
And more than just helping them knock on doors because of the national endorsement
On many evenings of the week they actually had folks from all over the United States phone back
Calling from places like Florida to Bay Ridge Brooklyn
Again pitching people to vote for father Elliott
I'm trying to show that my candidacy for City Council
It is for everyone in this District
This is what I find so fascinating about you
Did I see such a contradiction and everything you're saying there that you're saying you want to represent the whole Community which I'm sure
Sure you do
But at the heart of it like what's motivating that is wanting to give voice
To this group of people that don't have a voice
Absolutely I mean that that is 100% that I cannot deny.
What is vemos
Motivating factors of me running because I wanted to make sure my commute
City has a voice and has representation but
Running to represent everyone
You know
Because
Was that a question in your mind going into this like
How do I walk this
Probably
Tiny tightrope
Of telling
Deer community
IMU
And this is our moment
But simultaneously
Hummingbird
Majority of the neighborhood like
But I'm still you to like Dover I can be both people have to understand
My identity
I mean I went and knocked on thousands of doors
We we talk to people
My my
Talking points of the door was always I'm a
Father for my wife is a school near
I love this community and I didn't speak on the apartheid open listings
Livability in the community we spoke about transportation we spoke about
A police accountability we spoke about things that people in the community
Embassy Suites
Yes we are going to support
We need somebody like you who can go and in our behalf
So at the end of the day my identity is
Who I am
I am running as
And I would not allow anybody to take
That away from
And so just a couple of days before September 12th before the election
I checked in with Kayla to see how things were look
How many days do we have left here
And apparently she told me as Lu team and is canvassers had been going around to all of these doors knocking
They had been taking notes
In those notes each person was given a number from 1 to 5
Based on
Their level of support one is like that person was so proelia team you didn't even need to go to that door you're just marking them
5 is like
Sorry I'm voting for somebody else
Twos and ones are positive IDs
I'm just a couple of days before the election an election I'll remind you they only need four thousand votes to win
The number of positive IDs they had was
5500 so you currently a 5500 give or take
Sol Willoughby be interesting to see how the primaries will be translated the numbers when the
September 12th comes
Okay well we're going to take a break and when we come back it'll be Election Day election day
This is Jeffrey this is Marjorie from Boise Idaho Radiolab is supported in part
By the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloan at www. Sloan. Org
I hate everybody
I'm a producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
On the show
And I request
For those of you who
Who spend a lot of time with kids parents
Aunts and uncles teachers we're looking for stories about what we're calling
Tiny moments
Brilliant
Basically I want to hear about this
When a kid you know did something
It just means you lean back and say
How do they do that
Maybe it was the moment that I
A kid you've been reading to 4 month started reading back
To you
Or maybe the kid was a piano
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of their musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class
Music in the margin of their geometry
We're interested in the
Epic moments where
Kid does something super smart
It doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story
Go to radiolab.org
Flash brilliance
And record a short
Audio message
Again that's radiolab.org
Slash brilliant
Thank you so much
Jay Roberts radio that I'm going to go back to sleep
Okay with what happened
So the election
This is September 12th or 8 so it is 6 in the morning what he 17 is yet to rise
We are outside the
OU team
Get out the vote
Here we go
I got no no
So I show up at 6 in the morning and everything is already abuzz
Scrapy with dozens of volunteers
Staff workers
If you were coming this morning
Hovering around these plastic folding tables that were
Set up everywhere
Don't leave without one or two signs so what we going to do
All right
Sweet and shortly shortly after I got there Kayla
Father Elliott team both arrived
Matching that's pretty awesome
The memo
Yeah right they were in matching Democrat blue Kayla and blue jeans and a blazer father Lut
Am I in an Oxford with the white
Collar
Today's election day
This Is Us
September 12th
What is quickly as he arrived
No opposition insights
And enjoy yourselves sent out
To start the day
Beautiful day in the neighborhood
And so I
The beautiful day in the neighborhood
We hopped in the car and that was sort of the beginning of the day and really his job was just to shake as many hands with as many people as he could
Good in as many different disparate parts
Of the Disco
Strict as possible
Are you avoiding today and I'll talk to you speak Arabic or English
What should be the basis
Of whether or not you win a race
Is ID and
Ideas many positive IDs as you can
Pull out as many of those
People on Alexa
Pull out meaning pull them to the pole
Broccoli
Get as many of your positive IDs
Out to the polls
You can't blame for their campaign to do this
We have two affected we have two different operations
First and foremost
Salaam alaikum
We have likely Arabic
Speakers assumption was
That an Arab voter is going to need their hand held much more tightly
To get them
To the polls
Never been to the polls before
And so they had like six people on their phones just going down these list
Have you voted today
Simultaneously that same person who's been called basically the person that actually make sure that you go vote
Being flanked by a group of canvassers
This is a Muhammad marching up to their apartment in banging on their door saying
1 C to e r e d
4 + 40
Come out and vote we're going to pull you out
What time are you going to the polls
I need you to go vote father K need you to go look
They had this very
Long script they would go through
And I don't remember all of the Arabic but they would often say so are you going to the polls today and the responsibility and Shala
I like God willing and they weren't supposed to accept that they'd have to say no no no no no no no
Inshallah tomorrow today God willing you willing and then they would have to get them to say either like I
I promise on my head and I promise on my heart and
And if they got either of those then they felt like they had imposed social pressures that would work on the Arab community
And then on top of all this we have to do the standard operation of get-out-the-vote with the Triple Crown voters which is like
The voters that have that reliably vote in primaries
In this community largely White
Largely over the age of
250 St Nicholas
Old folks home
I am back again nursing homes sending out even more canvassers and even
Educational shout out the passenger window of your car
Early on in the day back at the campaign headquarters
I need somebody to free
It was clear just how complicated and resource-intensive running these two parallel campaigns what
Go to vote
I just received a call from several Muslim women saying that they needed a ride to the polls
His wife Grace was going to go pick them up
But you needed someone to go with her
But you know.
If I can leave the table
You got it
Yeah I'll be one of the campaign directors and eat said no you got to stay here
I'll take care of this
Muhammad
Can it be Muhammad like Justin Muhammad
But turns out at Muhammad doesn't speak Arabic
Arabic
Eventually turned out to not actually be a problem so why doesn't Muhammad
Sogo
But then we died put it up
Women
Would be more appropriate for all those going to pick them up
Three women
San Marino culture
Muhammad can be here
How to make it take my place for a little bit
What do I do
Define lie
Indeed a hectic
They said we. Just go
And this was all for just to vote
But I will say despite all that Midway through the day it did appear like this two-pronged approach woodworking
You didn't
50 doors
71 people canvassers we're getting good feedback
And on the street
Dr. Adam
Airboats
And hello
White folks were coming up to and saying like
We voted for you
Pomeranian teamholiday with the campaign from the beginning
You understand what this means for the American community
You only know what it means
Pretty personal
Are you going to say
Really emotional I don't want to be voice in the loop
My husband is dad in Malaysia
Because you send me a man
Okay Kendall
Thank you.
Public voting
Thank you
It is very personal
But then
Hi how are you
In LED in car at about 2 in the afternoon
How's the numbers looking
They got their first sense of what voter turnout was looking like
Right
So they never said that we're
Underperforming in a few poll sites
You should be doing better
Yeah
Sorry
This is Muhammad Khan the campaign treasurer
Yeah they never said that
You know post I swear we have
Strong support
Are showing lower
Turn out the way
So I can see what I know who people are voting
Informant we're guessing
Since less people are voting their overall that means
Lymphocytes where are we now
Our opponent has trunks
Support
And so what what are the strategies to remedy that
So is need to allocate more again
Areas where we see
Thunder performance
Turn more people
To go knock on the
Knock on the doors
Old people out of their homes
Make sure they vote
And so with about 4 hours remaining
The right now is all about talking to individuals Dragon people off the street
All of the leaders of the campaign including Linda sarsour
Barber shops
They were literally going into arab-owned stores
Barbershops delhi's hookah lounges
Google
And what was happening of the final push
Volunteers were showing up
It's a good time to push again
Liverpool sites that have been hit at 115
Seem to be working
So we just got to keep that up
What what what what's the what's the emotion of the moment
Yeah I don't know I mean it's a closed right there like if I eat it feels like it
Based on the turnout numbers that were seeing in the way that turn out happening there's basically two strongholds that are currently developing
North Bay ridge ave Bay Ridge
South Bay Ridge which is largely White
Seems to be turning out hard for the establishment candidate just
And Brandon in North Bay Ridge is where the majority of the arab-american
And in that moment the campaign makes a decision
So at this point we're zeroing in all of our efforts on just
Everything North
75th Street
That the only way to win
Is the push hard to get as many votes as they can in those Arab American neighborhoods and essentially
Write off trying to convince the white
So this is like you know we got it it's our people are going to make the difference so we go for our people
Yes
We're doing good
Inside like an hour remaining
Everyone went out
For one final push
Lock.
And I'll see it when I come back
Cars were driving by honking their horns for him
Brooklyn
Just broke the 12 hour shift
Hey thank you so much
Thank you so much brother
Can you take a picture of us
By my watch it is 9
The campaign is over
I was with eliaquim right when we hit 9
And in that moment
I don't know from where but someone handed him
What's up baby
An infant
And he was just
Standing on this dark
Street
His back against the minivan
His face illuminated by the Light
Pouring out from his campaign headquarters
With this baby in one arm
And his cell phone pressed tightly up against his ear
Asking Kayla
What the numbers were looking like
All of these volunteers staff and supporters
We're gathering in the patio of this bar Pizzeria called the Firefly
Waiting there for eliaquim to arrive
As well as the results
Kayla called me as I was walking up to the fire
Fly pizzeria
Because of that time the numbers from South Brooklyn came in
She said I've added these results with what we already know and she said the
Willis
The moment before I walked into
Biloxi weather
The Firefly
After word got around that they had in fact lost on Linda sarsour
Stood up on this picnic table
And addressed everyone
I know a lot of folks were here who are not
Children immigrants or if you're not arab-american or Muslim you do not under
Understand what
It is not over
And I want to see the father
Father, did not have to do
He did not have to
Quit his job
A father of four
But father I just did it
He did it to help us build the political voice that we knew we always had
In this community to allow people to pay attention to us and our issues
The weather tonight we're doing this again
But we lost it
Gwinnett to they know why we ended up losing by just under 700 votes
Which is about 7% of the total vote
Cast we know what what what would account for the difference
Because the voter records don't come out until December but there are a couple things that we do know one
Was that the Renault Arabic translators at the polls
Really
Yeah
See how far I can get I'm just follow we actually had reporters sarkari go down into one of the polling
To see exactly what was going on
Hi can I just ask what languages you guys are translating
Cantonese and Mandarin
How about you
Cantonese
Spanish
English to Spanish
Okay is there somebody in Arabic translator
Portugal Arabic is not a
Approved the language
4 in
Driving trip
Acting New York
Turns out
What languages are provided in any borough of New York City
Are decided upon
Based on census
And because there is no census data, that may be so angry
You can't come here like who they are they just have
Go neutral
What the problem was the interpreters that the campaign was attempting to provide for these folks
At several of the polling locations they were actually turned away from the
Play New York state official by the election people by the folks working the polls
Relay
Which is which it turns out is illegal
They were illegally turned away
But
Despite all that they did in fact get out more arab-american voters than have
Ever turned out
For a Raceway
It's like by
Factor of 404
Where they ended up
Coming up short it would seem
Is with the white photo
And nobody has a perfect explanation
But I did talk to some political movers and shakers down in the area and they they offer.
Three different explanations
When is that the message that he was delivering to the white folks to fail
How to connect
The second one is that
Having these two campaigns at the same time one for the Arabs one for the white folks that that just damn damn from the beginning II recovery
All of it either
IMM the third one is that
This had nothing to do with him
The fat nothing to do with this campaign
Just In This Moment there were not enough white folks who would be willing to vote for in Arab candidate
No matter what
No it's nice to
We're emotionally where are you
Are you are you
Do you like cotton
A couple weeks after the election I headed back down to Bayridge to sit down
One more time with Father Lut
Well of a truth is that I haven't taken a day off yet
You cuz I've been so busy
I'm not doing this to myself it is just
The outcome of the
Just convince husband
Unbelievable
So the moment we finished with the campaign week
Continue to meet
The discus
The boutique aboard that we have built
What the weather going to do with it
Because we have almost three thousand people came out and voted
We can make a difference in any election
And that's why I said we cannot slow down now we need to continue to educate the community we need to continue to be engaged
It's within we cannot oppose government
We cannot
Afford to lose the momentum
We just can't
So this is
Are you a politician now like is that what
This is the will of the community
We have demands
We have
Political power
And then we have an address now and the address is Heather Elliott
Also elected officials
You would have talked to us
You come and speak to us through Heather Elliott
That's the only way you can talk
Wow yeah I I feel like what struck me in that conversation
Would like he spent his entire campaign
Trying to
Speak to
All sorts of different crew
She was saying I can represent you all
I am your everyone
But in that final conversation
What I heard from him in that was
Can becoming more and more of a voice of just
One group
One community
His command
Mut yeah
But I said
Cut you know this is the game
I feel like this is him recognizing the nature of the game and
Deciding to come from a position of strength
I say also I'm also you want him to
Basically
Tighten his grip on the Arrow vote and then walk in the room after lumiquest next AC
When you want it our votes deal with me I've got votes
The push I've got votes to give and withhold
What I want I want that community
To step out
And be heard
Have a voice
And this is how it has
I think it has two
If you believe in this system it has
To be possible
If someone talented enough
To be able to stand up
Say two things at
At the same time
Two things seem contradictory but he does believe in
It has to be possible
Yeah I understand that but I mean in this particular moment in this pretty good I mean
I don't think identity politics
The choice
Yeah I mean you remember the woman who's like
Stele egyptian
He's being seen
That's one thing that he is not what are you doing
Just like pretend to have a Rainbow Coalition when there's no
Chances that you just want to fight
You got that out of your system
So how does he feel about me I was going to say oddly enough
I tried to put all of this in front of him
With that
That brings me actually to the question that I think is at the heart of everything IV
Is you were really trying to transcend
Identity politics
You were trying to at one time speak to those
People in yet
At the same time say no.
My turban is has nothing to do with
You trying to do both
And I think that
I worry that that is why it's
I don't know
To think about what you just said but the
You know I
With other as myself as an Arab American Lutheran pastor
But I had to take
Stance on issues that really matter to me and to the things that I am passionate about
But does that mean you're sort of a better person than you are a politician
I like to see myself like that definitely I mean I
Did I saw it with my team so it was the right thing
What ended
Would you would you run again
Sure
Yes
Our story was reported and produced by Simon Adler
With production help from Bethel hopday and anemic you
Real quicksand special tanks
Two of your kawas and Paula Katinas David Lewis and Bridget Bergen from the WNYC Newsroom Ralph perfetto
Oh and Justin Brannan
Rebecca chiasson David Fox sarakari and Eddie McCune for their help Gathering tape
The Muslim Democrats in New York
Salam Arabic Lutheran Church
And everyone on the other Elliott team for city council team
For putting up with me for 8
Namaste text assignment you're welcome
Nightwell ready to get out of here
I'm ready to go
Hi there my name is Mateo marching band I'm calling from Kansas City Missouri
And I'm going to read the credits
I apologize in advance if I mispronounce any of the names
Radiolab was created by Jack FM rod ends produced with Soren wheeler
Dylan Keith
Besides director of sound design
Our staff includes
Simon Adler
Rachel Cusick
David gebel
Bethel hottie
Tracy hunt
Matt kielty
Robert krulwich
Annie McEwen
Latif Nasser
Melissa O'Donnell
Ariana whack
And Molly Webster
With help from Amanda Ranch
Shamaley
David Fox
Garfunkel
Phoebe Wang and Katie Ferguson
Are fact checker
Is Michelle Harris