Are you awake
Listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
Hey I'm Jared I'm Rod I'm Robert krulwich Radiolab and what we're going to do in this particular show
This is one of my favorites
Yeah baby we gave it your all that
I don't know I just wait what we say here I miss is like at this is a little bit of a tussle
We sorta want to bring it back cuz you know Winters
Approaching things are kind of heavy right now could use a little lightning
This begins with
A very very
Successful
A film editor with what you'll you'll meet him in the moment
A comes to us with an idea which Chad loves I hate and things go from there
Perfect
Hello hello
Starts with Walt
Walter murch, film editor and sound designer and I've been working in film since
The late 1960s
Resume includes
I want to make an offer
The Godfather
Apocalypse Now
Carnival
Don't see think we're talkin about
Is the
One of the more spectacular stories I've ever
How do you
Bump into this
Well I was in
Leon
In France
Doing a film
Unbearable lightness of being
Is back in 1986
I was supposed to be there for a week and it wound up
Why was there for a month
But ran out of things to read so I went down the street from the hotel on
There was a bookstore
I was interested and still am in cosmology so I picked up a book by the
Carl Sagan
French
My name is Hubert Reeves
You better
You better actually is French Canadian
You translate to stop signal
Merchants up buying Reeves book ghost
The hotel
Because he's happily reading away and he was trying to explain
With some
Difficulty because it's a difficult
Topic
How did
Matter condensed
Out of the sort of
Pork soup
But we believe happened right after the big bang
And he tried various
Temperature
Scientifically but then he said
To give you a sense of
The Poetry of this moment
The best
Thing is the story that malaparte tells
Who is malaparte
Well
He was a journalist
Poets
Diplomat
Soldier
Prisoner film director
And somebody who
Got around and speaking of getting around in 1942 a
Milanese newspaper
Centinela Park
To report
On the eastern and Northern front
So the war
Specifically the Russian Finnish border you had a front-row seat of the siege of Leningrad
The agony of the Nazi bombardment of that City and its from there
In Menlo Park
So this
Day
This wasn't in the winter
Malaparte was posted with a Finnish Army who were fighting along with the Nazis
And they were perched just north of vinegar
On the shores of Lake ladoga which is this big
Lake
About in the city
And on this day
The Nazis bombarded.
The start of the forest fire everyone ran for cover
Soldiers ran Every Witch Way and in the middle of the forest there were Soviet forces that were locked up in a stable
And the horses
And broke out at the Stables hundreds of them and they just started running to get away from the
Do you have hundreds of horses vaulting through this flaming Forest heading towards the open space I had
Which was the lake once they first out of the forest and go barreling into Lake
Stampeding one on top of the other
If y'all get deeper and deeper
In the blink of an eye
Snap some shots
It just freezes
Suddenly turns to ice with a bang
It goes from water to ice with this violence
Snap
And suddenly the horses are in 2
Malaparte right cities in the waves on the Lake Weir gripped in midair and sort of suspend
Fade Out
The next morning when malaparte in the fins
Woke up and discovered the forest fire had burned itself out
And look at that the lake has frozen solid overnight
And his finished friends said yes that's sometimes
They look and see what are those bumps on the ice over there
They go to investigate and they find themselves in this
Horrific sculpture garden of
Horses heads
Sticking up out of the solid marble like
4 of ice
He said hundreds of hundreds of Horseheads leaderboard
These are these are not going to Decay right cuz it's freezing cold so they will be those horses stay there all
Winter
Malaparte was there in that
Region of the world during that winter and every so often he and the other soldiers
Go and have a smoke
Letgo
Into the sculpture garden and
Wander around looking at this miraculous
To this image of the horses Frozen in this Lake beautiful and strange and disturbing
Profound in some way
Latest Wonder
I told you I just don't trust this story it's not a scientific Lee impossible and I
Keeping an open heart
You got it would this possibly be
Could there be a grain perhaps several grain perhaps a Lakes worth of grains of Truth
Just your mind is like loose like a
Anyway
This year
We can strike that argument right now and take this up town
Alright let's do this
Doctor's review sites
Floors of argument
We ended up going uptown to Rockefeller University
Medical people who know about I so we're going to go play with some super cool ice
Magnum
This fellow
I'm Alexander Petrov in the Raymond and Beverly Sackler felco
They occasionally almost show up and I almost meet them but I never have yeah
By the way the Sackler family
Recently come into a bit of controversy
We all know that now
We didn't it
Daleks you must be said isn't amazing dude
Graciously agreed to demonstrate that you can in fact
Create the conditions of that massive Lake
Inside a tiny little stupid
Destructive Falcon Falcon tube
The plastic tube filled with water
This is not normal water this is the really nice water it's very very
Pure water no minerals no Destiny like super distilled and he says when you take water like that and you cool it down
You can get it far below its freezing point and it won't freeze
Unless that is
Yeah but
You have a tiny horse here
We have a tiny
And we are going to drop that into the Falcon tube and do that
That's going to be awesome so we handed us
The tube I'm holding a little vial of supercooled water with it Alex what temperature do you think
This is mine this is mine
C Celsius
When does water freezes at 0
20 degrees below freezing point at Stillwater but not for long
Unscrewed the cap are you are you filming
We held the little plastic horse over the tube
Count down or something
Okay on the count of three guilty
At 3
2 1
Because the moment that little plastic horse hit the water the water slammed into ice
Selling that little guy was trapped
In a nice guy
Oh my God is Thor's is Frozen
Please remember the horse was plastic no animals were harmed in this experiment
It is honestly breathtaking
But it happens
Selfie
Catastrophic ice formation
Just like that
You're the seaward Robert say it again
Catastrophic
This is Virginia Walker
Andaman the department of biology Queens University
Virginia was one of the many people that we called up to
To ask
What the hell like why does this happen
Action this water just freeze gradually the way that
Water does you know what 32 degrees Fahrenheit
Whatever new
So you see this
That's why we have to stop at the beginning as Julie Andrews said
A very good place
Start right
All right
So the only reason that water freezes normally at zero
Celsius
32 Fahrenheit
Is that the something they have that makes
Freeze we Colette and UK later
Sounds like a superhero
Yeah I'm alright
Citizen ukulele
A nucleator is like
Accede
Right
Didn't know this but it turns out
Water almost always needs a seed
In order to grow ice
It turns out water by itself is not actually
That good at remembering how to become ice
That is Erin Pettit
She's a glaciologist
At the University of Alaska Fairbanks and which of these is it when water cools down the molecule start to slow their movement
A little bit closer together that point they want all hold hands and become I set the water molecules don't quite remember
Very well
How they're supposed to be organized
Bill equate do you stand here and I stand here how do we do this again
They need to be shown what combination of angles work the best to create a nice day
Table
Structure what they need is a speck of dust that's the nucleus
He throwing some dust and to otherwise pure water now they have a guy
Because I scan start to mimic whatever the the the shape of the Dust particle is
What happens if the water molecule start to form a cage around the dust particle in that case shape
Is very similar to the shape they need
To make ice
Something that I like that's how we do it
Sooner sense the dust particle is reminding the water molecules
How to freeze
No I do
Think of it like that
Bridget says it's actually not quite so
So gentle really what's happening is the dust particle is
Forcing the water molecules into the right shape around it
It's like a it's like a command
Nothing about memory is its
It's a physical thing
They just got jammed in there
Started
Dog ate so if
As we just learned water needs
The catalyst nucleator
In order to
Fries
Doesn't least raise the possibility that that
Finnish Russian Lake
And reached
Supercooled state
Along come these horses and they
Where the nucleator maybe they had dust on their hair
Or whatever I don't know
Whatever it was it started a chain reaction
Ice
Spread outward from these horses shot across the entire leg
And froze the whole damn thing
Once
An actual excuse me for just a second because this is like at reading like in post I have
We're going to take a break and we'll continue this
Meaningless tussle in just moments
This is Alicia Bridges going from Saskatoon in Saskatchewan Radiolab is supported in part by the
Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloane @www.
Flooring.org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here I'm a producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help this summer I'm hosting
And I request for those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
We're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments
Williams
Basically I want to hear about those times when I did something
It just means you lean back and say whoa
How do they do that
Maybe it was the moment that our kids you've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons and you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed they're writing music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the
Specific moments where
Kid does something super smart but doesn't have anything to do with the test
If you have a story
Go to radiolab.org Brilliance and record a short audio message
And that's where you're at. Org / brilliance
Thank you so much
Okay so big Jad Robert Radiolab before the break
We posited what I thought was an interesting Theory robber
Not buying it now get to your skepticism I want to talk
A little bit more
About nucleator
Because when we were talking with Virginia
Tell us something kind of cool
Astrolabe
What else
Nucleotide
We learn about Josh but what else can do
Okay
So
The best nucleator
Is ice
So just have a little bit of snow falls into some water or a little bit ice
Forms in the water organically
The water molecules will rush around that and Bam if you don't have ice
What is the second best thing
Tenor ukulele size
Happens to be bacteria
She says there aren't
Three different kinds of bacteria
They can generate these
Special protein big hunk and protein that can instantly turn water into ice
In fact we were reporting the story of video started circulating on the internet
It showed a scientist taking a bottle of water squirting out a little bit of this bacteria in a minute
Nothing just shot in dice
And that
Cool thing is
These bacteria are actually Plum pathogen
Plant killer
So you've probably seen bras
Growing in your backyard or whatever and it can be all covered with frost
But then you know the frosting melt and it's still green
But if those bacteria present
She says they'll spit out their proteins
Under the plant
Generate seed ice crystals
Ice crystals
Then slice the plan open and
Expose the inside of the plant at the bacteria site yummy
His lunch and the eat the eat the inside of the
Good strategy
That's not the cool part
Regina said she is also found these proteins
Bacteria that don't
So that made me think
Mater wonder why
Why would they need to me
And that's when it
It occurred to her and a few other
Maybe it's about
Transportation
Exactly where
Nothing about these bacteria just sitting on these play
And what happens is the wind comes along
Blues up this little bacteria into the upper atmosphere
Blows them literally up into the cloud
Did not particularly cold hardy
Situation
Do you not want to be all the way up there
They got to get back down to the Earth
And unless I hit you right on those horses that you keep talking about
This a light
They might not come down to us
So what day do Shih Tzus back since they use the plant trick they spit out these proteins
Into the cold wet Cloud which galvanizes the water molecules around them
The Forum
Snowflake
Around their body
So now they got this little hovercraft
They can use to
Post on down
With they make ice they can get back down and they can get back down into different place
And start a new colony of bacteria somewhere else
And so but this way they get dispersed around the whole us
Think about that
The next time it's winter
It snows
Apparently
If you melt
Each snowflake
You'll find a little bacterium inside
You're saying all of them
I haven't looked at
Every single
Snowflake
But it makes perfect sense doesn't it
That's a bit that's a very very cool idea
I suddenly like the bacteria movie
Helluva lot better
The horse movie
Solis
At least as a shot of being true
Yeah
The horses
So when we were reporting this story.
Darren Pettit in Virginia walker and a bunch of other
We asked
Could entire leg
Flash frozen in an instant
Trappin all those horses
Uniformly the answer that we got was no
Did you hear her know there did you hear the sound of it
Can you say absolutely not or is it just a kind of gentle no
I'd say that's an absolutely not
Because Aaron told this when you're talking about freezing and it's
Prior Lake
Will you got a lot of problems to consider first
Process of
Freezing
Actually is a source of heat
Itself because like when water molecules form bonds to make ice
That's a lot of activity
The inactivity producer
Energy and now
That's going to make things a little bit warmer not to mention the fact that horses are warm-blooded animals
But they also would slow down the process
Also the water would never have been pure enough to super glue in the first place because I
There's too many things in the lake that would
Provide that initial nucleation plants organisms dirt
Did somebody actually see this what is the actual evidence that
No
Nobody saw any of this as it actually happened
When we told Walter Marsh with the scientist
In typical Baltimore fashion he was
Iseecars
Reminded us that he never told us it was true that malaparte often mixed fact in
Addiction and a theory real reason he's attracted
The story
Because it offered a metaphor for cosmology the beginning of the universe
Really
I mean
If you'll excuse me for a small bit of skepticism is true for the universe metaphor metaphor
Even so you mean here's what I mean
And if you're a physicist listening right now just turn off
So you can think of it in one of two ways right the first is that idea of super Cooling
Wechat Rockefeller where
Under the right circumstances water can cool down way below its freezing point
Not freeze
And then all of a sudden
Innokin suddenly do that
What you thought Rockefeller in the test
According to Jan 11
Professor of physics
Barnard College
Colombia universe
And therefore holds because
That Bizarro flash freezing phenomenon actually happen repeatedly
She says in the moments after the big bang
Yes
Supercooling is definitely something that happens in the early yunnan
She says right when the universe got its start
Still small like a size of a grapefruit
Inside the grapefruit is extremely hot back then it was probably a million billion trillion
Million times hotter
A million trillion trillion trillion times 32 times hotter
Bedazzled grapefruit began to expand the temperature started to drop and it dropped and dropped to a point where
Universe should free
To speak but it didn't
It's waiting is waiting for you and you're like what's happening why aren't you freezing then suddenly
Exchange
The guide
Okay I don't know exactly what you're saying we keep going a lot of phase changes some of them
Super cool don't worry
Okay
There's another parallel which I think is actually even more
Has to do with those seeds
Do we talked about
If you go back to the Grave
Okay inside
It's very hot you got this wash of energy in this energy
Is
Uniform
Write all the same thing
Spread evenly
Everywhere the same
Dentist in school you begin to get these
Tiny
Punctuation variations
Temperature
Density for the little bit hotter and denser in one point
Then another we're talkin about clumps
Like maybe were here is a little bit more matter and heat than over there
And bees rrc
I don't think that you're describing seed like I understand see Caesar Little Things
Things that attract others
Behave just like seeds
Because as the universe cooled down and expands and begin to add all these new forces and all these new particles
Gravity electron
John Adams
Those little bits of variation from the beginning or still there
And now they're growing bigger
Now we have gravity
Writes a little concentrations of stuff are now attracting more stuff
More stuff in the more stuff in as Universe expands they expand until ultimately those little blips have
Massive objects amazingly the largest
Structures that we know about in the universe have their seeds in these tiny f****
Does that mean when you go
On a
On a star
Worst
Kind of voice you and your spaceship in your going out
Some incredibly
Rushing through the universe
And you see
Huge clouds
Gas with
Nurseries for
Stars and you leave them and you go to a Galaxy and then another galaxy that has got to be here any Galaxy over there and what you hear
You're saying these massive structures
Walls of galaxies
Neighborhood
Stardust
AR
Reflections of a very
Early moments
Something went
In the initial broilers
This beautiful structures that you're describing are like the snowflakes around a little bit ago
What is that mean that the empty spaces that we see when we gaze at the
Current universe
Are actually filled with something that hasn't
Cool yet or that his
What are is invisible to us or is working under different rules
I can say we might not have seen the last of the basement
Our universe is absolutely continuing to cool
Is it really yeah
It's very cold right now
We have this
Dark Energy driving the universe
2 expanded a never accelerated rate and it's conceivable that in the future that energy won't do or some phase transition
And it will go away or or Decay to something else
And this new state of matter
It might do something different to the evolution of
So we might have a phase transition in our future
Suddenly in a
Oldies
We have many people to thank who helped us on this particular podcast totally
Producers Matthew kielty Molly Webster
Also Amanda rain check
Party spot you for sure and Marine budo the super cool people at Rockefeller University
IGT Garbarino Phil Kidd
Chris Alexander
Petroff exhausted at Jefferson strohminger
Herberg Mark Martin Martin Martin and Jason Wexler and sincere thanks to all the listings from
Facebook and Twitter who helped us
Translate
Russian and finish book
Oh and last but not least Walter murch
My hero
Jaguar
I love you
And more importantly he released
A book
Translating malaparte from
Italian
English
Which is where we got
The story
Of that
Dove the horse
It's called the bird
Swallowed it
Cage the select
Writings of
Curzio malaparte
All right so that's
Let us say goodbye
Go to my website
Radiolab.org
And you can see videos
We shot a rock
Of water
Turning into ice
In a Flash
Pulling right in front of your eyes
Radiolab.org
The ride
I'm Robert Pollard
This is Stephanie calling from Bushwick Brooklyn
Radiolab has created by Jad appenrod and is produced by Soren wheeler
Dylan Keith art director of sound design
Maria Montessori Padilla is our managing director
Our staff includes Simon Adler
Becca Bressler
Rachel Cusick
David Cavell Bethel Hoppity
Kasie hunt Matt kielty Robert krulwich
Annie McEwen lots of Nasser Melissa O'Donnell
Arianne wack
Pat Walters at Molly Webster
With help from Amanda aronchick Shima Oleo
David Fuchs
Vitaly
Phoebe Wang and Katie Ferguson
Are fact-checker is Michelle Harris