Hi I'm Robert krulwich Radiolab is supported by Casper and their expert to make quality mattresses that
Cradle your body
In all the right place
Get $50 towards select mattresses by visiting casper.com Radiolab
Add using Code Radiolab at checkout
Terms and conditions apply
Hi I'm Robert krulwich Radiolab is supported by Audible
As we explored more how the world is saturated in color
Sofft shoes 2 violet stains
Check out brain myths exploded lessons from Neuroscience available at Audible
Explore the Myriad topics for Neuroscience 224 lectures about MIT
Of the brain
Go to audible.com Radiolab
For a free 30-day trial and a free
Audiobook
Hey I'm back up wrestler and the production manager here at Radiolab and I'm here to tell you about a new WNYC
Studios podcast called
Caught
Do you remember when you were a kid or a teenager
You made a bad decision and you said to yourself if I just did away with it this one time I'll never do it again
WNYC Studios or launching a new series about kids who aren't so lucky
Cocktails with stories of teenagers
Who make the thoughtless impulsive decisions and as a result gets sucked into a punitive Juvenile justice system that
Change their lives you can find caught in iTunes or wherever you get your podcast be sure to check it out and subscribe
Are you awake
Northern listening to Radiolab
Radiolab wnyc
I was dismissed I was only dismissed from the day I was dismissed from I'm not even supposed to come back to my whatever
How do you so elated and I was kind of mopey until
What's wrong with you
I like to read
So you're gone all day tomorrow no I'm not
I'm drunk
Oh my God
Okay if you want to do this tomorrow we could go if you want
That's good to know
Okay so Robert
Where where do we start
But if you start where we left off right right where we left off we thought we had
Simply the most fabulous
Animal
Otherwise in the world champion of rainbows
South champion ring listen to Radiolab by the way
Roberts 07 issues ago we did a show about colors we had a very simple question
Who
Among Us earthlings sees the best rainbow
We found a champion
And we're going to
Reevaluate
That Carnation as time passes and science advances so
I think we should play the original segment
Because it is Delight
Rifle you hear the crowning of the champion and then we should re-evaluate whether the champion deserve to be crowned
End of the the early segment it started with Robert ask a question to
Cognitive Scientist by the name of Mark Shane giese
But here's a question if a dog
And be human
And a
Crow we can be staring at a rainbow would they be seeing very different things
Yes
Know this question that Robert is kind of tossed out during an interview
How different creature
See the rainbow
This ended up taking us down a little wormhole
We ended up actually getting a choir
Dealt with illustrator
What we learned
But just a set of Baseline your normal rainbow goes like this
Starting bottom up
Red orange yellow green
Blue violet roygbiv
Reggie Bell
Yea though I don't know why people put the i in there but that's it we didn't have the Indigo you couldn't say it though. That's why you need the IRS
That by the way is Tom Cronin
What's called a visual ecologist Mark suggest
McCall he told us that humans see
Seven colors in the rainbow
And in the case of the dog
Very different rainbow it's going to start off
Blue hillbilly Seafood is fine
So it was here rainbow starting with blue
St. Louis CNN grading off into green
Same for us
And then disappearing
Give me the weather in there
Video
That's it
Yeah so the rainbow the only good. Hafez
SRS wow
Lucky rainbow
Dog that's why when God promised that he would never deliver another day lose a game
If I made the promise in a rainbow
The dogs 2 strip totally unimpressed
What is it about the dog I that
Makes it see this way
It doesn't have
Red sensitive
Photoreceptors no red sensitive cones
The weird thing is it the difference between dogs and us
It's just one they have cones tuned to blue and green so do we
We have this one extra
Red
It's just a really seem like a big difference
It's just one call
But I have three
It's so much better than two that's janeites Vision scientist
Because of this kind of multiplicative thing
Redken get mixed
With blue
Check purple
Or red can get mixed with yellow
How to make orange
Green mixed with blue teal or turquoise
That's how we get about a hundred different shades
Colors that we can see
2 by adding one photopigment instead of adding just
One more color you actually add about 98 colors
Let's move on to now we have a
Pro unless you'd like to change the bird
Well the crow is not so much because it's pretty much like us
Let's take a listen or something like a
A sparrow sparrows have ultraviolet vision
What did they say
So they see the rainbow starts before I remove starch for wheezing see Sky it would see in ultraviolet
What color
And then it would see the violet
That would see the blue
And the greens
Les oranges
Is our first in your engine and then the writer probably would see
Further into the red mask because I have
Amore red sensitive red receptor than we have
See a much broader rainbow would start earlier and it would end later
So should we assume that we've now that this Powers the champion but that's the that's that's as high as a guest if you're talking about
Vertebrates
No I'm talking about anything that has a heart and a mind an advantage you leave the vertebrates then all bets are off you've got
Many animals have much better color vision than the vertebrate story
Like butterflies or butterflies have five or six
Kinds of
Of color receptors we only have
Tree ring
Butterfly see more colors than we do
Yeah
So if a butterfly release
King of the rainbow
Butterflies are out there when we see colors we have no names
For between the blues and the greens and the greens on the yellow so it would go from
Ultraviolet would see that then it would see violet
And then
Blue
MN blue green
Yep in green green Bluey Bluey or whatever
Brighten an orange and red and all that
I have very complicated eyes
Okay so just to recap
Here's the dog
Givens
Now the Sparrow
Lil bit more bass look more high-end
To speak finally
The butterfly
Just so you know not so far about this. What's got more meds in there
So I'm not thinking butterfly butterflies get the crown
Yeah but
Then you go on the coral reefs you come across
These animals called mantis shrimp
Where they called metal like mantis like a praying mantis
It was from catches prey using an arm like a praying mantis has
Shrimps are barn mostly pretty small about the size of a finger some get to be as big as your forearm
Big big animals
My God they're so colorful know they are colorful though
Your hair look at this
It's like they're Electric
And I like turquoise
And their eyes are like a little cartoon eyes
Gigantic
Yeah they have two really big eyes right on the front and you said the dogs have
Two cones we have
How much does a butterfly have again
Butterflies V
Depends on the butterfly
Mantis shrimp have 16
Teen dies of receptors what would the rainbow look like to them
They live in very shallow water and so the water is pretty clear almost like
They would start the rainbow way way way inside where we see Violet they would say
Extraordinarily deep
Ultraviolet
And then they would go on through as several kinds of ultraviolet that's probably five or six kinds of ultraviolet
I never get to Violet with
Not reaching our colors
And go through Violet and violet
Blue and blue and blue green
Will they have those green green blue blue blue as well
Then they would go out to the Reds
So they would be about it at that as red as ice when I got to the red end but only in the bed
What are rainbow that must
Yeah
They have the most complicated visual system of any animals
Factor of two or
Wait wait wait
He said any
Do you mean it means you may not unequivocally any other animals that we know of
Has a visual system
Within 50%
It's complicated
Alright mantis
But you know on the other hand their brains are
Hiney so who knows
What the time in tubes they may not have the ability for
Save the beauty of the
No I don't I don't know they're there
Venice turn into violence
Around in Spanish
Chill things
That's what they do that's that's one reason
So fascinating about how to go around
What what are the shells on crabs other many shrimps shrimps
Octopuses octopuses
Yeah small ones
A good-sized mantis shrimp
Can break the wall of an aquarium
What really
Yeah there's a there's one thing California that can break
Accordion walls
A pugnacious Muhammad Ali seagoing animal with incredibly great visual set
Special thanks to Jim Briggs our engineer for the acquire session
Blast to Mark Shane giese for setting us off in this direction since Michael Kirchner in the young New Yorkers chorus
And John McClay and the grease Church Choral Society in those folks from the Collegiate Chorale midessa choirs to join.
Just to Alex Ambrose wqxr for getting everybody together
Thank you thank you
Okay so here we are back in the present 2018 that was how we left it
7 ish
Years ago and I always take a second sooner
Lorde sober look
At the Sanibel glorious achievement
What actually I get to we get to actually look at
Like I I I get to
You know what you meant
I did I met the chance I met the champ
And we shared a moment
That I certainly
That's coming up after the break
This is Amy lantinga from Boston Massachusetts
Radiolab is
It supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding
A Science and Tech
Technology
In the modern world
More information about
Sloan @www
Scott Sloan
Phone. Org
Hi this is Robert krulwich Radiolab is supported by Audible
As we continue to rip the rainbow two pieces in this episode of colors
Check out green mist
Exploded
Lessons from Neuroscience available at Audible
Start building a more accurate understanding of current breakthroughs in neuroscience
Since you have to start by
Shuttering popular brain myths
224 different lectures you can explore the Myriad topics in neuroscience like
Memory
Dreams
Consciousness
More
The result is an eye-opening adventure to the latest understanding of why the brain works
What's the way it does
Go to audible.com Radiolab or text
Radiolab to 500 500 for a free 30-day trial
Thailand
A free audio
Hi I'm Robert krulwich Radiolab supported by Casper
Do you know did you spend 1/3 of your life sleeping
With Casper you can make the most of your sleep on an outrageously comfortable mattress
Casper offers affordable prices hassle-free returns free shipping in the United States and Canada
Plus you can be sure of your purchase with Casper's 100 nitrous
Free trial
Right now
Get $50 towards select mattresses by visiting casper.com Radiolab
Have using Code radio
The lab at checkout
Terms and conditions
This is Radiolab on Jedi
Okay so we did the thing about the mantis shrimp
And
Partially because of Us Part 2
Because I think just the world was ready
The Mantis
Shrimp has become a little bit of a celebrity animal
Popular a little looking but elevated in cartoon
Has had its moments deservedly so when you think about what we know
What is rods and cones apparently are able to appreciate ya know you just want to close your eyes and imagine
Whatever it is that animal might be seeing just seven years ago
What's happens
The science keeps going
One of the things that happened recently in the last few years is that the people who study the mantis shrimp
They have released
More knowledge
About what it might be seeing
And
We're going to update you on that on that right now
But first can I just tell you something
Actually got to meet a mantis shrimp a cultist
Very very recently in Brooklyn and Coney Island
Oh yeah I have dreamt of this moment
My say
To the Mantis isn't one of these tanks
Producer Amanda narancic and I we found a fish store at Coney Island
Then actually had a real life mantis
Hahaha hello
Wow
It looks exactly as I imagined it
Intel wow they're so cool
Viewster tucked away in an aquarium in the corner of the Tsar dimly-lit shop at the shop is run by this guy
Excellence and this is your store
And how long have you been here for years
Chris cells are all kinds of
Signs of brittle starfish
Different kinds of clownfish
We have designer clownfish
Have you ever heard of designer clownfish
Have you heard this
Apparently these fashion designers are designing new clownfish
I also would like you have a Gucci
Yeah definitely
Just a little weird fish fact any Outback to the Mantis it was in the corner of the shop in this
Aquarium of reinforced glass
We actually got someone from Sri Lanka
This man
Sri Lanka
This is one of the stranger creatures I've ever seen
And have you ever seen one of these things of closer
Very very stunningly call my God
Oh my God lyrics just a minute
Particularly color
This is a particular guy that we saw he was
Hiding in a tube in the middle of the aquarium this was a peacock mantis shrimp cuz they're called
So if you can imagine
Like it's got if they're big first of all there like 7 in or so
So that's a big creature
And I
If you can imagine the head of a hermit crab
Painted like a peacock
Stuck on the bright green slithering body of a miniature dragon
That's what it looks like
Swiveling in all different directions and they have these really big googly eyes
Mantis shrimp
Sitting in a
Lucite tube
And it's looking out at the world
Treating the two blankets his home bro which we were headed in the wild
Especially looking for something to eat
You can see the voice you just heard that Tom Cronin are mantis expert from the last segment
He's your salesperson
Health science
He drove down from Baltimore to meet us and remember when he was telling us in the last segment
While ago that the Manchester these violent little bastards
They love to go around and kill things
Yes he was not kidding
I just want to look describes to you before we talk about the vision
I was staring
Hat
Peacock mantis shrimp huddled in the tube in an aquarium
Chris is about to
What's the poor little blue thing that you were about to put in
We're actually going to be a damsel fish
Is there Point Chris drops in this little blue fish looks a little bit like Dory from that movie
America's
Ingested into the mantle
Stanco Fishers in
Another fish is sensibly hiding in the back
Fish is hiding behind the tube at the fish should
Little Dory fish swim around for like
I don't know 5 minutes trying to find a way out
The whole time the Mantis was like I see, I'm just chilling in its 2 and then
Launched out of it to but then
Well that was just so sudden
Ice cream
You know cuz they have these claws on the front of their body that they used
Punch their prey and you can literally hear the snap
From across the room
And then he and this is sad he then took a lap and then came back in and just full
Just punch the fish a few more times
Oh wow that's
That's
It's a hard ending for that
Fort Collins now
It's one of those like nature moments where you're sort of amazed but you'll see
I want to cry
What's up
It's okay. Let's talk about efficient cleaning his eyes now
After it killed the Fish Shack went back to his tooth and started kind of like scrubbing his eyeballs with its little
Russia's important thing
Houses like did you see what I did to that fish
No checking my eyes
And ask her what those I see our notion of that is totally changed over the last few years so
That another marine biologist that Amanda talk to
Do you mind introducing yourself
To me like a my name is
Professor Rosalind this is what I do for a living
How do you want to do that
Now is good
Hello my name is Justin Rose wife
Marine biologist Anthony are scientist working on the Great Barrier Reef in Australia
Just for contact he Justin is the guy who basically put the Mantis on the map
Kia
He was the first guy his lab was the first laptop
To notice that they saw color at all
The University of Sussex
The 1995-96 apparently he had a
Colleague from West Africa who's wearing particular dress colorful traditional dress
She walks in his lab where he's got all the aquariums and immediately all the matches sugar rush to the beginning of the Korean War like hey
She walked in and went wild
What does that mean they started waving the appendages and
Shuffle that colors now that I know a little bit about mantis shrimp so I know exactly what they were saying to I reach would be entirely inappropriate
They were turned on
Colorful thing what should we do
So just was a guy that basically proved
Okay these animals have color vision
Fantasy color he confirm that with this
Experiment with colored containers you can get them to just
Bait Living Daylights Outta that thing that's colorful
Focus I love to smash
Sonia that was all background here's a new for me
Recently
Justin and his lab decided to ask a new question
He decided to say all right
These all these shrimp they have so many rods and cones in their eye
And by the way he would say they were 12
Which is still
4 times a week
How well do they use them
What that means how well do
Do they usually have them they must use them for something
Flexeril like if you're a scientist you can't just ask
Soon the day
See things the way that we see things don't mean you have to make sure
So I mean you know you is simple question to start off with
How well do they see different shades of the same color
Kind of thing that we do at the grocery store all the time
So you know if you got take a banana from her stool
Even if you pick one that's just going yellow
Still a little bit green not yellow enough to Yellow you know you use your eyes to make
Call wunderkinder shrimp
Can this animal distinguish
Between discharge of red and black China
Is blue and black
Can they make this fine distinction
I assume so
Yeah because they got all the rods and cones right if they weren't putting them to some extraordinary
Obvious use would be
More blue or more exactly what do you want to be sure
Mantis shrimp I'm going to give you
Food from this yellow thing
So what did it basically is that you would show the shrimp yellow light give him some food
Little lights
Food yellow light food they quickly learned that yellow means food
Cool so then he shows the shrimp
A blue light where there is no food and naturally the foods with the yellow it's not with the flu
Mosto
Most can do this
But then he would gradually make the blue side to non-food side
A little more yellow Berry graduate
He would shift the color from Blue
32 Bluegreen
Green
Then green yellow just to see if
The shrimp could tell the difference between yellow which means
Food
And yellow Greenwich
Doesn't mean food that's what we did and we expect
Get the mattress room to have
Tophatter
Distinction of that sort of level
I was surprised
To find that it was the worst animal on the planet so far Chester
No
Now you're exaggerating
Are champion
Of the rainbow
What's the worst creature ever test
The worst so
In other words
Nature gives them a panoply of choice and then they
Can't tell the difference that which the point of that there something wrong with this Theory
Can I say you come to my pants. I'm going to show you 50 shades of purple
Are you can only see three then what are you doing in there like I don't know what you did they seem to have the equipment to see all the purple
All the colors
All the Many Many Shades but
Still they got these amazing ice they just don't seem to use them
The way that we do
I don't understand that
Yeah okay
So this is why you need to stop thinking about
Coloring
What colors are according to just Marshall the basic thing to understand is that you don't actually see color with your eyes I mean you take
Taking the light with your eyes
But then the color is rain in Ukraine
And
They have these little insect braids
That don't
Seemed to do color the way that our brains to the right which way
See color is
If I see a thing
That's a somebody wearing a blue sweater walking down the street
Nice-looking
Lady or gentleman wearing a blue thing at my blue Furniture except in my eye
Gets really excited
Tell your brains going to see that blue
Ugly sweater right now
If that blue sweater had a little bit of red in it
The red
Photoreceptor would also buzz but not as loud
The ratio of those expectations
Gives my brain
Sensational
All right got a lot of blue a little bit of red what could that be
Wechat
That's what you end up seeing like your brain
Sarah Paints the gap
And that's how every animal on the planet Ceres color
Except for my
It's brain doesn't seem that interested
In
Painting Gap
So back in their segments when we said it sees a full
Throated
WYD
Boise spectrum of color
Like this
Static
Glorious Vision best rainbow view of all creatures on Earth that we said that's what he said
More
Variety in the rainbow then we can or than anybody
That was at
That was our thought we might need to amend that
How do you say
They still see
Colors that we don't see
But they might not just be seen as many colors as
Maybe there rainbow
Is more a series of
Of rather focused
Discrete bands of color with not allowed in between
I am very very
Extraordinarily puzzle
They're given the equipment that we used to
To see
Various
Shades of color and they don't use it to see shades of color what are they use it to see what they use it to
I mean this is all speculative but
Tom Cronin was telling us in the fish shop that liked
The science seems to be heading towards the
This idea
Did they use colors to communicate
If that's the case that you don't need to see all the colors they just need to see the ones that mean something
At least in the ultraviolet there's really good evidence that way it's not
It's not public so I don't want to talk about too much cuz it's not my work
But it looks like
Different parts of the UV have very different meanings like one part might being
Fear
Don't go there another lightning
Sex
I'd like to get to know more about this
Maybe another part means home who knows certainly very
Species to species were talking about the whole Rangers
At least 500 species start
You should have blank
Explanation is a bit simple
But what you're saying is that
Instead of seeing rainbows there
There are having a conversation with
Yeah maybe they just vocabulary
They have all these rods and cones so they can talk to the world not so they can
See the beauty
And this is complicated but they have that they can do polarized light
Oh
So hard to
But apparently thought that some species can Flash polarized light at each other as a way of communicating
Somehow I'm not even going to try and explain that cuz I don't get it
They are
An unbelievably
Amazing
And
Different cysts
Any other item on the
You got to ask yourself
Question
And I've been asking myself that question
Society is
And I guess I'm a
Cuz I still have knots
You could call me a failed
I don't think we're going to do that
Already have that is not really true
If you had to distill
The new information that you had that you have how would you
Explain it like
That the thing that we know now that we didn't know 10 years ago is
Is this
What I'm left with at the end of the day
I mean you know
Yeah it has eyes
Are we have eyes we assumed its eyes do for it would all right do for us but I
Apparently not and I don't think a choir is going to bridge this Gap that's what's called
Likes like every animal in the world lives with its own senses any world that is defined by those senses
Heading away it's one of those tragic things that is true
Try as you will
You will never know what a bat
Knows when it activates you will never know
What a deer
When it looks out if we know that deer don't
CR and that's why all the Hunters wear bright orange and the others don't see that range do they see more of something else I don't know
Baidu what's an envelope
It's umw
It's a great word whose else
It's the word that says
That you are limited by what you can
Can
Feel touch
Mlc
Yeah
On some level I mean I feel like that's a problem that exists even between people like I have regular
Thomas with my wife Round Lake
That's not blue and she said yes totally blew it all the time
What you're seeing right now
I know
That's the lonely part
The unlonely part
Is that you can try
Yeah
That is
It is really fun to try
The original mantis shrimp episode was pretty
This by Tim Howard and Pat Walters
And updated by a producer Amanda around check recording the choir the second time around
Sound and to Chris Martin from creative grandma and the young New Yorkers chorus
And they have quite a range
Pancetta
Thanks for listening
One final note
After we wrapped up this episode
We learned that
One of the members of our shrimp choir
Baritone by the name of Daniel Thompson
Was one of the five people who died in the tragic
Helicopter
Accident
That happened over the East River
This past Sunday night
Wechat Radiolab or devastated to hear this news and we're sending our thoughts
His family into the rest
To the choir
We would like to dedicate this episode to him
I am Robert krulwich Radiolab is supported by Casper and their experts who make quality mattresses
The Cradle your body in all the right places
Get $50 towards select mattresses by visiting casper.com Radiolab
Add using Code Radiolab at check
Terms and conditions
Supply
Hi I'm Robert krulwich Radiolab is supported by Audible
As we explored more how the world is saturated in color
Soft shoes too violent stains
Check out green mist
Exploded
Lessons from neuroscience available at Audible
Explore the Myriad topics for Neuroscience 224 lectures about myths of the brain
Go to audible.com Radiolab
Trial and a free audiobook