Are you awake
Listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
So we can start with a story for my producer Pat Walters
About a couple
Oh my word
Okay so
I mentioned a couple episodes ago
By the way this is Chad Radiolab.
Will be bringing back some episodes back to the flow from time to time episodes that we haven't
Stop thinking about the field true or to us now than before maybe the opposite
New episodes
We still end up getting two fights with people about and a couple years ago we ran a story about a guy named Kevin
A little bit more recently hello Robert are you there
Yes snake gentle be here in just a sec
Robert sapolsky Stanford who
College and I have had on the show many times
Seriously would have booked
Which makes an argument that really tries to kind of just explode
That story
Anyway that we found her dancers
It was just my hunch
That it plays near a lot of your button
Sure does
So what we did was we sent him that piece having listened to it
NXT will do now is Replay that piece and then at the end
We'll come back and
A little bit of a fight about it
So we can start
With a story for my producer Pat Walters about a couple
Oh my word
The lady and Shannon
This is the guy I don't need you to introduce yourself that's usually the thing we do but we're not dumb people who you are
We're going to call him Kevin Kevin yeah yeah yeah that's
Yeah that's my name
That's suspicious at all it's not his real name
No make sense why we're not using his real name
Okay but this one starts a few summers ago
It was July 2006
Dan and Kevin went home
And
Some people
You don't know
Chill up and maybe I'll start with you
When they show up at the door
So we were it was we were getting ready to go down the shore was a Friday so we so we're in the kitchen and and they
Come to the back door but I thought that I thought they were fundraising
I thought they might even firemen just by you not that the blue the blue shirt and then realize that
That they were
Law enforcement
Two women and two men
I'm around that you know the side of the house and they show us their badges
Are they cops
Next door neighbor Homeland Security
They took me outside and they asked me to stay in the kitchen
And they had a woman with me
I didn't know it was going to nobody said anything to me sing to you on the porch
Meanwhile
When they when they showed up
I got to the door
I said you know why we're here I said yeah I do I was expecting you
I showed him everything was
This story about Kevin and his wife Janet inspired us to do the entire hour cuz it when was
Basic things that we do
Is we judge
You just want another judge what's right
What's wrong with this story of the two that follow
They will make you judge how you judge
At least they have that effect on us
Can I show
Blink
Omron arm Robert krulwich mogul
Baidu
You should know that this show contains some graphic
Difficult descriptions in a few
Teaspots
Turn on the mood or if you have kids around
You might want to sit this one out
Okay so what happened in that first scene and what happens next
Only makes sense
If we go back there
The first
About 15 years
It's just an ordinary day Kevin
Going home from work
And
I was
Driving home
Going about 65 70 in the fast lane
When
Suddenly
There was a thump
In my chest then he just that I hate voting
After that he said suddenly he had this thickness in my tongue in my throat and a foul taste in his mouth
Then
My hearing
Spit it out
Enneathought
Its back
If I did come to
He sees his car smashed into the side of an
I do recall the officers, you've been in an accident you better than any members want them insisted that he soon
Smelled alcohol
And I was talking through clenched teeth cuz I had bit my tongue and
And my cheeks
I was saying over and over again
I had a seizure
Kevin Scott epilepsy
He's had it since he was a teenager
But two years before this all happened he had surgery to remove the part of his brain that was causing the seizures
End
It seemed to work to be doing great eventually wasn't having seizures anymore
Until suddenly with you
He was
Lost your license I lost my license for a year things have kind of taken a nosedive like here he is he's 35
5 years old I'm living with my brother I'm divorced
And I have to call my Daddy and ask him now
To drive me to and from work
And you saying
I need to do something this is not sustainable
Now don't don't need that
So I walked into the office at HR person where he works
Export a list of all the employees
Give me a list of everybody who were the front so she pulled it up I go down the list and I get to Janet Woodruff Bloomfield
Only one asteroid close to me 5 minutes away
So I walk
To work you
Knocked on the on the wall
And
Introduce myself
Like hey my name is Kevin
House of work here
I got this thing though
He's kind of awkward I can't drive
And I was wondering if
You give me a ride
And
She said yes
I really pass by his street I mean on the way to work so it was
Right on History pretty much but I made it clear and you know I'll do it when I can start talking finding out
Little bit more about each other
Notice pretty quickly we like the same music that was unique because I sort of
Like music that was probably more in his error Kevin was 7 years older than what kind of music are you listening to
Jackson Browne mostly lie detector on James Taylor
Bonnie Raitt it's a little you know Elton John
They found themselves
Sing along to the lyrics
You cannot sing
With somebody
Day in and day out
And not have something
We want them as a spring came you know it's getting nice out so now it's like well let's not go home as well for a beer after work we're becoming
We'd like each other over Kevin
It was a little more serious than that
I'm thinking about her and I'm starting to wake up at night and what day in May is Jenna is dropping him off
Turn stir and he says I really appreciate what you've done for me let me take you to dinner
Dentist
Sure so
May 30th
Highlawn Pavilion
Nicest restaurant in town so your friend takes you to a 4-star restaurant you're thinking right away
He thinks this is a date come on now I'm panic-stricken we have our dinner we leave
She drops me off and I handed her the poem
What is the poem say
You still have it
Yeah I do
Okay this is a little slower
Each time we sing on the way home
I pray that traffic backs up
So we can sing together
Just a little longer
And the harmony can go on forever
And each time you reach my door
I feel robbed
Because we're always admit song
Amidst thought
Only he gets out and goes inside and try things awesome I gave her the phone she's going to be so
Smitten with me and you go home and what
Want to throw up
I just thought I'd got it you know
Next day I just looked at him and said listen we got to clarify this
This is clearly just going to be a friendship
He was 7 years older than me he had to
Your brain
You know surgery he has epilepsy
He's divorced he has two children
Try and try and he's just like
I'm not asking you to marry me
I'm asking you go out on a few dates
I can go out with me like four times in the next 6 months
I'm ahead of the game just handled it
Then I don't think it was long at all I can't even remember but it wasn't long at all before we were like
A couple
And Kevin I'm Dopey
Ethiopian love romantic things for her all the time
Flowers poems and illustration of the Jackson Browne cover Anthony year
All the while Kevin is having seizures since the car accident
It was a point where we were obviously Dayton
Japanese make his bed and
He said she pulled up the pillowcase
Covered with blood stain
1 2 3
4 5 6 7 and count the number of seizures that I had
In between my tongue and bled I knew nothing about
Epilepsy
I never seen anybody have a seizure in my past those would have been big red flags that I would have just walked away but
I just went with it
And they both want with it
50 years
Until finally Kevin agenda side
This is not what I wanted to be done with it
I just needed to be done with it
To reschedule a brain surgery
Which sounds like a big deal and obviously it is but they had every reason to think that this wouldn't change him
I honestly thought that he was going to come out of it fine a better
Quebec map in the first time giving head actually gone through a brain surgery much like this one once before
Any come out
Pretty much the same guy you still himself
In fact
He made sure of it
I had a I was awake for the surgery
That's crazy
It was had to be awake
Had to do with me
Kevin is a musician
And the doctors told him they said that if I lost anything I was going to lose my appreciation for music
That it would be like music with the white noise
Pasadena now for me music was
Is part of my personality
It was how I cope with
My Darkest
Moments in dealing with epilepsy and seizures
At 18 years old
I have a seizure
I take whatever Monica and I find a place
Decent Reverb somewhere and be right where I needed to be
I didn't want to lose that part of me
Do I have the doctors were doing the brain surgery that had his head open bathroom to sing remember what you saying
End of the Innocence
Some James Taylor
While he's saying they would tickle
Different parts of his brain
If you ever touch the part that made him stop singing
They say okay that's a part we cannot take out
Wow
And in the end I think they ended up taking out like 4 and 1/2 cm
Like a little bit of a bigger than a golf ball well but afterwards that he was recovering the I had my keyboard in the
And I tried playing right away data data data data.
It works
Partying that you really cared about
Was still there exactly after the first surgery so
I thought well you know
None of the country's second surgery he's already been down this road
We're fine
And after that second surgery
Editing by Janet didn't have her brother
Sneak my my keyboard up to the room again very very adamant that he wanted that keyboard
Just noodles a couple of notes played a couple of things and it was like okay I'm there
Tell me I was ready to go
To you go home and like
It seems to have worked
Yeah for seizures go we thought okay this is it we're home free and I was just happy to have some normalcy
But then in the winter by beginning the middle of January
Kevin knows he wanted to eat my physical appetite
A lot more than usual. Like insane
Or maybe a snack that was it but now I could eat the couch
It just was I thought it was not him normally but you know you're like okay
But then the piano
You play the piano for hours
Sing songs to sing in the car together he has stuck on a piece
He would play it for hours
How many hours
Eight nine
And then
No sex
You know we were happy
Healthy couple
Kevin's nodding
What was abnormal was it was it was anywhere clearly wasn't like all we're in the supermarket let's have sex here
I mean it wasn't like that but I mean it was like
I could just walk in the kitchen I'm an out-of-work and helical you let's go here
Which structure is weird
But then again we were thinking you know let's try to have a family make things confusing
And what's in that it wasn't like any of this stuff was out of character exactly
Fact
It was all stuff.
She liked about him yeah that was all turned up to 11 all the things that were wonderful
Became tours
And that's pretty much where things are at
When is federal agent showed up in July 2000
I was just completely blindsided
I said you know why we're here I said yeah I do I was
Expecting you
Kevin contagions upstairs
I took him right into here where my computer was
And they arrested him
For what was on that computer
I gave it up to him
Right away
Warning this next batch
Which contains some graphic
I mean I I hadn't
I don't know if I am fully like
I think I had just like black c********* be this kind of vague
Thing that meant
Someone younger than 18
But then I read some of the
The court documents in
They were like
Toddlers
Hair pic videos of
2 3 in
4 year olds
There their ID sites had the most
Despicable disgusting
Thanks
You can imagine
Infants on throw
Yeah pretty
Preteen in
Pre-adolescent up in at adolescence
Did it right and you bought this
And put them on your
Computer eye
Yeah
Yeah it it it bothers me
It bothers me
Like
Like I said initially it was and I was just your basic your basic
You know how to roast heterosexual Playboy like Penthouse like
Sites
And then
Windows would just start to open up pretty soon he says
He's going every
It was gay sex they were for me that there was due is bondage there was
Defecation sex there was a********* is Zeno sex
I went everywhere
That a button came up
The Porsche
I still don't understand it
I still I still don't understand
He said Disturbed you and you feel terrible. I just like Wonder like how do you
Do you tell yourself like that wasn't me like how do you
Explain it to yourself to
So that you can kind of
And I'm not feel like you're
As bad as
The person who goes there
Without a brain injury
You know like
Say that again I guess I'm just wondering I don't know like knowing that the thing that you did and it sounds like obviously you know that that was bad
Ever the wrong thing
Terrible thing
But it was
It was you who did it or was it not
I don't know you going to mean
No it was it was me who did it but it was me
With a
Complete lack
Under a logical control
Not I mean I know
I know who I am
I did idiotic things that I couldn't stop myself from doing I didn't want to do it
It would be nice where would be 456 hours of going to the same site and end in
Downloading one or two files and then deleting them
Going back
A minute later
Downloading the same files deleting them
I would download those files a dozen times and delete him a dozen times cuz I didn't want to be there knew I shouldn't be there in
And couldn't help myself from going back
I'm not an idiot
I mean I'm on the smart guy I'm not an idiot
I know I had no control
Ineptitude arguing Court
Can we plead guilty but at the sentencing hearing he asked the judge to be lenient
Arguing isn't played that the person who did all those things in some sense
Wasn't him
It was some other part of
His brain that he couldn't control
Play the hearing he called one witness
Orrin devinsky I'm a neurologist and epilepsy specialist at NYU Medical Center
Even treating Kevin for decades 20 20 some odd years
And he says as soon as he found out what Kevin had been doing had a terrible sense of
Of responsibility this is because the brain surgery
The surgery on recommended he have
Target in court that this was not Kevin's fault
I remember looking at those agents right in their face
And sing to them and to the judge
This could be anybody this could be those agents judge this could be you this could be me this could be anybody
And we would have no control over what we did
Explain to the court what the biology was
That the way the brain is working that is it there parts of our brain that are way deep down
The control
Base desire
Mike hunger
Sex keep the faith alive but it's teeming with the nastiest thoughts we all have these crazy thoughts in her head
Most of us are kept in check because there are other parts of our brain that sit on top
And act like a lid
Bank Evans case
The brain surgeon you did that surgery
Remove part of that filter
And suddenly the cork was off I mean it was just no lid
On his sexual desires he's a scientist
Condition for a long time difference. In monkeys
The rhesus monkeys when the monkeys would lose roughly the same part of the brain that Kevin laws they became very hyper sexual males
It would only previously be sexually involved with females
Now we're ten times more sexually active with both males and females
David feels too meme
Feels to me like there's a
It would be a brighter line
Before
Kids
You know
I think
There is a line for quote-unquote normal individuals
But in a brain disorder case those lines get blurred
And he told the court
That's what happened here was black and white can with sick
End behavior without his control
Well
That's not what
The facts showed
In this case
This is Lee Vartan what's the
We saw no evidence of impulsivity
He says if you're claiming that he had no control that his brain made him do it then how come he had all this c********* on his home computer
I believe it was
52 videos and 125 images on his work computer images
0 videos of child Pornography on his work computer
And you worked a lot
He held down a job he was working everyday
If you truly lack impulse control I would think
You would see
Child pronography on both computer
Nobody argued back was
What with the lid on at work and off at home seems to me to be an easy out
The answer is that this is common with neurologic
Disease
They tend not to be
24/7
If it's taken to make tourettes some people when they're engaged and playing sports
They tend not to have pics
Redlands didn't ground for distress
They do that.
So you could say well-dressed clearly isn't a neurological disorder but no Tourette's is a neurologic disorder we understand
Some of the brain things that go on Tourette's
The prosecution didn't buy it
Thought it was hogwash
What was hogwash was his level of certainty
Breskis and ask the Kevin be sent to prison for 5 years
Isn't paying for c********* you supporting industry
It does terrible things to kids
Kevin Oakes YouTube or jail time altogether and instead you placed on house arrest
Casper Janet
Rid of beer breath
Captain imagine that
You are in chocolate. Like
Uganda City lawyer
One of the questions he asked was this marriage going to survive this
And I said
I don't know
And at that point understand I didn't even know
The level of picture
But she said the moment she heard orange say that this was a brain disorder with the name
Kluver bucy syndrome once I was able to
Get that for me
A click like
You complain that we have these experts saying that
It was a disease and I kept thinking they'll understand
Give him some medication and dances
It was like flipping a switch
It's exactly what it was was like yeah yeah and back
He's Able I was able to sit and watch a movie with
You know normal
Did it actually says in a lot of ways those few months
Between the arrest
In the sentencing hearing
Baton
The best months in a marriage he now is just so much easier,
You could we just talk
The hearing took about 3 hours and when it was over the judge took a recess
Winter Chambers
When she came back
She delivered your decision
And we'll hear that decision when we come back
Traffic break
This is Amanda Darby
Calling from Rockville Maryland
Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloan @www. Sloan
. org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help this summer I'm hosting the show
And I request for those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
We're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments
Brilliance
Basically I want to hear about those times when I did something
It just means you bring back and say whoa
Maybe it was the moment that our kids you've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed are ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the
Epic moments where
Kid does something super smart but it doesn't have anything to do with the test
If you have a story with us
Go to radiolab.org Brilliance and record a short audio message
Fan that's radiolab.org / brilliance
Thank you so much
Hey I'm Jared I'm Rod this is Radiolab we're revisiting Pat Walter story about Kevin and when we left
The judge was just about to render her decision
She actually wouldn't talk to me for the story but I have the transcript from the
Hearing
And if you remember the prosecutor Bolivar 10 was asking for 5 years
63 months
Meaning no jail time there's no way this is clear-cut
Can use with the judge.
She says I do agree with orange it is a neurological disorder real question we can't be held fully responsible for
Behavior she was getting
And she said the prosecution did have a point that
He was very much in control of his impulse
At least some of the
I took the question for the judge was how does the legal system assign blame
When a person is sometimes can selves and in control
Sometimes not
This is a crime she said
A crime which ultimately leads to children being hired and considering that you did have moments where you were in control
But in those moments
Responsibility
You could have done something
Girl ask for help
You could have told the people around you what you were doing so even if you couldn't have stopped
Takers.
She made it very clear
That we have to do something here
Sentence
26 months
At a federal prison
And 25 months house arrest
And I I believe I believe that she she was she was fair
And I believe she was compassionate
About a week before Christmas
In 2008
Introverted person
How long was he in jail for about 2 years
And she was even though the judge said you know
He is responsible to that
Change her attitude toward him at all now
Totally stuck together she doesn't it
Pretty much every weekend
The whole time
I knew the rude and I had my own little routine down
In between visits in the notes he could send me mail that a store where he could get some cards
Super Walmart
And he would like alter them
I've ever remember the very first card I got
It was this very you know
Beautiful supposedly supposed to be beautiful but it was like you know if you need anything
You anything at all just let me know and then he writes
Of course if it's pressing you might want to ask someone else cuz you can wait 24 months
And I remember getting that and just laughing and then that became our thing like listen this is a horrible situation
But we're going to make the best of
Tell me a little bit about like
Where things are at now are almost normal
I'm still
On probation he's home he's working
Life is going on we have our normal routines
Can still take those medicines that
Keep that other part of him in check
I have no libido at all
But
I know who I am
I know what I am
I'm disturbed by that portion of my life
But I'm trying I'm trying to move on
Producer Pat Walters
Sew-in no nothing about your reaction to that will be which is my hunch is author Roberts
That it's sort of
It plays near a lot of your butt
Where does yeah
And know why we always felt
The at the end of the story the sentence that Kevin gets from the judge was this kind of
Interesting in Nuance balance
Between
You know the idea that he just had a brain disease and the idea that there's some still Center of personal responsibility involved
All right out of the gate sapolsky had a different reaction, Paul
Underlying worldview
Really
Yeah completely
And for him it all centered around that sort of
Key argument
This way the judge
That's some of the time he can control these urges
And some of the time he can't
The example and there was that never once it worked if you do anything like that and DFCS
You spend hours each night at home
And the fact that he could control it and other circumstances
Does that mean there is a separate me inside there
It's able to get to the control panel some of the time but not others
And thus
That's
Punishable
Yeah it said it's like
He's in a kind of
Pitched battle
With some
Inner urge that he has maybe two biological urge
But
Sometimes he wins maybe in the morning when he sets
The coffee and he's like nicely sugared up
But then at night we all know this when we get tonight or if we're tired by brains are tired
And we the it comes out a tiny little bit well let's
Let's translate what you just said
Industry nuts-and-bolts biology
Your frontal cortex
Which is making you do the harder things when's the right thing to do is one of the most
Expensive parts of the brain to operate
And when
You're starting to get hungry
Are you starting to get tired
Your frontal cortex doesn't work as well
And that's simply why
We have less regulation of our behavior in at night than in the morning
And the perfect neurological example where nobody would invoke Free Will in this one is he
You look at somebody with alzheimer's disease
Beverly stage Alzheimer's disease
They sure was sundra a sundowner syndrome
Which is in the morning they can tell you what their name is
And by night they can't tell you
And the next morning they can tell you again
Wow
Are we here sort of
A choice okay so they know their name and if they're not telling you at night they know their name they can tell you
Username in the morning if they're not telling it to you at night they're choosing not to
No
What happens at night is blood sugar levels drop and the brain is tired and the frontal cortex which has to do the
Like what was my name again with three-and-a-half remaining neurons
Can't do it as well
Nobody looks at that and says there's volition
They can do it part of the day
They should be expected to be able to do it and that's that. That's because it's a different issue I mean this isn't what you're talking about memory
Okay so let me let me
Let me go through a sequence here that I am they obviously
Prepared for the occasion
In the in the Kevin segment they made mention of the syndrome that he has which
Call the kluver Bucy syndrome
And this was first shown in the 1940s you going to monkeys
And you take out the same part of the frontal cortex
As they did with Kevin and you kept monkeys that eat themselves into obesity now they can't stop eating
Affair hyper-sexual male trying to mount everyone and everything on Earth
Can right off the bat we see some broad similarities haha you will say though
But Kevin has a moral system Kevin has
Meta control Kevin as we saw
Give control in some circumstances but not in others
We've left the world of blameless monkeys far behind
Yes yes yes yes goodbye but we have not you've got a monkey there
Who's got frontal damage and now is hyper sexual
He's attempting to mount infants he's attempting to mount water bottles in his cage
Completely out of control
But nonetheless
He doesn't try to mount the alpha male
Obviously what we have here is a monkey who has free will
Because of some circumstances
He could not do this
Bad inappropriate thing cuz he's got free will Sumter
No that's ridiculous okay let's
It's not that he
Could control his behavior
Some of the time it said in this instance
He was under the influence of something else
That he couldn't control
Fear
Fear of the alpha male activation of fear circuits override the feeble attempts of those for
And a half remaining from Ponder on interesting regulation in one circumstance but not in others not because there's
Free will or rotten choices or bad values
Is biologically broken system manifest is broken.
Under some circumstances but not others and
There's a logical biological explanation for why you get those exception
Okay
But you're talking about monkeys and one situation we're not closer to home now
So you sit down somebody with damage to the ventromedial prefrontal cortex
And you put
The frontal lobe damage patient now in a circumstance where they're in
A situation
Where
There's a smarter more disciplined better pay off thing to do
And they can do it just fine
But then you get them emotionally aroused over something or you get them tired they're horrible terrible compared
Two regular folks
Another words
We've just progressed from okay the monkey if it's scared of the alpha male okay
Fear
Can override the neurons that has remaining in there and they're swamped
Now we've seen in a human more in general
Strong emotions can override
But that so so far what you told me though
Is
Sometimes I have the resources to choose and sometimes I don't but it's about the resource
For the choice
Doesn't
Not exist
In there
Next Step
Next Step Closer in
So for my money one of them
I even have a clipboard here I've been sitting in front of me that's how much I prepared for this
Okay here's an example
You take a Drudge
And
Like this
Classic
Important study
And you look at the single biggest predictor
Of whether or not this parole board judge and this was
The whole panel of judges
Whether they will vote for somebody being paroled or not
The single best predictor was how many hours has it been since the judge has eaten
What you mean is that a hungry judge will not give parole to someone but a full
And happy tummy tea in the judge will make it make the judge more gentle
You look at the study and right after a meal
Are convicts had about a 90% chance of being paroled
And right before meal they were down to about a 10% chance and was a virtually straight line going down X
Messed up
And you know
The single biggest
Is Purdue episode up the study up and it turns out if the judge was making the decision
Right after lunch when they're full
Parolees had about a 60%
Chance of getting pearls okay not as bad as you say
But
If the judges were making the decision right beef
For the next meal like when they were hungry
Parolees had close to a 0
Percent chance of getting parole
What's interesting about
Number one the biology make
Perfect sense
What are you doing there when you are a judge trying to judge somebody from a completely different world from you to reach
Your point of deciding
There's mitigating factors you're trying to take their perspective you were trying to
Think about the indirect ways that Lit
You're using your frontal cortex
And when you're hungry
And your frontal cortex isn't is working as well it's easier to make a snap emotional judgment
Is person's rotten
The second amazing thing which exactly addresses this issue is
You get that judge
2 seconds after they made that decision
You sit him down at that point and say hey so why did you make that decision
And their get a quote on a no Immanuel Kant or Alan dershowitz that you they're going to
Post hoc
Come up with an explanation that has all the pseudo trappings of
Free Will and volition and in reality it just rationalization
Totally biologic
No no that's you lose me on the word totally
Okay so it's met muchly biological mostly biological I might I might meet you halfway
Totally know
Why does it have to be entirely why do we have to go out like all the way
Because if you're not going to go
All the way
Here's the things that
You're Siri
I'm just going to jump in here because this part of the conversation got a little dance
And a long butt
Sapolsky basic
Point was that you just have to look at
The story of Ark
Scientific discoveries
500 years ago we would have said the epileptic seizure was
Like bad
Demonic possession
Nanana we learned that biologic
Up to the mid 1950
If you're like adolescent child suddenly started having hallucinations and hearing voices me thought disorder
And you would say you the mother of this child would say where did this disease come from
And the best of science at the time have an answer they would say
You it's your fault it was cold schizophrenogenic mothering a mothering style that generated schizophrenia
You cause your child schizophrenia
And then in the mid-fifties the first antipsychotic drugs were developed in it emptied out the psychiatric
Warts all over the country and everybody in the field said
Oh my God
It's a biochemical disorder
He says same thing happened with dyslexia we used to think it was just kids who are lazy oh that biological also
His contention is it this is just going to keep happening like a science progresses one by one all of the things that
We think are under our control
That we should control and that if we don't can be blamed for
One by one
All the things you can get chalked up two screw-ups in our biology
Scrubs
That we couldn't have control even feed wanted to
So what you're going to have to do with that point
Is
Either say
Starting tonight at midnight there will never be a new scientific finding pertinent to this area we've learned
Everything there is
Or you're going to say
Free Will is just a biology that we haven't learned yet
Do you in your heart
In your deep in the even the center of your alike in that
Do you really believe this
Do you really think second
Not for a second
And that's the whole thing
This is like my like huge conundrum I have like zero belief in Free Will at this point
Yet at the same time I cannot for a second imagine
What the world is supposed to look like with people believe in there is no free will I don't know how to imagine it
And I'm constantly this hypocrite
On this terrible hypocrite
Because like I'll put on like my blue t-shirt instead of my gray t-shirt one morning
And later in the day someone will say how well
Nice t-shirt and all say
Thanks
Oh my God the hypocrisy of it here I am taking credit for it
And that circumstance I'm not able to stop and say well actually
I have photoreceptor
That
No because of this Gene variant that she invariance in my robe. Saint-jean
So that I'm particularly good at noticing colors
Combination since I can get the matching ad
Oh I pick the fresh fruit here because my olfactory receptors allow me to like
Be able to smell the pineapples that are fresh
And the luck of my socioeconomic status has me in like some like organic market and gives me that like ability to
Did you do that while listening to like fake Peruvian music playing in the back at no you say
When they say you really know how to
Pick good pineapple
And I say
Thanks
On the intellectual side I mean if you believe that every Behavior not just of Kevin
Because what you're really saying is that the Deep lessons the Kevin story
Is it everyone is okay
All of us are Kevin all the time
I'm at anything our worst and our best behavior
That everything we choose
To do
Is
In some sense
Chosen for us the if you knew enough
Stuff about
Anyone
You know what they're about to do next
Yeah
No
But I readily admit I flag in Plano
Get on board with this
This
At least we've done it in a few round
What is we are able to do it when you look I'm teen and I don't want to be a futurist here but
When you look 500 years ahead
Let's say that the things keep progressing in the way that you imagine where we just keep etching liked or chipping away at the sides
Definition of will
Free will
What
Do we do in that point do we not hold anyone accountable for anything but we simply
Prescribed
Treatments
What what is that world look like to you
Treatments and or constraints
You fix the things you fix
And the ones that can't be fixed
You can stream things of the damage can't be done
But it's done in a
And Away a car with
Broken brakes is incredibly Danger
Happy on the streets
And if you can't fix the brakes you put the car in the garage
And
You intervene
But you don't invoke a concept of punishment of the car in there
And if at that point you say oh my God that's so dehumanizing to be that mechanistic
That's a hell of a lot better than sermonizing people into having free will over stuff that they have no control over
We've done it
People with treatment-resistant epilepsy
You're not allowed to drive
But you don't sit there and say
They deserve
Not to be able to drive you don't get like moms of corydoras Yahoo peasants cheering
When is the driver's licenses are burned
No
It's not their fault that they have this thing called a seizure
Nonetheless
If it's uncontrollable they shouldn't be driving cars
And we have a therapeutic intervention here that's completely outside the realm
A blame
Justice
Deserve
Anything like that
Let's go back to camp
At the end of the story
Pat ass
Kevin what what what since he makes of his
Punishment
I assume a that you wouldn't have punished him
Right
You would recommend
But you notice what Kevin says Kevin says
Well I thought the judge was
Was a good judge and was
Fair Fare he called her Fair
So isn't it
Troubling to you
That this person
Somehow
Was able to
Feel blameworthy
I guess
But what this justice system is doing is it sort of saying
You were bad
Maybe I was
I feel sorry I've got remorse
That's okay
And now we give you
Your freedom
But there's been a
It's been a conversation here
About
You are morality you're in a morality but you do not spare only want to have
I wondering whether that's a healthy
Healthy
Mental healthy healthy or slightly healthy oil bad by saying thank you to your to your
What's your shirt of choice
So there is some human need here I don't know where you might quote by Logic or not but
There's something's justice system is addressing that you seem to be
You seem to be taking out of the system
Yeah
Punishment is pleasurable
It feels good to do the righteous thing
And it feels good to do that in a punishing blaming way
If you're brought up culturally as most of us are too
Have this notion of like
Agency
But I think I think of what Robert Mike
Did this Robert krulwich Robert
Might be
I think Robert let me know if you if you if it correctly from wrong
Is it it doesn't just feel good personally it's good for Society on some level
Do we want to live in a society where the concept of justice has been tossed out and more in a mechanistic
Take place
Well how about taking it further
Don't we need to have belief in a moralizing and punishing God because why else would people be nice to
To each other
I don't need to take it all the way there
In their wake God like that they rule over us I wanted to say
Setup.
You're right they work better as soon as you introduce the possibility of punishment in two economic games you
You evolve cooperation
You do cross-cultural studies and the more there's a belief in a punching Hell in a culture the more generous people
Foreign economic games yes that stuff works
Yet
Over and over
We've learned at least one domain
Where we step outside of all of that
The epilepsy example
When nobody thinks of it in terms of it being like
Justice is being meted out when the driver's license
Being taken away
Yep 500 years ago
Somebody who would have been just as smart and chest is introspective in chest is reflective and maybe even had like a
Nice bleeding-heart liberal NPR tote bag
Would have said if you're sad about this but that you told them to
Oh my God I thought we were on fire and that person nonetheless would have said this is tragic and
I feel so sorry for their family and all of that
But who told them to go sleep with Satan
Waylon living this way is there anything in the Kevin patch
Walter store is there anything anyone in there
Who is being
Harmed ore
Hurt by what you heard now
Well
He's paying a price
His wife paid a price
Shame
Imprisonment
The terrible price here
For what was simply
The biological problem
Still very hard to imagine
A world in which
You don't get pissed off at people who do like
Crummy thing and where you don't feel vaguely pleased when somebody says well nice t-shirt so what you just said is that
The feelings that you have about
The story of the
Lost to her of her husband
I love
Shame of being put away for awhile
You think that
Later on when the
Deeply
Biological explanation for this gets fully revealed
In a hundred years say people will be able to listen to
The story we just heard
I'm think
If they only knew
Absolutely
Big thanks to Robert sapolsky for
Chatting with us his latest book is called behave
The biology of humans at our best and worst
Which has
An extended argument about how there's no such thing as free will definitely worth reading
Call behave
Thanks also to Pat Walters for
Reporting a story and
Kevin for allowing us to
And we will see you next time
Hi this is Will's odd but I'm I'm calling from Sunny Seattle Washington
Radiolab is produced by jet album Rock
Dylan Keith is our director of sound design store on Wheeler a senior editor
Staff includes Simon Adler David cable Tracy hunt Matt kielty Robert krulwich
Annie McEwen Latif Nasser
Melissa O'Donnell
Aryan whack and Molly Webster
Help from
So Empower Rebecca Jason mcgarr fatalii Phoebe Wang and
Katie Ferguson
A fact check
Is Michelle Harris