Northland listening to Radiolab
Radiolab from WNYC
NPR
Ladies Vagina please welcome to the stage
Young Jedi been wrought iron Robert rovics Radiolab band a while back we were on stage
We're alive
At the Paramount Theater in downtown Seattle with several years ago he called that show apocalyptical cuz it was about
Ending different kinds of endings of different things
All of these incredible musicians and video artists
Then we had a huge yes
Paw Patrol all of which you can see on the video on my website at radiolab.org but we're going to do for you now
Is play you part of that original show
Actually the first
Story in that show which is about the end
Of the dinosaur
Because we have news to tell you about that story and it's a verisimilitude
So we're going to go first play you part one of our show about dinosaurs
Let's go back to the
Paramount Theater NC
Started off for us
You're at Purdue University and I study impact craters among other things
Create impact craters with his mind but he and his colleagues have been investigating this moment
Almost as if it were a crime scene that happened not 60 million years ago but yesterday
In the story that they put together it's more than just interesting it's frankly
Twinkly terrifying
Specific
Take for example
The seemingly simple question of when when did it happen if you don't mean like the year
That would be a little too specific
No I don't know if you remember but Jay got even more specific
Chicken at
This is a casual question that I threw up
Listen to his
By the way do we know anything about seasons was it so warm
Actually it was between well this is a bit of a stretch but it was sometime between June and July
You so specifically how would you know that
The reasoning is week we can for example this is the this is the first surprise kind of controversial ideas
The basic ghost
Json
Scientists have found some Paulo
In rocks which date from that
Two different kinds of pain
And based on an analysis of those two kinds of pollen
We know that the impact took place between the flowering of the lotus in the flowering of the waterline
Lotus you see flowering on the left
The water lily flowering on the right you can see this if you look at our video online
Fossils found at the impact site that had pollen from both of these flowers in the same Rock
Would suggest
The impact did in fact take place
Somewhere between June and July
It's one of those things in Geometry tweet
We got a glimpse of a moment far far back in time
Let's go deeper into that Moana
Let's collectively ruined our minds back in time 10 million
As of years into the past 66 million years ago to be precise
There they are Majestic beasts hanging out on the plains
Eating their Lotus leaves sometime in
June June 17th let's say
Everything on this day pretty much normal this particular
People day was no different than any of
Millions and millions of previous days as far as the dinosaurs were concerned but if there were any astronomer
Set the time with their work they might have had some inkling that something was coming because
Had they looked up we would have seen a Time Little Dot of light in the sky
Where is planets the Moon
Move with respect to the Stars this would have had a constant bearing
An old Seaman could tell you that
But if you see something constant bearing that's on a collision course with you
Nothing of course
Is Arash
Zeroing in on the Earth
I want to say that we do know quite a bit about
This asteroid
From the size of the creator
And from the amount of certain minerals found at the impact site we know that the asteroid was roughly
6 miles wide
And then again roughly 6 miles long which makes it approximately the size of Manhattan Island
Mount Everest is roughly the size of Mount Everest
That is the Robertson a geologist who knows quite a bit about this asteroid
And by the way it has a name
It's the asteroid called Baptists Tina
Baptist email
Why xtina
Baptist in Idaho
The name Astrid
On another subject
We do know that the Earth's moon was probably produced by a collision with something the size of Mars
Well
I just did that Inc
School doesn't really relate to our story
The whole evening he was just a do it okay the dinosaurs are here on Earth are eating their leaves meanwhile up in space are asked
Asteroid Baptist peanut is now hurtling towards the Earth 20000 miles an hour
Times faster than a very fast rifle bullet couldn't be sure what would happen that matter
Mount Everest size bullet traveling at 20000 miles an hour our atmosphere
The atmosphere is really just a very very thin skin over the rest of the yard sale
Scientists construct the story
Just take a piece by piece and 1st
Figure out
What would happen
And when this big ball
Hurtling through space
Slams into our atmosphere
Just made of gas
Of course
So just aproximate let's fire a bullet through some gas
And Watch What Happens live show de super slow motion
Video of a gun firing a bullet underwater
Can see it on the website radiolab.org very beautiful
See the ball coming out and freeze it right there at the edge okay
Basically Seasons bullet steaming through the water
By the way we use water as an approximation for gas cuz and gas you would have the same effect I'm about to just
Creating a wake
Behind it in the wake
It's wider and wider as a
Trails away from the bullets and if you imagine this shape in 3 dimensions
Really what you're looking at is a kind of a cone like a funnel shape
Inside the the
The waltz of the funnel
Inside that cone
Is nothing
Nothing
Nothing because it water so you saying there's a hole in the water that's what I'm saying
There's a vacuum in there
Because the bullet is shooting through the water pushes the water out of the way
And for a beat the water doesn't have time to come back together and so all you have is emptiness
Right there this what you're seeing is a massive hole in the water
Created by
Now imagine that bullet
Is 6 miles wide
And the whole it is making is right above your head
What is that mean if your dinosaur look you up with what would happen
Well if you were in the right
Play sand in this is going to be the wrong place in a second or two were in the right place
Tutu look behind the
Asteroid is it came in
You'd probably be able to to
To see clearly through the space
What
Does that mean you would suddenly
Be looking at a
Nighttime hole in the daytime sky
Right
Jay did tell us that you would need special kinds of eyeballs to see this Nighthawk
Today's sky and the Dinos didn't have
Science
Still
Just imagine what a last image
What do you see
Day and night
Come together in the same moment
But
Coordinate
Better not blink
Because before you could open your eyes again
The asteroid would have hit the surface
And if you're in a position to to see that then you're going to be in golf
Bike
The violence that is just about to
By the way the audience was just laughing at a dinos de los Muertos graphics
It just came on the screen
So we know it was a big explosion fine
Oedipus violent fine
I think we should be a little bit subtle about this because obviously if an asteroid is the size of Manhattan and it lands on your head your
You're not going to feel very good about that
But if
Manhattan is
Is hitting a
Planet Earth
That's a little bit like a pebble hitting an enormous beach ball and I can imagine that the little Pebbles
AltaVista
Peking pebblewood
Kratom damage
In the spot where it landed but let's suppose that you are
Alleviating mother-of-three hadrosaur living in New Zealand
Just at the moment of the asteroid comes in your on your auntie pogany other side of the planet
Would you like any idea this way
Let's the next question that we talked to Jay
How much damage would this thing a
Actually do
We can produce things
Situations like this in small quantities in the laboratory which brings us
Peter Schultz
I like to do impact experiments as every 13 year old
Dream job to get the blow s*** up for a living
Screen this is the NASA Ames laboratory in California and the thing that they're putting together their middle frame
That is a giant
3 story tall Cannon
What Pete has he takes projectile so for example you're going to see him
Take a little glass bullet over there and it's going to load it into the top of the cannon and then he's going to fire it right
Into a stand up for planet Earth which for him will be a sandpit
I'm looking for us when we call Pete he was just about to pull the trigger on this thing we're calling you on a date
What you are trying to Rick's re-experience vide actually survive
Opposition
Cross your fingers
Battles in here we go
That is gorgeous
Gosh is that good get instant playback
That
Is the sound of a man
Very happy
With his explosion
You can see
Piece of this what's happening so based on experiments like this people like pecan figure out precisely what happened
When the asteroid hit the Earth
They can quantify the explosions Power by basically leveraging up experiments like this so according to Doug the amount of energy
That would have been on weeks when nothing came rushing in on Earth
Roughly
Are we at the Earth
With an explosion that 100 million megatons
Sarah lipstate
Sarah our guitarist going to
Turn around had a metal moment
Don't look at her wrong and she'll do that to you
Okay so here's essentially how Doug broke that down
2 tons of TNT
We talk in tongues you're not megatons to tons of TNT
Will essentially do
This
On one of the three screens you see a 10-story building in floating
2 tons of TNT will takedown build
Now
15000 tons of TNT that is what the United States dropped on Hiroshima
In 1945 on a second screen we see archival footage of the atomic bomb
That chaos has 15000 tons of TNT Robertson a hydrogen bomb
Current hydrogen bombs are typically of the order of one million tons of TNT
Equivalent Now 1 million tons of TNT equivalent that's what we call a Megaton if you remember
Duck said that the asteroid impact was equivalent to 100 million
In megatons really what he saying in concrete terms is that that impact was the equivalent of 100 million of those
Bombs going off all at once in the same spot
Which is a lot
Dentistry
However I mean it's really depends on what you mean by a lot
Because I was doing a little Googling
And I was surprised to learn that
110 million megatons is not nearly enough to destroy the planet
Destroy the entire planet
You would need
Ready for this
110 quadrillion megatons
100 million * 110 million megatons of TNT
So going back to your hadrosaur situation Mother 3
New Zealand
If the thing came in Antipolo to her
Maybe she would feel the ground shake a little bit
But after minutes should be like whatever
To go back to eating leaves
Probably wouldn't notice it
Oh no no no that's not what we were taught in homeroom
Buy Mrs lagrou or whoever your teacher what
Here's the classic explanation
There was an impact
Of course and kicked up an enormous amount of dust to remember this
The Dustin kind of covers the planet
Blankets the earth makes the Earth very cold
Makes tears very nasty
All the big plants die little plants get sick the dinosaurs get hungry the dinosaurs get sick
And then gradually your leg
Dad
Better and better and better from different thing
10000 years 30 thousand years for till you get like a
900000 years later
Shivering the last
Dinosaur
That's the story we were told
In school is a long slow wintry collapse
That tired old story from Missy
Is what it is Magruder's McGruder tonight okay
What is offer up a completely different tablets
All right
But we'll go with that what's actually flipped the understanding completely new science
Keith
Pull up that to ballistics video that we showed earlier with the red sand
Can you put a pull that up and blow it up to the
Three screens in the
Yeah rewind it back
Bitten
Wilkie
Okay so this is a 6000 frame a second video that you're sitting here
Sir Pizza lab
This point on the screen all you're saying is
Pit of red sand
Now what you see in the first few frames as you see the laser hitting right there red sand flying in the air super slo-mo
The next
Rainford right there you see some fire see little ball of fire erupts near the impact
Right where the laser hits the sand there's a little
Clump of flame in
Refreeze on that spot
Scientists can now measure the temperatures in that spot
Just to State the obvious
We know from those measurements
But that spot right there would have gotten
Very
Barry
Hot TV on the temperature of the sun we were talking
Cooking temperatures maybe 20,000 degrees Sons temperatures about 5,000 degrees
And if we're talking temperatures hotter than the sun
Instantly turn to gas a very
Savory high-temperature high-pressure gas it's actually Rock Vapor rocks team
This thing comes barreling in this asteroid it doesn't Just Bounce Off the Earth if plows into the earth goes into the surface
2 miles in 5 miles in 7 miles in 10 mi in 20 miles into the Earth it goes
Close all the rock that is turning into a liquid and then into a gas and now
Watch What Happens Next is a basic physics experiment we're going to show you
On the screen you see
Is very lovely video actually of a
Hand
Dropping a metal ball
Into something
Just a dude dropping a bomb from Sand
Watch this right here
Magazin
And like a millisecond
Effort makes impact disappears into the sand
A little spear of sand go shooting back in the opposite direction
Triple bounce back
Does this always happen this whatever this is Newton's law of something
Newton's Laws
And what you see is you see this fine Lewis and you're shooting back in the office
What's the directions
Right now imagine
Did that ball is
An asteroid
And that's and over there that's the planet
To keep play that one more time
Play the video again but this time as the ball drops
It gradually morphs
Thank you for the sad so what you would get the same effect
You would get that
Simple boy that's just something we do
You wondering where we get all of our soundesign out of that man's mouth that's where
So you get that same bounce-back effect
A fine blue shooting back in the opposite direction but we know
Or we just heard
Describe that it would not be would not be staying in this case
It would be Rock
Gas
Tumble podcast
Six bends upward and pushes right on through the atmosphere
Up into space
Some fractions
At the Moon
Read some fraction of that hit Mars
Okay so now you got this sneeze of rock Vapor it's out in space
Basic physics says that as a travels out of
Farther away from the Earth
What's going to happen if it's going to start to cool down a bit
When it cools itri condenses into little droplets
Well that.
Basically Farm glass very quickly
Little droplets of glass about the size of sand
Now if you look at one of these little droplets of glass
Under microscope
This is what it looks like
Right there
On the screen you see what looks kind of like a translucent snowball that is actually of a magnified image of one of these
It's a classic fell from space
That day
Most of them didn't land on the ground
Talk about that in a second there it is
I know about you but I find that
Totally terrifying
Cuz that's
It's like a little backed
Christina Wright
Honeyville asteroid
Now imagine trillions of these things
In a cloud
McLeod of shrapnel going out out out
Away from the Earth
What's going to happen next is that
It's going to start to lose momentum that cloud
When does the Earth's gravity
He's going to grab back hold of it and say come on back
And 90% of them come back
The Earth
What does falling glass do
Because what happens is it the the
Glass out in space
Starts to spread out like north and south and east and west
And eventually it will appear in the sky over New Zealand
It's now a global phenomena and you know it's really hard to imagine what the hadrosaur would have seen
But the thing to keep in mind
Is it these things are coming in
97% or burning up in the atmosphere
So very few of them were hiding the gray
From her point of view
Probably would have looked
Greatest meteor shower
Anyone has ever seen
With one
Significant
Bummer
Which is this
When is the little bits of glass come in each one that burns up
Depositing
A little bit of heat into the sky
Collectively there's such a massive rain of these things coming in
Well
The heat would build up the sky would turn red
It would be getting hotter and hotter
Hot exactly would have gotten the cow much heat exactly would have built up there in the sky and then
And started to radiate down calculated the amount of heat that would come
10 kilowatts per square meter and get this number well what what does that
Well I went home and Ike current meter and
Tried to measure the amount of heat produced in my oven for different amounts of power and I could get
About 7 kilowatts per square meter in my oven on broil and
500 Degrees broil
Measuring other kinds of ovens
Pizza Oven a pizza oven is about right which means that if you were a terrestrial dinosaur any
We're above the ground on the earth on that day you would have experienced some heat it is almost
Unimaginable maybe it started it a hundred degrees cuz it was June was summer
But within minutes it would have been 300 degrees 500 Degrees
700 degrees 900 Degrees
Estimate or on that day temperatures topped out of something like 1200
Degrees at that temperature nothing can protect you your scales your fur
Whatever you got going to do any good if your blood will literally starts a boil inside your
Your body and you will die
To essentially
According to this Theory the dinosaurs and everything else on Earth that day would have been incinerated
Don't think that's what the demand not so much
The impact
All that objective
Went up into the sky came down as glass rain and created that he
That's what did the men
He would argue it didn't just do some of the men
Or even many of
When he would say it did
All of them in
All at once
There is
Zero evidence that any dinosaur made
The crazy part of
The series that Jay and Doug think the whole process
From the impact of the glass rain to the incineration of
All of these species on the planet
It would have taken a few hours
His best guess
He thinks Maybe
Hours
I mean that's less time than
A business lunch
You tried getting East
Northwest anywhere on Mercer Street at rush hour into
Miss you think about it
That is less time than you will spend
In this theater
Tonight
That means that you're saying that
An animal
That had been Supreme on the planet
100 million years
Disappears
In
Few hours
Completely
Yes
That's what
The evidence suggests
That's right
Well you can consider the evidence but also you can consider common sense and we've got
A world
Bills with terrestrial dinosaurs they were on every continent there even in Antarctica
And just say that they all disappeared
In 2 hours and
All that wood that suggests
But there's none of them in out of Harm's Way none of them in the cave summer
None of them in the grotto
None of them in a in a
Acted Paris that any climate the word all not connection
It's just too much
I just don't buy it
The truth is that the science is never going to be
So exact
To say
Yeah all of them disappeared
It happened on a
Single day
Renewing mean
Note that we have is
What json is
Happen fast
Very fast
Nothing made it through
What I find interesting is It ultimately
You don't need the ballistics
Anything we've shown you so far to know that something major and sudden
Because you can see evidence
Of it literally etched into the Earth
So
Here's the spot
Where we first found
You can see really well out in Colorado
Actually we sent one of our producers Molly Webster out there to meet of paleontology
Kirk Johnson
They hiked over a couple of hills
Stikbot dinosaur come around the corner and
He started to dig
Download
From where we were
Turns out
33 ft down 10,000 years in time
See the Earth has layers
Pelican tree has ring
And every 3 ft down you go you're going back in
Time about ten thousand years
When you go all the way down all the way back
66.09 million years
You will find this one little
Skinny strip of Rock
That's
This one skinny Gray Line
Grey crappie
Doing a very real way that line that you're seeing that represents
D-Day
The asteroid
Just above that line
That's a little bit after the day
Just below that line was a little bit before
The line is called the KT boundary
And what school is Uconnect
You can touch
Evidence of
And in fact her what he did that day was he took it
Peace out in hands at the mall
You hold in your home in the KT boundary
It's like
Homosexual
Yeah but it's not
What you're holding is a dark gray mudstone
Carbon-rich meds
In that must own you'll find all kinds of things and you'll find
A very rare
Minerals like iridium
It probably came in on the app
The Beltline
Those little glass balls
I was talking about the little hell balls
We could get out a microscope and you look at that rock
You will see them in there
We put up a funny cartoon of the
They're all in that line
Perfect you think that line is
What's it matter
Inch
Is hidden in there as sort of the story of the
Absolutely
And here's the crazy thing if this is the line right here this
Strip here
Robert chase the picture of the KT boundary
You didn't just below the line you were going to find over and over again dinosaurs everybody not going to
Baby Alive
It's just putting some toy dinosaurs under the line and making the move
Getting in a certain amount of energy which I shouldn't
But their fossils
And you will find dinosaur fossils
From Europe
Idaho
And Montana this one
Says with me
China
But
Maybe just go above the law
You don't find any dinosaur So Below the line
Find the sum look everywhere above
They haven't
Everywhere they have looked anyway
They found
Nothing
It's a different world that's the amazing thing is a different world
Innisfree rating
Is one world
You're literally just pointing
Pinky to pointer
Finger spread
Miss another moment where
I would urge you at some point. Now keep listening but at some point
Watch the video of his performance is what Sarah Darren
Glenn and Keith do in this moment
Officially
Freemason
Okay so that was the story we told about the end of the dinosaurs live at the Paramount Theater in Seattle
Washington
When we come back we'll take a quick break right now but when we come back I reported Molly Webster and I will dish about
What we have just learned
About
That day
Those
Hours
So long ago
We have all
I know I'm not going to tell you
Stay around
Coming up in just a minute
This is Mike Bell
Cam Newton North Carolina
Radiolab
Supported in part by the Alfred piece
Sloan sound
Lansing public understanding
Science and Technology
In the modern world
More information about Sloan
View. Sloan
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
And I request for those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents
Aunts and uncles teachers
We're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments
Williams
Basically I want to hear about this
Did you know did something
It just means you lean back and say
Wow
How do they do that
Maybe it was the moment that our kids you've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lesson
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the musical score
Or maybe the kitchen mat
Music in the margin of their geometry
We're interested in the
Specific moments where
Kid does something super smart
It doesn't have anything to do with the test
If you have a story
Go to radiolab.org brilliance
Record short audio message
And that's where you live. Org / brilliance
Thank you so much
Is Radiolab on Chad we are back now you just
Heard
Are drastic in-the-moment version of the day the dinosaurs all died
Enough
You're thinking of something different
It was some
Guy who sort of an amateur and he was lifting he went to South Dakota
We have enough
Maybe you should bring them to me
From our reporter Molly Webster who reported that story for us
Way-back-when and now she is
Here again with
Them
News
Updating the apocalyptical episode which was
Probably the last time I saw you
And the reason we're updating it is because
This science article came out the basically if
It proves
To be true
It could be
One of the largest
Paleontological discoveries of the day the dinosaur
First I day claims to tell the story of the first
15 minutes
Two three hours
After the asteroid hit down in Mexico
And basically what it is is geologic
Formation that is
Kind of like that line that we song Colorado but like that line on steroid
It's in the southwest corner
Of North Dakota
Those two
Is not close to the Gulf of Mexico. It's like
3000 km away
And this particular site used to be a guess
The assumption is 66 million years ago that it was kind of like a river but like a river valley that was muddy and
Warm and it was near something about the Western interior Seaway
So then what did they find there
So one of the authors on this paper is
On this
Super Famous paleontologist Ian Smith
He said
When he went to the site
And he stood there
He's like what I see in this place
Is a three-hour story of that day with all the victims
And it feels like a movie is playing out
Before me
Puerto Rican started turned into a scene by scene by scene Adventure in time
Story that they lay out in the paper
Is that
This area within like 15 minutes after the asteroid
It was
Hit by waves
From the Western interior sea
And they brought with them
Saltwater fish in like seashells and things like into this freshwater area
And then at the same time remember like we talked about those glass balls
He fell from the sky view
So the story that this area tells is that there are actually kind of like
Three phases
Of those glass balls of various like size and proportions and some they wouldn't really really far until like space
And came back and said they came back
Later
Then all the other ones and armoire
You know it's funny it's like all glass balls in the end really if you're a paleontologist you're really gay
Taking out right now over like the different types of glass balls that this site holds stress balls
Spill of the giant crash and some of them are actually made of
Particles from the
Actual impact site like in all of the previous sites they had found in the United States none of those
Glass balls are actually still glass
They had decomposed into clay apparently glass will change into clay overtime I did not know this
But in this
Location they actually have glass
Unaltered by the passage of time
So it holds within it like the air
In geochemistry jobs that day
And that place
And they found some that were actually I feel like the such a Jurassic Park when they found some that were trapped in Amber
That haven't that are totally unaltered
I really don't know anything except for that like Jurassic Park made me think that anything and Amber is really important
And Jerry Ojos
And I'm just the backup
Back in the day on the day that this
This asteroid hit the Earth
That was a
Tropical whale population place
Yeso subtropical well-populated have dinosaurs and it would have
Stores that would have fish it seemed to be covered in trees
Insects lots of insects
Mammals looks like yeah whatever our oldest man was
Yes it was a really like Lush
Happening area
And what they see
In this site that they've uncovered today
Is what appears to be instantaneous death
Describe
Fish that are stacked dead fish besides fish
That are stacked like logs and it's
Freshwater fish and marine fish
And they do describe it as like a mass grave
There are fish
Fossils like wrapped around
Tree bases
Like like creatures and plants and stones and Pebbles and shellfish and everything
Saltwater freshwater everything with smooshed together
Tumble of light that was like Throne like almost like thrown together in a wash in like
Mixed up you know if you're if you're an animal
In that moment you're there
And something happens in Mexico and you have no idea
But maybe about
15 minutes after that thing happened in Mexico that you have no idea about you might feel the Earth Rumble
There's some shaking and then that rumbling that shaking
I'm comes with it a big wave from the sea
And so you get this big
It comes in
And then what happens is that
Comes in as you're already starting to get
The glass balls from the heaven
And so
And what they see is you get this like wave of kind of what seems to be almost like raining glass balls
And then that's like Mick
Stand with the mud from like the title
And the layers of things that are dying
The fish like some of the details that stand out to me the most
The fish are all
Generally pointed in the same direction
And they're like
Stacked pretty tightly mouths open
And their fins
Splayed
But one of the things I think it's super cool is that
All that different stuff we talked about happening across the globe in are original
Show
Probably got really hot
But you know that was Jay melosh was like it's really hot that Robertson was talking about like the boiler the boiler effect and then we talked
What about the flashing blue light we talked about things raining from the sky and we talked about June or July all that's
Stuff a lot of that stuff was based on really smart models
This seems to be a place it actually will
Provide evidence
Either for or against those models
How much are tree trunks
Which I think made like Jay melosh really happy cuz he was like I did get really hot
Tea towel and then they're like the fish wrapped around trees
And then there appears to be a dinosaur bone
Possibly dinosaur bones
Skin still attached
Kirk Johnson said if if that is if it really is a dinosaur bone and that site is connected
Did the asteroid impact like I think it is it would be the youngest dinosaur ever
My last question is is there something we need to know about the man whose
Dig this
That would
Color are feelings about the studies
Author the main authors this guy Robert DePalma he's in his late 30s
Does not have a PhD
He works
A lot outside of normal Academia but
Jay melosh who is in our first thing
He is the editor on the on the article
And then
Walter Alvarez and Ian smitter in the article
Are co-authors
And then this other guy like Mark Mark Richards who's like a really famous
Tsunami earthquake guy
So you think he's got a collection of people around him and I think everyone else says like if the stuff that they say that they have is
There
It's amazing
They do think one of the things in the paper like is like
People are like you are claiming
To know a 3-hour window 66 million years ago that is a very big claim right you're really
Going to have to produce
A lot of evidence
And I think that people think it could be there
But you convinced me if you got
It look like a animal all squished up together all at once and you got rain that you can account for
In different stages
And that looks like you're right there at the
Black moment plus 3 hours
And everything's dead and
The forest is burned just like if it's almost like it's
Exactly what we said I know I was like well I'm hooked it's just it does leave you at the end of the day
Feeling a little bit nervous to be on this big safe blue.
Recognizing that we are so vulnerable with life
Is really fragile
When a pebble
Can
Murder know what I think is the crazy part is
If you were an animal
Standing in North Dakota
You would have no idea what was happening
There's like I like logic I like to be able to say oh there's a source
And then nothing happened
And to just be there and all of a sudden the Earth starts rattling like a bell around you and then a title
Wave comes in and then I'm dead
Casino
Like that to me is the most is the most stunning part is it should have salt on your mouth
Yeah it's just
It's just like
To just be standing there unawares and then a
Thing happens
That really has nothing to do with you
Nothing
That's a weird
Heart to me
Thank you Mommy sure
Apocalypse
I just want to give you a very special thanks
Sarah lipstate from novela Sangre on the base
Coaching the drums
They're both from the band on Fillmore
We are so lucky to
Share the stage
Along with
Video Maestro key scratches
Who's doing live video
Brilliant
Puppeteer Myron Griselda
So good check out
All of them
Ayat Radiolab
Average weight
Pretty
Robert Kovach
Thanks for listening
Is Jason studstill in Seattle Washington
Radiolab was created by John album run and is produced by Soren wheeler
Keith is our director of sound design
Susie lechtenberg is our executive producer our staff includes Simon Adler that cup wrestler
Rachel Cusick
David gamble Bethel Hoppity Tracy hunt Nora Keller not guilty Robert College
Annie McEwen lots of Nasir Melissa O'Donnell sarakari
Arian black Pat Walters and Molly Webster withheld from Shima ODI Audrey Quinn
And Neal Danesha in our fact-checker is Michelle Harris