Northern listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
That incredibly talented young boy was soon a talented young man
Opposing symphonies cocello
Hello
Robert hi mist of classical music
Play the public radio interrupted by
Science journalist and author David, are we all here now now we're all here and you are Jennifer
Radiolab
Actually what happened here so I called David because he has just published a book
Which
Contains an idea that I found so surprised I had not
No no
It's kind of a
Smack in the face
To Charles Darwin's theory of evolution
Yes there have been a number of excellent at Google that have been
Added to Darwin
Theory over the last
50 years or so since he published it but
This is this is more than that this is a big freaking asterisk
And that means David told me a story
About a moth
Yes the peppered moth
It lives in forest
SubCentral England among other places in during the 19th century
This moth was white with little flecks of black on it
And please moths
Sometimes rooster on the trunks of trees
In the trunks of trees surrounding Manchester England restorative light color
Roosted on the trees they were pretty well camouflage
Alight
Slightly peppered moth on a light slightly pepper tree trunk
So they were protected against
Predation by birds
And then
The tree trunk
Changed why do the tree trunks chain
Because of the Industrial Revolution
Because of smoke stacks
Of Manchester
Returning out a lot of
Cool smoke they were burning cold for all their industrial processes
And there was a
Good coaster that coming out and it was blanketing the trees in the nearby Forest so the tree trunk
Turn
Black
And
The mall
We're no longer camouflage cuz I'm always wear white you wouldn't want to be a white moth sitting against the cold black tree because
Cuz then you are you're married but know exactly where you are
Right
What happened
The Moth
Turned black
Oh yeah sure this is the this is the classic sort of evolution story
That
Story was told it was a became a textbook example of darwinian evolutionary change
In in real time and the way that happens what we were told is it once the trees turn dark them off
Change by incremental mutation again oh thanks to some tiny little mistake and some more
G the black
Spackling got bigger on certain moths and knows we're a little bit more protected and then the spackling got a little bit bigger
Tomorrow's got a little
Gray hair and then very very slowly over generation after generation after generation of moth
They get a little bit.
Darker still
To end up eventually with a population of Martha turn
Completely
That's the classic
Story
Except except that we now know
That's wrong it turns out it wasn't slow
It didn't take Generations in generation
Sequencing of the moth genome has revealed
Stretch of DNA
22000 letters of the DNA code
That suddenly jump
Into these moths
From somewhere
And in a Flash
The moths changed
From
White to black pretty much in one day really a white
Peppered moth mom
All of a sudden
Producers in all black
Baby
Wait so how did that
How did that happen
It's a whole pack of jeans just got shoved in
To this new
From where did come from David says it probably
Jumped
One part of the moth genome to a completely new part different part
But what
That means a question that living things
Turns out can change way faster than we thought
And therefore Evolution can happen much faster than we thought and on top of that David says
Scientists have now discovered
Is even stranger kind of super fast train
That
Cakes
Things about parents and Offspring individual species things we've counted on for years and just throws the whole mix into the
Yes infective heredity
Effective heredity
What is what is that
I don't even have to explain this to you I have to go back
Hello I'm Jah Devil Run and I'm Robert Bill Winston's Radiolab for tattoo in earlier version of
Because it was 11 years ago I think that we made a show called show called V
Not as we
Oh God that's Joanne in that show who dealt with
Early sort of more primitive version of this very question
Can I play you a few minutes of that other earlier show
World of living things
I say look at there's a cat and that's that is a dog and a new tree
You notice
List of those things of course
Are different
Yes and later we go to school
We learn about
Phylum's in categories like kingdoms and stops breathing but the nature of those differences and then you're taught
About struggle
Competition Darwin species and there is a new Siri
It's being talked about that all of that on it
I heard it first
I'm Steve strogatz I'm an applied mathematician at Cornell and the story he told me which is based on analysis
TNA injury tiny Oregon
Micro
Is it once upon a time he says
Life began with a very primitive very simple collection of cells
Diesel
These cells life
It appears that magic when you go back far enough there's a kind of
Rampant sharing of molecule it's a kind of orgy in which
There are no well-defined species are organisms and
I can give you my jeans and you can pass what were a communist
Totally room recording that
But that Kumbaya singing that certainly was there at the start he produced this piece years ago yes I think it was just
The office
It was a Communist economy
What do you mean what is it mean I know what it means in the 60s. Love since that what is it really mean what I what cells are
Exchanging is chemical
Chemicals that give them talents
Here's what
I did this with Steve
Huddle in Darwin public life might have begun in
Warm
Let's say that you and I are both cell
The once upon a time there was you in the puddle and I'm in the same family as you
And if it gets a little colder in the puddle
Also we should all get sick but you don't get sick
You have some kind of
Accidental towel you can handle cold water
I'm shivering
Describe again what happens
At this point my membrane that is I
I'm a cell I've got a membrane I got my outer
Player
Maybe a little bit porous
And maybe okay we're not talking
Desiccated organism maybe your poor is too and I'll well you just absorb some of those jeans
So now we both have this we both got any both Gene now I can survive
Coldwater cousins
And if I bump into you now it's part of you
So now that Steve has become a robber she twitches then become
Georgina doing over and over and over
I actually don't think of cells like people
Changes this jeans
Swapping was not intentional it's not
Purposeful show
That's Nigel golden tell a mathematical physicist at the University of Illinois give the science that
Play ideas. Maisel saying hey I'm going to just help out my buddy over there
Hit a couple of jeans I think you'll find Handy
It's not something like that
Cancel if we're swapping genes so much and you know you're going to be yours and mine what does it actually mean to be
B
MeetMe
So much money is spent around very weird imagine a world in which for a while I have your nose
And then I get my nose back you have Steve's hair than
Steve would get my ear that he would get you or knows I'm having a little
Exchange take your chin
Okay you can have my
Allergies and then you start even asking what does it mean
To be a species
You can have my love affair with
Doubt
Individual
No identity
Very strange
How long is the
Concept
Should we take the grandstand
Become Mormon
Further and further back
The roots of Urology
Take for instance Charles Darwin what night is really saying
Is it for the first
Billion years of life
Everything that Darwin teaches all that stuff hasn't happened to no borders no individuals has no species that is
Is Darwinism
Evolution
What's an interlude
In the real
Story of life
It's only
What's happening now what you got back at the very beginning with a whole bunch of cells
Swapping genes swapping advantages swapping disadvantages
Wilder tremendous explosion
In a way that life has knots
Until
3 billion years ago
Interpreted
Freeman Dyson
Remenda famous physicist
Working out their friend
You struck at Sears
Moneyville day
A bacterium
Anticipating Bill gate by 3 billion years
Refuse to share
Refuse to share the first bad guy is this
The cellular
Bill Gates
Who decides that I've got Innovation that I don't feel like
Or Paz
I believe I found a way to
That is I'm not going to be a
Seoul
And why
Play what made that one little cell
Decide to stop
A good question
We don't really know but we do now
Was maybe the most dramatic moment
Life on Earth
Transition
Age of selfishness
And gradually once one creatures
Stop sharing
The others followed
Same thing I now
For the first time in
Finally we get.
Now we get speech
Now we
Yes
The age of identity
Help individuals
Things change
Exchange money
Any great thing
You know like you are a bat and
Figured out sonar
But I don't have
I can't get some
Like you're in a little electric fish that lives in the Muddy Waters
Price of the Amazon
Carrots totally dark you can see
Because you can
C with electric
If I'm in the dark I'm bumping my head
Did we really use Bill Gates's is standing for like selfishness time he was the ultimate
It's horrible that we did that
Actually going over to the to the light side instead
Go to the dark side
That is a c strogatz I ended up calling mug
Get to Chatham through some of the stuff and he told me
That he actually heard this whole idea from a lecture by physicists
Freeman Dyson Dyson adjust a great writer in a great speaker and he had this memorable line in their least memorable to me when he start
Talkin about
Let me rephrase the whole thing in terms of sharing which may be why in that previous episode we had that come by awesome singing
But that wasn't my doing by the way I know know that I was
Primitive bacterium anticipating Bill Gates by 3 billion years refused to share its DNA and then
That was that was Freeman Dyson that was his only way was I was sitting there in this lecture we started mentioning assert
Biologist Carlos and he talked about him in such glowing terms as one of the Great
Microbiologist
Love our time
And see you after you hadn't heard of Carl was I had to before though I had not the reason I was asking
I think in the shower actually mentioned probably because I remember
You know I don't know if you guys know this or not but
So that was 11 years ago right I was actually an intern
At the time I just showed up
And I was tasked with tracking down Carlos who's the guy that we mentioned as or like the grandfather this idea
And he was like a huge
Huge deal in science he discovered this whole other
Branch on the tree of life the archaea he's Mister archaea
Whole nother Kingdom
Front page of the New York Times and I had to track him down and turned out
Use like the
Just the Classic
Curmudgeonly
Scientist
It took me
20 emails
To get him to even like just let us talk to his
Collaborator Nigel goldenfeld who we talked to in the show
But whatever is a very strange he was a very
Curmudgeonly man
But you know like he came to like me and I actually spend some time with him his office and we
I can do the curmudgeon anything if I need to know
Cherokee
Yeah I could we got some curmudgeonly jokes back and forth and
Anyway after he heard the peace
Hiromi
The most seizing skating email about nothing there was nothing in it about like you got this
Wrong it was just like you made a cartoon of my work
Which honestly now listening Bash
I agree with a little more than I did at the time
But he was like I'm a serious person and you made this into like a dog and pony show
And I was like I was brand new I was and it hurt any like I was I felt really
Really bad he's like you've disrespected Nigel
And so I wrote I wrote this hour called up Steve maybe and said man you know this happened in Steve was like a
Forget them don't worry about it
Yeah I don't know I
I'd it sounds like something I might have said to you but you remember having that honestly don't remember having that conversation
I needed that so bad at that moment my career for someone like with Steve stature to like balance it out in that way
Yeah I think
Venus orbit funny that he would
Tell me a little surprising that he wouldn't have gotten what you were trying to do what we were trying to do I think our play
Playfulness in an attempt to be clear and to communicate
In to attract people who might not otherwise listen to a story about something called horizontal Gene transfer
He should have gotten that because
He himself in his writing was very playful
He was very fun to talk to I mean he was absolutely Carlos was very playful
And irascible and grouchy and
Farming but he would certainly tell you what he thought yeah yeah this guy is a great character
David quammen turns out in his new book talks a lot a lot a lot about Carl woes and this Revel
Pollution in our thinking about the evolution of life for the end of his life he started to think that he was more important
And more profound and Darwin he got a very negative attitude toward
Charles Darwin Darwin's birthday he should be a day of Rage
That's right cuz he did that but I guess I'm wondering is now that you spent a book
Attention on him do you feel that he has
Some
Right to say
That's the picture we have of how life changes needs
Serious amending or is she just
Parking
Because he's a Barker
No he is
He was entitled
Not to think that he was greater than Darwin but to think that
What he discovered was
Very very damn important to understanding
The full history of evolution
On Earth what has happened all throughout the history of life on the planet
4 billion years
And is still happening today
This is where we are now
The crazy details coming up right after the break
This is Yong Yuan calling from
From Astoria New York
Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred p
Public understand
Information about
Www
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
On the show
And I request
For those of you who
Who spend a lot of time with kids parents
Aunts and uncles
Teachers looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments
Brilliant
Basically I want to hear about this
When a kid you know did something
It just means you lean back and say
Well
How do they do that
Maybe it was the moment that I
A kid you've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of their musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class
Are ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the
Epic moments where
A kid does something super smart
It doesn't have anything to do with
If you have a story
Go to radiolab.org
Flash brilliance
Mrecorder short
Audio message
And that's radiolab.org
Flash Brewing
Thank you so much
Jad Robert Radiolab I were back with David, and this new
Do do us
Way
Changing
Life
Infective heredity
These leaping jeans these transfers of
DNA
That create
New genetic possibilities
In a blink
Turns out David told us that the swapping of genes but we talked about in the early history of life that's still happening
Today correct
Yes bacteria all around us those bugs
Are trading jean jeans are jumping sideways
From one kind of
Bacteria
To another Even in our bellies Even in our guts
So let's say that you go to France
Vacation
And then you lick your finger
Are you eat something
New bacteria
European food has been into your stomach and now not only do you have some new bugs in you
But they can start trading their Gene with bugs that are already in you
What would that mean like physically like what it would look like without the cell wall and then
They found that there were several different mechanism
For this
Two bacteria would create a little pipe
A little sort of penis like thing
Between them and genes would be transferred
The jeans were moving sideways under other circumstances
From
Dead busted open bacteria into live bacteria does it acquire this new
Trade at once immediately
Amedeo in an instant
Anu population
Even the news
Species
Of bacteria can possess all of those
Gradually laborious Lee
Acquired adaptations that
Another strain of bacteria evolve they don't have to wait around
For Generation after generation to pick up
Random mutation
Are bacteria inside us can pick up
Kuiu abilities new tricks all at once from your new neighbors so Princeton's one kind
Of bacteria
Could pass jeans
Antibiotic resistance to another completely different kind of bacteria
So you got somebody sitting in a hospital with
A a staphylococcus infection
Some of the bugs inside her figure it out
How to resist penicillin
Bugs in comes out of
That human and it gets left on a table in the hospital and somebody else gets infected by it
Then they will also have
An infection that is resistant to penicillin in the hospital sick with something
Show me different they have a different kind of harmful bacteria do in trouble giving them trouble
And those old bacteria in them can learn in a Flash on the new bacteria
Now everybody's penicillin-resistant
And that's why
That's what I antibiotic resistance
Is spreading around the world
So lickety-split
That is really important that's a
That's a global Health crisis
The World Health Organization among others
Have called that a global Health crisis
Tens and tens and tens of thousands people
Are dying from Netflix really important
An urgent
The most important part of this
Whole subject is not
Practical
It's a matter of understanding
Understanding the history of life
Understanding
Who We Are
Literally because according to David the way we are the humans are has been affected by
Visits from other creatures genes yes 8% of the human genome
Is
Viral DNA
8% of the humans or into our mammal ancestors
Sideways
It's like you're sitting around enough virus gets into your bloodstream
And it travels into one of yourself
And when it's in there and drop some of its DNA
Enjoy your day
And if it gets new Dory sellers principal then it will be passed along 8% of our genome has come to us that
That way from these viruses
Some of that
Is just
Gobbledygook
In our genome
Some of it
Is instructions not with jeans
That are still performing functions
And one of those
Create boundary layer between
Human placenta in the fetus
An absolutely necessary
Sensual
Boundary layer
Now this is
He was totally shocked to me because after all the thing that's
Really special about mammals is that female mammals
Or at least placental mammals
Carrie young around inside
The body in the history of life this was a completely new development I mean you think about fish you think about reptiles like the dinosaur
The birds
What are they doing to him
If they lay eggs but now we get a creature
The comes along and figures out how to keep the baby growing inside it
Question what does that have to make sure that it gets immune system.
And the baby has to be able to
Poop and stuff like that get things out of that to be some kind of
Boundary
And how did we get that good idea
We got that good idea from a virus
Long long ago some ancient mammal ancestor got a virus got infected by a virus and not virus
Introduced a new Gene
Is the original virus it created an envelope a rapping
Around the virus
But
It has been
Adapted
To create a different kind of rapping
The rapping that goes
Around fetus and inside the placenta
So it carries nutrients
In it protects the fetus from the mother's immune system and it is allowing waste products
From
Fetus to be carried away
And disposed of by the mother I mean is this potentially the origin of mammals and woods
This being the without which if we hadn't gotten this Talent from viruses
We wouldn't have gotten
The kinds of mammals we have now that layer
Could not exist and does not function
Without this
Viral Gene
Telling it
What to do
Without this little bit of a virus DNA
Yeah you can't be a mammal
You can't be my mother mammal and you can't be a child
In light of the stuff in in
For me and light of five years of
Studying
I'm following it in interviewing people about it
The categories that we apply to the world
Categories like
Individual
And
Species
Now appear more blurry
The edges
Are fuzzy
Is there such a thing as a human individual or is it
A human a composite
Of other forms of life
And what this says is that we are composite
We are mosaics
Sis humbling and it's
Bennett's fascinating
Just think of yourself that way
Like for me David so it turns out that David is not just the descendant of
A Norwegian father and a German Irish mother
But he's also
Viral and bacterial
And who knows what else
End
I find that
Thrilling
I'm grateful to all the limbs on the tree of life for the things that they've given us
Thanks of course to Steven strogatz of Cornell University who is always willing to jump
Back into the pond so he's long since I left and thought he'd gotten dried off from David Clements new book
Book is called the Tangled tree and it's a gorgeous book so thanks to them and takes all of you
Wait a second
My name is David coming from Mexico City
Radiolab was created by Aventura
And is produced by Soren wheeler
D'link
Director of sound design
Maria Matos R Padilla
These are managing director
Our staff includes Simon Adler
Pick up wrestler Ric Ocasek
David Gable
Kasie hunt
Robert krulwich
Annie McEwen
Latif Nasser
Melissa O'Donnell
Arianne wack
Ted Walters
Emily West
With help from
Shima
Are fact-checkers
Michelle Harris