Before we get going
Earthquake warning this podcast contains some descriptions of graphic violence
And also some strong language
Be warned
Weight units
Radiolab WNYC
Look at
It's hard to
Kill another human being anymore right we are fangs have retreated
Hands are weak
But
Possibility kill each other weave
Games and ability to read each other's tone of voice
And facial expression
And often what's missing in these interactions is one side of that equation
Whether it's the police not seeing somebody because of running through an alley with their guns drawn and
And start or shining a flashlight in someone's face where that person can't
Can see the officers expression there's some mask with some breakdown in that in that equation that makes
Handicap sauce from a normal human interaction
Hey I'm Jared home run by Robert krulwich this is Radiolab and today we are once again taking a deep dive in
Into Tampa Bay Times Reporter Ben Montgomery's mountain of data about police shootings in Florida
Soap to refresh your memory from with try to account for every single police shooting from January 1st of two
2009 to
December 31st of 2014 and we just remind you ban in his team at the Tampa Bay Times collected data from
Police shootings
And there's all kinds of stories that you can tell about the status last week we looked at police training and racing
And racism
And obviously there's so much more they can and should be said about all of that but this week we're going to go in a very different
Direction maybe Matt you just want want to set this up for us
Plays out this this idea that then just mentioned that this is her Communication Breakdown it happens
And it doesn't in a very particular way
Because when one of these cases
Comes before a court the court more often then I will only look at the moment
That the cop involved in the shooting
Pull the trigger you don't consider any other moment it's only the objective facts on the ground of the moment the officer
Applies Force
So the thing that we found compelling about this story is that
In this case you can actually see
And kind of a rare instance
You can lie cats you can step in and see all the little moments that lead up to that moment
You realize how
Complicated
These interactions get
Citizen to give a story to story about white couple
Andrea and Rick Sheldon
And rushing to start story with Rick
So on one of my trips to Florida Ben and I drove to the northeast corner of the state of
I'm your Jacksonville to Rick's place
It's sort of like the the Wilds of Florida if they're guilty
Wild Big Bird back there
What on whenever you're going to property pretty much a little bit of everything to collect rainwater in barrels he's got potatoes tomatoes
Squash eat organic Gardens Ducks goats animals turkey
Turkeys
Oh my God oh my God
Aetna stop in this replace battery
Eventually we all sit down lyrics living room Rick
Sat cross-legged on the couch Rick I was just wondering if we could I pull up a chair across from him we can talk about your case
But even backing up before everything happened
Please tell me about about your about your wife
I'm a Dandy
She was down here visiting her mom
Panda
We hit it off
Straight from the get-go where'd you where'd you guys meet
Tradewinds Lounge
Downtown st. Augustine
Other Bar downtown look like
Knockout
10 dark dark hair
How tall
Osaka thing
Profit to make the first move
I know we can make the same movie same time
And I can remember telling her you know
We have a live burn tomorrow Rick was in training to be a firefighter at the academy one of her last events
And that I'd call her whenever I got done
And are we going to have dinner
She's like
Now you're not going to call me
You just don't come over like I'm going to be stinky
Tonight
Cuz I know that if you go back to your place you're going to pass out tired
And I never see you again
So you just going to come over here and take a shower and I showed up I ate dinner Batman
So that was a date number one Rick says it is connected and so the date
Everybody year she moved down here and then to him got married nursing school
Rick eventually became a firefighter for Jackson Fire Rescue
Jump Ahead to the night in question can you just like
Back up to Lake
The beginning
Of the Danes going to walk me through
We woke up extra early
Wait what day is it
April 15th
Yeah
We were in our cabin in Georgia
Getting it ready getting it all set up and whatnot is going to be a retirement place
Dammit
Backup
Came home
Long drive
Long hot Drive
We got home
Start unpacking the car a little bit start doing a little bit of the Sentinel are doing well. Chat and talk about dinner
Having a couple of drinks
But not what happened after that
Now now
I'm just kind of
Start getting grumpy at each other and
Getting
Grumpy
Now we talked about this for a while I'm just wondering if you can remember
Just kind of any detail of what you guys were talking about
And Rick didn't want to get into it I'd rather not make statement about that right now
About the conversation
All we can say according the police report is that Rick and Andy got into this screaming match and Rick says that he felt himself
Shortness of breath chest pain loss of concentration inability to think
Rick says he had problems with PTSD
Quite a while
Because back to his former job as a paramedic
I can't take this
I need to walk away
Grab the bottle out of the refrigerator and I got in my truck and I went I was like okay I'm just going to go fishing
Drove down this dirt road for about 5 miles to the big pond down there
By the pond I was stuck his truck is stuck in the mud I was axle deep
Tell him you'll meet up his bottle of tequila and he starts drinking
He keeps drinking eventually pop some pills sleeping pills
Next thing I remember was him I remember having problems I remember being upset and remember
Having my
PTSD shadowsocks
I remember I'm
Call my boss, and I need some help
And um
Ask for help ask for employee assistance program help now
Deb suicide hotline
Oh you thought you were suicidal in that moment I thought I was losing it
And in what way is it just like
Digging
Stop digging
You don't want to look in the shed
Is it get that bad
Did he say anything to you
I don't remember the conversation
Okay
What happened after that
Next thing I know I've got the cops calling me going where are you
This is recording that phone call
Hi there how you doing
15 + 9 + W tells Rick that he and a few other deputies are walking down this dirt road to Rick's place because
They gotten a call that Rick was possibly suicidal that he got into a fight with his wife
Where you at
I have no idea though
Retail tributary got in this truck drove away
And I've been enjoying myself
Your wife at the house
It's okay everything alright
Everything's okay at the house
Okay
Domestic dispute
Men
Wh where can I get a phone number to be like my contact with her
Rick is the deputies home phone number
Okay
And then
On the phone with you
Another deputy call her
So we can get her to come outside
Do it and talk for about another minute
Dogman
Was last night
Fall leaves
So at this point the deputy standing at the edge of Rick and Amy's driveway Rick is still a few miles away
O'Reilly's truck
When suddenly the background the call
It is here
Who the hell is firing shots
That's Rick trying to figure out what happened
Heavy D
When we come back we look at what happened during that phone call and the tragic game of telephone that led to it
Stay with us
Hi this is Albert in State College Pennsylvania
Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world more information about Sloan at w
Www.org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here I'm a producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help this summer I'm hosting a show and I've requested
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
That what we're calling tiny moments childhood Brilliance basically I want to hear about those times
Did something
It just means you read back and say whoa how did they do that maybe it was the moment that a kid
You've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons and you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed they're ready music in the margin of their geometry homework we're interested in
Epic moments where a kid does something super smart but it doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story please share it with us and go to radiolab.org Brilliance and record
Short audio message for us
And that's radiolab.org / Brilliance thank you so much
This is Radiolab to get back to our story
Rick Sheldon and a deputy were on the phone shots were fired in the background
And then the line went dead
We pick back up with our reporter Matt kielty
What we know is while the deputy was talking to Rick
The other officers that were with the deputy
I have gone ahead
And going up to the house
Rick's wife Andy
Heard something came out of the house with a shotgun
The deputies say that she pointed a shotgun at one of the deputies
They open fire and she was shot and killed
They're on the front porch did they say did they identify themselves
Ben and I were able to get all of the police dispatch recordings
From that night
And if you go to these recordings what you hear is
Discreetly drawn-out version of what Ben was talking about at the top of the story
The disconnected happens between
The deputies and the dispatchers and what they're thinking hearing and seeing what's actually
Happening
So if you rewind about 40 minutes before that shooting the first thing that happened was Rick called his boss
We don't know exactly what was said in that phone call because it wasn't recorded but what we do know is that Rick's boss left
Conversation bleeding a trick might be possibly suicidal that there been a fight at the house that Rick
I had some guns with minutes truck cuz it's freaking idiot on camping and that there was a gun back at the house
But anyways the first thing that happened after that call is Rick boss his fire chief calls fire.
Dispatch calls a sheriff dispatcher who raped in another
Daltrey dispatches get on the line what we can figure out what's going on
Sheriff dispatch number 3 he's just like
Information
Right around the time that dispatch number three is making that call somehow or another Sheriff's dispatcher afford dispatcher
How to call for a welfare check
Is it he is in the woods that has a handgun
But then things start to get more complicated because when dispatcher number three gets ahold of Rick's pasta fire cheese
Details what is issue with the deal
I said she come out you're hiding in the woods my wife chasing me with a gun just couldn't take it anymore
Some of it back but things are emotions then
Number for relays to teach story to the deputies in route or a handgun but it's chasing the male who took
Medication hallucinating what's going on
Is chasing him
Which Rick said he said but you said there was a gun in the house that's it
In the woods
I didn't say anything like that
Clarification male hath is hiding from his wife who signal zero with a handgun in fear of her
I'm trying to get more 1043
Howard's of miscommunication Because by the time the police show up at this house for what is normally a welfare check
Now she has a shotgun inside the house
I'm off into the woods what's that address also armed deputies they
So damn dark out here with blacked-out walk
Pull up in a blackout
Place to gather their flashlights and I start walking down this road
Rick's place in one of their views even puts on these night vision goggles because they think this woman is chased her husband in the woods
Supposably he's in the Woods by his house
Spell
Working out to
Start walking down the straight road towards Creek Place
The neighbors dog gets freaked out eventually
Vi at least get to the edge of Rick's driveway
Detective around here about 40 minutes after Rick
Made that first called was boss the Ricky said call from the deputy
Hi there how are you doing
Your wife
No I took all the guns with mags
Okay
Domestic dispute
But as the deputy is talking to Rick for the deputies start walking up
Rick's driveway so they get up to the house two of them walk up onto the porch one of the Moon looks through the bed
Bedroom window where Andy is and she has no reason to believe the police or anywhere on her property
Sleep a presumably she heard a noise grab the shotgun in the house and came outside
In This Moment all we really have to go on is what the cop said they saw
Which is Andy came out through the front door wearing nothing but her underwear
Holding shotgun
Cop saved a identified themselves they were her screaming at her to drop the gun
They say that Andy took a step forward
Level 2 shotgun against your shoulder
And then
They open fire if I 24 Shots to hit Andy at least 8 times
She fell to the porch
Some of the peace officers rescuer begin performing first aid
Let me see the radio for an ambulance and paramedics showed up
And pronounce and eat at the same
At this point you have any idea what's happening now
Medical
I never realized I needed to
Snap out wake up
Get my ass in gear and find out what's going on
Buttrick
Check the stock and so it took three hours for them to the cops figure out where he was Santa Cruz over to meet him Joe the ground crew came over and
Pick me up handcuffed me and put me in the back of a four-wheel drive pickup truck and took me to headquarters
I got another car brought me to headquarters put me in a room typical interrogation type room
And then I start noticing that they were drum
Being very very friendly
Some people are saying something about you oh my my camping equipment in the truck I remember them
Authorizing me to have a cigarette
And the broom
And then we pretty much went through the same questioning that we've gone through so far and at which time they
Inform me that
They had a
Come out to the house
Check on Maddie & Tae
She's come to the door and there was an altercation and they shot and killed her
That was the breaking news
Pretty much
When you hear something like that I mean
I can't even fathom
How you respond to some news like that
I still care
Responding to it
Did you say anything to him
Am I under arrest
Handcuffs off me
How long did it take him to
To uncuff you
I don't remember
We say anything to him while you're still cuff
From that moment on I pretty much just
But what do you say whenever somebody looks at me and says your wife is dead
Richard Gilder
That that the absolute implosion of your mind just
The Searing pain the explosive feeling the need
Do I get angry do I get
Sad Dua
Break down and cry why do I fall apart Dua
Hold it together long enough where I can figure out what the
He'll just happen
What
You did what
You went out at my house in the middle night
And you shot my wife
I mean
How do you respond to that to this day I'm still
Sx720 50 times a day answer myself
Radar map
Mimi
Stampy Cat
No
Did you see her at all after the shooting yes
Two weeks afterwards
Where was that
And funeral home
One of the funeral home and down
Simon Peter Billingsley
And reach down the kisser and
Felt the edge of what I thought was a casket move
I was at time that realize that she was on a cardboard box
If it had
Braille on it to make it look pretty
Did you say anything to her
I am
Tell her that we really need to do something about her hair because it was a mess
And the rest of what I said to her is between me and her
Yeah of course
Take a break
I put the microphone down Rick got up
And whenever the kitchen pour myself a glass of vodka
We kind of just walked around the property for a while we kept talking eventually
Eric Clapton
Computer bag that he keeps buried in his closet
This is bag full of gunshots fired all the police reports
Alexander's autopsy report
The autopsy report to said that there was no start previous surgeries
Growing she just had her gallbladder taken out these are just questions that we kept going on
Howard says that he made eye contact with her and she with him okay so
A guy is standing at the window
You seen the elevation of the window compared to win over six foot tall person is standing at
You really telling me that you were made eye contact
Rick also has all the recordings of the police dispatch how many times have you listened to those recordings
Count
Non-Stop
Hourly
He says he just can't stop asking himself
How did this happen
And then eventually Raekwon outside diagrams back inside
Rick went back inside came back out with this map that is lawyers and runner-up
Positions where the shootings were at
Hysterectomy and then walk through the shooting of his wife
Kind of like going
And placing herself reach office there was this one down here
He's the one that testified that he couldn't see what he was shooting at he just knew that the other guys were shooting so he's on the other side of the
What is over close to the porch one of the options was you can see some of the bullet holes in the house
There
I said that
Cibola internet for up Dorothea
Plastic
Here and we're off front porch over in the front yard with three the deputies wear
So they they here come out and they start moving across like this
Shooting a naked woman
Our front porch
Animal night
You know this one
F*** them
Rick and walk inside and left us
Standing in the yard
Performance after Andrew Sheldon was shot and killed
The state attorney's office sent a letter to the Florida Department of Law Enforcement that conduct an investigation in the shooting
Saying that there be no charges brought against the officers stating that what they did was a quote justifiable use
A deadly force
Rick has filed a civil complaint on behalf of the state of angry Sheldon
The complaint alleges each officer involved in the shooting violators civil rights used excessive force
Didn't follow training policy and procedure
And intentionally inflicted emotional distress
On Rick when we reach out to the st. Johns County Sheriff's office they said they could not comment
On the case pending litigation
Big thanks to our producer Matt kielty and Tampa Bay Times Reporter Ben Montgomery
Definitely keep an eye on her website radiolab.org as soon as Tampa Bay Times big feature
Is up we will link you there and it's definitely worth checking out radiolab.org is the address
I'm Jared I'm rubber thanks for listening
Calling from Long Island City in New York Radiolab is produced by dad album Rod Dylan Keith is our director of sound design sword
Turn wheeler senior editor Jamie York is our senior producer our staff include Simon Adler Brenna Farrell David devil
Matt kielty Robert krulwich Annie McEwen glass of Nasir Melissa O'Donnell Arianne wack and Molly Webster
With help from Tracy hunt Valentina bowhunting negara Fateh Ali Phoebe Wang and Katie Ferguson
Michelle Harris