Are you awake
Radiolab
Radio WNYC
All right
Hello
Hey how you doing
I'm doing
You just say who you are real quick before we start
Pat Walters I'm a senior editor here excellent
Where do we start made you want tell me how you got into all this
Yeah okay so it's this series in this all started for me or I got
Thinking about the
The thing we're about to talk about a lot
Because of
This
This moment several months ago where I should have got caught between to my closest
Friends I got
Caught
I get caught
All the time it's really like a political is really hard
Number one
Is it
Guy
I call him a bit of a contrarian politically
And we ended up getting a few arguments by this guy named Jordan Peterson
Precisely the sort of danger that people who are really looking
Who
You probably know he's just come with figures I figure Canadian psychologist to is gotten
Set a lot of things that are very controversial about
Gender and race
Like he thinks White Privilege is a myth and I said we should somehow enforced monogamy he certainly commands
Movement is Big with dudes he's really big with white dude
Yeah and
Best friend of mine is white dude
And so we were arguing about them things Jordan Peterson had said that my friend has liked
And it one point he was
He said to me he would have called me out he was like you've never even listened to the guy talk
Thank you you were having all the arguments about as ideas
And that you've never even listened to
Tulsa okay
FairPoint
I tried to tell her listen to him
And then
Enter friend number 2
We're hanging out couple days later and I told her I'm having a fight with friend number one
Again
He wants me to listen to this guy Jordan Peterson I told him I do it
Just to be fair
And she
I
I got this look on her face
And was like
Why would you
And like why would you do that
And then she said this thing to me that
I that really
Stuck with me afterwards
And she said
His ideas are Dane
And remember thinking like
What makes an idea dangerous
Even stepping down politic in my scientific thinking about the law all these Realms of ID
Yes what makes one so
Dangerous
Or threatening or risky that
We shouldn't even talk about
And so I
I decided to have a staff meeting
With off the radio my people
And ask everyone to bring their most dangerous
Idea
This is a diagram
People brought all kinds of weird stuff that I have a amaryllis and fight them eating their worth
Yeah it's a little tight
Maybe there's
One species that we should just like agree we're going to let go
We only have a limited amount of time energy and money
Stop worrying about the elephant let them all die
In February to just focus on that.
Recycling is pointless
Probably just true
Someone brought a lake
The idea that boys are better at math than girls right
A female staff member brought that one in cuz she heard it from her daughter's math teacher kratoville think that still
Breast cancer screening is pointless
There was something about a law in Nebraska that allows you to drop off a baby that you didn't want
God is dead assisted suicide psychiatric euthanasia
Britain arguing that I like mass incarceration is a tragedy
Ino end of solution would be instead of putting people in prison
We should bring back
Public whippings
So like instead of that's what it was that being sent to prison that's what that's what that's what things evolve to tiny bit yeah
But before they did
More than one person
Brought the same idea
And then this
Idea really
Stuck in my head
I'd like it
We we a group of us kind of became obsessed with that and then
That's the idea that we decided to base the series on
Anna McIntyre
Yet
All right
Radiolab
Over the next five episodes were going to turn things over to our senior editor Pat Walters
It's going to explore this mysterious dangerous idea
You know all kinds of weird places
Wakanda series let's make sense in a little bit
Makonnen
G
There's nothing I love more than picking the lint off my phone
Well
It's like a little game built into my clothing
You're so easy to please
Before we get started I should say I produced this whole series with Rachel Cusick as she's been a true partner on the whole pie
Project so you'll be hearing from her Bunch 2
Infants first episode began with a discovery that she made one day when she was looking around the theater
One of my favorite pages is today I learned
I'll I do love that I love a good if you don't know this is a section of read it and so I went there
I'm scrolling like
Just a general page and then I see a today I learned
Badmind that kind of stopped me in my tracks
Okay
T i l
Today I learned
That it is illegal in state of California to administer an IQ test
To child if he or she is black even when dispensed by school psychologist as part of a professional assessment
Wait it says it's illegal to give an IQ test to a black kid in California yeah that's what it said
Do you cook on it
I totally click on it because I'm looking
To find out that it's fake for sure so I start reading the comments
And they're really bio
Are Reese's
They mostly came from a group of people who call themselves race realist
And those are people who basically say let's just all agree
That white people are inherently more intelligent than black people
Okay so you see these responses you're like
Can't be real
Like my my head was spinning for a little
Yo by
It is the real sons like
After Rachel found that website we started calling around asking people about this and when the first people we talk to is this guy
Name is Brandon Campbell I'm so excited
He's the dean of Student Success at Oakwood University in Huntsville Alabama but back in the mid-90s Branded
I just got the job as a school psychologist in Long Beach California first day on the job
Shirt and short sleeves and a tie and onions first day of his two supervisors they are
Took him aside into an office and told him about this thing called the Larry Peru looks like who's Larry
And why should I be concerned about
And my supervisor memes like well
Like is a fake chain
Oh man
Well it's basically says that
Any kind of dancing around it
But he's like oh yeah because of Larry P we can't give IQ test
With African-American stew
And are these two white men that are telling you this
Yes they are
Yeah they are
Endicott it looked to me like what what do you think
It like put it in kind of awkward like
Up until that moment they're my supervisor now
They're at a loss as to what to do and it talked about
Eventually he says they pulled out a big 3-ring binder
Open data section in the middle Roman numeral
4 page 2
Initial list of about 20 different IQ test
That he was not allowed to give to Black
And I'm reading this stuff and I'm freaked out
Kinds of bass question
IQ test
People still use IQ test
Well wake you and I thought there was something that had been tossed out years ago
The real Beauty
I mean of course you still care IQ test
Talk about by
Low IQ
President Trump
You're going to have a child
Jordan Peterson IQ 6545
Decide
But when we started looking into it
It quickly became clear that
IQ test
Kind of all over the place that aptitude test for the single best predictor of Job Corps
Thousands of companies use them to pick employees every applicant entering the military has to take an ASVAB test
Every branch of the military uses them
They used in the justice system you are past the 70 Mark you are considered
Smart enough
Do face the death penalty
Even in football
And they're kind of massive in school
I'm more than a million kids get IQ tested every year
Do you still need me to figure out which kids will get into gifted programs and which kids will get special ed services
Button California
If your kid is black
They almost definitely
Work at 1
It's all because this larry pithan
Yeah
So then who's Larry p
Yeah who's there EP
Okay so let me bring in Lee Romney I'm an education reporter for kalw radio
And last year she got kind of obsessed with that
The course Larry p is a case
Velocity
The problem was
The guy at the center of that case Larry p
That was a pseudonym
Any actual guy whoever he was
Had a basically banished
No one had heard from him in about 40 years
But
Reusable tracking down
In a small neighborhood just outside Seattle
Play I knocked on the door and it came in
And I said home
Hi
Timely
I'm Darrow
Nice to meet you to turn down his name is Darrell Laster
Welcome
I warned you guys that I'd have you feel things on but oh okay yeah
Thanks so much
He's about 60 years old now
La CPAP and back in the 1970s and he was very surprised that this reporter had showed up wanting to talk to him about
Something that happened back when he was like
Do me a do me a loop but
It was
Happened so many years ago
Do you want to
Sit down over here
We can
Can we turn off the
Yes I got it makes it hard to
Right whenever there's a song
Soclean Darrell sat down in the living room
And we asked him to tell his story
From the beginning
Start back in the 1960s
Okay so maybe go back a little so you're from your from you guys are from Georgia
Yeah we're in Georgia
Did you grow up
Marietta
With how many
Brothers
Four Brothers in
My mom lost her only daughter
So she ended up with five boys
I am the Young
Dirt against in 1965
Not your girls mom your mom was she working
She's a nurse she decide to take the whole family she and her five boy
And move them to San Francisco because she wanted to get away from segregation and this was
A Time
When
The Civil Rights Movement is like
How did the peak end
Man it was so gorgeous they're doing the 60 that was a gorgeous
A little Darryl is suddenly in this like
Radically different world yeah he was in it just a much more diverse place
I had
Some nice get white buddy
My white buddy
His name is Tom
Man played on the 49ers
That was our football team and every day we do our work and then he ride his bike over to my house
And I get on the back of his bike
And we're at football practice so they were they were tight it was just all
Whole Change of Atmosphere
Darrell remember this one time when he and his brother went to the festival
Park
On Saturday January 14th on the polo grounds in Golden Gate Park
A human being took place
It was a gathering of the tribes
A gathering of people
And I remember the police picking us up
Witness on the horse
They got to ride this horse
Overland Park
I remember all of them
So
Everything was going pretty well for
Except
First school
We lived on that
Will slanted street light Kill Light
And then if you walk down the block
And turn right
Is a steep hill
Real Steep Hill you go up that hill
In the school was on
Top of the hill there
That was the first school I went to when we
We first got there
I stayed in trouble
Terrible
The kids was just way too fast
Coming from the country come from Georgia
He said he got teased and he said he would just
Have these outbursts come home and
You know I just
Had enough she said no you're going to school
You're you're going to go and you going to learn
Sweet having a little bit of trouble
First grade
And then one day
In the first grade
Teacher grabs Daryl
And a couple other kids
Pull them out of class
And walking down the hallway
To this room
Do you remember what kind of questions they maybe were asking you in school
For the test they did it all
They did it
All they did all of us
Gerald a little fuzzy on this car
But apparently when he in the other kids walked in there was a man
Standing in the front of the room
Cinnamon pulled out this broom Pre-K
This is never been used
This gun one on eBay
Basement Lounge
The wechsler intelligence scale for children
Copyright the psychological Corporation
New York City
This is the thing that that like
In some ways like yeah it like change this life even though Daryl doesn't remember all the details from that day
Here's how we think it would have gone down
Open it up
The man at the front were taken out a bunch of little green booklet
Okay everybody today we're going to take a few test
And the test
AR
General information General comprehension arithmetic vocabulary
Question and I want you to answer them
Best of your ability 1 2 3
Four five
10 11 12
Test let's begin
I'm going to say a phrase that is missing a word
I want you to finish what I want to say
Can you do that
Okay
Lemons are sour
Sugar Ray
Can you tell me what word is missing
Think of sugar
Sour
Cakes
Uber Chase
Yes
Good sweet
Okay now
Walk with your leg
Throw with your
Think about throwing what part of your body would you throw with
Let's try again
Your leg
Ulrich
Another one
If 3 pencils cost $0.05 what will be the cost of 24
The next one
How many years have you
How far is it from New York
Chicago why is cotton fiber used in making cloth
I want to see how many words you know
Listen carefully until these words mean
Nuisance
What's a music
Nonsense
What is nonsense he said really from the very
The very beginning
He said he did fine in math but he could not keep up with the reading when I look at
It's something and I'm trying to read it
And if I can't
Pronounce it I'm looking at it back
The reality was that he had a reading issue sure it's fair to call it like a reading disability
What is nitroglycerin are you okay would you like some water
It was just like very hard
Yep what is the most important part that says
I got it
Kidding me
So Daryl goes home
Not really sure what happened but
He feels like he didn't do well at it whatever
And eventually
Someone from the school approaches Daryl's mom
It says
We need to put your son in a different class
So the way she describes it in her testimony
Says well I was told that Larry was a slow learner and he needed help you know in his
School work
And by putting him in this class
I was under the impression he was put there so he could get more attention
Started going down
Heal
Intel's new class there were 10 students
It was mostly black
4 boys 6 girls
A normal day
A headache
A straight-up
Headache
Custom kids was loud
Some kids
Obnoxious
Just in care
Dell says they spent about 10 minutes then reading
Pennsylvania map
And about five and a half hours
Outside
And they thought
Calm us down
So they went on a lot of field
Going to the zoo Golden Gate Park
What is this
You know
They wouldn't teaching this
I walked
Schooling cried all the way
In what about time I got
Close to the school I straighten up
Got myself
Madonna into the building
And that was it
It was that bad
Darrell was in that class for more than a year
And then
Fast forward
And when they Darrell's mom is at home
And I should get the phone call but she gets a phone call apparently from
One of the n-double-acp attorneys
And the lawyer tells her that a man named Gerald West
Is going to pay her a bit
He says at West is a member of the association of black psychologists and it's in the way she describes it in her chest
Money
She
She said okay and and then Gerald West
Came over that with Daryl getting a few tests
And it would he was done
She says you know
She says then he turned to me and he says well there is nothing wrong with this child and I said what do you mean nothing wrong with him I'm his mother
I should know
Time is Mom I know there's
You know there's nothing wrong with him even if she did know that you needed reading help
She says naturally I didn't feel good about it and I got angry about it
This is when I really found out what was really going on you know
And then she's asked what did you find out
SNL mom says that he's been designated mentally retarded
That's how she learned that he was in a class
Educable mentally retarded kids
She never known that
What had happened to Daryl when he got brought into that room with the man with the briefcase is that they giving him and I cute
That's what I've gotten him designated
And that this is the term that was used at the time until we're going to use it in the story
Educable mentally
And his mom said he wasn't
But the test was wrong
And that I've been wrong about a lot of blackheads
And so
Darrell's mom
And the parents of five other little kids
I
Got together and filed a class-action lawsuit against the
The school district
Arguing that their kids had been
Scituate denied their education
Viking putting these classes inappropriately because of my IQ test that
Deem them mentally retarded
And that's
Yeah that's her to the beginning of
Rabbit hole
So what ends up happening is like
In the mid-1970s
These parents
The IQ test
On trial
That's after break
This is Angie Crumbley
From Fishers Indiana
Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation enhancing public understanding of Science and Tech
Technology in the modern world more information about Sloane @www.
Sloan's. Org
Paint welcome back this is
GR8 alive mini-series this episode 1 I'm at Walters
Jad abumrad
You were saying that the IQ test was put on trial that's
It sort of seems to be where we're driving to Super interesting but
Before we jump into that
I think it would be helpful to put the trial and the test
In a slightly larger context
Okay I answered you that I want to tell you where the IQ test came from in the first
You mean like
Who invented all the way back to the beginning of the
And to do that
If you go back to France
In the early nineteen hundreds
Yes this is Siddhartha Mukherjee I'm an oncologist and I'm also a writer
In the beginning he has a rose
Out of when I describe them as
Benign intentions
At the turn of the century in France there was a lot going on
The church and state were separating Prime scrape this equal Society
By the way is David Robson senior journalist. BBC future and the Wolf of the intelligence trap
David says one of the things that happened at this time is the government took over the
Schools public education was growing Universal education with pots
Suddenly all kids required to go to school
And within the first few years of this the government noticed that some kids were falling behind
And so
To figure out what to do
They called this cycle
Alfred Pinay in Paris
Set the time we've actually the director of it
Experimental psychology at the University of Paris
Pizza all kinds of things
But he spent the past
20 years or so
Studying child
The French government gave him an assignment
They said we want you to come up with a test
Predict which kids are going to struggle in school just to identify with
Children
What moves OneRepublic SMS
So that we can give the next
I can put them in three years and then when I say Dad is like 3 years
I know we didn't notice that
He's having a really hard time learning to read or do math Albert but I saw it as a chance to benefit
The individual people
Diagnose problem
Special hell yeah yeah
Taylor Simone his assistant at the time
Came up with this test 2
Look for
A whole bunch of different cognitive ability
Starting with simple ones bike
Can a child hold a conversation with the teacher
Moving onto slightly more complex
Such as I'm
He would give the children a list of what
Like how
Fork
Mother
And ask them to kind of recite them back to him from memory middle children draw pictures
And then he had a few harder ones
Like name three rhymes for at the French
Word
Riverwalk
Which is like a bow or curtsy
Anyway these questions
Summer easy summer card
The next thing you did is to give this test
To a whole bunch of kids
Crypto page
And then he compared how they did
Like for all the six-year-olds
How many questions did they get right
On average
Seven year olds same thing 8 year olds
On and on
For each age he calculated the average score basically I Norm normalization as it were
Calling the normal
And then you would compare each kids at Newark
So if your six-year-old and you got the average number right and wrong for a six-year-old
That's your mental age
Sick if you score higher than the average for six-year-old your mental age might be seven or eight
And if you scored lower
It might be lower ultimately that would be to a simple math equation mental age divided by the
Chronological age
* 500
K-50 IQ intelligence question
So that's how they do it yeah it's a little different now but generally how it works is like if your six-year-old
And you get the number of questions right and wrong that the average
6 year old got right and wrong your IQ score is 100
And if your mental age exceeds your physical age
You get higher than 100
What is your mental age
Is less than your physical age you get lower than a hundred
Sabetha basic idea
Felt before Bonet teachers and parents and lots of other kinds of people had been trying all different things to figure out how
And to compare them to their peers
But this is the first time someone tried to measure
Input a number on it
He was very clear that he didn't think
He was measuring
Everything about Intel
This is not the whole picture
I'm just
Measuring
Something
About these kids that helps me figure out
How they going to do school
Explicit about the fact that he didn't think the
Mark and his staff should be considered a covenant thing about
Someone tickles
Brutal pessimism if you type. 1 School
I do think of it as
Defining someone he said brutal pacifism
He believed that intelligence was malleable and that the human mind had
Eunice so many different
Facets
But had to be considered
He was apparently adamant about the
But
As We Know
Good intentions are the devil's toilet paper
It's right around the time but name was doing his thing Charles Spearman who is a statistician who and where it where was he in
What was he doing he was in England it was another psychologist
Neuropsychologist that's different doing research on this topic
I need Charles Spearman who came up with the theory of intelligence that the name
Would not
Look at your hand by the way my name is
Sure Richie I'm a psychology lecturer at King's College London he's the guy who told me about all this
And according to him Charles Spearman
Li keqiang
How to work with kids
Given lots of tests
And he noticed
Describe counterintuitive thing that in a Hadith
You know I mention that IQ tester asked me many many little test salt lamp together
Like you got vocabulary math all these different subtests
What time
Human shows in his
And I will see you solved
The tests where they all seem to correlate positively together people who to one type of test
Tend to be good at the mall
Say I want to see how many words you know
Listen carefully and tell me what these words mean what Spearman notice
Is the kids were good at vocabulary tests
What is a bicycle
Do kids were also likely to be good at reasoning test I am going to show you
In which there is a part missing
Tell me what is Miss
And pattern recognition look here and you will see a star a ball a triangle and other things
Speed test
Memory tests I'm going to say some numbers
Listen carefully
All the different kinds of death
People who are good at 1 or are good at the mall
And he saw this as evidence of
Sensor underlying mental energy underlies
Their comfortability
Instrument called the the concept of
G
And this idea that
This sort of general intelligence Spearman notice
Did other scientist noticed it to know yeah yes
Verses in the decade since Spearman first noticed this phenomenon has been proven
Again and again
And again
To be true is essentially one of the best replication findings in the psychological which
In the moment
GID I got walked out into the room by Charles Spearman
This is the moment that Pandora's Box
Ripped wide open
Because out there were lots of different kinds of intelligence is intelligence wasn't
Complicated
Do justice one kind
Spearman believed we each had a certain amount of it
Sometime we were born
And if that could somehow be measured
We're now being used as a social construct
Classified people
Rather than help individuals
This is exactly the same thing they warned against this is that brutal pessimism
Keith never got a chance to speak out against the testing use this way
He died in 1911
And in the years after his death
Got the teens and 20s and 30s
IQ tests were given to millions of people
Used to decide who should get which job
We should be allowed to immigrate to one country or another
And eventually
Who should be institutionalized
And forcibly sterilized
Get the thing we haven't mentioned about Charles Spearman and a lot of these early intelligence scientist is
Are you jealous
And so the whole early history of IQ testing is wrapped up in this ideology
These guys thought they could selectively breed people to create some kind of Master race
And we're going to go deep into that part of the history and future episode
Out with that
Avila Miller what are the creators of invisibilia
Type to say once I Q tests were being used to pick people to be sterilized
It just
Kept getting worse
The measurement
Was Central
Do the Nazi Doctrine
Off improving the human race and in their case it marched onto
Exterminate the Nazi version of eugenics started in the mid-1930s
When did begin forcibly sterilizing and then executing thousands of people that they've classified as
As mentally ill
Disabled or
What they called feeble minded
Meaning that they scored low on an IQ test
This program was called T4
And it was a precursor to and essentially a training ground for the mass executions of Jewish people
Are over the next several years would become
Hawkeye
So-so in the span of just about
3035 year is Hugo from
Something called G
Do selective sterilization mandated by a court
Two selectively extermination
Mandated by the state
And that happens in the span of 30 years
Given that history
I kind of expected that after World War II
IQ test
Gone away
No
Here in America America
Particular around that time in the post-war
Pierre was a very
Quantitative Society
Economy is booming and we are best with measuring thing
Your height during regular qunar biometrics
Turmeric of weed double down on used bike Utah
Reason for everything to track people you're mocking people for the right jobs making sure they get to the right schools Etc set
Petra there is a kind of efficiency clause in this which is you know let's make the society more efficient by
Allocating the right resources to the right
It's okay by the sixties and seventies mukherji status
That was the situation
Did really seeped into the center of American culture
With the trailer
Just about IQ
In the school systems of every state in the Union
One form of intelligence test to another are given each year to at least 10 million children of all ages
Big impact on their lives can be a normal
What get the trial is right around the time Larry P bumped into the test
People had finally started to push back against
The Civil Rights Movement was in full swing
Antique group of young black psychologists had stepped up and said hey
Has a problem
Not only because of its history
But because of the way it's made now
The test did not
Consider the experiences
And the backgrounds of minorities or black children or
Children who
Did not have a white middle-class background they were culturally
Pacific to European American
That psychologists Brandon gamble again for him Harold Dent who's one of those young black psychologist who started pushing back
Back in the 1960
And think that the problem was
Remember how I told you that I Q test is normed where they give the test to a whole bunch of kids
Encounter scores together to start to figure out the average score for each age
Well at the test makers
I only use white kids
If you'd set up one standard
Everybody doesn't meet that standard enter these black psychologists would like
What about 9
Skip that child is not from that cultural framing at cultural experience
They may give different answers
IQ test scores did not
Deal with the background and experiences of black children
Which is what this lawsuit ended up being about
I just filled in California today about intelligence quotient test a lawsuit has been filed
When says that IQ tests
Discriminate against black children because these tests
Okay take a picture to try to imagine ourselves into day 1 of this trial like what do we know
We don't lose a federal case so it was in US District Court this is Lee running again downtown San Francisco
You know just a couple of blocks from City Hall do you know what the room would have looked like we know from the court sketch
That right behind the witness stand with a giant American flag
You know that the the judge seated there next to the witness box
Robert Peckham hiza
Mostly ball
Gentleman wire rim glasses spoke
Someone quietly you got pick them up at the front and then the lawyers for the families
Number of attorneys
One thing you just heard
Armando menocal
Extend the trial Armando had only been aware for about 4 years
I was the only lawyer that was in court everyday
Myself
And the chief lawyer for the state Rose 12th of October of 1977
Pokemon for 7 months
10000 pages of witness testimony
10114 pages
Turn
Oh my god did you go through all of it
I did but like I whipped through some of it one of the first big things that happens is the plaintiff called this guy named AC
The halyard
The late dr. ASA Hilliard he had been the dean of the school of education at San Francisco State University
The big expert on racial bias in education until
Yep yep so Hilliard gosip
Dan get sworn in and Hugh
You have a second I'll try to find and one of the family boyars stands up and picked up this body exhibit
Pete 66a
And walked over to the Sea
And then he says let me hand you this black box and ask you if you can identify this for the court
Says this is what the actual Beast looks
Books like because of the Beast
Yeah
And so Hilliard says right this is a kit for the wisc
The wechsler intelligence scale for children
AKA
The Whisk which was the main
Test that was being used
In schools
Okay so this
This is Madden again you're just like explain what this test
But what exactly is it at Connecticut
Hilliard says
Right
Let me try one
There's going to be an actor right so do you want me to reserve a round
But the actors going to come by just have you read a butter stuff okay
Maybe I shouldn't pick number
The Columbus Day but take this question from a section called general information
One of the items about general information is
Who discovered America
And the only two possible answers here on Columbus and Leif Erikson
And of course there are some people would have a little disagreement with that
Any answers just being like wrong Hilliard brought this one up
Went out that this isn't a test of like
Thinking
Ability this is a
Acquired knowledge
We give it another day
Who wrote Romeo and Juliet
Shakespeare
Yeah good job thank you and they say Tchaikovsky
Tchaikovsky's also acceptable
Tchaikovsky Romeo and Juliet
See I didn't know that
I didn't know that the people make these tests what explains you at the point of a question like that
Is that a lot of kids won't know the answer
A question number 16 so it's supposed to be hard
The point being on there isn't that like
Knowing that information in particular is especially important
But the Pacemakers have figured out that the kids who get that question right
Are more likely to do well on all the other parts of the IQ test
Because that G Thang
We talked about before
The problem is
There are all kinds of other variables at play here
Like where do you know who wrote Romeo and Juliet
Say something about your intelligence
But it might also just be an indication of whether your parents told you about Shakespeare
Or whether you learned about him in school what right do we have to expect children from some areas of the country of
Some areas of cities
To spend time studying about Romeo and Juliet
And who argued this acquired knowledge problem affected a whole bunch of different parts
That would be the same thing here on math
Show me children and not had the opportunity to have good math instructor
They are going to be compared with children who have had good math
Instructions
Then to me you have an economic cultural bias that's represented in there
The same thing would be true with similarity
Vocab
For example
For example you're supposed to be able to answer the question
In what way are salt and water alike
Okay
In what way do they have to
Comcast
Compounds
That make them a thing H2O + NaCl
I mean I would say I mean the first thing that comes to mind for me is like
Together Rachel you actually
Got the high score right out of the gate okay so here it is
You get two points
If you give this answer
A response that indicates that they are both necessary for life
Or that they are both chemical compounds
So those are the only two answers
That you get two points for
If you say that they are both in the ocean you didn't know point
What
How do you say that you can drink both of them you get no poi
Points if you say salt comes out of the water there isn't a single right answer
I'd argue that my answer was just fine
But Hilliard explained that the Whisk favors a certain kind of
There's an arbitrary decision about the nature about the nature of the response
That will give you two points in terms of its abstract he said the wisc
Arbitrarily favors
Abstract sounding answers
Like
Salt is a compound
Andy asked
Why is that any more intelligent
Been saying salt
It's from the ocean
This is where the cultural bias
Comes in again
In point wise thinking abstractly in this way
Is as required as
Knowing who wrote
They argue there are big parts of the test that do measure things that feel way more like
Your thinking ability
Did the memory test work and just have to read back at you
Numbers
Pattern recognition test that just involve looking at shapes
There's a picture completion test where kids test appointment with missing from a drawing
But
For every part of the test like that
There's another part that feels way squishier
And are the test where you see racial bias most blatantly
Is this one called comprehension
This is Brandon gamble again in with comprehension they may ask somebody kind of a moral Quest
Kid is given a hypothetical social situation and asked how they should respond
Like what should you do if you cut your finger
Wire Criminal
Why is it generally better to give money to a charity than someone begging on the street
Or why should I
Promise B cap
Lorenzo's like a lot of the parts of this nasty questions don't have a single right answer which means they can be biased
Towards people
Answer the question in the way the people who made the test
Think it should be answer
Which is a big problem if you don't think the way the people made the test thing
Brandon told us about one of these questions that he I ran into when he started working at the school
Psychologist if you found somebody's wallet
Like sitting on a shelf in a store what would you do with it would you give it back to them you know try to search the mountains
Find out how to give it back to them
Or would you
Leave it alone or
Keep that money need correct answer is
Find the store manager and give them the wallet
But Brandon Tony
He would not have answered it that way
I've waited said you don't have and I'm not touching cuz they probably accuse me of something
Because you're black
And you know what I've been in that situation
I went with a scouting group and my mother was director of The Scouting group
And we were at
A science museum
I'm a nerd I didn't realize it back then how much
When I was
But I was wearing my scouting uniform which had this shiny belt buckle
So I keep
Try it it but I get smudges on it
So
I'm looking at my belt buckle
And they're thinking I'm stuck in my pants
So are you ready gets call
Oggi's
And I have no idea what's going on but my mother does
My mother thinks you're not strip searching
My job
When is Brendon says
If your blackhead and you see that question
You might think
Clearly the correct answer is
Leave the wallet where it is
Really what the
With is measuring is
Assimilation into American culture and how well you assimilate as a predictor
Not so much
Your actual intelligence and what you know
So at the family's footboard a bunch of argument saying the test is racially biased
And then the state
Get up
And have to defend
The.
And their argument
Basically goes like
There's nothing wrong with Tess
That they are just as valid
You know to use for all the american-born English-speaking kids
Psychology professor at the University of Missouri and it's in a bunch of research on the Larry P case and bias in test
He says it's not enough for test question just to feel like it's biased
You always have to go back to the data
And say what does the data say and does the data bear this out you have to prove statistically that it
And a lot of these arguments the data just doesn't bear it out so it's like take that question who discovered America
According to Craig to prove that that question is biased against the save black children
You have to give that question to a group of white children
And get the same question to a group of black children and show the black children
Are more likely to get it wrong then the white child
And Craig says
The families in Worcester
Didn't do that you know you're kind of going to shooting in the dark a little bit well this could be this could be so when
Whenever you try that kind of
Given ad hoc
Explanation for
What you see
It's not a scientific
Enterprise
But the reason ironically that didn't exist is because like we said before the IQ test that was given to the kid
It's like Daryl
Was only normed with only standardized
Unlike it
And everyone admitted that no one had attempted in the testing companies
Had attempted to validate the test
4 black and white
Still Craig says the state argued the families didn't have the data they need to
Prove their case
Statistically
But the date of the state did have
Craigslist
Show that when you give IQ test black kids
You find the entire range of scores that you see in white kids
So a test we're truly biased
Against kids because of their skin color their race and you would never have examples of
Of African Americans who get high scores on IQ test
And you would never have examples of white kids to get low scores
On IQ test said like if black children can scored very high on IQ test
How could they be bias
You have the full range
But
Even though you see that entire range
You see something else too
The means
The averages
Differ
I'm group the group the average shift down
The average score for black kids with lower than the average score of white
What the results seem to say about Americans
Blacks as a group
Scored 15 points lower than whites
So if the state were saying there's no bias
What explains that
Discrepancies
One of the first things that people will say that the poor gasoline
On the issue is vasayo
If you're saying the test
Are not biased and that means that
This group is genetically inferior to this other huge controversy happening in America at this time over
For that very idea
An old Theory
Originally revived by psychologist Arthur Jensen of the University of California
Is it better stay that your position has been
Black Americans a survey
Or not as intelligent
Egg white
By my definition of intelligence yes I would say that's a fair of State
And defend the state actually tried bringing this argument into the lawsuit they had introduced it in
In some of the pre-trial
Paperwork as a possible
Defense
But when they're getting ready to go to trial Wilson Riles
The state superintendent of Education who was the name defendant in the case and happened to be a black man himself
Stuff is
Rapist and disgusting and vile and I can't be a part of that and I especially can't have the state be a part of the
That depends never directly brought that argument up in trial
And that was kind of the ghost
In the room and even leave the state
Funny tried to shuffle that argument back under the rug the family's lawyers wanted to
Prove it
Out in the open
What we were attempting to prove is that
That test
Mislabeled blacks as being intellectually inferior
That Armando menocal again and he says
Take out a bunch of different Witnesses
A whole parade of experts
Medical background
Historians many psychologists many education experts to show in court
There's no evidence to support that theory
It's just
Not true
And then eventually say
And there's three times more blacks in classes for the retarded
It either means a black sword genetically inferior to whites
Which they just spent weeks disproving or the test of discriminatory eventually get down to the IR either or
That was our goal in cross-examination
And
We called every one of the states
Employee
As adverse Witnesses and cross-examine them
And it was one encounter with the Department of Education employee the main guy
Within the department in charge of the classes for the mentally retarded and IQ test at Armando says pretty much
Stop everyone in their track I pretty much got him into a corner where he basically admitted
Yes
He believed that there
Were more mentally retarded black people than white people
And packing goes wait wait wait wait are you saying you really believe that there are more blacks who are mentally
And the guy said
Yes
October 16th 1979
Did Beckham issues his ruling
He just comes right out and says this court finds in favor of plaintiff
Daryl
Is Mom
Five of the family
1 case
Dependence of utilize standardized intelligence tests that are racially and culturally biased
Have a discriminatory impact against black children
And have not been validated for the purpose of essentially permanent placements of black children
Into educationally dead end
Isolated
And stigmatizing classes
For the so-called educable mentally retarded
He says we must recognize at the outset
The history of the IQ test
And if special education classes built on IQ testing
It's not the history of neutral scientific discoveries
Translated into educational reform
It is
History of racial prejudice
Social Darwinism
And of the use of the scientific quote Mystique
Illegitimate such prejudices
Defendant's conduct
In connection with the history of IQ testing in special education in California
Reveals an unlawful segregative intent
To dumb it down he's basically saying they they proved everything that they set out to prove
That this was just a disguised
Form of
Segregation in under the guise of science
A group of Black Folk
Sue the state in one
How often does that happen
Question
Mrs. Lester how old is Daryl
Answer
Daryl is 18
Question
Mrs. Lester
I know that you have a plane to catch
Is there anything else you might want to say
If the sum of your feelings about this case
Lucille
Sum it up
I feel like it was a rotten deal
I really do
Because if I had an understanding in the beginning that Daryl was put in a class for the mentally ill
Retarded children
He wouldn't have been there in the first place
I would have went further
I'm taking him to the doctor
Find out what I thought anything was wrong with him
I feel like
To a certain extent
And even in his attitude toward people
Certain people have changed because he feels like he has been pushed aside
Feels like he has been discriminated and things like that
Come and told me
And I have to try and straighten it out and tell him what I feel is right about
At the end of the Atkins decision Brenda Campbell says
He put a ban in place no IQ tests are given to black children to make decisions about special education
In the state of California
By the time this case ended and judge Peckham issued that band years have gone by
Daryl the kid who set this whole thing in motion when he was in elementary school was 20 years old
Wasn't even living in the State anymore
His mom was still had moved the family way after things have gone so badly for him
Score
And that's really the last anybody heard from Derek
Decade
Until
Remind me came along
Say it maybe they've been reported we spoke with from kalw
Because I should start reporting on this
She kept wondering
What happened and everyone was saying now I have no idea and
To be honest nobody seemed
Terribly
Interested you know and I cuz everyone talks about it
Larry p is
A case
And she was like
What about Larry p
The person
Utah she ended up in that little house outside Seattle
Hanging out with Daryl last
Everyone who works in special ed in California
They all talk about the Larry Peak
Which is me
Yeah
So do they know me they don't
So and I don't know nobody had ever asked him
Not only not I asked him about this nobody had ever really told him
Like about it
This
And when I came up there and I had the ruling in my hand this was the
Just the judge's ruling it's like a hundred and thirty pages long
But it go
Was my face
That's my case it was just sort of like
Like I didn't really expect this
He was he and his wife were both like happy to have me come up happy to
Hear about it
Really
That you're here
I feel kind of Honor
You know and what actually did happen to him after the ruling
So I'm right after the lawsuit was filed actually his mom moved him and his family up to Tacoma Washington
I moved here in 71
Mom was like where I am
Yep they had an older brother
You have been in the military and he was up near
Tacoma
Sew-in weave
Moved here
I had like a
Third grade
Reading level
And I was in
The eighth grade
And then it was time for high school and pretty soon they say we're going to put you in a special lady
Half a day program
What was that
He was back in special ed program well
Yeah yeah get up in the morning
And
You going to go over there
Safeway
Safeway the grocery store
And they say yeah
I went to
Safeway
Had to be there at
7:30 and start work at 8
And I work
From 8
Toll lunch time
Were they paying you
No it was
Credit for my God
Wait that's a thing you never heard of that
Eventually his stepfather complained and got him out of that program even though Daryl was like terrified to just be dumped into the
The general population because he didn't have any foundation
Not for them type of classes
No
But he was thrown back into General ad
Without any help
And I he squeaked by for a few years
Moving you from grade to grade
Eventually graduation rolls around I miss my high-school diploma by
To credit
In
.
Nockamixon
Nowhere world
After that he moved back to Georgia for a bit and then he started partying a lot
Drinking
Smoking
Just all kind
He definitely had some substance abuse issues for years now
So that it was just sort of low and it was
A lot of
Really hard
Physical
Work the best job I had
Is when I was working
Kaiser number
Before I got hurt
Then there'll told me a story that
Just kind of showed how this thing that happened to him when he was a kid
Never really let him go
I got hurt on the job
I got slammed into a wall
And threw them back all out of whack
Currently he had received they sent me a letter I can workers comp decision letter saying that he
Would be awarded benefits
But
He said he took that letter I threw it in the trash
I didn't know cuz he couldn't
Read it you know
Hard to put in words
I've lived this long
These many years
Lack of reading
You know
There was
Things I needed to learn
That I didn't learn
And he still
I struggle with this sometimes
I'll be down here by myself so I come downstairs and he's
Cream for crying
And they say grown men don't cry that's a lie
And I should say
Daryl life is tough but it's not all bleach
Has a daughter
He's happily married
CU MIT we grew up together
Yeah we grew up in church.
Yeah that's how we know each
In a choir Are Family
25 years
We've been together 25 years
Long time
You know so they both sang in this church choir in that sense
Bae said he's been clean summer about 18 years
And so
People talk about the case and
And here like there's this fully dimensional
Human being
That
Seems like the
The case of merely
Mingle2
My life
Might not be like
My friends
That you know got better jobs
Nice homes
Not to say I don't want that
You know because I do
But
It didn't come my way
But I'm content
Right now
What what I have
So
Here today
You sitting here talking to me
I'm happy
I'll tell you over and over again
I'm not ashamed
Of who I am
I am
Daryl yuan
Gene Lester
Born 1950
E8
December 20th
From Marietta Georgia
And I am
Here
Still living at
59 years of age
And the band the band that the Larry P case led to
What happened to it
It don't life
Still in place
Yeah yeah
This whole situation that Daryl got caught up in as a kid
Has
Completely change the class that he got stuck in those classes are
Argon in anything anymore
And the test
That
Turn of shovelton into that class is band for black
And the judge didn't say
Banette for everyone or revise the test
Tobias a tester whatever he said just don't give it to Black
Yeah exactly but if you're white kid or if you're a Spanish didn't get her Spanish kid or ESL kid
You can take it and that's still in place
Yeah still today
It's like I
I hate this word
I would feel like this word just like
Hides all kinds of
Things
Anyways I just find that
China problematic
You are not the only one who feels that way
It is racism
In school district
That's not right
It's not right
In the next episode of the series we're going to return to the case
And look at all the weird way that played out
Now
I'm also keep wrestling with this idea of
G the measuring of human intelligence with IQ test
Trying to figure out what it really captures
And learned that despite all of its horrible history
It was behind solving one of the biggest public health problems
The 20th century
That's coming up
In episode 2
This episode was reported and produced by Lee Romney Rachel Cusick and me Pat Walters
Music with by Alex overington fact-checking by Diane Kelly special thanks to Elie mystal
Dominica Amanda Stern little panic
Is great Nora Lions Keystone from KQED public advocate's in San Francisco hour actor
Michelle Wilson Peter Fernandez and John Schaefer and of course
Todaro Lester
Radiolab G is supported in part by science sandbox
Assignment Foundation initiative dedicated to engaging everyone with the process of science
Oh and one last thing at the end of every show we have a listener read the credits
I realize I was really proud that listeners all over the world and we would love to hear you on the show
If you're interested in recording a credit to go to radiolab.org
5 credit it's super simple
Radiolab.org
Flash credit
Thanks for listening
Scenery
Play the message press to start of message
Brandon Campbell
Dean of Student Success at Oakwood University in Huntsville Alabama
Radiolab was created by
Jad abumrad it's produced by Thorne wheeler
Found tonight
Do you like hamburgers or executive producer
Staff includes Simon Adler
Becca preysler
Recusal
David gemmell
Bethel happy
Tracy hunt
Matt
Guilty
Robert krulwich
Annie McEwen latest Nassar
Melissa O'Donnell
Reny
Walters & Molly Webster
With help from FEMA only ie
Audrey Quinn
W Harry Fortuna
Samuel
Imani Leonard and Neal
Don Asher
Are fact checker
Is Michelle Harris in this message