I am Robert krulwich Radiolab is supported by the Netflix film they'll love me when I'm dead
This is the movie The Chronicles the last years of Orson Welles is life he's the genius behind Citizen Kane it's
Wildly entertaining full of nuance and depth
They'll love me when I'm dead
Directed by Morgan Neville only on Netflix November 2nd
Weight units
Radio WNYC
Hey I'm Jared I'm Robert krulwich this is Radiolab and today we are we're celebrating
A multiple set of anniversaries because it was 80 years ago 80 years ago that Orson Welles
And the Mercury Theater
Decided to allow martians to invade the state of New Jersey
One of the most famous
Broadcast in broadcast history because it freaks
People out
Yes
Nearly 10 years ago we decided to take
Another look at this broadcast which has gotten very complicated and Laird
And disputed in some ways overtime we are now celebrating our 10th they're celebrating their 80th so
Along with Orson Welles when I couldn't be here tonight
We would like to present
Our homage
I guess two microbes
He hasn't had to do the little earthlings that save the planet right so in honor of the microbes and honour of war the
The world which broadcasts 80 years ago today
Tonight here is our take
On War of the World
October 30th
I'm at 9th United States
Experience the kind of math
Stereo
Do we never see me fall
And the reason
What's today's sounds almost comical
Was a radio play
Affiliated stations with Orson Welles and the mercury theatre on the air
In the War of the Worlds
Around 12 million people were listening most got the joke
It was Halloween after
But if you consider that about one out of every 12
People didn't get
The job that's what surveys found after
That one
Every 12 people who
You heard the broadcast thought it was true
And it's some percentage
That 1 million people ran out of their homes
Towels over their faces clutching children tripping breaking limbs
Well that
Constitutes a major freakout
Inducer
First ever live our on Radiolab. St. Paul Minnesota at the Fitzgerald theater we asked
Why
Why do people panic
And of course we'll ask the big questions what which is
Can it happen again
I'm Jared I'm rotten thank you all for coming and where is my
College
So let me let me just say if you had said I'm just a tiny bit puzzled
Which is my name
And I
With all due respect I mean if we had
Any number things
We could have done in the hour
Sex lives of watermelon
Chrysanthemum
Why choose a martian Invasion radio show
From 1938 old old
Valquest USA
Truth is I accidentally discovered the world
Recently
In 2001
Maxine not long after that day in
It just
Really struck me
It wasn't
So much that the broadcast had a kind of end of the world Miss
I guess we're all feeling in real life that moment
It was more just the way that the
Story
Unfolded
And how in the broadcast you felt like you were
Lost inside a news
Which is not unlike what it was like Concerta
What was going on
And that's that was very much
I think what they were trying to create in the broadcast but
Now many years later
What I'm really left with Issaquah
Well if I were alive
Turn up the radio
I heard this sound
What would I say
What I believed it
What about you
I don't know I don't know
Okay well let's do something
Sexy go back tonight.
And see if we can figure out how these sounds landed on people's ears and what information they have in their heads
Say I need your help with this
I would like help with
I want to go over to that seat right there that's we're going to call that seat 1938
All right there
Okay
Hey now just let's just all a match
There you are and your easy
Charrier
Maybe drink
Cream soda
Tune the dial
I've got something on the dial
From the Meridian room in the Park Plaza Hotel in New York City we bring you the music of Raymond Raquel
Who is Rick
Raymond's Run
Spanish
You don't know that there's no such
Person is Ramon Rec
Hello
Set the record in a CBS Studio but it sounds professional enough so you sit back you relax
But then
Ladies and gentlemen we interrupt our program of dance music to bring you a special bulletin from the Intercontinental radio news
A 20 minutes before 8 central time
Recessive Jennings Observatory reports observing several explosions of incandescent gas
Occurring at regular intervals on the planet Mars
The spectroscope indicates the gas to be hydrogen
I'm moving toward the Earth
Playing for you in the Meridian Hotel
New York
So at this point you think
I'm thinking explosions on Mars hydrogen gas moving towards our it's a little strange but how could it be so bad if
If I still get to listen to The Fabulous notes of the lovely Raymond
Continue to play for another minute 34 seconds
It happens again
Why does he travel in following on the News Bulletin the moment ago
Getting further let me ask of really basic Quest
Dealing with Apple
Radio play
Why would Orson Welles and his
Passive
Starter play this way
The original it
HG Wells story
Was written in 1898 so was really old book
Time and there is no reporter character in the book by the way
Does anybody know this War of the Worlds story are most people do
The store base was this little green creatures from Mars for a number of reasons have to do with thirst
Is there something have to leave their planet and they come to Earth they're not very nice
People
They invade they destroy quite a number of us
And then Ironically in the end
They get killed by little viruses are smallest inhabitants are planted
Bite them and Destroy them
It's science fiction of course but in 1938
Most kids knew this story was a very popular
So I don't see why
Orson Welles producer the time John Houseman
Austin and I chose it
We decided time to come we should be doing up
Science fiction show I'm so we
Try to fuse it run very easy to do in just a few days before they have to be on the air with their next installment John Houseman
That book off the shelf
Shows at owa says hey what about this
Orson Welles
Says this
You want me to do this
But he had trouble in what sense in the sentence
If it was something that happened 50 years ago everybody knows it didn't happen
So who the hell cares
How to make people care about the old story we've got updated
1998 1930
And it just so happened
One month prior something had happened that forever changed the world and the news
You always at
Will begin with this man
Hitler was threatening Europe first Austria then Czechoslovakia World War II
Turn on the corner in CVS send a team of guys to cover the story among them Edward R Murrow
European country
And in September Morrow and his CBS producer did something with the news that
What kind of novel
They broke
In this program of music
Never happened before
But never quite like this
Life report
Discount and never quite so much
I'm just one month these buttons become so numerous program to bring you a special broadcast that bulletins were practically
Interrupting bring you a special broadcast
These constant interruptions it's easy to understand why this play
Didn't sound like a play
Astronomical watch on any further disturbances
Occurring on the planet Mars
We have arranged an interview with another the astronomy Professor Pearson.
In a few moments we will take you to the Princeton Observatory at Princeton New Jersey
We were 71 pill then the music
Isn't it interesting how slowly it start
What time do you got on your
Your
Watch there
Add a pocket watch says
Eat
Tell me
When it gets the 805
Fatal Five
Pans
Now this is
My favorite minute
In
Understanding one of the greatest media hoaxes
What times do the thing that's interesting
Is it at this moment in
October of 1938 Orson Welles and the Mercury Theater of the air
We're not that Poppy
They had a tie
Tiny
Tiny slice
Of the Aria
It's a not too many people were listening certainly not at the beginning from 8
Forced into not too many people heard
This
Very
Columbia Broadcasting
Was that the War of the Worlds
By HG Wells
But why why didn't I hear that
Well good at that very same moment
The majority people listening word tune into this
The Chase and Sanborn hour
It had the puppet Charlie McCarthy
Opposite Mercury Theater Viera
10 * 8
At 8:05
Host Don Ameche introduces
Not so popular singer
And just at that moment
1200 we don't know how many listeners started to dial sir
Where they landed on the Mercury Theater they are already in progress
Where they stay but we already know
Because by then
A strange
Meteor hits
Where Carl Phillips are commentator will interview Professor Richard Pearson famous astronomer
May I begin
And anytime is closed
That living intelligence as we know it does not exist on Mars
Better chance
Is against it a thousand to one
And yes
How do you account for these gas eruptions occurring on the surface
The planet
Canada consulate
Kneaders on
Meteors on Mars March
Meteors
What meteors on Mars and just as you are utterly confused Along Comes The X
People surveyed afterwards
I didn't
Believe this thing I thought it was all bologna until I heard that government official guy or the Princeton professor
And this script
Chock-full
Unbelievable
Natural History Museum
Enrichment Captain Lansing of the signal card
To convince people that something was in fact happening
A Feeling
Furthered a moment later when the professor
The reporter Carl Phillips Goliath
To that field
In Grovers Mill New Jersey
Meteorite
Whatever it is
Atlanta
Metal casing
Definitely Extra-Terrestrial
Not found on this Earth
The Earth's atmosphere usually test holes in a meteorite this singing
The end of the thing is beginning to flake off
Papa
Calling someone
Something like
Black holes luminous desk
The eyes are like their face might be on the timer
Something out of the Shadow like a gray snake
That's going to be shape with saliva I hate you
Me before we get too far into this
See let me play you a another clip like some great feather
Read message
All the humanity
This is tape of the Hindenburg crash
Still fresh in people's minds happened one year before the black
Before going on the air that night
Actor Frank Reddick who played
Border collie Phillips the field
Went to the library Doug up
This old
Taper not-so-old inflated to sew
All the humanity
Over and over
Baby girl
All the humanity
Baby girl names of Rights
Frame of mind for that now famous
Maxine
Nestle in New Jersey
Those pictures know what that means
What anything means
I got a small beam of light against the mirror
Transmission cuts off
12 million people
Have just heard
Slithery green aliens eviscerate
Policeman
Farmers
And reporters
Followed by
Nothing
Ladies and gentlemen go to circumstances beyond our control we are unable to continue the broadcast from Grovers Mill
Evidently there's some difficulty with our field transmission
However
We will return to that point of the earliest opportunity is it that grounded Flying Saucer that is that
Well this man has now stood up
It's as tall as a tree and it is marching
Through the countryside
Dumping everything in its path and then we are taking two
Field Report live battle scenes between militia and pause before we do
Let me play
One more
But this one is real
I wish to have been evacuated
You should send him to school
Tomorrow Friday
With hand luggage
Containing the child gas mask
A change of underclothing
This is Edward R Murrow reporting from London same time.
Just to give you a sense of how scary it was to be alive
At this moment
Kids in England were being told to take
Gas masks
To school
All of which would have made the following dramatize battle scenes
You take you now to the field headquarters of the state militia
Grovers Mill New Jersey
All the more real
37 degrees
Hear the New Jersey militia
Fire on a
Fleet of Martian pods
24 meters
Theirselves bounce right off
In the Martians in retaliation release date
Cloud poisonous gas
Slowly overtaking soldiers
Ladies and gentlemen I have a grave announcement tonight
Incredible as it may seem both the observations of Science and the evidence of our eyes
Lead to the inescapable assumption that those strange beings who landed in the Jersey farmlands tonight
Are the Vanguard of an invading Army from the planet Mars
The battle which took place tonight
A group of males has ended one of the most OP into feet ever suffered by an Army in Mountain Time
7900 rifles and machine guns
Hit against
The single fighting machine of the Invaders from Mars
129 survivors
Virginia
How much does now in control of the middle section of New Jersey
Effectively cut the states
Highways to the north south and west of clogged with frantic human-friendly tsunami reserves are unable to control the Matt's lights
Communication lines are down from Pennsylvania to divide
What's the time in service discontinued. New Jersey in Easton Pennsylvania
Increasing speed North Andover houses
This time we take you to watch the Secretary of the Interior
Feel the gravity of the situation
Oxygen cylinders
Calling all over the country this is the end now no more defensive
Everything wiped out
Exactly how many people panic
What we do now
Trenton
Police Department
Got 2000 calls in under 2 hours
The New York Times switchboard received 875 calls alone
From people
Wanting to know where they be safer
On the roof
Or in the gas raid shelter
The cellar
We're lucky we do have
Transcripts what happened on the other side of radios that night thanks to
The Princeton sociologist
Who went out and conducted a series of interviews after the broadcast
And what's amazing is how effective that broadcast was some Lister said
We actually felt
Like they were choking
Others reported to police that they saw with their own eyes as they go to the Manhattan skyline they saw
Hudsonville smoke from the battle over the city
Some said they sought Martian machines high-stepping their way down the Palisades splash splash splash
And many people when they called operators are police they didn't say oh my God we're being invaded by Martians
They said oh my God we're being invaded by
German
Here are some of the literal transcript of this is what real people
Actually said
Is everybody ready
I knew it was some German
Trying to gas us all
But when the announcer kept on calling them people from Mars
I just thought he was ignorant
I immediately called up the Maplewood police and asked if there was anything wrong
Dancer
We know as much as you do
Keep your radio TuneIn
I called in to my husband
Dan
Why don't you get dressed
You don't want to die in your working clothes
I looked in
Xbox on saw some chicken left from Sunday dinner that I was saving for Monday night.
Set to my nephew
We may as well eat this chicken
We won't be here in the morning
This is Orson Welles ladies and gentlemen
Out of character
To show you that the War of the Worlds has no further significant
But at the Holiday offering it was intended
Is the B
We annihilated the world before your very is and utterly destroy the CBS
You will be relieved I hope to learn that we didn't
Minutes
And the bothans
Institutions are still open for business
That was how Orson Welles concluded the War of the Worlds broadcast with those words
Basically
The joke
Gotcha
But it was only after he and his producer John has been left
Austin read the papers the next day
They understood just how much trouble.
Sweaters very disagreeable because
Of
For at least
A couple of hours
We believe We Will mass murder
Surprised to learn that
Victoria has become familiar to children
The meaning of comic strips
And
This is wells in the press conference that following day
Mini
Speeding
Novels an adventure story
Had such a profound effect upon radio listener
So immediately so profound that the FCC commissioner of the time
George Henry Payne
Labeled
The Mercury Theater the air get the
Terrorists
Radio terrorist
But there is one thing we must not overlook
All this took place in 1938
NLS sophisticated yes
I did not know the atom bomb guided missiles
A rocket ship made shortly fly to the moon
Eva demuro 1957 with correct
Really so unsophisticated in 1938
I mean so different from now
Wow
Let's see
We interrupt this broadcast for some breaking news this just in
It seems we may have gotten
Few
Things wrong when we perform that show many years ago most notably just now when I said that the FCC
Ochsner in 1938 called Orson Welles
The radio terrorist
In his statement
He certainly suggests that but if you read it it seems he was actually referring to a statement he made about a year earlier where he was
Who's calling
Radio producers
Who terrorized
Children he doesn't actually named Orson Welles by name
Just bought that
My apologies and we have this guy to thank for bringing it to our attention Michael sokolow and Associates
Professor
Journalism and communication at the University of Maine
Mike sokolow also makes an interesting argument at the panic
May not have been
Is largest we made it sound
For example
We stayed the 12 million people were listening on that night which is a widely
The quoted number
It comes from polling
6 weeks after the war of the worlds first aired
Stoklosa specs
The actual number of listeners is way smaller that's no way to know for sure
Petrus
Poll conducted
That night
That night when the broadcast was on 5,000 Americans were survey
By the c e Hooper comp
The reading Survey Company
Why are we bothering with
Study done six weeks later after the newspaper tells everybody that there was this giant panic
Why don't we look at the surveys that were done that night
And the survey that was done 12 hours later by CVS the following morning what are the two surveys immediately after say
The CEO of uber rating survey
Thumb 98% of the respondent
We're not listening to Orson Welles War of the Worlds they were listen to the Chase and Sanborn hour or the radios were off or they were listening to in
Another program
Of the 2% that they found
That we're listening to War of the Worlds
Not a single respondent thought it was a news broadcast
Sokolov strongly suspected
Panic was actually trumped-up by the newspapers
Who were trying to sort a piss on this new medium called radio
It was taken away there you know
Audience exactly
Here was the opportunity
Radio
The radio industry in the newspaper industry have been battling for years and throughout that decade
The entire newspaper industry had been losing
Money political Prestige and other things to the radio in the
You know some of their best employees
And so they were waiting for a way to really
Prove Advertiser
Improve the federal regulators
They had the first amendment
They understood responsibilities of the newspaper manager
These radio guys were conflating advertising with programming they were frightening their viewers they were acting irresponsibly
And remember this is a month after Munich when radio proved that news really works
On the radio
Well one month after radio news Pino comes of age
Suddenly there conflating news accounts
With fiction
And they're acting irresponsibly new terrorizing the public
And to the newspaper industry had the perfect thing to hang their critique of radio on
To all those
All those
Eyewitness accounts that
The panic and I thought it was this and I packed my bags and whatever whatever and all the sort of
Reports
People miscarrying do you feel like that's all
Memory embellished or what how do you clean up that I may give you let me give you an analogy okay
If you were asked 100 Americans today
Did you see a plane fly into the World Trade Center outside
September 11th
I think you would get an extremely high percentage
People saying they saw that plane fly
But that's because it's part of our national visual memory
It's really a trauma and it's it's it's the kind of Hysteria Panic or talk about that moment in time and our relationship to the media
Okay
But if you were to actually find out whose TVs were on live at 9:48 in the morning that day
And who was actually watching
It would be a discrepancy in that number
Now am I saying all those people are lying
All those people are
Confused
Know what I'm saying is that the relationship
Of memory to the media is extremely calm
Complex indeed and we think Michael sokoloff for checking her facts
And if you believe as he does the 1938 Panic was
What didn't happen it wasn't as bad as
Is it sounds that actually makes what we talked about next in our life Broad
Even more puzzle
We'll be right back with radio labs live
This is Lily from Lake nebagamon Wisconsin
Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloan
Hat www.zearn.org
Hi I'm Robert krulwich Radiolab is supported by the Netflix film
The other side of the Wind
Which is the last film from legendary director Orson Welles it's the story of
Director GGG candleford comes back to Hollywood after years of semi Exile in Europe
Complete work on his own Innovative comeback movie which as it happens is also entitled
The other side of the Wind
It's a cinematic event 40 years in the making the other side of the Wind
On Netflix and in Select theaters
November 2nd
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help this summer I'm hosting a show
And I request for those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
We're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments
Brilliance basically I want to hear about those times when I kid you know did something
It just means you bring back and say whoa how did they do that maybe it was the moment that a kid
You've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons and you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin
Maybe the kids in math class you noticed they're ready music in the margin of their geometry homework we're interested in
Epic moments where a kid does something super smart but it doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story please share it with us
Go to radiolab.org Brilliance and record a short audio message for us
Again that's radiolab.org / Brilliance thank you so much
This is Radiolab on Jedi from rod iron Robert we are in st. Paul Minnesota from the Fitzgerald theater
Our subject today is the War of the Worlds
Broadcast originally on October 30th
I'm going to ask the house for a show of hands do you think that
Somebody else could imagine the broadcast using the exact same script more or less
Also with martians also invading also interrupting the musical things
Same to you
After all the publicity for the 1938 broadcast
Could you do it
Twice show of hands
Please
Some of you don't think so
There wasn't another one of these what would we be doing for the
Those of you who raise your hand
You are correct
It has
Again and I want to tell you story it and amazing
Another reported
Story of a War of the Worlds
Reenactment happened
In the mountains of
Quito Ecuador 1949
We were very lucky we had a reporter Tony Fields who have to be traveling there we have to do a couple of interviews
And he brought back some taping
Play it for me
Alright so tell me set the scene for me 1949
Where is Quito Quito is the capital of Ecuador
Go to Iquitos
In the middle of the mountains in the Andes Mountains
And Motown Big Town
Keto now is a big city
At the time it was a pretty small City
The word that everybody who I spoke to use to describe the way the Kita wasn't 1949 with tranquilo
Exactly it is what it sounds like AM radio Quito
Was the most popular radio station
Everybody listen to it
Does your basic ingredients
You got a small town population 200
1000 station
Which also happened to be in the same building as
The one major newspaper El Comercio and the leader of the radio station
Kia devious
Fellow by the name of Leonardo
One day someone shows up with a script for Orson Welles not HD Wells Orson Welles version
Leonardo Pia series it says
We got to do this hearing
They insert local place named Jocelyn set of the Martians Landing in New Jersey they would land in Coca-Cola which is on the outs
Taquito
They write in parts for government officials and minister of the Interior the mayor of
Keto
Pictures of real death would be back
Doing impressions during impression
Not only that
Highest goddess boss
At the newspaper El Comercio
To agree to run little articles in the newspaper in the two days leading up to the broadcast
Reporting that
Strange objects
Have been seen in the Skies over
Marketo
Wow
So he set out to screw with people
He was
Planting paranoia
It really seems like he wanted people
I believe
What they were hearing that
Okay so Saturday February 12th 1949
The day of the Bride
All day long
Listeners hear an announcement
It is going to be a special performance
Like a Duo benitez valencia
Benitez Valencia
Where are one of the most popular musical acts in town
Are cockroaches around Benitez Valencia
Launches into their performance
They play a few song
And suddenly
There's any corruption
What was that
Well it turns out that Leonardo pies in addition to the other trick he had up his sleeve
He had a sound effects guy in the corner
Creating
The sound like when a Garrison keillor's guys kind of thing
The Music Stops and Leonardo Paez comes on the air and says
These dear listeners excuse
The technical difficulties there seems to be some sort of atmospheric conditions interfering
With the radio keep the signal but you are listening to radio keep.
Brought to you by you know such and such and
Now back to Benny despondency
So we hear another couple
Who songs and then there's another interruption
If Leonardo tires again this time
This time is the news flash
So now run script has out to
Report from the scene
Empire is doing the play-by-play you know what is this
Waiting on my God the cops on scooters in your combat tentacles
And here come the heat red
And that
Tires in scribe
You can wait wait wait wait do we have
Forget reenactments do we have
A copy of that the real broadcast from that night all we have our description
There is no existing recording
What was broadcast
That night and and you'll understand why in a second
By all accounts
It worked
Outsiders Shear May everything that happened next happened
Extremely quickly
Poured out into the streets
People were running
But they didn't know where to run
The spaceship supposedly was in the north of the city but this black cloud of gas was in the South and
Klonopin actually did what any good Catholic would do
Babe
Made a beeline for the church
The church because because they were difficult would be safe there or Hap's or perhaps they just wanted to
Get right with God before the world ended
They're even reports and I wasn't able to confirm this but the reports of man confessing to adultery right there in front of their wives
Increase volume
Whole trout
Google Google panni
Annette Garcia
Poquito
This is Jorge who is a longtime journalist with for many years at the newspaper
Do the thing with his family
They all believed it they all ran outside found a taxi cab
Who the kids in russom ran behind the taxi cab
Gazelle
Going the other way
Convoy
Military trucks
Filled with soldiers
RealTracs real military band real military bands of the real soldiers
And cops behind them and they're screaming
Towards the north of the city
Where they going
They're going to cut the cord how to fight the Martian
Yeah so if you if you had any doubt it
Once you saw this military man Siri like
Oblique
I've got to get the hell out right
Is everybody in keto believe didn't someone call the General beforehand say tonight we're having a boy
Dave the mayor or someone who sounded an awful like the mayor was on the radio saying martians renovate
The maiden call the General before I know now so so then what happens at the end of the show
They always do
Then what
Well they storm the radio station
By the time I broadcast ended and it was announced that the whole thing was a play huge crowd
What's Rena Street
And word that was a hoax
Spread pretty quickly
All that fear
Turn pretty quickly to anger
By 9:30 is he's a few hundred people outside
The station
At some point the boxer shows out there just been a match in the Central Plaza in the box of shows up he's driving his truck
And the truck is full of rocks until of what rock is full of rocks
And people start
Hurling The Rock
At the station at the windows
I'm Windows of shattering they managed to break into boat to the ground floor with a printing press
They're smashing printing presses
At some point some people in the crowd materialized and they have fees flaming torches
It just goes up like a match the clothes so so where people hurt during this
6 people died
Really
Most escaped there's about fifty people in the building most
Got to up to the roof
Jump two adjoining buildings butts
People died
According to a reporter Tony
One guy
Stay behind
The last guy on the air that night was a man by the name of Louis
Beltran
3 are you there yes I'm here
Okay this is Maria Beltran testagrossa
Louisville trans daughter
Maria
You were listening to it to everything that just came
Before this
Tell us the story from your dad's perspective from here
Forward that will he was he was on the air he was so I guess hosting the music program and also doing some of
The interruption with the with the bogus stuff
At the point at which the fire started what was he
Sing
When you realize the magnitude of the situation he went back on the air and began pleading for help
Pleading for assistance from the police and the fire department but
As you said before no help came because the police were going
The fight the Martian
Yeah
And eventually he was the last one left
And
And he
Jumped out the window I've got from the either the 3rd or 4th floor onto a
Second floor balcony
And to break the fall I guess
Instinctively want to break the fall he grabbed onto the railing of that balcony in
He was completely engulfed in flames at that point
And
Skin on his hands just remained on the balcony it was like a barbecue grill
And from there
He jumped
To the ground but before he jumped he
With pleading to the crowd to I guess catch him
But they didn't
He landed on cement
Broke legs
Arms
Ribs everything and
Compounded by the very very serious
Burned paddle over his body so he landed at the feet of an angry mob what
An angry mob and he
He recalled
That says he's losing Consciousness he just heard somebody say just just let him die in peace
Although some of the articles that I read they try to
Frozen back into the building
Really someone grabbed him and put him in a jeep
To take him to the hospital just a bystander
And he had so many scars here
As children like my brother and I would
We play with his scars you would Trace them with our finger and ask him what happened you know how we got the scars and he would tell us
About the fire
What would he tell you the whole
Storey or story he would just give us
And Justin broad term that he had been in a building that caught fire
Stop as children we didn't really ask him
Maybe had we been older and ask them he would have told us the whole story
We should say that your dad stayed behind
To try and help other people get out of the building
Let me ask you a question though
Eudoxie is a hero
But given the fact that he was one of the voices that
Created
The panic
Did he feel some sort of ambivalence about
I don't know in retrospect whether he did or not I'm sure they must have been some ambivalence
But from what I understand a story was kept it was very top secret so that even the employees did not know
No
What was going to be broadcast during that music program
I don't know what what point he was informed of the details so I don't know really how we felt about I wish I had had
Opportunity to ask him
Who is Maria thank you so much for your time and joining us here
Thanks
I just want to know what happened to the guy who planned the hose
Well he
He got out through the roof like a lot of others he hop to the next building
Hit out for a few days
And then fled the country to Venezuela never to return
Never to return never to return but I should say that
Among the six people who died that night
What's his girlfriend
A nephew
Okay so the 1949 keto broadcast caused a whole lot of trouble the 1938 New York broadcast call
Was a whole lot of trouble not everybody here before who raised their hand and thought that this could happen again
You are right
Again
Thou
Buffalo
Updated for the time it sounds kind of like your basic DJ set
Until you hear this
Anime shop in here that I'm supposed to read thank you
Li keqiang
Administration those people
I've alerted all their space watch and
Facilities to be on the alert for unusual communication difficulties tonight I supposed to be for the federal agency referred to the
Explosions on the planet Mars and said he was not knowing that they would have the same
Effect on Earth medication December explosions on the surface of the Sun
Sunspots and things like that so
I don't know what action other means it's going to be hard to hear Communications from NASA.
Are KB whatever Jamaica by communication
Structure as the original
Broadcast we heard tonight
Long stretches of music than the news bulletins in the semi realistic
Field reports use one of them
Pictures of martians
And according to the station manager JFK
You get the same outcome people
Bought it and Telephone Company reported to WKBW
But they received more than 4,000 phone calls
Canadian military authorities dispatched military units to the Peace Bridge the Rainbow Bridge and the Queenston Bridge to repellent
Story was tired the next day by 47 newspapers and Countrywide
And on the night of the shelling during the show
Can I press bureau's up and down the east coast of America where besieged by phone call
Asking about the Martian invasion in Buffalo
Incredible
You're absolutely right it is incredible
Thanks to the folks at WKBW Buffalo for that what is this music
This is the Disco version of War of the Worlds 1978
Obvious question to ask
What is the skip work
Well if that's a difficult question I came across a psychology
I'm Richard Gehrig Imo
Professor of psychology in
Experiment
Apple program
Here's this notion Richard
Does it rude people are suckers
The stories we just cannot help ourselves
When is Story start
You just kind of go
The norm is to fall in
Story and that it
Unusual
Keep yourself
My favorite example is there's a scene in Goldfinger
Boom boom
Best James Bond
Where bond is
Tie downs
Spread Eagle One app
Piece of metal on
Laser cut
Really looks like
And even if
Saying that right now I'm starting
A little bit of anxiety
Spoiler alert
Dustin Ackley
Go to watch the movie now and see if you can get through that
Suspense it really seems to say something
Pinkberry
Powerful
Armstrong
About how
Immerse weekend
To become in
Panera
This is Ashley a stack
Calling from Modesto California
Radiolab is supported in part
By the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloan at www. Sloan. Org
This is Radiolab on Jedi camera
Is the sound of 700 people who have come to Bear Witness
Can I record a live show today we are at
The Fitzgerald theater in st. Paul Minnesota talking about the strange phenomenon that is the War of the Worlds
You know I ate is very greatest everybody's he request but this
There's one guy I really wish had been
Is that at the Ecuadorian die Leonardo what's the tightest yeah
Because
He's the guy want to ask
What were you
That's what I want
Well he's dead
He's bad news well but how old was she and what were you thinking
Dead
Daddy
So I found a guy who I think is definitely alive
I am Daniel Myrick
Co-writer co-director of the Blair Witch
Before making the Blair Witch Project and my record a recording
King of the world
He was a teenager
I just thought it was
Brilliant
Absolutely
The coolest
Saying I'm with anything else he was impressed by the
The technique of the thing there's a couple moments in particular where they cut to the
On-site reporter cut in a second or two early
And you hear the report of saints are we on
And then he goes into his
In the character
Here I am.
This is little pizzas little mama that really
Guilty
Excitement when I when I know how it affected
He was fascinated by the idea that scary stories get even scarier if you think they're true
So
Years later fresh out of film school he and his friend Eduardo Sanchez
Has decided to develop
Their own Wells like product your basic scary witch Story 3 kids go into the woods
Okay we're leaving
Right now they got lost they bump into the witch
And then that they die or they think they die
Here's to never see them again
But when you entered the theater to see The Blair Witch Project the first thing that you see on the screen are these two sentence
In October of 1994
Three student filmmakers disappeared in the woods near Burkittsville Maryland
While shooting a documentary
A year later their footage
Was found
So the suggestion here
Is that what we see
Might be
We are what we picked a subject matter that was difficult to disprove
To the casual
Observer
Martians invading from outer space
Can you turn the channel to the next Network and if no one's reporting about it
Pretty well I sure it is probably fiction but
3 missing students in the woods you know that's something that is a little harder to disprove
Without a fair amount of scrutiny
And
It works
We were getting
Calls from
Police wondering where these
3 kids word
I never heard of this case you're killing oh yeah
Constantly still getting emails
What part of
Still any phenomena
Burkittsville in
All fix
When is all made
I think it reinforces what I thought
Ed and I suspected that
So much of us
Wants to be
Some people told Dan Myrick that after watching the three campers go in the woods
They themselves would never go camping
Again
That was fabulous
Why would you not want people to go camping
Why would you do that to people
I mean that's why you're doing it to me know you are not making this movie to kind of scare people
We were making the film to
Really scared
No regrets on people not wanting to go
Camping afterwards
So the question is is that what Orson Welles was up to back in 1938 was he just trying to get p
People are good old-fashioned
Show Business care make him scream way up in the balcony
This was
Simply
An entertainment this is Orson Welles ladies and gentlemen
Office character
To assure you that the War of the Worlds has no further significance
When is the holiday offering everything 10
The Mercury Theater Zone radio version of dressing up in a sheet and jumping out of abortion sing boo
16 years later Orson Welles change
The story
Here is on the BBC the year is May 9th
We weren't as innocent as
We meant to be
Why did the Martian broadcast we were fed up
Was a way in which
Everything that came over this new magic box
The radio is being swallowed
Turn away or broadcast
Was there an assault on me
Credibility
Day of that machine we want
Do you understand
But they shouldn't
Swallow
Everything that
Cancel the tap
So here are two ways to think about
The War of the Worlds 1
It was a smashing entertainment using every trick they could think of including inventing some new ones
To scare you silly Master storyteller
Or
4 +
It was
We're trying to send you a warning don't trust everything you hear on the radio it's not always true
Which one was it
You think
Well I asked
Professor Jason lives with me
Yeah you Jason pimp
Hefei radio historian at the University of
He says that what wells understood
Was it a newscast
Is Austin two things at once
The newscast
You here
Something scary order
Disturbing sometimes
But it's going to be told to you
In a way that suzhou
Meaning the authority The Voice the newscasters steady voice coming through the radio
It will calm you
Like President Roosevelt
Famous Fireside
My friend
I want to talk for a few minutes
The people of the United
States about spanking
When you study the rhetoric
Ted Roosevelt
He really did convey to
Messages 1
We're in terrible Danger
Into
I've got a
And that is the
The sort of the the
Authoritative voice
Coming out of
The darkness
Visible
Disembodied
The powerful man
The news on September 22nd
Octopus with marijuana
Standing on a rooftop
Flipping out over London
Straight in front of a noun
Yogurt to sounds in just a moment
Keep giving us
A story of an unfolding emergency
I should think in a few minutes or maybe a bit of shrapnel around here
But his Mastery of information
His Mastery of his own voice
His bravery on the scene
This was the beginning of
The format
A fear
Formatting
And some people go
To the news
Not to be afraid but
To be afraid and then to be
Reassured
Robert
You file things for the news
Do you buy this that a news
Reporter
Does these two things simultaneously
Scares and then reassures and then scares
Google cover the governor and say
Let me know what I would do that why else would you talk
Me not you
The Forum in Avenues is a
Because the guy is always there because he's an anchor that's what the word means
It is a reassuring thing to see them night after night
Telling and telling Butler
That the Real Genius of the War of the Worlds was that Wells put you
Into news
Will you expect anchors to Anchor and you expect reported to report
I meant
He kills the reporter and the anchor
And suddenly your left all by yourself in your own living room all alone
That is exactly right
The moment of the War of the Worlds broadcast which still frankly terrifies me
Is this moment right here
It's like that silence is terrifying
No anchor
No reporter
No-one to
We assure you
Okay
Forgetting up remember what about the second lesson that has a
Something about don't believe the radio
What about that
Did it work well professor says if that is really what wells was trying to do if you believe that will then he fell
Failed actually worse than
The War of the Worlds not months
Not twice we push on you three broadcasting
It was so good at grabbing an audience and sucking them in
At the wills formula you might call it the newscast that scares you enough to keep you listening has been adopt
To buy a Volvo
News companies
Right now at 11 at night of shopping turns into a night of fear
Muslim immigrants
It's a deadly mix
Terror in the toilet and sinkholes and landslides
Lights on in the car.
Baby go terrorist working at one of our airports
Terror in the toilet
Pythons in the potty
Maybe there was a snake somewhere near a toiletry facility of some kind but it's
Probably wasn't the python
It probably wasn't your toilet but you don't know that you want to hear that belongs to mrs. James C McGill
2214 Bode Boulevard and not you so
You you want to be reassured and so you listened and so you fall in
Any Orson Welles retelling a martian Invasion Story by HD
And most people already knew
If he could grab
And if I could do it again in Ecuador
And then if they can do it again in Buffalo
What is that tell you it tells you
And we can't help ourselves
Even if the headline is slightly proposed
Even if it's slightly scary
Even if it's slightly
False
We will listen
The fear of that these broadcast generate now
You suck I said and you think that 70 years later we be more sophisticated and critical when did local newscaster tell
Tells us that there's something we're feeding our children that could kill them and they'll tell us after the news
I still listen I'm a media critic and I still wait through the commercials to see
What is it that I'm doing the can my child even if it's really employed what your shoelaces will kill you
After this beat
I somehow it gets me everytime
Yeah and Wells new
I am json
I'm still calling from Seattle Washington Radiolab was created by Jad appenrod and is produced by Soren wheeler
Dylan Keith is our director of sound design Maria Montessori Padilla is our managing director our staff includes Simon
Adler Becca bresler
Rachel cusick david gemmell bethel hoppity tracy hunt not guilty robert cray
Annie McEwen
Lots of Nasir Melissa O'Donnell area and whack Pat Walters and Molly Webster
With help from Shima ODI cats Laszlo and mow other BMO are fact check