Are you awake
Listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
All right but tell us who you are
I am needy Mom we are in Hopkinsville Kentucky for the great
American eclipse
We are about a minute to totality look I can see it even when I'm even
When it's not on we can hear the cicadas
And we
I don't even have my sunglasses on I can I can
Still can't look at it
What do you think of this way
Looks like a storm coming in
Jupiter
Oh my God
Nothing there you look it up
Susie Duran
Holy toledo
Oh my God
Hey I'm Jared I'm Rod kush's Radiolab
Answer these last few weeks on planet Earth
In this corner planet Earth have been a little confusing
Little crazy
But then there was yesterday we all got a chance to look up
Look up at the sun people said this recordings from all over the place
Helen Georgia Nashville Tennessee Kenmore Washington
Watching the moon pass right in front of the sun that's the moon in front of the Sun
The moon blocking the Sun
They got to see you hear these recordings and you can't help but think
Going to be alright
Beautiful
Oh my God
Silk
In honor of the celestial miracle
Today we're going to keep looking up
But
Not in the direction of the sun when you look up at the sun you have to put on these glasses to you too to protect yourself from
In the sunshine
Sunshine is very powerful
Stretches across vast
Vast vast
Vast distances in space
What we going to do with the ends Travis we're going to leave the sunshine behind we're actually going to escape the sunshine
What humans have never been before right
And we're going to start
With a story that
I've been falling pretty much my entire career Radiolab
You can have to run back 1977 SS not when I started
Following story that's when the story itself started
In August of 1977 NASA
Launched
A spacecraft and on the craft with a gold record
And the record carried a message this is a message from us
To them
Out there
Our story it was Carl Sagan Cosmos
Is all that is
Or ever was
Or ever will be
Led the team that made that record of that team included actually was headed by
A woman named
Android
10 years ago
I spoke with an e and we made the story you're about to hear
Visit Annie at her home Ithaca
New York and we sat in the backyard near waterfall
In the same spot she says where Carl himself would say
And become so absorbed in what he was reading that he would not notice a deer
Right
Next time my name is Annie Drury Inn
And M
I was honored to be the creative director of the Voyager Interstellar
Message project
Which began in
Early 1977
Come about
I think about the project now and
And so
Exciting to think about I mean it's such a romantic idea did you know that at the time
Absolutely felt
First of all that this was a kind of
Sacred
Trust
Bad here we were
Half a dozen very flawed human being
Wave that you just huge
Holes in our knowledge of all of these subjects
Building
Cultural
Noah's Ark
It was a chance to tell something
What life on Earth was like
Two beings of perhaps
A thousand million years from now
Because they
The Voyager Engineers were saying This Record will have a shelf life
A billion years
That didn't race
Goosebumps when you have to be made of wood
I was also the but the
The season that Carl Sagan and I fell so madly in love with each other
And here we were
Taking on this method
Challenge
And knowing
It before it was John
Two spacecraft
Would lift off from the planet Earth
Moving at an average speed of
35000 miles an hour
For the next thousand million years
And on it would be a kiss
A mother's first words to her newborn baby
Beto
Greetings in the 59 most
Populist
Human languages clothes from the children
Planet Earth
As well as one Nan Yuan language did
Waiting for the humpback whale
And it was a sacred Undertaker
Because it was saying
We want to be citizens of the cosmos
I want you to know about that
Tell me what the mummy found love with Carl Sagan you said it was during the Voyager compilation
Yes it was it was June 1st 1977 I've been looking for some time for that piece of Chinese music
Take that we could put on the Voyager record and not feel like an idiot for having done so and done
I was very excited because I finally
Found a ethnomusicologist composer at Columbia University
Who told me without a moment's hesitation
That this peace flowing streams
Which
Was represented to me as one of the oldest pieces
A Chinese music 2500 years old
What's the piece we should put on the record
So I called
Carl Lewis
Traveling
He was in Tucson Arizona giving a talk
And done we've been alone many times
During the making
The record and his friends for 3 years
And neither of us had ever
Said anything to the other we're both in popular people
We had a wonderful
Storing conversation
But
We should both been completely just professional about everything in his friends
Ndk
He wasn't there left a message
Our leaders
Phone rings
Pick up the phone
And I hear this wonderful voice
Did he say I get back to my hotel room and I find this message and it says
Any cars
And I say to myself
Can you leave me this message 10 years ago
And my heart
Sweet lady
Skip to be
I can still remember it so
Perfectly
And I said
For Keeps
Did he said you mean get married
And I said yes
And you know
Even have any other kind of personal discussion before
We both hang up the phone
And I did
Read out loud I remember it
So well cuz it was his great
Eureka moment
It was just like a scientific discovery
And then the phone rang and I was thinking phone
It was Carla he's actually make sure that really happened we're getting married right
I said yeah we're getting married he said okay
Just wanted to make sure
And done
Spacecraft lifted off on August 20th and August
XXII
We
Told everyone involved and we were together from that moment until his death in 1996 in December
Wow romantic obviously
Part of what I was feeling in the recording of my brain wave
My heart my eyes everything in that meditation on the record
I have Carl whether or not would be possible to
Compressed
The impulses in one's brain and nervous system
Into
Sound and then
Put that sound on the record and then
I think that perhaps the Extra-Terrestrial
Of the future would be able to reconstitute
That
Data into thought
And he looked at me
Beautiful
May Day in New York City and said well you know
Thousand million years is a long time you know why don't you go do it because who knows you know who knows with
About twenty thousand million years
And so on
My brain waves and REM every little sound that my body was making with
Recorded at Bellevue Hospital in New York
This was two days after
Carlin die
Declared our love for each other and so
What I often think is that maybe a hundred million years from now it does somebody flags that record an and
I always wondered because part of what I was thinking in this meditation
Was about The Wonder of love and of being in love
And you know it's on those two spacecraft
Goodnow inmate whenever I'm down
Yeah I'm thinking it's still they move 35000 miles an hour
Leaving our solar system
For the Great Wide Open see if Interstellar space
Billions of years from now the sun will it reduced this planet to a charred Ashleigh Ball
That record with Androids brain waves and heartbeat on it will still be out there somewhere in tact
It's a remote region of the Milky Way preserving a murmur
Ancient civilization that once flourished
On a distant planet
That's how we ended the original story
It helps to BRC the 40th anniversary of the Voyager probes launched
Between the two dates were Pro one pro tour launched it's a weird thing about the anniversary and
A Preacher Man around chick called up and running again and they got to talking about the fact that we still
Scientists are still talking to those probes that's the thing that gets me
Here we are 40 years later
Are we still in contact with Voyager 1
We still know
We born to run into our
We were able to build something
So well
Deputy energy
Which is essentially
Morphe people
Any energy in a
Toaster
We can communicate
Voyager
As she leaves to wander the Milky Way galaxy
Intact
With a message intact well
The same engineers said it would work
Forgotten years is 40 years and it still work
So coming up we're going to ask
Where are they at
Where specifically are those two probes
Now and the answer is
They're in a very
Very very undiscovered play
EBay
I learning things
That we have never known
Skyways riding talk to you
Angleton sunbeams ride downtown
Play this is Becca I'm calling from Dallas Texas to let you know that radio
Do you like it supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloan at www.smud.org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help this summer I'm hosting a show
And I request for those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teacher
We're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments of childhood brilliance
Basically I want to hear about those times when I did something
It just means you lean back and say whoa how did they do that
Maybe it was the moment that our kids you've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons and you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed are ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the
Specific moments where
A kid does something super smart but it doesn't have anything to do with the test
If you have a story please share it with us
Go to radiolab.org brilliance
Record short audio message
Again that's radiolab.org / brilliance
Thank you so much
Hey I'm Jared I'm Robert krulwich is Radiolab and now we're going to ask where are those Voyager probes
Right now this is a story with bun
Falling forever in about 5 years ago
Producer Lynn Levy
Begin to ask yourself that question where are they because at that point
News was starting to Bubble Up
That the that the Voyager probes
We're about to tiptoe their way up
Cross a truly amazing
Threshold
And at that moment it wasn't completely clear what was
So here's what we reported them
We're going to break in a certain point in update things even further but
Lynn began this story where the last one left.
Okay so would like in the point of the mission wasn't really to deliver this record it was to go out and look at
All the planets in the outer solar system
So starting in 1977 these two little spaceships to spacecraft
Voyager 1 and 2 went racing away from Earth snapping pictures
And so every time
Where should we reach another planet
You know all of the Voyager people would get together
Going to the Imaging room and see the pictures
Come from the outer solar
Do you remember seeing them
I remember the child saying Life magazine in Iowa
Voyager was launched
This is me.
Professor at Boston University as a grown up she became part of the Voyager team
All the pictures
But you know as a kid
You look at the books in to see what how Neptune look
Revelations
Saturn the image of Saturn taxicaller I like pink and reddish turquoise color
Yellow nose ring
Just
Spectacular
They could see active volcanoes on one of the moons of Jupiter
Finally that vision of Neptune like a blue juul
Really blue
It's all
Came from voyage
We have no idea how they look like
Neptune was the last
Big cool planet and it was the last thing they were
Photograph
After that the camels were going to be shut off
To save energy
But
Carl Sagan convince them
Turn on Voyager back door
And take a final picture
So on Valentine's Day 1990
One of the ships
Luly Rocha
It's it was facing back
Earth
It snapped a picture
One last picture
Describe
So
It's
Mostly empty
Pretty dark
You can see certain streaks of light
Coming from the Sun
And then
You honestly wouldn't notice it if it wasn't pointed out to you but down in one corner
Kind of a suspended in a Sunbeam the ways of very small. Blue
Pale blue dot
That was us
In Carl Sagan's words
Everyone you ever knew everyone you ever loved
Every superstar
Every corrupt politician
Everyone in all of history everything the sum total think of the river
So that one indistinguishable group could
Have momentary domination over
Fraction of that Pixel It was one of those really rare
Images every single day I'm here from people who take that pale blue dot
So deeply to Heart
What to do with a complete reframing
After that
The, what sound off
But here's the thing
Bishop's kept going
Drifting through the darkness
Even though they weren't taking pictures anymore they were using like their other senses little instruments that
Text like how many particles are around what the temperature is so they were hurtling through this empty space really fast
Measuring
Sending that data back
And scientists like that off with their listening
For what
Was not clear but they knew at some point these capsules would get to the edge
The edge of what the solar system
The solar system has a big spider has an edge it's a it's like a bubble
Sean has a wind every start of the wind but the sun has its own wind
It blows out through the solar system can be between 402
All the planets and
Keeps everything else out
So these little things are cruising out towards the
Edge wherever it is scientist don't quite know where it is or what it is
Because the control room or like Panama shift like hey what's
What's up what do you see
Nothing
How about now
Not much
How long before the X
14 years
Oh man that's like driving
Kansas
But like a million times worse.
There Comes a Day end of 2004
Where
They stop listening for a little while because the antenna and that's only has so many antennas Matthews into listen to everything
So for a little while the boys are teams like okay you guys over there can use the antennas we're going to lunch
It's been 14 God damn near knocked yourself out at school
And they come back few hours later start listening again
And
Happened very sudden everything is totally changed all of a sudden boom speed of the wind
Drop them around 380 count to a hundred
Instantly I just all-in-ones density and then everything out there started to get
Poland
And before
Articles also behaving a very different way
And the fields are very
We are
The fields and magnetic field
So just like the sun has a wind system has a magnetic field as well the field starts at the Sun and then curves out in this
Kind of graceful Arc through the solar system rotates
Create what people called by levinas
Cart
You know how like a skirt with a flare if you spin around real fast that's
Apparently kind of what this
Field looks like
Way out there
It seemed like a skirt
Started
Freddy
Maybe tear a little
Threads
Broken often seem to be floating around on their own not connected to anything
So
What is this song
Fields are breaking down in
The wind is dying down inside the wind is what exit
Create the space solar system
This mean we're out to know
I kind of thought that was always happy
But no
It's not out
And it's not
Quite in
It's in the
Edge of the bubble
India but it's not like
It's a thick
The catch the edge isn't just a little line that you cross
Place
And while we listen to the to Voyager ships moved through this Edge
For several years
Then something very interesting happen that the wind on which one
Stop
Lie completely stopped
Yeah
So now we're out no no
I mean this is what people thought
But the other measurements like temperature and number of particles
Text field doesn't tell us
Nature surprise.
Again
So now we think there's a place at the edge of our solar
Customized at the edge
Shove the edge
Utterly still no wind at all
Pause
People Akinator
Stagnation layer
And there is a big discussion why this layer exists
And housing
And by how thick it is she means
When will it end
Because
Once we get past this so is anything ever crossed
The Foundry Buffet
No this will be the
First man-made object
To leave
Any Star
And the voyage was like right there smiling touching that Bounder
You know you only do those things
First one
Like your first
Your first taste of alcohol
Your first time driving a car
First time you see the ocean
Open up a whole new world
Going to freaking app
It might have happened while we were talking that was thinking from now any moment now next
Capital Moses
Or 3 years from now
It's closed
Everyday open my Google alert for Voyager and I look and see
Did happen today before the show goes out of me pissed yeah everyday
The first thing you do in the morning
Like the Thursday
He left that story at that point five years ago it seemed like the Voyager probes were in this
Weird
Liminal space
Kind of stuck somewhere in the edge
Of the edge
Of our planetary neighborhood
Transition moment
Could happen at any time that's where we left it
Which seemed honestly kind of frustrating like we did the story too soon
You know what that happens every so often
So we decided to call merav opher back
She's a scientist you were in the story who is part of the Voyager team
To pick up the story like what happened
Okay so since then we will waiting right and his stories is
Fascinating and a little complicated to
Because this was back
In 2012
Right Jesus shortly after our story was released couple of months later
So was in August on August 2012 but six months after
Name
Particles this was
Fascinating the energetic particles
From the Sun
Dropped
Some people thought out no sun particles that must mean we're out
Couple of days later they came back
And then there was the same test as before
And then they dropped again
It's almost failed that somebody had to open a window
And I close a window and then open a window and window so was kind of weird
Spectre classic Crossing
It should be sudden it should be all you're in or you're out you don't have this intermediate
I mean I'm out that mean I'm out I saw so this was not the classic textbook and was very
Women like Ayo what's going on
And there was very heated discussions because
You know you're waiting to say to the public are we really cross the solar system for the first time or not
And we can Jose
Super frustrating scientist started arguing
Me there's a bunch of conferences and meetings where they got together and the scientist essentially broke into faction
One faction
It was like we are out
Another faction was like no
Where in
And she says it one of those meetings
There was a vote are we in or are we out and and I and I just felt this is crazy this is such a mess
Major
My stone exactly
Did we really arrived to America's evolved
And it was just crazy they did vote and the vote
Was still well inside
So towards the end of 2012 that's what they thought we're still in
But
Something change and and the something is a sound we were hearing
Around the time these arguments the Voyager with sending back
Sound doesn't have a lot of energy on board
So they have a tape recorder
Soon as a tape recorder
Really yes
I think it's a 8-track
Janus Inc
It turns out it's true that there are eight tracks on both of the probes
They're capturing ultra-low frequency plasma
223 kilos
But you can actually hear
Now that whoosh
That is just a background of the power supplier of the Voyager itself idling basic
Cruising through empty space
But she says when you go to the following recording
This what you're about to hear is 8 months of time
From late 2012 into 2013 8 months
Collapse into a tiny clip
What you hear are these little swells
There's one
You have
Those ramps
Leavittsburg it's kind of confusing the Ascension Rob says those swells
That's the Voyager spacecraft
Colliding with some new
Galactic stuff
So you're hearing
It was a ramp of density as you go into Interstellar space
I thought that those sounds one of those two sounds
Is the Voyager bursting out of our solar system but she told me no no
What it is
What is the sound of the Voyager already on the other side
The boys are basically saying I'm in a new space now
After some analysis in this part I cannot explain
NASA pinpointed the ejection moment
Crossover moment
To just
Before
The first of those two swells
Took this is the first well
Just before that
Right there
Migrate
That's when we left
It's so undramatic
But we finally escaped
Official exit date 25th of August of 2012
Always ready to talk to you
The sunbeams ride Helena
So now we have a
Human manufacturer
That has left
The sphere of the Sun
On the other side in the other ocean
Is like I am
I don't know it's a Bittersweet till to see all this incredible data
That Voyager is giving us
And I want more I would like another mission there. Looks like somebody to give you like a taste
Look how interesting this day that he's in poop
They're leaving
Speaking of leaving merab says that we can expect to communicate with the Voyager probes for
Another age 10 years but then
Eventually they will lose power
Endodontic
Recording
What time is it 11:33
I'm already getting close
30 seconds
Turning on
Ariel mermaid
Look look up with the Sun
Is Big Black.
In the middle of the sky was white
Halos coming from it oh my goodness
Look at the stars bag
Is Venus there's a parade and then there's a
It's so pretty
So pretty
Thank you to everybody who sent him the recordings big thanks to producer Lynn Levy
Scientist
Amanda run check for producing this update
Who played the message press 2
I am a professor of astronomy of Boston University
Thank you and was created by God
Is produced by Stoney LaRue
Be like you cuz I won't get back till some design
I'm stopping clothes
Common Table
David Gaber
Tracy hans-mat-pagli
Flip a coin
Life is not fair Melissa O'Donnell ariani walk-in Molly Webster
Brickhouse, Beckah Shae son New York fatality
The one in Casey Simpson
Dreka is Michelle Harris
And this message