Northern listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
Hi I'm Robert and I'm left if not he's Radiolab and today we're going to do something completely upside down
And inside out yes if it's a sports story sort of would like none you've ever heard and therefore
We found a reporter who is a sports reporter like none you've ever heard I've been to a gym light
Mike Pesca is the host of the gist
Podcast by slate formerly of NPR still sometimes Roost NPR
And now he's here telling a story.
So this is Morning Edition from NPR news
I'm Renee Montagne
Who's covering the 2012 Olympics for NPR
Good morning
And the games of London
The stories of the Olympics
You try to find your own stories that are obscure but if there's a big store you chase it Sonos Olympics
What were the most notable at
In the first
Tweak of the gates
Well if history of the basscon
Michael Phelps breaking the all-time record obviously.
I never knew that a bolt
And his record-setting quest in the hundred would be huge
Brewery
But
Tennis badminton story pops up
And everyone rushes to figure out what the heck
Going on with Dad Minton
2012 London Olympics badminton
Tournament
It took
This somewhat obscure Sport and it morphed it into this Bizzaro thotics
About
Competition
Integrity and
What it means to win quotes
Mostly
I think that
Although to be fair
Mike
He jumped on the story for
Very personal recent as a New Yorker I say a lot of words and their mispronouncing the NPR audience
Jump on them but I always can say the n in badminton and get a lot of
Claudette so I'm attracted to badminton badminton
Into some
Hand wear at wintertime chastising a playful cat
And then also
You know you probably think of badminton as this
Backyard
Fun
Silly games but
According to Mike no this is anything but
It has nothing to do with the badminton you play in your backyard
It's much faster than you think it would possibly look
Flying all over the court stretching reaches diving
On a scale of the competitors is you know
Readily apparent
And perhaps not as impressive a thing as a tennis ball but it looks a lot like tennis
And there's a lot of
Tension
Severe pressure and there's a lot of grunting
I need totally seems like every bit of our legitimate and highly-skilled
Sports
Okay so
So Robert so you haven't seen
But I would like to show you something
Senad
Okay
This is the game that is at the center of the
This whole story
Women's doubles
Badminton
It is not a metal round it's in the group place
Staged
The huge crowd are like the
Place is packed
Chili's too
Teams come out you got China yellow
Same here,
Versus
Korea purple and white
And what's
Task if I had here
Alright so here we go game on this is the first sir
Rampant Korean serve
So the Korean player
Flicks her wrist
DeFalco's over the net
China returns
Right into the net that was the whole thing
Cuz I was just
Second serve
Chinese return
So that service is turned over now the Chinese are so
China Korea China
What does not exactly single and I've got to tell you
This next
The Korean player serves it
Yeah
It's sales over the net and then it goes goes goes goes goes and the
Chinese player
Clearly he's right there he has it
She then whines up justice
White big like you could see it's like she has this deep ingrained muscle memory from years of doing it
She wants up she's about to hit it and then she stopped
And the shocks
Trunks under the floor
Inbounds
Queen Taqueria
And then
Tellingly
She looks
Back corner of the
The court where coach
They both are
This is a fix
Spell fixing this
Like this is
But different plenty of occasions were one side wants to lose and then hard to lose
Any more important thing is it ain't hard to get away with it usually you wouldn't even
Notice
You know it's a difference between a couple serves
I over the line a couple balls into the net
In this case as the match goes on you start to realize
Seemed to be trying to lose to
Well it's actually a strategy
Because the wizard tournament is laid out both these teams
Are going to be moving on to the metal ramp
But
Whoever wins
This game is going to have to play another Chinese team a really strong team icing
And whoever loses is going to play a way easier Danish.
So boots
Teams
Are hoping
Toulouse
Yeah and it is the rare instance
Where you at Boost
Sides incentivised to lose
That you get something that should be scored by Spike Jones
A little bit of a prisoner's dilemma right
At either side could lose but when both want to lose it because this
Surreal waiting game
Right now who's going to crack first
And squirrel point and so
You got the best players in the world
Start hitting the shuttlecock out of bounds that's on purpose
Hitting the shuttlecock into the net
They're hitting it straight into the ground all by tripping over their own shoelaces purposefully until what you get
Is up all into the net
Durable badminton and it just devolves into this absurd repetitive
Crazy making
Louis Vuitton
Is not sleeping spice
So obvious
I mean this
Not this
Is not sport this is kind of a sport because
And this is why I really love it
At a certain point these two teams have to start competing with each other
Toulouse
Let me play you this point
Tilt
China serves at Korea it back but it's going way out of bounds
Now in a normal World China would obviously let that fall so that they can take a point but they lunge
Save it
Right there getting it back
North Korea then they are like no no you know what we're pretty sure we wanted in the opposite direction
Even further out of bounds
Tenille Traina goes to save it once again but they don't get there in time so the point goes to China which China actual
He didn't want the Koreans wanted those
So what are you saying then
Invented a whole new sport which is
The exact opposite of badminton it is it is photo negative Batman
But then
Towards the end of the first sat
Outcomes a referee
Hello toaster speaking thorsten Baron was the head Olympic badminton referee who got the
And I also heard these Spectators pool so I went to watch
It it looks
Pretty old for this was not right
In the past and
Chosen that they were
Not playing seriously
And they will making a very serious mistake and that they played stupid and set now who playing with Ryan
Krohn Conservatory
We were actually able to get in touch with
Three of the four players in that match
Both Korean players
End
Kim Hunter
And also one of the Chinese players
Do you want and once you lie told me they were trying to lose in that match what to expect
South Korea would they do the same thing
Has the mail song
And as for the Koreans
Junction and said that they too
We're trying to lose at least During certain moments in the game
But when the crowd started to do
Her partner Kim ha-na said that's how a surprise in
Embarrassed
We just wanted to get out of the Courts
As soon as possible
So person walks off the court they window court again and then the
Second
Serve
After twisting wants out the court
Nothing but net
So for the next few points
It does not get much better
Hopewell
So beset comes to an end
Korean Society
And while the players are waiting on the sidelines
You come again horse then comes back onto the court he walks up to the players and he pulls out of his
The players this black card
The black car which means disqualification
Is
Absolutely extraordinary
He has given Bose
Teams
A black card
I'm ready
Turbie show displays have written
2 quarts
It was now that they should play or they would be in
Deep
Sorry but maybe I shouldn't affect the back
Was out and I would like told them in 63 in very clear words and very seriously
In order to help themselves
They better
Play now
Shenanigans
I told her there and them and we are we so come get her
Richest play
And do our best
Second set starts
Pretty quick China
Size-change salad
But then as the points kept coming you started to notice like they were playing very slowly.
They were not getting the poor very hot
Shelby said that booth
Team Stephen change the basic
Fact or still trying to lose
How to say is exactly what it looks like when you watch it
It's for the rest of the match
You get a bunch of these points were like we're just built
Wabbit super high you know as if to say hey
Smash it down on us take your point
Or they will you know hit it out of bounds and then facepalm
Just
You'll practice their swing after they missed one just did
Two seats aob on my mechanics are off I just got to just practice
This is a few more time
Because it's like we've entered a whole third iteration of this game where it's like they're not just trying to lose
They're trying to
Cover up that you're trying to lose but you're kind of look like you're trying to win
I don't think you're seeing anybody here
So finally after 20 long minutes
Of this
The
Korean team
Loses
The match
By winning
Tonight has left me with a great and nasty taste in the mouth tonight does not support
It was a disgrace
Good night
Community
So all four players
Walks off the court
And
Kim ha-na Pleasant
Winning it all in Aaron's
Somewhere in the audience
Saturday
And afterwards they ask her
What
What happened then
Why do you have to get the booze from the audience's
And etcetera and I will I was
I was
Sad and feel felt defeated so
I didn't even want to talk to my mom so I remember
I just went to the
Hotel in
Head thrust
Shut down
Kill me.
And the next morning at 8
Order for pests in fact work
Disqualified according to the disciplinary regulations of
The badminton World Federation which has a rule on the books
State you can beat
Disqualified
For failing to use your best effort
And the same evening they were on the train home they were just thrown out of the Olympic
Text scandal at the
Is Holton
Players everyone was talking about some losers
Shuffle Council guy now
Tippy toppy in the shuttlecock into the net
Was just
Sac that the
They were
Committing suicide in that tournament
Look at that time the punishment
Hit me quite hard I was very sad
And I felt
Helpless
Tune your own phone numbers perplexed and didn't know
What happened wechat
Scryed
Just didn't sound like
Get any better but they're still more after the break
Hi this is Naila
From Hamburg Germany
Radiolab
Supported in part
Buddy Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of
Signs of technology in
In the modern world
More information
Sloan @www.
Watch loan.
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids
Parents uncles teachers
We're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments
Brilliance
Basically I want to hear about this
Times when a kid you know did something
It just means you lean back and say
Well
Maybe it was the moment that I
Kids started reading back
Do you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lesson
And you suddenly noticed they were doing
Or maybe the kids in math class you notice their writing used
Stick in the margin of their geometry
We're interested in the
Epic moments where a kid does something super smart
It doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story
T-shirt
Go to radiolab.org
Splash Brillion
Amber Court
Short Audiomack
And that's radiolab.org
Splash Brillion
Thank you so much
We're back I'm Robert krulwich this is Radio app
Korean and Chinese women's badminton team had just been disqualified
Kicked out of the Olympics
So what so then what happened to the
Play The Players like root what happened to all four of them did
Keep playing badminton professionally after this
Jung kyung Hoon from Korea even went on to win the bronze in Rio
But at the time this
Was a
Brutal punishment
For all of them
Well but you know later
They did something wrong just wasn't right
You know I don't even I question whether it's
Even on acid
I think it's ethical
It away what they did
How so
Is the definition of ethics in Sports 2
Twin Shore
Without using yes
Does that mean to win every
Point
No not necessarily you know in baseball there's a thing called the intentional water in football
Call a team will take a safety
Instead of
Pumping and letting the other team score a touchdown
What is a calculation where
Appoint
Cure there is not as important as the whole in the whole is the game
Pan out a little more
I think an individual game is off and we're not going to put our good starter here
We're going to manage the lineup
50 goal is to win the championship
Anything to remember about these players is
If what we want
Is players who are
Hypercompetitive them actually want to win at all costs
That's exactly why they were losing so badly
Because they wanted to win the overall championship at all cost
At the badminton Federation had a set of rules that open guarantee that this would happen
Stupid to have an event
What people are trying to lose to get that event is a sporting event
It's a especially at the Apex
Near the only time people care about Badness it seems really Chuck Klosterman we called him in
Because he writes a lot about sports and also because
He wrote the ethicist column for the New York Times magazine
No is this a
Some kind of tragedy well it's not
I guess unless badminton is really important to you than it probably is
In this case I think
The thing that people got really upset about is this
Is this idea of the Olympic ideal
Athletes
Gloria the song
To transcend the it in the way that Isaac
Super Bass what you're sending your Humanity but then also as like this representative of your country and
I think it did poke a lot of
People like a lot of people did seemingly get
Kind of upset about
Yeah I mean
For some reason it is disturbing to
To see
Athens Family camper
Adjusted
It seems to
Kind of like
Happened some
Like I somehow
Yes
Like like like I don't know if
Not trying in a sporting event is moral question but it feels that way when you see it happen
Chicken what do you think about sports is that we watch these adults
Playing multimillion-dollar games
Same games that
With a 6 year old and 7 year old place
So when you have a 7 year old kid
You would say
It doesn't matter if you win or lose doesn't matter what happens
Just play hard
You don't have to succeed
It's the trying that matters
So when you see people at the highest level not trying
There's it's almost
It's sort of
Rex the entire idea of why we play sports at all you know why if you're at a playground in two kids racing
The playground to see who can get to the swing faster whatever like
Biological thing maybe we are biologically driven to compete
So that's the Baseline expectation of what we have of these badminton players that they will try to compete
But it seems to me there's an opportunity here for True athleticism in a kind of
Topsy Turvy website and reverse it and see if you can do that as well as you do the other one
I mean
Sports only work one way though they don't work both ways
I mean it would be it would be like going to your wife
I'm saying like Okay you say you really love me
Prove it
By hating me in a creative way
Piano
Bang your fist against the keys
In a way that I will be
You know I will be sickened by matters of the heart put it back on the field
What would be the most radical
Solution that you could be mad
If your desire was
Vincent Lee and astonishingly athletically
I suppose if they were both trying to do it in the most convincing way it would be
That was not really the case here they never confronted how do you lose on purpose if the other side's all
Also trying to lose on purpose
I'm trying to think there are some sports oh in football licey in American football with they both sides one
You can't make the other team score but you can score a safety on yourself
Do the quarterback would get the ball and start running towards his own end zone
And then there be a jailbreak
By the defense to tackle the quarterback
You could hit the batter
That would be that would be an interesting game what about darts better aiming at the dartboard to turn around Amy at europol
Think about the implications
Will Ferrell movie I guess that's what I've been thinking
This is what we need you got to go out there a little
Other team
You can hear more of Mike Pesca on his podcast
Just more of Chuck Klosterman
In his latest book but what if we're wrong
Big thanks to all the players
To talk to us and to those
Who helped us get those interviews Joyce
Daily
Mickey
Communicate
Kike
Aparna nancherla who came in until
Puzzle with old match out
And in addition
A special thanks to Grecia Polly Grecia was on the
Indonesian badminton team in the same Olympics
And an hour after the match we featured
She faced off against a different Korean team
All4
Players in that match were also.
Disqualified for not using their best ever
First to win
She really helped us
Understand
What it was like
To be in that
This story was produced by Matt kielty and Annie McEwen and left
Nasir
I remember Chloe
And the
When's the game
At this point
Go to the next message
Es6
I'm going to do this it's possible that even if it's the fifth time I said David Cavell wrong
But I'm going to do it once
And I got to deal with an intro of myself
Yorgo
Hi this is Mike pesca
Here to tell you that Radiolab
Pretty fly jet album Rod don't keep his art director sound design Soren wheeler is
Senior editor Jamie York is our senior producer
Brenda Farrell Realty Robert Crowe vacanti McEwen
Latif Nasser Melissa O'Donnell
Nightjar Pharrell new
Nightjar fatali
Phoebe Wang Katie Ferguson Alexandria Lee Young W Harry Fortuna
Priscilla Berlin
Michelle Harris
Thanks for the
And this message
Here's an idea
There's an old riddle and it goes like this
A king talks to his two sons to print
Zenni says here's what we're gonna do
Did you get those horses out of
Here's what I want you to I want to jump on your horse
What is a ride to the city
Ever horse gets a City Gate
You're going to inhale
Maybe crazy
So the Two Princes look at each other
They both think
And then they jump on a horse
Disney ride fast as they can
Why
To reading it was at the very last minute jump off
I've been wait until the other one
I don't know are they are they planning on
Just removing a section of the gate and then just
Smashing it up against the other horse
Yeah
No thanks
What is the
They jumped on each other's home
They dropped on the other brother
Of course meme about that on the other