Are you awake
Listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
And NPR
Alright should we get to it
Yeah
McDonald's
Damn Gina coonrod armed robbery
High today just forget you're going to start
In a park
So let me set the scene couple days ago we gathered a bun
Watch Radiolab listeners McCarren Park in Brooklyn
Coming out today
You so much
And randoms
Random Sylvan Esso. Whoever showed up as a result of a few tweets and Facebook postings got about 70 people
A little bit more is it super cold days
Park is covered in snow and we had brought anybody there to help us makes noises
Using the segment
Like
Gasping or
Cantiague park annual it was amazing you'll hear them throughout the hour
But when we got there we had an ex explain to them why we wanted them to make these noises
So
Start things off
Ask them
Couple Quest
Okay so
Questions of the moment
Resume music how do you guys like football
How do you get tape
Football
This is not a shocking Revelation o kind of expected
Next 10 years but these anti-football sentiments I believe they say more about you and I and our fan
Then the game
In fairness I mean there are a lot of people who consider myself a
I watched for the ads for the ads like you were with love
Game like I have
Lowes it
Like some others
Football right now
Used it is monashee pastime ratings through the 97 and 1/2 million Sunday's game
Who was the most-watched event in American television history
It's massive massively popular that's not the same as
Also
Usually think about it
Sally Jenkins author of the book of the real all Americans
She put it this way imagine a thousand years from now
Maybe ten thousand maybe a hundred thousand years from now we're all gone
All our histories been forgotten all the silly trifling games we played and lost
Imagine the future human being
Looking back on
Let's say you know
Some archaeologists goes around digging
They're going to find these really really
Huge Stadium
That's what they're going to find
Okay and they're going to understand just like we understand about the Greeks
What was really important to us
Okay so here's the thing Radiolab listen to do an entire hour on the game of football
Depart because just seems to me that there are a lot of questions in the air about football right now
But what it really is what that means about us what it might or could or can't become
Am I going to like this
Absolutely this in any way this whole hours for the people like you
I really don't care about football and I am willing to wager that the end they will care more particular because of this
Which comes from Sally Jenkins
Just heard
Consumer book the real all Americans
This is a story at 9 about the game
As you might
Think of it now but
About
Where it came from
Then come to the people you'd expect okay I'm folding my hands
Secret my love
Three-point stance
We're ready to begin
About the beginning
Well or not quite
I mean football football is as old as some of the Celtic civilization when you can trace
Primal games of you know Danish Invaders
Kicking skulls around the shores of England I mean
Put up organized football is really a creation of of the 1860s and 70s in this country it supposed Civil War
For creation comes along
Just really a couple of years after the last
Great conquering
Armies
Settle the West
Basically says he had these kids who
Parents have fought the Civil War and then some of them is gone west
To fight the
Kota the Cheyenne Arapaho the Apaches and now those were winding down
Which oddly enough created kind of an issue
For young minutes
If you're young
Students ABAC east of fancy school like Harvard how are you been approved
Your own
When your older brother
Your father he may be fought at Gettysburg Battle Little Bighorn
What the hell have you done the American frontier experience was over there was this feeling among a lot of intellectuals
Spectre
.com
American men were losing their masculinity they were being
Feminized innocence Sao
Gordon historian David Adams
Those kids were desperate for opportunities
A man up there was a cult of Manliness around this time says they would
Damn see a bunch of violent Sports takeoff and in particular
Preferences
You see these kids at Harvard Yale
Get together and
Knocking the snot out of each other in this game that's kind of like rugby but just
More Violet the game used to be
Basically
Brutality
The origin football was such a profoundly different game writer Chuck Klosterman for him
Historian. Conrad at 3 to get five yards
Basically all the teams did
Was Liam into each other and try to move the ball incrementally it was almost as if every play
Play the entire game
Is a goal-line stand
And wait a minute for clothes used when discussing football scores
Is military it's the idea of taking land and giving
Will the origin of football that was even app
There were formations and strategies in the kind of thing but it was
Cure
Like right out of Napoleon's military Playbook and where you you concentrate your forces are showed my shoulder next to
Your shoulder neck to his shoulder as I get somewhere I
And she's in the piles of guys
Yeah and inside those files
There's all kinds of things go on and no scrubs I mean is kicking is biting his couch and I couching in crotch kicking and
Wowhead wrenching and Hardy Boys doing
I have to work to imagine that because I think of Harvard and Yale now and I think
Take off like a Pencil Neck Geek
Well at the time they were the I mean they're all these wonderful stories about these shops that they would eat for dinner I mean they
They were drinking milk by the gallon and
Power of the time physically as well as intellectually
Then Along Comes This
School
In 1879 in the middle of nowhere
That
If you're a football fan
The fan of American history
Kind of changed everything
Where was Carlo Carlo was in Pennsylvania
Very close to Gettysburg so so so tell me about what what is
This wind is it formed and what was it
The Carlisle Indian School is formed by a former of but actually he was an active military officer at the time named Richard head
Andre Pratt
The guide
Shock of white hair
Large-nosed gallantly quite gallantly in the Civil War
And then he did actually served out west in Oklahoma territory
He had fought
American Indians himself it was after winning a lot of those fights
Too many of those fights really
No talking a 1870s now that Pratt
How to change your heart and he
He suddenly became concerned
About the very people you just been fighting the fact of the matter is that Indians weren't very very desperate situation
Are the Bison were almost extinct that they were being pushed onto reservations
And population
Fallen 2
It's almost all time low
And a lot of other
Policymakers came to the conclusion that something had to happen fast or Indians would literally become
Extinct they would in fact become
The Vanishing race
Ethel Pratt
He comes to Washington with an idea
His idea was started boarding schools
Specifically for American Indian children
It was kind of radical experiment children will be taken removed for several years at a time
They would be stripped of their I was call their Savage Heritage and they would be civilized
IE they would be white italicized it was it was forcible assimilation
Pratt head of a slogan
Kill the Indian
Save the man
That's Barbara Landis Carlisle Indian School biography
Wait what up the Carlyle to talk with her and her colleague Kara Curtis
And they told us it Pratt basically made that pitch
Save the man
Not just to Congress but directly to American Indian families
All over the country I want your son
Is that how does that work I want your children because white people are going to keep coming and coming they want to settle
Telling your lands they want to take your land
And you need to learn how to
Deal with these people
So we need to teach your children how to speak English how to communicate with the white vans
When the white man comes and tries to get you to sign away the Black Hills
You won't fall for it again and it was a convincing argument
Well you know back in those days
You're talking about survival over here
Do I need to do to yourself
Hey my name is Joe American Horse
I'm sending 9 years old
Anime grandson of Chief American Horse
Joe lives near the Pine Ridge reservation in South Dakota East Lakota
He told us the story about his grandfather
I was a famous Lakota chief
In the 1890s is Grandpa's
Led a delegation of American Indians to Washington
Well he went to Washington DC
And if he was down there but he's a lot of people down there just as
Is Grandpa at this moment where he was just stunned by how many white people there were
His face was
They're like ants
And pretty soon they're going to come to the area so
He had the idea of a
Trying to send his kids to school so they can
Intermingle or intercepted whatever basically just has his grandpa just had this realization
Recant
Weekend
Go back
I got to go forward
And it seemed to him Carlisle
Was the way forward
Where we going now
Baskets were admitted here's how it would work they would
Come in
And it immediately have their picture taken
On arrival
Then they be given an Extreme Makeover
Which would also be photographed
This is Tom torlino
Barbershop is a picture of a Navajo kid looking maybe 18 years old is 1882 this is when he arrives
So you he's got kinda dark skin high cheekbones earring
Britt necklace looks like it might be made of bone and he's wrapped in a blanket
And here he is in a suit with clean cut hair the second picture his hair is very short not long
No blankets wearing a three-piece suit sitting there with spread collar and parted hair
Snapchat you have
Indian
Tom Wightman
Alex and Sophie
Joe American Horse said his family's all that transformation firsthand and Sophie was there in Carlisle for 5 years
When she came back and she looks like a white woman didn't know she had that real tiny waist and
Bloomington everything
And
She can't speak Lakota
She forgot
Haha
We just think about this for a second just think
We spoke with one guy oppressor Eric Anderson who teaches at Haskell is us apart Potawatomi just
Imagine the parents
The first time they see their kids
Parents are seeing their students marched around in
Essentially the uniform of
What had not
Very long before for many of the tribes been
The uniform of the enemy
At the very least
I think that would be
Startling
According to Sally Jenkins after the kids were recruit
And we dressed
Brentwood running through a bunch of drills in Carlisle was a little Military Academy
The Indian kids were so unhealthy at first they have been put on an unfamiliar diet they had been sleeping indoors
For the first time in their lives and a lot of them were getting sick we know that in the 39-year history of the school
At least
200 kids
Died
Of disease
Poor health or even home sick
And she was constantly trying to get the kids outside
And
At a certain point he hired some teachers
Sally thinks that one of those tires
Probably one of the first dormitory Masters
This guy who had formerly taught at Ivy League
School he showed the Carlisle Indian kids
This game with the kids at Harbor playing
Maybe he thought it would toughen him up
Knows but suddenly
They're playing football
No keep in mind this is
You know at a point like an 1882 where
Football's barely a thing
Not so many schools had teams it wasn't such a thing as a head coach back then they were volunteer coaches who tended to Beast
Students are asked students for the Carlyle kids self-organized level the field start to play they even start a scrimmage some kids across
West Town and at one of those games
Call you Barbara
Staci Matlock who is upon a student at Carlisle later became a Pawnee chief
He broke his leg
Playing football in Pratt that's it
Football
Is in his mind he was trying to civilize these kids in football was doing the opposite
But
Showtime later
Set David Adams approximately three dozen Carlisle boys came into Pratt's office they said we want to play football
Do we know what they said exactly we don't have we don't have the exact words
My Pratt says at one point
He says while they stood around my desk
I'm calling your mother stood around my desk there black eyes intently watching
This is the order gave practically all the arguments in favor
About contending an outside football
And ended up
Requesting the removal of the Embargo
According to his Memoir Pratt was
Sore bowled over by the eloquence and passion of the peel
Suicide
Okay you can play
If you do these two things Juanita's
Never slug
Okay
And the other one was you have to beat the best teams in America
And
At that early Point American football team was yell
Which brings us to October 24th 1896
Power off all day in New York who played New York yes at the old Polo Grounds
Apparently there was about 4,000 people in the stands including a handful of newspaper men New York newspaper men
Give me a big story how did they publicize it what did they say
University
Typically the Perfection of modern Athletics and intellectually the culture and refinement of the best modern American Life
On the other side
The real song of the forest and playing the Redskins history of story of War
Maybe by education
Written in this blood-curdling was shot through with Indian cliches you know from the Redskins
Redskins
Indian fashion
I mean try to put yourself in the shoes of a New Yorker in the early 1880s your contact with an American Indian
Was in a wild west show
It was theater
And here comes a football game
And all of these American Indian kids run onto the field and there's literally an instance
In one of the first games
Someone in the audience says will they look just like our boys
Because of course
That's a pratt wanted
Now one thing it was immediately clear to everyone in attendance when they saw the Carlyle players was that they were physically outmatched
The impression going in as it'll be an absolute smear job
But they released the odds are heavily against
But
3 minutes into the game in the midst of a big pile up
Fumbles the ball becomes squirting out
Carla guy picks it up
And runs
The entire length of the field 63 yards
Scores a touchdown
Now
Nobody had scored on Yale and seven games they were Furious so what they do is they use their bulk
Two slowed
Push the pile down the field
Twice
To take leave and the three minutes left
Get what's up 12 to 6 Carlisle has the ball
Carlisle running back charges the pile in gets clobbered falls backwards
Just as he's about to hit the earth he laterals the ball to a teammate
Carlisle scores a touchdown that would have tied the game but
It's called back
Bye
A referee
Who was the Yale man
Why the call was that the referee claimed that a whistle had blown
The play dead
It was a crowd reaction
Well they were they were Furious
Yes there was bullying on
And putting everyone knew it was a terrible miscarriage of justice and some of the Carlyle players head
We are leaving this game
But according to David
At the last moment Pratt runs down from the stand coming onto the fields of ways I don't forget rule number one
Be a gentleman
Pratt did not want
This game to end
Because of their tempers even though they've been wrong
Bye
By that call
So the Cowboys
Finished
And when they walk off the field
They get a standing ovation
Carlisle wins incredible respect in renown
In the aftermath of the game in fact one of the newspaper men
After another Carlisle Yale game or something
Similar happy
Wrote something to the effect of Carlisle could beat 11-year men but they couldn't beat 11 Yale men and a yield
Referee yes
After the Yale game of 1896 Pratt
Is committed
Pratt believes that it's the greatest thing that can happen to his school
It is an instant way to do what he's been struggling to do for 15
Years at the Carlisle school which is to prove the value
Are these American Indian kids against their white peers
Through the valley where the quote civilized
Civilize them
But also to prove that given education and equal opportunity they were the equal of there
That's another white Pierce
I mean he was
For all of his forcible assimilation methods which were to remain extremely cruel
And destructive
Keep
I truly believed
In the concept of of racial equality
The complicatedness
Pratt
Ahold Carlisle idea
Kep smacking ass in the face as we were putting the show together I mean on the one hand they were clearly students who felt that Carlisle was prison
Is that Barbara Landis
When she took us on a tour of the grounds of the former
Carlisle Indians
Squishies
Kids weaving Set Fire to the buildings
It's that yes M did burn down which is kind of typical on Indian campuses
Fires in burning building why
Is a form of resistance
On the other hand
When will you start looking around for original archival recordings of
See the earliest Carlisle players pretty much the only recording me to find
Much of your making is possible
With this oral history with a guy named
Andrew
Albert exendine
You are 15 years old
Can't really play you too much of this cuz the audio quality is really bad but in the interview
Brad comes up
Be alright
And xidan talks about them with a great deal of affection and gratitude
Time is it father of King in education
Call the father of Indian education
Man so he's a tough figure Pratt he's got a very mixed Legacy I mean I like to say Pratt was his country
Whatever you think of him he was his country
It's okay so 1896 he gets
The body
FootballScoop ER yes
What happens next
He begins looking around for coaches full-time coach
Just to come in and coach
The team
And he whines up
With a Cornell grad
Name Pop Warner
Glenn Pop Warner
Is this part right here
Just to give you a visual
Harbin Kerasotes pictures looks kind of like Mike Ditka
If Mike Ditka head Einstein's hair
Pops a little bit of a of an outlier
History status Texas routes
He's a bit of a rogue can be kind of vulgar
Party a little bit really
And that is exactly what he does in spectacular fashion
When he gets the Carlisle
Because popwarner looks at his Squad and he realizes that
Sure they're fast they got heart but they're underweight and they're small
Waste all your well they might occasionally force a tie with it with a Yale if they you know
Have killed themselves
Physically
They weren't going to beat the ivy League's on any kind of consistent basis without
Without doing something different
And dumb
There's a very fine line between innovation
And cheating
And Pop Warner starts at exploiting that line absolutely
As hard as he can
And he comes up with
The trick play
For example 1903
Pop Warner devices the hidden ball trick
But what is that
Hidden ball trick is the quarterback takes the ball
And actually behind the shooter pile of men
Tucks it under another guy's sweater
While the big pile of man is struggling in the mud in the center of the field not knowing quite where the football is but believing it's some
Summer in the middle of the pile with the football
Before anybody realizes it how did you keep the ball from falling out of his jersey I think they actually
Show The Jersey so that the ball would stay in there without falling out a cheating pocket native cheating
Pocket without legal because they got together legitimate touchdown was it legal you ask
Pop Warner would have said
There was nothing in the rulebook against it
Does which actually work brilliantly
Is a
He sews footballs
On to the front of their
Jersey's which were really bulky sweaters at the time he sews leather football-shaped patches onto the front of
Their jerseys in order to try to disguise who's got the ball
Ivory Coast goes insane
Black
Harvard did not take this lying. Harvard retaliates by painting the footballs the same color
As their jerseys it's maroon everywhere so when they basically
You can't see it American football is essentially a rule-breaking experience
As opposed to British football which
Didn't have referees
At least initially a British football ran on the on Earth
But with American football
The rest were there practically from the beginning and she says it was largely a response
The brutality the game but also to the kind of rule-bending
That you saw from Pop Warner in the Carlisle Indians Every Time popcorn and came up with an innovation the next year there was a
Rule against it
So immediately I believe we get together and pass a rule and say okay no more of that
NFL rulebook really virgins
In American football and it's thanks to Pop Warner
Sleight of hand and pop Warner's greatest sleight-of-hand
And maybe
The Carlisle Indians most
Soaring moment and I mean that literally
Happened
At a moment when the game almost disappeared
That's coming out
Start of message
Yes this is David Adams who's Conrad trained and I got an email message asking me to read credit Tech
Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation enhancing public understanding of science
Technology in the modern world more information about Sloan's at www.slha.org
The lab is produced by WNYC and distributed by NPR
Okay there it is
And this message
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
This summer
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
About what we're calling tiny moments of brilliance
Basically I want to hear about those times when I kids you know did something
It just means you lean back and say wow how did they do that
Maybe it was the moment that I
Kids started reading back
To you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lesson
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of their musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed they're writing music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the
Epic moments where
Kid does something super smart but doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story
T-shirt with us
Go to radiolab.org
Brilliance
Record a short audio message
And that's radiolab.org brilliant
Thank you so much
I'm rubber Coolidge is Radiolab and getting back to our story on the Carlisle Indian School and the
Birth
Of the
Monogama football
What is the most important moments in the story I happens at a time when football it was right on the edge
Disappearing
Timeout 1905
This was
The most violent year in football today
19 people died on the football 19
That's crazy cuz what would happen is that Carla will try and do these things to throw to open up the game
The Ibis would consistently respond by making the game more about Brute Force more about violence
So you had all these debts and suddenly all the major programs were spooked
Columbia polls are their football team
Harvard even think about doing that and so and this is kind of odd Into The Fray steps the president of the United States of America
Teddy Roosevelt
The conrad beijing
He'd like football he like the
The manly aspects of it's a tough aspects of it but nobody like people dying
And then there was his his his son
What's playing
And and getting beat up pretty badly as well
Broke his nose
Plated eyebrow the one game he got knocked out cold
So after the violence about 5
The president
Calls the president of all these colleges in Suwanee
The Washington and according to David Adams he basically tells
That the rules had to be Rewritten it had it become
A little bit more safe at least or it would be bad
In out of that we see a couple of roaches
China's first school to side in order to loosen up the
Pile
They're going to Tinker with the
Down yardage ratio
3 Downs of game 5 yards of pea
3 Downs.
10 yards
Renounce
4 weeks
Bubble years later
Is that the second rule change
Just may be the most
Important
Raise for the first time
They legalize the ability
To move the ball
Through
Free floating air
Surrounds us all
Okay so where do we go to the next today sick if I could if I could
Replace you in a moment unless there's a moment before this you'd like to hit
I believe
November 23rd 1907
Yes your big moment okay can you set the scene
From the standpoint of broader American history things have gone airborne
You mean Wilbur and Orville Wright 1960
There are aeronautical experiments happening really all over the world in France
Everyone is experimenting with flying machines things are going up in the air
But not so fast with football because
When the rule committee had made that rule about for passing they'd also hedged a little bit saying
If you throw forward pass through receiver doesn't catch it
You are penalized 15 yards which back in the day
With a monster amount so nobody threw the ball was too risky.
Story goes as soon as that ruled that passed pop when it goes back to his garage so he's a garage with a ball
Any starts experimenting and what would be the most
Efficient way
Apostasy
Why people have to understand that the footballs and those days are not the footballs we have today with the nice
Oblate spheroid or whatever they call it with a nice points and thinks he's a rugby ball
Citic imagine that deflated basketball
They're sticker in the middle they're not as well shaped
They're really tough to get your hand on
Death row right and in 1906 in Albert exendine zorrel history weight
We talked about this in 1906
He says called all the players together he tells them
You will have to learn
Karla Bonoff
He says I think you can have to learn to spiral the ball
Cuz if you throw the ball in the spiral
10 times less Air drag
And if you throw it and over and plus it's easier to
They start
Experimenting with it a little bit in 1906 but they come out in 1907 as a throwing offense
Which gets us to that game
November 23rd 1907 Carlisle plays the University of Chicago last game of the season where in Chicago
Chicago in the Chicago team is arguably the best in the nation video
I don't think you can argue about
What color is good at this point though
Yeah but Chicago is like
Stagg field
And they're 27000 people in the stands
Well what happened was the Chicago players had decided to try to defeat Carlisle's innovative
Forward passing
I just
Knocking the crap out of their receivers every time they came off the line of scrimmage
Until Carlisle's greatest receiver
Albert exendine our guy had been stymied the entire game because the minutes ball was snapped Chicago players would
Hit him and try to throw him down or knocking out of bounds
So Pop Warner said the exendine here's what we're going to do
Next time they hit you out of bounds
Sneak around the bench and get back on the field
By some accounts with X and I
On the next play
I would like to dine at expected ends up out of bounds
But he keeps running
He runs around the back of the bench
Renter and spectators
Maybe around the van and comes back on the field
Reddit that moment
Hauser the quarterback of Carlisle
Lex Luthor vicious spiral
Can I have urethras something shitbag
This is Sally's description of that moment from her book the real All-American
For a moment it was a frozen scene in a stage drama
The ball hung in the air a tantalizing possibility
Woody catch it
Or drop it
Defenders wheeldon stare-down field
Spectators watching from the stands
Brett had died in their Collective throats the spiraling ball seemed
To defy physics
What made it stay up
When will it come down
In that long moment 27000 spectators
Mashed together on benches and crammed on platforms
May have felt their loyalty to the home team evaporate in the grip of a powerful new emotion
I've noticed something they never had before
Butterball traveling through space traces of profoundly elegant path
They may have realized something else
That it was beautiful
The ball struck is human target
Action done caught the pass all alone
And trotted over the Chicago line
The stadium
Louder than sound in motion it was the game breaker the rest was just anticline
The final score was 18244 Carlisle
But very next year the ivy league pass is a rule that you can't leave the field and then come back on
That's what I wrote Come Together say that that description of the ball in the air
Is
Timeless
Anyway that's exactly why football is still beautiful at a time
That's that's that's when
Carlisle in 1907 is when American football becomes the sport that you watched
Oh wow this is this the field
This is the fee can we get out
After we spent an entire day looking at
Pictures of
You know Albert exendine in
Pride Pop Warner and doulas Lone Wolf and
Lino and all these Carlisle players Barbara and Carol took us to the field where they practice
Answer this is the Carlyle
Indian School football field
Covered in snow
10 degrees out here really really bright sun coming off this now
Insert empty
We just kind of walked around and
Try to imagine all the stuff we just seen in photos
He was a little bit like walking among ghosts
That's the sound of the flag blowing in the back
Understanding on that feel the end
Having two
Thought that I couldn't quite articulate
The later of Eric Anderson a professor from Haskell
Member of the Potawatomi Nation
Surprise finger on it
Essentially said that like there's a lot of room on a football field
Miss room for
Anger and war and violence is also room for pride
And a kind of coming together that's not a pratt coming together where one side gets erased
But it is a coming together
Yeah I mean there is a middle ground
Clearly it's more than a game
The stakes are higher than that
You know
Will we as Indian people be accepted
On our own terms
Also
In our ability
To meet you
Halfway
Will we be accepted
Through
This as the vehicle
It's clearly more than the game
A lot of people to think of this episode I we had original music made for us for that episode from Morgan okay
Kane you can hear him right here playing the banjo that's Morgan Oakland music.
Check him out
How to get original music from Austin musician Shakey Graves and the Albert exendine take that we played
Research division of the Oklahoma Historical Society Society in the US Army heritage
Education Center
Where you can go and see tons of photos from both archives or you can come to us on our website radiolab.org we have a ton of
Old archive football pics
None of those before and after pictures from The Amazing
Really amazing
And we also have a link to Sally Jenkins book
Which is
Highly recommend the real all Americans
Radiolab.org
Thanks also to Reggie Kathy and
Scott Graham to Noah Robbins to Michael chernus to Matt dellapina
Colwyn Bay
Jr McCarthy Tunica
Couple DJ Colin Michelle Campbell at Haber and special thanks for a special thanks to our amazing volunteer
Cheer squad
It came out
And whether the Brooklyn called
To scream and holler and bring the story to life
Speaking of that
Very special thanks to Brenna Farrell who found the story and produced it with us and production support from Damiano Marquis
That's a lot of people
To have back but we will help you will have more to listen to and what people to think in the second half of our broke
Yeah we're going to take a distinctly modern view on football coming up
Are we
Okay
How's your water
My water is refresh
Delicious
We like to go
Heavy on the minerals here in Albuquerque
Hey hey I'm Jared I'm rod iron Robert krulwich Radiolab
Yes sir
And the first half we talked about football
Came from
I want to look at where it's going
Conversation these days
Everything about that we have talking with one of my favorite
Horse riders
Chuck Klosterman
I'm a writer and a journalist in Brooklyn you may know him from
Ethicist column in the New York Times he also writes
About sports for Grantland
Any recently wrote an essay
About
Football and it's
Inherent country
Prediction
We called for us this way
Carlisle versus IV free flow versus
Traditional
Sort of thing but in a modern way
I want you to explain the statement
This is the thing I found most
You say basic
Bed bug bites
Training itself as a super conservative
Traditional manly sport but essentially
Operating is the opposite
It's really liberal wide-open anything goes going to
Football became the most
Successful Enterprise in America
Do you have The Descent in it
Pretending to be one thing but actually another
What do you mean
Okay it's it's a unique thing in the sense that you look at a sport like soccer or baseball
There is a real
Since from the people who sort of
The institution of the sport to keep the sport the same
But they want the sport to sort of almost transcend time would be the same game now is it always
Soccer particularly
They hate any kind of attempt to change the rules in the
Football works in the exact opposite way
Football
Constantly evolving
Constantly adopting new ideas and new technologies
And is very willing
To alter the game in order to make it more free-flowing
Oreimo Progressive game
I mean football will add things like
Coaches can talk to the quarterback threw a radio in their helmet
It has been determined that the receiver
Now the idea of instant replay was added very early on compared to other
The game itself
From an offensive perspective
Is constantly being reinvented
Chuck says if you look at all the new formations that keep getting at and all the trick plays that are tried out every year it is
Play clear the football as a game it actually is the most liberal sport in terms of adopting ideas
But
V
The morality of the game in the center of
The thing that really draws people to
Love it
Is sort of almost most reactionary
Air quality
That it's still sort of comes down
To the strongest toughest win
This is why I feel like football has
It is
Both song
Built for American
If the American way of thinking and also didn't so popular that it allows you
Sort of think about the game in a very liberal Progressive Way
Carlisle way but
Spiritually it like your heart of it can still be this kind of old
Comfortable conservative mindset
Does old Ivy fundamentals of Power Inn
Might
Tradition of the beliefs if that's really what most people want most people want to think of themselves
As Progressive
But feel conservative argument is it is it is footballs unique ability to be both
The same time reactionary
And simultaneously wildly inventive so that you can think about it one way and feel about another
That is what makes football the most popular part
Ivar sporting call
Right now by
Factory
What he means is it the NFL's three times as popular as the next most pop
Motorsport
In the question we got to
Just cuz of the quest
You can't really avoid right now is
Is it going to stay that way
Which is weird
Era for the
Sport
Certainly mylifetime the strangest are they
Weird things are happening one is that
Injuries
Actor in
There seems to be no limit
To the amount that we can discuss the problems with the game
Concussions in
In football if your coach how do you handle all this
This discussion about neurologist in head injuries doing
The idea that so many former NFL players
Are essentially you know decrepit and and
Why do I have problems
Study their brains after they die and they have the brains of people who
Should have been a hundred 80 years old and had Alzheimer's or whatever you know there was just a kid from Ohio State
Who shot himself
Has he sent a text to his mother saying
I am sorry if I'm an embarrassment
I basically text his mom and said it was like
I think it's contractions and are making me do this these concussions have my head all
Effed up
At the same time it is an American Pastime
Game with the most watch
Event in American television
I think it's very plausible that the Superbowl this year will be the most
Watched sporting event of all time
In America
And this is why you feel a small
Cold wind in the air like
I feel absolutely
Usually never been serious.
Discussion
About should we as a culture be playing football since
Since Roosevelt 1905
No one seems to be
Stopping themselves
From watching these games
So it's almost like there are these two silos
Two separate streams in our Collective unconscious that exist simultaneously and I both like shooting Skyward
Okay so we got to be honest like when Chuck was talking
About the whole idea of Silo shooting Skyrim
Cool idea but we weren't really sure what that meant
Exactly
And so much that is until our producers are in Wheeler Mets
Emily Bartell
You could add something like
She want
I'm on a Bartell I'm a Libra enjoy long walks on the beach
So money is a partner in a media production company she lives with her husband there for kids outside of Atlanta Georgia but actually
Go to talk to her about her son Parker
Because money says
The very moment he was born
So what are you thinking
When Park
As soon as the doctor
Saw his third thumb
We're going to the NFL baby yes and then Parker's 10001
Announce
He's the biggest thing he walked out the womb
I'm still going with 3rd Stop
Parker comes out and he's the biggest thing I've ever seen you know I've prepared for months and I've found
Perfect outfit to take him home from the hospital and and this Joker's too big for it
So right then I'm like oh my God yes yes
He's a boy and he's going to play in the NFL to play in the NFL a lot of families pass down quilts
They pass down family businesses are family tradition
What's football
It was football
My dad played football
The Lions leading Rodger was Mel fire he was a running back for the Detroit Lions actually Rookie of the Year
Year 1967
His brother played
Miller Farm Jerome
My uncle her brother is Mel Farr Jr and Michael far both play football and Jerry levias who they
Jerry ball
I can't even
If I
I said I was going to actually write them all down
But it's something like 33
Family members have played in the NFL
Coming from a sports family
We had to play a sport
So I can remember getting up in the mornings before school six 7 in the morning and having agility drills
We lived on the house like just at home in your backyard in the backyard
We lived on a hill and
I didn't have it as bad as my brothers because I play tennis I started playing tennis at 3
But
Like in the wintertime my dad would strap my brother to the sled and my dad was sit in the sled they would
I have to run up the hill with my dad in the sled
Tire drills everything
Do you have a sense of light
Why
I think for my dad
Sports opened up so many doors for him my dad's from Beaumont TX
He was in Texas at a very
You know during segregation
So Sports allowed him to get out
It allowed him to provide
An excellent
Lifestyle for
Prince family
And being drafted to the Detroit Lions
And being a football player in the Motown era
Weekends at my house consisted of
Marvin Gaye in
Glen Burnie and Charlie Sanders who are all in the Hall of Fame that my father actually and Lynn Bernie sang background
Marvin Gaye's what's going on
No my dad has a gold record
And when he stopped playing football
He opened up his first
Car dealership
Another
And another and four times the Mel Farr Auto Group
Was actually the largest African-American owned business in the country I mean that's what football did for him
Football
Gave my dad
A life
So Parker
Haley Bennett
So you start looking for leagues like we moved to Georgia when Parker was to
And I found one that started at 4
Just two more years of like a countdown
Oh my gosh one more year
And
When Parker turned four
I mean I can sleep the night before I might cat
Tomorrow's the day
Docker has no idea what's going on
I go up there bright and early first person in line here's my check
4 years old full on contact football at 4
Wood helmet
Helmet pads
Spring training
Parker heads
He's going to the tires
Keys for
Okay
That we don't even have team colors yet
But I'm there and what I feel like the team color should be
I hope they're in Honolulu blue
Is silver cuz that's Detroit life colors
So this is just at the spring training then we get to the actual team practice
They immediately they named in the tank
He was just going through people there like
First practice I'm not thinking about the other parents and their little
Normal sized children
And the fact that bite you know after the first day of practice three kids quit because Parker hedges
Wow them over I'm like yes my son is obese
Football in where we live
Is huge
At four years old they were tailgating
No I'm serious
The coaches have matching outfits that headgear like are you kidding me you guys are talking on microphone
And I'm like
Wow this is
This is freaking serious
And the coaches are cursing like
You guys are playing like a bunch of
Oh my god wow they're for
Don't even know what that is
Wow it's that
Serious
Are you starting
To think
This is ridiculous
At any point or it's just they were
Money says she knew that
Game of thorn Parker's team would take the field go fight with the proudest
Moment as a pet
My sign
It's a personal foul
I know
It's terrible
I'm my son
Just tackles this guy
Imma coach you know you would always
Makes me dirty
So after you tackle them my son took his head and play Future
But I had to keep myself down
Cut the kid who's eating mom every day start
Is when I realize I'm like God
If my son was just
Attacked by a 65 lb 4 year old I probably be a bit upset
Well this is a progression
This is okay they got the matching outfits
Okay to eat dirt and then you go home and reflect
Holiday Inn
Oh my gosh
Kids mom
But then
We get to the Super Bowl
So I'm fanatical
The superlative for 5 year olds
Super Bowl
My son has a trophy that's
It's probably
3 ft tall
The crazy part is that as all this is happening as Parker's taking the field with us
4 and 5 year old teammates
A family member had really really started showing
Signs of Life
Chronic traumatic
Encephalopathy
Which is the
What comes from Lake
Concussion
Symptoms include memory loss
Bouts of anger
In this case
It
Was
Depression it was
Suicidal Thoughts
It was
Everything was at other family member saying hey have you noticed
There was it
He himself saying I I don't feel right with everybody else
It was getting
Phone call
Like hey I need you
Come get him
Because
He's having dangerous
And at that very time
Knowing that
I wouldn't sign
What's going on there
Cuz that's what we do
It's almost like a split personality
Registering him
For football
Was just as natural
Is getting up every morning and brushing my teeth
Then you have the other half
As a
Mother
Daughter
Nice
Of NFL athletes
Who sees what happens on the flip
Emma Parker was playing the
Part of her that did see what happens on the flipside.
That part would campaign to raise awareness of CTE was other parents I was on a mission
I met with people I was doing health fairs
Helping creator
Pamphlet that would go out
Meanwhile
Since Parker was playing
My dad knows
It really your dad to my dad is now showing
Science
My dad just turned 70
And
You know it
I'm seeing it now with his
Speech
With his thought pattern
You know running backs what are you do manually with the head up
You know
But I can't
That myself
From wanting my son to play football it's
Just a crate I can't I can't even explain it
If you wanted to
Play I would
Be out there that he would be at practice
You don't even
Who tosses the ball around with him in the yard hoping that he'll fall in love
Football
Jasper Parker I asked Parker
Prodigy like
The season
His favorite things
Where the trophy and the pizza pie
Had no desire
You want to play again next season
Now
This past year
Or last
Hey Parker do you want to play this year
No
How to play soccer
Would you
Bring up the LA when would an ex
Possible season beef
Well
Registration is in June
And this would be what kind of
Is 8
Yeah
I don't want
Himtoo
If he decides to
To play the game
If not
Begrudgingly
But that's okay
I don't want to force him to play especially this
Early
So I stand firm on both sides
The debate
I know that's what makes it ridiculous
Eyes
Stanford
That children should not play football
I also stand
Confirm that
Children should play football
That it's a great
Sport
The current solution to this quandary
So now we're out there
Where am I
This year
We're dedicated teacher about a pick maybe soccer such a bad bad idea
Show all the kickers came from soccer
There's no black kickers there's no black punters
Even the kicker
Every so often
But there is a stiff
Death penalty for that it was 50
About this point in the conversation
Parker him up from school
Come on by and say hi
Wheeler
Hamister wheeler
Hey there partner
I'm not exactly sure how an 8 year old should look but
He's pretty big kid
Come sit with me
Your laugh
So do you know why I came to talk to you
Why
All about football
I play I play for about
6 week
I think
Cuz you just went really that into it
No I just still on the only reason I don't want to play it anymore is because I made someone swallow dirt and like
That's not his kind of messing up my history and I don't want to get anyone else hurt
Nothing of your history yeah it's just messing up history in my life
Batman UK I don't know what that means was that mean
It's like messing up it's making me have bad memories on have good memories
I like trying to make someone swallow dirt
Benefield
It was an accident I just tackled him and I happened
Did you feel bad about it right away or you just feel bad about now and he
I feel bad about it every time I say
Back
Really
I thought I heard somebody
Crying yourself
I thought I heard
Tears
Airsoft gun
Do you like watching
Football
No I'm not that into football like the rest of my family
I usually think about just having fun
And not winning
Where'd you get that
No I just know that
Winning stats for people trying to be better than everyone in bowling
Winner
No Lake
Mom
That's what I mean
It's trying to have fun
Not just to be rude to
When you win all you're going to do is like take a trophy and say you're better than them
It's not
Fair to the other
Do you like other sports
I really want to do synchronized
Is that true
Mostly because when I saw something about it
Kind of cool like
People are doing a lot of cool swimming tricks so I kind of thought it was
Something for me
Just you playing me
Synchronized swimming you like you're like this hasn't come talk to me about football and I'm going to tell him that I
I want to do synchronized swimming
I know you like it
Oh yes I'm going to do.
He likes this
They said swimming
But I guess you don't have to worry about that I would be a team sport
Yeah
Why was kind of exhausting
We can stop
Big Smo name Parker Bartell for letting
Legs or invade their home in exhaust them on short notice and by the way when when I went back and I counted all the relatives that
I've been in the NFL it wasn't 33
Louis XIII
That's still at the lot
Any case
Here's a logical question that we felt like we should ask
Ask Ellie somewhere
In the show
Given tags experience
Hayward football
Practically his Birthright but he is opting out
Are there a lot of Tanks
Out there
Like it is football the sport tanking
Nationally generally
Where's Molly Webster Define
Funny when one of my friends become tank
But that's cuz he can drink a lot
My dad can't remember his name just goes that tank fellow
Still drink a lot
In nek I started making some calls High School coaches hey can you hear me
Winning teams losing teams on the bigger picture I called this guy
Brian Marcellus Wallace in and I am a freelance sports reporter
I don't know what you want to name the places where I
Disename in freelance sports writer
She was an intern at the Wall Street Journal
Sports.
In my first week
A article was published on ESPN that
Suggested based on Philly Pop Warner youth football numbers
Person Pop Warner but he is a Youth Football League
Based on Philly Pop Warner youth football numbers Youth Football was declining
Felt pretty significantly
Do you remember what the what the drop was around 5% a year between 2000
Had in 2012 when people saw these numbers they were like oh my God
Why exactly
5% doesn't sound too bad well I mean if you assume that the 5% drop doesn't change that's what address by ever
Every year than in 15 years you're in the neighborhood of like
50% less kids playing ball
Wow
If this is true it's about the end of football
Pop Warner than they're not going to middle school
Football you're not going to high school football not going to college football so they're not going to the NFL
Needless to say everyone is like oh my God is this actually true or is there more to these numbers than meets the eye
The rain starts digging into them
To put them in
And he
Doesn't look just it pop warner numbers he looks at all the Youth Football League
And what I began to realize was that
Big drop wasn't as drastic
But if there was indeed a truck
Business because everyone was saying all right
Okay your relief will be short-lived
Because because there's a bigger story
Moon rhyme with the participation across all Youth Sports not just football
I came back with noted drops in all
The biggest youth sports
It's not just the footballs everything's decreasing or nothing was Rising except for lacrosse
Emperor haki
Edline
Kids are playing sports
Football gets all of the attention
Hope all gets all of the controversy you don't really hear about basketball and soccer or baseball so you know
You don't have any reason to think that those Sports aren't still as healthy as they've always been
But then
When you go and look
UCI drop that is comprable to the drop
And the sport that's got everybody's hair on fire and you just
Wonder why this has been going on for silently
Is this an extension of the whole concussion thing
Yes concussions were definitely part of the conversation but so were you know budget issues and kids
Specializing in sports and getting burnt out
Are basically everyone had two reasons and every school has their reasons but the guys I talk to
And it'll
Kept coming back to land on this point that had nothing to do with safety
Today is
Kingdom like the score
He just hits restart
He just starts the game over cuz I can get on a video game
They can play they start losing their hit reset hit the button and play another game they just hit a button start
JT Curtis JJ Woodward and George Salas there in Louisiana California and Kansas and I heard this refer
Find not just from them but I heard this in Ohio I heard this in Michigan and by this point I was like
Jesus
It's funny cuz it's as if
All the coaches all across the nation are reading the same book
Or going to the same bar or something because
I'm literally everyone I talked to his brought this up
Is it just that everyone said it to each other so much that it's
I can tell you that's not it at all it's it's because we all deal with the problem
So all this cuz I talked to her like you can't go hit reset you can't hit reset you can't hit reset like
These kids are used to like
It's like if I sound so old they're basically saying that what they find is they feel like there's some some
Commitment issues
I've only play if I win I only want to win
Yeah so the interesting thing was is the coaches I talked with the PowerHouse schools
We're not actually having trouble getting kids
Because we win
But the other schools in the
The conference
Stay know that coaches athletic director
She's not talk to some schools that had for fitting
Ends up forfeiting games they said like you just don't get the kids that will work their asses off and ride the bench
Everybody wants to win it just somehow it seems like that
Expect to win or isn't worth the effort or it's just that there are so many options like why would you choose the losing apps
Used to go home
After school
I turn the TV on
Nursery channels
So I had
And they usually wishon soap operas
So there was really no reason I will add no reason to stay home now you go home there's a hundred
50 stations you can find something you want to watch
Or you get out
Again
Alright so whether it you think it's video games or parenting or
Sheriff
Cushing's or whatever
Reason you want to choose
23 largest good happens
These conversations about sports like
Football is it it doesn't actually seem to be about football it's like some kind of negotiation between the generation
Cuz like
Back in the 1870s
The harbor kids
They were using footballs away to say back to the previous generation like look how tough we are looking manly we are
Maybe this generation
Is turning away from sports like football also to say something back to
The previous generation
Something about the world they want to live in
Sport do
Suggest thing
About
Society and about reality
That we are slowly trying
To move
Remove from exhaust
I'm the idea that somehow
Physicality matters more
In the mine
And that people really aren't equal
And that if you yell at someone and challenge their manhood off
I mean Albert masculinity of any kind
It's not something that were in the mood to celebrate these days
So it could be
You believe ridership last minute it could be that some kids are choosing away from sports like football because
To play football
It means it on some level you have to
Port
At least entertaining ideas that you don't like
No
At least you don't admit that you like
Mitsubishi bits
You Think You're Something unconscious about me
That is drawn to
The problems in the game that are based around what it really is
Which is a two dudes
Slamming into yes
Because you know I mean okay if this is like I'm doing can I get something pop psychology on myself
But I
I sometimes wonder if
If
Soho part of me
Mrs.
That
From my life
That you know that that my life
Build around sitting in a
Computer
And avoiding
Conflict
And basically thinking about things and
Going on the radio and talking about what they might mean you know any sort of like where they metaphors for what is this culture what is it
And that that
That perhaps football
Allows me to
The sword of
You know I'm not playing it I'm just watching it
But somehow by watching it allows me to tap into something
That is no longer part of my life because my mind has trained me not to want it
My mind knows not to
Look for conflict
Now
Do I
Spectrum
Socialized
To believe that would be a
Positive exciting thing
Absolutely
I mean I you know I talked about sports with my father
More than we talked about
Every other thing we ever talked
Regulation
How you passed away am I love him in a great relationship
But we definitely
Spent more time
Discussing Sports
But I would say every other thing that we discussed even though you would always say
It's like the most important thing he'd like
From whatever you know and he would be like so how was school today and I would tell him what school was briefly and he would be like
We know academics in the most important thing about football practice for an hour
I realize that
My relationship is Football goes back if you know my I have two older brothers man we spend so much time
Throwing the football around
And and and my brother one of my brothers were
Very good football players in like one playlist
College live on
First grader I was so proud of that you know I would tell you there's all of these things that I'm sure
Are creating obstacles for me seeing this clearly
And maybe the kind of person who sort of like this guy is crazy
He's not seeing the obvious thing that he is actually saying that we need to somehow find a moral justification for
For a game that's probably killing dudes for money
I don't know it's not my fault that's how I feel like kicking around a man I'm sorry
There you go
You have two new messages
Message
This is Chuck Klosterman
Curtis calling
Radiolab is produced by Jen
Abimar Foods
Molly Webster
Gaming York
Lynn Levy Cindy Mills Kelsey pageant
House from Iron wax
Joe Lerner
The mighty Arrow
Marchetti
Kelly Prime and Jenny Lewis
11 Volvo
Many staff members with names that are hard to pronounce
The Ricochet from Benji
Robert wheeler
Death Miller Fortune DoubleTree Road or Decker
Eric Anderson
Cumberland
County
Historical
Society
And this message
Back
One less one less
Okay if you grew up on inside the NFL
Yes I did
This is for you
The Voice
Using the Chicago players crowded along the sideline as a shield
Oxendine Circle the bench
And started running again
Behind the line of scrimmage Hauser launched the ball 40 yards downfield
Darting back onto the field
All alone uchicago gold remotely it was a frozen scene
In stage drama
Double hung in the ear
A tantalizing possibility
Production die
Wechat
Or drop it
Defenders we are down for you
Spectators watching from the stands
Founded the redhead died in their Collective throats
The spiraling balls seem to defy physics
What made it stay up
When would it come down
In that lawnmower
27000 spectators
Mashed together on bench
And Quinton platform
May have built their loyalty to the home team evaporate
In the grip of a powerful new emotion
They may have noticed something they never had before
Trouble traveling through space
Traces a profoundly elegant path
They make it real by something else
Bet it was beautiful
The bolt struck its human target
X and Y Kanto pass all alone
And trotted over the Chicago Goliath
Stadium exploded in Sound and Motion
I'm a Chicago sideline coaches and players screen without range of a beer the referee signals
Score
What in the stands The Spectators marble
Hilditch breath in amazement for a Time
Been stifled is local Pride
Turn bluetooth
She-Ra for the Indians
Chicago Daily Tribune reporter
It was the game breaker
The rest was just anticlimax
The final score was 18244 Carlisle
The long path had arrived in Chicago
Although by a circuitous and out of bounds route
The Indians declare the Tribune
Had given such an exhibition of its possibilities
It will not soon be forgotten in that vast throng
That was Mister
Scott Graham voice of inside the NFL
Thank you Scott you are the awesomest voice ever
And
Original music by Donkey
Baidu