Are you awake
Northern listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
What's up everybody this is Jad Radiolab
Spry podcast here tomorrow is the
The game
Go Eagles
And
Whether you like football or not
Whether you like it or not
One of the biggest
Sporting events
In the world
And it's a game that in many ways his
Is always been wrapped up
In what America is
This is what it isn't
It's a
What we thought we do just as a corrective measure is
Is Bring Back
Do we put together a couple years ago
About the origin
It's kind of Amazing Stories
It looks like we're all going to be sitting there watching
Tom Brady
Probably
Hopefully not win another Superbowl and we'll be watching Timberlands
Do the halftime thing
It's right at all no one will be talking about the people
Without whom the game would be nothing
So this is an honor of them
Just the way that we got to from
Journalist and author Sally Jenkins
From her book the real Olive
I mean football
Football is as old as some of the Celtic civilization semeniuk
Can trace
Primal games of you know Danish Invaders
Kicking skulls around the shores of England I mean
Put up organized football is really a creation of
Of the 1860s and 70s in this country it's a post Civil War
Creation comes along
Just really a couple of years after he had the last
Great conquering armies
Settle the West
Basically says you had these kids whose parents fought in the Civil War and then some of them is gone west
To fight the Lakota the Cheyenne Arapaho the Apaches and now those washer winding down
Which oddly enough created kind of an issue for young men at the
If your young students a back east at a fancy school like Harvard how are you going to prove
Your own
Your older brother
Your father he may be fought at Gettysburg Battle Little Bighorn
What the hell have you done
The American frontier experience was over
There was a feeling among a lot of intellectuals that
.com
American men were losing their masculinity they were being
Feminized innocence Sao
Korean story of David Adams
You just heard
Those kids were desperate for opportunities
To man up there was a cult of Manliness around this time says David
Fancy a bunch of violent Sports takeoff and in particular
Frye purses
You see these kids at Harvard Yale
Getting together in
Knocking the snot out of each other in this game that's kind of like rugby but just
More finely
The game used to be
Basically
Brutality
The origin football was such a
Game writer Chuck Klosterman 4him historian. Conrad
3 towns to get five yards and basically all the teams did
Was Liam into each other and try to move the ball incrementally it was almost as if every play
Play the entire game
With a goal-line stand in the Middle Ages use when discussing football scores
Is military it's the idea of taking land and giving them
Will the origin of football that was even Ampla
There were formations and strategies and that kind of thing but it was
Cure
Like right out of Napoleon's
Military Playbook me where you you concentrate your Force
Sia showed my shoulder neck to your shoulder neck to his shoulder I think it's a lie
All your man in them Pierce The Other Guys Army that was the basic idea
Piles of guys
Yeah and inside those files
There's all kinds of things go on in those scrubs I mean just kicking his fighting is gouging High couching in track
Kicking and
Wowhead wrenching and
I have to work
To imagine that big
Because I think of Harvard meal now and I think
Take off like a Pencil Neck Geek
Well at the time they were the I mean they're all these wonderful stories about these
Chops that they would eat for dinner I mean they were
Drinking milk by the gallon and a great
Power of the time physically as well as intellectually
Then Along Comes A School
My little school
In 1879 in the middle of nowhere
That
If you're a football fan
The fan of American history
Kind of changed
Where was Carlo Carlo was in Pennsylvania
Very close to Gettysburg so so so tell me about what what is the
This wind is it formed and what was it they are the Carlisle Indian School is formed by a former of
But actually he was an active military off
At the time named Richard Henry Pratt bagai shock of white hair
Large nose
Gallantly quite gallantly in the Civil War
And then he had actually served out west in Oklahoma territory
He had fought American Indians himself
It was after winning a lot of those fights
Too many of those fights really
We're talking about 1870s now that Pratt
How to change your heart and he
He suddenly became concerned
About the very people you just been fighting the fact of the matter is that
Indians weren't very very desperate situation
Are the Bison we're almost there
Extinct that they were being pushed onto reservations
And population
Fallen 2
All Time Low
Pratt and a lot of other
Policymakers came to the conclusion that something had to happen
Fast or Indians would literally become extinct they would in fact become
The Vanishing race
Ancel Pratt
He comes to Washington with an idea
His idea was started boarding school specifically for American Indian children
It was kind of a radical experiment children will be taken removed
For several years at a time
They would be
Stripped of their
I was called her Savage Heritage and they would be civilized
IE they would be white attire
It was it was forcible assimilation
Pratt head of a slogan
Kill the Indian
Save the man
That's Barbara Landis
Probiotic
Will one of the Carlyle to talk with her and her colleague Kara Curtis
And they told us it Pratt basically made that pitch
Save the man
Not just to Congress by directly to American Indian families all over the country I want your son
Is that my house isn't worth your children because
White people are going to keep coming and coming they want to settle in your lands they want to take your land
And you need to learn how to
Deal with these people
So we need to teach your children how to speak English to communicate with the white vans
When the white man comes and tries to get you to sign away the Black Hills
You won't fall for it again
And it was a convincing argument
Well do you know back in those days
You're talking about survival over here
Do you mind introducing yourself
Hey my name is Joe American Horse
79 years old and the grandson of Chief American Horse
Joe lives near the Pine Ridge reservation in South Dakota East Lakota
He told us the story about his grandfather
I was a famous Lakota chief
In the 1890s is Grandpa's lead a delegation of American Indians to
Washington
Well he went to Washington DC
And if he was down there but he's a lot of people down there just as his grandpa had this moment where he was just
Standby how many white people
His face was there like ants
Come to the area so
He had the idea of a
Trying to send his kids to school so they can
Intermingle or whatever
Basically Joe says his grandpa just had this realization
Recant
We can't go back
Got to go forward
And it seemed to him Carlisle
Was the way for
Who are we going now
Baskets were admitted here's how it would work they would come in
And it immediately have their picture taken
On arrival
Then they be given an Extreme Makeover
Which would also be photographed
This is Tom torlino
Barber showed us a picture of a Navajo kid looking maybe 18 years old today 1882
This is one of your ride so you he's got kind of dark-skinned high cheekbones hearing
He's wearing elaborate necklace looks like it might be made of bone and he's wrapped in a blanket
And then I hear he is in a suit with clean cut hair the second picture his hair is very short not long
No blanket
It's wearing a three-piece suit sitting there with spread collar and parted hair
Snapchat you have
Indian
Tom Wightman
Alex and Sophie
Joe American Horse
His family's all that transformation firsthand and Sophie was there in Carlisle for 5 years
When she came back and she looks like a white woman to know she had that real tiny waist and
Vomiting everything
And
You can speak Lakota
She forgot
Haha
We just think about the
Disrespect
We spoke with one guy oppressor Eric Anderson who teaches at Haskell is us apart Potawatomi just a mess
Imagine the parents
First time they see their kid
Kids parents are seeing their students marched around in
Essentially the uniform
Of
What had not
Very long before for many of the tribes
Ben
The uniform of the enemy
At the very least
I think that would be
Startling
Did a case
According to Sally Jenkins after the kids were
Cropped and redressed
Brentwood running through a bunch of
Drill sanding Carlisle was a little Military Academy
And the Indian kids were so unhealthy at first they have been put on an unfamiliar diet they had been sleeping indoors
For the first time in their lives and a lot of them are getting sick
Movie know that Hindi 39-year history
The school
At least
200 kids died
A disease
4Health or even homes
Hand soap
Was constantly trying to get the kids outside
And
At a certain point he hired some teachers
Sally thinks that one of those hires
Probably one of the first dormitory Masters
This guy who had formerly taught at at Ivy Leagues
School he showed the Carlisle Indian kids
This game that the kids at Harbor playing
Have you thought it would toughen him up
No it's but suddenly
They're playing football
No keep in mind this is at a point in 1882 where
Football's barely a thing
Not so many schools had teams
It wasn't such a thing as a head coach back then they were volunteer coaches who tended to be students or ex-students for the Carlisle
Kids self-organized level the field start to play they even start to scrimmage some kids across town
And it one of those games
Call you Barbara
Staci Matlock who is upon a student at Carlisle later became a Pawnee chief
He broke his leg
Playing football in Pratt that's it
Football
Is in his mind he was trying to civilize these kids in football was doing the opposite
But
Showtime later
Set David Adams approximately three dozen Carlisle boys came into Pratt's office they said we want to play football
Do you know what they said exactly we don't have
We don't have the exact words
Buy Pratt says at one point
He says while they stood around my desk
I'm quoting here around my desk there black eyes intensely watching
This is the order gave practically all the arguments in favor
About contending
An outside football
And ended up
Requesting the removal of the Embargo
According to his Memoir Pratt was
Bowled over by the eloquence and passion of the peel
So we said
Okay you can play
If you do these two things what he says
Never slept
People who are looking
Okay
And the other one was you have to beat the best teams in America
And that early Point American football
Team was yell
Which brings us to October 24th 1896
It's a r off all day in New York New York
Yes at the old Polo Grounds
Apparently there was about four thousand people in the stands including a handful of newspaper men New York newspaper men
Give me a big story
How did they publicize it what did they say
They represent specifically the Perfection of mod
American Life
On the other side
The real Sun
Origin playing the Redskins history and story of War developed
By education and if you read the newspaper stories are written as they're written in this kind of blood curdling
Shot through with Indian cliches you know from the Redskins
Right right Cody's David Adams in one paper
Indian fashion
I mean try to put yourself in the shoes of a New Yorker in the early 1880s PR contact with an American Indian
Was in a wild west show
It was theater
And here comes a football game
And all of these American Indian kids run onto the field and there's literally an instance
What are the first games with someone in the audience says will they look just like our boys
Because of course
That's a pratt wanted
Now one thing it was immediately clear to everyone in attendance when they saw the Carlyle players was that they were physically outmatched
Dell Rapids
Shaklee 20 lb Spider-Man impression going in as it'll be an absolute smear job
But they released the odds are heavily against them
But
3 minutes into the game
EBay big pile up
Squirting out
Carla guy picks it up
And runs
The entire length of the field 63 yards
Scores a touchdown
Now
Nobody had scored on Yale and seven games they were Furious so what they do is they use their bulk
To slowly
Push
The pile down the field
Twice
To take leave
And with three minutes left
Jealous up 12 to 6 Carlisle has the ball
Carlisle running back charges the pile in gets clobbered falls backwards
And just as he's about to hit the earth he laterals the ball
To a teammate who grabs it runs around the scrum the entire length of the field
Carlisle scores a touchdown that would have tied the game
But
Called back
Bye
A referee
Who was the Yale man
Why the call was that the referee claimed that a whistle had blown
The play dead
Well they were they were Furious
Yes there was bullying them
And hooting
Everyone knew it was a terrible miscarriage of Justice we're going to walk out of
We are leaving this game
But according to David
At the last moment
Runs down from the stand coming onto the fields at Wayside ways I don't forget rule number one
A gentleman
Pratt did not want
This game to end
Because of
Their tempers even though they've been wrong
Bye-bye that call
So the Cowboys
Finish the game
And when they walk off the field
They get a standing ovation
Carlisle wins incredible respect and renown
In the aftermath of the game in fact one of the newspaper men
After another Carlisle Yale game or something similar
Wrote something to the effect of Carlisle could beat 11 yell men but they couldn't beat 11 Yale men and a Yale rep
Yes
After the Yale game of 1896
Pratt
Is committed
Pratt believes that it's the greatest thing that can happen to his school
It is an instant way to do what he's been struggling to do for 15
Years at the Carlisle school which is to
Prove the value
Are these American Indian kids against their white peers
D'Abruzzo value or civilized
To civilize them but also to prove that given education and equal opportunity
They were the equal of there
How's their white peers
He was before all of his forcible assimilation methods which were
Remain extremely cruel
And destructive
I truly believed
In the concept of of racial equality
The complicatedness
Pratt ahold Carlisle idea
Kep smacking ass in the face as we were putting the show together it mean on the one hand they were clearly students who felt
The Carlyle was prison
Is that Barbara Landis
When she took us on a tour of the grounds of the former
Carlisle Indians
She said the kids will even set fire to the building
It's a yes M did burn down which is kind of typical on Indian campuses
Fires in burning building why
Int form of resistance
On the other hand
When will you start looking around for original archival recordings of
See the earliest Carlisle players pretty much the only recording me to find
If you're making it
With this oral history with a guy named
Albert exendine in the early 70s
Justice
B99
You are 15 years old
Can't really play you too much of this cuz the audio quality is really bad but in the interview Brad comes up
Stratosphere
And xidan talks about them with a great deal of affection and gratitude
Father of indian education
Call the father of Indian education
Man so he's a tough figure Pratt he's got very mixed Legacy I mean I like to say Pratt was his country
Whatever you think of him he was his country
Sookie sookie 1896 he gets
The Berkeley
UCF football score PR yes
What happens next
He begins looking around for coaches full-time coaches
Just to come in and coached
The team
And he whines up
With Cornell grad
Name Pop Warner
Glenn Pop Warner
Is this part right here
Just to give you a visual
Kerasotes pictures
If Mike did go ahead Einstein's hair up Pops a little bit of a of an outlier
East Texas roads
He's a bit of a rogue
Can be kind of vulgar party a little bit
And that is exactly what he does in spectacular fashion
When you get to the Carlyle because Pop Warner looks at his Squad and he realizes that
Sure they're fast they got heart but they're underweight and they're small
Wasteful yeah well they might occasionally for Setai with it where they yell if they
You know
Have killed themselves
Physically
They weren't going to beat the ivy League's on any kind of consistent basis without
Without doing something different
And dumped it was a very fine line between innovation
And cheating
In Pop Warner start 6
Exploding that line absolutely as hard as he can
And he comes up with
The trick play
For example
1903 Pop Warner devices the hidden ball trick what was that
The hidden ball trick is the quarterback takes the ball
And actually
Behind the Chute Parliament
Tucks it under another guy's sweater
While the big pile of man is struggling in the mud in the center of the field not knowing quite where the football is but believing it's summer
Summer in the middle of the pile there's this kid who squirts around the end but the football hidden under his jersey and he's 30 yards downfield beef
Before anybody realizes it how does it keep the ball from falling out of his jersey
The Jersey so that the ball would stay in there without falling out a cheating pocket native cheating
Pocket without legal because I got to go together legitimate touchdown
Was it legal you ask
Pop Warner would have said
There was nothing in the rulebook against it another thing he does which actually worked brilliantly
Is a
Piso's
Footballs on to the front of their
Jerseys
Switch for really bulky sweaters at the time he sews leather football-shaped patches onto the front of their jerseys
In order to try to disguise who's got the ball
Sane
Betches Bachelorette
But
Harvard
Did not take this line. Harvard retaliates by painting the footballs the same color as their
Jersey's it's maroon everywhere so when they basically what you can't see
American football is essentially a rule-breaking experience
As opposed
British football
Didn't have referees
At least initially a British football ran on the underside
But with American football
The rest were there practice
In the beginning and she says it was largely a response
The brutality the game but also to the kind of rule band
That you saw from Pop Warner in the coral island
Everytime Pop Warner came up with an innovation the next year there was a rule against
So immediately I really would get together and pass a rule and say okay no more
NFL rulebook really virgins in an American football and it's thanks to Pop Warner
Sleight of hand
In pop Warner's Greatest Latest
And maybe
The Carlisle Indians most soaring moment and I mean that literally
Happened
At a moment when the game almost
Disappeared
Nest cam
Start of message
Yes this is David Adam Strange and I got an email message asking me to read credit text
Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation enhancing public understanding of science
Technology in the modern world more information about Sloan
At www.
Sloan. Org okay there it is
AdvoCare
And this message
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents
Aunts and uncles teachers were looking for stories about what we're calling
Tiny moments of brilliance
Basically I want to hear about those times when I did something
It just means you bring back and say whoa
Maybe it was the moment that I
I kid you've been reading to 4 month started reading back
Do you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lesson
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of their musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed are ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the
Epic moments where
Kid does something super smart
But it doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story
T-shirt with us
Go to radiolab.org
Flash brilliance
And record a short audio message
And that's radiolab.org
Brilliance
Thank you so much
Amgen abumrad and Robert krulwich
Is Radiolab and getting back to our story on the Carlisle Indian School and the
Birth of the
Football
What are the most important moments in the story I happens at a time when football it was right on the edge
Spearing
Timeout 1905
This was
The most violent year in football
19 people died on the football 19
That's crazy
Cuz what would happen is that Carla will try and do these things that are open up the game
The iveys would consistently respond by making the game more about Brute Force more about violence
And suddenly all the major programs
We're spooked
Columbia polls
Are there football team
Harvard even think about doing that and so and this is kind of odd Into The Fray steps
President of the United States of America
Teddy Roosevelt
The conrad beijing
He's like football he like the
The manly aspects of it's a tough aspects of it
But nobody like people dying
And then there was his
Skip gets his son
What's playing
And and getting beat up pretty badly
As well
Broke his nose
Plated eyebrow
The one game you got knocked out cold
So after the violence of 05
The present
Calls the president of all these colleges in Saint
Washington
And according to David Adams he basically tells
That the rules had to be Rewritten
It had it become
A little bit more safe at least
Or it would be bad
And out of that we see a couple of rules
First school to side in order to loosen up the
The pile
They're going to
Tinker with the
Down yardage ratio
3 Downs of game 5 yards
3 Downs
10 yards
Renounce
Forward
Couple years later
But the second rule
Just may be the most important first
Is for the first time
They legalize the ability
To move the ball
Through
Free-floating
It surrounds us all
Okay where do we go to the next today soak if I could if I could place you in a moment
Before this you'd like to hit
I believe
November 23rd 1907
Yes the big moment K can you set the scene
From the standpoint of broader American history things have gone airborne
You mean Wilbur and Orville Wright 1960
There are aeronautical experiments happening really all over the world in France everyone is experimenting with line machines things
Things are going up in the air
But not so fast with football because
When the rule committee had made that rule about for passing they'd also hedged a little bit saying
If you throw forward pass through receiver doesn't catch it
You are penalized 15 yards which back in the day with a monster amount so nobody threw the ball was too rich
Back story goes as soon as that rule got passed Pop Warner goes back to his garage
Show me the garage with a ball
And he starts experimenting and what would be the most efficient way
Costas
People have to understand that the footballs knows days are not the footballs we have today with the nice
Oblate spheroid or whatever they call it
With a nice points and thinks he's a rugby ball
Citic imagine that deflated basketball
They're thicker in the middle they're not as well shaped
They're really tough to get your hand on
It's all right
And in 1906
In Albert exendine Zorro history we talked about this in 1906
He says called all the players together
He tells them
You would have to learn
Carla ball
Spiral the ball
Cuz if you throw the ball in the spiral it gets
10 times less Air drag
And if you throw it and over and plus it's easier
They start experimenting with it a little bit in in 1906 but they come out in 1907 as a throwing offense
Which gets us to that game
November 23rd 1907 Carlyle place the University of Chicago last game of the season were in Chicago
And the Chicago team is arguably the best in the nation V best
Will Carlos good at this point though
Yeah but Chicago
Stagg field
And they're 27000 people in the stands
Well what happened was the Chicago players had decided to try to defeat Carlisle's innovative
Forward passing by Justice
Knocking the crap out of their receivers every time they came off the line of scrimmage
Until Carlisle's greatest receiver Albert exendine our guy had been stymied the entire game because the minutes ball
Snap Chicago players wood
Hit him and try to throw him down or knocking out of bounds
So
Pop Warner said the exendine here's what we're going to do next time they hit you out of bounds
Sneak around the bench and get back on the field
By some accounts with X and idea but
On the next play
I would like to dine at expected ends up out of bounds
But it keeps running
He runs around the back of the bench spectators
Maybe around the van and comes back on the field
Reddit that moment
Hauser the quarterback of Carlisle
Lex Luthor vicious spiders
Can I have your recently shitbag
This is Sally's description of that moment from her book the real All-American
For a moment it was a frozen scene in a stage drama
The ball hung in the air a tantalizing possibility
Could exendine reach it
Woody catch it
Or drop it Defenders will then stare down field
Spectators watching from the stands
Redhead died in their Collective throats the spiraling ball
Defy physics
What made it stay up
When will it come down
In that long moment 27000 spectators
Mashed together on benches and crammed on platforms
May have felt their loyalty to the home team evaporate in the grip of a powerful new emotion
I have noticed something they never had before
Set a ball traveling through space traces of profoundly elegant path
They may have realized something else
That it was beautiful
The ball struck is human target
Action done caught the pass all alone
And trotted over the Chicago line
The stadium exploded
Sound in motion it was the game break it the rest was just anticlimax
The final score was 18244 Carlisle
But very next year the ivy league pass is a rule that you can't leave the field and then come back on
That's what a real company
Description of the ball in the air
Is
Timeless
Anyway that's exactly why football is still beautiful
For the time that's that's that's when
Carlisle in 1907 is when American football becomes to sport that you watched
Oh wow this is
This is the fee can we get out
After we spent an entire day looking at pictures of
You know Albert exendine in
Pride Pop Warner and doulas Lone Wolf
Lino and all these
Carlisle players Barbara and Carol took us to the field where they practice
Answer this is the Carlyle
Indian School football field
Covered in snow
410 degrees out here really really bright sun coming off this now
And sit empty
And we just kind of walked around and
Try to imagine all the stuff
We just seen in photos
He was a little bit like walking among ghosts
That's the sound of the flag blowing in the back
Understanding on that feel the end
Having the
Thought that I couldn't quite art
Calculate
The later of Eric Anderson a professor from Haskell
Remember the Potawatomi Nation
Surprise finger on it
He said she said that like there's a lot of room on a football field
Minutes from 4
Anger
And war and violence is also room
Pride
Kind of coming together that's not a pratt coming together where one side gets erased but it is it coming
Together there is a middle ground
Clearly it's more than a game
The stakes are higher than that
You know
Will we as Indian people be accepted
On our own terms
Also
In our ability
To meet you
Halfway
Will we be accepted
Through
This as the vehicle
It's clearly more than the game
A lot of people to think of this episode I we had original music made for us for that episode from Morgan Oak
Cocaine you can hear him right here playing the banjo that's Morgan Oakland music.
Come check them out
Also add original music from Austin musician Shakey Graves
India Albert exendine take that we played as from the research division of the Oklahoma Historical Society
Cumberland County Historical Society in the US Army Heritage and education center
Where you can go and see
Tons of photos from both archives or you can come to us on our website radiolab.org we have
Ton of old archival
Football picks
Nunavut
Before and after pictures from The Amazing
Really amazing
And we also have a link to Sally
Jenkins book
Which is
Highly recommend
The real all Americans
Radiolab.org
Thanks also to Reggie Kathy and
Scott Graham to Noah Robbins to Michael
Turn this to Matt dellapina
Colwyn bjr McCarthy
Tunica
DJ calling Michelle Campbell at Haber and special thanks for a special thanks to our amazing volunteer cheers
Squad that came out
When whether the Brooklyn called to scream and holler and bring the story to life
Speaking of that
Very special thanks to Brenna Farrell
I found the story and produced it with us in the production floor from Damiano marchetti
That was part of an episode called American football the we put together a Radiolab few years back
Hope you enjoyed it there's more of that episode sexy some great interviews that happened in the second half
That you can hear it radiolab.org I'm Jedi boom Rod thanks for listening
Go Eagles
This is Graham Elwood from Memphis
Radiolab with created
It is produced by Soren wheeler
Maria matus R Padilla is our managing director
Our staff includes Simon Adler
Rachel Cusick David devil
Bethel Hobbs
Tracy Hut
Matt kielty
Robert krulwich
Life of Nasir
Melissa O'Donnell Ariana
Pat Walters
Aunt Molly Webster
With help from Amanda or on check
Shima OluKai David Fox
Nygard fatale
Phoebe Wang and Katie Ferguson
Are fact-checker is Michelle Harris