Are you awake
Northern listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
Hate this is Radiolab
I'm at Walters
And today we have the fifth episode of our mini series
G
Last episode we had a story from Google Miller about eugenics
All about scientists who were applying the darwinian idea that species can be shaped by natural selection
Too Human
Like instead of waiting for nature to choose which individuals
Of the human species were most
A quote-unquote
They thought
They could speed things along
And in the process
Create like
A perfect human
Which I as we got into last time was
I did after
And at a certain point Lulu argued that these eugenicist
In emphasizing
There one narrow idea of
Perfection over everything else
They sort of missed the point of Darwin Darwin talks about
Sing this one ingredient that he Marvels at he doesn't understand why it's there
The thing to which we all
Oh
Existence on Earth
Variation
What makes a species resilience
Is differ
But that's a very selective reading of Darwin
Turns out not everyone agrees with her it is true of course that variation is really important to evolution
But it's variation coupled with selection that actually gives you
Success so
You know I disagree with
Her interpretation
So not too long after we talked to Lulu
I I did an interview with a scientist
Who takes a very different
Aficionado
And he's come into a bit of controversy
Some people argue
Betty's
Taking those
Old ideas
That certain people can decide which humans are fit enough to exist
And which ones aren't I think it'd be very careful because
Nobody here is trying to optimize
One specific trait or number what we're doing is identifying outcomes that I think most people agree
Free maybe are not good
And arguably he's walking those ideas
Into the future hello
Okay to backup a Beat
Hello
Hi is this Steve
Yeah this is Steve this is Pat
Hey Pat how are you
This is
Steve Schuh
I'm a
Theoretical
Physicist who also works in computational genomics
Steve in his early 50s
Has short black hair little wire rim glasses
And he says he's been interested in genomic
The power of DNA
Yeah actually so when I was a kid. I watch too much TV
Is that right
Yeah this is 70s there was no parenting going on
Things were so laissez-faire back then and so when I went home in the afternoon if it's the very favorite
Thing I would watch
Was
Star Trek the original
Star Trek with William Shatner as Kirk and Spock
And in the Star Trek universe in the late 20th century
Engineered intellect
How to survive they had these so-called
Eugenics Wars
In which some genetic Supermen were created
Check out who is this man
Bite technology
What do you want with us
They were smarter and more capable and they almost took over the Earth and all that was quite Vivid in my mind when I was
Was growing up and he says
Elsa made him Wonder
Steve like lots of kids growing up in the 1970s had to take an IQ test at some point
End
He says he's bored
Really high
Like in the top 99 percentile
Any bathroom self
Why is that
Am I getting better vitamins is it cuz my mom and dad
You don't make me go to bed early at night
Is a city environmental causes that are making me
Different from my peers or is there something different about my DNA
Mrs. Pete
At one point took this question to his local library I found this whole section where they had book after book
About studies done on identical twins how they measure IQ or are they measure cognitive ability
So I just it was
Very Stark in my mind that something about our DNA
Could influence
The power of effectiveness of your brain
This was
Dope that late 1970s
And at this point science just
Wasn't quite ready to tackle those questions in a serious way
At that time we had no way to actually directly measure DNA
And even by the time I was in college
We had not
We're nowhere near being able to sequence a human genome
Soap Steve went in a different track
Went to grad school for physics
Said well I'm going to work on black holes and Quantum field Theory because
Where are you know we would take a huge technological breakthroughs for us to make
Progress on these questions
In my lifetime
But
It wouldn't take as long as he thought yes
Speakers
15 years later
This is when roughly this was
Mm
June 26th
2003 back
Good morning
The moment we are here to witness was
Just brought about standing beside podium in the East room of the White House
President Bill Clinton announced
We are here to celebrate the completion of the first survey
Of the entire human genome
More than a thousand researchers across Six Nations
Have revealed nearly all 3 billion letters
About miraculous genetic code Eastside come to fruition
Search Project huge advances in our capability to
Read out somebody's DNA and along with all these advances Steve watch as the price of a
Soda for Human Genome was sequenced at a cost of 1 billion dollar
Dramatic
Today the cost
Does Pell Grant decrease
Genomic sequencing
$47,000 in a roundabout $1,000 cost of genotyping
Is going to come down here I realized wow
It is amazing how this rapidly
444 is born even conceived ideas about genomics and
Genetic engineering will come true
And if I get to be one of the scientists
Who makes real
Some amazing trope
From science fiction that would be the most awesome thing in the world
Maybe thinking
I was anyway
At me Steve Mister point about Star Trek episode about the Eugenics Wars
But
That was his interpreter
So
Those thoughts were in my mind when I thought what is it going to take
For us to figure out
The genetic architecture of human intelligence
Still around 2011
Steve started to Pivot from physics
Did you know me
Just hoping to find a portal
Secular
Place in the genome
That was influencing your say IQ score
But now
I'm Diane Sawyer
Tonight on 60 Minutes
Even if team ran into a problem
You mentioned the human genome in all of the things that it was supposed
Do
Ashley
A lot of people have been this
Pointed genetics turn out to be way more complicated than a lot of people thought of
Because way things were promised and it hasn't really happened
It was definitely oversold an initial hope had been like let's find the one gene causes
Best rate
And the one mutation that causes
Is that disease
And I in the early years scientists found a few of those sort of one to one
But
Only if you
Failed to turn up
You know some of the Hidden connections they had expected to find or they turned up stuff but then it couldn't be replicated
The same within a decade all human diseases would be cured
Not too many of them. That was kind of the
The first
Face this is Megan molteni I'm a staff writer at wired and explain to us what they found was that
Became clear that most traits in human beings are caused by a single gene or even a handful of genes
They often arrive out of the complex interaction of hundreds
Thousands or even tens of thousands of genes and other bits of DNA working in concert
So the challenge sort of shipped
It was about finding a single gene or mutation for any one thing
About mapping the huge after the genome and looking for variation
And so we realize we need many many more phenotypes
And much much more data
And so
How the address that was
Dexter began banding together into these big International Consortium to pool together data and dial up
Statistical power for everyone 2017
Public Square 23andMe provides contributions
Their data into the mix and so by the summer of 2018 they're comparing the DNA of 1.1 million people
Japanese giant data set that essentially launch
This next wave
Genetic study
Yes that is the data set that has been studied to produce predictors
And that kind of brings us to
Can I bring the city's genome-wide Association studies
Explaining these can get pretty complicated but the basic ideas
But that you have a bunch of talk
People and you want to find out what makes them tall
Genetically
So you take the genomes of all the top
People billions and billions letters
And you feed that data in Turkey
Computer that scans all the buildings flat
And it looks purple
Like what do these people have in common
And computer might say like
A bunch of them have a certain mutation at
Spot 270 3674
And a bunch of them also have mutation in spot 920 3672
And another mutation is about 38000
I'm just making
App
Steve actually did this an hour
For height and the
AI algorithm identified about
20000 different
Locations in your genome
That
Determine tight
At least informed
20000 spots in the genome that have
Some influence over how tall you are
It is
This is called
Training docker
And went to train
What's its found all of these pattern
Once it has figure all that out
You can men do
Is prediction
For people that have never seen before
So what you do is you take the Genome of someone knew what we call out of sample data
This person is not involved in the training and feed
Gestageno
This guy have a RB at this location how about at this location how about at this location
You at 20000 x
End of the fing world
Predict
This guy's going to be 6 or 2
Wheaton in how accurate exactly is this thing
Well so we recently just a year-and-a-half ago so
Succeeded
In
Building a predictor which has an accuracy of about
Plus or minus in
That's pretty amazing
Yeah and we don't know like what those genetic variations
Doing we just know that
Computer said there's something different happening
Indonesia
Places
I pray the taller people then for the other
That's correct
Avere eyes are almost like Black Box
Does you train them
And then you got to carefully test them but once
Once you validate that
My God
The Lord
Are the Martians just came and gave me this black box which does
This thing
It predicts height
And not just
We have a pretty good bone density predictor turns out that's pretty heritable
Things like
Diabetes atrial fibrillation
Breast cancer prostate cancer
So you can you can do us
Like literally anything
Again
Cheney
So where this gets
Interesting
Is
That
Perhaps unsurprisingly just in the last
Years
Steve Hsu starts wanting to
Use these genome-wide Association
Study is
As a way to
Predict
Intelligence
Intelligence is a complex
Straight so we know there are genes involved
We know there are lots of them
But environment so where you grow up even how much you get to eat like all of that matters
2 but decent dozens of studies
Lockman tenant wins when it comes to intelligence
Or cognitive ability basically whatever we want to call what an IQ test measures which
As we know how is it going to take
The evidence that we know today suggest that genes are responsible for somewhere between
20 to 50% of house market
Bar or
How we can house how we can measure
What we call in Telugu
And so that gives you hope that if you had an update at your AI algorithm
Figure out
I had a crudely predict
Cognate perform
From from your genotype alone
No Estes allowed to do that
The first hurdle community in Renton
She was only a fraction of the 1.1 million
People
In the study
Had
Peace Corps data available
And without that it would be
Serving pasta
How to predict someone's IQ
But nearly every Jewish researcher on the planet was collecting
Educational attorney
And that's just the number of years that people have been in school they did that is like
Person that got nice
School diploma or a PhD
I am with Steve and I actually a bunch of other res
Searchers would eventually figure out
Is that the genetic pattern that predict
Educational attainment is actually
Very good at predicting IQ
Earthquake comprable
Flash Forward
2 today
We have predictors for cognitive ability that correlate
About 23 or .4
With actual
IQ score
So just put that in
Correlation
1 means the computer would be able to
Predict the IQ score
Exact
Every time
I'm based on
Genetics alone
Correlation of 0 means computer base
Physically beat guessing
At random
2.3
2.4
I bet like that doesn't
Team very high to me.
Directions to
Pretty low analogy
Let me give it to you this way
If you admit a bunch of
Kids to college
And you have their SAT scores
You can predict their GPA in college
And the correlation between those two variables
Is also about point
Got so we're kind of at that level of capability from
Pure genius
The way Steve
Using
That predictive capability
At the moment we are out
Starting to use it in multiple Clinic
Around the world
That's where I start to get cold
Morgan and all that
Epic rock break
Hi my name is Alex.
I'm calling from Los Angeles Calif
Radiolab
Supported
Park by the Alfred P Sloan son
Enhancing public understanding
Tencent Technology
More information about Sloan
Www
Scott Sloan
Great stories deserve a great platform
That's why pocketcast delivers a beautiful design simple but powerful experience that offers more control
It's the premium app for listening search and Discovery download Pocket Casts today at Pocket Casts.
WNYC or find us on the Apple app and Google Play stores
Okay we're back from break
Look at Walters
This Israelites Jeep
Back to my discussion with Steve Schuh
So you also have a company yeah actually it's a it's a tech startup with invest
Stirs Venture funds and
You know wealthy individuals
What's your company called again
It's called genomic
Genomic prediction
Prediction
Okay
And you you're starting to apply these things you've discovered to
Two testing yes by testing for embryos
First of all the embryos were talking about here are the ones that were produced through IVF
IVF
Speedo basically pass to baby
Take a little sperm and egg combine in a Petri dish for later transfer
So every year about a million babies are born worldwide
Using IVF a million I didn't realize was that high
It's about a million worldwide
And that means are actually many millions of embryos produce
Because when you do IVF you often produce
More embryos then you end up using
Which means that oftentimes what IVF couples face
Is a choice
Which embryos to use and which would be the best to use
And so
It is now common to do genetic testing on those embryos
Typically really basic
The most common thing right now is just a
To test to see whether the number of chromosomes is normal to screencast down sin
Relatively simple test that is by far the most common kind of genetic testing is done
But now though if you think of the technical breakthroughs that I described to you you can you can screen against
Much more than just down syndrome
And so the company that we started
Takes the same standard biopsy that's already used to do the chromosome count screening but takes it a step further and
And actually sequences a chunk of the Genome of that
And we can then applied all of the genomic predictors that I described to you
To an embryo
So the doc might say
Embryo number 4 looks like
Stephanie can have type 1 diabetes
Umbria number 3 has a very strange outlier for heart attack
Etcetera etcetera and applying the information you have about
Intelligence
Today's embryos in this decision
As well
So that's the most challenging
Question that's the one that everybody wants to focus on
Because we can do it
But you know it whenever journalist contacts me
Even if the person I know has an unhealthy fixation on IQ and doesn't want to talk about all the help
Positive health things
Associated with this technology
Just wants to focus on the one thing that
You know everybody gets heated up about the end
But yeah I still want to have the conversation because Society needs to understand what is actually going on
So
Our current policy
And we arrived this after really a lot of
Thought
And not wanting
To get out ahead
Of where Society is on this
The only thing that we report
About the intelligence of
The individual embryo
Is if the embryo is an outlier
In risk for
I think the medical term is
Takacs what is it is it a mental disability
Something like that
I think it's
Intellectual disability intellectual disability
And that
The predictor would be
Saying that it's likely that this embryo would have a
And IQ score below a certain number yes I think intellectual disabilities
Probably something like IQ of 75 or something like this and
It would mean that
The IVF physician will get a report
Saying
Embryo number four has a very unusual
Large number
Of the variance
That
Depress
Intelligence
And I think that's a reasonable thing to want to know
Is there a parallel track happening in your mind
Because the other
People who had gotten excited about making super people besides the science fiction people are like
The Nazis
Oh yeah
You know the idea that you would
Dehumanize some people because they're less able
Is extremely dangerous
But this notion that all we shouldn't do any of this research because there was a guy called Adolf Hitler
That's kind of crazy
Tumi
We every technology really powerful technology weathers AI or genomics or nuclear energy
They have
Risks it's always the case
Sure but I
I guess I don't trust the IQ part of it like
Pretty well-established that I
The IQ score isn't a good way to determine intellectual disability like I think it's way
Be more complicated than that
Right but keeping my none of this is a sure thing in the sense that we're not saying
That we know
Embryo three
Will have IQ below 75 we're not saying that
Purchasing the chances
The child
We'll have a lot of difficulty
Modern society
That probabilities elevated
I guess I this is me where we disagree is that like I don't I'm not convinced you can know
What's the quality of someone's life is going to be like based on
And I cute
We're talking buddy that what you saying that conditional on that
Score
If I go out in the population I look at people with that score
A lot of them have not
Had
Very
You know I think positive lives
And I'm pretty sure that most mothers when they're pregnant
When they go to sleep at night
They're not dreaming about that outcome their dream about another outcome for their children it just feels like
Bad idea
The only question here is
Imagine that you are
Sister is going through IVF
And you happen to have the genotypes of all the embryos of your sisters
Potential kids
And you find out who a embryo for is predicted
To be
In less than the 1st percentile
For cognitive ability
But all the other ones are in the normal range or maybe even above-average
Would you tell your sister
I mean that's the basic
Question right
Who anyway we're going to make some kind of brutal decision like okay these two we implant
Those 8 we donate to science
Yeah right so it was going to happen anyway
2/8 of their 10 embryos
Right so
The thing is
If we can help your sister with little bit
Let's Help
That's my attitude
Ind2
I also want to emphasize that typically the embryologist will actually just look at the shape
Mike did the cells grow in a nice symmetrical pattern they just literally look at the shape of it and say like
That one looks nice yeah with your sister rather
Go with the gut
Feeling based on the shape
Or would you rather go with
Some genetic evaluation
Well I don't
I don't know because
It's probably really hard for parents to know like
The really interpret that information they might just hear 75 and then here
You probably intellectually disabled I don't want that
And I think
That freak me out
Yeah I do think the
We need really good genetic counseling
So the people understand the world that we're entering into
Because again no one's saying that embryo for is going to have IQ below 75
That's extremely bad that that's actually not the message
The message is that the risks are a lot higher than for all your other embryos
That's always
Well
But as for what a lot higher really means I mean there's different ways of quantifying
The strength of the prediction
The way to interpret it
Is it's a good
Predictor
On average and that's what makes it useful
In research
I talked to this guy named Dan Benjamin
But in general
It's not a good predictor at the end of each what level
He's a professor of economics
At USC and one of the founders of that big Consortium of scientist social science genetics associate
Consortium that help pull together the million or so genomes that Steve's genetic IQ predictor is effect
If we built on
And he says
Think about that comparison Steve made to the SAT
You know it's very hard to predict who's going to do while in college
And SAT scores are
Among the better predictors of that like
On average
The kids who score well on the SAT
Will do well in school but I mean if you look at a
University
You boys seen your grade point average yet there are going to be some pretty poor performers
And you might ask yourself
Why did the squirrel admit those students shouldn't they have been able to tell
Go students
We're going to do
Praying and the answer is they couldn't tell
For any individual person SAT scores
Are not
A good predictor
There are just too many
Other things that
Matter
And justice
Shift away from the sat back to like
Using a polygenic score to try to say something about an individual
If you had to
Quantify
What not a very good production meet how did you do that
Well if you pics two people
Randomly
In the sample
And you asked
How likely is it that
The one with
The higher polygenic score
Is actually the one who
.
More
Years of schooling
The answer is
About 60%
60%
Yes there is a 40% chance
That you'll get it backwards
And more to the point
You know in the context
Embryo selection
The prediction is most likely to be right it's going to be something like
Reducing it from 60% to 55
So according to Dan these predictions can be useful in large groups
But on an individual level
They're just a little bit better than a coin toss
So
I worry that companies that are offering a service
Exaggerating
The potential gains
And also
Are not being
Upfront
About what the risks are
Two things on that real quick
First dances
Because we don't really know how the genetic variations that predict IQ score really work
If you select against them
You might accidentally be selecting for others
Like mental illnesses or certain diseases are are these risks and we don't even know what all of the risks are
Number two
Which might even be bored disturbing
Dance has the genetic data all of this is based on
Came only from white people of European descent
I think they can get their hands on
Consequently if you try to use at a test like Steve shoes
I'm someone who's not a white person of European descent
It pretty much doesn't work
That correlation
Drops to the floor
So even the possibility of doing it is pretty much limited to
Well off
White people at this point
Insulin Steve
Thrift stores with this comp
That the genetic predictor is pretty much like the SAT
That's just not the whole story
For complicated
And what worries me is that you know you have
Guys like
Dan Benjamin
Advocating for this
You no more
Complex understanding of what
Statics really mean
You're saying they're being funded groups
They're not meaningful and individuals
You on the other side you have
Steve story
Which is
It's just so
A straightforward and compelling and you know it's Steve story and dance story
Happy face off
I just feel like
Steve's will win every time
Story of Stow
Simple it does feel like
In the end what you're able to tell someone
Like isn't that much because it is in a one-to-one predictor or even really
Close to that
Well it will get better
I guarantee you as we get more data the predictive power will get much better I think it will eventually
Achieve a kind of
Capability kind of like what we can do with height
Where are you you know that the error is about
I need a maybe plus or minus 10 points of IQ
You know I will say that
Mega miltank
Right now while he may
Be an outlier
In terms of what he's willing
To offer based on kind of where the models are now I don't think he will be an outlier
Furlong
The
Information is going to become available and it's
Only going to it's only going to get better
And of course there are many ethical
Things that we have to
It's sort out and I think different societies will decide different things about
How they want to deal with this
And so
You know if a particular country
Said
We do not want you to ever
Report
Anything about
Cognitive risks we just don't want you to report that
I would totally respect that
But then I think you have to read
Respect
If the nation of Singapore
If they decide this is an important thing to do
Will you better respect them too
Otherwise you're some kind of racist
Colonialist guy who says only my ethics
Count
So I realized I eat I realize the NPR audience may not like it but
This is the world that we're entering into
Have people used to act like has the
Predicted tool been used by
Consumers yet
So
They're different
Segments
To the
Product
The full-blown thing where you report
Genetic test scores polygenic scores for variety of traits
Is in the process of being used
What is the process mean like
Well I eat I'm not ready to report the birth of Annie
Child or anything but let you say samples have been analyzed
Okay
And it's been that information provided to
Couples
I don't know that I can comment on exactly
Any specifics
Along those lines I'd probably have to check with RCU
When I staying just the other day as we were finishing the story
Steve roach rosson said that while the company has provided brisk reports
Do IVF doctors
For various diseases like breast cancer and diabetes
They have not quote
Given a report warning of high risk for intellectual disability
Yet
And at the end of this
I find myself thinking about
The thousands of couples out there who are doing IVF
And the thousand more who will do it in the years and decades ahead
Honestly wondering like
I would love to use any name they want to know
Cycle early stages of IVF cycle 1
You can tell them
A really hard question
Feel uncomfortable
I think I would have a lot of anxiety over that.
You sure that is
Not that act
Brilliant
Healthy
I don't see what harm
We would need to ask
Before we would ever
I would probably want to know you want to know but then you're looking at a world where
People who have a lot of money
The Lacs
For the ones who are more intelligent are offered to me and it wasn't
Prohibitive
It is something I think we will test for before we do our next round he's probably will do
I don't think about it long and hard
Question
Who also wrote all the music
Help from Rachel Cusack
Our fact-checker is Michelle Harris
We have engineering help from Jeremy Bloom
And a special thanks to Katherine
Radiology is supported in part by science sandbox
Simons Foundation initiative dedicated to engaging everyone with the process of science
Will be back early next week
With the final episode
Pubg
Who plays
Message press 2
This is Megan molteni coin from The Wire
Offices
San Francisco
Radiolab
Is produced by Soren wheeler
Filling pieces are directors down design
Suzie lechtenberg is our executive
Simon Adler
Becca Bressler
Rachel Cusick
David gebel
That'll happen
Tracy hunt North Keller
Matt kielty
Robert krulwich
In Methuen
But he's not there
Sarakari
Aryan Lac
Emily Webster
With help from
Oshima Ali-A
W Harry
Their sound box
Melissa O'Donnell
Vanessa
Bruce Samuel
Anime
I got checker
Thanks bye
And this message