Are you weightless
Radio WNYC
Hey I'm Jad abumrad I'm Robert Radiolab today we have the story of just how hard it can be to be who you are
Actually are
But it seems like the entire world is doing its best to make you who you actually
Aren't I guess I could admit this could be too many details but
Story starts for us
With reporter David Conrad
So for me it was back in late 2014
I was living in Philadelphia as a grad student
It's time David was
Applying for jobs
And one of the jobs he's applying for was at a radio show that was doing the series about International women's issues
And so I had this on my mind and I was taking a bus
Southern University and I just overheard somebody talking about their recent trip to Venice
Of course
The classic tourist thing to do when you go to Venice is to take a ride on the canal boats the gondolas
And go down the canal maybe someone sends you a famous song
Very romantic
In case
Person sitting on the bus next to David was telling their friend
That they had
Taking a gondola ride with this
First ever woman Gondolier Venice
Yeah it really cooking around me realize like how how does it become a we
How are you I'm Kristen Kristen Clark also a journalist radio producer
And she and David are partners and collaborator
I mean this is it was interesting is like
We realize how big a deal it is to be female Gondolier is like
900 year old tradition and it's always
Father son father son father son or like uncle nephew down the line
Now nobody's there no ladies Evernote 900 years
Think about that for a sec
Almost a thousand years of all men men men men men men and then one day
You get a woman write as a headline
Woman breaks
To 900 year old glass ceiling I thought that sounds like a good pet
It sounds like God kissed you on the lips exactly it sounded it sounded like the perfect
Empowerment story I guess it's all over
What from the Guardians of the New York Times to the financial times to the Cedar Rapids Gazette
Time music made it all the way to Cedar Rapids newspapers in Germany and in China and Australia
They all all the Articles laid out the same basic story
It was this Algerian woman from Germany
Name Alexei
Tulip in Venice 20 years ago got around a gondoliers Association that never wanted to see a woman become a Gondolier
And eventually became the first ever female Gondolier Venice
The whole thing of course parking this giant gender War
But
That was sort of it
Pretty much the headline in the picture was the story
Many of the Articles didn't actually have all that many quotes from Alex
And so for me it sounded like a great
Simple opportunity to go back and tell a deeper story
Hell-bent on getting into this club
Just so clearly does not want them to
We evil Alex just
We're we're interested in your story were wondering if you might be willing to spend a few days with us this summer
And I was hoping it would just be like yes I'm happy to meet with you for a couple hours
And that would have been great but
We got an email back right away that said
If you come do the story you have to spend a week with me a week and then there are these questions about like who
We were as journalist what our purpose was and
A bunch of Demands you have to stay in the city you can't stay in like one of the suburbs and margary even though it's cheaper that you have to be in
In the city jerseys found at this time at a vision for things
I mean the message was definitely I want to tell a different story
Did you have any idea what that meant
No idea
But we had that
Echo I had that come into my head
So we flew to the Venice Airport. Took a bus to city center
Stepped off the bus
And you can smell the salt in the air from
Come from the Grand Canal and it was
Kind of rain a little bit was around midnight
We're kind of you know getting our bearings grabbing our bags and we
We look up
Across the parking lot
There's Alex
Standing under a Lamppost just leaning against it with a cigarette
Smoke
Kind of curling up into the light of the streetlamp
Short hair dark
It was slick back
Do you think you were in a Fellini movie
Honestly I didn't know what to think
This person
Was legit under a lamp
Smoking
Absolute Alex
Taller than I expected
The strong build
Afisa was a little weathered like someone who works outside all day on the water
Quite late so when you called I just finished school
How was your flight
Moscow first
And since it was late
We made a plan with Alex to meet up at 5:45 p.m. the next day
On the steps of Latin DJ Opera House
Okay beautiful Opera House
I loved all the mess in the
So anyway the the plan was to go out on a gondola ride which was one of Alex's demands in the first email
So we walk around the corner to where there gondolas Park
Hand
Taobao is like Shining
So the gauntlet was made for three people
Narrow jet black
Allison had about 12 years
What's up already quite a bit when I got it had a name
Can you choose it
All right
Sup
She wants to come in
Roku stick
So we climb into the boat
Perfect
And Alex stands at the back
Holding you are and
We're down sitting in the in the lower seats kind of just like pointing the microphone up
If I take photographs every once in awhile
He came here to study it first
It's not what I said
And
It was pretty much immediately cleared
I mean
But it was not going to be an easy interview
You came here when you said I know I know that was wondering right right
Yeah we had a notebook full of questions and things that we had pulled from all these articles and read
That pretty quickly became useless
Whenever I asked about being the first female Gondolier and they're the first woman in 900
4 years to do this
Star
Such an over and over
Nova Nova
Why won't you repeat things already
Done
This is very frequent journalism problem you become boring to the person you're interviewing you just start flailing
What are you do
You know we just thought maybe we should just be
Quiet probably
We are about to
We moved away from the tourist centers of the city and into the smaller canals
As we go around these tight turns
Alex would sing out for the other boats know that we were coming
So here are the Crossway this is why I shut off my direction
In order to
Avoid accidents because
Is it going to be is it going to arrive
You know we going to these beautiful archways
Pakenham Gardens
Necessarily need ice in order to
Appreciate
Econo Lodge
Every channel has a different song
Singing
Flying face
Song
Is a beautiful entry
Pittsfield
At one point a gondola cut through this rectangle of light
Shining from an open kitchen door
It was nice I mean the side of Venice was
Unexpected and really beautiful but
The whole time we were sitting on their notepads in
We're definitely quietly panicking
Well you know
Didn't know this at the time but you know I was like maybe you're a little too young and I think
Alex
Testing us
It may be a little bit too
You don't have enough experience Maybe
That was my concern but I like the
I like the enthusiasm
And I like the
There was an honesty which I like
Did you ever figure out what you were being
Sussed out for what was going on there for sure not on the boat
But we we actually made plans to go out to dinner that night
Considering how the boat ride we thought at this point we should return to square one
And leave the record at home
Alright then just trying to have a conversation anyway we sit down outside and very few people are in the restaurant where were the only tape
People outside they had to open when we got there too we should say we met Alex's girlfriend right now we're making
How to making small talk
And
Yeah it turns out
Turns out Alex's girlfriend is over
Photographer and she done this photo essay about
And the photos are really striking
Like one of them Alex is just like drowning under the water there's one that's just like Alex's back is to
Set the camera at this trip to muscular back like looking out the window over the city of Venice
Venice's loan Defender
Kind of like superhero style
So where is Alex girlfriend
Can you tell me a little bit more about what inspired you to take these photos and you know like small talk friendly stuff and
She kind of looks like
You know it's just it's so strange
You know we thought
We thought it was so clear
Wait like the photos were so like they emphasized every masculine quality on Alex's body
We
You know an artist statement you know we used all of the mail forms in Italian
Little Lake Louise which means
He instead of Les which means she but everybody at the photo exhibit was like oh must have been a typo or you made a mess
Mistake and she's like which is funny because I'm Italian so I should know and I was like
Pro pronouns
Louis
Key Alex
She used he
Key Alex is a key
Is Alex Translate
Oh my gosh Alex is a transgender man
Wow
What did you
That means you in that moment
What I thought that meant
Was
Alex was
Probably born in the body
That he didn't identify with
Mine was
Hey I didn't think transgender I didn't think
Alex is the guy of course
Alex at the guy I wasn't I wasn't that surprised
I would say that like flipping into heat not a thing
Like like it was like Alex is
Alex is a he
Alex is he
He is sitting at the table with us
Alex and his girlfriend
Very quickly it was like him
I'm looking at him
And then I start thinking about the story that we had come here to tell
That was about all of the women things that she had done her her her her woman here
Hero heroine first female in 900 years International symbol of female power
You start thinking about that and then it's like
Those things are really hard to square in your head
This real person
Is
Also the stories and how did that happen
What is it been like for 20 years to be inside of that story
When you're actually a man
After who knows
How many articles have been written about Alex this the first time that he is
Publicly telling his story
As a man and so we should probably just stop for a second
And talk about pronouns
Because this is really important for many transgender people
In moments when Alex
Publicly understood as a woman and was getting
Price for it
We've decided without permission
To only use his name or his title of first female Gondolier
While some of the people interviewed for the story were unaware that Alex is transgender and do use female pronouns
Or do you refer to him as a woman we
When were talking about him we
Will only use male pronoun
So after that dinner we made plans for the next day
On his motorboat he would just take us to a quiet spot and we would
What's the agreement on the water on the water
Shut up
Stop it Basta
Okay
A lot of false starts
Guadalupe baby I can
Ask
As if it has anyone ever asked
What
Pronoun you prefer
No never
Never have
Ever
So after getting some of the basics out of the way
Alex kind of started at the beginning
Well you know
It's a long story
I was born twist in De
Zoos in Germany Alex tells us he was born with a female body
But at a pretty early age knew himself to be a little boy
I knew you were ready before I went to school
Whiskey yes I was standing on the toilet to pee inside
Alex is it you know for him even when he was three that there should just be something on his body
That wasn't there I was praying for a penis every night
My my parents knew about it his parents were actually both doctors
But they
They will not
Supportive
You know I heard them you know they were talking about
All the weird
Stuff I did
How you rip your arms off of his Barbies
Cutting them like in always black
Pennsylvania
Trying them
By the way Alex dressed himself
Little pencil
Bay suit for for boys
And you know what's up
Of course very aggressive
As a child
Lot of fights
I was quite the Wyland
As I catch
So now I can up about this but you know
If it was a drama at home
It was a drama
The constant
Try of my
Mother
Get this
Behavior out of me
Alex's pretty early on
Apparel
Basically gave up on him
Ignore me as much as a good time which was
Saving me because I
Could wear whatever I wanted
Do whatever I wanted
A little brother was born in
That was a shock
That was a terrible shock because
Basically it confirmed
That my mother wanted
Desperately
A boy
But she didn't accept me as her son
That's what it was
Alex said basically you know that was the first time he saw what like
It should look like basically when a parent loves their kid
So when he was 15 he ran away from home
Pembroke and the number if you have a huge
District Court employee where they have all the prostitutes
All the bad things and that's exactly
Well I win some people kind of took him under their wing got a job kind of figured out how to take care of himself
I got lucky
But I know also very unlucky
Gay stories
But I got lucky
Did he ever think about
Transitioning to
Male body
He says he thought about it at one point but
In the 80s when I was 15
The opportunities you have had to become a man were very very
In particular if you wanted to go down the road of surgery I can remember for my family was
Constantly talks about how operations went wrong
How they went wrong and what went wrong answer
For me to go to the hospital to do an operation
And of course many transgender people don't end up having surgery
But anyway after homburg
At some point Alex fell into filmmaking and ended up in San Francisco working in in the filament
History and so 1996
He got involved in a production that sent him abroad to go scope out locations for a film that was going to be shot in Venice
The shows up in Venice in 1896
He's not a kid at this point originally he's just supposed to say a few days
Kind of just enough time to do some research and scope things out but somewhere along the way
He sees these guys rolling their boats down the canal and
Reasons Heat
Can't entirely explained
He's just
Transfixed by this kind of
Bored and I was fascinated by The Rolling star
That you will forward to you
Actually see where you going
So was just fascinated and I just wanted to try it out myself
Eventually
Alexandra Bachelor meeting a Gondolier
And asks like
Do you think I could do this and
Actually ended up down at the gondola station isn't a princess
Did they ask you to they ask you why you wanted to study I remember the first day
I was introduced by the
The head boss of the group Okay so
Alex she's going to be all mascot
Because this all Alex's a woman and there never been a woman Gondolier muscles them sought
For sure
This was like kind of a joke
There was a very old man
Who is the latest hit now we have a Gondolier with tits
For the first several months
Alex says he basically just picked up after the guys you wear the Busboys for everybody so you needed to
To clean that potent
To ship out the water
Like 10 20 *
A day
He says it's really backbreaking grueling work
Somebody that everybody everybody sees as a woman you think this would be like the worst place on Earth
But you know actually first those first months in the city just kind of with the boys dirty jokes
I saw this is great
Alex Newell the gondoliers nicknames walked and talked and acted like them and Kirsten the same way and
He says he felt like he was part of this tradition of new learning from these old guys work mentors to him
Really like maybe the best time of my my life
It was like he was home
And then the the trouble began
It started with a journalist
Reporter Consuelo Turin
We met in the noisy Cafe with a translator
She was a cub reporter in Venice working for a very politically Progressive newspaper and
She Was Out
Looking for her big story and she runs into our
How did they encounter each other
She was like
Whoa it's obviously did this is struck her attention
Araminta santalo here
It looked at her like there was this woman rolling among men
In Lake Stevens.
Cotton blend right in the mega
Unusual addition to tennis
So she looks like a whole morning and basically just
What's Alex's Behavior
Alec didn't want to talk so I can talk about it later basically I'm just a student they're teaching me
Don't make this into a thing
Recognize that you don't want to talk to me that you're apprehensive and that this might be difficult and I get this my TV
Can damage your reputation with the other Gondolier's
But this is an important story
Your Pioneer I can't ignore you and so Consuelo said the two options
I'm going to write the story no matter what so you can either talk to me and we can do the story together or I can write what I think
Leadville Co
You know I said he can't go out now and she said it will
Edible
And why wasn't Consuelo
Persuaded that she should wait
They will join this coming from all over the place
I think the story was going to get out there and somebody was going to write it
And Alex never started stopped and was like listen
Consuelo whoever
Let me just tell you the real
The way out of this is to speak and yet he stays quiet right
Would you ever since why
I mean
Just like some blank data points that might be helpful in understanding kind of where we were
So we're talking 1987
Just to give you like a corollary thing
Where we were in our discourse around LGBT issues was like Ellen DeGeneres I think that year
This is this is so hard but
Came out on her show
I think I've realized
That I am
I can't even say the word
Why can't I say the word like shortly after was canceled
Caitlyn Jenner was just a few years ago like we we didn't even really have a grip on what transgender was that wasn't a conversation that we were have
Having in public
Can you imagine what it would be like to be like guys guys guys don't worry though I'm actually a man
That wouldn't have gone over so well with the dudes at the gondola station
So what ended up happening after
Consuelo in Allen
Add to Showdown about the article
Well couple days later Alex is on the way to the gondola station I found it in the
Newspaper
Stop
The headline
A woman is challenging the gondoliers
So I was like I was on my God
Going to be hell
So it's in the newspaper stand Alex shows up at the Gondolier station of course is a big hello
Big unfriendly hello hello
We do everything
Teach you well and you know
Alex has one of the gondoliers stopped talking to him they wouldn't even let him watch their boats and then the
The ones who said
I told you in the beginning told you she's just going to blab to the Press
The whole thing you know what's like a little Stone becoming like that huge
Huge sink
By the way this is right this is coming right before Alex is about to take the very first exam
There's actually a series of exams and it gets a little complicated but eventually
Anybody who wants to be a Gondolier has to take this rolling test
And by all accounts
Alex was
Good
Let me talk to the guy who is ahead of the gondoliers association at that time
This guy phobia Scarpa was like
Is it more
Google the other manga
And this is the head of the guild
We also talked to this legendary rower named Franco kreia
Alex is better than most of the guys
Alex takes the test
And I failed the
Exempt
Which wouldn't have been
That by itself would have been such a big deal cuz a whole bunch of people fail the first exam but the thing was
There was a feeling that like something deeply unfair was happening
She had analog recording to Consuelo a lot of people started to think
Maybe the fix was in
So what other boys there
Field
Who are better than other boys who did not fail suspiciously pretty much all the people that passed
Four sons of gondoliers are from Gondolier families cuz if that's the right last name
Then I got angry I got a lawyer
Alex. This is going to be attention to how corrupt the license practices how crap this Association is I wanted that they exist
Repeat it for everybody and this
We let everyone retake the test that will basically be admitting that we favor certain families over other families
That was exactly what I want but it's not what they wanted
They said we don't want the bad press of this
But then this is another moment
According to Alex where his story just gets
Hijacked
Myeloid negotiated without my permission
According to Alex without
Telling him the lawyer together with the gondoliers association dug up this old law that says
Cuz Alex is a woman I mean he's not he's a man but they thought he was a woman and
Is law says that as a woman
He had the right to take the test again this time with women judges in the boat
When she came back and said okay here's what we're going to do
Do you remember what you said
Boston
I was so very upset
That was not what I wanted nothing to do with man or woman
Do you think she
Was your champion because she identified with you yeah for sure I was not my so it's faster
But
Unfortunately for Alex as soon as the lawyer did that
It became everyone's story
Oh yeah because
Is there rain with it
In the next 2 months every paper in town was writing about it
Show me statistics, then the story went global
Happy to become Banks first woman on the sink first female Gondolier
Build Gondolier blames chauvinism
And then things escalate into a full-blown gender battle
The gondoliers record super pissed because of all the stress that they're getting we talked to a couple of he likes Gondolier guys
She didn't
Disaster
Alex is it 1.6. So bad
That was one of them was saying you're not going to wait for you in a smaller than the street with a knife
2 Yuan
So I grabbed the guy I said where's your knife I'm here
Get it out
Can do it
That was one episode how many Oz's
So on the one side Alex said he has Gondolier's wanting him
On the other than feminism kicked in and Alex said he had all these women
Need to see them
Do you want me to lie because they thought he was a she read in the paper that she had
Try to
Take the test and had failed
And head cold fowl saying that the venetians remain and the United States system wouldn't let women become Gandhi
Is this is Jane Capital she was active in the community of Venetian women rowers of the time
Women gondoliers at that time but there's a whole community of female rowers they have teams
Isn't a race being doing Venetian Ryan for over 20 years
And being a female rower in Venice
Who is very difficult Elena this woman roar I was talking to
Was like I'm routinely when I'm out on the water like old men yell at me and say
In the kitchen
Cooking or cleaning your house why are you here
You're just a side dish table told me when it comes to racing there's a big discrepancy in the prize money
Getting like
Full times as much prize money
As the women
We are now trying to
Convince the city of Venice who gives prices
We are
Make men
We are not less than them busting their ass to try to be taken seriously in the sport
We are here we can do this when I saw this press about Alex fighting the gondoliers
They reached out I sent one of the other considered as down to speak to her when I come to
Bob and come and work with us and help us out help us teach people who got your back but she wasn't injured
No
Because Alex there are two problems first of all that you cannot compare
The golden robots with racing Ross
They're two different styles of rowing and second of all
Listens I got was it was kind of like I don't want to roll with you you guys all wear matching white skirts
Like not my thing
Say I remember there was a lot of
Resentment
Be one of us in this battle for equality
They see me and then they are convinced
The times feminist
But I am one of them and I'm not
And all of this comes to a head
In October 2004 when Alex has to retake the test
And this time with champion women rowers in the boat
Judging them
There was a lot of pressure
Everything about the test is supposed to be a secret location of the test the path that Alex is going to row of at no clue
We going to go
Suspiciously as Alex stepped into the boat
He noticed that there was a huge crowd wind up all the way down the canal and then difference
And they're shouting and yelling screaming what kinds of
Swear words in all kinds of go home and
Canada messenger hate
Female rowers in the boat glaring it and there's press lined up along the entire way
Every everybody has a Bus full of people
It feels like I'm going to in a ring
I tried to block it all out because I needed to do it next them
I wanted to do a good performance
I wasn't able
It was
He'll it one of the worst
Birthdays of my entire life
I really don't
I don't wish that to know
Texas real house
Hello this is David from Berlin Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan foundation in hunting public
Understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world more information about slowly www.ops.org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help this summer I'm hosting
And I request for those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
We're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments of childhood Brilliance basically I want to hear about those
When a kid you know did something
It just means you lean back and say whoa how did they do that maybe it was the moment that I can
Kids you've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons and you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed are ready music in the margin of their geometry homework were interested in the
Epic moments where a kid does something super smart but doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story please share it with us
Go to radiolab.org Brilliance and record a short audio message for us
Again that's radiolab.org / Brilliance thank you so much
Hey I'm Jared I'm Ron I remember Publix this is radio app and return now to a story from Kristen Clark and Dave
Conrad about Alex Haley
Transgender man who became somehow the first female Gondolier in 923 years
And that's an international feminist hero sensation and so we now find Alex being painted by everybody
Korean town in colors that he doesn't particularly agree with yeah and what's interesting is
How easy it is
To do that to someone Okay so
I'll tell you as we were doing the interviewing in the reporting I'm like I'm feeling like I have a good grip on Alex Asta
I'm feeling like I know what it feels like to be inside of a narrative it feels really achy and so I feel like
I'm kind of getting it and I'm like understanding the full Alex and like it's about all of these other things that have nothing to do with j
Gender so Alex's story isn't about gender at all
An end for me that made sense because I was like in my life gender has been a box like even even when you're in the right
Even when you're in the right box
Gender is a box and it can feel shity to be in that box since I was like yeah let's
Bust open those boxes together we're going to show you were going to show people who you are Alex
We would have these moments where I would be like
Wait a second
Like one night when we were in Venice
We're like trying to park our boat on the way to a restaurant and end like this guy is like trying to parallel park is by
About and Alex's kind of sitting there like chuckling at him
And so the two of them are like me or joking about it and then Alex says like he drives like a woman
I know it's like you know and the kind of rolled my eyes at it
But then later at the dinner
He was like he was like
You don't like
I don't really think that like a real woman could do this job
Minions like all like Macho about it too much a thing
Remember this
Of course you are very right
A woman can do everything but
This job
Just going to be very tough because
It's a real cool
Community
Images very cool
But when you said that but when you said that I got so I was like I'm so frustrated
And it was because
Think I was attached to the idea of like
It being equal
You know I mean I was I was just like super confused like
I don't know I just
I just want to know what you think
I'll admit in the moment I asked
Clumsy question
Do you feel bruised because you seem to be almost like
Prodding me you know I having fun and winking at David and do you feel like
You're fundamentally on a different team from me
Okay
I am on David's team
But you can't see that
Because he's you identify as me
But that does not that I can help that
How can I explain it to you let's put it this way when I'm in a group of woman
For example and they start to talk
I feel uncomfortable
The check thing says
I caught a chicken check
It's not really my cup of
TN.
I like it you can amuse me
But
The minute
They think that I am one of them it doesn't amuse me anymore
And if you uncomfortable
Like I don't I'm a man
I'm a little alien there
Cuz they think I am one of them and I'm not
When I'm with the boys
Comfortable
If it is a nice
Voice which I liked and we have the same type of humor and you know the same
Stupid jokes about women
For Alex
I think it was really striking is it whatever it is that makes him feel comfortable being seen as a man but not as a woman
It runs very deep for me there is a difference between men and women
Not everybody or even every transgender person would feel this way but the way that he sees it if there were no differences
But is there would be no but no wish to do Transition and there would be no transexuality
It's like that if if it would be the same
Yeah
I see you were singing is like a gender doesn't matter kind of Icon and he was
Saying
Actually it does match
Yeah
Obsessed with simpler question when
When does he actually become the first female Gondolier
Also Alex couldn't get one of these
400 or so special Gondolier's licenses because he failed
Protest in 2005
I open up my own business
He figured out that
If he Partners up with businesses in Town Lake hotels
He can actually real for them privately is the time I was looking at those olores and I found that it was false
Possible to open up my own business without having a license so I did
And so
For years he was just kind of doing this
Quietly then Alexandra
Square Hotel
Some of the gondoliers began to notice that Alex was throwing passengers without a license and of course they did
You can't do that
You have to be a member of this organization you have to have a specific license in order practice
I got some frets
Bubba fretzin
Damaging the gondola and six kinds of stupid little boys
So when they understood they cannot threaten me this way then they
Fish at City Hall to change the lot City Hall basically it's like you can't roll
You can't roll with Taurus in it without a without a license
Yeah it's a one-day Alex is out on his boat and he just gets pulled over
Basically told you're breaking this new law
And so I wanted to defend myself so we went on trial in
Court it was Alex is one lawyer City Hall in the gondoliers association there for lawyers for lawyers
I thought this was a lost case any already City Hall
Lust
City Hall fights back
Case goes to the highest court in the land
The lost again
Influence of a quart
With me a little stranger from out of nowhere
Technically the decision just said hotels can provide for their customers away that they need you so if they want to hire a chauffeur
Who happens to Rowena Gondola they can do that but what that actually meant was it now for the first time
Alex
Could be considered a Gondolier
There was a huge deal massive
Fix on Venice Gondola cartel
This is where we get all of those articles we read before we came to Venice
The story went all over the world
And and every single one the message was the same
We have our first woman Gondolier
I did that was something it was Unstoppable could not go in there and say excuse me
You know I'm not really identifying
No it was gone
Okay
It was done
Alex at this point in 2007 doesn't have any other income except for being able to Market
Himself through hotels and eventually online in Seoul
Of course I need to have a website people are actively seeking out this person who has broken the gender
Barrier and become the first female Gondolier in Venice so did would have been stupid to try to go
Against all this
Was already written so Alex decides to make his email his Facebook page and his wife
Website
Call Prima gondoliera
Or the first female Gondolier
I'm wondering if
Trading website with that name
Did that feel like you taking control of that narrative
Always that narrative taking control of your decision on that website
Has nothing to do with what I want
It's a label
You know I cannot change the label who has seen on 20 years of History
Shut up
Alex told us he was talking to his therapist one day at this
Transgender Center they have near Venice and she said you're like in the cage
This is like a cage for you you can't get really out of this
You know
It's the it's a difficult
Situation
It's a very difficult situation
I'm tired
By the time we met Alex he been living almost 10 years like this you know just kind of
Between these two stories out to his
Close friends but by day giving these tours as the first female Gondolier in Venice every few months every
New Taurus season these headlines would just regenerate first female Gondolier first female Gondolier first few
We left Venice that's kind of where we left him
Hanging in the middle of that
Any impression that we got is
Maybe that's just going to be how it always is for him
But why we didn't see each other so
Fast forward six months
We get an email from Alex
He says he's in San Francisco
Happening in your life
He had some news
Well you know I don't remember what we were sitting with a stalking in Venice
And we were sitting on the Terrace
I remember the
I was already in a news about something coming
But I wasn't sure what it was
It was a very difficult yeah I was kind of depressed with
You know I'm not I'm not that depressed person usually so I was hanging out
I was not moving much it was hanging out on my on my cell phone and I was
Trying to think and I was
More and more everyday was telling me that I was she another he
I don't know why I got completely intolerant before I was like I don't care what they say to me
I care that they're nice and now I was last night I can't do this anymore
Alex was about to turn
And it turns out that part of what was happening
Was that he was beginning to go to the early stages
Of menopause
I will
Hot was tired
Breaking out for nothing
After fighting with the gondoliers fighting with a feminist
This
Would like a final insult
So
I have this idea that humans might help
Wiz how I feel
I start to take the
The testosterone that was on the 7th of November
Which of the six hours
I get V smile on my face and in the end
Amelia yeah
Next thing you know I felt so good and the mood swings.
So I'm
No I'm like I knew me because I was looking in the mirror everyday Mall
What's this monster
He decided to fly to San Francisco meet with a doctor
Some people to wait like 2 years or 3 years before they start to do a surgery
I want to do it now because for me it was something like now or never
So now I'm here in San Francisco
Surgery on The Voice
That's about
Help for disabled
Into
I want you to start this year
Busybody witches
Confirming me
People see me as a first woman laundry means something for many people
It's not fair to them so you know I need to
I needed to say something
What changed on the Facebook side of change the name
No it's Alex I going to let loose
And
I did already a statement on my on my old website Services statement
It says
Tear gas
Colleagues and Friends
After holding myself back for three decades it's time for me to depart from my wrong body
I'm not changing who I am
I am becoming who I am
It is he back in Venice now yeah
Any sense of what that's going to mean for his job or
Life
But I have no idea
I have no clue
I don't know how my voice is going to be in a month
I have no idea how
My face is going to look
And my body is going to look in the three years three years from now we all leave it as a surprise
Toyota
Elmo
Why do you
That's scary
Next report is Kristen Clark and David Conrad also thanks to Alexis under and summer
And of course a huge thanks
To Alex
Preparing very difficult sore with us
Are you worried about what
The responses might be to it oh my God David I'm a warrior
You think this is boring me worse I guess
Corner sitting out on the balcony you it said something like I don't want to do another battle
But if I have to I will because I I hope that I can
Can at least help one personality
The story was produced by Annie McEwen and Molly Webster with help Kristen Clark and we got reporting train
Translation help from Valentina Powers Florence orsino and Anne-Marie Soma
Lucky
Eagle Eye
Show music from Jeremy Bloom and Alex overington
Anatolian Shepherd
Yo Cayenne on a very different note very belated note we would like to take this moment to say
Goodbye to her our longtime reporter producer Brenna Farrell Emily goodbye but like thank you time
To the 50th power has been with us for many years and I think with the station
Even wrong decade I believe it done every single job isn't that you can imagine
We're here Radiolab and the whole station are going to miss you very very much we already do
Fildo and do even more like right now
Yellow turtleneck men
Spring Shabu Sheila's ballet
Maritime Jad abumrad robert krulwich thanks for listening
This is Kathleen hearing calling from funny River Alaska
Radiolab is produced by Jad appenrod
Dylan Keith is our director of sound design Soren wheeler is senior editor Jamie York is our senior producer
Our staff includes
Simon Adler David Gable Tracy hunt
Matt kielty Robert krulwich
Annie McEwen Latif Nasser Melissa O'Donnell Arianne wack and Molly Webster
With help from Valentina bow giannini soham power Niagara finally
Phoebe Wang and Katie Ferguson
Are fact-checker is Michelle Harris