Hi I'm Robert krulwich Radiolab is supported by
Casper
As we begin this episode on reproduction in the human body
Check out
The Casper or the wave mattress
Providing supportive comfort for all kinds of body
Visit casper.com radio app use code Radiolab at checkout
To get $50 towards select match
Terms and conditions
Hi I'm Robert krulwich Radiolab is supported by Audible
As we begin this episode on reproduction and develop
Check out
How We Do It
The evolution and future of human reproduction
Go to audible.com Radiolab or text Radiolab to 500 500 for a free
30-day trial and a free audiobook
Are you awake
Northern listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
Exaggerated very proud to present you guys starting today here in Radiolab
A miniseries from producer Molly Webster
NetSpend
Hertz Venice
Hardwood curio
All of you
Hi
Emily Webster's the last
I take three years
I've been
Tomorrow
A lot of reporting about
How humans
Make more of themselves
Spritelike science stories ethical stories
End
We came up with this idea that beat
Play me reporting only on reproduction for the next 10 years of Radiolab that what if we just put them all together in a series
And so
We're about to do that for the next month we're going to do the series
And the name of the series is
Gonads
I know you're thinking why I would ask you a question you can say now what do you think about the work going
Donuts
It's almost like that word moist
Like a little
Yes that word does have certain connotations what do you think of
It's a slang term for balls Falls festival
Dumawall
You just think like sweaty balls in mail jokes like kick you in the nap great
Would you think it has anything to do with ladies
No no
No no no
Did you know that ladies actually have gonads also
The gonads are both testes and ovaries
It is actually for men and women
Really I did not know that did not know that
90% of the people I talk to
Didn't know that
They didn't know it both have gonads
Culture they stolen the word
And I think it's time we reclaim this word like
As a citizen
As a human
As a lady
As a science lover
I'm taking the word back
Go home
Okay so this is episode 1
And this whole series like
Kind of came into being
With a single phrase
All right the duck is in the house
From this guy
Can you
Stay for me your name and
How you identify your
Good luck. I I am an ovarian biologist
So I have a research laboratory at Yale University School of Medicine
So
Taipei
He is the one who said they going to Hazard a magical Oregon
They are
So aktay is Turkish
You know I was a curious kid he grew up in Istanbul I was a tricky as a child
And I and I was 10 years old I would dinner
Do you know looking to University
Sky Zone
And trying to understand.
Make make sense out of this whole thing
What was it about the
The sky that attracted you was the concept of infinity
You know
We're just
Living a mundane life on this
Planet without thinking of
Anything but
Routine that concerns but at the same time
America
This vast
Space around us and most of you have no clue
We live
Oblivious to that fact
And I would lose
Sleepover that when I was
Really
Fast forward activate goes to medical school in Turkey he becomes a doctor specifically an OBGYN
Silver a lot of babies
Probably 20000 or so
That's like birthing a small town after having read 20000 delivery I said
Yeah perhaps
Stop
This is not my calling to be a little bit more
More towards the beginning of the process
You know when you are an obstetrician you're dealing with the finished product right
Why is think that's a crazy statement because most people think babies are the very beginning of the process
I'm not sure what gets more beginning then like a small baby
Hypnotic
A lady that feels like the starting line started something
Scents that
Most of the decisions most of something had already been decided by the time the baby gets out and that hole for
Processes
Fascinating
To drag him into the studio to talk about
Magical gonads basically just figure out why are they met
I'm interested how you settled on that word
Yeah what did I say
Did I think Madrigal
For many reasons one is
Their original aliens told me
What he learned when he started studying this stuff
We set the origin of the gonad like it's
Creation
Restorative the beginning
Because it starts with this whole Saga that is so involved and so extreme
Did the baby itself does kind of feel like an afterthought
He calls it the Great Migration The Great Migration
Oxy got me into the story and so answer calling a bunch of people about it
In my lab we have a slogan that says gonads or go home
We have T-shirts
You don't you do ever t-shirt
That is Blanche Capel professor in cell biology at Duke University Medical Center
She eventually
Studies
All the parts of the story we're about to tell you
Okay so
Place this story in time that begins at about
Oh
Two or three weeks in humans I bet that's a day 24 just to be safe which basically means a sperm fertilized in
An egg
23 days ago could be petri dish
It could be sax
Who knows
But inside this woman's uterus
His little organism that has been growing for 24 days
What does embryo look like
If I comrade-in-arms Pat Walters who's the editor of the series
I don't know how to describe this
Very well to you I could send you a picture because it kind of look like a tadpole
Exactly that's not
So wrong looks like a tadpole ever look at very early embryos like curled up
There's a tail there's like the the
Sort of ball of the embryo that's like
Forming
The developing body and then it has this like sweep
Of a tail that's coming off
If you zoom into the tail you'll see a little region it's called the Allen towis
Call the Allentown
Which is the trash bag of the Umbria
Before the embryo has an X
Excretory system
It dumps
Things that it doesn't want in the Allen Towing
Urine flows in and out there
So have a terrible place
It's like a foreign Planet this isn't actually part of the embryo itself now it's sort of in the hinterland
Valentine was I always imagined was is
Is
Where Harrison Ford was camped out in Blade Runner 2049 which is like that fast
Dust desert super orange dust yeah there's like
Storms in end like winds blowing over the desert
And it's here
Where you find some cells
These very specialized cells germ cells a germ cell primordial
These are the sounds that are going to go on that Great Migration
And put the magic
In the gonads
They are very interesting cell type there
They're set aside
Very early in embryogenesis and how many are there like
It's not that I think you're
Something like 40 week that's it
Yes
40 biblical number and the irony here is is
Besells sort of like huddled at the edges of this Wasteland
Might actually be the most important cells in the body
Because after the embryo grows
After the baby gets born
After that baby goes through puberty
And one day maybe decides to have a kid these cells are present at the very beginning
Vcel
Iron charge
I'm making a next generation of you that's the meaning of life right that's the origin of life these cells
Everything else
Are we think it's brain heart Etc but
I think everything else
Is there
The supports
The survival of the germs
They're the stem-cell of the species rights or stem cell means
A cell that can create other cells
An originator cell we have stem cells for long stem cells farts stem cells for neurons these cells are the only
Cells that can make on their own all the other kind of cells that they can make a whole person
So it's a
They have a remarkable underlying
Pluripotency
Do you think they know that well that's
I mean that those are very difficult questions answered
No I think germ cells know they're really special cells
But I don't think they know what they're going to become
We can ask question if they're so special why do they start out in the trash
Yeah that seems like a bad place
You would think
Very curious at The Germ cells arise near that position and it's unclear why or
You hide your most precious object in the trash
Dumb as I got like the best Mission Impossible
Like murder on the Orient Express. Maybe that's the plan I don't know
In all seriousness
For some reason scientist
Don't know exactly why it seems like evolution is decided to
Giuseppe's sells a side at the beginning of development
Which means I have to make a journey
Back to the middle of the embryo where their Destinies will be revealed
And if they make it there we make it there
If they don't
We don't
Okay okay so so they hang around to Dusty Wasteland
For a few days old against the elements
Imagine if I was in that situation I would just like to be wondering how I this was my lot in life to some sort of cause
Cosmic joke
Since I have a sense I may be important but I'm just here
Don't know why is a wasteland
Don't they hang out like that for a couple of days
And then
Place a call
The hear call
Baby smell call procedure there's a signal there called into action and so-so starting my grade
They literally move wow what a wait so
How does a cell March they actually extend Philip odia which are Little Love cell like feet
Is it like it pops out to feet and then it goes walking self send out extensions
And that extension has a little adhesion molecule on it like a little sticky
Spot
So when it puts his foot out it can pull the rest of the cell up to it
So
They take a hike pike pike
Bike
And The Germ cells seem to be
Holding hands like a long string of paper dolls
And they touch each other
Though they are
The whole crowd is like going together and after a bit of a hike they get
To the wall of the embryo just like I don't know if pulsating mass and somehow
This is a very blurry. I have to say they push their way through the wall
And on the other side
It's just chaos there
It's like a foreign planets
Because what's happening is I need this the embryo is just like dividing dividing dividing dividing dividing it.
The whole embryo is developing very fast at this stage
Trying to start forming Parts like once before
Oregon's wants to form a nervous system in all kinds of signals flying around to tell the got the form and to tell the liver.
For blood cells are popping up
You know all these signals are flashing all around
And yet The Germ cells their job is to block it all out
They migrated right down the middle of the embryo
At the midline
Almost like where you could think like a spine would be
Through a forest of sickle
Going around in the embryo
And the signals are from farting
Trying to tempt them like hey
B letter sound
Believer South Combee liver B liver
Sometimes you sounds like
I want to be a liver
Am I a liver
No wait something tells me I should keep marching
It seems scary doesn't it yeah they go through a battle
Hey do you know if they ever lose one along the way like the chain is going and they're trying to like don't differentiate don't differentiate
Just like the fourth one from the end ever going to become a stomach and then like oh crap
Probably
It happens
But they try to stay focused
Together and they try to resist
All of those signals that
Could divert them from their destiny
They want to say uncommitted
These might be the last
Shells
In the developing mammalian embryo
To give up
Their world of possibilities
This is David page
He is the director of the Whitehead Institute biologist
Did a mighty if you see what I'm saying so
Basically when I want an egg
Is fertilized by a sperm
To go back to the
That beginning
The resulting cell called a zygote
The fertilized egg
Has the possibility has the
Pencil to become every type of cell in the body
And as
One cell becomes two and two become 4 and so on and so on
Eventually some cells
Give up that broad range of possibilities and become committed to narrower
Occupations and specializations
Are we have at least
200 or 300 specialized cell types that make up our body all the other cells
Make the transition from possibility to reality
And those migrating primordial germ cells are the last cells
To give up a wide range of possibility
How I like them for their like
Pugnaciousness
Yes
Okay we're getting back to the band of 40 we're back in the thick of things they're marching through the middle of the embryo
Rio being like pelted internet fighting off all these other signals
And they do this for one day
1 days
3 days
I imagine they get tired as they go
The signal that they're following is getting strong
Longer
And then pretty soon
Over the Horizon
I'm kind of either side of the
They start to see
These mountains
Urogenital Ridge is going to
Emerge as sort of a mountain off the
Back wall of the body cavity
They're still marching down this path are following the Cigna
Now the mountains are getting closer and closer
And then it's some point the path in front of them
It goes left and it goes to the right
And half the cells will go to the left and half the cells will go to the right regardless of what direction they go in they end up at
The base of a mountain
In the mountain is a mass of
Dense mass of cells
And they come right up
To the edge
Of the mountain wall
And they're able to just like
Push those sell the side and like squeeze into the entire
Carrier of the mountain
Which is an entirely new space
So
The Germ cells enter
Enter the gungeon at
Oh this is the gonna yeah this is the place that will either be
An ovary or testis
In which
Has it been figured out which it is
At this point it could go either way
I think about this place
As a cathedral
And the cathedral
Struction
And as they walk in there they probably know immediately that this is the place that's been calling that because that's
Signal that they've been following everywhere
Maybe when I get to the gonad the whole cell is surrounded by the signal
And that tells the cell to stop
But this is just a guess what do you think it's like
For that for the germ cells like sure they've been going on this walk
And then they get to a place that says
Stay here so I wonder what the stay here like
Kind of feels like I think it feels like home
You're Marching for almost two solid weeks
We finally arrived
They recognized
This is where they belong
Everyone I talked to said probably still at this point
They don't even know what lies ahead for
Or even why they're there but why not
David page again
I would suggest that the primordial germ cells
They have been instruct
Did
To migrate to the genital Ridge
But they don't know why
And they don't know what they're going to do
When they get there
They have not a clue
But the clue
Is coming
This is Jefferson
Calling from Grand Island Nebraska
Radiolab presents
Gonads
Supported in part by science
Sandbox
Simons Foundation Malaysia
Dedicated to engaging everyone with the process of science
Additional support for Radiolab
Provided by the Alfred
Sloan Foundation
Hi I'm Robert krulwich Radiolab is supported by cash
As we continue listening to this gonads episode on reproduction and human body check out
The Casper mattress with Zone support for you
Your hips and shoulders for better alignment or
The wave
Which mirrors the natural shape of your body
You can be sure of your purchase with Casper's 100 night risk-free sleep on a trial
Right now get $50 towards select mattresses by visiting casper.com Radiolab and using Code radio
At checkout
Tencent
Hi I'm Robert krulwich Radiolab is supported by Audible
As we continue this
Gonads
Episode on reproduction and development check out how we do it the evolution and future of human reproduction by robber
How we do it provides even more context
Reproductive and child-rearing practices
And what it all means for the future of our species
Go to audible.com Radiolab or
Text reader
XI you 500 500
For a free 30-day trial and a free audio
Okay to pick up on the action
The tribe of 40 they find themselves in his Cathedral like space
Technical name the medicine effort gonadal region
There in this beautiful space
But what happens is immediately when they enter they are surrounded by
Somatic cells
I imagine these cells as like friendly Monk
Gliding around in red robes
Their job is to just protect you and make sure that
Nothing bad happens to you
Tell these are the cells have been calling them
I don't know
That's kind of a hard question to answer because the general Ridge Head
Started forming when the germ cells began their migration so don't really know is like
What was sending the signal
But
After a few days some people say a few weeks
The somatic cells that are gathered around the
They reveal the destiny
They tell them either one of two things
You will become a sperm
Or
You will become
Anime
What exactly this box I was doing though
I mean
Make some changes lately
Bumping them in some special way or releasing protein
Well there are molecular
Signaling Cascades that are controlling the male or female fate of some of the germ cells
And what makes them go one way or the other
That is super complicated and we're going to get into it later in the series so for now I'll just say and mammals
Sex is genetically controlled
Bye
Whether or not you have two X chromosomes or an X and A Y chromosome
So she's basically like your fourth grade biology as if the cells in the cathedral have a y chromosome
Though though say sperm and if the cells and Cathedral have an XX
Chromosome Dulce
Acted so busy just fate and luck
Which way they go
Yes
But here's the cool part
If the monks tell the trim styles are there going to be
Sperm they basically divide a little bit and then the monks
Take the germ cells and they put them to
Sleep disorders
I don't know he's like catacombs until
Afterbirth in puberty
But
If the germ cells get told that there going to be a eggs
Something different happens inside of them and they just
Go
State divided they divide quite a lot
Rapidly for a while and suddenly the band of 40 becomes
Thousand in 2010
Amongst men take each of these new eggs and embed them in the wall of the cathedral
/ / / /
Boom
They literally shove the eggs into the wall of the House of gonna
Yes
And this goes on for months as a matter of fact
The numbers
Probably reach around 6 to 10 million
During the 5th month of pregnancy about 20 weeks
Soca station
That embryonic ovaries going to have all the eggs they will ever have when it's only 5 months along
With this is all still in uterus this is all I can uterus happen
It has 10 million eggs and it is still itself months away from being born
Yes
Theoretically at that point
That is 500 times more
Babies been acting a ever delivered in his career in this one developing embryo
Just occurred to me
If you go all the way back to the beginning of the story you told a 24 whatever
Everett was
You got this little
Organism forming Pi the mother doesn't even know it
There yet
Already
There are the cells
The in existence that will be
Of the kid she doesn't even know she has yet
So her grandkids
Are in there already is that right so when your pregnant with a person you carry inside of you
Cells
That will make the next OU right it is Grandpa. It's like your grandkids are already inside of you inside of
Your unborn child
Child yes
That's been
Yes
Do you think the great grandkids are in there too
Will it stick all that that's what she means by stem cell of the species
Because
It's the same material that makes vayven
They not only make the body they make more eggs
It's burnt they make the next generation of egg
Sperm
So they're still there
So they're both making
A generation but then making the ability for that generation to make another generation
Oh my God this is like
So it is look like you're mad at its mirrors
You're not only cradling like
Your child your
Cradling like infinite future
Homosapien
Wow
At the infinity
It's crazy that all that is there and you're not even a thing
Did the first thought
Thought
The first thing that this organism has been programmed to do is not
Hey make a make a person make a brain
Make a life
No it's make more
It's pretty gnarly
You know many many people believe that we exist just as a
Harborfreight germ cells until we can make new people like we're just their host
In some sense that's absolutely true I mean or as as was said a long time ago
A chicken
Is an egg's way of making another egg
I've never heard that before
At 2 I was in Michigan a couple of weeks in months ago
It does in Michigan and
I was
Kayaking
On this river that has super Sandy Bottom that's a
Pretty shallow, looks like 3 or 4 ft deep
And the cool thing was that it was Sam and responding
Huge
Finish they were like
324 ft
They were so stick around and and there were so many of them that they would like Russell my kayak
And I see something
Carnival is one part of the river like buy it
Self
And I look and it's
Fish it's a salmon that's lying on the bottom of the
River
I see like through the Ripley Water I'm some like pink
Turn the car around to go like look at it when I realize is the
The pink is not like flash
The pink is like
Hacked eggs
The body was sliced open so you could see into the hollow
An in Halo We're just like
What felt like millions of these like Bubblegum
Pink drops of eggs like
Higher body cavity
Wizpak
And to think that parts of our body male and female by the way because the the testes do this just
Little later
In life
Different parts of our body are like that fish
Felt like just
Pulling back the curtain and
Pink something that I I can never unsee
This episode was reported by me Molly Webster and produced by Jazz original music by Dylan Keith ballad
Are the fish and the gonads theme were written performed and produced by Majel Connery and Alex overington Radiolab
Is gonads is produced by Rachel Cusick and edited by Pat Walters one last thing
Before I go later in the series we're going to dig into sex ed and one of the things that comes up in
Every conversation you have about sex ed is a book that somebody read to learn about the birds and the bees
It might have been given to them or they found it like in their library book sale
So we want to try and create an online sex as library with as many
Any of these books if we can find for all ages to go to radiolab.org sex ed
And tell us about a book you got as a kid and the reason you loved it for didn't
And then we're going to add it to the shop
Baby grind
So that's it that's her episode and see you next time bye
This is Katrina
Our staff includes
I'm a naughty word homo
That's a wrestler
David Hasselhoff
Tracy hunt
Matthew Roberts
Patrick Nassar
Melissa O'Donnell
Pat Walters and Molly Webster
Carter Hodge
Hi I'm Robert krulwich Radiolab is supported by caffe
Chicken
The Casper or the wave mattress with a support system that mirrors your body shape that $50 towards select
Mattresses by visiting casper.com Radiolab I'm using
Code Radiolab at checkout
Terms and conditions
Hi I'm Robert krulwich Radiolab is supported by Audible
Check out how we do it the evolution and future of human reproduction
Go to audible.com Radiolab or text Radiolab to 500 500
For a free 30-day trial
Andy free audio