Is Jad bar before we start case kids are listening just know that this episode contains what Molly curse is a little
And this one
I do too
Are you awake
Northern listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
I Molly Webster this is gonads episode 4
This week or releasing 2 episodes
That are related
Starting with Duty
Hello
Angie Woodley
I figured
Minnesota building radio access dutee Chand is a world-class runner from India
Immiticide Molly B bacteria
Hi
How are you
Taking me
Have you had that I called her with more perfect producers sarakari I was having Sarah Translate
Duty speak Hindi
We caught up with her and Hyderabad where she's currently training
And
I called her because a few years ago
Right as her career was taking off
She got caught up in this
Maelstrom
That almost ended it
And throughout the series we've been asking all these questions about biological sex inside the body
And this moment in her life takes all of the questions and thrust
Sim out into the world
It is very public
Way
Just a start
At the beginning
Optima battery
Miss Colima
I'm from the village in Orissa called check agaval blur
There 9 people in my family
6 sisters 1 brother and my parents
Is the one who got me into running when I was 5 years old
Duty sister was a track star in school
How older she started training me
There was no track to run on so I would run along the edge of the river or
On the road
Or in the village
What time is it
Our family was poor and we couldn't afford shoes
So I would run barefoot
And the tiny pebbles in the road would get stuck in my feet
My sister pushed me
She didn't let me slack off when I would complain or not want to train
Years Minaj kept training with her
Sister and she just got faster and faster and faster until 2012 she had his big break
I'm trying to think of how old she was then I think she was 16 this is a journalist who has spoken
2 in written about Duty Ruth paddler contributing writer at the New York Times magazine and Ruth says what happened
12 is Duty qualifies for the National Youth championships in Bangalore and she wins.
100 m in 11.8 seconds
Indian female Runners are running that same race in 12.2 or 12
Grown-up professional runners while she's still a teenager and then the next year
She goes back to the youth National Championship with gold
Can a hundred meters and the 200m that same here still 2013 Bailey
Beauty starts racing internationally
The world youth championship
She ran her best hundred time yet
11.62 only about a second slower than the world record
Any June 2014
She wins gold again at the Asian championship in Taipei
My coach and my family started saying to me
Do the you're going to go to the Olympics
So duty is
Basically the hottest young female runner in India
And then
Was preparing for the Commonwealth Games
Which are sort of like a warm-up to the Olympics
It's for certain countries and as she's
Preparing for the games
She gets sent to the team doctors for doping test
And she said like this was kind of a normal part of her life
Blood test
I had blood test done ever since I was little
We did take a dope test
A month before every tournament
Also after the race
So she goes to see the team doctor
And he's like
No blood we're going to do an ultrasound
Which is not normal
And so she asked them
Why
And they just said oh we're like looking at your bone density and so she's like okay whatever
Eventually she does do a normal blood test
Goes back
Keep straining to the games
Couple of weeks later picks up the newspaper and sees her picture on the front page of the newspaper
There's a picture of me with a huge headline screaming
DT disqualified from the team
It said that
I was a male not a female
She has no idea what's going on but you said at that point her phone starts
Blowing up
The media called me and told me all the details like there was this gender test that have
Saying is it true is it true you failed a gender test
No I burned them just yet. There was this hyperandrogenism test
Is gender test and the results said that I wasn't a woman that I was a man
Compete with the women
Didn't understand how this could happen
And the media kept asking me what are you actually
And I said
I don't know my parents gave birth to me and I grew up the way that they raced me the Mello Kings I'm a girl
Woman and I didn't know about anything that was being reported about me
You feel the gender test
Yeah what was happening the MRIs in this ultrasounds
What exactly is a gender test
Like what is that
Exactly
I I didn't add that.
Duty thing it was the first time I'd ever heard that phrase but it's
Actually the thing that's been happening in sports for a long time
And I'm going to take you on a journey back to the beginning of it
So I didn't know this but the but the sort of first modern
Olympics of 1896
Simsbury Center
There are no female ass
And apparently like the one of the people who is
Charger assertive like restarting the Olympic set something like this
Like no place for women
But
Sure nuff by 1900 decided to allow women
Meet the Press time
You had
22 female athletes
Which pills works best for athletic competition could physically damage the week of
Was not uncontroversial
But
By the 19 by 1960 summer games of the 17th Olympia
Which were the Olympics in Rome there are 600 female athlete
And so two things complete at the same time which is a lot of women now participating in the Olympics
And the Cold War
You know the Soviet Union and the US
A lot of posturing there and there was this Psych
Fear
Not very merited it
It turns out that
Maybe the Soviets were
Taking men
And putting them into
Female athletic
To win more medals
Or that the US was doing that also
And so what started
Were these things that everyone calls
The nude parade
What is that
So women
Would line up wearing bras and panties
And they would go in front of
Three doctors
Cement
And I had to lower their underpants
And are you serious
Yes and they were examined palpated and measured
And
This makes me very uncomfortable
Yeah
Sewing base so invasive invasive is the first word that comes to mind
So this is happening all throughout the 60
People start to complain
Brightly and the
Iaaf
Which is the International Association of Athletics
Confederations and the international Olympic Committee
Both come under criticism
Anto
In the late 19th
They come up with another approach
Another
Okay and that's a chromosome
Body test
Spell scrape from the inside of the cheek
A place under microscope
And then tested for x's and y's
Dog spot showed up only on female test anybody who has
XX
Is okay cuz that supposedly goes female and anybody with something other than XX
Is
If they find a y chromosome in there that means you your mail theoretically less invasive
I have to pull down their underwear
And way more precise the idea
At that point was
Will Ohio see a 1968 said that the chromosome test
Quote indicates quite definitively the sex of a person
Except
When it does
Like we talked about in our last episode there is a gene on the Y chromosome that if you have it and if it turns on you will
Likely become a male
But
There are a lot of XY women
In the world
These are women who had a y chromosome which is associated with male but that little Jean it didn't turn on
Converse so you can have XX males meaning that little piece of a y chromosome got onto an ex
There are all of these different chromosomal like aberrations youku
Xxxx
You have two extra access when you can have three extra taxes
As a woman
As a female yeah
You could be xxy xyy Easter perfectly healthy people
It runs the gamut you could have
Are fertility issues or developmental issues or were or no issues at all and tow the debate was
You know there are a lot of
Geneticist
An endocrinologist who are saying
Sex
Isn't determined just
Buy chromosomes
Determined by hormones and by physiology and
You know
Totally getting away from gender which is even more complicated but
Just because you
Don't have access
Doesn't mean that you are
A woman
And eventually all of the Sport's governing bodies
Came around to that conclusion and by 2000 everybody was like no more chromosome testing
In fact the World Federation that governs track and field has voted to scrap all testing for gender
This moment where
It looks like gender testing is going to go away
Cold War is Over those fears
Zircon
Maybe we didn't need it anymore
But then this
Other idea walked into the room that
Actually been there all along
This idea of
Fairness
Because the fact of the matter is
If you compare male athletes to female athletes
Pretty much every track and field event except for a few
Is a big difference in performance
Like take the 800m
Soccer World Record women's record is 1 minute 53-28
Where is the men's World Record
Alarm 1:00
Almost 13 seconds fast
In fact I talk to HR some background to one female athletes
World champion one of us women in the world and she said
Her fastest mile is regularly beaten by like a good high school boy
I'm so if you're a female athlete
Or even like a spectator who's watching the sport you want to make sure that females and males aren't race
Other
And so what you saw
When this sort of like organized gender testing went away
Is that whenever someone that runs really fast
There's finger-pointing
And it's all came to a head in 2009
So that we go down to Trackside off all that excitement as the women try and gather themselves called the 808 is fine
On August 19th of that year a South African runner just 18 caster semenya
Virginia weather
Just crushes
Chesterfield
On the final lap she wins by
Is soma
What is the wealthiest
What am I to seconds
And almost immediately after the race
My conclusion was
Something
Something's going on here there's something not right
There was just a thought that there was a problem oh yeah yeah
This is Madeline Payton the PHD candidate in sociology and an Olympian for Australia she ran against
Semenya in that heat
Is she since become a big defender of Pastor but she says that the time
Because the menus times recruiting
So quickly because she was kicking the field ass like so totally
People around me with talking about heaven
Spinning room is it spreading what were the people around you saying is she a man
She just looks like a man
Cuz she's a tomboy
It wasn't that I was like
I didn't hold a strong opinion about it I just
Like I just want the audible I have to
To do with it and make it go away
And so you had gotten to the point where you were opposed to Castor compito I was opposed to cast a competing
Almost immediately
In Berlin
Over the next 24 hours she says the rumors got louder and louder basically like a
Cacophonous
Level in Berlin last night but the drama had to do less with who won the race then who was
And whether they should have been happening in the media is whether one of the runners should be
In the men's or women's race
Is she in the new world champion of the women's 800-meter race
That's when
The iwf
Passports
Governing body
The autoclave claimed that they had no
Choice but to announce something at that point
But yes
They were going to investigate caster semenya
Because they had concerns about her sexual development
Effigy
Investigation
Proven
Physically
He's not a female
Daily Beast
He'll name
4D result
Beijing today
It was one of those things I think with us
Looking back I feel like
It makes me sad
Yeah it really makes me sad
What ended up happening to caster semenya
Wells ijas banter there all these closed-door meetings in Xi'an Tracy like a year
What the audible app
Testing
Reveals about semenya is physiological makeup never has been confirmed actually
Emerge from all the mishegoss is that
In the end iaaf
Recommitted to gender
Trying to figure out some
Clearbright measurable
Way
To draw a line
Between
Male and female choose. Two classifications for a competition
Men's events in women's
This means we need to be clear about the company
Syria
But those two cats
And the way they decided now to
Clear was no longer about chromosomes
No more medieval nude parade in
Stead
They were going to look at hormone
Specifically
Testosterone
Either naturally occurring
Or artificially inserted into the body
Provides
Significant
Performance
Advantage
I think there is little
The idea was
We know that testosterone causes muscles that are like faster stronger leaner
And that men have 10 to 30 times more testosterone in women
Which is a byproduct of having testes
Enter the concern was in these women the
Have that
Why Jean
Either that they might have
The internal testes that having descended or like a ganado streak like some reproductive tissue that would be
Emitting testosterone giving them some sort of mail like advantage
Antonio in 2011 the
The iaaf
Besides that
They will institute a test for eye test
Gastrin levels
And so if the testosterone levels Falls
With within quote the mail range
Then there to be barred
And this is the first time I try and put a number on it they say that you're
Testosterone levels if they're greater than 10 animals
Our leader
You cannot run animals
I know what does that even mean
Put into place
And this is the rule that Duty bumps into
And
Ultimately
Pushes back against
That part of the story
After the break
I'm kelley-ross calling from King George V
Radiolab presents gonads
Is supported in part by science
Sandbox
Simons Foundation initial
Dedicated to engaged
Everyone
Process
Additional support for Radiolab
Is provided by the outfit
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
And I request
For those of you who
We spend a lot of time with kids parents
Aunts and uncles teachers about what we're calling
Tiny moments
Brilliant
Basically I want to hear about those times when I did something
It just means you read back and say
Wow
Maybe it was the moment that I
I kid you been reading to 4 month started reading back
Do you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lesson
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of their musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed are ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the
Epic moments where
Kid does something super smart
It doesn't have anything to do with the test
If you have a story
T-shirt with us
Go to radiolab.org
Flash brilliance
Record short audio message
And that's radiolab.org / brilliant
Thank you so much
We're back I Molly Webster this is gonads episode 4
With Indian Runner dutee Chand
So when Duty shows up in 2014
When they
Take her in for a secret gender test
Because she's doing so well
It is to test
4 height
The Athletics Federation of India
Decided she did not
Count as a woman
Are natural testosterone levels were too high and so
We did wait what you need
Who gets banned
Indian Seneca
I was just called five three days before the commonwealth games begin
And I was told that I couldn't participate because of hyperandrogenism
Had you ever even heard about like the idea that women could have high testosterone or something called
Yes I want to see Bella I've never hyperandrogenism
Give out admit so not talk about it
Mishka
No I didn't know anything about it will be duties first thought was
Images
Basically this is b*******
My family and my friends and my fans kept saying to me
You must be the victim of some kind of politics
You were running so well and that's why someone's trying to stop you
So
She gets her own doctor and she does the test again
OSHA test results in this test we're the same
And I
Started to believe that there was something wrong with my body
She told me that
She
Tried
4 days
Scared cuz I didn't know anything about it
She said I felt naked
I'm a human being but I felt like I was an animal
I wondered how I would live with so much humiliation
In our village
Children are born at home and no one goes to the hospital to deliver baby
Had I been born at the hospital maybe the doctor would have said what was going on inside my body and I would have probably understood
Did this better as a child
Animatic
Cuz I wasn't the case I was born at home and raised like a girl and there were no issues surrounding the
When suddenly the question was raised about my gender calling me a male
Is very confusing
How could I have just become a man one day
Ultimately
Duty decides I'm going to fight
Andrew says she sends a letter appealing herb and the Athletics
Federation of India
She writes
I was born a woman
Reared up as a woman
I identify as a woman
And I believe I should be allowed to compete with other women
Many of whom are either taller than me
Or come from more privileged background
Things that most certainly give them an edge over me
And eventually Duty ends up at the court of arbitration for sport
Is that a
Higher body than the IA
AF it's like the it's like the Supreme Court
Sport
Aaron golden calf
So on the one side you have duty and on the other side you have the iaaf iwi ask governs trackinfo
Around
The world are the weight breaks down is
Duties essentially making two main arguments
The first is that the hyperandrogenism rule is
Discriminatory
Discriminatory towards women
Twitch the iaaf essentially says
Yeah kind of is
But
We're doing it for a reason
And that reason outweighs
The risk
Definitely there's definitely an argument that if you eradicated gender
You would be screwing over hundreds of thousands of women
They're sort of
Their big thing is like listen
As a society
Even in this court case we all seem to agree we want to separate men and women
We need to figure out some way to do this
Duties response to that
Her second argument is sure okay fine we need to separate the Sexes but
The way you chosen to do it is not solid you have this number 10 animals for leader which is supposedly the high
High-end of testosterone for women
But if you actually look at the data
They're crazy variability like you will see women with levels that were like
Less than one
And levels that were Bus 30
Which is typically considered 30 like considered high for men
So there was this
Dick the studies that came out where one study was like
We've we look at all these different testosterone levels and
You know there's an average for men in there's an average for women and they're on different ends of the spectrum but we saw is
There's totally overlap
It's not like one and the other at never the two shall meet that like there's
That that some women go high and some and go low
And you've got
You know men with low testosterone who are world-class Champions and you've got women with high testosterone that never win
It's just it's not always
Clear the role that testosterone has in performance
Oh really I thought it was I thought that was well-established today the testosterone will make
Faster likes and then what steroids do there is agreement that synthetic testosterone
Steroids
Ramsa performance
Helping both male and female athletes jump higher
And run faster
But there's
Vehement disagreement about whether natural
Osterone one's own test
That same effect
Why why wouldn't it
Well that's a really good question
The
Idle AF Witnesses
Argue
That
Logic suggests that natural testosterone is likely to work the way since
Testosterone does
But
Some scientists argue that a sudden burst of testosterone is much different than sort
A natural level of testosterone that your body is calibrated to
The long and the short
The science is surprisingly can test
Furthermore Duty argued
If you really want to talk about fairness
You need to look Beyond sex
They're all sorts of advantages that
People have you know some people are born with
Increased aerobic capacity and others with resistance to fatigue or super long limbs or
Flexible joints
Large hands and feet
And other people have disadvantages like Duty said I came from a village and in
Southeast India
Where I raced for years with no shoes
And only had
Vegetables and rice
You know like if you want things to be fair
Then like we should all have the exact same
The exact same coaching sis
The exact same shoes
But the idle AF say well that sound about
The division between men and women If Sports is / men and women we need to find out what the thing is
Divide 9 Lima
July
Two thousand
The court of arbitration for sport rule today
That dutee Chand
Could continue to race the spider higher-than-normal levels of testosterone
Court rules that Duty can continue to race
And they say to the I was like you don't have enough scientific evidence
To have is hyperandrogenism
Go where found that
Let us know what you find
And
Descent through this whole controversy at least a year goes by Duty never stops running
If my Coach told me no matter what just keep training
Define puzzled I wake up at 5 a.m. train from 6 to 10
Hit the ground again from 4 to 6
Picks for the 3rd round
Training with the coach
And the summer after the ruling at a big International meet in Kazakhstan
Duty ran 11.3 in the hundred
Setting an Indian National Record
And
She makes the Olympics
Becoming the first-ever Indian woman to qualify for the Rio Olympics in the hundred
Since 1980
Meanwhile the iaaf
I just like the court asked
Go back to the drawing board
And they commissioned their own study
And last summer it was published
What they did was analyzed blood samples from a couple thousand
Athletes at the 2011 and 2013 World Championships and what they were looking for was to see if the women
With high testosterone outperforms the women with low testosterone
And what they found is that if you are a female Runner
Who runs the 400m and 800m the 400 hurdles
By the mile
You
Are conferred an advantage with high testosterone levels
In only those events and only those event
There's also a throwing event
And one other
Having high testosterone levels
Conferred an advantage of like 1.8
Percent and a half percent
Faster
Or like 2% to 4% rough
And just to say like if you're a runner
1%
Could be like two tenths of a second
Which is which is off and how races are decided
And these studies these distances are the higher distances these distances the middle.
Middle-distance
Yeah
Sprint not not the Sprints and not the long with their study finds is that the Sprints
Do not you do not get an advantage from testosterone the long-distance
No Advantage from testosterone
Deez middle distant races
Seemingly an advantage from testosterone and
A throwing event
Would a hammer throw
What a f****** mess
We started with like the nude parade and now where we end up with at the line that we've chosen to draw is
Hinze's
Middle distance races
That's where we're going to like make a big deal about
Trying to separate out the sex
It feels like yes it feels like everyone's just arguing over change at this point
Even since that study was published
The data has been called into question and there's a call for retraction and they published there's a bunch of
Data errors
The author still stand behind the study and in fact I double AF is now using it as the basis for a new test
Classroom rules
They introduced
This past April
We reach out to the I was a few times and didn't hear back
But
I mean right now we're arguing about test
Testosterone but I think it's a bigger issue here is that
We're like
Coming into a moment as Society
Where were more and more open to gender fluidity
But if we all agreed on a whole
That that
It's that it's unfair to group
Women with men in
Sports
Then we do have to answer a real question
Which is how do I keep
The dichotomy the binary and Athletics
All the rest of the world is changing
And what you see with Duty or any of these female athletes is there sort of caught
At the place where these two worlds meet
Hard place to find yourself
Lamborghini
What's the name of Adam when he died
Duty told me when this whole thing blew up
She was only 18 years old
Is boys and girls are falling for each other and there was a
The guy who fell hard for me and
I fell for him too
We used to talk a lot on the phone and
Thought that one day when we got older we get married
Peking duck
1114 Mason
But when the news in 2014 started appearing everywhere
He started asking me who I was for real
But I do like that
He said if you're a boy then how can the two of us
Both boys
Stay together in the future how will our dreams of having children or creating a family ever come true
Eventually I did tell him that
The results confirmed that I had hyperandrogenism
And I asked him
Are you going to love me and marry me
Or not
He said
Name app
I don't love you anymore and I can't marry you because my family doesn't approve of our relationship
So I said fine
So he forgot me and I forgot him too
After that guy left me there haven't been any other guys that like me anymore
A lot of girls have started like
Liking me
And a lot of them say that they want to settle down with me
How do you feel about that
Guess the logo
I guess I feel happy and sad
Images of my childhood dreams of having a husband creating a family with him might not come true
I want to see all these girls still attracted to me
I often wonder
If I could make a home with a girl
In India only boys and girls get married girls don't marry girls
It was more acceptable to marry girl in India do you think you'd want to do that
Happy Thanksgiving
Right now I haven't thought about it and I'm focusing on my sports career
But
After I'm done with my career I am going to need someone to spend my life with
Birthright
There is any guy that likes me I would marry him and settle down
But if there are any guys interested in me and girls still like me then I would settle down with a girl
Mallorca
Whoever likes me
I would spend my life with them
3 weeks ago Duty Chan made
Headlines by breaking her own National record in the 100m
To Beat It by 100
August 2nd
This episode was reported by me Molly Webster with KO reporting in Translation by sarkar
Is produced by Pat Walters with production help from jet up and Ron and Rachel Cusick
The gonads theme was written performed and produced by Majel Connery and Alex overington
Special thanks to futuremark
Mayans today
Andrea Denise Burke you try and pay Ashley Mitra
Plus things to Jill osmundson and madelaine petsch
Who's currently working on research about the regulation of female transgender and intersex athletes in sports
Emily Webster
See you next week
Hello my name is Amy Boyd and I'm calling from Abuja Nigeria
Radiolab was created by Jad appenrod and is produced by Soren wheeler
Do you think Keith is our director of sound design
Maria matasar Padilla is our managing director
Our staff includes
Simon Adler
Maggie bartolomeo Becca Bressler
Rachel Cusick
David devil
Bethel hat
Kasie hunt Matt kielty Robert krulwich
Annie McEwen lost his Nasser
Melissa O'Donnell
Aryan whack
Pat Walters and Molly webs
With help from FEMA
Aaliyah
Carter Hodge and Lisa Yeager
Are fact Checker is Michelle Harris