Are you awake
Northern listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
Jtime Jedi run I'm Robert krulwich Radiolab and today well today
The story of an axe-wielding nun
Coming through a window to smack some staphylococcus
I take you back to the future
Exactly
The Story of O
Story comes in two parts both of our producer lots of Nasser
Did he respond
So the way the story goes it starts in 1928
Alexander Fleming The Story Goes who knows if it's apocryphal or not is growing stuff staphylococcus
In his lab that's why she's a science writer
Staff is a bacterium that lives on our skin
Especially like
Parts of the body that are
Warm and damp
Up our noses or genitals there in our armpits places like that
And generally it's no big deal doesn't really do us any harm but if it gets into a
Scratcher
Hot and makes its way inside our bodies
Stop
Goes from being as benign companion to being potentially deadly
Anyway
London 1928 Fleming is growing staff
In his lap
In these little.
And
Was a slob
Basically
And
Eagles on vacation
Leaves his
Petri dish
Auburn bacteria
Around leaves his window open
End
Something blows across his lap type
Tiny little speck of a thing just
Floating through the window and comes to rest
On one
Until a few weeks later Plumbing finally
Back from vacation
He needs to use those lab place again and he and his assistant go to clean them off
Diamond you'd imagine that she would see some
Real
Nice furry
Lawn of
Staff just overflowing right out of the
Play because it's been sitting there
But on one of the places they pick up they realize that
It's almost polka dot it's got a little dead zone
All over it little patches where the staff is
Dead
Dead patches in the something blew through the window landed in the dish and starts
Killing the bacteria in Fleming looks down at his
Is play
He sees that at the center of these
You know
Staff dead zone
There's a tiny Speck
Natural mold
They realize that that mold is a
Expressing a compound
Killing the staff
Around it
It's like emanating rays of death for the compound that compound is called
The first
True antibiotic infectious diseases that have been killing people for as long as we had been people
Suddenly could be stopped
It just blew in through the window that is the that is the story that's always been told
However it got there it was
It was amazing
It was a miracle it was called the miracle drug
It was just it was really was a moment when the world changed when Fleming was
Put on the cover of Time Magazine this is 1944 height of World War II
It was a picture of his face and the
Banner on the cover said
His penicillin will save
More lives
Then War can spend
And this is
I had no idea about this
Virtually at the exact same time when Fleming's face is on the cover of Time Magazine like 2 months later
Stanford researcher
Publishes that he has found
Five different
Strains of
Stop
The do not respond
2 pennies
Really
Yeah this is happening
While he's on the cover
Virtually the exact same moment and it's the first
Fine
That
Stuff
Has responded to the penicillin in the world by developing resist
Doma flag
Set producer Stone wheeler the era of penicillin was over before it began
Before it's even released to the General Public
Wow.
Penicillin
Resistant staph
Moves across the globe
End in 1957 in Cleveland some scientist gather together and they are in a panic
They have no idea why they've lost the antibiotic miracle
So quickly
The scientists across the globe for their brains together and try to come up with a new drug next amazing
Edit 1960 they get methicillin
And it works for about
11 months
11 month
And so we started this
Armstrong
There was a bug
And then there was a drunk
They took care of it and then there was a better bug
Ashley found this list
You want to hear it
Streptomycin 1943 resistance 1948 methicillin 1960
Resistance 19c
61 clindamycin 1969 resistance 1970
LeapFrog or you can think of it as a whack-a-mole Brazil in 1961 than 1973
Carbenicillin release 1964 resistance 1970s
Drug development was doing really well for a really long time for a cylinder introduced 1980
Resistance 1981
Their best interest
The end I have on this list is
When is OLED which is introduced mm resistance mm into a few more but you get the idea
Antibiotics
The entry of new drugs
Market
Fell off a cliff
Why it takes 10 years in a billion dollars to get to the point where the drug is Market
But as soon as you get the drug on the market the resistance clock
Is running
So you
Probably won't make your money back
And as you probably heard we now have these
Situations a warning from the Centers for Disease Control about the spread of a string of germs
So-called
Superbugs
Are now turning up in hospitals and the patient dies
There are now bugs that can resist all of our
I've seen
Physicians breakdown weeping over this it's not the way that medicine is supposed to fail anymore
I know that that possibly the
The origin story of penicillin
Apocryphal
It's all a little suspect but you know just to enjoy imagining
For a moment like it just seems like if that happened was just open up a bunch more windows
Something out of blow in
So we could wait a long time
Right I mean we had staff had been around
For millennia
Before 1928
But you know the whole reason
I wanted to do the story is because
There is a
New window it's a different kind of window window next
Window Nexus in Petri dishes
Kind of a window next
But it's totally different kind of window
What kind of window is it
What is something blow into the window
Yeah but it's not mold
It's way more fun than
It it it it it
There is an axe
How about that it's a person
Baby
Hello
This is Isabel and the birds
Calling all the way from Montevideo Uruguay
Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing
Public understanding of science
And technology in the modern world
More information about Sloan
At www.slha.org
All right guys out
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
And I request
For those of you who
Who spend a lot of time with kids parents
Aunts and uncles teachers we're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments child brilliant
Basically I want to hear about this
When a kid you know did something
It just means you lean back and say
How do they do that
Maybe it was the moment that I
A kid you've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of their musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class
Are ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the
Epic moments where
A kid does something super smart
It doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story
Go to radiolab.org
Flash brilliance
Mrecorder short
Audio message
And that's radiolab.org
Flash Brewing
Thank you so much
Part 2
Yep okay hey I'm Jedi boom runheim Robert krulwich this is Radiolab but ready now for part to know remember when parked
One ended there was a window open and something was going to come through we don't know what
Do you know it's not my fault so whatever it is whatever it was whatever it will be
We will hear about it now for my report
Actually there is this
Story about these two women
Who did open a window
Alien and distant land
The story about reimagining the past but
To me it's it it's a
It's a it's a story about a friendship
Hey everybody
The story about a nun like
It's
It's a buddy yeah somebody movie
Okay baby just walkers
Through its I told you so you have hello I'm dr. Christina Lee Christina and Associates
Professor in Viking studies at the school of English at the University of Nottingham
She's a story
And then you also have
Hi I'm Fred Harrison Brea I'm a research fellow in the center for biomolecular Sciences at the University of
And free of Frias of microbiology
Studies bacteria
I will talk with her
Okay so most of my work is if I consider looking at how bacteria if all is going very very long lives
Infections
Coffee is is Anglo-Saxon Viking re-enactment
So I knock you into the amateur interested in the history and
Bambi in dressing up as a warrior and going to fight club every Wednesday night and learning to use the
So this is actually
Not Ray's group this is a group in New Jersey but
Basically do the same thing hundreds of people go out into it you know something filled with
Some adult weapons everything from sword Spears axes and
We give it to the roof by Tony good bashing and have a good time
I only mention this cuz it
It actually plays into the story
What was it was really nice to become incidents ready
New years after finishing her doctorate Freja goes off to work
The University of Nottingham
Who sings one of these places in the UK 95 for microbiology book
. Anglo-Saxon Viking history
To study microbes but she figures hey
Why not while I'm here brush up on my old English with her it's and with his it's him up with this.
I studied some old English to a level where I could sit
Breeden
Unspeakable
She could be better and if
She did she chewed it deeper into the hole Reno
So I rode the cheekily emailed the school of English is Old English reading group that's where she met Christina
One-point Christina Vista
What do you do
Prince head
My day job is in a microbiologist but
On evenings and weekends I'm
History nerd
And Christina said the moment she heard that I just kind of thought
I found my kindred spirit here because she was like wow I'm like your mirror image because
I'm a historian by day but by night I'm a microbiology nurse
I've been interested in infectious disease
Quite a long time which lamp
I don't I don't find any kind of friends in my department she told me she's the kind of person who would
You know watch Ebola coverage on the news and not be able to stop watching
So
Eventually they start talking about historical diseases
Seoul
How would people back then have
Treated something like you know Ebola
Bria is especially in
That's because
For historical reenactment is developing this none
Character who goes off in heels
Back and forth
Define themselves both in
Particular
Book
Undisposed Beach book
1100 years old what's it called
Bold Leach book
Nothing to do with no hair
Even though it's a LD
It is indeed a leech like leech like a like a leech like a little worm that grabs onto your blood
Night comes from the old English what leche which is actually a Healer or a doctor
So that took the little squeaky animals the code leech is because they're medicinal
Not the other way around
The doctor wasn't named for the leads the leeches name for the doctor and bald is
Is a man the guy wrote his name and what is this book
So it's kind of like his old healer's hand but it's filled with
These potions
Cures the original manuscripts in the British Library locked away 21st century
Very kind people of digitalis the original Old English text and and put it online
And they start going through all the remedy
United it describes to you remedies for. Status
Light phone
Bonamana by the devil which according to sleep book the remedy for someone who is possessed by the devil
If you view A Drank
Lutheran
A little makeup
Vomit out
The devil
Nnnn there's another remedy
Ready for War
Michelle Wie
Ignore us all involved
Helms urine
In mouth
Anthony things like how should we say make your husband more
Physically attentive
That's physically time to wish I was actually need to moisturize it
Orto do I drink on it
Nestia actually it's just you boil up
Planting some water and give it to the guy
Yeah
Supreme Christina are going through this
Which book
Looking for some kind of
Wound healing infection
Something that starts by serial
The end of the road
Recipe it says an Old English
Say bats
Stop
Sebastian.
Custom
The best medicine the best medicine
Did I move over laughter
Yeah and we
How can we not tried
What was the best medicine for
So
Said it was for a lump in the eye that occur when
Play Mike a Triton but there is a suggestion by archaeologist
Infection was
Rice
Monks Anglo Saxon speakers
You lived in buildings where you you have smoked going on
Scrum together
So that could also be a stye
What is a stye an infection of an eyelash follicle
Who is Clinton St Redlands Spa in your eyes
Stye in your eye
No just so happens that the bacteria that causes
The song your eyes
Is staphylococcus aureus.
The same stuff is the mr. Window Man penicillin man exact
Wouldn't it be nice to have a basis first time another couple hundred quid to buy the ingredients and just
Skip this guy
Let's give it a try and I white why the hell not
And matter fact
Look at this place
We thought that too
Studio
Recently produced and I went to
To my tiny apartment
In the city and all right
We try to hook it up to
Are you ready to cook
Oh I'm ready to go
Behave
Okay it goes like this
Wow that's the first line of the recipe and right off the bat
That first ingredient would strongly urge
Nobody quite knows in a water test but luckily just a couple words over
Ungodly hour
Second ingredient garlic
Which sum is an allium species
Cropley at me know this was another alley on top of the dictionary of Old English
I'm tells us that I figured probably what they were dealing with
Onion
Carly could we didn't know which one so he's okay which one that has onion and one that has a leak
But we did it anyway
Peel the onion
Chop it up
Disable a garlic recipe that doesn't tell you how much
So you take out the measuring cups do you measure at equal amount
Is a pestle
And then after that
It says
Big Canoe wild well
Pounded well together
Okay
Lots of lots of time with the Voltron Paso muscles built up from wielding a sword for pounding the ingredients
Starting me more
Third ingredient you wouldn't have nothing around your kitchen
Oak School
Skull face
What are you going to kill the cow and go Reach Out And Touch the extended ingredient in microbiology labs
Ox bile
Today in 2015 you can buy
Should not just buy them
Here we go here we go added to the onion and garlic ingredients
Red wine white wine with
Choose and we don't know who really did they have red wine that they have white wine what was the alcohol content
But I just figured out that the monastery
Wealthy
She figured out where they're Vineyard
I'm just down the road that's is more than organic formula
So they use that one
Dave Coulier
Just want to point out how different
Italian
Soolantra doll
Once you get all that stuff
Together
Yuan to the final
Specifically told that you have to mix
These ingredients together in a brass or bronze pot
I don't have one so we had to divide 2 pieces of a have a couple that would have been invited
Time do we have to do some research but they figured out that the
Hopper of today that is most like the copper of a millennium ago
Was actually cartridge brass which is what's used to stand it in plumbing fittings
A few pennies
We actually
World War
It looks and smells like quite a nice quiet a noisy Soma suit
Clearly we
Botch this whole thing
Honda mowers
And finally
Directions say we have to let the whole thing sit for a while
Has to be stored for 9 days and nights
One day goes by
My two days
Before
Six seven eight nine
Later
You ready
On the modified
Arena through class
Then you have to strain it too
The liquid that comes off you apply to the person's eye with liquid
Don't matter
Say bets the lock the door
Now clearly we didn't have any staff.
Try this out on but
Freya in her lab
Jimmy D's mock wounds
Swifty's little plugs of a collagen says it like jelly
Made to become like a flesh wound infected wounds with bacteria
Then he put his thousand-year-old recipe that has been standing there for nine days
They put it
On the back
Material that was in the fake one
We obviously where we didn't think this
This is going to work no we saw in I've given the ingredients we might see some small killing effects on the bacteria
. but it won't be anything to write home about
10% and 20% of the bacteria when they came back
Next day
That was a stuff masicka
Went on a rampage
It went on a staff
Ramp
It was killing you know 99.9999 9%
Cereal so yeah first we thought we made some sort of mistake
And this is some kind of sleep you know we accidentally mixed up our plates Obits label something so
They would run the entire experiment again
The grad ingredients Mash'Em up
Put on somebody
Serie A
She's absolutely wiped out the bacteria and have them Daddy
Any third time at 4th and 5th and it works every time
And I suspect this is just telling you you really don't
See in your trigger some hiker playlist
And eventually they escalated from just regular staff
To the mercy
Methicillin-resistant
And this is one of the bad one
A superbug
New government data estimate that about
2000 people are dying of community-based
Every year
So Christina and Freya they sent
Some of bald
Brew
To one of their collaborate
State-operated Kendra rumbling in Lubbock in Texas
Put it on some MRSA bacteria
And then a week later
Scent-free in
Christine an email
I think it was actually three would respond so I said I think she just simply said
Bald best medicine had just
Greek
Havoc on the mercy
If she stays beyond the walls
Streams
Free and Christina made very clear that this is not yet a miracle drug I mean it's not even being tested in Hume
So absolutely
Do not
Do this they don't even know
It might be that you don't do it in exactly the way we did nasty fungus could grow in it give you a question
Infection so
We should not have
American Eyewear
Domtar Ashdown
But the thing about this whole story that is
So intriguing and so cool to me
Is this
Time travel
Which is so strange like it's like
The ideas
Something
Thousand years ago
Like a bullet Forge
1000 years ago
We could
We could use it now and then it could work
That that
The time-travel dimension of that is
So weird
It kind of makes you think differently about
I don't know program
Song without you
Harrison
For example
Just a few weeks ago
Bria and Christina got off in front of
The Royal Society of
Thank you very much
Pleasure
Bahia hotel confort
Prince room hundred or so people
Apri actually got up
None
Scientist
Makeup look like
The results
Ingredients
Cooking demo and then at some point
Tina said something really interests
She was like okay sure we want to write this off
Because it has demons
Dragons
Bealls
But are we
Sure that we know what they meant
By those words
Like for example
There are remedies which ask you
Sing For Ava Maria
And we would say all that so
Distichous this is all in their heads But there again
We should also remember this is a. When people do not
Watches
You do not have your nuts you know so that's
Everybody knows
The Ava Maria
Everybody knows the length of an Ava Maria
So maybe it's
Maybe it's take this medicine and weight 20 minutes
And I know how to standardize 20 minutes which is
Full album
Appear one way and its it impact could be a totally different way
Suggest
Stat the in order to time travel
He have to some out
Got it so you don't even have to
The language people understand what they were doing
There's a phrase
That the past is a foreign country
We need to learn the language of
The doctor's office
Stop time we need to kind of
Be a little bit
Dismissive
Lindsey Morgan
From them
Island of Italy
But you were some reason why this is
Dokkan
USA map
1100 years
Sizzix
Breezy long time
Humans
And for bacteria that's like a exponentially crazy long time
That something that this man bald
Was
Doing to these back
Terrier then
Like like it's not even the same back
Yeah how could that even work
That's it that's an awesome question so you said one thing we put to think about is
But why do these medicines drop high with you
A maybe it's because when they were used
The bacteria evolve resistance
But no
1000 years later
When these medicines is not amused you would expect that resistance
This is something that
Maryn McKenna mention disorganized
Sometimes when you take a drug out of circulation
Sometimes
Resistance will decline
That doesn't always work
But sometimes resistance does the climb
So if we have been using this compound
True the ensuing
Thousand years then maybe it wouldn't work
Steam Discovery there like
At what worked once
And then would resist
You give it a rest
I can work again
I will be resisted
Can you put it to rest
If you had enough
Different
You could go to different places
The different path
Did you go to China with a now got all these two
People studying Chinese
Cures
Yours Uke
Come up with a
With a rich
Historical cocktail
Of armamentarium that will work
If you bring them in take them out bring them in and take him out in the whole world
The whole world of the past then becomes the
Food if your future
So it's also positive like a now I have a suddenly an image
It's possible that
This is Karen wheeler by the way
In conversation with Marin
McKenna
1000 years ago these
Volkswagen
True
What we went through with Penicillin in that they
This guy wrote something in the book in the section
Play called the best
Medicine
He probably got on the cover of whatever their fur
Time was he got their Nobel Prize in Every Day celebrated and then
Years later styes were coming back in the garlic wine
Didn't work anymore and they stop using it and it
Put away and then
Here we are and we discover it and it's been put away long enough it
Like that now I'm thinking about future some future
It's civilization digs up an old medical textbook that was in some dusty whatever and discovered penicillin
And it works
Did I lose you on that mare no no I'm still with you I'm just I don't
It seems like such a great Thai pathetical construction I just didn't really know what I can
Jakarta
What is relative Nasser
With helping someone wheeler and
Produced by Matthew guilty
Special thanks to Sarah 2
Steve diggle after Alexandra Rider and just
Tupac Rakim down
Yale 2BR Old English readers to Jeanne Moreau from the Gotham early music
Adam Marshall Young on the medieval harp
Call Monroe tadcaster the rest of the Barony of iron bog
Totally sure what that is but I know they help
Yes very quickly
I'm Jedi with rubber covers
Thanks for listening
Message
Five new Erin McKenna is Justin Park to English
Apartment at
Yeah okay sonny Fox
Anna reading
The appointed
Message Radiolab
Produced by God album Rob
Includes Brenna Farrell David Gable Dylan teeth
Robert krulwich Andy Miller's Latif Nasser
Ariana
Alexandra Abigail
Finding Dash and Michelle Harris
And this message