Before we start
This podcast contains some tape that
Describe some pretty graphic violence
We
One let you know that
Before we get going
Are you weightless
Northern listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
Hey I'm Jedi Cam'ron Garden Robert krulwich Radiolab in today
Going to start
This show with it with a fellow named Ben Montgomery a reporter for the Tampa Bay times has had on the show before then say something
Hi
Okay
From you like what are you guys doing how are you doing it
What are you thinking I'll start at the beginning yesterday what you're doing
So after the Mike Brown shooting in Ferguson
American Teenager was shot and killed when that became a national story
There was a lot of bellyaching in the Press
Each year I know one keeps accurate statistics statistics on
Police shootings law enforcement officer involved shootings
And it struck me at the time that liked what we react to is all anecdotal you know once in awhile one of these things will catch fire
Fire
Sam Dubose in the story and I personally was having
Processing that like
Number one
Is there
Is it trending
One way or the other
Are police shooting more black people than white people
Just very simple
The problem is
We don't know
We have no idea because nobody traxys FBI doesn't state agency
For the most part I said that. That doesn't exist somewhere within the police find itself in the police department does
On the local level
However
It doesn't exist in any Accurate Way
I'll buy a broader agency
I can tell you how many
Purse snatchings there were in Florida 2011 using the FBI numbers or the numbers submitted for Department of Law Enforcement
I can't tell you how many times please
Shots
Now there have been a couple of organizations that have tried to keep track nationally but everything that's done so far is
Incomplete
Yeah cuz most of those
Yell at the guardian has an online database
Most of them rely on media reports they're only really keeping track of the ones that serve hit the public consciousness
That's right
So Ben and his editors
. let's do something that's more complete let's do something that's unprecedented
First study guide
Florida is the third biggest state demographics are pretty similar to the rest of the country and Florida has wonderful public record
Legally it's easier to get information Florida then and a lot of other places that sell
Events at down insert emailing every single police precinct in the entire state of Florida
88 emails
5 years
Worth of paper any paper generated when an officer fired a firearm and someone was injured
Or killed as a result of that shooting.
This involves a year of work County Police Department's getting lawyers involved this is a massive thing that evolved
Probably no less than a hundred people but
Eventually
Been put together
The most comprehensive police shooting database
That we know of
Richard Matt
Barbecue Center producer Matt kielty down to the Tampa Bay Times
I was just in right here
To check it out how many how many documents you think you have sitting on the stairs and it's probably 5,000 pages
Add a stack of paper that
About as tall as me
6 we talked we got a broken down by County but you can see
So a b Bay County
Boca Raton
Boynton Beach
Do the alphabet manila folders with tons of papers and then spread
Craftsman Tire desk
The combination of
Use-of-force reports civil court records
And media clippings the represents
Shootings
I hope every shooting in the State of Florida pain in 6 years time
2009 to 2014
Toys R Us
Go through all of this material
Scrapy each of those reports for every
Bit of information that we could
Yet that we thought was useful
Circumstantial stuff did involving SWAT team
Didn't involve an armed suspect was there Chase
All the demographic information for the firing officer or officers and the
People are hit by those bullets
Then we thought
Let's like learn from these let's see how
How we can compile the data and build a database and
Hopefully Draw Something
Conclusions lessons some
Solutions
This is all going to go into it server giant online database
Tampa Bay Times website
Hopefully other
Organizations in other states will start to do the same perhaps even one day we'll have a national agency that keeps track of the stuff
In the meantime
Do some of the things have been founded initially some of it you know country priceless
Well the biggest sword
Counterintuitive
Line in this the numbers are flat
He says if you look at the numbers what you see year after year
After year the numbers of states that a
About a hundred thirty people shot by police
Every year which seems odd cuz you know the past couple years B's videos that go viral
Makes it seem like this is a
I knew an intense
Problem
The numbers show that that doesn't seem to be the case
We also broke these down into categories
Because you know what you see like on the most basic level are there
About a third of the police shooting cases involve someone on the other side who is
Quote mentally unstable this is a case we're not taking to guess
That whether the person is mentally unstable these are cases in which
There's some evidence in the report that the person has been diagnosed mentally ill maybe off their meds time of the shooting
Allegory Ben says they found a surprising number of cases they called suicide by
Hot
Which is which somebody who's usually
Mentally ill
Apparently trying to
Get themselves shot intentionally person is in view of the police
Standing on the porch standing behind the screen door
And raises a weapon tour
It's either weapon or or what they
I want the police to
Think his weapon
So it's called I'm going to kill myself but I'm going to make you do it
To me right and that's considered a suicide attempt because they know they're going to get shot it's an attempt to incite the shooting
If you will cover police apparently know quite well you know there the news briefs
That you see
Once or twice a week
But it was
News to us
I mean clearly
Police are now like the de-facto Frontline and dealing with mental illness in this country
But when it got to bend Central Quest
What do the numbers say about race
I think I'm start with the fact
Stat
I'm not sure it was so surprising
That
40% of people shot by police
Are black
And that is that is out of whack with
The Florida
Demographic
Text me what is the percentage of African Americans in Florida it's not 40%
It's more like 17
That's right which means ultimately that if you're a black person in Florida you are four times as likely
We shot by police
Then if you're white
Sometimes much right now but the breakdown
Between fatalities
For the same demographic
They're going through this particular set of numbers
50.9% were carrying a firearm 9% had a blade 70% involved
Some form of resisting arrest numerous times over 2 years in a drilling down on those numbers and as we were doing that
50.9
You know what's weird I start to feel like you I'm really glad that we have these numbers finally that in itself is a good thing but before the down
91 + 5706
The numbers themselves don't really get you very far
60%
It's just like yeah this is
Only one
Ultimately limited way of knowing the proper
Yeah I mean
I mean what
This means like that I don't know it's
Back to where we were and why we want to start this
I'm still just moved by the single case the individual cases
And it's hard to remember that each of these is
And they're all written in this
Employment investigations revealed that a SPD officer Matthew Fowler received the colonist
Staccato
Sterile police
Speak Fowler approach Department 255 and confronted by white male later identified as Anthony Skiles
Armed with the knife apartment 255 sounds
Every one of these
Every report is at least one human life
Someone was either
You know
Martin the night Gravely injured or killed
So we have on this table.
Investigation of the deaths
Or severe injury of
People
So what we decided to do in collaboration with the Tampa Bay Times is we grabbed a couple of folders write-off been
Giant boulder stack
To follow wherever those stories might lead
Matt guilty and been traveled around Florida on a few different occasions
Talking to the people behind those statistics you heard
Over the next couple of weeks
We're going to bring you two of those stories
This podcast is the first
Maddox was turned over to you
So where was the place again DeLand
Deland Florida
Down
Hot
Hey ladies
Little town on the east coast of Florida and we were there because Ben
Is it bad you know what that thing is called
It's the third
Because celebration
The third anniversary celebration of
The police killing
Marlon Brown
And isn't that was being held at
It's the West Volusia shrine
Club Shrine Club
Shrine Club Shriners like a Shriners
Walking induce myself
So I walk in and you know it's like a small community center for fluorescent lights
And the first thing I noticed about 20 people in here mostly black we're just knowing about
Talking butt on the walls of this place the photos of all the Shriners
Run the length of his wall is just like portraits of old white men wearing fez hats who are all the former Shriner presidents
Names like George Seger Denver one way
This woman came up to me who is hosting the event her name is Crystal Brown I try to do something like this once a year
Anniversary
Call black women long dreads meet a piercing hazel eyes and a relation of Marlon ex-wife
It was a cool sweetheart since I was 15
And I don't I don't know Marlon story I don't
Marlins
Three years May 8th
He was 12:30 in the morning
And he was allegedly being stopped for not wearing a seatbelt
And so he didn't stop he got out of the car near an
I'm using to get some kind of community control where you supposed to be home by 12
He's on probation for a drug charge been caught with some painkillers so he ran in immediately the cop car follow them and
Slip
Fell the cop car hit him
I ran into him he was spending the car for about 45 hours
For 5 hours
Yep crystals neighbors got at the scene until they were able to get the car
Milam's pronounced dead
Until Christmas
Three little bit and that okay just walked around and started
I'm just messed up people are you guys from in Florida Tampa Florida from Tampa
Know what I was expecting I guess I just thought it was going to be a local event for this one person but
I just started my people I started people from all over from Tampa from Palm Beach whereabouts America are people from all of the
Country East Flatbush
Brooklyn Chicago Georgia in
I said TV people who wearing these t-shirts at pink shirt and then you have to gov
With a big picture of a young black man's face or a name
Watching over woman with
Picture of her son's 8th grade graduation photo on a shirt
In red use 14 years old when he was killed
Cap and gown
Another mother
4th year so I have maybe about
Fixer 7/22 year old son Rodney Mitchell on her shirt
Wacken
Yellow one I have this
Jamaican color when I have a black and white
I have different shirts
Oh yeah
I start seeing shirt after shirt off your shirt and I think of the time like 40 people had showed up in all these different chores I just
Oh
This is
Not just a thing for one person this is
A network
Like almost everyone there had lost
Either a cousin or a brother or husband
I even even a daughter to
Police violence
In fact when I say just go to one of those women you just heard have one with the graduation
Natasha Clements Route 23 old son Rodney Mitchell he was shot and killed by police during a traffic stop
In that story later
But she told me that about 400 other mothers
They've reached out to me and I
Oh yes yeah through like traveling around through Facebook I've met 400 other mothers who's lost
The children
Wow
Does it seem like a fraction of that at this community center
Scales
Surprising thing for me was how you see these stories pop up 37 year old Alton Sterling
At least the ones that get pulled up to I like a national level and you see the family members come out
A man with children who dependent upon their daddy on a daily basis
For like two days you see them on television
That big fat do
Was a father
Then they kind of recede
And they're gone
I guess what I thought is you know probably they have these long drawn-out legal battles and then
They go back to their lives
Whatever
Whatever that means
Oh no
What happens if you get
Like folded up into this
Network
Can we pray for those mostly
You coming to this
And so at the Q Center there was a moment of prayer where the 40 to 50 people sat down at these big round dining table
Once upon a time ago
It was no Coalition like so we have today
There was no way
Oh how to make changes
And how to protect our kids now lover
We excuse prayers and all prayers
God's name
Amen
Until after the prayer
Crystal Palace in the back of the room forever to eat so everyone stood up and in the Bible
Totally changed and somebody put on some MJ and
Black people circus crowd around these two big picnic tables you ladies mind just
Can I eat
Describe for me what we got on the table
So I think you have cheese you have sweet tea have orange juice
And then you have your condiments for that
But on The Breakfast Table
Sausage
You got everything you want to have to get nice good in full on today
Can I get your name
In case you don't remember
July 10 2015
Give me a few minutes alright
Sandra bland is pulled over in a small town in Texas the cop runs information comes back to the car
I'm in my car what I put on my ding-a-ling
Step out of the car
Or I will remove you
Or I will remove you I'm giving you a lawful order
What's so funny
Don't touch me I'm not under arrest you have the right to tell you are under arrest
For what
And then I will let you up now
Get out of the car over there
You about to break my wrist can you stop
No
Sandra was eventually taken in jail
4 days later in that jail cell she was found dead
Hang up lights
The garbage bag
The death was ruled a suicide
Instant family
Speed of that ruling
You got everything you want to have to get nice good in full on today
Geneva reed-veal Sandra Bland
Events like this before
Jobs in Missouri last week we go all around we try to support as many mothers as we can because it's
Is that exactly what it is is it really just like it's important because
Who is lost their baby
Need to be able
See somebody else who looks like them
Who's in the same situation if they are
As opposed to someone walking up to them and saying I know how you feel but you really don't
Anything but something then and I had talked about a lot which is
And getting to meet these women and talk to these women
You sensed it through their experiences is really
Unique
Sort of loss
It sucks to lose somebody to cancer
I've lost
Friendly cancer recently
Is a horrible
Every ten ten times a hundred times worse for his
Prince wife
Children
It is for me
I need the different
When
Your person is killed by another human being and that human being
Is returns
To the streets
With a gun and a badge in a you know
In a position of authority
And something you do see in bed numbers even though the numbers themselves
I can't really tell you whether or not
A shooting with
Legally just
What is queer
Is that over 800 + shootings even the shootings where the person was unarmed
Only one police officer
Has ever been charged
It is weird sort of like
Double grief
Yeah it's like past and present
Same time
Mercante
Put it away because it's everyday is another insult kind of
Right
Batman against Chris Brown somebody one of us
You know here in Florida we're going we're going to reach out to each other and then we're going to invite a man weave
The club that nobody really wants to be crazy but this is family
This is my family and I could not have made it this far. I couldn't still be
I wouldn't be doing anything if it wasn't for them
So after the event ended up Community Center Crystal took a bunch of the mom they all got their cars and drove over
Dislike little gem shop
Just like you guys do this after every every event or is this just like crystal meth just once around
And has been telling everyone about this
Is Deanna Joseph her son Andrew died in 2014
Be part of the different type of learning this is a part of just poking and dreaming we all just simply trying to fight
Find a way
If a crystal gathered like probably 15 of us into this tiny little store because you wanted to show these women like here's how I
I cope or here's how I deal with
My grief you can even get there
The largest age women in a big bundle of sage in her hand
I want to do like your house I can look like
Then I open my windows and I just be real I go through my house
Concert
And then they went from The Gem Shop
Holy Crystal
Oh no
Mid-sized one-story house into land and lot of women hung out in the living room were drinking juice talking
Band about his story
Crystal and her cousin in the kitchen cooking chicken
Me by surprise is how these women when they come together
They like they bring with them and their own stories he's stories of grief of of suffering
And yet when they're in the same room together
It's like they just they just have fun
Play the night before they all gone out dancing together
Fire
And now we're doing instead of getting motel room
Again this is Natasha Clements
Restarting to stay over it until the cows
With eating each other's dead air mattresses it becomes like a huge sleepover
Inverse of a quantity for uptalking eunos getting to know each other you know some stories about each other's children so it's like
Bike therapy for
Becky let me pass but it was this moment when I spent the day with these women.
Really
Stop at me believer ad
Guilin Brown's death
There's been Crystal let some of us over to the site
Where
At her ex-husband Marlon was hit by that squad car
At 12
People are in about eight of them were women who had lost either a husband or brother or child
Movie theaters in someone's backyard just walking through this patchy grass
Mom's house probably over like right now
And then the police car that came behind him was probably right here
And then the officer that hit that hit them
Came in
We came in he came right here
That's why we spent all day
Vegetable garden
The garden was
And vegetables
Growing and
All that lay I ain't saying
Cuz
When a 2018 Ona
Took him away and released in 2008. We came back he has all you can smell
It's not as bad now but just the association smell
Packages
You get those flat
Just brings you right back here
And it was just kind of
Stood there for a minute
Are the one that started to cry
Men
You want me to do
Text
Yeah my phone in the bed
Couple women had me their phone
Mine is broken
Probably about these eight women who
Hobbled together and they just
Stared at the camera
With this sort of straight face
All right
3 2 1
Anime
Fat
Think we got them
Emil start walking back up to the cars
Crystal I just want to thank you for
So just sharing that with us because I know
It has to be pretty hot even come back to the side
Yeah we haven't been it's been awhile
Last week
At night 3 in the morning
Remember be nice to tell you all the time how do you live so far away from him
Oh my God that was that was
Amazon's greatest about 15 minutes tops and where I live
Time for
Yeah
How could you not
Right
Anytime you want to go take a chair and sit there
And it's crazy cuz like it's up with some it's a cemetery like a little bit further out
Chinese crazy like a certain time every day and it's this little white man with his chair
Everything I setup
My dad is the beat
I don't know if it's a cemetery Popeyes and all of that
He take his chair.
Set a trip to Florida was almost about a year ago and I feel like I have to be there at this
Redeem steam moment because
Just a few months after that trip
Who is the mother of Sandra Bland by met she spoke at the Democratic National Convention
Yesterday
I need the worst
Nightmare
Anyone could imagine
She's on stage with Michael Brown's mother Eric Garner's mother
As my daughter
Was lowered into the ground
A few of these women started to call themselves
The mothers of the movement
Some of them showed up at the women's March in DC
I'm it was weird because in this short amount of time
This thing that we had stumbled into this thing that really
Felt like
At the thymus
Support group
Atomy become
A force
Coming up
Put it Down cop with a gun a man with a knife
Is Earth in life-or-death moment between them
So stay with us
This is Christopher calling from South Florida
Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloan
Www.zearn.org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents
Aunts and uncles
Teachers were looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments of childhood brilliant
Basically I want to hear about those times when I did something
That just means you lean back and say whoa
Maybe it was the moment that
A kid you've been reading to 4 months
Started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of their musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed they're writing music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the
Epic moments where
Kid does something super smart but doesn't have anything to do with the test
If you have a story please share it with us
Go to radiolab.org
Flash brilliance
And record a short audio message
And that's where you're at. Org / Brillion
Thank you so much
Hey I'm Jared I'm Ron I'm Robert krulwich and just
To pick right back up with our our story from Florida with Tampa Bay Times Reporter Ben Montgomery and our own
Activity
Alright so did you did you was Daytona
May 3rd Daytona Beach Daytona Beach about everything what happened was went to the same with these women mostly black
12 lost people too
Police violence
And I'm sitting across the table from the African American city councilman Daytona Beach and I told him what I've been working on I told him some of the numbers with
Learned and he said you really need to meet our police chief
Name is Mike Chitwood
Is chief of Daytona Beach spring break scenes
Are they have Bike Week
500000 bikers from all over the country in Daytona International Speedway
And on top of that
Department of population Arizona
C2000 people
Remember that six-year. They only had 4 police shooting
And that's low-key like that that's
Really low
Jessie
I need the breakdown for 2015
In fact while we were there by race
Tickets
Pinterest
Joanna's assistant print out these spreadsheets
Every other day
Stats
Thank you
Any kind of fascinating cuz if you look at them can go right down here and you can add them up
Things like
Aggravated aggravated assault theft
Shoplifting a speeding or arrest ratio
And our ticket ratio
Basically mirrors are City
In terms of racial Democrat
It was roughly a 60/40 shity 60%
White 40% African American
It's pretty much what you see
Tickets for speeding about
60/40 respite apus 60/40 that's the way we're supposed to
In theory
Approach the law
And so what are they doing differently
First of all when all these the incidents were occurring in
Around the country with Fergus and everything else we did it racing policing mandatory training for the entire PD and basically
What we wanted
Our officers to do with number one learn the history of the country
Good history of the country is that we are a racist Nation no matter how you look at it
Started with moving the Indians
Off of their land
For manifest destiny
When you look at Jim Crow laws when you look at the Civil War youku
Slavery when you look in the fitt bull connor for example
I'm turning the dog in fire hose is loose
On civil rights Marchers
George important for officers to understand that that you may go into an African American community
And you may think and I can't walk away where you think you're being respectful and understanding but in reality you're not
But let's not for a moment think that there isn't biased
In in policing Vice we all have bias in it
And a trick is at and I don't know what the trick I don't know of any of us know how to contain that
How do we stop at bias
I'm coming through when you make a decision
And I think a lot about him
Seems like
I feel like a Kinder way to say
Pier
Kaffir
A black person
And that fear is greater than
What you feel when you're encountering a white person when you're out on the job
What is a cop
When you look at some of the shootings record on video and I and I think of the poor
School Janitor who lost his life
In Minnesota
The Atlantic
There's a guy who
Told the officer in no uncertain terms I'm a good guy
I have a gun permit
You can't get a gun permit
If you're a convicted felon you can't get a gun permit if your drug dealer
It was a minute that young man tells that officer I have a gun permit
For some unknown reason
That officers
Threat Level with a baby in the car
And I got a guy and his kidneys girlfriend is a gun permit holder
This is Chris's Music Arts.
For some reason in an in reason is because of the color of the main skin all of those things never registered Black Irish
Pocket
And I shoot
And then I would like to tell you in all my years in policing I would like to sit here and be not even tell you
Bat
We don't shoot unarmed people
L28 year practitioner law enforcement second generation cop
I'm appalled at what I see when those videos I cannot believe
At my profession
In some cases is that out of control
Some of them I understand what's going on I mean wrestling in the ground for your life and you and you and you know they weren't there are times we have to use deadly force but the answer
South Carolina
Dancing in Minnesota I mean are you kidding me you looking or what are we doing
How do you how do you train that out of an officer
So that we make a traffic stop they're not already operating with a
This level of height
Iran
Is perceived threat in my opinion number one you have to train tactically sound
You have to train using a real life scenarios
That take that extra split-second
Before you fire your weapon
And I'll give you that it go to rubbery quickly when I first went to Philadelphia Police Department we were shooting people
Had a crazy rate
On an accidental discharge
The officer had your finger on the trigger when they would go to grab that person if that person pulled or moved you would get your back in
It was a natural reaction to squeeze the trigger
Go back up to the police academy and we all had to be retrained on how to keep your finger on the side plate of the weapon
Not on the trigger so that that happened you wouldn't accidentally tripping fire and shoot somebody
And you went to photo is Armageddon oh my God going to get us killed one reality
What it did was it slow down your field division
It's load everything on that split-second it make a difference that blink-of-an-eye didn't make a difference it made a difference in you not shooting
People that Split Second let you see what you thought may have been
Did the color of my glass coming at my cell phone was it cell phone
So you buy yourself a little bit of time and this is the thing that you would come back to again and again is this idea of time
In certain situations
Slow down
When you're dealing with a mentally ill person
Slow down cover just crates in space to buy yourself another 30 seconds that extra 30
3 seconds maybe the difference between saving your life and somebody else's life
Another interesting thing was
Ben 10 Tennyson also threw some herbs reporting with other police chief
Is the idea that somebody's cheese don't like to hire kids at a high school like 19 20 year olds
In part because this
Text a lot to communicate is like this
Anyway when they look up and go to talk to somebody I'm and I'm serious about going through the drive-through McDonald's
And I could piss off the person ordering cheeseburger
Halle how did you do it
Just her demeanor just the way they act
And back then told me that he thought it in police chief who told him the young people were coming into the
Academy
Past years
I've never been in a physical fight
The problem because when they get into a fight their heart starts to race in the muscles tense up and I don't really know what to do so they
Freak out and they're way more likely to draw weapon and use the weapons
Tutu in the confrontation
So how do you do that you can't ask her how many times have you beat somebody up or been beating up on your messenger
Says that that's why I at least you told me he looks
He said from just my little myopic world that I live in we have an awful High number
Of many women have served in the military
They are my best officers they are level-headed they're well trained to know how to follow the policy basically know how to not
Freak out
Dirty competition
And
Lasting
20 most important things to it says you have to get into the community and I'm not talkin about that the good stuff over there before Christmas gifts are they
Play cook Thanksgiving dinner I'm talkin day-to-day you have to get to know key
Yeah I mean
Until it to make this point Chitwood got up walk me down the hall to another office
Computer
Okay
Show me this video
Tobias card
In silence and its body cam video its body cam on the cop who is driving a squad car he goes body cam
Hammers Manitou was I on his glasses
Do the cameras going with his eyes go next to him is his partner both cops are white also
Night so
The call is Borg I was running around in like trying to stab people he's off his meds that he was going to
Crack cocaine binge if I remember correctly
Blue neighborhood street and you can see down the street and walk away
Shirtless black guy
That's the cop talking to him copper in the body Cam and
This black man got his arm raised walking towards the cops
But it gets closer
Closer
Closer body cam pulls out the taser
The other officer behind him with his firearm out
And the guy is approaching approaching approaching approaching
And then
The goat body cam Fires at Kaiser the guy holding the 90 Falls onto his back on a dislike cement driveway still
Play It Again
Hey girl are you going to get him again. He hustled over a kicks knife out of
Is hand grab them by the hand turns them over
And then he's a chain Central code for
Cups and it's not as it's not a smart idea to have a nice coming out the police officer
Cheryl say why didn't you listen to me and just dropped the knife and walked her me why did you keep coming at me
Moonshiner best to get shot
You want to die
You can't die he tells you overdose on Jesus Christ
And I want everybody know the police bullets can't kill me
All right there
We going to stand upright
Counseling 1 2 3
Need to come pick him up walking over to the squad car
Put them in
So this is the thing that you guys would you use this video for what exact one of
Let multitude of videos that we show officers on the correct way to do things
You know when and that's the point we get home or the officers used time and distance
To their advantage
Didn't pull right up
And right away
They use verbal command first
Warren and let him know what's going on
Trigger control with another thing
You know what that Taser Taser Taser
Heard a pop and fired his gun
So you know he's appointment Kaiser and communication is this key communication with the person you're trying to arresting communication with you
Your fellow officers
Those are the things that we drive home
And again there was no doubt in my mind
That they won officer in particular knew that individual from prior contact
Read minutes interesting to hear me say
The name Derek
Lake Derrick
Is Derek and Erika Sanchez
The black man
Shirtless with a knife in his hand
When there's no connection error
It's a lot easier to see somebody is nameless and faceless and I got scared and I shot him
But because of that knowing that officer
Because of that and establish some kind of rapport
That made the officer
Think
Lexi after we finish watching a video and I was packing up chat with told me that just a couple months after that incident
The neighborhood
Information on the front step waves
Did Derek does
You stupid sonofabitch you on how close you came to being dead
Recycling medication
Wasn't
Doing drugs
Is normals mean you are right now
Again almost kind of like
When I was with these women it felt like I was just
In Daytona at this
Specific moment because
Just a few months after I left last night
Primary election among the big Winners Daytona Beach
Police chief
He is now
Volusia County's new sheriff Mike Chitwood was elected
The sheriff of Volusia County
Which is the county that Daytona Beach belongs to
Has organization called Perth which is the Police Executive Research Forum it's as big coalition
Beasties 2016 / put out
What they called her 30 guiding principles for the use of force
And the number one principle rather than being something Law and Order Law and Order is
The sanctity of human life
I'm just a month after proof put out those principles to the biggest
Gleason organizations in the world the ICP the International Association of chiefs of police
Fraternal Order of Police
Epic leasing in both came out against
These guiding
Baby saying that being a cop is a dangerous job and some of these principles make it
More dangerous
And then just like eight months later so the ICP and the Fraternal Order of Police
Started to adopt
Some of these
Principles publicly
Despite that there still is a bit of a divide between but according to Ben for the very first time I think you're seeing these masks
Conversation
The police weren't talking about this two or three years ago
I don't know man just thinking about this like you've got these women
Cool how I become kind of a political
Force
You have also this growing movement of cops who are
Possibly changing way policing is done in America at least maybe slowly
But cumulatively does
I hesitate to use this word but it does make
Just feel like
Reason for Hope
Ray and I thought the same
Wait to bite
It wasn't anything I had registered realized
How far
Hope Has
You go we are here to see Natasha Clements
Natasha Clements the mother of Rodney
Woman who you heard earlier but I'm back at the community center
That's actually when I first met her
And have been reporting on Natasha for like a couple years by this point
Are they because Ben was going to hand a ton of documents over to Natasha on her son Ronnie's case
Have any
And I'm sad because we set up a short interview with Natasha but when we got to the door
She just started
Sobbing
And
Can I just had no
Idea what happened
Appendicitis
Tape recorder off
So what was
What was happening in that moment
The backup
So meeting somebody like
Chip wood
You know
I sort of hoping that I've believed
The thing about a Chitwood
Sheriff police chief is it
The only have
The power to fire
Police officer
And that's
Good about it after that
It goes into the court system
And so
Natasha
Her son Ronnie 23 years old unarmed was shot and killed by
Two police officers during a traffic stop
After the shooting a judge ruled that the two officers had done nothing wrong they attacked
Accordance with the law
And
It just so happened at 45 minutes before
Bentonite
Showed up at her door
She just got an email from a lawyer saying that the appeal that she
Filed
Against that decision
I had just been rejected
We sat there and Natasha's apartment for a while we actually
Even left for like an hour
Eventually came back
Kind of just hit
Reset on the whole thing
Natasha show me some pictures of Rodney long dreads
Big smile bright white smile
Let me sit down at a kitchen table
Okay so
If you can walk me back
The night that kind of everything everything
Xiaomi
11 2012
Natasha was at home 9:30 at night Rodney who is 23 years old with back from college and out driving a Tesla car
That's another phone call start happening
People calling saying something's going on with your car
I knew something was wrong so I immediately started screaming outside to see if I can get somebody to you no response
Help me so I can get a ride
Nobody Camp came out so I started running down the interstate
Barefoot
Left I'm leaving free call locking the door or anything like that
Let's see if family member actually picked her up they drive to the scene she gets there
Everywhere police
Cars
Where is Rodney I was looking for my vehicle
Smione card
He's over there
20 by 20 feet over to where the car to come to a stop it
Clyde with gas
Potatoes sheet
The back of my
Poop my pants
Xidan run over there
The whole place was surrounded by police tape and eventually Natasha says it took a couple hours but a cop pulled her off to
Genocide
And told her that her son
I've been shot and killed by police
I just got on my hands and knees and started praying
Don't make the speech Rose please lower
Basically begging you playing
I think I could.
What
What else do you do
Cry ring
Pray cry stream Praise Christian pray next thing you know I woke up I was
At the hospital
Natasha says that she apparently was so frenzied the nemt on the scene stuck with something that's on me.
So when I woke up
I see my family standing over me
Not fair
Now as to what happened to Rodney that night then his look
A testimony from the cops involved from eyewitnesses
Different court records
The piece together the events documents that night Rodney and his car
Did Saturday gas station they left the gas station and we're driving down this highway windy in his little cousin
I get pulled over by two white officers
Doctor said he saw him without a seatbelt
Turns out Rodney was wearing a seatbelt and these two officers approaches vehicle one is kind of standing in front of the car about several feet away
Towards like the driver side and also approaches his window
Corning Ronnie's cousin boy
Why didn't you pull over sooner
And and then orders Rodney to put the car in park
Ronnie's got both hands at this point on the steering wheel
And he reaches down to put the car in park
Invisible things in the story started to purge
Because the cops say the Rodney
Put the car in park but then quickly put it back into drive
Accelerated at the officer in front of the car
Annie's cousin gives two conflicting accounts as to
What happened there was apparently
My witnesses
Stream said the car had yet to move
But what is clear
Is what happened next which is Deputy
In front of gun fires Two Shots into the windshield
The deputy right by the door here's the fire
He pulls a gun in fire
One bullet went through Ronnie Platt and would you put up in self-defense another bullet entered through his left temple and
The car lurches forward and Corinne's across the street for about 300 yards until it collides with this gas station Ronnie's cousin at this point
Get out of the car
Sweetness in unharmed
Mention paramedics arrived in pronounce Ronnie debit the same
My mind is always on Rodney
Natasha says when she does think about that night
Joy comes back to this one
Question
Why were the guns.
Why
Why what
Why was it what was that all about
What do you think the answer
He black
And that's just it
Deborah moment where you try and put yourself in the mind of those two officers
Absolutely not because I would never do
Buy skate like that
But never
Cross now
I would never do that
You feel like it's like
Do you feel like the cop in that moment
Ronnie's black is what
Frightens the cop
That's why he pulls his gun out
Pizza Boli's
Hell if he if somebody gets hurt or somebody gets injured or killed
He's going to get off
He's behind the blue bad she's a bully
Is that what you think of cops like writ large
If I what is
That's exactly how it is Nokia Femmes and buts about it
Is it hard for me cuz I think like
Like it's clear that there's discrimination with that exist within the police force
And the people who they are
Sworn to protect and serve
But like at the end of the day
There's probably
Ain't like no I don't know I couldn't give you a percentage of the number of officers
Which lake
Yes they're probably
Violent individuals
Don't belong in a place for us
But I would
Assume that like a majority of the cops
Meanwell
Have probably probably have
Some sort of bias
Where
They don't think I see
A black person
And I'm going to Lake
I'm going to get that boy
But that there's like it like there's some sort of triggered response
And that the police
Are currently being put into different situations where they
I feel under threat
And concerned
And that like
It looks like a
Whole host of factors leading to this moment for somebody
Is shot and killed
It's not just that they're out here
Bullying people
You say that because you were
You're white
That's why you say that
Tell you what
I tell you what we can try this
Go to my sister will make sure you get your wig
Go to tanning salon get yourself sprayed black
My guarantee you'll get a different response
I dare you try I bet you we can make you look like a black boy
I'm telling you
You'll see a huge difference
And that's just it
Like sitting like sitting there
In that moment
I felt
I felt the Gulf
And
Wandering Lake
How long does it take to fill that golf
Like how many
Chitwood's does it take
How many conversations need to happen
In case you want to stay
Ben Stiller to give Natasha those files on Rodney
To get those documents for you
Appreciate it
Okay
NetSpend credit
Huge
Folder of paper out of the trunk of a car
Waterside
Everything
Then put the stack of Ronnie's files on this glass
Table
Like
Crime scene photos
Because I don't want to be the person
To give you the
Unless you want me to go get him right now but they're
I don't want it I won't answer it I don't want to read travel-size you
Yeah when I'm ready I'll
Something I'm going to
Eventually
3 Days Later Natasha contacted been
And said that she was
Ready to see those photos
Who sang Steuben Moe coming at the Tampa Bay Times into the staff of the paper that
Did all the hard work of gathering to tistics material in the near future they're going to be putting out Ben Storey a hole
All series of videos interactive graphic with all their final numbers
You should be amazing
Definitely check it out we will make sure that we link to it when it's live
From our website radiolab.org
And then of course to our own Matilda
Who reported and
Reduce the speed
Next week will bring you part 2 of
Matt kielty been Montgomery's reporting two very different kind of story
Checking for that
Okay
Thanks for listening
This is George Washington the third in Charlotte North Carolina
Radiolab is produced by jdevil Rod Dylan Keith is our director of sound design
Soren wheeler is senior editor Jamie York is our senior producer our staff includes Simon Adler
Brenna Farrell
David Gable Matt kielty Robert krulwich Annie McEwen Latif Nasser Melissa
Donald Arion whack and Molly Webster
With help from Tracy hunt
Valentina baldini
The Garfield Show
Phoebe Wang
And Katie Ferguson
Our fact-checker is Michelle Harris