Before we start
Quick heads up
This episode contains some graphic language and descriptions of
Very sensitive sexual
Situations
Including discussions of sex
Consent and accountability
You might be married if
Are you awake
Radio WNYC
Hey I'm Jared I'm Rod this is Radiolab today we have parked
Of a three-part series that we're calling in the know
No as in an o
We were inspired to do this
After hearing a set of stories
On the show called The Heart produced by Kaitlin Prest
Last week we played excerpts
Of that series
And if you haven't heard of last week's episode I would encourage you to go back and listen
Is the stories that Caitlin told
We got some very intense reactions
For my license online all over the map
Have you feeling those stories that you made are a very
Striking
Personal view of
Consent from the inside
Now it just so happens that Caitlin
Produce those stories
In the spring of 2017
Spring just before
All the accusations started hitting the news
First against Harvey Weinstein and then
Congressman like
Al Franken
Actors like Kevin Spacey
Medians
And then in many cases the very people very men who are reporting about those stories
And much of what made it into the news with pretty clear-cut
Criminal cases
Or accusations of
Clear breaches
Consent but then we started to hear about
The cases that were harder
Not explicitly
Criminal
More nuanced
That Gray Zone
Which Caitlin was
Exploring herpes
It occurred to us like a dick this is a conversation we're all trying to have right now
So what we started doing the wave listening to her stories was doing a series of interviews of our own with people
All over the map
Who are thinking and rethinking consent in interesting ways will play a couple of the next two weeks but we ran into one
Particular
Interview
See if it's working Kaitlyn you there yes I'm here
That we could not
Stop thinking about
Santa created a lot of really difficult conversations internally
And so we just kind of decided why don't we play this thing relatively
Raw
We don't do very often but let's just put it out
More or less how it happened in all of its flaws
Kaitlyn Kaylee can you hurry Hannah
Yes it's out it's Hannah
Hannah okay sorry Caitlin could you here hun I'm speaking can you hear me yes I can hear you
Thanks for coming in
Both of you guys
Thank you really glad to be here okay so since I'm already pronounce her name incorrectly can you tell me who you are
How to say your name what you do
Sure my name is Hannah stotland
I'm an independent consultant I work on
Sorry I'm an independent educational consultant
And I specialize in
Educational crisis management
Particular vantage point
On this whole set of questions
When I see a
Unfamiliar number from a distant area code on my phone
And if I can I pick that up
And it happens quite regularly. I pick it up and I just here sobbing
That's a mom whose kid just got expelled
So that happens
Regularly
More like
Once or twice a month
Often the calls are coming from moms whose sons have been accused of some kind of sexual misconduct
I got my first two calls on that topic
In January of 2014
And since then it's grown and grown and grown about a third of my work now
I'm is students who are involved with
Title Nine in one way or another
Title Nine is a federal law that deals with
Among other things
Sexual harassment sexual violence on college campuses
What Hannah will do when she gets these calls it she'll work with these young men
Havana Cuba
To get them back into school
By the school they were in
But more often it means transferring to a different School
So families hire me to help their
Kids get into a college or grad school usually
I think it is a good thing
When people in general
Even people who may have done something very bad
Who want education can continue to get education
As long as they're seeking it honest
What if you but what if you're then just deferring the problem is some of the campus I mean let's say there's a guy who
Victimize somebody
And then you help him get to another College where maybe they do it again
Well that they be in the community one way or another and I think this is an area where I
See a lot of problems with
Classism
And probably racism to
We're we're so concerned about that accused person being on another college campus
If he isn't on a college campus where do you think he's going to be
Cuz he's not going to jail
The student said we're talkin about typically the police don't even get called but if they do they come and see
The evidence to say this evidence is so thin
You know we're not we're not even going to impose charges
So
Saiino okay well he's not going to college anymore he's going to work at McDonald's and so if there's a risk to that fellow people at McDonald's and weed
You just don't care
Because they're not the upper middle-class white women who were actually worried about
On the college campus
And
I have misgivings about the ideas at
Did the
College students are special needs
Community needs special attention that other young adults don't need
So you're interested so that I know that I have your point of view that I understand it
Is that you don't
It's not that you
Don't sink
But some people should be
Spelled sometimes
Oh sure they sure that yeah okay
But
I feel very comfortable
With the idea that
People who want to continue their education
Audi be able to make their case
Friday
Want to continue it
What I do
Is help them talk about what happened
So if you're interested in covering it up or hiding it
There's no reason to hire me
I hope you have that hard conversation or write that difficult essay
About what went wrong
Even if
You feel you were wrongly accused
You were railroaded by the school
You better find
Unwise choices that you made
Selfish choices that you made
There are not a lot of these cases where I think well you handled everything perfectly you didn't make any
Risk preferring choices
There's nothing you could change
To keep this from happening to you in the future
You still have to tell a story
About mistakes that you made
And how you're working to fix
How does that go I mean do you find that
People will maintain that like will they sort of hold on to the idea that they did have consent even if the other person says
But they didn't
And imma try my Facebook
I'm not necessarily trying to change their mind about whether they had consent
That means they were there and I was not
At the City Museum
It in a scenario where you have both sides of the story
What's the usual difference
It depends there's a few cases where the stories just are incompatible
But there are
Most of my cases
The dispute is narrow
Everybody agrees that the encounter was
Generally consensual
But
Either the consent to all of it was withdrawn
According to the Accuser
Or there was consensus to access A and B but not C
And see just happened before they knew it and
There wasn't a conversation about it and
One party feels that c was
Arepa
Or that snow I agree I acted like I wanted this the whole time and maybe even I said yes
But in retrospect I was too drunk or high
And that. Consent was no good and nullifies Atkins
At this point in the conversation we talked a little bit about like
The different kinds of cancer
What works like affirmative consent
Marissa Bell
Clear
Permission often verbal permission that can be withdrawn at any time which Hannah says she is all 4000%
Question is if you don't do it is it rape
And
That's the dichotomy that I object to
Or I'm a skeptic about I should say I mean if if
Again if people can show me that this works and I'm interested but when you say I guess that's a thing like when you say if
People can show me if this work
Can you cut sirloin pack what you mean by that like
Let me get it seems so clear to me that it does work
Let me tell you a few stories there's a couple that I can give more identifying information about because
That this
The case is in litigation now and so that's on the public record and the fact that I'm involved in the case is on the public record so I
I can say a few more things
Facetune
He had a girl wearing his room
After party they didn't know each other well
He touched her private parts
And there was vaginal penetration
With his fingers
Both parties agree
That he asked for and got affirmative verbal consent
He said do you like this and she said yes
And she faked an orgasm
Both parties are telling the exact same story
And he was found responsible for sexual assault cuz she says I didn't mean it I said yes I was enjoying it
In order to get it over with faster
I wanted a graceful way to leave his room and I saw it
Making him think I was having an orgasm
Would would help me get out of there more gracefully without being rude
And he will have to see that Monday for two and a half years I'll let you finish I'll let you finish and then I'll say what I think
Close my my
I mean this
That's that's when singing practice
You know it's it's
Other other cases that I've seen
Is someone who basically my my student
Is big black guy
You know well over six feet tall a lot of muscles he's an athlete
And
It's Undisputed that
That
He and the accuser were in her dorm room together
To hook up
They took off all their clothes
And
Chi
Touched his genitals and
Performed oral sex on him
And
She said
That
She did that because
She was fearful once they were both naked
I'm and she felt that
The situation was so overwhelming that she had to
Reach Out And Touch him
And then reach out and use her mouth on it
And the school decided in that situation
Is that the only thing that had gone wrong
Was that there wasn't a verbal confirmation
And so
If if you go in somebody's dorm room you take and both of you take off your clothes
And she
Touches you in places your penis in her mouth when you're not speaking
She has not conveyed consent
Which I think something is yeah
Yeah I guess from my from my point of view like the rules rsr setup
Up and Away
That the kind of protect
The person who feels violated like it
Like I guess to me
There's a man who feels violated
Sorry but we're not supposed to be concerned about who feels violated we're supposed to be concerned about who was
Violated
Yeah but I mean I guess
The person who was violation
I mean if they feel violated then I would argue that they are they bad were violated
What I'm saying is that like I think that having affirmative consent be
A rule that's that's that's followed and taken seriously when it comes to like
Legal stuff it just protects that ambiguity you know it if it's favors
For not getting the verbal yes
What message about definitely complications
What I think it's complicated but I think that it it it makes it so that the person who
Was violated feels violated is the one
Who's always protected and who's the one who's always in the right and I think that that's a good thing
Yeah I don't agree with you about that I don't know they're always in the rain
I don't think they're always in the right
They're always in the right but I think that it's
Safer to assume that they're always in the right is going to be a very small margin of people who are not
But I feel like
It's important
But how do I access my that's just my point of view how do we know how small that margin is
I don't know how small it is
I mean
I'm thinking to
Various
Various encounters that my students have had for example where
They both agree that they were having consensual intercourse
And they both agree that the consent was withdrawn
During the Intercourse and the theater.
The dispute is about how rapidly
Stopped
And so and and their
Isn't
You know in that case I I just
I just hesitate to say it in again in it it's it seems
Clear on paper it at the absolutes of that what you control your body II you convey
For example
Start to cry during sex
Alright well then okay I would assume non-verbally that
This should stop or you know we should make sure
And it didn't stop but
You know did that take
2 seconds 5 Seconds 30 seconds
And that
From from the the moment of
You know what should you reasonably
Be aware of and I am very uncomfortable with the idea that
Person has feelings
Determine whether person B's Behavior was rape or not
Because I always calling it rape I mean sometimes it would also if it's called sexual assault
You know sexual assault I feel like that's a really
Important distinction
But like the terms even sexual assault is not it is not adequate you know because there are so many different grade
Gradations but I don't think I don't I don't think like I don't think
I I personally I do I do think that if someone
It's someone's feelings should determine whether person be
Have assault at them like I think even thinking about like when someone cries in the middle of sex
You know like talking about talking about like that is it is it 5 seconds is it 10 seconds is it 30 seconds
Like what are all the things that happened leading up to that moment
What cuz he eats
He disputes he says
I stopped as soon as I realized she was crying yeah
And she says she says
I I was I was crying for like 25 seconds less than 30 seconds
And so that
Period between when I started crying and when he realized I was crying
But I feel like temp to me when I hear a story like that
I think that there was actually a lot of other there are probably a lot of other things leading up to that moment
That we're not
Received you know or that the reason why she's coming forward and saying that this was an assault this was a violation
There's probably a lot there's a
An unseen architecture 2-2.
Did that story
That is really complicated I guess like I could I don't think that someone would just come out and be like I cried for 30 seconds and then
You didn't you didn't stop like it's probably a lot it goes it runs
Much deeper than that there was something there's something unnameable happening in that room
And she sort of hinges that unnamable feeling of a violation on
This is a field trial is Trivial when you talk about it out loud
But she's trying to say something was not right here you know I agree
Yeah
So I very much agree to get into the complicated area of a kite
Terry we agree on a whole lot that
I don't dispute at all
I see even and even in my cases where have the most doubt about what happened
I don't dispute that the accuser feels violated I think I think that's
True
They usually can be violated she is violated
Because there's all kinds of reasons besides being sexually assaulted that a person might feel violated
I'll talk about
One instance
For myself
You don't work the people have broken my heart when I was in love with people
And
You know there was a breakup where I got treated like dirt
When we were in love and like knew each other's family isn't all of that and then you know basically ghosted me and then
Don't me
Free phone call
10 months
I felt extremely vile
I can't put into words how bad he made me feel
Ito en +
How
It colored my memory of every interaction weed had for 10 months
And Christmas together with my family Hawaii
You know and and
Calling into question you did
Was he lying to me then
Feel very exhausted by his
It's probably not a word I would have come up with
But I
Feel
Unbelievably. I'm happy married now it's all good
You know I should not have ended up with him
But especially at the timing that that was an experience that permanently changed me I'm not the same person I was before that heartbreak
Sexually assault me
You know this is it was it was awful what he did
I I just make sense to me that people could be unbelievably deeply hurt
Buy all kinds of behavior that isn't sexual assault
But I can
I can see that I can see I can see
I can see that but I guess I feel like
You know what we're doing right now is working against history you know like I think that we're trying to
Make progress on on this issue of sexual assault and the much larger issue of
The imbalance of power as it is distributed between the genders
Like
Right can you ever really
As a woman and this is I don't know if I fully agree with what I'm about to say but it's just I'm just posing it as a as a Fil-A sauce
Topical question
You know if you're if you're taught from birth to Define your pleasure based on someone else and someone else's pleasure
How can you even know what you want or don't want
In those private moments you know in like how do we restore that that balance
Sino yeah I think a lot of what you're describing is
On a
What I'm seeing as a as a generational divide
I'm in in feminism
I don't know how old you are on 42 yeah I'm I'm I'm 30 yeah
Yeah women who are my age and older
I find tend to agree with me
And the women who are
College major in their twenties now often don't
And the disconnect stems I feel like when you were describing
How because of
Societal pressures and training from birth and all that
When the man was naked in my room I could not do anything but give him a blow.
I could not say no
And I would say you did not say no
And there may be
Situations
Where we agree that this is a Kent situation
But I don't see it as
Positive
My feminism
Agency
They put her in a pink dress. She has to give a b******
I understand that and I think that's a really important point of view but I also I guess
People have done research about that the fact that like young girls Define how good sex was based on
How much they perceive the other person enjoying it and then an even something as simple as that creates
Up a power Dynamic and I feel like I'm not really seeing the men and the minute I know the
The young man that I know I'm not seeing them understanding the power that they have that's really easy to
YouTube to abuse you know and like how do you fix that that's what it's kind of all comes down to and like there has to be
What there has to be some kind of consequences if we're going to see a change
We're going to take a quick break and we'll come right back to
This conversation between Kaitlin Prest Hannah Stalin and myself just Mom
Hello my name is Erin Davis I'm calling from Tempe Arizona
Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology
In the modern world more information about Sloan at www.slha.org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
About what we're calling tiny moments childhood Brilliance basically I want to hear about those times when a kid
So did something
It just means you read back and say whoa how did they do that maybe it was the moment that a kid
Did you been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons and you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed they're writing music in the margin of their geometry homework we're interested in
Epic moments where a kid does something super smart but doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story
T-shirt with us
Go to radiolab.org brilliance
Record short audio message for us
And that's radiolab.org / brilliance
Thank you so much
Amgen having rods Radiolab we're back with the second episode in a three-part series that we're doing inspired by
Collaboration with Kaitlin Prest
It's called in the know
And we're going to jump back into the conversation that Caitlin I were having with Hannah Scotland before we do
I want to bring some other voices
Cuz Allen
Where you're sitting and wouldn't I just place you for that way I can just like soap
As we were working on this series
I mean it really was an exploration for us one of the things that happen along the way as we can be in groups of college students
In different spots across the country
Groups of college-age men and women on my colleagues back a wrestler and she Molle II or with women
Going to hear more from the women next week
Don't play with the bit of the man because
When Hannah and Kaitlyn and I were talking it called to mind
Something that I heard a lot in these conversations
You have to take a leaf at some point
You have to take like you're talking to this person you're making eye contact whatever
And like it you can also can I kiss you
And Mike
They say yes but like at the same time
Sometimes you just go for it and like
That's where gets if he because of weather like
Sacrificing that
Is what we need to do
For no one to get raped
You know Nann
Super malicious scenarios like maybe what we have to give up is just
You're looking to rise the sun's Rising you're like
Hello would you
Can I record you on my cell phone if you saying you're down to make out right now
You know I mean
You know what something I guess I'm willing to give up if that's what's being asking if that actually solved the issue
I just think that we're coming to a point where that might be the line by the way
The thing you talk about that is actually an app that exists we talk to the guy who made it but what would he and other guys were
Saying
We sit there on easy
They still feel somehow caught between those old gendered expectation that it's the man's job to pursue and
The world at war now which seems to not
Want that but maybe not entirely not not want that there. Sure and a lot of them
Worry
Then maybe they've already
Cross the line
Without knowing it
Always in the back of my mind like I've hooked up with a girl that's like instigated it like
Like while having sex you decide that
But she doesn't want to be like she was going to
Gets up late
You know like then what then if if
To the next day if she decides that
But she realizes that like if she did want to do that
Maybe after the fact
Then it just be my
I've definitely hooked up with people where they were very drunk the first time we hooked up
No one ever was like oh that was not okay or anything but
In all the situations I guarantee they thought myself I was drunker than the person I was hooking up with
But
Because I'm a man
That could be retrospectively
That could have been sexual assault
That's definitely the biggest question I've been asking myself post
The thing is like wow
Could it even be claimed like I don't think that I sexually assaulted someone
At all I mean given that
You know what I asked are you sure but
That isn't even enough cuz that's a alcohol
You know even if you get a vocal consent
If there's alcohol involved
So I guess that's work at then just interesting nothing make a cold but yeah
Everything that you did make a mistake
Benson was like that wasn't okay what you did to me last night or something
Right
You say your sorry I believe I really do understand that you don't like you learn like we now have to be I don't think my
Be free like but I understand that but if somebody says like you sexually assaulted me and if it's
Situation like you're talking about where you both have been drunk
And you say I'm sorry is that not
I would be scared to say
That because
How to say what I'm sorry I'm sorry because that's like you're admitting you're guilty even if you don't think you are if you try to engage in a
Conversation like that so just maybe like you don't say I'm sorry say oh my God like please explain to me like how I did that were like what
What happened cuz I was too drunk to read
Remember or like something like that
And after that you know after I
Having
Pleasure after listening to these guys and then having this conversation with Caitlin and Connor I mean four
For 1
Things that they were afraid of her exactly things that we were talking about into I started to think about the
Fear
That sort of ambient fear that was always in the room
Can you argue there something useful about the
Fear
Because that fear
Mike push these guys to address exactly what Kevin was just saying
Am I push the guys too
What what what I what I hear over and over again when I talk to it when I talk students is that
The women in the end I get a sexual encounter are thinking about 12 things
And the guys are thinking about one thing which is themselves right they're just they're not reading the room they're not reading their partner
What's going to change that if not fear
Like the fear these guys feel right now could actually make them
Start to pay attention
Make us I should say start to pay attention
Yes it might
I certainly think of my
SA
Writing support
As a form of Education
Coaching how a student should handle
A tough situation
I'm not sure that
Making the consequence
It's really bad
Is what
Makes it more likely that the behavior will change
But
I would love to see
Young men
Encouraged
To go through the kind of
Analysis of their actions
Is that
My new with me and it and it's
I think it's a really positive process for that man and
I see what looks to me like greater insight
Tonight it's going to bring it back to the moment itself
Cuz a lot of what we're talking about
On a macro level
Still have to be negotiated in these moments right
And you've talked about
The idea of we need a reasonableness standard for for the consensual moment
What does that mean
Do you
So to me it means that
Communication needs to be in a shared language
You know if if someone says to me in Russian
That doesn't feel good
I just don't speak that
So is it reasonable to expect me to understand
What this person was conveying
In a language that I don't speak
Like I would consider trying to be a universal language now if it's dark
And
You're not touching the person's face whatever you might not realize immediately
That they are
Crying without
You know it's not why Loctite crying
I was just it's
Tears and and and emotion and punch throat and all that
How rapidly is it reasonable to expect
That you pursue
Steve that communication which it is communication
And if you could see the person's face
That I dated Ariana ambiguous
Communication
It is it reasonable to think it might take you a minute
To to realize that
My partner's feelings are totally changed
So there's a there's a spectrum between saying no no no stop and expecting somebody read your mind
Right that there's a million different ways to convey that
With different levels of urgency and clarity
And I just think we should we should take into account
What can we reasonably expect
Him in this scenario to realize
About her changed frame of mind
What do you think
For me I think a step forward is just being aware of the power dynamics that are happening in sex talking about them explicit
Italy understanding what they are understanding the ways that they're fun the ways of their pleasurable
And I'm being really open
About those things and I think that like it all comes back to the communication I mean like I really like
What you said Hannah about the about the languages you know figuring out how to speak each other's languages
Figuring out truss
And also just like
Having there be less of a stigma around conversations explicit open
Totally Shameless conversations about sexuality
Would bring us
Forward and in massive massive leaves around this stuff
And also just sit like that they gave me I think the thing that I'm not seeing that I wish I did see was just
Giving a s***
You know that Karen likes having
Had like we know when somebody says hey that that experience sucked for me
Having the other person be like Wow Let's talk about it are you okay you know it cuz I got to like so many situations would
Would be would be would be solved if that was a dynamic as opposed to what are you talkin about
Like
The gaslighting all that stuff
Yeah that's my little Mexico
The work I do with some of the students
When I say so what do you regret
And sometimes you're not sure they're like a really didn't attack her
And I said but do you regret is it ever your goal
To get into your bed with someone and have them walking away going up I'm glad that's over
And the guys like no I don't want that and I was like well
That's what you got
And we can't dispute we can dispute whether it was an assault or not
It is objectively the case
But this person had a bad experience with you
Everybody agrees on that
And if that wasn't what you wanted to happen
Then you probably have regret about that I should have done something differently so it didn't come out that way
I'm not telling them what they ought to want sexually
But I do tell them
To consider what they want sexually
It is it is not I want to preface this by saying I'm not saying that the training of men and women is symmetrical it's not
But that some of them
May may realize
Some of the men
May realize
You know what I was told that men are supposed to like any any kind of sexual contact we can get from anyone anywhere we're supposed to be happy
Happy about that
And is that actually what I want or is that what
People expect me to want and maybe I would prefer more of a
You know loving gentle kind of relationship
Maybe I'm the man and not that kind of model would actually work better for me
Then this Conquest model
Interesting cuz it made what I hear a lot coming out of the me-too movement is that I hear a lot of women saying
Guys you need to do the work
Okay like this is this is largely your work to do
Right now
And I hadn't expected
To hear you
Talking about
What you do as in substance being part of that like you are actually
It seems
Involved in some of the guys doing the work
I ain't like how to do the work
Is its own sort of can of worms like which is something we haven't really talked too much about
But it is interesting to hear that I wasn't expecting
That to
Medication assistance that it's not necessarily Michael
But it may be necessary in order to achieve my goal which is to help you advocate for your education
You can't do that effectively
Unless you've been thoughtful about your past
And
Might my thesis is gray help the kids
Caesar Gray
And
You know this is this is not a binary world we live in in terms of gender in terms of communication
And and to some extent I feel like we have
Work with
The complexity of what's in front of us
Even if we wish it were black and white and that would make our job a lot
Caitlin any final thoughts
Amen no I don't think so
I guess
Yeah this is the
Great combo
I want to thank Kaitlin Prest and
Hannah Stalin for sitting down to talk
Few notes before we close if you have experienced sexual assault
There are resources out there to support you and the national sexual assault hotline at 1 800 6 5 6
Hope that is 1 800 6 5 6
467 3
Can provide support and connected resources in your local area and also one thing I do
I want to add
Is this conversation recently aired it without a ton of edits
Amendments is that
It's not meant to be comprehensive take on anything this is one small piece of a much larger conversation if anything
Salina temp
To hold a space
For that continuing conversation
Facebook and talk about the stuff which we're going to continue to do next week
Next week will end up in a place where that conversation happens very explicitly and very differently
For Better or Worse
In this episode we had production help from Rachel Cusick research and Reporting help from backup
Wrestler in chamoli I said thanks for listening
To play the message press to start of message
Hi I'm Caitlin it's Caitlin hello
Radioactive created by God album Rod and is produced by Salon wheeler filling pieces are directorates and Design
Maria Maria Maria
Is a managing director
Assassin Clues xiamen Adler back of wrestler
Rachel Cusack
David Campbell
Guys
Kasie hunt
Hot Robert krulwich and it makes the peace Nasir master
My fair Melissa O'Donnell Arianne wack
At Walker
And Molly Webster with help from FEMA only cats and mo
I should be Elmo
Glee end
And this message