Northern listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
Which is Radiolab and let's just
What does okay cool
With a reporter and producer lots of knots
I think the best place to begin it sounds like
Is in 2008 so this is Jason De Leon I am an associate professor
Master of anthropology at the University of Michigan I direct the undocumented migration Prague
But back in 2018 Jason and actually just finished
And my doctoral dissertation was on ancient stone tools
Holistic Industries
San Lorenzo tenochtitlan
An economic and technological studies about as far removed as you can be from
The stuff that I'm doing right now using a city in technological data from 11 domestic and non-domestic auntie
Explain json was on his way to being an archaeologist
So she would go out into the field you these digs
Parts of Mexico and find these little fragments of Old Stone tools to study focuses primarily on
Percussion flake
Dating back to about a thousand BC industry that is often ignored in Mesoamerican lithic analysis
And then you would write these
Papers by comparing differences
In the frequencies
A various tool type
Journal
Search said really did a handful of people agreed
But
Like many academics and I can say this cuz I wasn't academic the study also finds
Introduction
An adoption
Prismatic blade
He had this moment we're just kind of
Hit the wall
Like okay this is enough I'm not I'm not doing this
I want nothing to do with it
You know when I finish my dissertation I had really become
Kind of disillusion with the work that I was doing and I have no idea what I was going to do I remember telling my wife at one point I feel really bad I feel like
Wasted the last 10 years of my life doing archaeology
And to make matters worse I taken his job at University of Washington it's just got in his job where he was supposed to teach the very thing
Yeah it's just like
Dove just an exit just a
Full-blown crisis
But then
States Dept
Will json Was preparing for one of his freshman classes
Someone handed him a book writer named Luis Alberto urrea call the devil's The Devil's Highway
Five men stumbled out of the mountain pass so sunstruck
They didn't know their own names
Going to remember where they come from
Had forgotten how long they been lost
One of them wondered backup a peek
One of them was barefoot
They were burned nearly black
Your lips huge
McCracken
The Devil's Highway is actually Willits
It's a true story
326 men who came to the US hiking their way through the Arizona desert
14 of them died along the way as I start reading it and
Visions of Home flooded through their minds
Soft green bushes
Waterfalls
Children did you shock me I mean I knew a lot about the Border least I thought I did
You know tell Texas my parents were immigrants
But just I couldn't believe that
That's
You know that this was
This is somebody's world they were drunk from having their brains baked in the past
They were saying God and Devil days and days of walking
I'm running out of food they were dizzy from drinking their own urine you know dying of thirst
Poisons clogging your system
And a certain point Jason comes across this past
Where the author is describing the things that were in these men's pocket
Belt buckle with a fighting cock inlay
One wallet in the right front pocket of his Gino to change some keys and silver belt buckle fake silver watch
1 km
You know these personal effects green handkerchief
And he's trying to reconstruct
The story about who these men were that died from
From exposure John Doe number 42
Pure jeans
Colored piece of paper
Jason says when you read that book
Alight
I thought I bought a plane ticket a month later I was in the Arizona desert
Jason gets out to Tucson Arizona and he manages to convince
Someone from a local NGO to basically like showing around and be his guide but I said
I want to look at the stuff in my turtle leaving in the desert
Cuz I already want to see this FAQ real deep into the desert and see what you what you're made of
Misguided ran me through the wringer
That part of the Sonoran Desert
Is Haley covered in sagebrush
Cacti everywhere red sand
Jason said certain point in a few hours in the height
They walked a distinct line and got to this Rich where they could
He'll look out over this huge expanse
Just imagine like a
A ravine or a wash
Jason says he suddenly noticed that the desert ground below them
Was just
Hubbard Inn
Stop over a thousand backpacks and water bottles at me
Well what ends up happening is
Stuff gets left behind
For a couple of different reasons
If you're in route you might throw something out because you get so tired in your bag just get so heavy
I know things are kind of sprinkle to posses migrant Trail
But once you get to the end
Pastor checkpoint
Your Smuggler said okay we're safe now we got to a new road we can get picked up someone else
Will show up in the truck and then they will say alright the 30 of you get into the van
Leave everything behind
Change your clothes so it doesn't look like you just walked for 2 weeks to this desert
Until when groups are moving really big you would see things of size of like football fields of just
Stuff everywhere
Gatorade bottles Bibles photographs
Toys
The kind of random things that you might throw in your bag and say I'm leaving
My home forever and annie's I think I want to take with me
You know you busy think like a diaper bag or a baby bottle
And you wonder my God
You know who
Who just came through this
And what's
What happened to them
So
For the next several years Jason just keep going back to this stretch of the Sonoran Desert close to closing
Gathering whatever he could find dirty socks and
You don't like an archaeologist he would collect the stuff
Categorizing cocktail dresses
High heel shoes try and figure out who it came from why it was their baby bottles hair curlers toy rapper
Who did the Lakers photograph for year
Backpacks Bibles bottles
Human arm
He finds an arm weigh between some rocks
Like an entire arm up to the show
Sticking sticking out between two rocks
There was no flashes other than the
The things are holding the joint together
Yeah
Jason and his guidebooks you there with they began to search the surrounding areas for other parts of
The body let me really the goal is to try to find
The skull
Because in terms of
You know
Identification
Your best luck is going to be if you can get if you can get
The
Pieces of the skull
Because if you can find pieces of a skull maybe you can ID the body and if you can ID the body
Maybe you can tell the family
Here's what happened to your loved one
So we were out there basically digging around
Four four other parts of this person
We come across a human tooth some little tiny bits of rib bones
But we never find the skull
But I realize that
Nobody's ever going to identify the person
There's not enough left of them and
Does not not likely to be a case that will be solved
Now Jason says he knew of course that people are dying in the desert
But to see this
The fragments of a person
Erased
You know it's very
I mean it's kind of just it started to kill you
Eventually he began have these nightmares snakes coming out of the eyes
About the missing skull bird swooping down and then picking up the eyes coyotes playing soccer with a person skull
Couldn't shake the simple Quest
You know what
What did this to this person
And how many other bodies like this might be out here
How'd it get to be like this
Questions
End up sending Json down
Sort of rabbit hole digging in the library
Forensics papers
Missing persons report igartua gone missing historical trends
Sociology paper is demography paper government document illustrations and the figures in the bitter Berry gunny's appendices
And over the next several years Jason would end up putting together this
Truly startling portrait of lost stories hidden statistics
Little known policy decisions along our Southern border that completely upended how I think about this
Issue issue
Poses real problem
Challenges that were constantly fighting about
Don't never quite
This part one of a three-part series
On our Southern border
Will be doing it today and then next week and the week after
Part 1
Hole in the fence
All right so I stopped and started off
With Json question
How'd it get to be like this
How did it get to be
That's so many
People cross into America through the desert like
That's the classic image you have is someone who
Walking through the
The desert
Why
Out of all the places
Along the border that
You could cross
Why is it that
So many people are are crossing in the hottest and most unforgiving place
Imaginable
One of the things that Jason ended up telling us about that we found
Mosto
Striking
With simply the numbers
Yearly numbers
Of Migrant deaths
What's in the desert
And I mean it is shocking if you look at the date of their
A very Stark moment when things ship
Is it turns out that
If you're looking at
The number of people dying
In the Sonoran Desert the numbers are a bit tough.
Pain down butt in the early nineties
It's single digits five bodies one
On your six bodies another
7 bodies
All of a sudden
Overnight in the late 90s
You go from 5 to 10 Bodies 2
I mean it used to be that if you wanted to cross the us-mexico border
You go down to
Cassandis to Tijuana
At dusk
Please call the soccer field
You would hop the fence with about
100 other people in the witches
Bum rush the border patrol in
Pappy we get by
Would make it into the US in
You'll have to get caught sent back and people do it again the next day
That was a system for a long time
I'm in love tell me what change
Well
In the mid-90s there was a lot of push back up
Against the visibility of
Muffin topping
And
It all kind of starts
With
This little-known story
There's a great book by
This guy Timothy Dunn called
Blockading the Border
And it's about the Latino high school students in Texas
Is right on the
We ended up calling the author he mentioned Timothy done and it and I'm getting so interested in the story that done laid out for us that
We're going to leave Jason behind for a while
I'm going to go on a little
Yes
That by the way is co reporter Tracy hunt
All right well so where we going to go
We're going to El Paso
El Paso Texas
So
Yes at Racine I went to El Paso a while back
Tomorrow of course he thought that if I was born somewhere else yeah
Of course I mean I think about that
I feel like
I guess I got distracted you didn't finish the American flag
And a Texan flag
We went down to El Paso to visit
High School
Call Bowie High School
Did you guys understand
You know in many respects it's just you know your typical American High School
Yeah baby, do they get your taco Tuesdays it's nice to talk
Afraid
About
Coventry students
The detectorists know football
And on their campus to have a huge football stadium with those big ghetto Friday Night Lights
Marching band The Pride of the south side
Yeah your typical Texas High School
Yeah but there is something a little different about it and that is that almost all the students here
Scared Jose or Mexican American
Gisela
Oscar and we actually talk to you one former teacher this is one cyber Coronado I was eight
Teacher at Bowie High School in the 1980s and 1990s
And what did you think
I taught history and he said that in all his years teaching at Bowie out there for 21 years and never had a single analyst
Really
Single white
Did we went to Bowie High School it's cuz something happened there in the early 90s
Something that
It's sort of a note in a roundabout and and totally unforeseen able way completely change the way we
Think about that the US Mexico border
So we're going to start the stories actually in one of one Seibert tornados class
The class was immediately after lunch
And on this particular day that we're going to have a debate in class
And one of them debaters
First one of the kids was
Going to be part of the debate
With late yes
Albert alphin came to came late to class
And so we've been waiting and waiting and waiting for him
10 minutes went by
20 and eventually he showed up being dragged in by the scabs
Security guy
The school security guard and I thought you the security guard and brought him in because he was you know
Out doing some miscreant stuff like smoking pot again and
And so I kind of lay into Albert for being late again and for you know that pulling up his wrist
Responsibilities with glass
But but I was like no no no other says that he had been at the handball court playing with his friends
And then when it was time to go from the quarterbacks
Class
These two border patrol agents just came out of nowhere and their green uniforms demanding to see his papers like who are you
Where you from let me see your ID and he Albert tries to give them his school ID but they wouldn't take it
And they actually told him do you need today
Federal ID of some sort
For them to believe it all that he was a United States citizen
Or belong on the camp
And one just standing there like haha border patrol really bringing the kid obviously
Virginia three or four other students in class just kind of stepped in and said know what Albert telling you is true
Not only is Albert telling the truth but in the last couple of weeks
Border patrol had been on the handball courts and on the playing field
Repeatedly stopping students harassing student and
I was quite frankly shocked
One says of course he knew that the Border Patrol was around
Because of where the school is situated which will
Talk about in a second
But he just never understand
Present they weren't his students live
I was having a hard time processing
So the next few weeks
One started asking around different students being like
Hey have you had anything happen with border patrol at school and I got literally hundreds
The stories I was walking home from school and then I have my backpack on
This is Nidia Rodriguez who was a freshman at the time and all the sudden I saw this truck
Border patrol tracking
Eating my way a couple of Agents got out of the truck and started questioning her where am I where am I going
We're all rounded up remember is walking to
School with a bunch of kids
Her backpack and again you know a couple of Agents got outside questions or we were born
Birth classes were taking.
School what do you have in the bag
When I go books
You know what else would I have in my bag
Play like walking through yelled at me over here
Sped up to me in the stopped in front of him to ask me
You know what's what's in the bag of the books
One of them rip the bag out for my hands
As I was trying to pull it
Away from home the other one grabbed me and pushed me up against the truck
Forcibly
The bag way
Rifle through it
Push me out for the
I already pulled me away from the truck
I threw my bag at me and told me to get out of here
As the stories came out it became clear that even the staff had had its run-ins with the border patrol we talked to the
Assistant football coach
Ben morea
He told us there was this moment he was driving with
Two of his football players they got pulled over by the border patrol
And one of them actually pointed a gun at his
Had never had a gun
Hold On Me
So I thought okay my life is over
I know I got a dinner fied myself my name is coach been with you coach Bowie High School I have two of my football players
I would really appreciate if you holster your gun and the guy barked at me
I appreciate you shut your mouth and get out of the car did holster The Gun Ben did get out of the car
Car everything was fine
What was that like
Rainier
One of the scariest
Things
In my life
Why was the Border Patrol
On the grounds of the
They have some reason what's a little bit more maybe because I seem to understand
What was going on at
Bowie High School
You have to understand something else
The legend of El Paso
You have to understand
El Paso
Flavor
From 30000 feet
Right on the border of Texas
Mexico and New
It's also the biggest city
Shares a border with Mexico to the other thing to know about it is that it's like it kind of has a mirror City on the other side of them
Which is
Water
Ciudad Juarez
The largest city on the US Mexico border
The two cities are separated by the
Little sliver of the Rio Grande but they were essentially the same city up until 1848 when the US
Invaded Mexico in Annex half the country
And even now according to Juan this mythical division between these two cities it's just
Doesn't exist remote
I mean I go to the dentist over there I buy cigarettes over there okay I smoke it
Almost everybody El Paso knows people live in ciudad Juarez
People feel a lot of snow people in have family members who live in El Paso
And this is literally one community
But the thing is when everything was going down in Bowie in the early 90s it was a community
In crisis
The night shoot
The peso crisis has spilled across
The Rio Grande
In the eighties the Mexican peso
Trash
Until people in Juarez started flocking you a passo because
Well that's
Swear the jobs work like Johnson Construction childcare gardening
Kermit.the coming to El Paso legally that then you had all these other people workers required by
Lock and get permits but they still need it to work simply respond to the laws of supply and demand
And so they started coming to across the border to the United States
At unprecedented numbers ten thousand people a day
A day
You legally basically for their commute to work
It was chaos
It was a mess here
Border patrol Agent Venom David Hamm as a special agent
He told us that when when he was on that job
Before Dawn you can go down a certain parts the Rio Grande you have a hundred two hundred people lined up
Waiting on the River's Edge sun come up in here they come
Rush hour has begun the rush across the Rio Grande into El Paso
And there videos where you can see that you you see people waiting into the shallow parts of the River to cross over to El Paso
If they don't want to get wet they can pay a young entrepreneurial small fee and raft across
Is border patrol agent
It becomes this cat-and-mouse game probably the way we've always done business
They come in you chase him
Catch him and send him back
Day and night and day and night it was it was
Never ending job
And it was something you know you catch the same guys to three times a shift sometimes
Hello I'm sorry
It was it was chaos
Obviously we're not accomplishing 100% of our nation
Eggs that you got a hilarious
Salt Lake
Around this time in 1992 there was a television interview
And they'll misegades he's the secretary for the board of
Paw Patrol in El Paso
He's wearing a green hat with his green uniform with the gold shield on his chest
If we were not here
Did not keep a lid on this situation
An in the shop
Behind him salute free
Import from other country
You can see people
Climbing up the banks of the Rio Grande and just walking into El Paso
Laughs like having Wyatt Earp standing in front of three bank robbers robbing a bank
Like so
How many
Alright so it was reported
At a time that for everyone migrant the border patrol caught
There were at least three to five
Who snuck in and didn't get caught
And The Weather Channel said that this was because they just didn't have the right
Didn't have the money or the agents
To apprehend all these people that are coming in
Which finally brings us back
To Bowie High School
Okay alright okay yeah let's try it
Because there's two important things about
Counting my steps
Who is
Right right or
5 6
Right on the ball
49er basically it's 50-50 steps 50 steps from the
We can't fit into Mexico into
The former
Assistant football coach and teacher benemerito he showed me
What's the what is that
Dispense
The old manse
Put up a bunch of fencing on the border to curb
Illegal immigration
So it's like a
Did so much taller than us but it was it was pretty flimsy they called it to Tortilla curtain and
Right at this spot across from Bowie High School
There was a hole
In the fence
Yeah
And David
Former border patrol agent told us what that meant was that you had mine heard you had a lot of migrants
Could be
Coming through that hole in the fence for Bowie High School
And he claimed that it wasn't just people looking for work
It was also people bringing in drugs
No way I know that because I work
Anti-smuggling unit
Watch him come through
And so border patrol agents had taken
To just sort of hanging out around the school on the school's property on the football field across the
Street from the school like just they were just there all the time even rumors that border patrol
You just would go undercover as students
And that they would you no wonder the Halls that they would go into the locker rooms I've noticed the
The Suburban
Parked on the bully camp
Again former Bowie teacher
1 Seibert Coronado the whole reason you know that I thought they were there was the chain link is cut and they need
Stop people
From entering into a high school
Instead of realizing that what they're doing is they're using the high school as a hunting round
And so the one when he started hearing about all the stories of these 14 15 16 year old kids
Stockton shaken down
It wasn't about border patrol trying to stop migrants from coming in or trying to stop drugs from coming across the border
It was the border patrol simply stopping people because they were Brown
And that's really
His Radio
Angered me
But for most of these kids
Look out of the ordinary
You know kids like Ernesto Munoz
Ricardo vielma
Day today
Life talkative into some of the committee members Tony Santos the told me don't worry about it
Core neighborhood right next to the Border real life
Hear it in South El Paso go to the park
Shoot some basketball
You tell your your schoolmates we going to guess what happened after school care
You know how you got stuff
Because of your hair cutter probably cuz of
You know how you're dressed or whatever you're more likely to laugh about it then be angry but in his US history class that year
One started teaching his kids about civil rights
Actually getting them to
The beat the different ways of thinking about
Talking about stuff like
Over the last
Hugh Dane
Letter from Birmingham Jail on to my mine
Mark the non-violence movement coming of age
And Malcolm X's Ballot or The Bullet
Interview students are learning about
Farm worker strikes in California 1960s we learn about Cesar Chavez
We learn about Dolores Huerta Vegas La Patilla Karina
He was like
Okay I'll bring that book and I look outside the window and
There they are
Border patrol agents in SUV's
On the parking lot stopping student
I think that's funny that we were
Wait
Hannah would like
Not okay I mean I didn't fully know exactly the letter of the law.
Find you that's what they were doing was wrong to get together
But you think this is right what do you think this is about
Potluck
Are we wanted things to be different
Let's see
What we can do about it
Because this has to
Alright that's what's up
Coming up
Juan and his students buy back
Will continue in just a moment
Let's do some more warm up
Hi this is Monica calling from Oakland California
Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding
Science and technology in the modern world
More information about Sloan at
Www.slha.org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here I'm a producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
And I request
For those of you who
Who spend a lot of time with kids parents
Aunts and uncles teachers we're looking for stories about what we're calling
Tiny moments
Brilliant
Basically I want to hear about those times
When a kid you know did something
It just means you lean back and say
Maybe it was the moment that I
A kid you've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of their musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class
Stay Ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the
Epic moments where
A kid does something super smart
It doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story
T-shirt with
Go to radiolab.org
Flash brilliance
Mrecorder short
Audio message
Again that's radiolab.org
Slash brilliant
Thank you so much
Chad Robert and hello
Ricardo
And Tony
Okay alright so some of these kids at Bowie High School they actually belong to this group
Which is a Chicano civil rights
This has been around for holidays
Cintas 1960s it was a college group that these kids at Bowie actually petition them to have a chapter at
And I said sure
We were the first ones to get the Collegiate group
Supervised we would meet about once a week
And
Our meetings tended to be 30 40 50 kids
Packed into a classroom
And for one of these meetings one brought in one of his friends a woman named Susan Curran
She works for the Border rights
Coalition and social
She comes in and he student start telling her you know what's been going on
And they asked her if we have any rights here
She tells them absolutely you do because according to
The US Constitution
The border patrol or really
Any officer of the law they cannot
Stop you
Without reasonable cause
Beyhadh 15 you cross the border or when you saw them he started acting fidgety or you ran away or some
They can't just arbitrarily stop you question you because of the color of your
That's not enough to stop you
Because if that's the only reason they have to stop you then they're violating your fourth
Right the right to be protected from unreasonable searches and seizures
Exactly
They just said you know what
You're getting your rights are getting stomped all over let's see
What we can do about this because it needs to stay
After Susan explain that the rights were being violated the conversation turned to what are we going to do about it
We have a lot of students who were suggesting things
That were probably you know slightly inappropriate
Like how about we just curse him out which I thought will make us out a bad approach
But apparently
According to one's friend Susan
Better to salt and so away from them
Definitely don't do that
But
Finally
One of the students
Who's been watching Law & Order attempted murder of your mother
Who's knew all about
Saying the right to remain silent
You would like nothing it's your 5th amendment constitutional right
Isn't that you typically hear or instructed by my counsel
Not to test
The five based on my fifth amendment constitutional rights
When rich white dudes get into
Advice of counsel I broke my 5th Amendment privilege
And respectfully
Decline to answer your question
But this one Bui match a student would like
Why don't we do that
And that's exactly what our students started doing
After that when border patrol agents would stop students and say hey give me your papers
Some of these students would say
No I want to use my Fifth Amendment right I want to take the Fifth Amendment
Simple as that they have the right not to incriminate myself
Tremaine Style
I do not want to answer your question
Start Heidelberg right to remain silent
I don't want you to go through any of my stuff backpack
Amendment Amendment right
Spreading around right to remain silent
That we really
Dump near me
The answer people's questions
The reminder
Why why why
Myself being
Being you and giving advice to these
Students and on the one hand obviously this is their legal right not to
Provide
Information on the other hand
I can imagine that you know I've heard that there are
Border patrol abuse has there are
You know this
There are times when it doesn't go well and I'm telling you student
To go out
And basically
Be home
Stonewall
Agency
It could put them In Harm's Way
And it did free
Students were harassed for this
Students were
The most notorious case is the case of David Renteria
And the way I started was on June 3rd
What was made in the 90s
Is about Bowie High School
Yes sir David Renteria he was a senior at Bowie legally blind students coming home from graduation
Practice and
And it's one day he just ran or just walking down the street and a border patrol truck
Rosa
My friend is the same thing in the office again what is a citizen
Seances again
Stand up
Out of the truck comes up to David break his arm if you tried to walk away
On my own
Slept album
You turned it
Exercising
Stance
And I he put his neck on the back of my neck
A kick my legs
Laughing at his face apparently
And you know David wasn't
Physically injured after that he was freaked out
The recent one called
Particular incident notorious is because
Immediately after
The local news in El Paso picked it up and started doing a lot more reporting on
On Border Patrol
Andouille
And so did
National news
Good morning freaking America you know what I mean that's that's that's pretty huge
Explain the relationship between the Border Patrol
And some people at Bowie High School
And that alright
Daily on a day-to-day course are being violated
Wyoming wrestling
Because we're Hispanic
Because the color of our skin
Because we live right on the border and because
Well we live in a really poor neighborhood end
That's the only reason
Atavist new started
Grow the border patrol sector Chief Dale musegades
Decided he was going to come to Bowie
To talk to the students
Is that something you remember him showing up
Doing damage control at that point
Discuss the alleged harassment he kept us out
We tried to contact you on musically.
Multiple timezone
The story but he did not reply to her voicemail
But
Wednesday morning
We were able to get footage
Which of that meeting Mousa Gates
Kept Good Morning America out because one of the students take this
And then we need to get our hands on it
So it's like 30-40 kids from matcha in this classroom
And Dale misegades
He was sitting in front of us
Wearing a suit and tie trying to put things into perspective
Started telling the students like
Look the holes in the fence
I can't hold it hold
We keep patching them up they keep getting cut open
I can't I
I don't think there's any way in the world
And he told the students say they busted some people who had brought drugs through Bowie
Investigation
So music is this like we're essentially trying to stop the flow of drugs here why are you guys complaining so
But eventually
Decedent start speaking up
One student stands up and says hey you're harassing us and that's why we're upset
And be your strategy for capturing border-crossers seems to be to heard them all into the school where they're penned in
Relevant to a place where they can get out of the you circled in it
It's raining like cat people
Will not stop
I don't like
You know I don't know a better way to do it but not at the sacrifice of a right
It's a little hard to hear but he said not at the sacrifice of our rights
I do not have right
What did it feel like to be sitting in that meeting I mean
It felt bizarre I mean that you know somebody is denying what everybody sees with her own eyes
There was no face value to what what he said now cuz it that when we were standing cynical about the whole situation and
And are you trying to undo the stuff that was already
To the meeting goes poorly
And a bunch of the students and some of the staff including benemerito this is
Football coach who had a gun
They all together decide that they want to
Sue the Border Patrol
The phone rings one day
And eventually they call up this guy
If we're getting ready to sue the Border Patrol
Will you be our local Council
And I said no but hell yeah
El Paso civil rights lawyer
Albert armendariz jr. optimistic
It's never nice job during the government is not easy when you live on the border and working Segundo Barrio
You are never optimistic
Then a governmental system is going to work for you
So
October 23rd 1992 the trial between Bowie High School and the border patrol begin
And apparently the courtroom was
Pretty much divided in half on one half you had the border patrol like
Agents in full uniform sitting there
Another half you had these boots
Dressed in their finest
Mini dresses black
Those kids were little Troopers
They all done up in the stand
Told her story
And then eventually
Border patrol sector Chief still missing
Do you remember what the defense's argument was
Well they had lots of argue
Now we can't verify this
Specifics of what happened in the courtroom because a lot of the court documents of being destroyed
Music it's got off there and his basic argument was it
If you look at
The US code
Federal regulations
Powers of immigration officers and employees
Number one
Officers
Have the power to interrogate
Any alien or person believed to be an alien
As to his right to be or to remain in the United States
And I can do that without a warrant
And then
They can do that quote within a reasonable distance from any external boundary of the United States
What's a what's a reasonable distance
So this is what nuts has I I don't know exactly what
Went into the germination of what that is but the distance is
A hundred miles
Really yeah in that hundred mile Zone border patrol has the power to interrogate has the power to arrest without warrant
And they can also and I'm quoting here
Quote search for aliens in any Railway car aircraft conveyance or vehicle within that
And then on top of that within a narrow word
Distance of 25 miles
Miles from the border
They can go right under private property
Whenever they want
There's the zone
It's designed
To prevent
Border patrol officers for being charged with
With trespass
When patrolling the Border
Akai cross-examined
Music
And so
What music it was arguing is it like if they have all this power
And if they can go on private property right up on the border
And you got this High School On the Border
Then there's no question that they can be on school property and do their jobs that's how they read that
But they couldn't understand is
They were
Doing it in a way that violated the Constitution and that is against the supreme law of the land
This was Albert's argument that
No matter what towers you have you can't violate somebody's Fourth Amendment right
You have to have a
Gintama treason
To stop somebody
So what did the court ultimately happened before this court is finding us that says findings of fat
Facts and conclusions of law
Bunton
, senior District
Judge
Before this court is plaintiff motion for temporary restraining order and preliminary injunction and memorandum of Law and support
Pursuant to rule Seattle
Does that sound
What we got in front of me here
Jurisdiction and venue
Okay that means
Keep me the findings of fact the litigation the name individual plaintiffs are united
Is it. I hereby order
The court hereby enjoying the immigration and National Naturalization Service the ins
It's about the time with both of them
From stopping and questioning an individual as to
His or her right
To be or remain in the United States
Unless the agent has Reasonable Suspicion based on speed
Specific articulable facts
Involving more than the mere appearance of the individual being a Hispanic
Descent
Okay that's a fancy way of saying stop judging people by their looks
Side the judge
Yes
So they wanted they want
It was just
Absolutely
Like she was a big celebratory school assembly
They're all
Hardee's
Plaques I think I might even have some of the wall up there
It was pretty awesome again for my student Ricardo vielma
Holds that the border patrol did violate constitutional rights
You just don't see the agents on our campus anymore
Deputy assistant football coach been Maria who ended up being a lead plaintiff in a lawsuit
Treating us like people like second-class citizens
Federal agent
And we couldn't believe that we took on the federal government and one
That was one of the first times I was really proud of what our government
DL stands for
Ricardo said
Coming out of federal court that day
It was like him and seven other students
Send it came out
And there's a bunch of other students and faculty from the school there everybody was like cool let's go back to school hop in the car like now
Yeah we kind of want a basket
So we walked from
The federal courthouse downtown to Bowie High School
And you know when we were getting there where
Did we are all
Discounted tearing up
We're proud we are just
Happy and
And that surprised all I want Susie
And
Tell if we had a camera Crews and news crews waiting for us as we were walking up cuz I guess they
We got wind that we were just walking
Put in the week of
This victory
In the months following their be a chain of events
That would
Really
Jurassic
We change the US Mexico border forever
And take us to
Really where we are now
When you receive what you wrote in that essay sort of just three
You don't see the text you don't think there's a connection but the fact that the connection is being made
Associative weighs on you
That's okay because I mean
Because of us
Fences were bill
Because the fences were built
Maybe 10000
Men for their faces
Open chewing saguaros
Prickly pear
Leaving garden plants that look like animals have torn them apart book
Claws
The green hair
Scream
They walk Quest
Thought they didn't know it
They have no concept anymore
Destination
They were in a basket
One of them said
So how the story goes from Jubilation and pride to
Death in the desert
That's the subject of our next episode
This episode of our story was reported by lots of Nasser and Tracy hunt produced by Matt kielty with Bethel hopday
Tracy hunt and lots of knots
Special thanks to Timothy done for writing a book that really guided our story of Bowie High School to Chris wanted
Kevin Lavelle with kvia for the archival footage they gave us and to Gustavo Rivera Reyes at the El Paso Independent School District
Principal Francisco ordaz San Mateo High School
Thanks also Maggie solar Gladstone from a shed for allowing us to use excerpts from The Devil's Highway
Eric robledo Michael Wells the Parsons school of design at the new school
And a Susan Kern
And to Debbie Nathan
I'm Jedi bomb run
Bojack next week with more from the series
This is Rachel calling from
Fredonia New York
Radiolab was created by
Jad abumrad
And it's produced by Sauron
Dylan Keith is our director sound
Maria Montessori Padilla
Is our managing director
Our staff includes Simon Adler
Maggie bartolomeo Becca breast
Rachel Cusick
David Gamble
Bethel hockey
Tracy hunt
Matt Kelty
Robert krulwich
Anemic
Lots of knots
Melissa O'Donnell
Arianne wack Pat Walters
Add Molle webbing
With help from Amanda or on check
Shima Oleo
NJ Carlo
Carfax
Michelle Harris