Quick note 4 restart this episode
Contains graphic language
And I just ripped
Pictures of sexual situations may not be suitable for all this
Are you awake
Listening to Radiolab
Radiolab WNYC
This is Radiolab and this is the third and final part of our Series in the know
About sex and consent
We started couple weeks ago
With some excerpts from a podcast called the heart
Chris by Kaitlin Prest and then last week had a
Long
At times difficult conversation with education consultant Hannah Scotland
Heard it from some college-aged men in that episode today
Yeah yeah
Have you anyone make up their shoes get comfortable
We're going to start with some college-age women need to stretch you can like be like hey it's been too long like
We can do yoga
No
Cuz we ended up doing
Zirmed
Sway through the process of
Was gathering together a whole bunch of different groups of men and women college-age men and women
Three different cities
I just asking him general questions about
How they're thinking about
Are you excited
I ended up interviewing the man song I'll turn this part over to Becca wrestler and she boldly
How are you were with women
Yes so the average group that we talked to was maybe a dozen women we try to make it as diverse as possible
You got coming
Why did it have
The first thing that really struck us I think she would tell me if you agree is there was sort of a disconnect
On the one hand it seems like affirmative consent for almost everyone we talked to seem
Like second nature
So I sent for high schoolers I'm going to even teaching classes on it
Yeah okay so you know like ch
So like a clear and concise yes at every step of sexual activity
I think that's like amazing that works
Teaching kids. Now and like I do feel like it's my Generations
Problem 2
Change it
And change the narrative about it
So a lot of them were really committed to actually changing the way consent
What's the way that these sexual experiences go and how their navigate it but then when we would
You know focusing on
What we were actually experiencing in their lives
What we saw was much different
My friend and I ended up in a bar like the bartender I was really
Lacuna really flirting and he like
I don't want to give any identifying information but we are just Levi bang and I like
What's up with him and then like immediately after I started hooking up with him I was like oh this is not what I want but like at that point of kind of like
Signal would be like much more of an uncomfortable situation and just like going through with this and like
Understanding I've already regretted kind of don't know why I didn't leave but eventually I was just fine
Like whatever they please we come on please
But you know you're turned on a little bit like and I'll be like fine whatever like looks
Pilot asked me if I wanted sex when I said no
I'm actually like I just like kind of wanted to be like over with like the entire interaction and I was just uncomfortable
And I was like okay like let's have sex
Just because I thought that like that was the easier way to like
Make him happy make like get done with it and then like
It'd be over
We just heard a lot of stories
People having sex that they didn't want to have you know
Where maybe affirmative consent was in effect they did say yes
But it was either because the guy wear them down or they were way too concerned with how he was feeling
Like it would make him feel really really bad
I know that like
If you would have known how I felt that way he would have gone through with it
And like I just didn't want to like hurt his feelings and be like and make him feel like he like took advantage of me or whatever when I knew
That there would be no possible way that he would know that I was feeling that way some women told us that they say yes sometimes when they don't want to
Because
They're scared heart of the sphere in
Sing hard no is the. Hard no can then be violated and that's like
That's like a terrifying thought like
To say like a hard no
But that's more traumatizing to me like in my head almost been having like a soft no just sort of like
Sweat past
Having fear of future trauma
It's like having a fear of future trauma
You got to mean if your aim is to stay in control
And you feel like you might be out of control
Then the best way to still be in control is to convince yourself that you are cool with what's going on
I walked away
Feeling like
Many of the young women felt
Frustrated both with
Their worlds but also with themselves
Yeah afterwards I would feel like
Very disappointed in myself
Cuz I feel like
How to compromise my own needs for other p
People that they would walk away from the situation and they would have
Regretted
Wednesday maybe didn't actually want to do it but didn't
Pick up for themselves and then I
And then you fight like a battle with yourself cuz it's like wait a minute like I'm like strong like I know I can like
Just stopped are like white but it's
So hard I could like
In that moment to find like
I don't know like the
The words just to say it you know cuz then it is sometimes you just like yeah it is just easier just to be like let it
Like
Just like let him finish that's it like it was clear for
Most of these women that in the moment of these encounters
There was some conversation that needed to happen that was not happening
But then it there actually was this one young woman that we spoke to some people
I think a lot of people talk about consent as if it's like awkward and weird and like
She just said consent has really become
Popularizing is really
Well advocated for by the BDSM community
Play something abbreviation abbreviations bondage discipline or domination sadism and masochism
Because you constantly have to make sure that somebody is okay and be like this is broke
Some Community has this figured out and then she started talking about her experience
Does that mean that abuse and community health
Figured that out
Hello
Oh yeah
It's like that B-52 bomber Buzz
Hope that sounds better
Okay High did it we did it
Did you feel like I always feel like after these technical snafus there's like a bonding that happens to it actually bought it two guys
Well I thought it was true thing that people suffering together feel bonded
One another
Well there you go
Who are you by the way
What are you doing
My name is Julie Finnell I am an associate
Professor of Sociology at gallaudet University and I've been studying the BDSM community
Since about
2012 we called Julie because she is one of the things stick to say leading academics
When it comes to a BDSM community
And all the subcultures she has written
Papers she has done surveys
And she has done from the inside
Like me pretty much feel like we were sort of Born This Way
And it's really common to talk to a lot of kinky people who will tell you the same thing like
I was five and fantasizing about tying up people genitalia
Antioch
One of the things we heard from Julie
And we subsequently her this
Also from a lot of academics we talked to after
Is it the whole consent conversation
In many ways
Grew out of BDSM a lot of people trace like the history of BDSM in the United States
To the Leatherman community
This is World War 2 era by the way
These gay men would hang out in biker clubs
Bars
They would socialized they were really tight-knit Brotherhood over the Decades of Brotherhood grew into this much
Bigger community
And then it really
Loaded in the 80s
But
There's a problem
At the time
No one had ever really formally distinguish between
BDSM a package between willing participants
And violin
BDSM community that they were not insane
Let's go we're not getting off on hurting
Roll and Bowl playing on
Power this is Joe cashell he's in Sochi
Professor women's gender & sexuality studies at Yale
Slogans to convince
Non kinky ball that what they were doing was not violent or from
Volkswagen that came up with
Encinitas was safe
Sane and consensual and
It really stuck
Today you can find it on
T-shirt if any of any BDSM Community event or play Party parties that are organ
Nised at
Formal spaces
They're called dungeon
So getting back to Julie we asked her okay if it is true as that one woman said that the BDSM community
If it is true that they have figured something out
I had to do a better it will what is it
Panda
Show us a couple things first
Drinking to my way of thinking of incredibly risky very frowned upon in the BDSM world
That's what we call Edge player just like kind of the things that people do or you're like
Like a bad idea negotiating sex when both people are really really drunk with somebody that you never met before
I just really really risky
And speaking of that negotiation another thing that was an interesting contrast
Between the
Quote vanilla World in BDSM is that
When two people are negotiating
Trying to figure out if they're going to get down
BDSM
That conversation is formalized and it's often public generally speaking most of what's happening is is out in the open
Did you have people called
Consent monitor is it sometimes roam around these parties
Uncommon to be standing there negotiating with someone where your friend or their friends right next to them
Laundering mixing safe
I'll ask her to zoom in on a specific
Content cop
How does it usually go
People with different experiences levels are better and worse
Pacifically like let's say I was going to play with you
Great Lakes
You're telling me you've never done anything like this
Write 0
Z-Ro so I like the knife top
Which is a way of
Describing the fact that I like to do things with knives onto people
Actual cutting a people or or Alexa threatening event or no
Dragon knives along people
Is threatening with somebody like
Playing with my Pinterest the thing I do to make it more interesting as I liked
Pick up people's clothes off
Okay
How to cut people
Are they are they like serrated
And it can be some of them have rough edges and some of them
Don't and that's actually one of the questions that I would ask you
I would ask you if you
You maybe would be more interested in front of a poking type sensation or more of a
Scraping tight sensation based on just hearing that
I would select my knives accordingly that point cuz I separate knives for the president
And then I would
If I was going to cut your clothes off for example
I would ask you I would I would let you know
That there's
I'm pretty good at what I do but there's no way that I can guarantee you that
I won't cut something that you don't want me to so if possible it'd be great if you could take off
The thing that you wouldn't want me to cut right like a necklace or your socks or whatever
Okay and I also like when people going into my garden pretty experience of this but I definitely have accidentally cut people before so
So
You know I just need to let you know that
This is not a 100% guarantee of our
Is that
Something that you absolutely cannot tolerate then
Then we probably can't go forward with this or if you say
Oh yeah I'm fine with it as long as it isn't on my arm cuz I don't want to show up for work that's a great like we'll all just rest
Stretch what I do to not your arms
She said sometimes she'll even get a pen and make it
Tiny little.
On all of the places the person
Says are off-limits
Just so you can be super duper sure she's respecting their wishes
They're actually
Hello everyone
Well-organized BDSM scenes in the country
The guys are allowed to talk you believe me I know we have mites around at least month
Sleep classes
And we actually went to one how many people here have taken any of my vents before
Macy's vans
Arioso Vanoss's new
Who's in Manhattan a small Studio space about 15 people were there and the instructor a guy named David
Eros was
Start at the front of the room
In a leather Kilt
These two leather straps across the chest now is everyone here familiar with consent
Bass
All right good
Does anyone know the difference between consent and enthusiastic consent
One guy in back brace and a sort of a new thing I started coming up in a lot of Clubs
If there's a moment of hesitation in that person's brain
You should automatically be picking that up in Black
Do you actually want to do this thing with me
Generally within the first 10 seconds someone
They won't have sex with you
You're not going to convince someone otherwise younger but I'm going to wear them down
We're not technically pisses me off at a party nobody owes you anything
Everyone on board so far
Menards
Chemistry the hell all of this works in Action a first look at the table
He took everyone over to this table show them the toys
Different kinds of whips
Floggers
We'll stick with the feather on the Enneagram
And then he and a woman named Bella
Who is in Black lingerie they walk over to the
Giant
Cross looking thing in the corner of the room
She then leaves against it
So I currently have Bella with arms spread on st. Andrew's cross
Alexa is not that tall
Now we already had our talk
Hey what school I just met you
Am I allowed to put my hand in your ass
Shoulders your skin
Do you want to keep you close as is late or do you want to sort of slowly chondritis
As we play
Get all your things because you don't know where they're at
They can tell you just want to be like this Bella has told me she does not want take anymore clothes off correct Bella
LLC has make a huge amount of pain so then we go with that Illinois
You want to warm them up
Don't go to the gym do you have your set right away
Breakfast
You going to start of warm up the muscles I do light touching like hitting
Start slowly whipping your shoulders
I'm sorry I'm just observing waiting for their bodies or the tell me some notes when I do impact
Their bodies might tell me something
A little heavy
Is little bit of a startling in
So you two have scroll in
If the ass comes right back out right away that's saying
Daddy hit me again
If this stays turtle in I've went a little hard I can come in and stay and again you're talking to me
Be sexy
That's too much for you baby
Zack needs to go lighter
Keep it sexy you don't have to say
Hey was that too hard you can tell they keep it in very sexy and see how it goes
Staying engaged
Is very important
You're in a space that's loud you can't f****** hear anything cuz I can't hear if she's moaning
I want to be able to get my ears in clothes say how they do
Then I tried to sort of cadence
Play around a little bit more
If I'm there I'm combining between using impact play and since play will go a little more in-depth once you guys are playing
A little bit
Elder on the room
Domino's spent the next hour sort of moving around the room
Helping people if they paired off with their whips their floggers
Learn how to better read each other
And for a moment it felt like
Oh
We should all be doing
Maybe not
Using whips and having sex in
Public
Nothing but finding ways to help each other be explicit
Communicative and
Have a code
For what words mean
When we talk to college-age Men Women a lot of them were like we need a script we need something written down
Because one of the things that's been found in surveys
Is it there's very little agreed-upon language for example of phrase like slow down when surveyed
Many college-aged women will tell you that means stop
Many men will say
Don't we just beats ghosts
Slower
Well in the BDSM world
They seem to have started some of the South
House rules say yellow men's
Check-in or pause
Red beans
Stop
And if somebody says safe word that means that
You're calling for help from one of the people that surround
It all seems so clear and sensible
And dare I say uncomplicated but Julie was like
Let me come back Julie rains
On
The parade
We were throwing
This is Kali calling from San Francisco Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan
Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world more information about
Sloan
At www.slha.org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
And I request for those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents
Aunts and uncles teachers
We're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments
Williams
Basically I want to hear about this
Did you know did something
It just means you lean back and say
Wow
How do they do that
Maybe it was the moment that our kids you've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lesson
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the musical score
Or maybe the kitchen mat
Music in the margin of their geometry
We're interested in the
Specific moments where
Kid does something super smart
It doesn't have anything to do with the test
If you have a story
Go to radiolab.org brilliance
Record short audio message
And that's where you live. Org / brilliance
Thank you so much
A Time Jaguar back
37 the know and
Julie was about to tell us Julie canal
That
Even in the BDSM world it's very clear rules and safe words like red and yellow
Things go wrong a real problem with that yellow red situation is that in public people almost never end up using
Red Liquors
What are the huge problems with the DSM subculture basically has is that
There's Mastiff
Massive social repercussions to calling read in a public place
Musically
Can we talk about this more
Started to sound a lot like what we
Heard from the college-aged women
Cat saying no
Even when it's much worse by all of these rules and norms
He still be really hard
There's a cost
Are the worst situations that I ever personally found myself
Was Iowa
Girls tied up and suspended
And
So all of my feet are off the ground and I'm having a great time
I had negotiated ahead of time that there was to be
Nothing genital happen is very clear about that I was like nope
There's not there's not a thing
Then she says the person who she was playing with the tire up
Decided to try some genitals
Stuff and
I was really caught in that moment
Turn a very public place
I could yell red
But in that place
Yelling red means the whole scene has
Stop and I didn't want to seem to stop by like being tied up and I'm also cognizant of the fact that
This guy is my friend I really like him
Aaron's
I don't want him to get in a ton of trouble
What if I yell red really loudly in this public place
Pretty decent chance he's going to get banned from the event
It's pretty decent chance
You can get banned from
A lot of events
Look at them in the face
He stopped
Cuz I was going to say you're tied up. That's very
The whole point is you're in a compromised situation
Even though she navigated that one fine in the end she says General Lee
Speaking the BDSM Community is
Negotiation not
A Utopia
In fact what she experienced in that moment
Was for a long time
Not uncommon
So I should explain that the scene actually got its own me-too movement about three months before the me-too movement hit like I didn't have that #b
Exactly the same thing happened where
Bunch of high status people got out of
The consent violators on the scene
These are bunch of dudes or
Yeah they're all men
Definitely what I can sit violations that happened with women but people don't pay attention Sarah and I have a whole other rant about that but
A lot of attention on them where men and
Pretty much everyone that they had hurt with women
And that's part of the reason that Juliet is
Any other little suspicious
Of all of the rules that we were just
Enamored of
Or I should say she's a little suspicious
Placing too much faith in those
It's not
About foolproof rightly so I may I definitely know people who
They don't want to tell you anymore that they're not having fun
So there's a real sense of like I don't want to disappoint this other person
It's the one of the things that I also will ask any types of negotiating my version of negotiation is like
You feel reasonably certain that
Will be able to tell me
If you don't like what happened
The more I
Thought about
That question
I got to read an interview tomorrow I have certain noodling on that at the creek me like what that's
A key question
Can you say no when you need to
To some of us just a people pleaser
I am one of those people
Hertz
Tuseno
Fino's coupon someone out
Others have no problem with that
So she asks which kind of person are you right now it is situational who are you at this moment if they say yeah right now I'm not
Good with a nose and she goes One Direction if they say no I can tell you that I'm like alright can we both agree that we are
Adults
That we don't have to get into all the stuff about what we don't want to have her
And that we will take responsibility for
Actually communicating how we're feeling in the situation and if we fail to communicate that
That we will also take responsibility for that
So are you okay with kind of whatever and you're going to tell me if you're not in the other person goes yeah
That's how I want that
Stop playing our conversation changes from what am I not allowed to do to what do you find hot
What is things that we kept running into
Again and again
Was
This sentiment
That was maybe best captured by a guy that Becca and she missed
Michael lissack I'm the director of empowering victims
And I'm one of the people who came up with the concept for the week
Concentra
That app
Was actually the one that a guy last episode
Search jokingly referred to hello would you
B
Can I record you on my cell phone if you saying you're down to make out right now
Turns out it's actually real.
Did this guy made
There's no really good the problem is that we've got a meme in the meme is already well established
Unfortunately
That means
Frames the entire question the wrong way
Sent means but you giving someone permission to do something to you
We don't
To sex to someone else
We have sex
With
Someone else
Are you saying that that's the like dictionary definition of
Can send it interesting cuz I'm curious if this is just like
Aston Manor
Is giving someone permission to do something to you or on your behalf
Yeah I just looked it up and you're
Compliance in or approval of what is done or proposed by another
And Joe for Shell the academic that we heard from earlier
Capture
Greece
Which is all of the sex was consensual but unhappy and unpleasant than unwanted
People typically women
Indoor
Curry shoes
May not be non-compete
Batman or leveraging definition to power
Extract sex for women that don't want to be there
Did you call at 9
I was a second day I went home with him and I wasn't really sure if I wanted to sleep with him and I was kind of going through the motions
And at one point he pulled away guess you could tell that I was like
Not entirely there and he's like you want to have sex
Say yes or no and he just stopped
Entirely and we just like
And I remember being like
Like relieved first and
Like really
Surprised because he read my part like second date like read my body language respected me and like
Didn't push
I was at a bar
And
As of this girl
And here she was
We're about the owner was pretty drunk
She was like yeah hey you want to go
I like
I'm drunk you're drunk
Should I
You're right and just kind of weird that we can see like dance I was fine once we have
Finite and then like I woke up the next morning and she texted me and was like
Hey thank you so much
Like
Not taking advantage of
Me like that means a lot
I was like that that was really
I've been lucky in that regard that like
If I'm uncomfortable having sex with like my partner like
Like right when I'm about to be like I can't like I don't want to do this right now she
Always catches like my eyes like
Like he'll stop immediately and in like
You know I've had like my own sex
Yes, stop and he like I'm going to cry
But like he will stop
It's so nice to have a
The partner that can like read your body language and be like this doesn't feel like
Feel-Rite
Are you okay
This episode was reported by Becky Bressler and she Malawi
Produced by Bethel hobday
Very special thanks to Katelyn Crest and the team she worked with at the hearts produce that series inspired this whole thing for us
To all the men and women who share their stories with us
Thanks to Humana Prieto royval check Samantha Shahi lady Goodwill Don black Margo Weiss Dominus Arrow
Vegas Paradise
Jad abumrad
Thanks for listening
To play the message press to start of message
Created by God abumrad and is produced by Soren wheeler
Dylan Keith is a director of sound design
Maria Montessori Padilla is our managing director
Assassin Clues
Simon Adler dr. Bressler Rachel acoustic David Gable
Bethel hoptak
Tracy Winkler
Matt kielty
Robert krulwich Annie McEwen
Melissa O'Donnell
Aryan whack
Pet walkers
Emily Webster
With help from FEMA
Catch La slow
Animo I said yelmo
Assata Shakur is Michelle Harris
And this message