Are you awake
Radio WNYC
Hey I'm Jared Radiolab
So
We got an email from you
You can head
Not long ago our editor and we learned i weekly got into a conversation with this woman
Her name is Janelle Jenny I like the Packers
I guess photographers would technically be my job but I do a whole lot of different things
None of which really pertain to the story at hand
And our story really starts when Janelle sent an email to the Radiolab inbox basically saying I need your help
Yeah
Something that happened to her
That was a wondrous
An unexplainable
And very
Weird
And as a result Janelle had found herself stuck
In
Story
A story told a hundreds of thousands of people all across the country a story that's its rights
Smack dab in the middle of one of the biggest cultural divides in our country right now
It was a story that wasn't hers
She wanted us to help her find a way to finally tell her story
Do you want me to kind of just
Sure well
When I was 18
I went to a concert
A rock concert he has actually is at Warped Tour
Looks like a festival of rock concert
Tons of bands on different stages all over the place
And Janelle is walking around between all the different stages in merchandising tables when she sees
This
10 by 10 white tent with just a little cable insurance
Table with a sign on it that says sign up to be on the registry sav-a-life something like that
So this was rock music and good deeds
Ride together especially right was just a pretty good mix in hindsight
Soap Janelle read the sign and she thought to herself out sign up
Why don't ya
Did you knew what did you know what bone marrow was
Yeah yeah I mean that would mean that they take a really long needle and stick it in you
Second bun stuff I suppose at that point that was probably not the for thoughts and I think the altruist
Thick like do something
Yeah that was probably the main motivation
10th was sign some papers in the swapper cheat because
With a bone marrow donation they actually have to figure out if your a genetic match with someone who would receive the donation
Which is part of what Janelle's that was cool about some I always thought that you would just be an amazing opportunity to
Be the one person who could do something
For somebody that like literally no one else in the world could
What's a deep connection with someone that I don't know if either of you are only children by
Yeah it you know how they're just like
You have cousins are not friends but at some point there's not that
It sounds so stupid that biological connection like besides my parents are
When I look at you you missed
The
Idea of someone who was
Muchly like you and muchly in your world and muchly
Even the kind of the need like somebody out there dependent on me on kind of that almost other
The worldly level
Seokjin L swab your cheek sign the paper and then went about her normal life and then about 6 months
Later she got a call
Yeah it was a phone call to my landline
That's a long-ass
So what are you doing here
Alex knost 2009
Okay
It was a phone call and I remember very specifically it was a voicemail
Because I hadn't had the chance to answer it and they said something to the extent of
Your high from the national bone marrow donor registry
We've done some tests and we
Nailed you down to be a preliminary match for a patient so we need you to come in and do some further tests that in
The blood and stuff
Oh no I forgot that I did that or are you thinking oh boy or what were you I was so overcome
With emotion I remember just just
To think
There's somebody there's somebody out there that might be my
Person
Awesome absolutely no hesitation am I in
So
Janelle heads in the clinic because well
Bone marrow the stuff in the core of your bones actually produces all your blood cells and in
Importantly including your white blood cells which are a key part of your immune system
So you doing
With a bone marrow transplant is taking a healthy immune system out of one person and putting into another person who is
System is
Cancer or messed up in some kind of way he is owed because the immune system is that part of you that
Like recognizes you from not you and attacks anything that's not you
You have to like fool a new body into thinking that this immune system is down
To the parts of your DNA that have to do with your immune system couple key parts of that have to match with the door
So that's what they're doing but you know they're taking her into like test your DNA to see if the stuff that marks out her and
Matches closely enough
But this you know recipient so that the bone marrow transplant will work
Maybe a months later
I get another call and this one I was able to answer and they say
Well
We've done tests and you are the ideal person in this 8 million person registry
To donate for this patient
You are a perfect match
And
Will you do it
Sounds like
Absolutely
So you like the call of Destiny like a Maybe Maybe This was meant to be
Yeah
There's something I feel that's like bigger than myself
It's happening and I don't
Really I mean I can't really explain it yet at that point
But I know there's like
Okay here's if there's a big thing
So I go in
Unfortunately to disappoint you Robert the way that I donated bone marrow wasn't the actually
The real
Bad way with the big needles
Let me come up with a small meat lovers
You and this is actually the four more common way of doing it now is
Inject you with all these drugs
And it is like eight injections that
Boost your white blood cell count up to astronomical Heights
And you know like when you get sick when your immune system kicks in overdrive and you feel sick imagine that like 8 time
Friends over every bone hurt
And while Janelle is feeling achy and sick inside of her her bone marrow is pumping out a bunch of new baby
Blood cells
Unmatured stem cells
That can really become
Almost anything
Let me just go in and grab those cell
Harvest you I guess
Do you have a needle in both arms and you pretty much sat still for 6 hours
Phillies suck all your blood out of your body
Put in a machine and give you back what they don't need
So I think they've got about
You're one of those little IV bags
Just a quart size plastic bag
My
And once you're done to put some Band-Aids on your like all right
Let us know if you need anything
And do you know anything about like what happens to your blood cells like who gets it or what
Registry is very very strict about
Patient confidentiality but
They did tell me that it was
A 29 year old man with
Acute lymphoblastic leukemia
And that's literally that's all I knew for a whole year
Endless Google searches of
29 year old man
Acute lymphoblastic leukemia
Animated find anything's course
But once that year is up if both parties agree
Then we can talk
And that's that's kind of really interesting because
I definitely was looking forward to that your mark but once that hit
I kind of got
Cold feet
A really
Just
Wasn't ready
To know exactly who he was and then I was also worried that maybe this guy is like a real
Piece of crap like maybe he's a
Clan member criminal or something so there's a part of that too
Open up the Sentinel formerly ill person robs three banks in hits old lady
Yes man saved by Janelle James it's so stupid
I thought that
So I did end up eventually sending
This email and whatnot in
I think about October
They took them a couple weeks
To actually give
Mindful to my patient and vice versa
I was eating lunch with a friend of mine
And I remember having chips and guacamole
By the way my medications name is Jim
So they gave
Jim my info off my pocket there was an email in my inbox
End
There was a
Scan PDF attached to this email to open it up and
Xi'an
Fill this out with their own hand
And I just broke
I totally got his web like a little baby and I
The booth at a Mexican restaurant Grapevine Texas
And I got on Facebook
I saw a picture of some picture of her and as I
Oh my gosh. It's got to be her an email
Facebook
Friend request
From
Said the sky name Jim Monroe
In Texas
And
I was like okay I don't know anybody in Texas and then
It clicked off on
This
This is the guy this is him I can see his picture I can look in
What does he look like
Not very much like me
Yeah
Tall for a blunder hair
It's time right now but I've liked strawberry blonde hair blonde hair blue-eyed white guy
I'm very handsome
What are you by the short blonde hair
You lied so I guess
Yeah if we could be cousins I think
And guess what I look at all these pictures it's
His wife was a model and these
Kids are so adorable and try to find as much as I can
As far as his
Profession I was like oh he appears to be some sort of magician
So I guess we'll talk about that later
So
I don't even know like I guess
Why don't we just plan on like where you're from where you were raised
Showcase to that way
So I was
Born in Orange County California
Fullerton California I went to school in Anaheim High School in Anaheim was a baseball player
So I ended up going I was very very good baseball player I got drafted by the at the time they're called
The Tampa Bay Devil Rays now they're just the Tampa Bay Rays OU would that good
Yeah. Turn down a professional baseball contract to go play at the University of Texas in Austin
What did you play
I was a picture
Cuz I was a hard-throwing
Right-hander
And ended up getting
Like I said drafted and went to the University of Texas to play baseball that's what I thought was going to be at those going to be professional baseball player
My my sophomore year college I blew out my shoulder I had a surgery my freshman year and then came back and was throwing harder
Remember then did it again
So baseball was kind of over
Uber like 19 like that's
Noticer yeah it was a pretty it was a big Kick In The Head
But he finished up school that maintain my scholarship as a medical Redshirt majored in business and psychology
Then moved at the Boulder Colorado a got married and had a couple kids
One of my really good friends during this time was his name was Tennyson and became my best friend's he was he
It was just my best friend is like my brother he was nasty too so he's a former college football player
And peed also lost his football career based on injury
And then also knew Magic
An illusion
And Magic was actually something that Jim had been fascinated by ever since he was a kid
Yeah I saw trade show magician when I was
1011 it was at the Anaheim Convention Center of all places in an Optometric convention with my parents are, Tristan
Things to do in trade show stuff at a booth
Do you know what he was doing
He did a version of this
Call cards across he made a cigarette. She pulled out of your head or out of somebody
Casually holding his hand and was holding a zigzag in the tips of his fingers and he goes delighted
The puff of smoke and there's a there's a real cigarette
I thought you had at that moment was
I want to do that
It was how did he do that and that is cool and
You know I'm going to go learn how that's done so I just begin to
Look at card tricks and read books on all hell all the stuff was done to figure out how it's done
So when you met Tennyson you know they started practicing together in and doing shows
In front of friends and family
And pretty soon enough we start doing gigs
They started doing these shows at like schools and festivals and stuff and they would do these tricks
Like a lot of
Card tricks
Number tricks to say
Pick a random number and it went end up it was written on a piece of paper in the shoe of Nadia's number
Something like that
But then
The show would turn into something else
Because
The thing is
Tennyson
Believer
Overwhelmingly so
Believer like in God
Yeah Christian
Tennyson was
Very
Commenced
Until after an hour or so of magic tricks
Just pure entertainment Tennyson would say to the crowd
This is been great we're going to take a quick break
I'm going to give you guys a chance to take off
Cuz during the second part of the show we're going to talk about what the Christian perspective is and why we believe
Christian thing
If you want to stick around great if you don't take off
No gym says during this part of the show missing and particularly was way more of the Evangelistic piece of this
And
I consider myself more of a producer
Now Jim actually grown up going to church
Yes I was my parents went to Lutheran Church I was
That was my doing that
Pittsburgh Steelers
Yeah you know
At the end of the day it's just there was nothing in it
That's up
Seem to be
Satisfying
So at this point in the show Jim Wood
Stand back
As Tennyson talked about how
Magic is actually all about the eye
Seeing behind the veil of reality there's
God
Watching over us
And Jim said he would
Standing there on stage
Watching these people in the audience
We're feeling this real connection with God
However I wasn't having that experience
Like I don't feel what they're feeling and he started singing to himself I didn't want to be the guy that's a while I'm a Christian because my
My friends were or
I'm a Christian cuz I was raised that way
I want it to be true
He just wasn't sure that it was
Right
And after he in Tennyson and been doing this show for
Year-and-a-half or so
Jim got a call
Anderson had been out hiking in the mountains
Just outside of Boulder and he was found
In a river
His body was
Partially submerged
Just at the edge of the water
At the base of a 40-foot cliff
Peaceful Valley
Is always calling
No one really knows how he passed
Looks like you might have actually fallen from the cliff
The police.
Maybe suicide but it could be
You know exposure to the elements
I kind of thing
Yeah Jim says he was just
Devastated now he's probably the closest male friend I've ever had just felt like he was
In the bottom of a hole
Yeah
Bottom of a hole
Figuring it out
Best friend passes away my wife and I as a result
I kind of got into this really strange season where are you know I'm depressed she's depressed
Pretty much on the verge of
Calling it Quits and then my leg starts hurting
Really badly
Where in the leg
Underneath my right knee
Jim says he started popping Advil everyday
And more and more
And I'm trying to get it out
Then he came home one day and he says it's the pain was so bad he couldn't even get out of his car and so his wife was like look
We're going to the hospital now
I'm sitting there and in an emergency room in this man walks into my room he looks me says
You have cancer
Jim had leukemia which is on cancer of the blood cells to the white blood cells inside of your bone marrow have literally
Exploded out of control and the reason why your leg hurts so bad is cuz your your bone is breaking on its own
From the inside
Wow and he said that if you don't do anything you're going to die in 2 months
Just before Christmas of 2008
Jim checks into the hospital
Right away they do two things
When they put gym on the bone marrow registry in the hopes that he can find a donor
To just to keep him alive while he waits
They start putting him through round after round
Chemo and get this wicked concoction of stuff and then be let out loses his hair
His body starts
Fall Apart
And all you can do at that point is just
Hope
Like tick
Coptic
Tik Tok Tik Tok yum
That's when you think you know what you believed to be true
How is in Kai's University
That's when you find out so for me it was not
It was not
A Christian worldview
There is an all-loving omnipotent
Powerful being that
Makes the universe go round then why would things like
You know suicide or
Murder or rape exist in it and
Goodness constructed world of his
Jim just couldn't get himself to believe in the existence of God like that or
Really any guy
Now it wasn't any Rhyme or Reason or purpose is just this is this is my lot
This really sucks
And then when he was
That is
Lowest point
Remember driving back to Houston Texas from or chemo and my phone rang and I didn't recognize the number and
I said hello in this woman on the other line
She said
There's a one-person
That we've been able to identify on the planet
Out of all the databases everything there's one you are
The ideal person in this 8 million person registry
To donate for this patient
Think about that
Is in the world you are
A perfect match
Will you do it
Feels like
Absolutely
My wife and I were in the car together and it was just tears
You know
Wow
Amazing
So April
20th
And this is
Important to remember
April 20th was when
I donated
And if they're pulling
The cells are Janelle's body up in Wisconsin
Full
My
Himself
Denton Texas gyms doctors were telling him
Your bone marrow transplant is scheduled for April 23rd on April 23rd the nurses they come inside of your room to celebrate your set
Second birth
And then I remember Dr draw tell me are you ready to put your boxing gloves on when he was preparing me for was
A death
Come to find out later on they pulled my wife
Out of my room and it said we're going to give this to end with all this medication
He could potentially receive this and reject this violently and passed away
Just remember they're essentially replacing Jim's immune system with somebody else's in this case Janelle's
And in a very real way the replacing that part of Jim that determines who he is
Would someone who he clearly isn't
And Southern
A real chance that the body will just
Short Circuit
So
Forgiveness drug the nurses nickname shake and bake
Designed to basically wipe out whatever is left
Jem's immune system his white blood cells
What inside of your RV
Your body just starts convulsing and then they put Janelle sells
And they monitored me and over the next couple weeks to know cells enter Jim's Body to get into his bone marrow and they start Ford
Reducing new white blood cells producing a whole new immune system
And eventually
Jim is cancer free
I mean it
It's literally like
New Life
You know
Now I will say this
Some Bells kind of began to go off of my a little bit
Jim says before he even got the transplant his Doctorate come into his room and told him you're going to be like a baby in
Inside your mother's womb literally being born again
Because on April 23rd and once again this is their terminology
Or someone else that's going to be living on the inside of you
And this new system of blood is going to
Be your life
Why is that interesting
You know
April 23rd my new birthday is April 23rd my old birthday is April 20th
I my new birthday is on April 23rd
That's on the third day and on the third day is significant because of the
Google Echo
A Biblical Echo
Young
I came back from
Whatever I was in
Because of the only blood implant that could save me of my disease
Soto does this land on you the way it sounds to me like it lands on you now
Or did you go through Omegle like what happened
Those words
Yeah those words
I'm particularly Bells went off in my head is that right is that mean that you know
Suddenly
Believe in God
Again or
The first time
I mean I
It's process right you follow
And then I think
Puzzle pieces are kind of all swirling and coming together
Albert
Everything changed on that demarcating day April 23rd all things
Obviously
Did you know and
Not long after they got each other's information and saw each other on Facebook they hopped on a
My phone call
So she gets on and I get on
But it's all kind of like
Hey oh my gosh is crazy I cannot believe this is nuts yeah this is so crazy in
And then she drops this on me
She said I went and got a tattoo
Of a jigsaw puzzle piece
On the very spot where they stuck that IV in my arm to pull out the new blood knowing
I was the missing piece in someone else's life and without me that person wouldn't be alive
And I said you I was like what I was attempting to have a ton of tattoos
She said no I have one
Did you know what Christians believe to be true right
Is it their savior rolled-up
And show them the very spot on his body
Where blood came out
So that they would believe
So you're just going down this I really your you just you're driving like at a hundred miles an hour.
This
For me it was like I was being introduced to a person
There is an experiential understanding
Of
That which was going on behind the scenes of this existence that was
Answer my prayer
The prayers for is the pair is called are you there
Yep. Are you there God
Basically Jim sajan on her donation to him as almost
More than just allegory is like something close to a literal proof of the existence of God like a very real very
Present
I told her to
I told her that we need to meet I said can I please bring out the Dallas Texas said I have to bring you to Texas
Which is my nightmare
But absolutely I thought I wanted to go right into it
Super excited so guess I flew her
To Dallas Texas I actually recorded it
Let's go save my life
In the video you see gym sort of
Standing at the bottom of the escalator in
Dallas-Fort Worth
Airport he's looking pretty thin and pale and
Nervous
The camera turns
There's Janelle
Coming down the escalator
Andy hug
Names kids come up
And eventually his wife
Okay so so so now you go home
Wright & Phillips
In a very big house
Outside of Dallas
They had dinner with the family and then you know once everybody else
What kind of heading off to bed
Jim and Janelle StarTalk
And.
I think if I remember correctly we
The just outside by the pool and
Stalking
Figuring out
Who each other was
Feels like so you know magician
What is that Intel
He started telling me about what kind of magician he really is and he is
A
Christian
Magician
Oh my gosh I just saved a Christian magician from Texas
This is life
Jokes on me and that wonderful you know
When we come back Janelle becomes Jim's
Greatest magic trick so don't go away
Drew Doughty from Daphne Alabama Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan foundation and
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world formation about Sloan at Double
BWW. Org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help this summer I'm hosting
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
About what we're calling
Brilliance basically I want to hear about those times when I kid you know did something
It just means you lean back and say whoa how did they do that maybe it was the moment that a kid
Did you been reading to 4 month started reading back
To you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons and you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed are ready music in the margin of their geometry homework were interested in
Epic moments where a kid does something super smart but it doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story please share it with us
Go to radiolab.org brilliance
Record short audio message for us
Again that's radiolab.org / brilliance
Thank you so much
Okay we're back I'm Jared I'm Robert krulwich this is Radiolab let's return to
Wheeler sister and you left us in the backyard they're about to talk right
Yep sitting in Jim's backyard by the pool and he's basically telling her his whole story about
Is Joe diblasi
Faith and the cancer and how she saved his life
And then he tells her that right after she saved him
He started doing the magic show again
That show that I used to do with tennis in the show is called the maze
This is the maze
So we actually got to see Jim show and I have to say
He's a pro it's
It's an impressive production he gets big venues
Usually thousand people are so there's crazy laser light show stuff
And he does he's really
Complicated illusions that are sort of Half Penny teller have David Blaine
Simple picking a random phone number out of the phone book ends up being someone in the audience
And then they're going to end up like hidden somewhere like that
And
Very good
So Jim is telling Janelle about all these tricks
But then he says second half of the show
Is about
Explains the magic show at this point ends
Tell people they can leave if they want to
He start to talk
Openly
Especially to the audience
Where I quickly found out that I had
Answer
In Barrie
Personal terms about what
Happened to him
Raced down to MD Anderson Cancer Center
Good afternoon
Open the kimono strategy Cannon
He's in the hospital
My maths
Throwing up into a bucket
And he's
Huge circles under his eyes
And then
He's playing
Right when he was on
The edge of death at his lowest point this
This thing happened
A miracle happen
One person
Just
When his
Blood was literally poisoning his own body
Somebody substituted there blood on his behalf
So he could be
Reborn again
Three days after his birthday
The only Global Atlantic Infinity Lite
So there's a whole three days thing there which is the story of Easter in the rebirth it says
In cases such as
Like definitive proof that there's a God
Either either
Vista tistical number that continues to propagate this false ideology of Supernatural
I like being bitten by shark and struck by lightning at the same time
Or you might have to believe what I believe is true
But that is the result of the girl in the final scene
So yes this is all
Being thrown at me
And is he
Is he saying all this
To you by the pool
Is it all it all comes tumbling out
How are you
Feeling
Inside
Stranger and stranger
Going down the Wormhole because
I am
An atheist
In the sense that
I don't
I don't believe
In the tenets of Christianity I don't believe really in the tenants of any
Established religion I've ever seen
Honestly I just think that once things
Are labeled in your pigeon-holed and the exclusivity of really any religion is
Is the cause for a lot of problems
It's world history
But
Face can be beautiful and there's definitely parts of me and there's moments in my life that
Boy praying and really feeling like that was going out to somebody would feel great
But I just
Can't
They just can't do it
So
At that moment and he's telling me this
And
Yeah and he's like well
You know you're here in Texas for this weekend
And would you be willing
To come on stage for one of my shows
So I can introduce you
And
Of course I said yes
Really
Of course he said yes
Chris
I've always kind of looked at our story as
Something bigger
Then what he believes and what I don't believe it's
Diggers capital B underline bold
It's big
Partly because Jim and every show he has the bone marrow registry people right there
Ready to sign for
Because
Of the show they just
Saw
You can get a hundred
I know that dozens of people have gone on to be matches
So
This was truly the combination of
From
The moment I signed up to be on that registry this
Felt like the Zenith of this entire thing
So last night at Texas Christian University
Packed house
Chanel's in the audience I was in like the front row during the second part of the show when Jim goes through the rebirth
He stops and he says
That's what everyone
A person who saved my life
She's here
He has me walk up on stage
Crowd went wild the first time in my life I got a standing ovation
Haitian
Because you're Jesus that's why the Catholic crazy is because
Yeah
All of these kids in the audience who are all pretty much my age as well
Arsene
My being on stage as
Quite possibly the
Biggest proof they've ever had
There is
Oh God
Will you will you now
Wheat was there any part of you that still I shouldn't be here or you all there
There was
A part of me that felt
A little bit of an imposter
But for now she says that feeling was outweighed
Just by the number of people that were lining up
The bone marrow
Donation table
So the next time she had a chance
She did it again
And again
She's now appeared at the end of the show around a dozen times
All around the country
Playing the role of gems
Personal
Savior
And she says the more time she did it the more that feeling that
Fraud feeling kept
Popping up
Each time a little bit louder
Yeah
There's parts of me there's Little Fibers in my being that are like
While if
If this is a sign if there is a God
I'm a real jerk
This is such
A beautiful and really literal
Story being told me about like hay
You know maybe there is a God
Said she started to feel that like if she's both
Apache wedding vows
Story and misusing it
There's a special place in hell for me
And this is
Why Janelle got in touch with us
Because she wanted us to help her figure out a way to tell a story
Gitlab
Her way of seeing the world
Into the room
Okay are you guys
Is everyone there
I'm here I can hear you guys dinner can hear me
I can
How are you
So I'm pretty sure let's have Nassar actually started talking to Janelle about what exactly she wanted to do and they decided that we
You just all get in the studio gym and her and all of us and see if we could
Okay I just like Janelle do you want to just kind of talk through what
What we've been thinking
Oh sure I can try if you want to
Help me lots of sir
Essentially
Lots of eye and I have been talking about
What would be the best way for me to kind of tell
My side of the story
Yeah my side of our story so to speak without
So much of the religious stuff
Yes so when are you guys going to do that
Maybe I missed the point I'm sorry
So do you say we as in like we are going to do a version of that
Flashlight
Help me
Oh cool well
I have no problem
Yeah cuz you are so not only a magician with magic things but also with words
Haha
So
Maybe if we could
If you could help me
Yeah totally that's that's so interesting my mind begins to spin
And I have it so at first we suggested maybe Janelle come out at the end of one of Jim shows and just read a statement or something and Jim said
That's probably not going to work as you guys know in this world
Mean audiences come based upon how things are marketed and booked and
Jim said you know he has to worry about
Turn up as a business the expectations of a
Sponsors and an even the audience were
We're looking for a certain thing
Producer cuz I'm
So we're like okay fair enough maybe we could be like a
Q&A
After the show
I have to really process it but I'm totally open to it
I would always love to help
Janelle figured I mean help her
Put it all together in like I think
So eventually we landed on a plan gym was going to be doing his show up in St Cloud Minnesota
I and we decided Well we could just
Do a show with him and Janelle the next night
So long with preachers LiftMaster in enemy we headed up to steam Cloud met up with Jenelle and that night we went
Did you all go see gems show
Olympic venue there's probably like
Thousand people there all college students
Intercourse because Janelle was there right after you did the sort of personal Journey back to God
Check this out
She's here tonight a little bit hard to hear but there was literally like
Shutter of energy that went through the crowd at that moment
So yeah like I said
Better speaker than you encourage all of you to
Consider
So Janelle just pointed out that the national bone marrow registry would be there that night and she encouraged everybody to know
Sign up and have a chance to
To Save a Life and do something good
Considerate
Oh yeah Jim Heather show the whole audience for puzzle piece tattoo
Only one
And wants to know it step back off the stage
Before we close I wanted to know if I can pray for you
You guys still pray in Minnesota right down here lyrics
Lord Jesus
Tonight
Hi chews
Turn
It's not letting myself my own version of My Own Story
I want to trust you
I don't have all the answers but I know you do it tonight by faith I choose to follow you
Thank you for loving me text you in a bit
Provincialism
I love you too
In Jesus mighty name amen and amen
And then just before everybody stepped out
This is very important
I'm going to be here another night I'm going to be at work tomorrow night
Play the podcast Radiolab
Has about three people that shout it out
Nobody cares
Radiolab is going to be holding
This side of the story
What happened to her
All right
So after the show we actually got a chance to talk to some of the people from the audience
The whole three days
Oh my God I can't believe that she was actually here
Here in there I would have been so shocked to sit right next to her
Pretty much everybody was totally floored by actually getting to see Janelle in person and they all seem to
Take her story The Way Jim does
Today's weather
So many things fell in mine were
You just have to believe in my
So the next night
My name is Mark Springs much less Fanfare in a much smaller room like maybe a hundred people there is so with the help of the
The religious studies program at st. Cloud University
We did Janelle sting
I saw I'm Robert College I am one of the co-hosts of the public radio program called Radiolab
I want you to salser and Wheeler who's our managing editor
Who's going to
That's him he's going to be adding his two cents from time somewhere very Democratic show in like nobody controls everything and everybody pitches in so that's our hero
Go to
And I want to begin by
Just telling you a store
So we brought Janelle up on stage
But you're not going to just come up here and sit I guess might as well sit here we told her whole story of
Donating and then waiting a year to find out you know who Jim really was
No idea
Talk about you know his whole processor
Recovery
Trying to get your bearings you talk about how grateful and thankful he was and then return back to Janelle
A little more complicated could you just run
I asked you like how you felt
Inn at 4
Brown and usually told me in the interview
There was
A part of me that felt
A little bit of an imposter
When would you use the word imposter
Can we should start getting in
I think so
Part of me
I'm in at that time
Especially
Thought that
I'm up here
Again
Asda
Pretty hard and fast proof or very compelling
Narrative for a lot of
People and their faith
That I don't
Particularly Cher
At all
The question
Knowing that
You know what I thought
Why was I was very concerned knowing that you
You know
Didn't agree with what I believe to be true that that you would feel like
Secure in that spot
That's why I asked you
Yeah
I'm a good person, doesn't make anything different in the fact that
It's still what it is
Exactly
I would have done it
Regardless
Whatever it was
If your whole theme of your show with Halle Berry
The Dallas Cowboys were and it got everybody to join the bone marrow registry
I would have got a boys have a show
Even though I don't have
You know what I hear to the
The religious tenets of it
I still get that feeling and everybody
All my family all my friends whatever their religious even my Muslim friends that I've told the story get
Do you know that feeling
And you know what that feeling
Is
Is a little intangible
But I think it's something even a little
Bigger than
I'm so crappy to see
Bigger than Jesus
That's really Blasphemous but I can't think of a better way to say it
Well you know
That
There is good in this universe and there is
Good and everybody and it is
Regardless of
The goodness is at the top of
The list of you and everything else is follow us here
Religion and your race and where you're born and it's your favorite pizza topping
Thanks and all that
But at the very top
Is
Good
With a capital G in underline
All right
Jim
In your show you have a rather gorgeous take on on moral relative
You have a string of thoughts
But this idea of being good and doing no harm and living as ethically as you know how
Is
Satisfying to some people
But in your ovulating
Really enough
I am this is where we I mean
Obviously there's some disagreement here
I think
That
There is good and I think that there is evil
In this world
And
I think the people in and of Their Own
Left their own vices left to own devices I think that the struggle of being good
I think that even on our best day
I think that we
And so in hearing her account you just say you just saying thinking what that is that she's not
What if what if we're does she falls to where does this idea
Lose you
I don't mean it doesn't lose me I think it's
Phenomenally good it's
Not not acknowledging his good I just think that
For it for the Christian
It's not about being good or bad
What is it about
I think it's about
I think it's about having a relationship with God
You know he made it clear that
Definitely
Wasn't condemning Janelle
Didn't have a relay
God
But then we
Start a different approach she started talking about the unlikeliness
This whole
Story which is why the things that Jim talks about in the show
Until that point I decided I should jump in
I say this
Really say this only
I'm because it is our job as a show on that when we hear a story like this
We dig and we investigate and we do that from a frame
Been really focused on math
Facts science and couple things happen to you if you happen to be in my position
You run across stuff like this and I'll just read from the
Be a match
Website
A patient's likelihood of finding a match and donor on be the match Reddit
Is estimated to be between 66 and 97
Percent chance that you'll find a 10 to 10 match
In the way that
Jim and Janelle work anime
10 matches
Is around 50%
Good Witch
She was the one that let me say that this does not actually contradict with Jim and Janelle's experience of it for
For that to happen to Jim
Is truly staggering it is truly
It could be one in a trillion you know like
The way winning a lottery is one in a trillion
One in the can because what happens is if you backup away from the individual and ask not
What are the chances this would happen the gym but what are the chances that this would happen to someone
Somewhere
It's like there's a there's a story about if you're golfing and you hit a golf ball
Nicholas however many hundreds of yards
That lands on a blade of grass
And a blade of grass is
Why me
Why would this golf ball crush me like this
Which is a valid point
I would feel that too but that ball was going to land on some
Way to browse
So are you
It doesn't like there is the Waimea still a true thing
It is a true experience
In which
There's still this difference I think
The bull can't point to anything greater
No there's the argument lurks behind this is
That these things happen and it is
Places to random View
The ball of Mercy landed on you
I also not coming at it from just that angle and I wonder if it was just
The bone marrow transplant if it would be
People get that all the time I think
Press the other bits and pieces of the puzzle maybe help Shadow it in you know a little bit for me
And so I don't know what's meets its multi-layered cake
I thought you really don't like
This idea
Like in this science version
There is no design and there is no first cause except the first random event that sets the thing in motion
Right
You both
Could you either of you live with that version of what
Yeah well that's perfect cuz it's exactly what you're talk about in your show
With
Nails referring to a thing in gem show where he talks about how unlikely any particular order of cards in a deck is
And idea of a particular set of cards being
Dealt in a particular way is 52 factorial
It is impossible to possible number you couldn't
Statistically right right
But yet you deal the cards and they happen
Right there so
This really gets into just the different viewpoints on
The proverbial deck of cards
Who is stealing them
Is it in a particular fashion and I think that's
And what Jim believes that there is a
Proverbial dealer
And I don't
And you would be.
Yah mean
Haven't you given thought to that
I believe
Did that there was some sort of
You know mind personality
So I believe part is where you is where you stand but it is absolutely absolutely it is
And you know
Your
Is
Savior I guess who saved his life
But in some way
You don't
You haven't
You worried about this at all
Yeah absolutely
Uneven
Right now on this stage there's a part of me that
In front of all of you
That I'm sure lot of here at the show last night
There's a part of me that is
Afraid of disappointing
That I don't share
What you believe to be true I mean
Your entire
Experience pretty much points the arrow
That like
I'm like an alliteration of Jesus
And that's really difficult
Reconcile
Doesn't have faith
A sad song
Cuz I think it's
It would be alot easier if I just believe
Exactly what
And I think
That I
Always
I'm very afraid of letting that
Be known like
Super
Like clammy right now just saying it in front of this many people
I just feel like people would
See
Your story and it's so
Immensely
Compelling it's unbelievable
And then see that that
Last piece
Photo puzzle
Literally doesn't fit
At all
I mean it's not like I haven't
I haven't thought about that either and how you might feel and
I empathize and I don't know how to add
I just I just want to give you a hug
There's a unconditionality to how I feel about you that
I just
If you can do no wrong in my eyes for you the hardest thing I was just trying to
You have been saved your life has been saved by her
She is in affect your savior
And yet you are believe
Is the unless she except
Jesus the consumption
She's outside of Grace
And you know I don't know I don't know what happened but
But she might be punished what do you do about this weird and she's insisting nope not for me
This is the way it is
Oh my gosh
What is it hard for you no not at all
Because
It's not my place to do that
I'm very sorry to everyone who isn't
Whoever feels like they got judged by Christian
Cuz it's never their place to do that
And this is where
I think most of the time never listen this podcast is
Place
Positioned or pigeonholed Christian
And
What they don't understand is that
I'm not commanded
To do anything
But to love
And to start conversations
I'm not the one I'm not I'm not that I'm not the one who sent it
Into the world
The judge
Right
But what I sow
So
Putting it like that I know where you are know where you want to go with
Judge that may not love the woman who saved your life
Yes but
But at the same time
That's not what I'm
The temperature in my place
How to say I think we were
Sort of expecting that maybe there will be
Sharper Edge the differences
Between Jim and Janelle
But to be honest
Their conversation that night and
Story started to feel like
Almost an allegory
How to move through the world and
Hold your differences but still be one
Let me just finish this way do you have a sense between the two of you
I'm because obviously you if you stay very very good for
Laptop
Is there some something to eat either of you can say
That explains why you can
Dignifiedly but emphatically disagree and still stay in such extraordinary
Close
Touch
I think
The idea of
Humility and as Gimli even say grace
Is
Absolutely essential no matter your tenants of belief
And that's really what's going to get you
Brutal conflict
So
Yeah
Is it because you're in
They speak ocean of the world and the two of you were just little
Little dots in it and so
Whatever you think it's till you're in the big ocean and they watch you got there
I think maybe yeah
And
Do you feel
Do I feel small
I feel tiny
Humility
Root word
It comes from
The rudest
Hummus
Is dirt
So when you become humble you become
Creates things but I won't go there
But you become dirt and
I think I think where we get hung up
Is
That
We want to be right
It has been brought into the
This yet
You want to be right
And right and wrong
AR
The words right and wrong
Are are are dead I think in relationship or deadly words I think that saying I'm right you're wrong
Is this is this is not good for relationships
I think it's like that's fine that's fine
You're right or you're wrong to her
I think so
I think we're done now. This we were done done that means that I'm going to let these
Two people
Who's the person
Brought them together
At the end of the show we had the
Bone marrow registry people there and encourage people sign up in quite a few did I think maybe
20 or so
But
That was pretty much nothing compared to what gym got at the end of his show
150 people signing up right now that account them
Better producer Annie McEwen
Is this bigger than no more
Always like this
This is a little bigger than normal I think anytime but I'm actually in the shows
Love it better so I've Been Told
And what is it how you feeling when you watch this
It's really overwhelming like
Yeah kind of makes me want to cry
Me Without You this wouldn't happen
It's almost too big to think of
Both thank you so sure this piece was reported by left
Reproduce by Annie McEwen look up from Bethel hop day and Alex overington special thanks to Julie Schmidt with be the match
And by the way they are one of the several bone marrow registry this is the one that Jim and Janelle were connected to it is
Be the match if you want to donate but we made a special arrangement with them all you have to do is go
Go to join. Bethematch.org as capital b capital T capital m one word join. Be them
Match. Org / radio Avenue get up a spit swab thing in the mail and maybe I maybe you can save a life
It's free if you are under 45 so again that's join. Be the match that or
Org / Radiolab also thanks to Ginger Galvin break Harney & Stu true with the main Center Mark Springer
Kevin Sharp Jim Gray Kelly Larson and the rest of the wonderful faculty and staff at st. Cloud State University
You can see and hear and learn more about Jim show at what is The Maze., when
What is The Maze. Com Jim has a book about his
Francis and his his story that's also when I website so
I want to go there and look at that night I'm rubber toe which to listening
To play the message press 2
For complimentary stay message to
New from phone number
We have made several attempts to reach you message
How to count it appears that you are now a message
Hey this is Jim Munroe the magician
And Dallas Cowboys fan
Janelle Jenny I'm calling from Milwaukee Wisconsin
And is produced by Soren wheeler
Masataka DSLR managing director
Becca bresler
David devil
Bekele have
Tracy Honda
Not guilty Robert krulwich
And lots of Master
Amanda
FEMA
David Fox
Vitaly
MKT Ferguson
Are fact-checkers is Michelle Harris
That was exhilarating
Usually disappear
How can I say something so I'm just going to say
And go Packers in this message