Are you at your looks
Radiolab WNYC
Alright here's a good one
At his
This guy is murder conviction overturned
He shot and killed somebody
Violence right ends up not being a crime
But he took some of his life
With a gun
Heat his position
Hey I'm Jared I'm Rod this is Radiolab and we're going to start off today with a conversation that happened in a conference room
Somewhere in Ohio
Let's see so just how I got to clean comes to us
I reported Molly Webster September we were looking around for stories
For something one of our challenges like bears are bad news breaking things and so
I don't know if I've ever mentioned it but I'm from Ohio
And so I thought I'll pull the Ohio card right now I'm going to look at this online
News site cleveland.com
But there's nothing in the story that is like
I mean yeah it says he shot someone but he did shoot someone
I think I saw a headline on their homepage about
The right to be forgotten
So
The information about the case
Is Preserve
It's just when you search his name
It doesn't come up
Wait time at this is a room full of people trying to figure out if someone has the right to be forgotten
I didn't actually know so I just
Email the guy hello written about the experiment with Chris
Chris Quinn
I am the editor of cleveland.com basically the head honcho I started at the plain dealer in 1990s
As a reporter Chris's story is he started out at the print newspaper the Cleveland Plain Dealer
And he did he was a reporter. He did that for about five years and he moved on to
Become an editor in 2013 that created an entirely new Newsroom that they asked me
Me too
Weed
The he basically became the editor-in-chief of their online paper cleveland.com
And what we really were trying to do was figure out what kind of content does the digital audience want
Once he moved online was like the audience was different the format was different this
Feed which they had to put up stories was different now but there was one part of the online price
Kind of stuck out to him
And it had to do with time and memories actually it began I think
I was in 2014 when I first wrote about it
Back in the day if you did something stupid got arrested and ended up in the paper
As it was for decades
It is printed in the paper
People would read it in the morning and then they throw it out drops out of sight it's not easy to find me nurse
Some newspapers that
They kept indexes that would be at the library but even with those you have to go to the library know there was an index
Look up a person's name and get to it
If someone really wanted to find it
They probably have to spend hours or days just
Rolling through microfiche slides
To finally
Navy
Discover that thing about you from your past
And now that everything is online it's
There
Always and forever so if you're going on a date
It's bear
If you're going for job
It's there
Just
Never goes away right up front
Forever so is cleveland.com started putting up all these stories about you know people driving drunk or vandalizing property
Streaking across the football field
Chris started getting these emails
I am requesting that my name be removed
From the January 3rd Quest from people
To take down stories about them a big mistake hold up to it and paid for
Order situation has had a horrific effect on myself and my entire family
Any search using my name and the word eternity stories
Come up in every job interview had in the last five years it has hurt my career or their children are getting
Older and might find them that article is a nightmare for me it is cuz, to myself and my children in arnor
Animal lives I have two daughters 11 and 14 years old we were the cause of
Some major suffering I've suffered depression during people a lot and crushing
Psychologically
I'm just in a corner and it don't know what to do
It didn't feel good
But we didn't address it at the time we kind of put it aside and didn't act on it but why not
Well
I mean editors all across the country were getting these emails but there was a long-standing feeling that
Were the first version of history and that these archives are sacrosanct than you would never change them
Journalist like as a profession had this idea that
That they are the first draft
Active history
Or the public record and you just don't mess with that
And every month I get more of these requests from somebody saying your story is wrecking my life
Can't you please take it down and I dinner every time I'd be Hardline yeah we don't do that
By the number of these continues
The antenna increase the man when you read them these are people that are
They're different imploring you to help them
Over, mistake
And edit it just it in the end
I'll let you know we had enough of these in a row where it was
Okay
We do not want to be
The agent of suffering
So Chris made an announcement
This was a column that I read
And it said something like you know if you had an article written about you and it was by us
And you want it taken down or I don't know your name deleted or something send us an email and
Will consider it
I and I and I just thought
Who has the right leg who has a right to be forgotten or who doesn't have the right to be forgotten who's making those decisions what
Are the kinds of things that they're thinking about when they're deciding who to delete and who not to delete
It's nice talking to Chris I was asking him all of this and for reasons I don't entirely understand he just
Said you're welcome to
To listen in now you just come see for yourself
We talked it out
Just acknowledging this continues to be very much an experiment
Into the room
I Molly Webster high so we can meet you so they meet
About once a month
When I visited there were seven people in the room
Hi Molly Heidi standard-issue conference room there was the special projects manager
Social media editor the public advocacy manager
Crimes editor Mike and Mark
A former Rock critic who is now the head of the culture desk mark
Mike
And
You're okay
Okay we all sit around a long table
Chris outlines the rules of engagement
We're not going to name the people's we talked about him we'll just use the numbers for the cases
And everyone has in front of them this document that's about 50 pages it has 12 different cases outline
In each case has got the Articles attached to it the statement of the person about what they want removed the name arm
Mugshot in a personal plea for why they want it taken down
Cool
It mean there's one sentence really about him
I caught up in a in another case
It didn't plead to a misdemeanor
And did have it expunged mean this would seem to me
Meaning no brainer
And
But he's an attorney charged with obstruction of justice
He pleaded guilty to obstruction of justice
A misdemeanor charge of obstruction of justice
Quick note
For a morass of legal and ethical reasons we are going to try to keep all the people we talked about Anonymous so you're going to hear
Here a number of bleach
Oreo cake using minor figure in it
Other quarter midgets work you'd want to know that he would have
On your behalf cuz
Get your off
I think it's it
That it is a public service delete his name up
So that people know
No
Formation
Have the record expunged
But he saying
So one of the first things that happened was that they started getting in these arguments about
How much value in article had and whether or not it was serving a public good that's the
That's the use
That journalist point
We do need names we need to put names to these arrests because it's part of the public record
Kelly McBride she's an ethicist at the pointer in
I did have this experience where my kid was on a soccer team and there was this coach you seemed really
Questionable to me in the his behavior and the
The way that he acted around the kids
And you know sure enough on the mugshot site in my local hometown
This guy showed up for domestic violence
And
I will let you know so I went to the athletic director and I was like Hey the sky can't be
Working for us
And that's the that's the use
That journalist point
Is that
You should be able to find out the bad information about somebody because you might be considering employee
Famous person around your children
Really employing them at all
And back in the room you know the whole sense of like if I'm one of his customers
I would probably want to know that there was a lot of debate is this thing the lawyer did bad enough that all of us
Need to know about
But
License to practice law alright
I mean
I need the bar here I mean they're pretty thorough about
You know looking at this stuff and deciding whether somebody is fit to Pratt
You know I mean
The bar didn't do anything
So one of the big questions is
How do we make that judgment
Should we follow the courts
You can hear them putting a lot of weight on whether or not a court has sealed or
Expunged record
Which is basically the court making this decision to remove the case from its own record
This is silver lining on a cord
It said yes you've done your time
You can have it sealed
We would need a very strong argument
You're not to do that
How to make your argument stronger why
I mean
No I guess
Anybody want to make a strong argument here
In the end they decided that this lawyer dude I had the right to be forgotten and so they just sort of like
From the article
And that was one of the simpler ones like
That thing's definitely got tougher because some of the cases they talked about where
So complicated like
Someone who killed somebody
And then it was
Legal self-defense
And I was like well that's is I mean it's not murder murder but that's like still killing someone like does that person have the right to be forgotten
And then one of the hardest cases
Alright on the fourth one he did have it expunged
Actually a cop his record was sealed
But
You know it is a police officer
It's fast enough over the course of a few years
Light on his timesheet and walked away with
Thousands of dollars
We've said
On the front end of this
Sex crimes
Violence crimes in corruption
Were were much less likely did to do this
So
I guess this comes down to
Would you view this as corruption or do you view this more as a guy who was
Afton office kind of thing
The cop
In his email
Plea to the group he said basically
Look I've been on the force for many years
I've never had an issue
I should have done this I know that but this was just one mistake
You know this was not
Some elected official this
It was not
Use of force
I mean this guy
Skimming over time
You know what I think
The firefighters
We're having
Time stuff to I mean that was a big problem
So
It's
But this is one guy doing one thing is
Like I'm so back and forth on this one
Authorities enough
He stole from his employer
I mean this is like any other theft
I hold him to a higher
Standard
It was interesting to see people's just like opinion shift
It's not a momentary lapse in judgement this went on for like
It's only been
Pearson
The story ran
And so
I know that means something to me like this was an ongoing thing about what he had going
Taken
I need extra money
And I'm with Mark bike the the public Trust
Issue here
You know this isn't some
You know
Water department guy skimming copper off the
You know some job site
This is a police officer
Stealing overtime over
The corset
I mean that's
A veteran
Describe himself
But I think that it's
Yeah I mean I guess I see that
I don't know I first read that
But yes I think
He said let him be forgotten but now
I'm kind of on the other side like
And it's not a ton of money is not a public threat
People but
Because he is in a
Position of trust in a public position
Tax.
Taxpayer money
I think
You got the right when you're saying
He should be held to a higher
Get back to our central question is the value of having his name there
Greater than the pain it's causing him for being there
Again and again Chris just steer the conversation back to that question
Which is
Does the value of having this article up
Outweigh the harm it's causing someone
But the trip was that question is
How do you know what information will be valuable
In the future I mean if we
Put the story behind a wall and other police departments don't see it what stops them from going to be
To get a job if he gets it sealed and the story goes away
Other than other offices might not be
I wonder if you lost it
We should look that up
We should do the research cuz if if
I mean we're talking about another Tamir rice guy
Hovering over the conversation was what happened to Tamir rice 12 year old
Tamir rice gun
So in 2014 in Cleveland police officer shot and killed Tamir rice after they saw him holding
I did not know this but the cop shot
And killed Tamir rice before he worked in Cleveland he worked at another Police Department where he was deemed
And when the
Cleveland Police Department was hiring him
They didn't
Dig into his records and then the other police department didn't like offer the records
And since it had never been a new story that was Google able like no one knew about it so he was
Hired
If
If all records of this disappear
And he applies to be a cop again your your would be basically our fault that he's able to
Do bad things
And so
In this case one of the thoughts in the room is
What if
One of these people
Does something horrendous
Write what if
In in a future
Year
You know they go in and
It'll kill 17 people
When you want to know
About their past transgressions
I mean wouldn't that make those past transgressions
Relevant again
And he told me that
When they do decide to delete someone work we're keeping
A spreadsheet
Of the names
We've taken out the very limited access how that feels like a crazy
Powerful
Spreadsheet
I bet it in a vault
I'm not sure I keep saying is this is an experiment
And we're not
We're not there yet
So Indian what they decide to do with the guy
Split Decision
I think no I actually think by the ended once Tamir rice walked into the room
You could steal them the energy shift to the non deletion side
They just sort of like
Wrap it up
Decided not to delete him
And then on to the next case which is a very good one and we'll get to it after the break
Okay Radiolab will continue in a moment
Calling from Firestone Colorado Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation enhancing
Public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world more information about Sloan @www
Phun.org
I'm Jedi boom rods Radiolab were back with Molly webs and the right to be forgotten
And I have a question for you
Yes
DIA
Play the cleveland.com Newsroom are they the
First people to do this situation
Country around the country newsrooms are tearing their hair out trying to figure out how to deal with this that's pointer
Kelly right again because
There are thousands and thousands of people who did one stupid thing
And that is the thing that the internet remembers them for
One of the things I found out was that it is a huge conversation but not a lot of people are openly talking about it
And all of these kind of quiet conversation seemed to be
Happening now
Because of something that's like bubbling up in Europe
What's bubbling up in Europe
Well
So basically what happened was
In Spain in the sky Mario in 1998 he had basic
Gone into bankruptcy at which point the local newspaper published an announcement about it
And then 10 years go by
Mario
Cleaned up got his money back as life back on course and so he reaches out to the newspaper and he was like
Like a I cleaned up my life
Can you take this bulletin down so it doesn't show up on the internet and the newspaper says no
DIY they said no
The usual reason that we publish this this is local news
Public records
First public record done and then he goes to Google and he says he can you delist this from your search
Search engines and they say no and so long story short
Yeah she takes Google
Court
It's all the way up to the European Union Court which is like the Supreme Court of the European Union
And in 2014 the judges in this European case make a decision that
If something is out of date
Irrelevant
Or not accurate
A person can request a search engine to take it down
In Europe you can petition to have things taken off the internet yeah and it's
It is this
Moment we're like a new right is established this is when you start to hear the phrase right to be forgotten
The unfortunate element of human remembering is it because our
Brain forgets automatically we never had to deal with
Deliberate forgetting disinfector victimization Burger professor of Internet governance
Oxford University I called him up when I was trying to figure out what was happening in Europe we can't deliberately forget if I tell you
Please forget that my second name is Michael
You will remember that exact opposite
Insult the problem is we don't know how to disregard memories
Avara pass
We don't know how to forgive if we remember
And so as we become a remembering Society we become an unforgiving Society
So he is a strong proponent of policies that help us
Forget
Even just a little bit and that's the point that I wanted to make
I'm not in favor of
Annihilating memories
I'm in favor of putting them into shoebox
And stashing them in the Attic
Send it if you really want to make the effort to go up there you can take them down
You can read
Choreographer for glass of wine and go to the
But
You don't stumble over them everyday
And it's some level I think
That's part of the thinking behind the European Union policy like can we just take
Take some of our stuff and put it back in the attic
And pretty much
Everyone I spoke to
Here
Says a Mario type of cases
Is coming I mean basically the consensus is this is going to start going to court in the states
Trailer when the European Union
Went with
A right to be forgotten
Yeah I started to look at that thinking is that we shouldn't have a la like that here cuz of the First Amendment
What is that something
As an industry we should
We should consider it and Chris's like we got to do something
But
We don't want to be alive because of the First Amendment we still want editorial Independence
So why don't we just figure it out on our own
And this is like every Newsroom figuring it out for themselves
That
Seems to be the moment that were in right now you do really get the sense that it's like on the Fly
They're figuring it out as they go
But then you think at what point do rules come into play to do everything on a case-by-case basis by its very nature
What is subjective
Alright this is a good one it's college kid who
Fountain
So one of the cases that Chris and the other editors
Talked about while I was there was this college students
Who got involved in a drug operation
We're not going to say which drug
And he was doing it with some friends
We're not going to say how many this is one of the kids asking us
Again it's it's going back it's funny
It is
College kid doing something very very stupid
Bye
You know what are you
He's going to talk him for the rest of his life
If it stays on our side
Somebody knows about it
Yeah but this is this is a college kid
Doing something really dumb that mean it's bad leaving he was enabling people to do drugs
Is later
He's trying to get on with his life the first. You here in the room is just
Oh my God we were all idiots in college we should take these articles down
If somebody does speak up
But then on the other side difference between
And you know selling pot on the side when you're in
College
Or even selling drugs
Other drugs
So it seemed to me like you're I don't know if that's
Think white girl let's take a
Now look I mean so I'm like give until I give this guy a break
But
Seems to me that
Judging from like some of the other cases we've looked at this
Fairly serious
He wasn't one of the ones
Said they had
They were getting cleaned right like he wasn't saying I was under the influence
What's the drive time
Diamine
The conversation turns to okay
Who is he does he deserve to be forgotten
And to figure that out there are ton of different questions you could ask
You know is he sober is he reformed was he sober then
How much time has passed how much time was he doing it
Question
Are the other people in here having a difficult time getting job I mean there's a lot of unknowns here
You know I mean all these other people their life might be fine maybe there's another reason this guy isn't getting jobs you know
We know
That he hasn't done anything since then
How do you say it's coming up in every job interview yes right
Doesn't employer
Have a right to know this
Does an employer
Let us know
I will take it down
Later he was in college was 25 it wasn't like he was 18
To remove the fact that
This is a clean-cut kid
Who was going to a private college
And move the scenario to the same age
The same race
But not in college and in some rural community
Questions of race and class
Come into the room all the other doors are white
Most wins College themselves
Is that biasing them in some way
I mean what our willingness to to forgive this kid
Be different if the social economic
Issue taser
This isn't about forgiveness
It's about the idea
Then on our site
Because we're so big
When you search for somebody
This is the first thing you find and we haven't set any kind of economic strata for this we have instead of geographic
Xstrata were considering each case as it comes in this case does this kid
Deserve to have
His name is Izzy and always it
Is enough time passed
Is is
It's not a crime of violence and Corruption
And you're not really the central question
As you heard Chris reacted
The abruptly to the word forgiveness being brought into the room
I don't I don't think we are in a position
To forget I asked him about it
After meeting ended I think it's almost
Presumptuous for me to think
That I can forgive these people
I bet you but
I agree that is that is it
But in a sentence
Taking on
If we if we
Acknowledge these people and
Offer them respite
Will help the rest of the world do that
To that that to me sounds like
Forgiveness
Okay I don't I'm not
I don't feel like
We're forgiving
7 people
Who asked for this relief I feel like
Wer
Or enabling them
To carry on
With their lives
Without the baggage
Of the mistakes they made cuz we're at societies very judgemental and end
If somebody looks them up
Cease that they did this
It's a big Mark against them I think what we can do is
Is
Is kind of revert back
To the way things worked before the internet the way it used to be
Right well if we think the answer to this is to find a way
To unpublish everything that
Somehow we collectively think ought to be unpublished that is a pipe dream
Iran Chris's thought by Deborah Dwyer
Who is a doctoral student at the University of North Carolina Chapel Hill School of media and journalism
I was talking to her because she has been studying journalists
And how they're approaching takedown requests in this whole like right to be forgotten issue
And basically what she told me is you can only delete so much
Yeah. We're never going to be able to eradicate our path that
That day
That ship has sailed
But
The power
That we give
An arrest report from 10 years ago
On a minor offense
That some
Dilly child dead and
There now grown-up and responsible and attempting to get into law school
People
Actually have the power to determine
How important that is
Right
How much weight do we give that
Organizations I talked to said they were considering not
Covering
Arrests
Or Court
Cases actual trial
Unless they could see them through their completion
Part of this might be being better about choosing on the front end what types of stuff we want to commit to
Digital memory
But part of this is a shifting our perspectives
Because if you can never totally forget something
You have to learn
How to forgive
Without forgetting
Right
But we live in a world of revenge p*** and mugshot extortion website and public
What shaming
And
So is that the type of society we want to be
Because against Society that's going to forgive you for that thing you did 10 years ago
Well
Likely not right now but that information
There's never going to be
A perfect way to clean up everyone
Path that is we've got to learn to live with it
And
If we
Cant decide Maybe
That
We oughta address it with a little bit of compassion
That just be hoe
Doing that one I'm looking for one of the simple ones just the delete
This is just to leave him like a two sentence paragraph maybe you're one sentence paragraph to just has his name Skies name
Delete
Then I add a note at the top
Pizza Hut
The story was updated to remove some
According to the
Cleveland.com
Pacific mattress
Top
Oh you put in a date
Allen
What's a note
Save
Fiance
Thank God
All right will one person's going to be really happy when he Googled his name today
Right
Is it all just changed
Google take me to private
I'll get the ticket to all of them by
Probably well the end of next week's I'm going to be out of town in the beginning
Cool
That's This Is Where I Leave You
When's your flight
Well I'm going to say we
What do you walk away from the whole Cleveland experience think
That I was confused
I just wanted the things is that
You can walk into that room
You're making this decision
And
You don't have a lot of information to go offer like if you're lucky you have an email
Maybe
Stealing order
And articles that featured the person
And at times I feels like not enough information
I used to think like I want more
And then other times you think it would be bad if we had more information because then I might just start
Like judging this person
Am I taxed to get more subjective
I don't know
But
There's one more chapter to the story
While a very long while after I got back from Cleveland I got an email from Chris
And it said that that day they had just done another round of right to be forgotten
Petitions
And that he thought that one of the people would be interested in talking to me
About what they did
And
Why they wanted to be delete it
So at that point I called the sky
Hello
How are you
Okay
I made it
Nervous is fair
Gresham traffic
I was a minute late
I'm just make sure everything's settled on my end so I have you until noon is that right what time do you need to get back to work
Are you
I can be here longer if need be I will just like roll with it then
Let me power down my phone
Do you know how
Try this whole episode we've been like Bleeding Out facts
We're going to keep doing that with this case will just like hold back some information in some instances we might
Change the fact
Sure it is obviously a risk
For the sky be talking to us
When I give him the chance of anonymity
I'm but he is up for that risk
Well
You go on a journey like this
Is a
The person who really never
Insight from a speeding ticket really never interacted with the criminal justice system and
You
Between Jazeera
Way of thinking
And how you approach life and how you approached each day and so
By me perhaps talking about it
Maybe
It gets people thinking about it
Trying to
To gain understanding I guess
So the story is this guy
Should I give him a name like fake name
Yeah give me a call
Seth okay
So
Back in the lake
Mm 2018
Seth
Was just like living a pretty solid life
Job
Wife two kids
And then
Over the course of a few weeks
I expose myself
Two women
Once in his neighborhood in front of a woman who is driving by
The cops showed up later that day but they just sort of gave him a warning
We all nothing really happened
Until days later when I did it again
This time it was to another woman
And what state was at the gym
Cited by police
The demonym starting
I called my wife
And I and I met her
A local park
I told her he tells her
What happened
Because everything
Tell her everything and part of what they talked about that day with something that happened years before
Yeah
When I was 10 or 11
I sexually abused now
It
I didn't think of it as abuse at the time
Are you
Build a lot of Guild a lot of Fame
I thought I was in on it
So
Who's probably okay you know that's what I was thinking
And I really didn't think it had an effect on me
Again these are not excuses but I think the
Really though the
The most
Damaging thing was
How I
Was introduced
Two sacs
And how
That became an issue me not
Getting help for that
I guess I'm talking all about me
But you know what
Really
Frightened
Two women
And
Sorry I'm just
Sorry
Eventually set the has to go down to the
Police station
His mugshot taken and actually get charged like misdemeanor charges against him
This was a couple weeks later when the police officer called today actually going to file charges come down to police station
I am
I went dumb and I'm pretty much okay we got to go we got to go I got to go
And I was wearing a hoodie and it just woken up and
No thought of my mind was like they're going to take a mugshot
But they did
Molly if you ever get
Cited
Ever get called police station
Come take a shower wear something nice because
It was so horrible
It's always there I'm not I'm just a couple keystrokes away
For my mugshot
The worst picture I took the worst day of my life
So if this it just stayed in the court system
No one would have ever seen that mugshot
Because
You know Seth just gets this point where he's like guilty I just want my
I will plead guilty to everything I don't want
I did
I want to take responsibility for
And I'm sorry
He pays a fine
Service probation
We're told the issue some sort of statement of apology to the women I get to New therapist
But then of course
In the midst of this he gets a call from a local newspaper
Somebody
Tip them off that I had then
Cited for
Indecent exposure
From there it was picked up by paper after paper and different like online news sites until it was all over the place
How do you think about you think about me or my parents are still alive what are they going to do
Iridescent paper
The kids
Yeah
Stellata shame
It's almost like you
James what you deserve
And so by the time that stuff starts rolling out he tells his kids
He ultimately loses his job
In the whole same thing
So when I would walk around and go to the grocery store
Things like that
And I'm sure it was delusional by like everybody's looking at me there is pointing it out since you know again so my kids to my
My
Your son goes off to college meets people
Hey Google
And
Unique name and Hometown and there I am
So
I think that that's really up
Big part of the damages
Family
And they don't
Aiden
You don't deserve it
He said a particularly low moment
Was
When his daughter came to him
And said you're the number one news story
Oh wow you know how you can see like a top news stories for your area if you're in a search engine if you doing like Google Now
News or something
Apparently his story was the first one
And it was his mug
Shot in really salacious
Story about me
He didn't do a creepy dark
Condescending
Totally but that's
At the heart of the question like
How do you weigh
The value of US knowing about Seth and what he did
Against the harm
It's doing to him and his family
You know in
This moment all of us are probably making different decisions in our heads
But here's what Acts
According to the law
Year after he's done everything the court asks him to do he can apply to have his records sealed
Which he did
And the judge agreed
I got them
Finally sealed
Mets
This year and no one has access to the judges thinking the records are sealed but not long after that
He saw the cleveland.com is doing this right to be forgotten thing
And so he was like oh that could be me like I could do this
I wasn't sure if I get approved but I still had hope when I sent it
Try to get craft a good email really
State my case as much as I could
So I
Have the letter that Seth wrote
To the right to be forgotten team at cleveland.com and I'm not going to read the whole thing here but just to give you a few
You excerpt
It says
Years have now passed since my mental crisis am I very public and salacious brush with the law
I'm grateful for a few things
The love and support of my family guided me out of the darkness
I'm here and not in a cemetery because of that
I continues I'm also happy that I was able to model for my children
Exactly how a person should behave
After making a Monumental mistake
While I would do anything to turn back the clock alter my actions and spare two women from my frightening Behavior
I simply cannot change the past
And it goes on
I ask that you consider me and my actions for the right to be forgotten initiative and that you remove my name and photos from the
The Articles written about me
I'm grateful for this consideration
Thank you
So
I got an email from Chris saying that we met and we've been
And you've been approved
And
He said something like they were mentions and there's really no way to
Just take out your name
So we're just going to take the
Stories.
Wow
So I talked to Chris
About
Taking all the Articles down and he said like first thing
McKay's is just so notorious
But taking steps name out wouldn't actually allow him to be forgotten
And so it just made more sense to delete all of the articles
The other thing is
Seem like a case of just kind of fit into the rules that are emerging in these committee meeting
These are misdemeanors
You know it wasn't violent crime it was a corruption it wasn't a celebrity
They thought he seemed apologetic there had been no other instances
So
To them
It seems like
Pretty cut-and-dry decision
You know it's still like I still have
That was not the only Outlet
That the stuff appeared in
So I still have a Google problem but again
Like the record Being sealed like every little step and every day that passes every bit of time
You leave a mistake in the past
Inure
One step
Closer to a New Life Second Chance
Something better
And this was a big milestone
I have question about the women who you expose yourself to
That's Radiolab producer Annie McEwen she was in on the interview with
Fat
As far as the women go their Anonymous and all the articles in the records are sealed
But it's their story too and so at the end of the interview Annie ask Seth about this
Just going to put myself in there
Shoes
And if they wake up
To somehow discover that
The article about their experience
Was taken down like do you do you think about that from their perspective
I have
I hope
I don't think about it
Honestly
I don't know
How they
How did think about it
I don't know
I don't I don't know
I know I don't know if
They might be upset
Don't think about it
Thank you Molly you're welcome
That piece was reported by Molly Webster and produced by Molly Webster and Bethel hopday
We have a few people to thank Kathy English
David Ayer.
Ed Haber Brewster kahle Jane kamensky
Do everyone
Share the story with me
Okay well I guess we should go
I'm Chad Ivan Rod I Molly Webster thanks for listening
Hello this is Eli from Eugene Oregon Radiolab was created by
Is produced by Soren wheeler sound design
Executive producer
David gamble Bethel have Tracy hunting Nora Keller not guilty Robert krulwich
Which Annie McEwen lots of Nasser Melissa O'Donnell sarakari Ariane wack
Scott Walters and Molly Webster
Neil danessa fact-checker is Michelle Harris