Are you awake
Northern listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
Alright hello hello hello hello hello
I can hear you
They can't hear me
So we can hear you and can't hear you but we could also here is us here at us
Hey I'm Jared I'm Rod Radiolab today
You don't even on here are you on here
Wheel story
About how
The Echoes of you can go out into the world
And come back
Invite you and all of us
In the butt
If my ankle gun
Yes
Okay
And it comes to us from a producer's Simon Adler
Okay so
This is Nick. My name is Nick. And I'm a special correspondent for Vanity Fair
It is beat
You can say is trying to predict the future of technology
To look into the future
Comment
Is kind of crystal ball
Try to predict what
The next five
10-15 years would look like for the media industry you have a good batting record like that did you did you call some big wild
You know
Songs in our pockets that would be like supercomputers
The social media would drive news
Not newspapers and so on and things like that so
Yeah it's it's
It's been pretty good I reached out to you because I I came across this article that you wrote an article that
Send shivers down my spine and I'm not one to
Typically be given Shivers by article so I guess how did you stumble into all of
Who is this and where did where does it start for you
So I was sitting around with some friends
In my living room and
Friend of mine mentioned out did you see this thing that adobe put out recently
More people than ever before
Believe that they can change the world
And that conversation LED Nick to a video a video online of
The Adobe Max
2016 conference
Are tons and tons of people in the audience
End up in front of them it looks like the stage
Of a Apple product launch but Serta beach-themed
Why Beach
I am absolutely no idea
TMI
But hey
There are two hosts that are sitting in these like lifeguard chairs
Canadian Jordan Peele Jordan Feliz in Key & Peele Jordan Peele
And the other host is this woman Kim Chambers who is a marathon swimmer and an adobe employee
And then on walks
Hello everyone
Young guy
Classes you guys have been making weird stuff online
Free photo editing
Annie sez
Adobe is known for Photoshop where known for editing
Photos and
Do magical things visually
Well
The thing today let
Do something to humans Beach
Pull up a screen on a Mac computer
I have obtained this keys are bald you aware
There's Michael Key talkin to peel
About his feeling after getting nominated
Keegan-Michael Key have been nominated
For an Emmy and he and Jordan Peele were talking about it pretty interesting
Joker solo
And
And I kiss my dogs and my wife
In that order
Not a bad joke so that's still supposed to send this
Audio to his wife
In other words what if Keegan-Michael Key was feeling like that was a little bit rough on my wife I was a little bit mean
You know maybe if you wanted to
Going to rewrite history
Say that he kissed his wife
Before
Spell he actually wants
His wife
To go before the dogs
So
Okay so what do we do
Easily
The button automatically generated
Transcript of the audio and projects it up on the screen behind him
You nope just text of what keegan michael Key
He said a little bit
And then copy paste
Judith highlights the word wife and pastes it over in front of dogs
Okay let's listen to it quick play and I kiss my wife and my dogs
Oh so he was able to move the edit the audio by moving the
Next round in a textbox exactly
Okay well that's kind of cool kind of impressive
But then
We have to type something that's not here
Wait
Actually if I'm not there
Michael actually kissed hour
Jordan
So sorry
Siri, the truth let's go is back in that little word box that's removed
Your secret's out
Type of word
Jordan
Protected. Jordan
Ann just be clear a Keegan-Michael Key did not say Jordan anywhere in this
And my dogs
What you just typed in word that the guy never said and it made the guy say the word
He never said
As if he actually said it
Exactly
Jordan's jumped out of his lifeguard chair there so to stomping around the stage
Oh yeah
Magic how can I show you guys is
We talked Lee pipes small phrases
Play
Okay so you delete the words my dog's any types free
And 3 time
You were saying
The Keegan-Michael Key never said ever said Jordan never said
3 never said
X
Any of those words in somehow just from the typing in it the guy is now
Saying and we're healing in his voice
That's what just happened
Yep that is exactly what the Democratic
It's essentially Photoshop
4 audio Nick Bilton again
You can take
As little as 20 minutes
Someone's voice
Type the words and it
Create
And that boys
That's in 20 minutes of the guy talking
Yes what how
How is
Heaven
Do you do this
We're here the Dobby what what exactly do you do here
Sure I'm the product manager for audio
This is Drake leaves
I flew out to Seattle and tracked him down to ask him exactly that Quest
So essentially what it does is it doesn't analysis of the speech and it creates a model
It basically
Explain to me that this program which they called Boku by the way
What it does is it takes 20 minutes
Actually 40
If you're the best results
Have you talking and it figures out all the
Genetics of your speech all of the sounds you make a block of sound and speech that
What is in the recordings chop them all up and then when you go in type things in it will recombine those
Into that new word
What if it encounters are sound that I never made
Wella the theory is in 40 minutes of speech which is the amount they recommend you feed in your goodness
Probably say just about every sound
Written English language
Is really sore like phonetically I go I run through the gamut and in 40 minutes
Yes
Like what would you or what are you hoping people will would use
A product like
Like foco
So for the video production tools and in for what i dishin is used for a lot of dialogue editing
The whole idea during said is to help people that work in movies and TV a lot of our customers
Record great audio on set
Actors in The dialogues Never
And when they come back
If sometimes there's a mistake or they make a change
Like the actor on set said shoe
But what he was pointing at was obviously
Sabu and right now there's they do what's called a Dr
Belt bring the actor in the
Rerecord
Wines and I'll try and drop that into the video
You're not using the same microphones you're not me
Kissing location the actor Midas
Sick that day so is voice sounds different in a lot of times you can really hear that stand out in in Productions if they don't get it
Boku you just delete the word shoe type in Boot & Boom
There it is
Using the same
Source media and the same characteristics
And have it just sounds seamless and Hatcher
And so is it is
It's going to be a sort of
The hope is that it will make
The lives of professional post-production edges easier for world over
That's our hope right now
But that's not exactly
I mean it's
What
Nick Bilton. When when he saw the
This video could be Donald Trump's Voice or Vladimir Putin
So I saw that and I thought wow
If imaginative
Audio clips
Start getting shared around the internet
Is fake news fake conversation between
You know Vladimir Putin Paul manafort
About trying to get Trump into the White House or something like that
I was like what this is
This is scary stuff
But
We're just getting started
In the words of John Raymond Arnold played by Samuel L Jackson in the movie Jurassic Park in his own voice
Hold onto your butt
Things are about to get a lot
Forget voices first
Second because now 1 2 3 4 5 1 2 3 4
Are we art
Paul g Allen Center at the University of Washington in Seattle when across town to
Talk to the head of
Grail
Laugh
Versailles Apartments near SW 6th and Elsa work at Chase
Okay just a backup for a second when Nick first saw the vocal
Demonstration keep starting to wonder how could this be used on the road
The my original thesis was I will maybe what will happen is that
You will be able to
Create 3D Act
Just like you didn't Star Wars
Benjani with the Valco stuff to create a fake Hillary Clinton
And you know Donald Trump having a conversation or making out or whatever it is you want to do
And that led him to investigate the type of work that you're a dud
Driving using these terms like facial
Reenactment and facial manipulation of what the hell do these words
Me
Yasso
I mean it's a way of animating faces
End
It Started from the movies right remotely control bodies with avatars
Think like the aptly-named movie Avatar
Or a
Going a little further back
Intelligent life anywhere Toy Story
How to make the characters come alive what you need is deep
Expressions of the actors playing them
What's the movie space it means that
You will bring a person to a studio
Then you
Your face with you
Sticky sensory marker things
And then you'll spend hours hours hours
Capturing
The fastest little Dynamics
Like smile
Keep a smile no teeth had
Surprised
Disturbed angry bloated
In front that they create a virtual character capable of emoting all those
Expressions in to make that character believable the animator's sometimes have to model
Bone structure and muscles
And if you can imagine this can get very very
So what people like your ass started to wonder was like
Can this be done on a bike
So she and others in the field started feeding videos of faces into computers and
Train those computers
To break down the face into a series of points
Armada starter bolts 250 by 250 that is 62500 points
On one human
Face and wants to know that's right to get ragged point
Once you can track how my face move through a video clip by
250 x 250
Points
What can you then do with that information
Well
I can apply the points on the face on a
Difference
Model of a different person
Now this is this is where things get
Quite strange
Because
Instead of being able to map all of your facial movements onto a computer-generated
Virtual character or purse
Whittier and others in this field of
Facial reenactment have figured out how to do
Is to map your facial moving on to a real person
A pre-recorded real person
What does that even mean
The best example of this is I is this
Piece of software that Nick showed us
Add the software that I found
From the University student
Called face2face real-time facial reenactment method that works with any Community webcam
Download this and when you open it up at this very monotone voice comes in saying
Uses RGB data for both the source and Target actor
Set up on the right you got this heavyset man
Goatee
Spiked hair on the right Source actor is captured with a standard webcam
Arching his eyebrows
He's pressing his lips
She's opening his mouth widely sir like a like if you're making funny faces for a two-year-old kind of thing yeah
And then this input drives animation of
The face in the video shown on the monitor to the left
On the left you got this
Dell computer screen displaying a CNN clip of George Bush
This is a real clip of bush back from 2013 and his face is there looking right at the
The camera occupies most of that screen
You start to notice is up
When the man with the goatee smiles
George Bush in the CNN clip
Also
Smiles and when the man raises his eyebrows George Bush raises his eyebrows
You realize this man is complete
Trolling George Bush's fake wait so this is a guy in the present controlling a
He passed
George Bush a real George Bush when old video clip
A little while back when we were just learning about this up we happen to have her friend Andrew Marantz
Who writes for the New Yorker in the studio
So that is George Bush
His face
What
Oh God
That's
Terrifying
His
Okay so yeah I cannot stop watching George Bush's face
Putin now holy God so
I just have a guy just sort of
Going around Aurora
And then that's what
Goodness doing
You know what I mean those videos online
Had my mouth
Again victim
This is this this is a form of puppetry where
Your face is the is the Puppeteer in the only thing is is that
George W bush
The puppet so I sit in front of a camera
I smile and the business is taken care of this isn't like you have to render some software on your computer
Peter it's literally you download
Clip or you take a clip from cable news
And you turn on your webcam
However long it takes you to do what you've done
Same as the shooting a video on your phone
What is this for
Applications of this
I want to be able to
Help
Calvados
Telepresence
This is Sarah again
So
Telepresence telepresence
Self example
So my Mom leaves in Israel
And I'm here
NCI
What is be cool if I could
Have some guys it's kind of crazy but right but
If I could have
Some kind of hologram
Of her
Sitting on my couch
Cher
And we can
Have a conversation
Going one step further one of your is colleagues a guy by the name of Steve Seitz and the professor at the University of Washington and I also
So work part-time at Google
He told me that they see this technology as
Like a building block
That could one day be used to essentially
Virtually bring someone back from the dead
I just think this technology
Combined with virtual reality
Other Innovations could help me you know just be there in the room with
Albert Einstein
Carl Sagan
That that's about it
That's what they want to do that's the motivation
Ghosts for them yes and
When I was talking to some folks
Who work in commercials they're developing their own version of
And the idea is that they're going to make a million or billion dollars
Because I say you bring
Jennifer Aniston
In
To film some makeup
And in the makeup commercial in English she says so coming by this product this is the best sort of whatever product
Right now you got China which is a booming Market you maybe want to Market things to China and you'd really like to be able to use Jennifer
Problem is Jennifer Aniston doesn't
Speak Mandarin
So either you use the same audio clip and you have someone come in and speak Mandarin
Over her in the lips don't line up
Or you have to hire a mandarin-speaking actor to come in
And do the part of Jennifer Aniston
With this technology
All you have to do is record Jennifer Aniston once
You can hire a mandarin speaker
And the Mandarin speakers voice will be coming out of Jennifer Aniston
Mouth as if she had said
And in front of the camera
Her lips would be moving as if she were perfect Mandarin speaker
Exactly
Wow
I think I've heard of it is actually a vegetable
Yeah
Oh my God
I'm Amazed
Completely frightened
By what you're telling me
NFL point of what Nick was writing about that they gave me shivers
That someday if you join the video manipulation with the vocal voice manipulation
You're the ultimate puppeteer
You can create
Anyone talking about anything that you want
In their own voice
And having any kind of emotion around it
And you have it right there for everyone to see
In video
And all you need to do
Is take that
Put it on Twitter or Facebook
And if it's shocking enough
Minutes later it everywhere
Like the timing of you guys making this thing and then this explosion of fake news
Like how do you guys think about about how it could be used for
Nefarious purpose
Oh yeah it's a good question
You're coming back or Slytherin
I feel like when everything college has developed under there is danger of
Vdara technology you can create fake videos and song
Are there any college fake videos like to create video from audio rights
But they are fake videos
But the way that I think about it is that
Like scientists are doing their job in science like
Invented the technology and science
It's off and then we all need to
Let's think about the next steps
I mean that
And the answer is not clear maybe syndication maybe it's every video should come up with some code now
That's this is
This is like authentic vdrf antique attacks since you don't believe anything else
Yeah like it maybe was the timing more than anything but I saw this video and it really felt like
Oh my God like America can't
Handle this right now
Like we're in a moment where we're truth seems to be sort of
An Open disc what is true is Pez become an open discussion
And this seems to be adding fuel on the fire of sort of
Competing narratives in a way that I
I find trouble
And I'm just curious that you don't
I think that
I think that's people
If people know the types of knowledge exist
Then they will be more skeptical
My guess
I don't know
But if people know that taking is exceeded
Everything all that shake that
Texas
Fake videos exist fake photos
Then everyone is more skeptical in what
They read
But like a man in North Carolina I think it's from North Carolina believed from a fake print article that
Hillary Clinton was running a sex ring out of a pizza
Parlor in DC which is like
This man believed didn't shut up with a gun
If people are at a moment where they are willing to believe
Stories is Ludacris's that
Like I
Don't expect them to wonder if this video is real or not
The weather you ask
And ask it what I'm asking do you are you afraid of the power of this and
If not
Why
I'm just give you my answer your questions but I'm a scientist
Not really because I know how I know that because I know that these Technologies reversible
I mean nobody
Well
There's not
Nuts
What
Too much
Have you seen the videos otherwise I can tap you okay
And if we're feeling worried and more than that surprised that the folks making these Technologies weren't
We decided to do 30 gut check to see if we were totally off basin
Get in touch with one of the guys who's on
The front lines
Can you describe what was going through your head when you were watching Bush's face
I can tell you exactly what I was thinking I was thinking
How are we going to develop a friend to techniques
Detect this
This is honey for read I am a professor of
Computer science at Dartmouth College he started like a Sherlock Holmes
Ace of digital misdeeds which means they spent a lot of time sitting around looking at pictures and videos trying to understand
Where has this come from has been manipulated and should be
We trusted season work for all sorts of organizations
Beatty the times Reuters want to know if they a picture is fake or
They often will ask me you have to leave when
Like this just happened that yesterday images came out of North Korea
And everytime you just come out of these regimes or there's a history of photomanipulation there are real concerns about this so
So I was asked to determine if they've been manipulated in some way and if so how had they been manipulated
And what how did how the heck would you do that well
Everytime you manipulate data you're going to leave something behind
Let's say you do some funny business to a photo
You might create some noticeable Distortion in the picture
Self but you also might distort the date and we're in the business of basically
Finding those distortions in the data
For example imagine you get sent a photo
Probably a JPEG jpeg which now is
99% of the image formats that we see out there
Is what is called a lossy compression scheme
Just a fancy way to say that
When a photo is taken and stored as a jpeg
The camera you know just to save space
Throws a little bit of the date away
So for example if I went out to the Dartmouth green right now to the picture of the grass
The camera isn't going to store all those millions of little variations of green hidden in the grass because that would be
Huge files
It's going to save space by throwing some of those greens away
You just don't notice if it changes
Like a lot or a little bit less than that is grass as far as
You can talk nice trick every camera has a subtly different pallet of greens that's going to keep and greens at store
Throw away this
Very tremendously from device to device on iPhone compresses the image much more setlist greens and a high
High-end icon or ion cannon which would keep more of those variations
Now if you hold these two pictures side-by-side you might not be able to tell the difference
But honey says when you look at the underlying pixel
There are different recognizable patterns
You take an image off of your iPhone
I should be able to go into that JPEG and look at the packaging and say I got this
Should have come out of an iPhone
But if that images upload to Facebook and then re-download it or put into Photoshop and re-save
It will not look like a tiger consistent with an iPhone so basically he can see at the level of the pixels or data whether the picture
And this is of course just one of many different ways that honey can Spotify
Yeah let me ask Mike if you could go up against
The top 100
Best counterfeiters
Do you think you'd catch them
10% of the time 50% of the time that have cats what's your sense
I would say we could probably catch 75% of the face
But I would say that would take a long time to do this is not an easy task
And so yeah
A sandwich
The medium moves
Does not lend itself to
Careful forensic analysis of images
I'm always amazed that
Nicodemos you like. You got 20 minutes
And I'm you would need
You'll have to day today per image to a very manual on the very human process
It's so
Is this video editing
And this audio editing this coming down the pipeline here I guess it should I be
Should I be terrified
Yes you should know
Did you really you really mean that
Yeah I think it's I think it's going to raise the fake news thing to a whole new level
I did see some artifacts by the way in the videos they are not perfect but that's neither here nor there because the ability
We have technology to manipulate and alter reality is growing at a Breakneck
And the ability to disseminate that information is
Phenomenal
I can't stop that by the
Because at the end of the day it's always going to
Easier to create a fake lie detector fake
Thank you very much
Dad
Himself just handed me a cup of water which shows none of you have gotten too big for your britches and that could be a
Serious problem
I would like to have seen Peter Jennings do that
Ever
For this guy my name is John Klein co-founder and CEO of tap media
Before that president of CNN us
Before that I was Executive Vice President of CBS News where I was executive in charge of
60 Minutes 48 hours
A bunch of others
And he's had to react to some serious Evolutions in the media industry
He was Manning the helm is social media exploded as
Smartphones become ubiquitous
Consequently he had to deal with figuring out
How and if to trust thousands of hours of video taken on these smartphones and sended by viewers
What's a broadcast in
Why not
And so we wanted to know how someone in his position would
Think about the
Deepfake videos
Soapweed
Set of all the different demos and videos we come across just
To see what he thought
First thought was that this is the kind of thing that
A James Bond villain
Would put to use or
The Joker
In Batman
Ernie's great girl
Right wants to be most popular
You know I mean this is
There's so many ways to abuse
Blow your mind
I mean
It
It goes
To the
Very
Score of
Communication
What weather television
Radio
Interpersonal
It is what I'm seeing true is what I'm hearing real
Over the course of your career you've seen multiple technological development state of impacted
Intermediates in rather profound ways
Where is your Terror level right now or your fear level
Caused by this relative to all of the other
Sort of advance
Instead of occurred over
It's terrifying
It is
Hurdles us even faster toward that point where No One Believes anything
How do you have a democracy in a country where people can't trust
Anything that they Siri
Anymore
What
What we saw happen with
Fake news during the election cycle was that
I'm only the lead to matter if anyone
Pino
Wood
Rebuff it afterwards this is Nick Bilton again it would reach millions and millions of people
Mere seconds
And
And that was it
You don't need a dentist it's job and I think that
With this audio stuff
And the video stuff that's going to
That's going to come down
Online in the next few years it's going to do the same thing but
But no one's going to know what's real and what's not
It says if you think about
The video that came out Donald Trump from Access Hollywood
The thing that was really interesting about that video
You can do anything
Grandmother you don't actually see Donald Trump until the very last second when he gets off the bus
How are you I only hear him
And so if that technology existed today I can guarantee you
That Donald Trump would have responded
By saying it's fake
Take nudes fake audio you can't see me I didn't say that
And it would just be
This video is word against his
Galaxy that's kind of like for me that's sir the real problem here like you create this this possibility for like
Plausible deniability
So broad like
Tobacco industry in the sixties and seventies
I was just reading this great article by other
And the writer Tim Harford about the
In sixties and seventies a tobacco industry LED this very
Calculator
Did effort
Disorder push back against
Cancer signs by
I know a little bit of doubt
Year little bit of doubt
On the other hand on the other hand isn't that just enough wiggle room
But nothing happened
I do that with climate change to
And it's that little bit of doubt that creates
Paralysis
And is that what's going to happen that like there's going to be paralysis now
Writ large because now we're talkin about
The very things we see
The very things we hear
But wait but we don't you think that before we get completely carried away with the threat of History
LGB
Maybe we should just find out
Literally where we are now
Yeah we should give it a spin
Sentence with this moment do you think making one of these eclipses is is possible
I think it's entirely possible
I just decided I would be careful what it is
After the break
Things get
Fake
How did everyone it's Angela calling from Dallas Texas to Radiolab is supported in park
Buy the outfit
Eastland Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloan at www. Sloan
ORD thanks Radiolab
I hate everybody Pat Walters here I'm a producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
About what we're calling tiny moments
Brilliance
Basically I want to hear about this
Times when a kid you know did something
It just means you lean back and say whoa
How did they do that
Maybe it was the moment that I
Kids you've been reading to 4 month started reading back
Do you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lesson
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed are ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the specific moments where a kid does something super smart but doesn't
Have anything to do with the test
If you have a story
T-shirt with us
Go to radiolab.org
Brilliance
Record short audio message
Fan that's radiolab.org / brilliance
Thank you so much
Jad Robert Radiolab. We're back we're going to now
Fake something
We're going to build our own video from scratch
Fake words fake faces cuz we want to know
Back in use
How dangerous are these
Technologies
Really
Can they make a convincing fake are they as
Easy as advertised
So we will find out by giving the assignment as well
Long suffering
So well I was in Seattle talking to drink leaves
Not so subtly hinted that I would really like to
To give vocolo world let's say I had my hands on it somehow when can I do it
Well right now nothing because we haven't shared it with
At first I just thought he didn't want me to be able to play around with it but then I realize that and I don't even have a personal
Copy for myself yet
I said not even on the premises
No it's it's still very much contained to research
Oh
But
Hiya hiya hey man great eventually I got in touch with this
Matthew eyelets on the Chiefs
Science officer airport Limited
Yeah okay so
Called you up because I was hoping
That you could help me to make
A video clip that has I don't know
Bush or Barack Obama
Saying things that
They have never
Yep this is right
That's it
Uses game the thing is what his company does is not
Quite the same as vocal
They do is like for a client node
Create a voice that you can then just type in Word
They're sentences and make that voice say whatever you want
I feel sad that's an interesting idea accents
Variety of languages
Internet spare time when they're not making voice
For clients
Discover Donald Trump nigga I think they're building celebrities
And it just so happens
It got to Barack Obama and George Bush
Yeah how did you create a George Bush robot
Well a great thing about
George Bush says he was president United States
Sometimes morning
Good morning which means
She had to give
The weekly presidential address
The other great thing about me dresses he's completely copyright
Free summer Alliance
To do anything we like that video
For the people of America
Maybe things that they have envisaged that we got to do with it
Real quick digression here just because it's absolutely fascinating
It looks like we're actually about to enter this really sticky gray area when it comes to voice
If you record an audiobook
And you sign over the rights
To those audio files to the publisher
The publisher has a copyright
You you don't own it you do not own your own voice
Is that really true
Anyway
Back to Bush
Lowe's weekly addresses
About 6 hours
Which is a lot more tape invoke has 20 minutes but what you did with it is
Pretty similar
Right fed them into this machine learning algorithms along with their transcripts
And then with the program will do I type the text and it will analyzing Sons it linger
Twistix I will say this is the word Social Security social
What's OSHA's made out of
The sounds
Oh
And so
Bootcut low sounds app
Lots of little tiny pieces did that for all of the words
All of these addresses River Run 80000 in total
Put them all in this database with tons of info about What song came before it after cetera and
Once that database is built up all that's left to do I type in some text and then I put go with it trying to find
Set of little sounds which will join together really nicely
And then I push play and see how well they came out
So what we did was we found an old video of former President George Bush and Barack Obama today
Free shaking hands making generic statements
Exactly is an import
But we wondered
Could we turn that clip
From a boring meet and greet
To a scenario where bush is telling Obama a joke
So we convinced a comedy writer Rachel axler who works for the show Veep
Let's write a few jokes
Optomap in
This is what the computers bad
And well
It goes something like
Knock knock who's there
I think it's something about the Oval Office probably
That wasn't a very good joke
The president
My wife Laura tells her better
Wait what was that was terrible
I told Nikki that was like where that I don't even get a I don't understand that joke at all
That's literally with the computer spot out
That is what computer set out in
Trippy. I don't think it anywhere it it did it is not worthy of the negative response that you are getting an error
Let Live let me show you another one
So happy to be joining forces with this good man
But God is all in your drinking water
Cortisol
Cortisol to help protect
People cheat so they don't get fillings
Isn't that alright
OSHA
I think I signed the wrong bill
This is what you do chords
The robots is massacred that is in itself
But I do think it yet I'll let me get it while you two are far more critical than you should be and you are far more critical than the average Lyft
However
Matt
Conversation
Getting people to set the
To talk back and forth to each other are still really difficult for it
Synthesizer
I need a long time before we get really really easy conversation
Human quality
A tour to a conversation that that the synthesizers
Can't quite capture
But he also told us that
You know if we at once we add the video or if we add a video to this
It will smooth out a lot of
A lot of the prop
When you have to say she's as well speaking people not focusing me audio
Coneheads of the iris in the same way
So
Great great
Two grad students
My name is James get title from the University of Southern California USC
Also do a lot of facial reenactment
Surgeon agreed to help
But
Making these visuals also turned out to be way harder than we thought
Turn off the clip we chose post some serious challenges there were too many side shots of Obama's
Space at the lighting was all wrong
And eventually I got an e-mail one late Sunday night saying
It's not going to work
Okay
So now I think I can draw a line here
And I can point out that this
That we may be got over excited about this technology
It is not yet ready for True deceit you have been fumbling and fumbling and fumbling here
I have with them if they are you not the rug as people I find it interesting psychologically the timer
I feel like it's a personal failure I don't like to fail
You should
So okay just just descansamos behalf on the behalf of extra trying to answer the question we fell
Okay maybe
Maybe
We should try this one last time let's find a simpler Obama video and with the audio rather than
Michael phrases let's just do a couple word Replacements here or there
By the way the only reason we're using Obama's annies
All these Technologies
Is your belt around
Play Sweet shows the video of Obama's last weekly address and which was the audio from a talk he'd given a
Chicago
After he left office
What's what's
Nsvt Surah talks about what he's going to do next how he's still going to keep fighting for what he believes is right
Build with
Idealism
An absolutely certain that somehow I was going to
The world
But what if he didn't
What if you could at that moment see the divisions ahead and he was just like
That's too much I guess
The truth is we didn't think too hard about this
We didn't have much time we just whipped
Together script based on words
Used
You change it send it off to the guys at USC
Vienna videotape myself saying this new script said that
Use that video my face
The puppet eyes at
President
And at when when we got the final video back
I have to say it was
I was expecting it to be horrible and we're to have a good laugh but
I
It went from like Laffy Taffy to
Oh
Wait this is
Creepy I was suddenly
I had been gangbusters we got to release
This thing is
And not tell anybody and try to fake out the entire world
But when when I saw that there was
A real active
You mean your own oh I know God yeah yeah I thought I would
This my personal thought was like it was convincing enough that I got genuinely spoon
But you know just baroness we shouldn't sit around talking about something people can't see
Go to Future of fake news.com and check it out for yourself it's all one word future of fake
Use.com
And it'll pop right up you can see tell us what you think
You can see how Simon made the video
Check it out
The whole process
Got us all thinking like
Like oh wow what if we bunch of idiots can do this
For no money
Very quickly
What will this mean
Feel like a newsroom
To start there
We're at the level now with with this kind of thing
Where we need
Technologist
Tutu verify
Ward knocked down
News executive John Kline
I don't think journalists
English Majors
Are are are going to be the watts to to solve it
Can I eat you may have been editor of your school paper but
This is beyond your
Your capability but
If you're good at collaborating with
Engineers in
Scientists
I hope you have a good chance of working together
To you to figure it out
So we need we need
Technical X
Petitis
More than we ever have
Can I ask you in your hearts is it let me compare your heart to my heart
In my heart
I want somebody
Tell the researchers
Yes are you can't do that
Sorry but you know I I know it's really cool I know you I know you probably are really proud of that algorithm but
Men In Black are going to walk in right now they're going to take your computers away
And and you give you the Cancer Society is going to overrule you right now
Did you eat
Is there a party that
Just dictatorially want to just like squash this
Wilshire
But when he still have the
What are the FSB in Moscow or the CIA
Utilizing this
And developing it anyway
Weaponizing it
So to speak
Probably
I think that the
The top
Down model
Could never contain
John says ultimately what's happening is probably going to be bigger than any one organization or any
A1 Newsroom consult
Said it'll probably end up coming down to the 14 and 15 year olds
Weather tomorrow
Who will grab using this technology making fake videos being the victims of fake videos
And maybe
In the Maze of them having two parts truth from fiction in such a personal way
Some kind of code will do
I'm an optimist by Nature
I do I look at this and I said well somebody's going to figure it out
What worries me is
The larger context within the state
Within which this takes place
This is all occurring within the context of
Massive music literacy
And the the
Consumers
Seem to be
Is throwing their hands up
Tiring of China even figure it out
And so just the
The work involved
In getting to the bottom
Of the truth
Is
Unappealing to a growing
Percentage of the audience
And
I'm not sure
We're genze the teenagers of today
Come out on this
Let's hope that they are more willing
To do the
Maybe out of selfie
Pinterest maybe so that they're not dissed
Bye
Yeah the girl in social studies
But that's our best hope
For overcoming
Is everybody else
Seems to be sick of trying
Reporter Simon Adler
This is produced by Simon and Annie McCune
Very special thanks to kylo schefsky and the entire team at USC Institute for Creative Technologies
For all their work
Ovulating
That video of President Obama
It takes two
Matthew a left for synthesizing so so many words
Forest
Rachel axler for wedding
The jokes that we tried to use
Self Empower for Burlington
Amazing website and Disneyland apparel everybody WNYC Newsroom
For advising us and giving us reaction shots of the face-to-face video for putting us in touch with Nick
In the first place to Nick Bilton for inspiring this whole story with his article
He's got a new one
Book actually American Kingpin about the founder of a black market website called The Silk Road
And to supersonic computer scientist who works in Ira's lab
Who helped us understand what the heck was going on and finally you can see the video that we created this was a bunch of other
Kind of crazy clips that we mentioned throughout this episode it's at the future of fake news.com
All one word
Future of fake news
Dot-com
And with that
My real co-hosts
And I will bid you a Jew I'm Jedi Beaumont I'm Robert krulwich.
Who we really are
I'm glad we could finally be on all these years message
New from an external number
Images
Radiolab created by Jack
Ruler
Melissa McDonald black and Molly Webster
Rebecca Casey and Katie Ferguson
And this message
To hear the message again
Press 2
Delete it
Chris Evans pics