Are you awake
Northern listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
Jad Robert Radiolab
Are these all 20
4 amendments
Sia songs
Oh my friend
Did you say 24 Amendment for the 2727
I know every weekday Edwin every so often
Okay so
More perfect now is entering its third season right
First two seasons what were they they were
They were extended
Investigative
Highly reported and researched and elaborated stories about
Supreme Court
Cases in front of the Supreme Court
But the idea was
Of more perfect was always broader than just the court I mean the idea is to look at the
The argument
It just so happens
Time in ND
Process of Americas
Trying to claw its way out of the month to get to it
Higher ideals those ideals of course are outlined in the car
Which has been amended
27 time
In waser
Crucially important
Especially right now
And most Americans can't name more than one or two of them I was one of those people
The Forum
And so when I was on my break
I had this idea
Crazy idea
Which was
Could we make an album
Could we make a Schoolhouse Rock for the 21st century
That reanimated the cement
Modern exploration by well
I said you got to go big right
That's a very didactic thing like that in those songs
You actually are told
Exactly how to feel about the contest
Yes I'm only a bill
And I'm sitting here on Capitol Hill
Yes but Daddy was could we take the spirit of
But not like didactic in the way the old stuff
Southwest but like taking these things that we have been covering for two seasons the amendments to the Constitution
Bill of Rights 1 through 10 the other ones from 11 to 27
Taking them and cuz they're so so
Stodgy and musty like a language some of them are really opaque
Yeah I mean enter the idea was to take these
Stuffy stodgy sometimes opaque
Deeply important
Words
Bring them to life
So we reached out to attend a different positions and ask them like would you interpret these amendments
Are you can talk it
Explicitly about the Amendments if you want or you can turn it into something very personal to you but could they do it though
I don't know what means play you a couple of me
Should I choose one
Women's soccer
Which one is that that's the 1950s she was a good one
You chose a good one my friend looking to get musically free
Okay you are going to
To get drum roll please
Dali
Parking
Come on
Dolly Parton
Dolly Parton or Dolly Parton
Somebody and it's Ernie
Doll - Ali his first cousin.
No
You got it
Really yes
A little bit of a song
August 18th
Women's suffrage amendment
Stratified
Women have been fighting for the legal right to vote since the 1840s
In 1890
National American women Suffrage Association nawsa was established
Was Susan B Anthony is leading Force
But women have been fighting for their rights
Since the very beginning of time
We couldn't drink
Speak
2 we were spoken to
The truth that's when he's got smart enough
Fast food
We have to fight for women's rights
Tarrytown because the time March up and down the street
When women finally got the right to vote
Wow
Do you want to hear another one
I mean I'm really curious about like a an amendment like a technical and I'm like the 26 like what could you possibly
All 25th is the is the one that's missing
Session 1
The 25th amendment is the amendment that
Establishes an order of succession if the president can't do his job
So Devendra Banhart
Is a
Is a sort of a freak
Folk
Musician
He does like soda psychedelic Folk
Psychedelic
It's a whole genre hello my name is Devendra Banhart and I chose the 25th Amendment
Truth about succession
He's an amazing songwriter and he wrote a really funny song
Takes you through the line of succession 1600 Washington DC
Even though I'm at the bottom of the list Allura and Ever Wanted
Please pay attention
That's been in place in the 1700 still today
It all began when the president
This state of Hawaii
11 West and the new negro moral compass in a developing
Who ate too much drywall after seeing Lincoln's Ghost in This House
Tubing down the hall
New Speaker of the House of Representatives
Glendale
And so the president pro tempore of the Senate
Show that every person who becomes president
Vineyard Vines that you meet the next one in the line
And I think I think assertive that the whole
What is that everybody dies in adults
With him being president has really went to law books
They just look very kids sometimes yeah yeah
We we we just get somebody took the idea of the amendment and went with a feeling rather than with the league
Yeah
Persimmons
The First Amendment
Number one
The big one
Weasley that one after
Hi this is Robbie
Brooklyn New York
Radiolab
Supported in part by the out
Peaceland Farm
Meaning of Science in
Technology
More information about
Sloan at
UW.
Loan.
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
This summer
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents
Aunts and uncles teachers were looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments childhood brilliant
Basically I want to hear about those times when I kids you know did something
It just means you bring back and say whoa
Maybe it was the moment that I
A kid you've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of the musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed are ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the
Epic moments where
Kid does something super smart but it doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story
T-shirt with us
Go to radiolab.org
Flash brilliance
Record short audio message
And that's radiolab.org
Brilliance
Thank you so much
Radiolab Jad abumrad
College
Offering up a preview of an experiment that we're doing for the new season of more perfect
We are releasing an album
It's called
27 the most perfect
Album you can find it on iTunes
Spotify you can also find all the songs
The most perfect
Album. Org
On the podcast
We're not just
But now music
Where it was telling stories
For telling me
Funny
Poetic
Sometimes sad sometimes hilarious
Explainer
Stories about each of the 27 Amendments
I think yesterday like audio liner notes for the songs
The story that we tell in conjunction with
The First Amendment
Sarkari producer more perfect
Creative
Full story of my drop into the middle of it
Wichita newborn who is a law professor
And he to him the First Amendment
Is like
Poem
Tow strap into that way
When you hear a reporter sarkari actor Jeffrey
Rewrite
Reading the amendments
Professor Burt neuborne talk about
1st Amendment
Freedom of religion speech
Press
Assembly and petition
Congress shall make no law respecting an establishment of religion
Or prohibiting the free exercise thereof
2 or abridging the freedom of speech or of the press
Or the right of the people
Peaceably to assemble
And to petition the government
For redress of grievance
Could have been written on the back of an envelope
These days the first amendment is
Wrapped up in all kinds of
Thorny stuff like
Kneeling at football games and
Hate speech and money in politics
But if
You
Just step back
From all of that
And you read the text of the First Amendment and you really try to think about
What the words are trying to say
You find that the logic behind it is
Kind of beautiful
The order of the words in the First Amendment
Is the life cycle of a democratic
Trinity means
To boost first two clauses
Congress shall make no law respecting an establishment of religion
Or prohibiting the free exercise thereof
Create a
Free space
Inside your mind
Believe As You Wish that's the founder saying that's space inside your head where you think your thoughts
That's sacred
The government can't touch that there can be no government so that's the first idea
The freedom of your thoughts what you believe.
We don't want to see it which brings us to the next class abridging the freedom of speech
Call says if you got an idea formed in the freedom of your mind
So you the freedom to think about the freedom to speak that thought
If you really want to make a real name
See you need some way to be able to speak with people
In a very loud voice which brings you to the 4th class
4 ProPress
Which is speech amplify
Once you've gotten your message out to a large number of people when people would listen to these ideas and move
It's natural for those people
I want to do something about it to move together
I'm too organized for the right of the people peaceably to assemble
So you can think of that even speak that.
You can create a movement
Which is the 6th
Idea at the petition process once you've assembled once you've organized
Web search web search
And to petition the government
For redress of grievances
I'm forced to government
Into confronting it and either accepting it or rejecting
And then that government if it says no
Is subject to being voted out of office
Suited
This is Madison
Giving us the blueprint
For tomorrow's Big Bang
When democracy begins
The way I'm hearing it is like
Like cocentrix circles like starting and inside the mind of one person and then like reverberating
The first amendment is
A series of concentric circles
Beginning within your mind
And then moving
So you're closer
Acquaintances
Then to the
Society at Large
Yeah I've been finally
To the entire polity to the entire people
By the way is the only time in human history
But those six ideas
Never been United
In a single tax
Only time
I went back and looked at every single rice bearing document in our tradition
All the way from the Magna Carta
Through the English Bill of Rights through the colonial Charter through the state constitutions through the French Declaration of the
It's never been done before
To put the 6 building block
Blocks of democracy
Feet together
In a single coherent
Text
The first amendment is the ideal city on a hill
It is the ideal community
Got the founders were trying to establish and remember
That was for the first time
History
I've never thought of
A little bit like some
Kind of
Very thoughtful relay race
Each at the Baton has passed its way it's the next logical step
To Turning what is inside you into
Powerful statements
Yeah so that's
So the First Amendment liner.
About now that you
Me thinking about the way that God
Describe the First Amendment
As this progression of ideas
I mean it
It just comes almost
Just invite a couple of centuries after people like Shakespeare and Cervantes
Begin
Creating interiority like this
Do you want to meet
It really wasn't
Any place
To go to hear someone talking to her
Or himself yeah
And not even
A couple of centuries past and then you get a government
The takes that idea
The people have an interior and that interior is
Distinct and needs
Protection
From the Devil
And then comes this
Explain flow
I never really thought
Yeah it's a cool idea
If it's interesting the song that that's paired with
On the album I mean actually that we got a couple
What different submissions
For the First Amendment but
One of them
Came from
A guy named Joey Styles
Seizing native Canadian
First Nation metis
Hip hop artists
West End
She made a song with sort of argues with a spirit of Burt newborns take
You should have looked at
It's sort of all the
People that have been left
Out of that
How much rat ghost as far too I was dealing with the freedom of religion
Illegal for Native Americans to practice
Add am I specifically the Ghost Dance as a teen
150 to 300 mostly women and children Massacre for ghost dancing
It's me that shows they were
Scared
They're scared of us having our culture and ceremonies because they have powers
I truly hope the warrior Spirit Shines on this track and our natural side of being Wild and Free set stone
Sparrow Hood drama mystery
That is really I mean above the lyrics and the musical choices
On that there
Are you really
Challenge
Your senses the amendment a little bit
So that these
Songs the way they're written and the words they've been chosen
And then what do they mean strikeout
Paul
Either
Arguments
Temple or argument
Spirit argument
History
Yeah I would say 80% of the songs on the record
Our argument
Put the amendments
Celebrations lyrics
Explanations of the
What was the
Very interesting
It's cool right
Yeah very different way to do it
Yeah
So this is just a preview if your city here more
Go to wherever your podcast search
For more perfect
Sign up
Radiolab.org more
I'll take you there
If you want to hear the record
Execrate
So proud of
Go to iTunes Spotify wherever
Search for 27 the most perfect album you can hear all the songs
In their entirety
The most perfect
Pic album.
Okay
I'm Jedi Cam'ron
Thanks for listening