Are you awake
Northern listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
Do you do you just want to like lay out for us the chronology of your
Obsession I think I feel comfort
What's a dalliance I mean you just noticed
Crumbling building and ran over to
Sticker can I mean I am
I'm a contrarian
I'm interested in alternative facts about science let's say
Hey I'm Jared I'm rod
I'm a back row which this is Radiolab
Talk to a science journalist named Dan ingber
Who got us kind of Tangled Up
About something that we thought we knew about the world but ourselves
Something beautiful as I recalled that we talked about a great links on the show
Hello hello and said that conversation up
We're going to start
Isaac Steele
Pastor Claude Steele
Eastern's Emeritus professor of psychology at Stanford University
We actually had him on the show
Number of years ago sometimes I can't remember how many years ago is 2000
On the show back then was because he had done study in the mid-90s that just completely change the way that we thought
About
The power of stereotype
Well my mother was white my father was African American and they were very active in the Civil Rights Movement so you can imagine
The erase was no distant or passing thing
In our life
Family for Claude growing up that was just
Everyday dinner table
Yes exactly
So the topic
This is so the family Birthright
Then years and years later Midway through his career as a
Psychology
Claude ran into a demonstration of the power of race that
Really surprised and I got a job offer this is in the 80s
University of Michigan and it was part psychology and part to administer a minority
Student program there
This is Clydesdale the original program we ran back in 2009 and
In the process I think I saw dated at surprise me
What he saw was a
Troubling trend
Two kids would enter Michigan one was black one was white they come in
Exact
Same level same skills
Same SAT score should do the same when they get to Michigan but
Without fail
Or almost
I feel after one semester or I could was
Winding up with lower grades how much lower
Pretty pretty pretty dramatic
At least two-thirds of a letter grade in a black kid who should be getting an A2 is
He said getting a b
Insignificant
Also by the way saw this performance cap
Between women and men
When it came to math to the same degrees degree in advanced math courses it was
Comfortable
I learned this is a national phenomenon
If I was to walk into Emma's any college class
In the United States
I have a very high probability of finding exactly that
So I think it's important to put it in context of what was going on at the time this is Dan anger again and he says that that
Japanese treatment between black and white students that clouded notice
It was actually a huge topic of conversation at the time there's a lot of discussion of what to do about this evening cap
And
The Familiar argument is well this has to do is systemic racism and systemic
Differences in opportunities
That play out
Through
An individual life span
That seems right
It's also daunting
Because our we ever going to be like
Cure all of it
Socioeconomic status in our own country
But then
In 1994
Different and in many ways very dangerous idea was being tossed into this debate Charles Murray
Co-author of the book The Belk
When the bell curve
Came out the bell curve
Intelligence and class structure in American Life
Bell curve argued that one explanation for the treatment Gap among others was genetic
IQ Bass
Of course
It's not
But even though there is no scientific backing at all
For the idea of genetic differences like this
The bell curve was still significant just because of the kinds of
Conversations
It was creating of the time the effect it had on researchers in this
Well the bell curve is one point in a long history of that
Kind of argument.
The difference between groups really is rooted in genetics
Let's just be frank and honest and if you really can't admit that
Then you don't have the courage needed to be a real science
That's a thumbnail way of describing this experience that I've have been confronted with
With that note
This was obviously disturbing to Clyde first on a personal level in order to be a scientist are you
You supposed to actually be open to the possibility that you and your
Your family and your whole race
Have some genetic
Limitation but also because it was so weak
Scientifically
It's been very difficult
Colts impossible
To produce anything like definitive data
That the
Between groups
Genetic differences between christening and Michigan clearly wouldn't be explained by genetic differences
It also didn't seem to him like it could be
Explained
Simply by their backgrounds or their opportunities
Because you take what's a black and white kittens Michigan they both have extraordinary scores like
You know during the 98
Percentile on the SAT
So the background
Between the two kids
Whatever it is
Has not resulted in
In a difference to that moment in time
So if going forward and taking a test
The black kid gets a lower score or lower performance in a chorus of some sort
There's something must be happening
Right there
Something must be happening in the moment
There was something
There
That people didn't understand that we certainly
So he figured he would start with the woman in math
He brought a bunch of a bunch of men
Software documents in the laboratory one-at-a-time gave them a half an hour section of the graduate record exam
Can you take if your a math major
Very very difficult math
And sure enough
The women who had all the same credentials coming into the situation
Perform dramatically worse than the man worse as a couple hundred points in an SAT test
So Claude Steele. Alright
Step 1 complete I've got a lab situation
It resembles the real world good next step is to
Tweak things a little bit see if I can mess around with it
Normally in these situations
Test givers got a white lab coat on and he brings in a big stack of cellophane wrap test
Put the clock on the table that solve it's all like that's
Intimidate almost anybody maybe that's what's happening
What if I took away the
Took away the coat and most importantly
Right before the test I had the test giver instead of saying the normal I'm going to give you a test
Protest thing maybe instead
Say something like that
Look you may have heard that women don't do as well as men on difficult standardized math test
You may have heard that
But that's not true for this particular to
This particular
Does not show gender
Never has never will he wondered
It may be saying that
Simple sentence before giving the test
Have an effect
And sure enough
I wouldn't be here if
Their performance didn't go up in
Go up to match that of the equally skilled man that performance Gap
Vanish
She look at this
So we raced and did it
Very quickly the same company
Experiment with African America
They're the pretest disclaimer went like this
That we use to study
Problems
And it is not diagnostic
Pic of individual
Intellectual
Mobility in other words this
Is not a test of your intelligence I repeat not an IQ test so just do the best
You can't with that simple disclaimer to start
The black students
And the white students
1 L equal
Just recently
Ryan Braun and Eric dated at you clever
Treatment think there is a an IQ test which is nonverbal healthy Advanced Progressive matrices has
Figures very abstract I got
Lines crossing that you have to match
This essentially pattern match diamonds with dots in them
And so they could represent that test as it as it is an IQ test attraxion is the gold standard of IQ tests because it's cold
Culture free no math there's no reading because it doesn't involve language or you can represent the exact same test
As a puzzle
Meaning you can give an IQ test to watch a kids and the black students will perform worse but if you give that same test
Lose the word test lose the word IQ just call it a puzzle to Black participants
Suddenly
Jump up and they're performing basically we got a reversal represented as a puzzle black before me as well as white
Let Me Tell Ya that's all it takes
Just change a few words
Stereotypes of powerful okay that makes sense
Snapper in terms of understanding how this works
Can you make this
Tactile stimuli
If the stereotype
Having all these effects is like a
Like a little Gremlin that bites
When in the test-taking process is it actually like
Do it stand up
Whale
What does seem to be clear from the data according to Erik day and Ryan Brown and Claude Steele is it the gremlin
Only seems to appear
When the test is sufficiently hard
If the test is easy it's important to point out
These effects don't happen
It's not that the gremlin is not there with you
But he doesn't speak necessarily
Until things get challenged as soon as the task is difficult
Which means it for most of the test everybody's doing about the same it's only a problem number
Cosines and factorials whatever where things start to go wrong at least that's the theory at that problem
The black student
Starts to stiffen up a little bit
Your blood pressure is elevated there
Short-term memory is impaired
Flicker of frustration through their body that wakes up the gremlin who starts
To whisper in their ear I love you can do this
Is what they say about us true they don't think you can do it all the usual
Even if the student doesn't believe it which is likely so you don't have to believe it that's
The kind of Insidious thing here just the fact
Did he has now
Extra bit of mental chatter that little guy Whispering Willows a distraction
Makes their performance go down
Just a little bit hold this dialogue
Is keeping you from being 100% focused on the task at hand which is solving these problems who the real
Subtle
Power of a stereotype isn't it prevents you from doing the thing you want to do
It diss track
Cu
Forget the beat
I'm doing the thing you want to do
You and that may be all the difference
So that's how we ended the piece that we did back in 2009 but in the Years
After Claude did that original study
Defect
She called stereotype threat
Became one of the biggest
Stereotype threat and most important ideas
In all of social psychology
But now some psychologists say stereotypes can become self-fulfilling prophecy
Steel ladies and gentlemen is my great pleasure 2%
Clydesdale
It became a sort of academic
Rockstar
Speaking to overflowing audiences to places like Columbia and
Cornell
Steel
And this idea of a stereotype threat was shown to be relevant in cases with that had to do with age and socioeconomic status
There were studies about women playing chess
Men being tested on like social Sensitivity I mean
Clyde's work ended up inspiring sort of the whole
Generation of social psychology
Yeah I mean I was I would say that
The original stereotype threat paper by Steele and Aronson you blew me away
Spoke to me and was beautiful and it seemed to
Offer
Answers
You have two questions that you have come with me
So this is Michael and
And I'm
A professor of psychology at
University of Toronto
So when did you begin
If you could give us over the cliff notes version of your history with
Stereotype threat in particular
I mean
I think
I was certainly attracted to
That's that part of social psychology that dealt with prejudice and discrimination
Some Jewish I went to New Jewish
They scored High School in Canada
Perhaps bacon to me was
Desire to to prefer social justice
And you know seeing you know what the evils of prejudice and you know how
It was evil taking their logic
Dreamwalker happens
I was passionate about the topic
I
Sort of explanation that also offered
Route to easy solutions
Text effects
Sounds like you really came into it with a very social political
Should have been stuite yes that's right
I wanted my work to have an impact I wanted it to
You have to change the world
Coming up after the break
Michael tried to change the world but the world kind of changes
Yeah
Hi this is Vincent Rojas from Norman Oklahoma Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloan at www.slha.org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents
Aunts and uncles teachers we're looking for stories about what we're calling
Tiny moments of brilliance
Basically I want to hear about those times when I did something
It just means you read back and say
Well
How do they do that
Maybe it was the moment that I
I kid you've been reading to 4 month started reading back
Do you
Or maybe the kid was a piano
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of the musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed are ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the
Epic moments where
Kid does something super smart
But it doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story
T-shirt with us
Go to radiolab.org
Flash brilliance
Record short audio message
And that's radiolab.org
Brilliance
Thank you so much
Chad Robert Radiolab we're back
And we're talking about Claude Steele's seminal research
On stereotype threat how the threat of a negative stereotype
Can impact a person's academic performance
Sprite and just before the break we were talking to Michael into it
Cool after getting into stereotype threat research you went on to grad school and really
Focused in on stereotype threat as his
Fielder's choice
Yeah so how many studies of stereotype threat did you end up to it
I would say in the order of like
Number of studies
20 maybe 15 to 20 something like that
He did a lot of studies on women's performance in math but also just looking at different environments and how they create or incur
Courage the stereotypes
And over the course of his career he ended up editing a book about stereotype threat
I mean numerous
Talks on the subject all over the world even signed a brief kind of explaining stereotype threat to the Supreme Court
States the Supreme Court heard the oral argument in Fisher V University of Texas at Austin as it applied to the question
Of affirmative action the court will decide where the race used in University and College admission policies it's constant
I'm sorry you don't put my name to this
But then
I started my current job at the University of Toronto
In 2005 and while he was there he was running a lot of his stereotype threat research on women and men
Matthew know giving women a test and then doing some intervention to reduce the stereotyped and seeing if there be a difference in
Standard test scores
And
Sympathy
For the first time I was not able to consistently
Show any effect of stereotype threat in other words the women who had received this
Stereotype threat reducing intervention perform just about the same as the women who hadn't
You know
Belta Tropical Smoothie
Let me go back to the drawing board let me think about
What is my house my population differ
And his first thought was maybe have something to do with Toronto petrano
Someplace like take the Freshman psych classes
We're talking about a third East Asian 1/3 South Asian and only about 15%
Caucasian or european Canadian
And then a little bit of everything else so he started wondering
About you know women in math
I'm in remarkably when I would ask you know our students this
Mikey task know who here is heard of The Stereotype that women are bad at math I would say no more than
Like a quarter to a third
Add your strong awareness of the stereotype
Joey started running experiments again but I'd only pek
Those women and men
Who actually had awareness
But even then
I still then come get the f
I'm so sick okay well
Maybe I'm doing something wrong like maybe the interventions he was designing weren't reducing the threat or with these goons maybe this
The threat just wasn't that much of a threat in the first place
But by this time Michael had already done
Ton of research on
Stereotype threat and you know I done I'm a person who gets bored
A rather quickly Majesty know started
Amazon
But just a couple years later well so
Things changed
On October 17th
2011 this one paper was published in the paper called
False positive psychology
In this paper details
Help just by doing some very standard practices
In Psychology research you could sometimes end up with
These sort of
Ludacris conclusion
Yeah
So you're saying there was this paper was showing ways in which
Experimenters could subtly unknowingly juice the results that is NC
What it was essentially so the paper was pointing out that it becomes her standard practice that you know when you were research
Searching for some effect like oh how happy people were about well they did on a test
That you would measure that thing in a couple different ways
Which direction is considered a good practice right you want to know one measure captures your konstrukt perfectly
So you should measure that thing in this many You Know Places pasta
But now what if you find that it could Works your hypothesis
Just confirmed with one of those measures
But it's not confirmed with
Three or four of the other one
And it was not uncommon practice at that point to just be no report the one place where you got in effect
You could even argue that you were just
Dialing in exactly where this effect
Happens but the paper this fall psychology paper pointed out that if you ignore the places
Where it didn't work a picture of
Weather
Find the data you look at all of it
Might not actually support
Your conclusion I remember reading that
My jaw dropped
I sent this
This paper I circulated it to the other faculty in my department
And
All of us
Are many of us
I saw the
The importance of this paper
And we we call emergency meeting for a call emergency meeting
What is an emergency meeting look like
The Graduate students
Discuss the contents of the paper
To see what I meant
What implications were and if they talked it over they realize that in some ways probably some of their own work
Mom had fallen prey to the problems that this paper was
I did see myself in in some of this
And I thought
You know how like will he know
What has been implicated what papers of mine
What paper is more generally have been implicated in the fields unibit large
And in fact meetings like the one that Michael found himself in start happening at universities and conferences
All over the world
Yeah
People looked at that paper and everyone thought
Just an anger again this is this is what we're all doing the stuff
And now we know from this
One paper that
It's very very easy to turn up
Spray lining
Yeah it change change everything because a group of scientists are taking well maybe we really need to go back and Rihanna
Investigate some of the key findings in our feet like all them high power replication so you're just kind of doing the same thing but
More people so they start doing these studies with bigger sample sizes and with strict rules about what data you were looking at
Say hi to find exactly what they're going to do and how they're going to analyze data
So you know there's
No possibility of monkeying around
Get the answer you want
Any attempts to replicate or reproduce no major findings in social psychology
And after
Panic that went along with it
Came to be known as
The replication crisis
The Cornerstone of science
News articles
Are talking about
The reproducibility crisis
Ensign like oh man
What's your what is going on here
Because as they re-examine some of these studies
The facial feedback
But he's got lots of coverage in newspapers and magazines
He pardoned today involves
Some of these replications
Where
Feeling specifically what got me reeling it's covering the replication crisis was
News about ego depletion
So this is a whole literature of studies that were all about
How we sort of use up
Our willpower
Original studies
You going to a lab in your presented with a
A dish of delicious fresh-baked chocolate chip cookies I love the method section of that paper they described baking the cookies in the lab
Set up a snail would be
Around the subject when they come in
And they they put these cookies on it so you can't have any cookies
And then they leave you alone with a cookies and what I found was that you know if someone has to sit there resisting a cook
Cookie with it right in front of them in the smell is walking up their nose as they sit there if they have to go through that it'll actually be much
Harder for them
Complete certain kinds of logic
In the argument was he use willpower on Dino task a
Then you try to do tasks be and you just won't have a store will power unless
Later studies found you drink some lemonade in the meantime because sugar the argument goes replenishes your willpower
Increasingly bizarre elaborations of this original Theory
It ended up working with M&Ms ended up working with cookies
Over the years dance has this idea that you use of willpower one place and have less than another just started entering all
Three corners of Our Lives the inside of that original study was
Replicated again and again and again for deca
But then this group of scientist get this massive
Effort to replicate the original study
They had over 2000
Subjects
They follow these rigorous rules about like what day they were going to look at this is as rigorous a replication is
As you can get
And they just found
Like no offense
Basically no affair
Brake brake system understand like how is it the dark that they're finding
Nothing now but before they had a study that was then replicated
A bunch of times in a bunch
Labs
Look what I still don't get
What's
So so you have that original cookies
I think it's notable that no other studies that I know of used cookies
Now I found studies were M&M's where use
So
That just makes me wonder I have no idea how that
Lab to their study
It makes me wonder what would happen if I ran a lab and I wanted to reproduce
Does cookie find
Standing in a New Direction and I kept trying it with cookies and it just never worked
Let me try it with
Charleston Chews
Doesn't work because it's not hard to resist
Yeah
Baby Charleston shoes
Are not good candy and I end up in like I do with M&Ms and it works
Boom there's my dissertation I publish a paper out of it
So now that's in literature and so now ego depletion seems like an even
Stronger more valued thing because it's not just about cookies now it's about cookies are M&M's
My point is that you don't really know how many things were tried and each individual lab do you think that might be
What's happening in these Labs is that there's a lot of
Trial and error in the heroes or swept
Decide
And the successes
Are offered up and then suddenly you have one more success that bolsters the idea is that what you think might be happening I think so
That is
The heart
Whatever the problems are not with those follow-up studies the big thing was that scientists work continuing to fail
Hell at replicating these
Bigen in Fairly well-known
Studies like the
The idea that when you smile it
Changes your mood or
Start
Free
Notoxlife
The idea presented in one of the most watched
TED Talks ever that the way you sort of
Hold yourself or stand
Yourself big
Stretch out
The idea that that could have a measurable impact on your behavior or even your hormone levels
That one also failed to replicate that kept happening with study after study and of course
The other people come back and say all the Wrecker
Application effort wasn't done right or you didn't really design it well you're seeing a lot of the researchers
Who have made their career studying certain effect
They're just
Not budging
Few of them are but most of them are not budging so
You just have a split for a man
Iowan researcher describe to me a second civil war was in social psychology
Estates of stereotypes
Threat
Now
Itself under threat is it one of these
Bodies of research being we thought well
No one has yet done the big multi-site
Pre-registered
Replication that they did for ego depletion the one that like really woke me up to this
But Dan says there have been sort of smaller-scale here and they're kind of attempt
To replicate some of the studies and
You know some of those had failed some studies came out to
Found it
You know what
I tried to redo I tried to do the stereotype threat thing on a big group of students
And I found it sometimes
The opposite happen when I try to induce stereotype threat the students did better
It's a beautiful day
Will let me let me say this maybe this
Wealthier I fix this is something
You know I thought a lot about in the very beginning when we talked about all this
Couple things
First of all
This research has been dramatically well replicated
Stereotype
Threat effect has been demonstrated
Way more times and way more
Send really any of those
Psychology
Study zone of this another
It is another phenomenon it has
Mapreduce so many demonstrations
And
If you can't replicate
One of them
Six of them
I don't know I wouldn't
I would that doesn't surprise me
He says you know you can even see the failures that's just information about where the effect really applies and where
Where does this is science
Gradually getting sophisticated enough
To help
Applied inappropriate places
For example he says he would only expect the effect to appear
At times when the person is really invested
What they're trying to do
Linda's the negative stereotype
Really
Threatening
On top of that he says
The kinds of stereotypes that are actually threatening to a given group
Might change
Overtime if you just exactly replicated what we did 25 years ago I'm I'm not sure that the
Stimuli and that procedures would have the same meaning
What's today's
College students
That they had been
Delete your social psychology
The meanings come from the
Contemporary moment the way the state of the culture at that time
Jimmy that is interesting actually
That is what this research is doing is studying like an individual's
Relationship to life
Threaten like
That's going to be different
Anyone who you are because you're going to find different things threatening where you are or even when you are
Yeah I don't have I don't
I think I know enough
About
Quote the cultural
Black students
Today versus
The cultural
Black students 25 years ago
But it wouldn't surprise me
That there is some real difference
So I don't put as much stock
In the exact replication of
Experiment A or B
Yes I do
In the
Conceptual replication
Is it possible I mean you mentioned there just hundreds of studies that
Kind of foggy circle around the same idea in different ways
That is
Artspace very compelling
Evelyn
Patapan on This Is Us
Robust phenomenon
But the same time you know there's people who gather all the data together and they say look you know maybe there's some kind of bias
Lips in when people are genius resources they just keep
Trying different versions until they
Get
Something that looks like a results
Does that seem plausible to you
Boy that's a deeply
I guess cynical
Account of
I was scientific
Literature this big
It would seem
It doesn't seem highly probable to me
Is clearly real or applicable under these circumstances we just because they're not everything
Doesn't mean they're not
Incredibly important to
To the progress of this
Society
Stereotype threat is pretty unique in the fact that many of the
Studies in this literature are not just in the lab
They've been taken out into the streets with
The real people
That's really where the
You know the tire meets the road is can you actually move
The
Educational performance
Of real people
In real
School situation
Jean-Claude actually sent us a list of several dozen studies
Showing that that interventions designed to reduce stereotype threat
Can have
Traumatic
And long-lasting effects on achievement
Now we should say there was at least one case
Are there was a study done in 2000
6 that a researcher try to replicate in 2011
This is much smaller
I'm the original
2069 just last year
You did it again with more students this time
I got
Pretty much nothing
This is the same guy in the same school system trying to do the same study
With you know hundreds and hundreds of kids and he came up with nothing serious to know Lehman given that replication is become a cop
Conversation that you have to unfortunately contend with
I'm just curious if it
Change your opinion of the work
No
I don't think there's anything
This whole thing is not true
I mean
I want the truth out there more than I want anything else
This is Steve Spencer he was in early collaborator with Claude Steele especially on those studies involving women and math test
I did recognize
In some of the critiques real issues that we need to deal with
But Steve like Claude is very confident in in the results of his studies in the effect
Of the stereotype threat in general so much so that I'm writing right now and article
Where I'm going to disclose every single study I've ever done what the results are input the data up for everybody.
I will admit
To the questionable research practices that I've done
And
Be as forthcoming and honest with everything in my own lab
In addition to doing that I've entered into an adversarial collaboration it's called which just means he's going to do
Big scale reproduction study with people who have serious doubts about whether stereotype threat is real
You know I can't say I haven't time what my reaction will be
I think what I can promise is that I will take
The findings very serious
And I will do my utmost not to be defensive about
Are you nervous about this I mean it's looks the stakes are pretty awesome I mean
You know
What you mean the stakes are high
I mean I'm a full Professor I have 10-year real steaks for me in this
Not really much
But will not everyone in the field is
Handling these
These kinds of niggling doubt
Sowell there so many pieces of evidence that things are not alright
This again is Michael inslicht the professor from Toronto
Alba face
Squid
Dr. The probability the likelihood
That all this might have been for naught
Or much of it
Vitamin for nausea
It's a loss of meaning
What was I doing good work with the contribute to knowledge
I would have part of the problem
Weather
No signal
I think the effect is Ino
It might be there
But it might be so small as to not be
Naughty meaning clean parts
How to say I know it's hard to know where to
And on this
Well one thing that you know
To make clear is it stereotype
You really damaging it mean having someone tell you
You suck at something when you're under
The gun to do it
That's always going to
You know that's going to happen effect I guess the question is
How you know
What affected
Exactly
And when
And how and why
What can you do about it and
And those
Things feel like maybe
I guess it feels like the part of me that wanted this
Be a kind of
Very simple fix
That would work everywhere answer
Save the world
You know that part
Bleeding Out feeling a little bit
Lot like wearing the
This whole thing is shrinking
Yeah totally
It does feel a weird little girl growing up a little bit
Is it you kind of have to walk away from the those big simple promise
Yeah maybe that's
Exactly what you need in order to be able to find the smaller place
This is for you
And have an effect
Right here right now with this
This person trying to do this
Particular thing
Producer editor sternwheeler
Thanks to him thanks I had an amber
This piece was produced by Simon Adler and Amanda are on check
Okay I guess we should go next to listen
Hey Liza
Anna Monday morning with staff credits and a strong cup of joe
Radiolab was created by Jennifer on
And is produced by sternwheeler Dylan cave is our director of sound design Maria Mickey's are pretty eyes are managing to
Our staff includes Rebecca Bressler Rachel Cusick David Gable Bethel habte Traci Hines
Vacuity Robert krulwich and McEwen Melissa O'Donnell.
With help from Amanda raczek
Shimano reel David Fox
Phoebe Wayne and Katie Ferguson is Michelle Harris