Are you weightless
Radio WNYC
And NPR
Okay so here's how I got to
I have a
Former producer
A good friend Pat Walters
Oh yeah yes
We responded and then he came to see me speaking summer
Yes and it was based on something he saw your talk about
Which is why I am now contacting interesting okay
Hey I'm Jared I'm Robert krulwich Radiolab a story about a set of pictures
Pictures
Yeah
Set of questions about those pictures regarding who gets to see the pictures
Who gets to decide who gets the ticket
Do we get to see the pictures
Well
Kind of a question
But I should say that there are some moments in the story that get a little
The word
Heavy heavy
To be forewarned
But we'll start with the picture taker
My name is Lynsey addario and I'm a photojournalist
Chicken covering War for the last 15 years
I've done military and beds
Infantry units patrolling going in house-to-house searches
She's worked in
Well everywhere Sudan Libya Lebanon Pakistani million places she's been kidnapped twice
You want to pull up ceramic Arthur and she's been called one of the most influential photographers of the past 25 years
In case this particular story that can you set it up a little bit
Shorts
So in December of 2009 for Time Magazine
Afghanistan
Kashmir District
Helmand Province
Station database
In the middle of the desert
I was
Embedded with the Medevac team and their role is to go in and pick up injured troops out of
The theater of war is a small team of basically helicopter Pilots Medics doctors basically whenever there's
Winter Soldier
These teams are called whichever team is closest to the injured Kentucky like helicopter dropping into
Yeah I mean this is fast
2 Lindsey had been embedded with this team for a couple of days
And not much will happen if you just sitting around reading magazines I've been re-reading the same magazines and one night
I think I was lying in bed and I was totally like if I wasn't asleep I was on the verge of sleep when they
Someone ran was like
There's an alpha alpha is like
Alpha means the most
Gravely wounded like you have seconds to get there I mean is it's life-or-death so she grabs two cameras her helmet body armor
Runs Out to the Blackhawk I strap myself in and we take off
And I think it was about a 2-minute
Flight which is so fast
And I remember I was shooting the fields as we flew in because I was trying to focus and see
But I can see luckily they had lent me a set of night vision goggles which was really nice of the military
Because you can't see anything without them in the middle of the night because they are using my fishing so they don't ever turn on the lights
Look see the camera directly you would see nothing just nothing so what you do for photographer do you put the night vision
Goggles in front of the camera lens so it looks green it's fluorescent cream
I mean the picture you get is green yes so they fly for two minutes to the pitch black land the helicopter she has no
No idea where everything is happening extremely fast I'm trying to focus as I'm looking out the helicopter.
And suddenly my viewfinder I see
A man
Serve wrapped I think he was wrapped in a blanket and he's
He gets
Courtright
In front of me on the floor of that of the Blackhawk
The first thing I thought
Is I think he's already dead
He seemed completely unresponsive
And he seemed so young I just remember looking at his face and thinking
By what are we doing here
Within seconds there are born again flying back
Field Hospital Lindsay takes pictures on that brief light back grainy fluorescent
Green images of the Medics 10 Soldier checking his vitals
Wheel and
At the field Hospital in the hospital tent
The anesthesiologist everyone is there a carry him inside and put them immediately on the table
Cut his clothes off their cutting his pants off open up his shirt and the room
Start filling up
With everyone because everyone has heard that there's a
And so troops come in from across the base
Children support
She says with a minister room went from the handful of people 5 6
Do a dozen 28 you can hear a pin drop
I'm in the room is
Silent except for the doctors
You know they're trying to resuscitate him he had lost I think eight or nine pints of blood they're bringing in blood
Everything in all sorts of things
And I
Well yeah of course you know I'm basically trying to be invisible because it's so sensitive to be a photographer
Current situation
What I do I don't shoot like thing I've ever I shoot
1 frame
And then I put my camera down
And I shoot another frame
Cuz you can hear the click of the shutter
And it is like exponentially louder than normal in a situation like that
What did you get did anyone look give you a look
Back off at one point I was shooting for probably
I don't know five or six minutes maybe and an officer walked over to me
And he said
Hey stop photograph
Yeah and I put the camera down and I looked at him and I said
I have permission
Kid worked all that out beforehand
What are the conditions over in bed at all these conversations you know what happens in the case of this what is my ass
Access what can I do but this one she says the room was full of people from across the base who didn't know any of that
Didn't know who she was but she had permission and so she was sort of at this fork in the road
There is always like that officer clearly felt with camera.
Stop
Obviously this is not the time to argue or to be disrespectful so I didn't say anything else I put the camera down but uses the moment she
She did that several other troop said no
Let her shoot this has to be documented interesting so you have one guy who says you can't take a picture of
Of this right almost like anything but this other guy is like no
This
Especially right right first of all the guy who said no was being protective it makes perfect sense for
But I think the guy to who stood up and said this has to be documented
I think it's some point everyone realize like look this war is not going away we are losing so
How many lives and Limbs and no one is seeing it
And keep in mind this is 2009 this is
Just the tail end of a
18 year ban where the news media couldn't even photograph
Military coffins
Andie Case the officer Let It Go Lindsey continue to take pictures for about another 20 minutes
She took pictures of the doctors cutting open the boy's chest massaging his heart at some point I remember someone one of the doctors
It looked up and said does anyone else have any suggestions basically 4 how to save him
And
Everyone said now and they should have disconnected the time he died
People were looking down and then they were looking at each other and
Someone went to go get a flag and American flag to drape over
First body I continued photographing and there was a moment where
The whole room was silent and people stood around
His body draped with a flag
And said a prayer
That to me
Is one of the most powerful images that came out of this whole series
There's an old idea in photography called the decisive moment
That
The world is filled with these far-off realities but every so often a photograph can capture a moment
Takes you there
This is one of those photos
And the picture you see all these men and women standing in kind of a loose semicircle
Some of them still have the blue surgical gloves on
They look totally spent
They're all looking in different directions
And they all look
You're not even there
I totally lost in their own thoughts
Their attention is
Clearly
In words
Yeah I'm sure all those troops were like
Cod it. Could have been me
Why couldn't we save him
What are we doing here in Afghanistan is this world worth it
And read the Expressions on their faces like it's even you can be at War as a journalist
Never actually get to the heart of the war because
We don't have access or people don't open up and I felt like I really had reached
Like the
Crocs in the war
State was war
Using an essence
If something
Attention problem
Any photos that she had taken that included that soldiers face
Or any other identifying marks like tattoos and he didn't have tattoos
According to the rules of her in bed
She couldn't use those photos without the soldiers permission you never got to speak to him
No
So was it
Days later
Weeks Later months later where you began to ask yourself can I eat it was minutes later
Military does not let journalists cover something like this without coming directly to that person and so
Literally like I followed
The young man's body out to the morgue
And had to walk him outside
And I remember it was the moon was so bright that night and I was shooting with the Moonlight as he was B
Carried outside
And then I went back to the tent where I was staying
Within minutes of the military payo the Marines public affairs officers
He said you know you can't send those images out without permission from the next of kin
That's the rule for soldiers unconscious and then dies before giving permission I have to then go to the next of kin then I said
Set of course I understand you know I'm not doing anything with those photos in that moment I sign this piece of paper
When I give my word I keep that word you know but then the other side of me was like
F*** you know in Vietnam no one was signing pieces of paper and in Vietnam no one had to
To go to the next to Kin before they publish anything and that's why the American public I think
Rose up against the war in Vietnam because they saw them was graphic devastating images that were uncensored
So then what do you do in that situation room science I mean
I imagine you go to the next of kin right well you're not allowed as a journalist to reach out to the next if they asked me are you
Are you interested in being contacted by the next of kin if they're willing to speak to you so you can even know
I'll give you the information but I said you know of course I would like to be contacted by the next Canon please
Pass my information on and
I was sort of just waiting
I'm at this point where you thinking the pictures that ever see the light of day
I had no idea
And
Few days later
Maybe you're less than a week
Her in bed was over she was flying to JFK on her way to meet her family for Christmas
And why voicemails on my telephone
And I listened that it was his father
Any left a voicemail and he said I understand
You were with my son
When he died
And I would like to talk to you and this is my phone number
I sort of choked up
Just listening to his voice
Anticipating how difficult that phone call with me
That phone call
When will The Fallout
Is coming up
My name is Lucina basilica
And I'm calling from my office in Houston Texas
Radiolab is supported in
In part by the National Science Foundation and by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public on
Standing science
And Technology
In the modern world
More information about slow net
Www.
Found.org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help this summer I'm hosting
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
About what we're calling tiny moments childhood Brilliance basically I want to hear about those times
So did something
It just means you lean back and say whoa how did they do that maybe it was the moment that I can
Kids you've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons and you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed are ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the specific moments where a kid does something super smart
Don't have anything to do with the test if you have a story please share it with us
Go to radiolab.org brilliance
Record short audio message for us
And that's where you live. Org / brilliance
Thank you so much
Gatime Jad abumrad and Robert krulwich Radiolab so lynsey addario photographer has these photo
He's intense photos of a soldier dying but you can't use them
Without getting permission from the next of kin
Right
JS later I had voicemails on my telephone
And I listened and it was his father
Father's name is Todd Taylor
Son's name is Jonathan Taylor
And just jump ahead for a second as we were talking about the phone call
And the Fallout from that phone call I had all of these questions about
What Todd Taylor was thinking at questions about a son things that Lindsay couldn't possibly answer so at a certain point you just tell
Tell me how to know I mean you could maybe interview on
Do you think you would that mean
Is there any
Provisional me Tottenham
Well I'd be happy to give you some I mean you can try
Lindsay put us in touch and I'll just about to visit for a second
Todd Taylor was willing to talk
Yeah two conditions one was like, do the story about these photos of us
Astonish at least get to know his son a little bit
And the second was that I come down to Florida to meet him and his family personally
Morning how are you
Taylor family live in a section of Jacksonville that's near Naval Base are there a lot of military families there
Doggie goddess XCX Navy himself
He introduced me to his three giant boxers themselves and then
Men's daughters I am Lauren Taylor I am 16 going on 17
Oh God my name is Mackenzie Taylor I'm dropping to their sister and I'm too
20 years old
Tell voice you're in the background is Easton he's about to
My name is Paige Larson and Jonathan step sister and I'm 21 my name is Sue Taylor and I
I'm Jonathan stepmom
And then of course I'm Todd Taylor on Jonathan's dad
We're here to my house in Jacksonville Florida
And today is Jonathan's birthday it's April 8th
2015 so he would have been held today
28 years old today
When I got there they pulled out photo albums of Jonathan we all set at the kitchen table
And look at pictures
Pictures of the baby that was
Very young
Toddler this was on the Disney cruise
I took him on adolescent can you space center teenager semen in track invite cross country
Going to prom that was Jonathan's girlfriend
Thing you notice immediately in all the pictures
And big blue eyes
Really blue
Boosted the brightness in Photoshop or something
Yeah that's I forgot I think we're on vacation here but
The class clown lot of goofy faces
If we knew how to make anybody laugh full of energy
Always into stuff
Just to see what grades they had
If I had a crush should be like Oh no you're not going to have a crush no no boys there was one time before he left for Afghanistan
But I really sick with a fever and I remember him holding my hand
Just so you can make sure that was okay
And took care of me
They told me story after story about how he doted on his sisters
I would love to read and want to become a history teacher after his four years in the Marines
And inevitably the conversation turned to the day that they found out he died December 1st 2009
They got a call from Jonathan's mom
I'm saying
The classic scene
Oh my God they're two marines at the door
And we just kind of like like left everything
Zooted the girls jump in the car race over
Who made all the girls stay in the car
I remember walking in the door and everyone just had this look on their face like
The world
It just ended
Dandong
I remember asking what happened
The first thing I did was run to his room because
Everything with the same before you left
Open having his closet
And I'm grabbing one of his shirts and just holding on to it because it still had it sitting on it
And I was really hard
One thing I never occurred to me
Totally caught me off guard in thinking about
Those pictures
Is that
When does Marines came to the door
And told them
The news
Well they didn't actually give much news
This right here was one of this is what was red
Galaxy read me the circumstances of death statement
Hostile action result of multiple traumatic injuries received as a member of a dismounted patrol
That was struck by an ID while conducting combat operations in the Helmand Province
That was that on patrol night Patrol that's all I had
She didn't know anything
That's it
Jonathan's unit was still in Afghanistan so he
Couldn't talk to anyone he had no clue what happened to his son so when that casualty assistance officer
Told him
I see there's a photographer in the room
With your son when he died
I'm a class like I wanted
Want to color
Earlier in my conversation with Lindsey I'd ask her
What do you remember the call
So the call
I went to my mother's house in Connecticut
And I asked my mother to be left alone which in a big Italian American family means
Look at me like what
What happened to the gas bedroom
And I called him
And he picked up
I think he thanked me for calling him
I don't remember exactly what we said but I said
You know
I was with your son when he died
And I will give you as much or as little information as you want
And he said
I want to know everything
Because I wasn't there
I was here
He said I want to know every single thing I want to be with my son not be there for him.
That's notes hard
Really hard
And I felt very awkward because I felt like
We know why was I privy to this moment and he is the father could not be perfect
Most important question me was
They suffered you think it is ever
I said
Now she told me Miss Taylor I don't I don't think you separate I think
He was in shock
I told him everything how much blood is Sun lost how long did they try to save him and at some point
I said look I have these pictures I have
All of these pictures I shot everything
And I need your permission to publish the ones that show his face
Oh yeah
She asked me a proclamation and
He was quiet
I said
I told her yes
But that
He said II can I see them
I wanted to see him first
Before I give permission I want to see every photo
And I said you know I'm not sure you want to see these photos
Cuz they're graphic but he wanted to see the outfit he wanted to see every photo all of them
Course I we were on the phone I couldn't jump pictures and legally I needed
Permission from Time Magazine to show anything because
It was a journalist you can't show anything to anyone until it's published you don't show people pictures of
Journalism before you publish them
This is one of those Cardinal rules it's drilled into every journalist said if you show a subject the raw stuff before it's out there
You kind of given up the only Independence you've got
That's why she says ordinarily I would never ever ever get out for a second if
He to be cynical about it if you show him the picture
He might take away permissions you might have otherwise give you exactly
Exactly you can say is a publication no I won't show those pictures before you have to just say yes or no
What do you give your permission
Like it anyway if you get down to it I feel like one of the fundamental layers here is just like a question of whose rights
Comes to that information is more important I could hear an argument that says
The battle is important it was authorized by public figures it is carrying
America's message into the world
And shouldn't Americans see what goes on
Yeah but I could hear an argument says shouldn't dad be able to protect who sees his son
Malaysian
Mini case Lindsay called redditors a time they had a series of conversations that went all the way up to the editor of time we had a
Very intense conversation and we collectively made a decision to show him the photos
To say that decision was unusual from their perspective
Would be severely underweight
When I first got these
I'm from
FedEx
I know they were coming
And
I was actually
Scared to look at
I saw my son there
I just kept looking
I don't mind looking
You can see
These were they in the Medevac when they got him on
You see the night vision lens there is Jonathan's body
I just there's a space thirsty ox
Plus watch on still she is as close to her that was
So many hands not working
Consider doing CPR there
No
Are you saying
Right leg is really
Mangled
Unbroken
That's really why I lost so much blood it was just
All right in here some of these pictures that are really hard to see ya
But
Leaving now
They show that messed up War
I got a piece of Jonathan
This is as my treasure
Now she want the pictures that
To me it's
It always stands out
He brought up the picture of the prayer
All those people standing in a semicircle
Far Away Eyes running
When you see a little different interfaces hair
I mean
Hitman something
He was somebody
It wasn't just a number
Dad said you wanted people to see this picture
And the others to convey
What's
Happy over there
This going on everyday
And he says for him it's not a political thing
You can feel however you want to feel about the wars were in
For him it's about
People seeing
What is actually happening when we don't want to
Let people say in the sacrifices they Boys Town
It took Todd and his family over a month to decide what to do about those pictures
Weather in Grant time permission to run the photos or not
He says ultimately he called Jonathan's mother over for her husband
And I'm
My wife and I
We all discussed it
And ultimately
She said no
And it was a lot of back-and-forth you said no to showing any pictures at all
Well he can't say no to any pictures because
Exactly
He said no to any pictures with the face or identifying marks
Wish I didn't really that
Waiting on these pictures to get out
Prepare that
Is sisters
Tell me how to get back to them and
That was the big thing
Adam Anthony belsito shot as her dad I want to protect them
I'm saying something
So
We decided not to do it
Time had planned to run a whole photo spread on the Medevac team trying to save Jonathan Taylor's life
Since they now couldn't use most of those photos
They have to make a photo spread more general what had been the basically the death of a soldier ultimately became
Photo essay on the Medevac team
And those pictures were maybe
Two pictures of three pictures in that spread but they were not the focus
Print photo is in the new Sprite because
In that photo
How you can't see the body
For the flag there no identifying marks
Somehow in that context
It's
It's not got the same in back
Ridley
Because you see me after without the before it exactly and Todd showed me
Original photo Sprite cuz I had sent that to you
You know again super on YouTube
This Is the End
This is the
Future they wanted to do
Yeah
See the pictures of someone's Montclair
This is
Tumblr layout is going to be
29 minutes
Scrapping it out minute by minute
This whole process
So there you see all the before pictures
Lead up to the
And what seems like if you don't see all that stuff though the wounds in the blood in the tenderness
As they tried to comfort him and then the emptiness they feel
When they couldn't save him
If you don't seal that
You're not really standing with him in that prayer at the end
You still seeing him across his face
The original spread
You are
There in that room
I did a they did a great job
You know
Really powerful
And
I couldn't help but think that like
Maybe
This would have created that conversation that Lindsey talked about
And how weird and I'm one of the only people
And to know that like I
The only reason I can describe it to you is come on the radio
You know I will always feel like
Journalistically
We we sacrifice you know we did not tell the story as powerfully as we could have
But we had integrity and I feel like we treated everyone with respect and we kept our word
Lindsay and Todd now stay in touch
Over email once or twice a year
And just keeping your word Todd has made a deal with his daughters that they can see the pictures when they turn 21 but interest
The three of them don't agree as to whether they want to
Paige Mackenzie
You are about to turn 21
Say they don't want to see the picture
I just couldn't handle it
Nothing for me I just don't want to see him in pain you know it's Mackenzie
Amber him in one piece how he was I'm just
She's sensitive
Bethpage
Now Lauren the youngest for me
She said she needs to see this picture
Because
I want to know what he went through and
I like constantly knowing things
And I don't like things being kept for me
I just want to
I guess I just want a visual
It sounds like she says she knows he's gone but she still somehow need to proof
Not that it happened she knows it happen
It's so it feels real
Okay so
Big thanks to Pat Walters
Kira Pollack
Taylor family and of course lynsey addario
She has a book out now called it's what I do
Which is sort of a memoir
About her War photography and how it changed her life
And that book is filled with
Photography anything like the wind
We didn't see
All this amazing pictures in there but nothing like
So yeah that's it
Robert krulwich
Thanks for listening