Forget started
We could ask your help on a little
Little something so
WNYC Studios
What is our home
Wants to get a clear sense of how you look
Listen how you engage the shows
Was that we make here
Shows like radio
So if you have a second there is a survey wnyc.org
Participate
It really helped us out if
Couple questions
That's WNYC.
3 / 4
And that link
Is also in the show notes
Thanks
Wait wait
Radiolab WNYC
Okay so then if
How we can introduce this how would you convince
The many people listening
Listening great story doesn't matter that it's figure skating it's like a really good story it's a good story that like
What's off of it's like I'm Jedi Cam'ron I'm Robert krulwich Radiolab and I've never been a huge
Savannah figure skating but like this story
I think asked a really interesting question
The question would be
What if you
With all your
Wanted to be
The best of Sade
But the persons
To judge what's the best
It's something you want to do don't share the best mess with your sense of business so you do your best in their best in your best or different
Now you can't
What are you doing
Story comes from our producer life
If Nasser and also
Tracy hunt okay okay okay
Okay so let's start van
It's okay so we're starting in 1998
Were the Olympics in Nagano
In Japan Japan and warming up on the ice
You have this woman this figure skater
Surya bonaly
How do you spell Syria
F u r y a
She French
24 years old
6lack
5 * European Champion but all sorts of problems particularly injury problems
That's been stitched together hold a muscle he's on painkillers
And computer for France in 1994
I just missed the party has never medaled at the Olympics
This is
Her
Probably her laugh
Go
In front of the world
The France
Here is
Surya
Bourelly
It was joined this performance bit Surya bonaly did something that had never been done by
Anyone anyone
As a as a kind of middle finger at The Establishment like it's huge
Oh my goodness
Just as beautiful
Moment of self-affirmation what you do
Lookbook
Hello
Hello how are you doing
Pretty good thanks I laughed out loud when I when I heard you say that you would call me on your Zamboni break
Idles like it's only time
Really understand just the context of
At all this and the six of that that moment
But we got to go all the way
How did you how did you first get in the skating well I did
Suffocating because
Of my mom actually I'm so sorry it was actually adopted
As a baby
By this white couple in the south of France
She grew up in nice my mom was a sport coach
And she was able to be
Like a volunteer for a gymnast
She club and Skating Club
So even though in our small tiny tiny
She just put me on the eyes and say hey just hang around and chill on the ice and
Spend lots of hours
Waiting for my mom
And one day I guess I find out that's a hot
Some skating boots
Fit me
She started
Fortunately I was good at 8
Pretty soon
She had two coats from the local ring I guess a coach can of cold and having meeting with your parents say Hey you know it'll be nice if you could come
Like two times a week
Let me know will be nice. Maybe four times a week while how about everyday
Here we go
Age of 10 she decides she wants to spend her life figure skater it was my dream to enough
To do it and I know I can so she would go lead Ice shows like holiday on Ice the One S is a show I love zucchini
I love you too
Showtime and just so you know
Fantastic costume see with the Aldi's Dana skaters. My eyes grew on those skaters
Flying through the air I thought it was like amazing but you would go to practice and she would practice
All of the things she saw that the double axel and triple toe loop
Spit gemz towels in the double salchow
And that you know quadruple double the triple Axel do you have any idea what you're saying
These are all just words to me it was very fast at improve. Every week every month you can see a difference
And speaking of different
You know if we fast forward a little bit
And here she is on the world stage Surya bonaly in 1989
Careers at the world championships
The thing that becomes really apparent is that she is
Different yeah
Because I was black so that people like what
French black so I'm black and
I definitely remember
When she was about to skate my mom would be like
The black roller skating so we all have to like pay attention and so
People's South
Can a
Curious
Is very different
Start with some
It was arrested that Janet Howard espn.com
Getting an exotic figure on the ice she is just arrested her eyes when she stated that the contrast of her skin on the ice was
And then there were these fanciful stories that
Sprung up about
Where she came from as far away as possible
Pretty much as soon as she hit the scene you started hearing these rumors that she had being adopted from a coconut
Trend beach in reunions island off the coast
Madagascar an unlikely place to find a world-class figure skater and that she had
Fitbit
What was it she never cut her hair
Herbert existed on a diet of birds
She didn't eat all these things
Siri says you know at that age
She really didn't know
Too much about what was going on
And all your kiddos like whatever my coach till it's you know he's the one who speak
She barely speak English
Young baby I did talk to the guy he was
Coaching her at the time this guy named Didier Guy gay
And he told me he planned to be
We use
Depressed very well
Play was he said that he made up the beach thing he made up hair thing because he was trying to
She was a star
And what do you want to hear
Stories
So we made some Stars
Some good ones
Do you know what I mean
I'm just saying that we making up stories
Because you want to hear
That is
Yeah you're absolutely right it's kind of see where he was going because
What he was trying to do with that he was trying to present her to the world
As is like
Radically new kind of
Because female skating at that moment
Where nice
Cute girls
Especially for ladies they like to
To keep little girls pretty famous skater like Katarina Witt
Katarina vet
Oh
Woman in those pretty graceful Nexus mens
Sinnoh crazy when they were watching it
They were also
Why
How would I say
Baby has a sudden
Conception
A female
We didn't have
It wasn't just that she look different
She also
Skate it
Different
It was a totally different approach Surya was always very like
Closest Elvis stojko is in the building
3 time world figure skating Champion for me it was sort of new
When you face on the scene, is the still like the fresh ticket young tiny fifteen-year-old French kahoot
Everyone's imagination to hear Tonya Harding Style skating is so exciting
Just no boundaries for her this is Tonya Harding
And she answering over friends strengthen the power except on the ice
People are crazy
Take off Surya would go from one end to the other hits speed across the online
Soaring through the air
What powerful spin Institute
Combination
Combination to do pretty spread eagle
And shoot attack
Everything is a reference to step sequence she had the the gliding
Running
She had it all what cloud here appreciate it
This sucks jumping ability and there's no end to what she might achieve
Outside of competition should be revised shows and exhibitions
And that's when you would see like whiskey
Can really do just do all kind of other jump
Backflip
Yes very first time that I ever saw her do a backflip I mean I just my mouth just draw
Dropped open that's honey Harding again I was like how did you do that cuz it's really dangerous Elvis stojko
Joe told us that one time he tried it and it did not go well
I came down right on my face
And I split my eye open
And almost broke my neck and I was like
You know I don't think this is going to be a good thing and just a little teenage girl Surya bonaly no problem
Just doing it like it was nothing absolutely Fearless
And the crowd loved it. Making noise in table fit
Into the grown
I can feel like the whole building building I'm like I swear it looks like an earthquake but
Here's what
And this is where things can I get
Felix
3 blows up and all these people who never like figure skating fall in love with her
Over and over
The judges don't artistic impression when you can see this Terry from
And the crowd do not like amox
Even with
Doesn't get high scores
No
Begin to flow
Have it all the time I skate dude
But somehow I
It's not for me in figure skating goes from Z
0 to 6
And on Syria's artistic marks
Get scores like
Yeah you get your low five would you like sounds like it's a good Market but that's not a
What did you think about Mark
Very very disappointed
She said nevermind that's life
I'm used to it
Excel Sports
Sportsman challenge
Everyday I try to do the best
Lava kudu
You do your best
Is fine
But clearly there were some times where I got her there was this one time we found on YouTube where she
Cabooze the judge
What her she gets her
Why was she getting bad marks
To begin with what
What was the problem
Well that's the question and it's
Kind of complicated yeah I think there's
Several things John Howard
That ESPN writer
The first thing you got to know and
Quick little dive into the weirdo world of figure skating
Is that there's this
Fundamental tension
In the sport of figure skating between
Artistry on one side
In athleticism Monday
Powerful Mistress of prettiness
Slate they want these people to look like little ballerinas but leap into these jumps
Looks like
Predators at the time Skating was sort of
Locked in the
Loud and fracture
Debate about
What do we want to be
And
Sorry I was sort of the epitome of
Almost the endpoint what could happen
If somebody with unrivaled athleticism and no aversion to risk
Was willing to go after it and I think there were a lot of people in the skating that didn't want it
I went through it
I know all about it
Tonya Harding's she said that she had this issue I didn't want to skate like what they wanted
Skating to look like
Elvis stojko two-button
Surya's case a lot of work to be done on my car
There's a lot of books
To be done on the grass all those words used to criticize her skating Salat 36th
I'd like to see your stop jumping for 6 months and learn to skate
We just a little bit more loaded
Baby taken glyco brought a lot of raw talent
But it's not
It's not fully kind of
I can be refined and
For us like none Skeeter's like that's one of the challenges of the story I guess it's like trying to see like
Is Zazzle legit
Criticism
Is this just a way of
Saying that
Cease
Black Beatles
Westies
I have the courage
How to say because she was black
This is Marie Wren Laguna and she is a former French figure skate
And she was part of it
Team whose job it was to decide which girls to send to
World junior Championship
And we have to choose to only two girls and we had
Three possibilities
She said that she backed
Surya
The majority of the
The people do don't didn't want the black
Cato's
Were they saying it out loud like we don't
Want somebody don't want her because she's like it was a very subtly inside
According to her what they would say she levitated kind of things like
She's too muscular or she wasn't elegant enough
Oh yes
I have to say that
That's what Elegance many times I have heard that
She's not there
Marie Wren is an outsider in the figure skating World these days because of an unrelated
Scandal and so we weren't
Totally sure what to think about that but
Wait how did
Sorry I feel bad
Well I asked her
Did you feel like any of the difficulty was because you're black
No
No no no
But then moments later she said
Well
I know
When you go black you know
Everybody knows that you have to do better than
Anybody else was white
Well
I think the idea that she was held back
In Martin her mark
For any other reason other than
The quality of
Skating I think his
Incorrect
That Sandra bezic
Has been involved
Skating World my whole life as a
Competitor is in
Olympian
Commentator
And actually as a commentator I'd like to see your stop jumping for 6 months and learn to skate
She was kind of hard on Syria
And when we asked her why
This is what she said everything about
Skating is built on
The radius could be huge but it's
Phyllis Circle
Everything is about edges
Leaning into those edges
And leaning into the
Returns
And in carving
Massive circles on the ice
And that is
R-sport
Which
Leads to Syria
And if you want to jump starter
They were on straight line
And
If a jump is on a straight line then it can't land with
Blow
Because the idea is
Tool and you jump
With as much
Evenflo is you
You had going into it
And that's something that she couldn't do because she was jumping on straight line
And in the other thing about skating that you don't necessarily get on
Is the sound of yet
The sound of
Of a beautiful
Skater going for
Edge-to-edge from lean-to
Celine
What is that sound like
It's a beautiful sound
It's a sound that we all love
It's a gentle carving
No no no no
No because
There's no there I can tell you
There are no scratches
It's a Glide
It's just that it's a ham
Is there a different sound to me like there's a sound of Brian Boitano's back crossover
You know used to
Like excite me when I was in the rink with
But then there's also
Sister did the gentle almost
Soundless
Quality of
So you can saute
Katia gordeeva
Weather like a witch
Farrah Fawcett
I said yet there
In a flipping from one address to another Edge
And forward to backward and it's
Almost
It's just a
This
Glide
I haven't got a good word
Damn it's a win-win 3 was hitting would she have that sound
No
She would be
Scratchy
Now we should say that wasn't the sound of Surya skating or any of those other people we just like
Mic'd up a whole bunch of
Like pretty good figure skaters with a professional skin yeah yeah yeah these are legit scared
Reset the clip
What is Sandra at
Since you gave me the thumbs up
Do we got a ride or whatever it is she is hearing and think yes I sound different
Not even that different really so that's exactly the problem ice skating is largely about aesthetic
So as far as it's like kind of in its own category
Like if you're talking about Serena Williams is facing a lot of these same kinds of criticism
It doesn't matter there's a line on a court and it's either inside or outside There are rules
Where is there aren't these rules
When it comes
The beauty it
It's super slushie
And that makes
Someone likes
Surya much more vulnerable
So what so what ended up happening
Well after a couple years of getting these kinds of marks
See
Best insults
I mean I was born March 1992 at the age of 18
I have new car garage
Change my whole skating rules you know I change poachers
And she decides to take the note
Jackie travel to California and works with Frank Carroll who's like this legendary American coach
And what you doing
Trying to be no
B
More graceful more beautiful more elegantly mohr Circle yeah
And
After that you kind of
You can watch the Youtube videos from that. And if
It's like she's a
Does it work
Yeah in 1993 in the world championships
She comes in second
And then by the time I'm a 94 rolls around she is a favorite she is she busy
Probably going to win
And
What happened
Things take a risk
Estranged
Will be back right after the same Bonnie Brae
Hi there this is Kirsten recording from Orlando Florida Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan
Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world more information about Sloane at
Ww.w. Sloan. Org
This is Radiolab skip back to our story
Eeyore
Benalia
French
From producers Tracy hunt
And
I was really curious what
What happened at that at that medal ceremony in 1994
Iaaf world championships
Well we had this world championship in Japan
17 World Champ
Justice at the world championship
Are the second most important event
And at the Olympics
Richard get the month before the top three ladies sixteen-year-old Oksana Baiul Oksana Baiul
Nancy Kerrigan Nancy Kerrigan got silver
Chan luu got the bronze
Sports please
What's urea
Now those top three ladies
Oksana Nancy Liu
Out of the picture
Injuries
Some turn pro in
Whatever point is at these World Championships
The the highway had been cleared for Surya she was going to take it
Is a purse for the ticket
So jumping forward to the final day of the champion
Surya is in second place
60 years old
From nice
South of France
Start the program
Immediately starts with his double axle occur incredible after that is just
Triple triple triple triple triple
One of the baskets of her life I know I did my best I did everything it was not perfect because nobody's perfect but pretty good
Good condition overall eventually after about four and a half minute to finish
Escape json loads and loads of testicles
The question is how will I see her artistic after
And she goes over
Beside to a bench
With her coach
To await her
Results
S59 goes are as high as any we've seen
How to get your marks
She jumps in the first place and then and there's only one skater left
It's a skater who usually finishes below three-eyed comedy
Yuka Sato
Again that's Sandra bezic we all know you could
The smile on you
Your face Nuka was you know one of these really
Lyrical skaters painting is return Elvis stojko and you can have it
How does very beautiful
Chipper skating
Gentle almost soundless
Quality
Like a whisper across the ice
Physically hurt
Skating style was the exact opposite end
From Sirius
21 year old son Tokyo
So she gets up does her final skate in for the home crowd
My favorite skaters but she doesn't know she's going to need all her jumps opening up
XXX
And she gets her first jump
Crowd loved it and me but she was prettier
It in her routine there were these moments where it just
Looks like some sort of skipping
Crusty eyes
Just very balletic moves
It's good to know
Just one here at makuhari event center 4th the local favorite Lucas
Songs to Sato of Japan orbitalia France
You know get off the ice she goes to wait for her marks
Birthmarks of course for technical Merit bowling alley strength osako stated
And every one of those marks except the Finish judge
Go to bowling alley she wins 8 out of 9 technical Merit
The light came down to the artistic mark But the French judge
Giving her higher marks
What this is going to be closed
It actually ends up being a tie
So it goes to being a timer
And that's been the the judges basically pick for 2nd and 3rd
And in a 5-4 decision
The new world champion
Unfortunately the truth hurt
Medal ceremony
What happens next is
One of these moments that really defines serious story for a lot of people
So what happened was that
Right after all the results were out
He set up the medal ceremony they called out
Skaters they first
Called-out yuca
She comes out from
Tunnel backstage under the ice
What about waves Smiles everybody
And then
After about a minute
Syria
But
Where is the European Champion all the cameras Friday around and
Timeout
Not an idiot
How late arrival and here she comes
Cheapskates out
Santa dice
She weighed but her faces
Smiling
No and then when she gets to the podium she congratulates you Casado
But then
Finally has chosen not to stand on the podium
She just stopped before getting on the podium she just stood right
Next
I think this is a form of protest
I really hope she doesn't go through with this she wouldn't stand on it she was crying
Elvis actually was in the crowd watching
I feel bad for her cuz I know what she was going through
Where
You know you out skated
Your competitor and they just wouldn't give it
And I was like Siri adjust
Get on the podium
Take the metal
International skating Union president Olaf
Official is giving out the medals he gives you cuz of gold put it around your neck
But then when he turns to Surya he just sort of
Stands there looks at are you said something that you can't hear what it is
She shakes her head
What's the metal around Serena's neck
Shakes her hand and he holds her hand and it's kind of like
Is her off the podium
This is a first for me that's for sure
Takes off the middle
I'm not sure if she takes
It's over metal off of her
Had
Play call my God he's actually doing this news huge
It was huge he was a huge deal
The camera Zooms in on her face and and she is just
What's going on inside
That young woman
So after the medal ceremonies over
She just gets mop
Why would you not accept what was the problem
I'm just disappointed
What are the judges unfair to you
You're saying
Did you deserve the gold medal Syria
And eventually what she says
Is I'm just
And I'm just not lucky
What what was going on like what happened you use I seen was more like a plan Jose is this it it stop now
Can you put your fist on the table
Enough is enough.
Say Hey you know
I'm not dumb and I'm just getting sick and now I'm sick of it. I keep my eyes open that is not fair
We have those task. I was just sold
Depressing
And was so not fair mostly it was not fair
What about it felt unfair
Joseph Savino
Up and over and over so many times that's every time
It's never me because whatever I can do how many people I can be pretty I can have the best choreographer I can so everything was made
To be on the top
I'm like what do you need more me to do I just want
You know how many triple-triple you want me if I don't do you kill me
And if I do
You don't care anyway you took somebody choose somebody else
Don't you think
But that's a little
Unsportsmanlike
Yeah totally absent
Yeah but if she's other girls have to work just as hard as she has one cuz UMES
Sure but okay so picture yourself if you're at that
Is it your you're in that position you find yourself getting second second you feel like you're not
You're not she came in second that always had the margin with
So close
It was so close
I just more like soap empathy for heart for her
Can't imagine what it
Be like
Like anime
What atmosphere
But you know in that kind on that scale
To be the only one
Xerosis
Anything for you know
A friend of mine once told me that racism can make black people crazy
Which is very very broad way of looking at it
In the sense that you kind of almost never know why people are reacting to you the way that they do
And it's it and it's kind of a
You're always sort of second
Guessing
You know what's up
You know that
Did they go that guy just came and he said hi to everybody in the room but he did say it to me
What is that what was that
There's no obvious thing about it but it can make you feel
A little paranoia a little
Crazy now I cannot
Put myself I can't imagine how
YouTube Sevilla felt in that moment
But I didn't necessarily like think that you know these
Prejudiced people had denied her this if anything I felt more like
Man
It really must
Skating at that kind of level
And not really understand
Why
Things Are
Gormiti
It must be like a very confusing
Situation to be in
And that is in and it was more like empathy
Don't know
You know if if if if
There was racism
Quite frankly Yuka Sato is an amazing skater it's very legitimate
Feel
Like you
Put your finger
Never goes away
No
Never
Always there
And always
Happens what happens
That's a pretty
I think that I think the the wreck that she got after this moment was that she was a sore loser
And that she was Define
That
She had a bad attitude
Does she
Quit at this point
Well she keeps going
She competed again in the world championships in 1995 the very next year she came in second
Again again
3 years
In a similar pattern was there like
Just the 100
That one wasn't as close
Second again for the
I think seriously no European championships you know Skate America
Is doing a lot
Not at the Olympics not at the world championship
But I guess it depends on how you define
Find First
What do you mean he said that actually takes us right back to the beginning
We're here live at 10 a.m. on Saturday morning in Japan
So bored but
Remind
Where in Nagano Japan
1998 Winter
I knew it was my last Olympics in the last
Major major big competition and everything was fine until the day before
The short program
I pulled a muscle
Her left
And I couldn't leave
I can do anything
To make matters worse Surya. Moment was already recovering from a ruptured Achilles tendon
To carry me
To walk stairs because I couldn't get there so you have to leave me to go to my room because you're not doing a village
I couldn't walk
You know even broken I'm damaged I'm like a used car that's really good good for Life trash
I'll let you know really I was so messed up
Between my legs
But in my achilles I was like
Nas the disaster
And the doctor said maybe we should withdraw and I know I'm already here and I don't want to
To trust me retires my
Probably my last option I don't want to dress
Metallica
Just give me anything you can
I have to keep going
And so on the final day she says that she
Between May DC massage acupuncture Hills
She goes back out on the ice
And is now getting ready to skate
For her country
Golden blue
Sequins outfit and
She starts her
You can tell she
Favoring one leg but she manages
Didn't work for the Telco
Get back up
Going through her routine
Triple sow-cow
And then she said
Chillicothe this point where
She couldn't do it
It was so much in pain
I hadn't oceanos program I was supposed to go
But you know what I don't feel it I know I'm going to crash I can do I'm not capable
My leg is not
With me anymore
And then what comes
There is this movie
House in a repertoire that you
Can do
But it's illegal
A special thing in my backpack and say hey I can't do it
Is my last
Is molluscum t-shirts or going through your mind was you were skating
Yeah oh yeah you know me is like a computer if you know if I would have missed something or dramas okay here
I can see the triple here
I was there I can do a combo triple triple I know I need to feel something you're like the GPS lady you're like recalculating
Turns around from getting forwards to skating backwards
Picks up speed just like she's about to do triple
But she does
Backflip
But not any old backflow
Sheetz Wings on leg over
Blitz
In the air
Upside down and then she lands on one
Oh my goodness
What is it when you do the backflip do you go do your skates go up towards the ceiling and then come back down underneath you again
I just am having trouble Avenue
Because it
It's so dangerous
Also she says you're supposed to land all your jumps on one foot
But she did that
You didn't want photo just hold hold I just want this whole
And couldn't be like totally illegal because they are as long as laying on one food maybe we'll be
We will sing about
And she finishes her program with her back to the judges
And you know usually is it you skate you perform you smile in front of the camera but was it gives a mock neck skater
Call me to collect 10 minutes seriously 10 minutes people think about what should we do
Do with me and I said whatever just put a zero and so we can move on there or the marks that you get mailed
Presentation absolutely 48522 how do you get noticed in Olympic competition
Nope so she ends up finishing
Intense
I like yeah I finished and it's okay
Adele afterwards a lot of people interpreted that backflip as a
Big fat middle finger up
To the entire
Skating World I know you don't want me to but I'm going to do this anyway
When I asked no
I don't know what
I was just trying to
Be happy
She said she just wanted
Something that was her
Yes
Yes I had anyone ever done this
Backflip onto one blade before
No
No no no I'm the one who created this one
His wife is a Benelli
Oh that's what I'll do
The only one who did it
Wow
You're the first person in the history of the human race who has done that
So I'm not going to with a jalapeno
I'll be able to die in peace don't steal my backpack it's mine
This mine
So I'm just
Kings like what is happy
Story end
Well as she retired from figure skating after
The 98 Olympics
She continues
What to do
Isozaki
Occasionally
But right now I think the main thing that she's doing is she's coaching she was in Minnesota
And she's coaching and skaters yes
Black women weed
Ask people like oh did she
She
Did she changed
The sport
Did she change figures
Answer the
Giving
No
Oh she did
You know sound like all of a sudden
Ito figure skating rinks across the country but across the world are flooded with
Little black girls learning their sock house in their Lexus and things like that
I will say for my
From what I can
Until
For the first time that there are
There's more than one
Black
Skater
Competing
At the same time internationally at least by their backflips
They are still
So
This is sort of like
Almost
This way to blip
On the skating
Where's he was just
You know no one would like her before
And there hasn't really been anyone like
But there is this kind of ironic
I guess we just did
If
You took her and
NNU put her in competition
Today if she was
Competing on the world stage
Today
She would
Probably do better than she
She did back then
They've changed the
These are the scoring systems hope so now
You get points
For doing the kinds of power moves that
She was doing way back when and and even if you if you spill even if you fail at those moves
You still got
You get points for trying
Yeah
For daring
And Syria was
Is Darren
Vdara
British lot of Nasser
In Tracy
Tracy spent the last few months with us
Producing that story is part of the WNYC
Fellows program Tracy we will miss you
The piece was produced by Matt kielty
Original music format and also from filling teeth
Special thanks to Vanessa Riley Moira North skaters Eliza Anjali
Christian Irwin from the Ice Theater of New York
Internet Haber
For recording it all
And a very
Heartfelt thanks to Marilyn Wiggins
I'm Jad abumrad
Thanks for listening
Start of message
Isla T's this is Tanya, this is Sandra bezic
Jad abumrad
Design for n wheeler is senior editor
Simon Adler Brenna Farrell David Gable
And Molly Webster
Withheld from Alexandra Lee Young
And Micah loewinger are fact Checkers are Eva doctor and Michelle Harris
I wonder if you can hear the truck outside
Hope that's okay and on behalf of everyone at the Radiolab
Bye-bye
And this message