Are you awake
Northern listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
I'm a patrol which Emily Webster's is Radiolab and this week at Jad is off
Nestled into his office working on the next episode which will play with a lot of the ideas
I came up in our in our last
Gary Hart
Podcast but like with pop stars in music we've decided to offer you guys
A little
Valentine's treats
It's going to be part Pros
Arts musical in hip hop
Soda weigh
With some extremely
Cool gas released by promise you yes
Animal grows out of a tail we heard
About a very
Small app
Animal which begins
Appropriately
Pretty very small
Noise
Yes I was saving in days
Stung by people
Tended to
Diet higher mrs. grab a couple hundred years before the hospital
This by the way is David Guzman I'm a professor of biology at the University of Sussex in the UK
Nostalgia producer
So you mention that that
Grandpa's
A land looks like he might die soon
I just want to know why that's funny but sit and stand
It would be out of respect
Would be very quiet
Creeping around the house
And when everyone was really quiet
They tear these faint drumming noise coming from the from the Timbers of the hives
I can try and do an impression of the noise I hear you very well
You get that
Yeah
Yeah so
506 identical beat
End and Legend has it book
Was the Medieval drumming his fingers and patiently waiting for the soul to depart the butt
But
Wenzhou actually it's the mating call of a tiny little beetle
The death-watch beetle
Before it gets its name
So they became a kind of a fan of these
Yeah it's a widespread species and he's got a house that's
It is
Pretty decrepit is
Slightly falling down the roof leak
Whatever but is it hiring to a whole host of
These little people
And in the quiet he can hear the
So a while ago he found himself wondering what's this noise really loud
At which you might not think would be a great mystery
But what he discovered is It's All About Love
Or at least
Sex
So today
A story that reminds us so difficult
Lonely
How hard
The Mating Game can be
Perfect Valentine's Day
At the beginning of the life cycle
Yeah so so the female betta lays an egg
At peace of death
Basic he would watch the
And the moms we just
Drop their babies randomly
Here
There
Usually into a hole in log
Going to a would be a little tiny boy
Grub
So you might have to pitch black
Do you have any time on its own
I need stop chewing
I choose away at the woods
Very very slightly
And eventually
10 or 15 years later years it going to shoot for 10 to 15 years
Yeah it for a decade or more
Whole thing and eventually it reaches the Magnificent size of about a quarter of an inch
Which point is
Heights at turns into a little little chrysalis
And a few months later
Seattle beetle
Tattoo sizes
Until finally it crawls out of the log and onto the
Is that the first time they see light
Yeah yeah
That would be it
3070 the adults that you have a really
See
I'm possibly the most boring looking insects
Bullet shape
Still Brian
They really easily mistaken for mice
Things actually end
The beato Lenny has really one job and that's tonight
Shop the male betta
Has to find himself a female
Who is aeschylus work for one thing as an adult
He doesn't
Econ Fades series
Going to starve to death in a couple of weeks so side on top of that he's nearly blind
Yeah that's where this strange
Drumming noise
Comes in
That's bad why finding each other in the end in the usually roll the dock
Places where they live
That's your way of saying
Hello
Hello yeah and they make it by drumming the head
The male betta Lee kind of braces himself and then he wipes his head 5c
6 *
Oh you start rubbing your head you mean banging your head
Yeah it's like headbutts the timber he's sitting on but he's kind of full head if you like
So that's what makes the drumming noise
Buccaneers head against the wood
So
He comes out of his
Just one day
Disease little drumming
Noise
Now if a human happens
To hear him
People these days they tend to spray that
Houses with inside
I didn't like the end of The Beatles
But
Lettuce you
Assume that he doesn't okay
He just keeps wandering by banging his head
Any poses for sex
I'm listening to see if anyone reply
Reply you want the zone
Unfortunately
According to David
Deathwatch beetles quite rare these days
Except there is a distinct chance will never find a female
This just gets more and more depressing
Can you tell the same story from the from the female's perspective
She just sort of his
Is she just
Waits in silence
For three weeks and if no one comes she just
She just purchased
She doesn't she wanted to ride a little bit I spies in the in the hope that she might
I might help it that's what that's
That is all she does
Tedious life I'm afraid
But let's imagine
Begin for the sake of argument
That's after the 15 years of chewing and no fumigation
At all
Really
He gets a reply
Big fine teacher
She makes the noise immediately after
Is she hears the cry but of a male
And he get Ben gets very excited
Could you buy if you're wondering about Chinese headed for today's
And this'll do you at get scared
He stops running around banging his head over and over again
This is his moment and eventually
Eat more often than not he would eventually
Find a female in jail
Belial will immediately jumped on top of Eden
Continues to draw me his head but this time he's not head-butting the timber he's he's walking her
Which Wich Dominique that works for a
The female that's what's Pizza
Because they very short-sighted they will often jump on the runway rang
And and that's that's not so good
Because the females can actually control the cat he called. Tonight so he has to persuade her
Tequila price
Well so you usually she she carries on replying
Finding hair in the back of the head and she's she's
That's usually a good sign that you if she carries on buying a head on the on the 10 but that means she's probably going to make it in the end
Within the next minute or two
Birthday says when he has watched this happen
He's noticed that caught up in the females wouldn't matter what even though you know that maybe been sitting there for days waiting room
Finally doesn't he finally gets
They're not interested
To me this is a very
Discerning lady that she
Chooses death over and ugly
Make well I guess she's not
She's hoping that she'll get a Best invite another fish in the sea another fish in the sea
But I told what's the difference why are some male successful in Sumner
I need quickly became clear that the heavier the man the more likely he wants
2 BC
Successful
There's some explanation
Hawaii
They produced
Staggering amounts
What do you mean by stagger
The average was 13% of his body wash
13 /
What he wants us like what would that be like at 3 or 4 gallons
Pho
Think about that from girl just best not to think about that too much pretty disturbing
So the Deep tragedy
Would be to be a member of this species and to be born
Scrawny
Scrawny how big are you
Really skinny should I be in trouble anyway
What do I really want you tonight what
Where the females actually
Just weighing in the mail
I also was it something that was car lights with being a Big Mac
Maybe they were
Strong girl made a lot of noise
The ugliest way to try and
Fine.
Restaurant officially changed
The weight of the male
To make tiny fat suits
For the exactly yeah I'm not quite but
I wish this work for people that would be hilarious but it
We have the stuff called Blu Tack in the in the UK do you have Bluetooth
Sticky tack I guess he used to stick posters on the wall
So Dave went to the store bought some of the stuff and then just beat it up into little bits and
Stuck them on the back of
F mail
To make them a little bit heavier
And for the skinny males it would
Apsley tree tinsel
I do feel slightly main but they spoil females obviously we're getting a bit Short Change
But
Hopefully they managed to produce some eggs anyway they find these beetles the males and the females surprising
Pycharm
And after all he doesn't live with
A lot of
Play stealing my hypothesis
Chewing away at the beams
I I've been
I told you a part of me knows that if I didn't spray them
Some insecticide been eventually
The three.
It's going to take decades
Wind Point Lighthouse
Safe for the moment I bet they've been spayed and
Antique white light listening to them
Tuckaway in the springtime
So you're sitting in bed at dawn or dusk
Can you hear the
Quiet banging and you think
Yeah
Yeah it's it's it's funny as me the people full this was a Sinister noise and actually it
It's All About Love
Thank you to Dave goulson who wrote the book all about these bugs a buzz in the meadow the natural history of
French farm and he has this little place in France
It goes to one month a year and that's what he communes
Beetle friend
And has one of them
Saddest months
Thinking about this drug I found it it made
Give me think that dating a New York was pretty easy
But for people who are feel if you're feeling said we want to end that problem right away in the next
Part of this show
We're going to revisit this story in such
Recently new way for us
The guys from Hamilton
Hot Broadway show
I told some of them this story that you just heard and they have decided
2 m
2 musical.lys
Detail and they will do that
Right after this beef pot pie over for a while during the pause
You know how raunchy this story is well it is only gets more so when it's in the musical tell so you might want to ask you
Your little ones
To leave the room around now and then you should by all means stay
This is Melanie coming from Durham North Carolina
Radiolab
Play supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding
Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloan
Wwd
W. Sloan. Org
I'm Roberto which I Molly Webster this is act to it which I we don't want to put together these any story
As you know I just wander around until
Every single person I know
So I got to be strangers as I was talking to
To a friend of mine who's in the theater
We can help him talk to you in a second I'm wondering what's going on in the mind
Abuse
Little
They have mine
Ansel Adams
It seems so unfair
So we could be those people who's the we
But we is an improvisational
Freestyle group called freestyle Love Supreme and it's now this I should tell you
Tommy goes
The lin-manuel Miranda
Is no joke who is Hamilton
I meant they go to guitar
Ambedkar who was in a movie called pitch perfect when he played a rap
Oh yeah by Wiz all guys
In an Elizabethan Beetle situation is Shakespearean deathwatch
That's right well the lady by Speedway by mail toll is going to be a woman
What time is going to be the man
So here
Is the male beetle
Being the beetle that he
Poops he can be
Hey ladies I said the wait is over get ready for the beautiful Beto Casanova he is all
I and I am him the most masculine be so by the name of slim the evolution may be small so I can slip through the cracks up
I'll be the first one to jump on a lady Beetle back but it's hard out here and I'm not playing
They think that they don't understand
Slimmer so I'm a winner I finally see the sun people shorty and I know that you the one so I'm like Beetle baby doll
Let's get involved I want to give it to you all right
Feel so good and why
Yeah I guarantee I'm your chosen but can you remind me which end goes in
Is it hard
Yeah but I doubt therefore a beetle but for the female play by Lin Miranda I mean she's going to have her own agenda
Needs to find a guy in half
She hopes it will be the best guy but I don't know
Could This Be Love
My mama told me to never said I was good as I was to
I'm looking for a hottie with a body for the sperm and deep.
When you hear that knocking
Somebody's knocking
Power of the female
And the sadness for the guy
But this is a Valentine's pic
And she's like oh my god I've waited 15 years for this and I can't do it with you
It's just a move on and fall off the table okay okay but now you know
That Professor goes in his are Cupid
Both of our sad soul
This is the kind of lame validated here is
Finish
Char on Valentine's Day
Lil Romeo and Juliet is
Again
I'm going to make
Yumani I'm half-blind
Where are you trying to put the work in beetle
Baby doll don't let me down
Loose inside your caboose
Okay but seriously I got no clue what I'm doing so if you could help me out you'd be doing me a real solid
Little did she know before I beat it
The doctor help me
I cheated
Slim Windsor
Okay it is time request for us to go thanks specially to Freestyle Love Supreme into cuz I'm a car
Otherwise known as utk to Thomas koln to lin-manuel Miranda
Episode Soren wheeler
And Simon Adler thank you thank you I'm Robert jovic
Emily Webster and happy valentine
Happy Valentine's Day Robert YouTube
YouTube
Message one
Hi this is Dave cokin a message
Advocate B
Credit Solutions
Radiolab is produced by God
How to correctly
David Gable
Not guilty
Lubbock Master Chelsea projects
Are we on
Molly Webster
How do you spell New York
We count from Alexandra DeYoung
Icy Hot
And Meeker levenger
Time in Shanghai
Lauren Daigle
Good night
And this message