Any pro you there
Yeah I am
Hi
High Beast allergic to meat course you are
That's totally
It's okay I don't miss it anymore
Gate jet here before we get to the show I want to reintroduce you to
What's a my name is Amy
Remember Amy from an episode we did a couple years ago about
Ticks and meat allergies and
We brought her back into the studio because she is now
Hosting your own podcast
It's pretty great
Call ten things
Scare me
End the show 10 things that scare me
Name kind of says it all
Because a couple times a week they put out of show
Would they come out three times a week so holy moly
The really short
I mean for podcast
Unprecedented
Each episode is only
About 5 minutes
Microdose
Each episode you hear one person
Explaining their 10
Greatest
Steers and explaining why each of those 10 things scare them
What was the idea behind it
Add
I feel like radio is not weird anymore
41 and Iris Leaf wanted
I'm like let's make it weird
And so a while back she heard this recording
I'm Ida
Dino
Custom kit
Download yes I'm a friend from work
Made me listen to the
A recording of their kid
Has made a list of things
We think are really
Scary a recording of things that they were afraid of because
Of the pipes
The pipes of scary when you look up at them
They look like they're going to suck you into the tube
And I listen to it so many times because I'm going to take you back to like
Those pipes are scary
Until she was like if it's compelling
To keep your kids talk about their
You don't even really know
What if we actually heard people that we did no tok
I'm afraid of poisoning but even more than I'm afraid of poisoning I'm afraid of my
Fear of poisoning that got an episode with John Green author of The Fault in Our Stars number two
Divorce attorneys
Anthony the mooch
Scaramucci divorce attorney was fantastic by the way Miss literally become a very close friend MP3
Comedian Jo Firestone appointment Ali where unicycling seems cool Nae even sick
Can you also hear plenty of not so famous
People people who are like
Thoughtful
Manchester Industrial
I recommend this podcast
It's really fun if
If you downloaded you will not be sorry I even did one
You may hear my voice in the flow of things
You can subscribe on app
Apple podcast
Or wherever
You get yours and if you are a thoughtful anxious fearful person
The 10 things team wants to hear your fee
You can record them and find out a whole lot more
10 things podcast
Are you awake
Radiolab WNYC
Oh my God I wouldn't know this
I
Hey I'm Chad I will run
Is Radiolab and we've another story for you another adventure
Courtesy of
Who else will reporter
The the way I first learned about the story is that I saw that there was this article trending in this
The players Tribune which is like a ton of athletes
Magazine which
Are you subscribed to
I'm the only scrawny Couch Potato race
Basically
But anyway that
The
The thing that
Jumped out to me
About this article
Is that it's a sport story but it's
Is actually so much more like it is a story about
Voting
About cyberbullying
The story about you know
Taking it to the establishment it's a
It's a sports story but it's
Like is one that
Feels like it could only have happened at this very specific moment that we're living in
Right now yeah I mean I don't know if we can always
Paint
Sports as a microcosm of
Society
But in this case
It's undeniable that it was
To the whole story starts with this guy
Graduation
Hockey stuff
Greg is a hockey Journal a senior NHL writer for ESPN known to his Legions of fans
Puff Daddy
That is self given name know he got it from his editor when he first started blogging about hockey the other option
The time was Zamboni Pony
Which would have been a horrible name
And I very much avoided an entire
You know 10-year Runner
People calling me the pony true
Right but now I have bites
Avenue
I am ready to roll now
Okay well let's just jump in
Yeah so we our lives
Story really begins on the podcast that I did with the gentleman by the name of Jeff Marek
Basically couple hockey writers
Shooting the breeze on hockey
November 2015 few months before the NHL
You know big midseason
Spectacle
To Amalie Arena All-Star Game
There's a sense
Should I have
About this game
It's worrisome
Is this year
Yet again
The NHL for the hundredth time in the last 15 years
Changing the format of the all-star
Hockey typically five-on-five 3 on 3 however is supposed to be like
You know way more action
Taurus
Jogasaki puree
They're like yet again the NHL is just changing things up to get more eyeballs on this game that
By this point has just become water down
Cast
Joke of a game
So the two of them as many die-hard traditionalists do
Go off on the NHL
And eventually that leads them to talk about the other what they see is the other really dumb thing about that year
All-Star Game
Fan voting has long been apart of the game
The kid
There's nothing else better
Then grab a little punch card
At a game
I trying to grab like 30 of them
To make sure that you know
Kirk Muller
But over the years the NHL have started reducing the number of players that could get voted in one year they were Eva
Turning off the boat when they didn't like where it was
Headed
And anyway this year
The NHL has limited the vote so much
Did the fans could only vote in
4 players
The captain Bridge division the Pacific to Central the Atlantic the Metropolitan
All you could vote in
What the All-Star Game
History tradition should be to what we really want
With this All-Star game which is
Fan engagement
I just hope that everyone
That somehow a collective and maybe we can meet
And that point they start thinking
What if we use the little voting power that we do have
Mess with the all-star
We need some we need someone in there who normally would not be in this game
Like is a joke
We should vote somebody in who just does not
And Greg's like I like that thought
Okay
But who
Fit the bill there and it was thinking about it he thought you won't be funny
You don't really mess with you
Is if we told in a player player who couldn't really keep up couldn't really shoot couldn't really handle the podcast
The slow guy with a bad hands
What's what's what's really you know drop a stink bomb in the room
And then
Github
The perfect guy
A Goliath of the league
Oh my God John Scott All-Star
John Scott
He was a guy that would only play between like 5 and 8 minutes and night couldn't really shoe
Couldn't really stay and on top of that
When John Scott was on the eye
Unacceptable the only thing he was good at knocking other people
In hockey terms
Scott has a predator John Scott was what you would call
An Old Fashioned
Goon
Oh my God that's the one he's the one
From that point on there was no other answer to the question like that was the guy that it would have to be
And what started there as a train joke between two guys on a podcast
Would end up wasting the fate and Fortune of one of the most
Beard load
Punishing players
In the National Hockey League
You be quiet
Yeah
Change some things for his family to
Be soft
Hello
Hey okay I'm calling you from my cell phone how's that much better
This is John yeah we're good morgan gave me the thumbs up
Alright great
Okay I might my daughter's here too so if there's like sounds
It's just my daughter Cruiser
No that's cute I love it
Okay go
To really understand what it was like for John to be on the other end of that to be like
You know what the butt of a joke
You need to understand what
Hakeem antigen
Like what it meant for him to be playing in the NHL
Like everyone has their dreams like
When your kid Express Estates football baseball Canada
When you ask a 7 8 year old weigh
We do those projects in class what do you want to be when you grow up
And I think 90% of the boys
I'm going to be in the NHL and I always said that my parents have all that stuff all over the walls and stuff
But yeah I always
Dreamed of playing NHL I think everybody
That was a big dream so
Yeah so John has dis
Classic Canadian hockey kids
StoryBots on skates when I was three my dad built the rink in the backyard played all the time every single day morning Newnan
And you just go to sleep in your gear and wake up and just jump right on the ice
Skate until 7 or 8 at night
And you just jump in bed and go to sleep and he just kept it on to save times.
But
The thing about John
With that even as a kid I was a monster
I came out of the womb
524 and a 1/2 in long and I was
11 lb
12 lb I was huge
School pictures with a joke everyone thought it was like
A teacher's assistant when I hit like grade
Seven ate nine because I was so tall
And
When you're young and you that's all you have
Zero coordination
Until John was
Never the top Dynasty
Never the fastest
It's never the most skilled never
You know the best of anything I just kind of telling my daughter to start applying to panel beside us
Yeah
Is he
Are you okay with the piano and see if I can
I'll get her out.
Thanks
So you
Is there something you said that you
Let me let me put her to bed 1 Second Star Realty
Keep you on the phone
She cries
Good questions
Yeah from Mississauga
So what year in Boston York now
I am calling you from Boston my cell phone is Boston my job is in New York but I actually live in LA
Oh wow you're just like all over or not
Oh yeah I'm not I mean I feel like compared to you you've been all over the map for real
All right
You going to let me
Now she's done
Perfect
What kind of chips you have
You can put her down so easily
I don't know how we lucked out with her
She was on number 5 in
We needed that.
But perfectly evident
We're back alright let's let's get back
Okay we're back
Jump back in
John plays throughout his school years by the time he's getting closed
College a lot of his friends are getting
You know offers scholarships to different
Yeah big-time schools University of Minnesota Boston College places like that
4 John
There was just no intro
Like the coaches thought he was too big to play wouldn't be able to
Keep up out there on the ice
But eventually he did get one offer to play for a mid-level university
Michigan
And I just figured I would
In all honesty I would finish college and get a job that would be it I would have got an education for free and
You know I play hockey with
The guys on the weekends but that was down to the end of hockey
But then a couple of things
First at school I kind of always noticed him because he was
About 2 ft taller than anybody else on campus
Engineering student started dating senior year
The rest of History
Any other thing that happened was I got this opportunity to go play
Time for the Houston Aeros
Minnesota farm team minor league team that wasn't crazy money it was 30,000 or 35,000
To talk to Danielle about it he was like
Well let me give this hockey thing
Like a go because the only chance I'm going to get to be able to say I played Pro
In the way that I kind of looked at it was okay
It's just like
A little head
Start and then once I graduate like we'll both get our jobs like a real job
And move on with our lives
So John moved down to Houston I didn't have any expectations I just work my tail off I was the bad skater I work
At skating I was a bad pastor I would work at passing after practice
But he says no matter what he did
He would not get any pie
I was always a step or two behind
I think the ninth defenseman on the roster and you only dress 6 for a game so I never played
The first
I think month of the season
Buljan was in Houston
Notice
If there were these other big guys on the team
And they were getting
They they kind of took me under their wings
And they said Hey listen
If you really want to get noticed on your if you really want to go to the NHL
You should learn how to fight
It work perfect
Play because that's what happened
So for those of you who don't follow hockey
I have guys in my team
Million nine million eight million dollars and they are paid the score and they are paid to perform and play well
But there are also guys out there who their job is to
Pester annoy and we call them the rats the pest
And you can hear these guys like when they're mic'd up
Like 10 guys her right now running their mouths they try to get under the star players skin
How do you spell star players put sometimes
Immortal check them into the Borg
Dope in order to deal with past
You got people like John
Floor
Called
Enforcer
So basically my job is to make sure those pests
Don't pester my top guys
And so when we would go into a game
I would know exactly who to pinpoint because you know you do your scouting and I would go up to those guys and I would say Hey listen
If you're going to do that I'm going to
Put my fist through your face
And more often
Minaj
The fear of
The retribution if they did something with
Would stop them
Can you could see the frustration in Big John Scott.
But if they did do something my job was to beat them up
And I was the heck of a fighter when I made the NHL
They wouldn't fight I would usually grab their tough guy
And beat him up if we were playing flat and we didn't have energy
Big John Scott trying to spark his team I would go out and try to fight to get my guys going
Or if it was a really bad head I would just grab that guy and I would be his doors off
Itsfunneh throughout my career I really hated fighting
Thursday's I wouldn't sleep at night just because I knew I was going to get into a fight but
You just do your job
And I think I did my job well
Well enough that John was able to make a career in the NHL it's everything you dream of as a kid
It's kind of like a leap of faith and it worked out great
So by this point Danielle and John had gotten married you know we had bought our first house ever had their first tooth
Kids beyond anything we
Are I ever expected
Will tell me tell me all the names of all the teams that you played for omigod so I'm embarrassed
Doe in 2008 John started playing in the NHL for the Minnesota Wild
After that he played for
Chicago in New York
Buffalo in San Jose
And and throw his whole career as an enforcer
There was this shift going on
In professional
Justin incredible
Printable play a lot of the hockey establishment in the media decks in the league
We're pushing for the game to be more heists
Anymore about
Gil
And a lot of people started coming out and saying there should not be a place in this week
For fighting I was an easy target
This guy
Is it cool if you haven't seen the movie you don't have
Have to bother this is
They went after me and they said listen we don't need guys like this in the league has no room
Forward in the game
There's no room
Their sole purpose is to punch people
Not simply
Ignite a fight
You were going to eliminate
Players like this
Which is one of the reasons why
Four guys like Greg wyshynski and Jeff Marek
Booting John Scott in the All-Star game was not
Just a hilarious joke about a big I couldn't skate
What is also a big fat middle finger
To the hockey is
I'm sorry I'll just do the whole day
The big point I do it I was we were
On the road and we are on the bus heading to
A game or pre-game skate it was December 2015 John was playing for the Arizona Coyotes
And a guy my team Anders lindback gargar goalie he
Was sitting beside me and he's like a year you know you're in
It was like 56 place or something you know
About the fan voting I was like oh you know it's great people think it's a joke they're going to vote
For me a little bit and it was it was nothing
Seriously that's how I first heard of it on the bus
So we go to the we go to the rink we do our skate
Literally after the skate
He checks his phone again and he's like holy comment your like
Top 25
It happened that fast
And then
The next day I was top 5 and then like the day after that I was number one
There's a surprise leader in fan voting for the upcoming NHL All-Star Game and his name is
John Scott
So is like a
For the mega story. Is leading the NHL
It was unbelievable how quickly accrue
Number one the number one vote-getter among all players in the NHL
Which method would be at All-Star Game captain
King cat
At the All-Star Game
Let that sink in for a second
And for the fans who were voting for John there's definitely a bit of like oh you Shrunk the number of players we can vote in
Oh really
Here's Johnny
But I think for a majority of Voters voting for John
It was just released
The reason John Scott's leading voting is because it's funny
John Scott is not an ulcer
Star is one goal over eight games he barely plays
Skill
Wouldn't it be funny to see this
Arizona Coyotes thun ogre objectively bad at hockey
I don't know what he's doing in the league
Make a fool of himself though I hated it
This isn't funny anymore I get it like on this
Durable player who
You guys think would be fun to watch me you know fail in this game but
I just figured it would end on its own honestly I thought it would last a few days and people would get
Me and older enough of it and it would go away but it just didn't
And that's for the NHL
They were pissed
Frankly
I definitely got the sense
From some of the people that I speak to you on a regular basis the NHL that they were really
Angry this was happen
And white like I can you get any more specific about like why this would have been an embarrassment to them like what is it exactly that they
They were so sensitive about about the fact that the All-Star game is something that a lot of old-time
I'm hockey people and there's a lot of old time hockey
People that run the National Hockey League
See as something prestigious
One of the ultimate honors for a player
And so
This was not something they wanted to happen
And it was happening and they didn't really know what to do about it
Because they didn't have any fail-safes
Someplace to Ravenna from half
After one day of John sitting atop the All-Star vote
Kids are sleeping
John gets a text
He gets about a bed cuz overdose phone starts reading it
And he's
Standing there for a while
Selfishly I'm just want to go to bed but then
You know I can sell something
Just got him
Doing over there and it was his
PR guy from
My coyote
Say they thought it'd be a good idea really
Statement and
They rolled up this statement for me
And they basically said thank you for the support I don't want your votes please vote for other guys on my team
Basically his own team is saying step away for
From the All-Star Game
I saw him like respond yeah that statements fine and then delete it and then just sit there and look at it
And I just remember us
Acting like see you deep would you want to go and he's
Just like what yeah I think
Cuz as a kid I watched all the All Star Games
It was so
Fun to watch in Iowa
Dream to be in
So yeah
I'm like woah
They want you to release the statement released a statement but make sure that it's
True
I'm so John and separating statement that reads
Quote
It's nice to be thought of by all of the fans
And for that I am truly flattered and grateful
And while I would love to experience an All-Star Game
I think a few of my teammates are a bit more deserving of
Enzo tour lights
I would go if I get voted
But there's other people who deserve it
I said yeah sure send it out I wasn't totally on board with that but I just wanted to appease the higher-ups to hopefully
Help them
But even after that
It was
Still John's got number one go-getter
Go by far yeah it
It's funny they stop showing how many votes to players were getting
They took that option off the website because I think I was ahead by SoMo
You broke the website
Yeah I still they they took that away and then
The NHL
Babe really try to strong-arm me what happened there so I was in my bedroom in Arizona and they called
And
It was one of the higher-ups in the NHL and he's a
You want to know how I was feeling was getting really close to the end of the voting
I just said yeah you know I want to go to the game I think it'll be fun I think it'll be good for everybody involved
And he's like really you sure like you think you'll be able to keep up
You think you're good enough like guy you're not exactly a skill guy John and they started that way and I just kind of brushed it off you know I was like yeah
You can stay pretty well I'm a good Dees
Easton hockey player
And he was well you know
What it what do you still talk to your dad what do you think
Percy goes are you is your dad alive and I'd like
Ohio
What do you think he's going to think about this situation you know you think you're going to make him proud
And I was like what's like
I don't think that has anything to do with this and I kind of brushed at off in at this time I'm getting a little angry
Because I'm sick man
Flip and fly and then he's like whoa
What do you think your kids are going to think when they only look back on this
If you think they're going to proud of their daddy
Who went to the All-Star Game this way
And as soon as he brought my kids into the equation I just like lost it
And I kind of snapped back at him like you're being a real
Sleeping sleeping sleeping sleeping on your back
Forza he started cussing at me
MN Lake ice
Finally like
Snapback is Michael Lee, yelling at one of the head guys in NHL I should like
Dial it back and I apologize look sorry
Do you know you're pushed the wrong button like
Talk tomorrow I'll let you know
If I'm going to go or not I left it like that
Jean-Claude
Woke up the next day all the do the next morning
I said I'm going
Athens break
See you at the game
Maybe we will maybe maybe not
Hi this is Sarah calling from Scarsdale New York supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern
Information about slowing
A w wwd
Phone. Org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your
And I've requests
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents
Aunts and uncles teachers
We're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments
Childhood brilliance
Basically I want to hear about this
Times when a kid you know did something
It just means you lean back and say
Wow
Maybe it was the moment that our kids you've been reading to 4 month started reading back
To you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed they're ready music
In the margin of their geometry
We're interested in the
Epic moments where
A kid does something super smart
It doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story
T-shirt
Go to radiolab.org
Brilliance
Record short audio message
Again that's radiolab.org / brilliance
Thank you so much
321 Chad Robert Radiolab
And report a lot of Nasser
Okay so
2 weeks before the All-Star Game John is just getting ready
Practice
And the GM of the team comes out
Been talking to me
All the time throughout this all star stuff and I thought it was just going to be another
Conversation about that and he pulls me into the stick room and he's like yeah
I just traded you to Montreal
And I was like
Are you effing kidding me
What
And he said yeah it was a hockey move
You know we we needed a little defensive help and we traded you to Montreal for this guy
And I said this is enough and Joker are you kidding me and he said sorry
You know the deal has been done
Okay
Whatever super Shady to be traded right after I
I'm finally in the All-Star game is like
You know
If it smells
Like a
You know Walks Like A Duck talks like a duck to 38 Special
We called John's former team and the NHL about this neither wanted to talk
Nonetheless what happened next is that a short while later
Jonathan the locker-room Gathering my things trying to say goodbye to the guys and he pulls me aside again
And the GM Delta
Ashley Montreal the team we just traded you to
They're not going to demote
They're sending you to st. John's Newfoundland their farm team
In the mire
Go to the trainer get your stuff ready or leaving
Today
According to the terms of the trade
He had to be on the plane that same day
And that's what I was just like I was done I was like okay
Done
And I just checked out I went like found somewhere in the rank I called my wife who by the way was 9 months pregnant
With twins
I get the phone call from
John
In those situations is kind of a man is like
A few words
Telser
Where in the minors
And I'm like alright
Will be fine
Clancy where is the minor team like how do I get there you know
And he's like yeah it's literally on the other side of the world
It is North America's easternmost
You could not go further from where I'm at right now
Still be on this continent
And I say
Can you please handle all of this
Take my two kids take the two kids in your belly take all my stuff
Pack it up
Like I have to leave
It's so Bazaar
You have to say that to her end
Like there's nothing I could have done
I need to say I'm sorry I have to
To go and I was just thinking to myself
Okay
You know like
Just trying to hold onto hope like we can make this work but
See where it's at and I'm like looking at flights
And like I pull up kayak and I'm
Being like the
Safelite
And it's like
16 hours to travel 14 hours
Travel
18 hours of travel and like the prices for like a ticket is like
$1,500
They really all hit me at that moment
And I just like stop
Compose myself got my gear told the GM to go
You know wherever
And
Jump in the car
Pack up my s*** and went to st. John's
You want to talk about John Scott so we have the debate know I guess so
Canadian Legend
Don Cherry on a TV show
Hockey Night in Canada
Hurry up you jerks
That it put him up
4th division the All-Star Game what you've done
You taking this kid who was doing pretty good plane 6 minutes
12 minutes that matter
Arizona NHL contract what you did was
Your truck and put him in the minors now lots of fun
I bet you're very proud of yourself because the NHL
This year is going to be terrific
And you're going you tried to ruin it all and your ruin this kid
Is in the minors
Never to come back I bet you should be ashamed yourself you should be ashamed yourself
That's it
I saw this news hit
And my first reaction was you have
Got to be kidding me
Greg wyshynski started the John Scott for All-Star campaign
Oh man they just
The problem go away is there part of you who was like oh my God like I
I started this
This is on me
No because
At that point
You know there had been criticized
System of us
Having this campaign and obviously when John Scott came out I was like you guys ruined my career this sucks
Caputo
Right off the bat
Made you feel like maybe you've done something
Kind of bad dude dude
But the campaigner kind of Taken on a life
If its own
And at that point
John Scott said he wanted to be an All-Star wanted to represent
A certain type of
Player my role is like almost extinct I'm like the last of my
Kind of here in like oh be cool to go out with a bang all of his friends were saying you should do it
He wanted to do it because people are selling them
Your fault or anything but in a way that like
Youjizz
And not that you could have forced
You started
The train was their party that was like
Oh my God like if I had
Said that one thing on my podcast
Like this guy wouldn't have had to uproot his whole life I mean again like I feel like
It was the National Hockey League
That was
Standing in his way
Now whatever you think about the initial prank or John being demoted
This is the moment
When the crowd mood
Totally shifted
Complete outrage this is trash
The computer outrage this is garbage
I'm not going to go about a democracy it became protest
Online is a lousy thing to do
Sweeping through the hockey world
Like
The fans voted this guy in
The NHL is doing all it can to keep this guy out and that's not right you want to change this
Contact
Your favorite
Sportswriter in York City
Since the NHL is so damn image-conscious why don't you put pressure
On your
Favorite reporter
Stick up for John Scott
I Can Only Imagine
How John feels
Pissed off
Sorry for yourself and you feel you get sad boy want to play hockey
What do I want to do like guy
Do I just quit talking go work like you think about all these things
Now that you're in the minor leagues
Are you allowed to
Play for the All-Star Game
That's the thing no one knew
He says right after he
He was demoted to the minor league
People started did you know read through the by-laws read through the books
Trying to figure out like
Hen a minor league player
Play in the
Professional
NHL All-Star
And it turns out there was no rule that even remotely address
Situation like
It was totally impressive
And so the pressure stayed on the NHL new
That
If John Scott wasn't in the All-Star Game
There's probably Visions from the NHL of protest signs along the glass
The band out the outside the arena holding a rally because John Scott was
And according to Greg hockey
Keep an czarnota
Aureus
For throwing jerseys on the ice
Protest causing
Scenes and eventually
The National Hockey League had to acquiesce they put out a statement they made a statement saying hey if John wants to go you can go
But John says at this point I told everybody I'm not going
Like nhlpa I told all my friends
The teammates like I'm done like this is a bogus sick I don't want to do this he says between the fans making fun of him and Allie demoting him
The whole thing was just
Just to humiliate
But I was
Was just like
John
Yuan may regret that I know you want to like
Run away and hide right now and like going in front of all these people the very last
Nothing you want to do
But you might regret it
She's like let's go it'll be fun for the family the kids will love it
I would love to see you going through these people wrong
My wife was building me back up and
Slowly but surely I was like okay you know what
F*** this
Let's do it
Very impressive
January 31st
The complete circus it was unbelievable
I was obviously the big story so the moment I land there is reporters everywhere ask me questions
I would be representing the
Pacific Division in the All-Star Game
And we had to play
It was essential who everyone said they were stacked because they had all the
Stud players on our team
Players play
Patty dushane James Neal all of you much younger much higher
A player
And then you had
John I knew everybody was staring at me and I'm weird about my hair cuz I'm
Going bald and I'm
Skate around like I wish I would have grabbed my hat
McDaniel
Everything is buzzing
Danielle from the stands there two little kids everybody's looking for him.
Stay off this dumb he's going to make it nasty
And before the game the coach comes up to him to ask me if I wanted to
The starting I just said no
Please let me stay on the bench
Nicole chisley
All right
But you're going in early
John teammates get out to center ice
He's sitting on the bench butterflies in its stomach
Karina and goal
Ref drop the puck
Right away
26 seconds into the game
Jaheim
Go down one nothing
Literally one not too late and how about the hands in the playmate from the Maddie Duchesne right there on the Colorado Avalanche
Brilliant Steve
The James Neal it was like it was like
It was a goal that all stars
Gunsmoke
Scott
You're in
Remember this is three-on-three there is a ton of open eyes there's nowhere to go like there's nowhere to hide
And John says it's kept thinking
Don't mess up
Don't make a fool yourself that's all I was thinking of
Rats got the puck
Hold it about Center Ice I don't belong here I think you're a joke don't screw it up
Drop set what's the puck drop
You just kind of you know everything else goes away
Can you just start playing hockey
This was like going back to when I was younger I wasn't the best I was in the fastest but you and I know you just start playing
And that's what I did
This time
John Cena
Frenzy at the park
We're going up the ice
John and the team is charged across Center Ice they move into their opponent Zone
When
Brent Burns passes the puck to John
John manages to control it kind of up against the boards so he's using his body to protect
Tupac trying to figure out what to do next
Burnsy had to park on the right wing and all the sudden I notice
Between two of the Defenders there's a nice little Lane right to the net I went to the net
Burn spotted Johnny what the f*** rate on my
Stick
John's just like a few feet from goal in the Ghoulies actually out of
Position that a wide open net
And I shot it and I missed the net
Like a like a white oak
Open Nat
But the goalie was luckily sliding back into position
So the puck
Hit the goalie
Bounce
Off the goalie
And into the back of the net
There you go
It was awesome like I was so jacked up by Goosebumps like after the goal I was so need
It was cool
That was anything the crowd I didn't know how they were going to react
Usually they boo me
Everybody boo'd me and they they they are all for it
The weird thing about the masses
Two it's like
How quickly everybody can go from hating you
You to loving you
It was such a sense of relief for me
The huge monkey
Was lifted off my back cuz I was like okay
I did something for the team I didn't mess up he's going to relax
Have fun
Just playing
Be himself in place which he did
Laid out the guy Patrick Kane
Drop the glove pretended to have a fight
He got a couple make passes at a real
Bluetooth shot on goal he was just kind of doing everything
Everytime John Scott
Was on camera or touch the puck the crowd would come to life
Greg wyshynski was actually they're reporting at the game and he was down in the tunnel
What happens when you're down in the bowels of the arena is at the All-Star games on TVs
But there is a
Delay between what the broadcast has and what's happening
On the ice
So typically you'll hear something happen in the game
Before you actually watch it on TV
And I remember hearing this
Gigantic Roar from the
Crap
And then everybody kind of looked over at the
The TV
And watch the all-star
If tie-dye shootout
What happened with a listed it. Rohr was that it was getting to the end of the game tight game
Johnson was up by one we were in our Zone
Point defense all of a sudden
13 shot it
We had a save and burns you got the puck behind the net
End
I just
Bluetooth on a skid loaders on as fast as I could cuz I knew he was going to get it
He saw me up in that all I need
Fire tonight pass and I corralled it
Took off down the center of the ice
They had someone hounding me able to keep the defender off of them
So it was just John
The goalie
And then that
Gather dipakai Ripa shot top corner on the goalie
Can a 1in
No goalie deflection tool
Bounce Jeddah
Solid steel shot
There was just for this moment of this black
Laughter from the players being waited to be interviewed laughter from the media downstairs
Unbridled Joy of watching it all happen
I was just like as it's even happening like it I started to just be like
Cuz I think I could
Physically
Adidas Milan
Stan
The guys on the ice jumped on me they're like holy cow this is unbelievable
The Final Chapter
Of the John Scott story
At least as it pertains to the all-star game
Is
Really beautiful thing
And so
So there's this scene in Star Trek II The Wrath of Khan
I swear
It looks like
The Enterprise is going to get away
Having defeated car
Pecan
Young
Still alive
He's going to try to trigger the doomsday device on a ship
Kill Everybody
It's so as as as as their prizes
Is flying away you see a blood conse
From hell's heart
Hell's heart I stab at thee
And I thought of that scene when the
Voting for most valuable player at the All-Star game start
To explain
At the end of the game there's one final bit
The fan voting
Fans were going to choose the MVP of the NHL All-Star Game
Most Valuable Player and the fans in the arena and watching on TV
They would text the name of the person they want
Do a number or they would go on Twitter and use the special hashtags
Text first
Ndk
It will be coming up shortly write as a voting
Is about to begin up a bunch of names of players
On the jumbo
Here are your choice and John Scott name was not listed
Among the three MVP candidates
On the Jumbotron
All Star MVP award
The fan saw that I wasn't on there they went not they started the boo
Loudly
Visibly
You know feel it
Around the ring
I thought it was the last gasp
Of all the people at the NHL that tried to keep
John Scott out of the All-Star game that was their last chance
To get them
Like Khan
Trying to get
Captain Kirk that's
Trying to say with the NL
Anyway
What ended up happening is that during the voting
Thousands of people
Road in their own show
And when it was announced
The 2016 NHL All-Star MVP Sports
It's funny I didn't hear it because on Ice level you don't hear what speakers are playing because
They they point the speakers to the fan sliding head here until like
Somebody's like a like going like a choking hazard weird
John Gates out to the center of the ice
Laughing looking a little scared boy should I was just like the MVP of the All-Star Game
John Scott is with the air
There's been all kinds of motivations for you
What do you want to say first offense
Thank you so much you guys are just thank you so much
And in what was
V
Teary-eyed
Disney Family Sports still moment
Let's go to me and then they're going to
He was wasted on to the shoulders of his teammates
And paraded around like he was Rudy
Greatest sports movie ever
I wanted to go down by
The ice so that the kids could see John and
Keep for trying to help me down the stairs like parting the sea so I could get down there
And it was so weird like it was literally like Disney wrote a script and said okay now he kisses his wife
You took me in her eyes locked and it was just we both are kind of like shaking your head like we're both a little bit
Beast Boy
Now he grabbed
Kiss
Scoop them up
Cliche fashion I grab my kids
Scale
You think you smell bad in
Like every time
Like I would just look at him and I can't even believe this is happening and it was no
Like I just can't
And if it came off the ice there were crowds of people waiting asking questions
Pictures with. But we had to fight the next morning at like 5 a.m.
He had to get back to the minor leagues
And before that
They still had to have these babies
City Russian to give birth to the twins
4 days after babies were born and went back to St John's
My God
Yeah
I feel like that was really the beginning of
The rest of our lives
John finish out that season
Play one last NHL game
And then retired
And Danielle live with their five girls in Traverse City Michigan
Butts
The Legacy
Arby's All-Star appearance
Lived on in two ways
First
The day after the game it was announced that John Scott's helmet-to-helmet he wore during the game
Would be flown to Toronto
Where will be put on display
At the hockey
He Hall of Fame
But the other thing that happened was just in time for the next year's All-Star Game
The NHL created a new rule
Known as the John Scott rule
Which states that any player who is voted to be a captain in the All-Star Game
Then gets demoted to the minor leagues
Will be disqualified will not be allowed to play
Effectively ensuring
The never again will the fans have
White the power
The overthrow the system
And vote in
A John Scott
Reporter electric Nasser
This episode was produced
By Mr Matt kielty
In fact check
By Diane Kelly
Also if you want to hear more from John Scott and of course he has a podcast is called dropping the gloves
Available wherever you get
Podcast
Footloose
Gloves and intercepts are there be a lot of original music from John Dryden the OCS weed
Eater and a bonsai
Unless special thanks to Morgan Springer Faisal camisa and
Ben hankinson
And that's it
I'm Jedi runtime Robert krulwich
Thanks for listening
Replay the message press 2
Scott
I didn't even stop
Is it happy hour
Radiolab
Was created by
And is produced by
Director of sound design
Novia
Magic Dragon
Is our managing director
Executive producer
Our staff includes
China
Weak excuse
Beauty camera
David Katz
I'm so happy
Max penalty
Robert Pruett
DIY angry
Any feeling
I think he's here
Alexis Diner
Alex overington
Sampaoli
Cherry pie
Reny
Amoeba
Footnotes from
And now a week
Fact checker
Goodbye
And this message