Are you awake
Northern listening to Radiolab
Radiolab wnyc
And NPR
You ready yes
Feeling feeling I'm old work I'm feeling full of valuable in that Spirit on Jedi
Which is Radiolab different stories to try to put a dollar value mouganis okay
$1000000 $7
Kendo
Fun things
It seemed priceless
Priceless priceless
Okay so start bring on the pressure
To tell it to
Sorry we can start the show with a story from our producer Molly Webster
So we might actually want to rename Ali Wong sister
Because she said she recently got herself into some serious numero sizing
Actually didn't start as a wonky thing it starts at 2 with some medical journal
So that was that was interesting because it was some of the most
Poetic writing I've seen out of doctors
Ever
One Journal article said like what would one more month mean to a 37 year old mother who has
For children
Or what would one more month mean if you are a 67 year-old who's about to go traveling around the world
People were just kind of like drifting these questions out there
All these questions seem to circle around
The seemingly simple story of the pricing of a drug
Cancer
And the story
If you really want to tell it from the beginning it begins with this guy named Leonard
Leonard saltz I'm a medical oncologist at Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center witches here New York
It's one of the largest cancer centers in the country we have
17 doctors here who
Curry College
Just for colon cancer
Very large number
It's a huge Hospital
And one of the things Leonard's been noticing in the last
Decade
Is cancer drug prices have just gone through the roof I mean we have drugs out there that are many hundreds of dollars
Really yeah just wait
Let's see where's the start it starts
It's June in 2012
Leonard saltz is at a conference and at this conference is
Is a pharmaceutical company called Santa Fe
And they
Give a presentation about a new drug that they
A drug called zaltrap and zell trap
Is a drug that
Without getting into the science too much
Target
The blood supply to the tumor
Cut off the blood supply which means a tumor
That's that's the
Scientific iPod
The new drug is presented and they like present the data and they showed
That the
Survival difference
Between the people who got soundtrack in the people
Was 1.4 month
42 days
In other words if you take this drug
You could get
42 more days of life
On average
Which means you could get three more days you could get no days you could get 42 or you could live another 3 years
242 days
Don't please I could show you some graphs have been put up at meetings that show
Survival curves
Calculate it out
To two decimal places in terms of months
I'm look at the
100 of a month
A hundred a month that's a little over 7 hours
Free
Amusing acted why would you why would you
It's pseudo precision
Pseudobursa
Anyways after the conference
The FDA approves the drug and basically once the FDA approves a drug
Public insurance has to take it and then the private insurance companies just follow suit
Which means
You get prescribed the drug and people pay
What is the drug cost
That's the thing it cause
Roughly 3004
Three-month course
Soap
Stew Leonard's like wow that is expensive
And there was already another drug on the market did the same thing and it cost half as much
To put that in context this is just one drug that's $11,000 a month
A normal cancer patient might take dozens of drugs there are anti-nausea medicines that are sometimes used to that
Getting in the range of 90 to $100 a tablet you take a tablet once a day for 3 days
One needs growth factors to help support the white blood cell count which is sometimes need and chemo those can be five
$1,000 every two to three weeks if you need antibiotics to treat infections those aren't cheap and and then you need a pharmacist
Prepare their labor-intensive need tubing and equipment and needles to give it and he trained nurses to administer if you need to talk
To take care of the patient and don't forget there's a cost for a CAT scan or MRI and and then of course someone's got to pay for the realest
State the heat in the lights
None of those prices are figured into it
I'm just giving you
The
Cost of the truck
So Leonard calls up one of his colleagues
My name is Peter ba
I'm a physician at Memorial Sloan-Kettering Peter the number cruncher of the group he does the statistical analysis
I don't know what the cost of care
And then grabbed him and ran him through
And we walked through the out-of-pocket expenses for Medicare beneficiaries
Medicare beneficiaries
If they don't have additional insurance
20 cents of every dollar they pay out-of-pocket have hit him because he realize for Medicare patients
They be paying something like $2,000
Out-of-pocket every month
For justice truck 2200 if I remember the number correctly
For a lot of Medicare patients
All of their money
Nevermind other drugs
That
When I thought we should go public with it
Memorial Sloan-Kettering they decide to boycott
This truck
Now
Is that
I mean I'm just stopping you because
When you guys made that decision was that that feels like a big deal it did feel like a big deal and it felt like a big enough deal that
We decided to write
The op-ed piece in the New York Times
They write an op-ed in the times that basically says look this is crazy $11,000 a month for a drug that made
Baby gives you 42 more days of life is that worth it
Little less than a month after the op-ed piece came out
The company that makes eltropy went to individual doctor's office
Sent representatives and said
We are offering a 50% discount
Because
Price in half just like that
Yep Nationwide or like just in this area
It was sort of in
We reached out to Santa Fe to talk about the prices out rap and they decline to comment
In a statement that they released when this holes out that thing happened
They said that
They incur so many costs
For researching and developing and bringing a drug to Market
But that is what the pricing is
Leonard doesn't disagree we need these companies
They're the ones developing the truck
Which aren't easy to develop I mean Leonard gave us just one example
If we talk about colon care
He says four years there was only one drug on the market
Called 5-fu
5-fu was patented in August of 1957
It was from 1957
Until 1996
That a second drug came along
That's how long it takes to develop a good
Drug or that interim that were over 70 drugs that were tried and failed
Didn't like I don't get enough credit cuz that just astounded me it's very very hard
And that according to Leonard is one of the reasons why prices are just going to keep going up
But
Sooner or later this system
Is going to fall apart
And it would point
The society say
There isn't an infinite number of dollars
We can commit to our Healthcare System
It's funny because I have an interesting reaction to the word Society
Salveson I thought likewise
Not not like a dino crazy death panel white but
I thought y
Why is society involved in my conversation
With my doctor about
If I want to take this drug that may give me
Another month and a half of life
Why is society involved
Cuz you're not paying
Unless
You have
Hidden resources I'm aware of probably couldn't afford
10 to $15,000 a month
Someone else
Obviously he says it's your insurance
Say you're part of a policy that has 1000 members
Let's say that the premium
For that
Is
$100
So we had $100
Thousand people
We got to come down and out
Okay can we now have $100,000
To take care of that thousand people
Whatever Matt time if now one person
Comes up with a healthcare cost let's say it's for a month
That is
$100,000 in that month
Everybody else is in trouble
So
They write this op-ed
Saying my prices are too high in the drugs are not
Decorate and sort of the next like notable wave is
There was this there's this journal called
Blood which is really big to anybody that works in a community that Hamlet called blood
How did we not know about this we make the blood show
Just kept it in here Journal called blood which is basically like
The journal for anybody that works in a field that has to do with blood
What happens is like
100 doctors get together and they
Cosine and editorial
Which basically says
I totally agree with everything you guys are saying but we haven't even bigger issue
You know was out rap you're talkin about an expensive drug
Maybe doesn't really do that much
It's kind of easy even though I had never been done before
To say we're not going to use this
What all of these
Doctors in the blood editorial or saying
What do you do when you have a really
Expensive drug
It's really really good
I could drag you actually want
It is that like a like a one day in the future we will face is going to question now today
The most important new medicine approved this year everyone I talked to pointed me to this new drug sovaldi
Known as the sovaldi
Sovaldi came on the market last
December 5th December 2013
That's correct
This is Bruce small I'm the editor of Commonwealth magazine
He's written about sovaldi and here's the basic story right
It is a drug that treats
Hepatitis
Which is caused by a virus and the disease itself
Goes to work on your liver
It inflames it
It's cars that can cause liver cancer cirrhosis that can be fatal
And for the longest time the treatments that they had just really weren't that great or they just had
Ratchet side of
But along comes to Vault
And it's one pill 12 weeks
To take it with some other antiviral meds it is a super simple treatment option
And the side effects are very minimal
Like this it was like kind of
Like the savior
And so a lot of doctors start
Describe it in the first half
The country in the United
And it had a 95%
Rate of
Sure
In other words
Cow
That's very big
In fitting with our story this drug
Cost $1,000
The pill
For like one one pill that I take one a day
Which as you can imagine and angered a lot of people with hep C in total it costs
$84,000
And if you think about the fact that in
2014 we know at least 70000 people got this drug you're starting to talk about
Serious money I just want to say that I
I just X doubt 70000 * 84000
And I got something with seven zeros in it
588 and then there's seven zeros which is like
Abbott 5 billion dollars
Yes
The big question is how States will pay
For what could be upwards of until we have a situation where
States are basically having to ration is currently are requiring
Some liver damage
Before you can take the drug similar restrictions are happening in other states
Florida happening in Oregon Illinois
And then there's Arizona out of the entire state
Public insurance only approves 180 people for treat
Adjust 180 just 180
Now when I talk to a representative of the company that makes the drug
Greg Alton jacket vice president for
Corporate and medical Affairs for Gilead Sciences
He says you got to keep in mind
This is not a chronic care situation this is a sure actually curing a person of a disease we're talkin
In about
12 weeks of therapy
Period that's it and you're done and you cared so
So he says
This is a one-time deal was like one time $84,000
And then you're done think about all the years you live without having an illness
Then you'll see 20 year. The savings that will accrue to the system
By having a patient cured of hepatitis C
He also said it's important to understand
That every hepatitis C suffer is not going to hit
System
At the same time so all of the
Cost
Is spread out right
Wichita totally true but I think there's like the bigger picture here
I Am Bruce pointed out to it's sort of like a precursor of what could
Come because
These companies
Are developing drugs all the time what if
If you could get a drug but it was very expensive to treat diabetes
And then you're talking tens of millions of
Enormous segment of the population
Even if just a fraction of them want a drug that's $1,000 per day
It's practically our entire us budget what do you do in that case
A drug comes along like that
And throws everything out of whack
This is the part where I really sort of got hooked in where it's like
How do you answer this question is it that
You know at a certain point you just draw a line and you say
Beyond this point
We're not paying
But beyond what
Exactly I think that's the hard part
How good does a treatment have to be
For you to say this is worth the price that it's been said I don't think we have rejected out of hand foot I got into this
In the case of soundtrack they said alright 42 days that much money we're not going to do it
But would it have been different if it was 50 days
Is that enough I'm sure you want to be talking in years but I guess the question is like what would be a mall is there a magic line for you
If I
This is it
I can't personally determinate for everybody
I wouldn't presume to try
But
Ultimately as a society
Going to have to reach
An understanding of what that cut point is
Because we can't afford not to
And the question is sort of bubbles out of this conversation is what is one more year or one more month or what
One more day of life worse
Are we going to pay $1,000 for an extra day of life
But what about $100,000 reduction of life people like to say yeah so what's the value of a human life
The answer is boy that's a complicated question
They're really important one
Because
Nobody thinks it's infinitely
He said that
And I was like okay
Sub-Zero and it's not instant
Is there an answer like in the middle and so
I started looking around
I guess I was wondering if anyone actually thought about this
Since I started looking around what I realized was at the World Health Organization
Actually
I mean I guess they almost have a number but it's a number per country they have the recommendation that that country spend
Can I get gobbledygook eat but just bear with me the country spend one two three times
The GDP
Per capita which is like
The gross domestic product per individual
Go to take the entire
Fat ball of money that is in a country and divided / individual / the individuals and then you spend one two three
Times that on
When were Goodyear
Movies that be for us
Search for the us if that's about fifty to a hundred fifty thousand
Interesting
Is that does that have any any teeth
That recommendation really doesn't have any teeth but it has teeth in the sense that
Doctors in the US
Going to start using this who number to evaluate
Medical Treatments
For Cardiology
They said they were going to do this in a paper and it was kind of very quiet very subtle
But in other countries
This conversation
Is very loud actually it happens at the government level
They're also passing out surveys with her asking
Citizens what is your limit on how much
You want to spend on one more good year of life
And they did not hear
Far as I know no
Because
Because the last time we tried to talk about cost in medicine it ended up in the hole death
Death panels or so-called death panels thing
I don't know I just wondered right into the mess of it hey Times Square if I actually tried to go out
A very basic way
How would people respond
Excuse me can I ask you a question what is a year of life worth
But a question it was really surprised at how
Seriously people took the question
What is a year of life worth
That was the first thing I noticed
Then the next thing was
No one to answer the question until I had answered like a million questions of there
Where do I get that year do I get it at the beginning and middle or the end how would I spend that you have life
Goodyear's life depends is like a pie in the sky kind of answer they wanted to know would they be emotionally happy
Loan with friends or family where did they get the money they borrow the money they have to pay the money back where they dying was it in
Emergency or other people also trying to get money at the same time because then there'd be like a rush on the money in America
So interesting
Did you actually ever end up getting
Numbers
I did get numbers but they were
10 - $15,000
Stop 13th $7 all over the place
$44,000
Interesting one woman said 10 million million dollars for a year
Irresponsible you asking me about my personal choice not about a public
Why do you have any way of parsing office
No
I really honestly don't like I think my biggest takeaway was like no one punched me
Switch
Which makes me feel as if people are ready
Not ready but willing
But I also realize that
I kept talking about things and
I just want to
To be in the room with page
Play Patience in the room with me because it was like we're all having this conversation that
Eventually we'll all be patients I guess but
We're also
Having this conversation around
Like a group of people that weren't ever present like they're not a conferences or not in
Research articles
And so that was when I started talking to Paige
Wow
I guess what is 42 days
What is 42 days mean in the sense of
Is that something that you pay 50
$1,000
If you were
I mean of course you would
It's like I haven't even asked the question but I don't know I know I think it's a good question I think
Ethically it would be to the good of patients
And doctors
To have this conversation this is Susan
Susan gubar Rider of
The living with cancer blog
Did the New York Times back in 2008 Susan went to the doctor
She hasn't been feeling well for a while they thought it was some sort of foul issue but then the doctor walked into the room and said she had
Advanced stage ovarian cancer
Most ovarian cancers are diagnosed at ale
Stage and
It's it's basically
Incurable
It can be handled it can be managed at
Can be kept at Bay and
Longer periods of time now we hope
But you're given a diagnosis of 3 to 5 years
That is
You go from having unlimited time in your mind to
Three to five years in like a docker
Yeah it's it's it's a big shock
You said Ventura Zone
Well you're not quite aware of what
You doing
That day the day she was diagnosed she was told
Pack a bag get in the car and drive to Indianapolis
You need surgery now
So I went to the next day to Indianapolis and the day after that I had to do bulking surgery which takes out the
The ovaries and the
Uterus in the Fallopian tubes in the spleen and sometimes the cervix
Sometimes the appendix in holy times the bowel and are you serious
Yeah it's called the mother of all surgery
And then just like that
Shooting multiple rounds
Chemo chemicals that are used
They destroy all quick-growing cell
So for example you have no hair
No eyebrows no eyelashes that you know
You also can I got terrible sores in my mouth
I have no idea why but I know this happens to other people but yeah the other thing is this extreme
Fatigue
And Susan who writes for a living couldn't even read
I would look at a page and think that I turned a page
Chemotherapy it really is toxic
To the spirit
To the heart to the mind
Just the normal aspects of Life feel polluted
Have you ever had to think about
Cost
I was never
Formed of the cost of
Any drug
Or any
Procedure I was
Which really makes me think about how Mass
These costs are would you
Want to be thinking about cost while you're going through it or is it better to just
Stay here your treatment options
Visa statistical outcomes
Like
Pick one
And then we'll deal with it on the other
I think there's an
Kind of
Unspoken agreement among everyone that the insurance company or Medicare is going to pay
And if it's the government that means our grandchildren
Are going to end up paying
For all of this
Money so yes I guess to answer your question I think it would be healthier to know what
Distance Quest on the other hand I have to say is
Patient
I was so traumatized I'm not sure I could have taken that information in
I was thinking about your what what is worth
What's it worth
A title and I was thinking that
The American individualistic
Optimistic
Response would be well whatever it takes
Whatever it takes
Life is worth it whatever it takes
But whatever it takes
Will not cure my cancer
So I think this question changes
When you have incurable
It becomes a different question which is one is enough
Enough
She said that when is enough enough
I was just I don't know that we are ready to say there's one magic
Thrown back to this conversation that I had with Leonard saltz where he was saying that we have to look at everything in terms
Of value
You need to think deeply about the kind of life you want to live
It's not just about
How many days
It's about what kind of
Daiso if you told me
But there was something that gave 72
Day survival benefit but it makes people feel nauseous for most of the time
Is that worth it when were trying to draw this line as a society
Before we figure out what we're willing to
Pee-Wee have
Think about what
We are
Paying for
Yeah I don't think we know what we're Susan
He has six years ago she decided that she was going to get chemotherapy be
Because
In part it would be more time with her daughter
Yeah
And suddenly
It's worth it
Yeah
But I think we changed by the treatment to
For now Susan's cancer is
Basically under control
Because she's on this new drug
422 years and now months
And I am counting has been alive without a recurrence without the key
Cancer growing
By taking these pills everyday
I take them at home they're not infused in the hospital through my veins
They're just pills
And it's made last
Few years
Remarkably
Normal light
The new Norm
But when these drugs stop working in
I've been told they will stop
Working
I'm not sure I would want to go back to chemotherapy
But I suspect I don't know until I get there
Producer Molly Webster
And now for the thank yous for that piece week we want to thank Stephen Hall and
Fundimension Susan gubar Facebook
Both Memoir of a debulked woman and thanks also to dr. Atul gawande for all his help
And his latest book is really I really found a wonderful is called being mortal
Thanks also to Nikki Haynes answer Glen Bloomquist radio level continue
You have two new messages
Message
Fun
Radiolab is supported
In part by the Alford plea
Sloan Foundation
In about slow Nat www.org
And distributed by NPR
And this message
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
This summer
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents
Aunts and uncles teachers we're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments child brilliant
Basically I want to hear about those times when I did something
It just means you lean back and say whoa
How do they do that
Maybe it was the moment that I
A kid you've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of their musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed are ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the
Epic moments where
Kid does something super smart but doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story please share it with us
Go to radiolab.org
Flash brilliance
And record a short audio message
Fan that's radiolab.org
Brilliance
Thank you so much
3-2-1 hey I'm Jared I'm Ron I'm Robert krulwich this is Radiolab in today but we're still on the subject of worth but the
This is a totally different take
Matt kielty
Next
Slightly different story about worth
Story
It rather than being about how much we value our own lives
About how much we value someone else
Mince tarts
BuzzFeed writer Gregory Johnson
So okay maybe you should start with what has now become sort of Feasts infamous
Well wedding wedding drone strike is that
Was that sort of where it started for you yes so this strike happens in a very rugged part of Yemen
Brother no paved roads no electricity there's no running water Thursday morning
December 12th 2013
Early that morning
In small village group of guys
Roughly
50 to 60 people in a soon-to-be married man
Allendale country cars
And they start driving this is the Convoy
The wedding Convoy
Now in the lead car this Convoy
Tasha Cobbs
His name is Abdullah Muhammad LTZ
We had spoke to him through an interpreter in Yemen
Do to me
It was his neighbor
Who is the groom to be married that day
The bright Cellars
Beulah said they got there a little before noon eat lunch
Resided wedding poems
Your lunch
They got the bride and just a few of her Bridal attendants a few females and they start driving back to
Grimm's Village
The actual wedding ceremony
Melt
Do said that ever since they left that morning
Lunch
All day long
They heard this
Humming the sort of metallic worrying this
Metallic thumping overhead no one of the conflict
See it but
Anywhere
Address
Sound sound
Hearing all the day
Nothing new for people in rural parts of Yemen by this point they don't think anything of it common to hear those sounds
Yeah it's usually held there
So
Try me
Basically if you can imagine it there
Serta winding through these Waters these desert mountains
Places
The road
He said they're all strung out on this
Ride it out little dirt track
11 cars single file
Up near the top of the
Cliff where they'll slow down and started the
Bunched together
Apparently
Model cars that got in a flat
How do you
Fixed it
Got back in their car
Right at that moment
The sound
Somehow
And then the missiles * 4
In quick succession the shrapnel is just flying everywhere
In a blink
Dover
People are trying to figure out what has happened all the screaming
There's fires that are burning
Anne Abdullah
His car was
Torn up
Metropolis Facebook
You mean really sorry
Is right hand left
Bye
Wonton in the back
And he says that
Muncy salary smoke
Express Outlet
Where's my son
He was he was looking for his son
Balsamo's there yeah young man you have been a few cars back from
Porsche car
And he was married
Two boys and one girl
Abdullah said he
Move so
You got a fast car
End
Stumble back for the 4th
Define the Sun
Just next to the car
Victorious
He died
Oh yeah
No he didn't
I'm just you looked at
Passed away
So
It turns out that there are 12 dead
And typically what happens in Yemen is that as soon as someone is killed their very very very shortly thereafter
What happens here is something different
The people in the Convoy
Take the bodies
Of the Dead
And they take them back to read the
This big town near where the Drone strike occurred
There's a video I have
It's what you're hearing Ricci cement take these 12 dead bodies
And a line them up in the street on this
Bright blue tarp and they sort of a wrap them in these cheap blank
And so there's this huge crowd that just gathers around 2
Stare at these dead bodies who are laid out in the
And at a certain point this very tiny very very leathery old yemeni who sort of
Holding onto the back of a
Pick up with one arm stands over the Dead
Sort of swing over the bodies and just lecturing the crowd on what happened he's
Screaming at them and so
You can hear his voice
Talk to Bill horse
Any screening in American drone killed these it was a massacre
People are on their way to a wedding
Why did this happen
Why were they kill
Why did they target this
This Convoy
Well according to the US
Did received Intel that
On that day in this Convoy
Al Qaeda operative
Name Sookie or badani apparently have been plenty of attacks
Mexican to us
That's why they took the shot
And in fact they say that he was wounded in this
In this wedding Convoy
Strike
And do we have any reason
Believe that
I have no reason to believe it
Greg spent weeks in Yemen.
Two survivors of the Drone strike talk to people who are there no one knows the
The sky
Brakes at the guy isn't really a member of either the tribes that were involved in the wedding
And so to him
It makes no sense that he would be there
To him this was
Terrible mistake
But what really got me interested in Craig's reporting
Which can be done buzzfeed.com highly recommended question of like
What
The US did next
The question is like
What do you do in this case how do you repair something like this
We have two totally different cultures with two different traditions
How do you find a way
To try to make this right
I mean historically
Do soldiers have an obligation to repair
No
There's no obligation
But what happened is we've actually
He created an obligation for ourselves
Americans have yeah yeah this has a really long history of History that's illegal
Legally yeah yeah a legal history
And they're said there's a great law professor at Yale
His last name is
Is Witt
John Wick
That's me
We ended up tracking down John Witt
Talk about how the US first started to try to right the wrongs
In war so what is the
Foundation
Story of Aldi
That start
Will General
Pershing World War
Caldwell
Great War ramps up
So we start shipping young men
Minions Malta
Physically France was a man
Name John Jay
Commander of
American forces on the Western Front
Mr Man
Pencil mustache bit of a Maverick single person is your nickname
Blackjack
And when he first arrives in France with the troops
Beginner bike at Pershing she's got this problem which is what he has Jeeps
Ship to France
Man by armor
World War 1
The first war in which
The US
Shipping a lot of automobile
More than a hundred thousand
For the soldiers to drive cars trucks
Cheap Jeeps are really great they got his men from one place to another Perry
Yenta
I also run into French Farmers chickens
Cows
Children sometimes just
Farmers themselves
These random collisions over there no roads I'm going to bet there was some of ever
Sometimes it was probably just ordinary car accidents in sometimes No Doubt
A little French wine was in
This is precious problem
Eastern Runner
Overseas
And it wasn't any good
For him to have
Grumpy civilians at his rear
And tell her she has an idea
Which actually bars in the bread
And that is
He will use
Money
Right or wrong
Once we go to the Congress and begs for a statue
And Congress blige's really quickly there's no sign the controversial thing but if it's genuinely new thing because For the First Time
In history of War
As far as we could tell
United State
Compensating individual
Usually the state state hear you have state
Individuals
Inside the US government starts
Systematically pain money
For the loss of a non-american life
In war how much
No actually surprisingly hard to find documentation mentioning
Pacific mounts
But whatever
Teen support Christian biography
Swift and prompt
Settlement claims
Had a great effect
On the people
Seem to work very well
Genesis
Semi CID here that like
What we would do with the Drone strike victims we talked about that
Pay the money
What's actually it's a
To be trickier than
Because the thing that person got
In World War 1
And that is
That
There's a combat exclusion
Kids just walked in that's Gregory Johnson and what he means is that this law
Basically what it said is that will pay your claims
If it didn't happen on the field of battle and it wasn't a combat
Situation
What's combat
And it was on the field of battle than
Tough luck
Just War so if u.s. soldiers were driving to a fight
And they
Ran their car into
To somebody
And they damage that car killed that person
Those people would not be able
How to get compensation whereas if the u.s. soldiers
Driving to a bar
And got in an accident they would be able
But
Covenants
Once we get into these counterinsurgency wars
Civilians are suddenly
In the middle of The Fray
Chargers have been made that troops killed as many as 567 South Vietnamese civilians
This is the story of Modern Warfare
President
Mothers and children by the time you get to Afghanistan and Iraq
So there's no difference really between Battlefield
My people live
And so the line between what's combat-related what's not combat-related
It starts to get
Blurry
And so in 2003 and Iraq what happened was there were actually people lining up
You know there were
Civilian military operation centers people started lining up outside of the saying
My family has been harmed I want help
How many people do you remember if I had to guess who is
Maybe around 80 people are so
That's a ton of people
Yeah
That's John Tracy he was a military lawyer in Iraq in two
And for him
Molly Keenan and managing director of Center for civilians in conflict
So when they came with a complaint with
So what is it like you ran over my chicken or you knocked out my window much more serious
Cluster bomb
During the shock and awe campaign
One of the
Types of bombs
That we were using
Are the Air Force was using what would they call cluster munition
HP chances Air Force plane to fly over these targets and drop
Hundreds and hundreds of these tiny little bombs
Smaller than a Coke can and a lot of them with land in maybe a parking lot
Field and it wouldn't explode so on a number of occasions you'd have mostly was kids right because the kids would
See it
And
They didn't know any better it would just run over and kick it
That's when it would
Explode
Right
I had a lot of those
Cost of a dozen and so
That was a
That was a difficult one because well
It's combat
Because they are forced dropped
Because they were
Mommy
The city right
But at the same time days weeks
Even months have gone by in this thing is just sitting in the ground
Couldn't we say it's not combat
It was a real question that John had to ask his boss and then his boss
His boss babe I actually sent the question up to the Army claim service
And they said no it's combat
Meaning they're not going to pay
Basically like we are in an in an armed conflict
And this was an unfortunate incident but an incident that happened
During a lawful combat operation and therefore
We're sorry
And that's basically it so I said no to a lot of pee
Until like in World War 1 with General Pershing Military Officers they started lobbying their bosses
Expanded system so they can
Start making more payments
Eventually the military.
Bandit
I talked to one of the military's top lawyers
Brigadier General Richard Cedros
I go by Rich
I'm the legal counsel to the chairman of the Joint Chiefs of
And you told me that around 2006
Peanut
These kind of condolence payments
Actually became sort of a
Key part of military strategy absolutely even had its own acronym
Malls
MAA WS6
Money as a weapons system which
You know I
I'm not sure that
Title resonates with everybody but in inches
Can be used
To win hearts and Minds that help bring the population over
And it just got me wondering
How much money
Makes
A good weapon
Well I haven't liked the US military hasn't given me access to a database or anything like that but it's through foia is and and and and
Interviews I've seen difference
Numbers Melissa's didn't 2060 ACLU file the foyer
And eventually got their hands on hundreds of claims files
In those files what you see are bunch of different numbers
One that comes up
Begin Again
$2,500 2500 bailar
Now it's someone like John could have paid more but that meant they have to run the claim up the chain of command exactly
It was almost like there were these ceilings
2500 for a life
1504 property damage and then eventually the property damage amount got raised to 2500
Well
And
That didn't make any sense
But somebody could get so much
For a Toyota Corolla but
You weren't you were just make it the same amount
File for a lost life
Like I can't get over I mean 2500 seems like just such a nominal amount in the practicality of that money
If like if you were to kill someone who is the
The Breadwinner of a family
That $2,500 would not be able to support this family in any way
Right but we're not actually trying to pay full compensation right like we're not trying to say
We think if this
20 year old man had lived
To be the average age in Afghanistan that he knows that it would have been
$60,843
Right like that's not the thing you ever
You know we had
People who were killed here
Federal government is one step closer to cutting it
First check
2 families of those
Killed and injured on September 11
And those people have been comp
The levels of compensation to the New York victims
Is it is
Pretty
The range of payments for death
Playing
Range anywhere from 200
$50,000
To just under 7 million
You noticed that
Baidu
But it is to a large degree comparing apples and or
That's generous again because you're talkin about 8
Illegal
System where country is
Paying
Their own victims
Purses
Condolences in a in an area where there's no legal obligation to make those
What's in the first place
So that's a very different type of
Monetary payments
Yes or no essentially it's a
Person's life
And yeah I mean
I need is an argument to be made that
Is empathy in the number that you come up with
Any amount that you
Pay for someone's
I totally get what you're saying
The $2,500
I think it's any amount of money if I told you 10 would you feel better about it I mean a little bit better I think so Tim what is it
Get you though
Indian $10,000 doesn't buy anything more back than what
You lie I don't know what time doesn't get you exactly in Afghanistan but my
Assumption is that it gets you a lot more than 2500
But does that really help you
Is that really what you want
Where's the money unimportant you really
Sounds like the money is really
I'm not a victim so I don't know that I can answer that to me
At this point my oldest story about how before she got in this line of work I had several friends who were
One of his friends was a man named Chris hondros
Back in 2011 Christmas on assignment Olivia
Movie with the rebel group
When they were fired upon
Chris was killed
Yeah
Am I
When she found out that happen
I wanted someone explain to me why that happened
I mean
I just want to know
Lane
I didn't even like
The newest family was going to get any money I need that
These guys were shuttle rocket propelled grenade at him working to care
No one was going to explain
I wanted that
And the money then becomes
An occasion
Please say sike
Not just I'm sorry but here's what happened
Is the Hughes what happened part
I think it's the token
It's given with the apology and with the exponent
But it's the apology and explanation
Yeah that's why we call it a mints
Making amends
One of the things that is true of money damages
Generally is there
There are desperate effort
To find some common language between the the party paying
And the and the victim
Some Esperanto for communicating the meaning of what's happened in a language movie
Other side nose matters message on witblits it because we we see it everywhere we look we see
Apologies apologies at all but we see the the almighty dollar which is both distress
Sing and also we knew we know it's meaningful
But the problem is
In order for that Esperanza to work it has to stay the same meaning to both sides
Which Wich on Tracy
What's it really about the money at all
Not just about the money
It was as much about the envelope that the money was in
Or that there was a real person there two handed
I wasn't the one who raided their house I wasn't
The one who
Killed their daughter
But
Most of them
Babe you know just wanted to look at somebody who's in the universe
You really messed with my life
That opportunity
Is exactly what Abdullah LTC
Alessia Cara
Will never get
His son was killed by a drone he never saw operated by a man who never meet on behalf of a country that still doesn't admit
It was a mistake
Into the money he got
Which Indian he says was the equivalent of 30000 US dollars
Way more than anyone got in Iraq
Afghanistan
Still
All I can do
Without anything else to go on
It's just compare amount
He can accept that only if
If
He gets to know the
Like the payment
Equal to CC
To like in America how long you can persuade someone who
Who lost his son from the payment was the payment was equal
Yeah
Producer Matthew
Guilty
Big thanks to Gregory Johnson writer Lodge from BuzzFeed who started us off on this adventure when you brought us
The initial story also thanks to a buzzfeed editor Steve can tell you about Misawa for helping Matt organize that interview with
In Yemen when the country is going through an awful lot of
Hamilton
He was able to
To get interviews that we didn't think he'd
Yeah absolutely thank you to him coming up
Hey this is Gregory Johnson
Jonathan Tracy
40th and park by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation understanding of Science and Technology
World more information about
Www.
Sloan. Org
And this message
Okay now.
And how are you
Good how you doing
Hey I'm Jared I'm right I'm rubber forward to Radiolab and so far we can talk about the value of our lives and then the value of other people
Whose lives next up
Value of
Everything
Audit
Kevlar
Rethink I buy everything's going swimming this value
Of nature
That's Carl Zimmer science writer regular blower of Mines soap
We
Think of ecosystems as just kind of
Sitting there actually they're doing things
They weren't doing them for us we would have to pay
To do them artificially
For example cotton farms in South Texas
So that you know the farmers are doing their thing like this guy
James Parker
I don't usually five to six seven hundred acres of cotton Soul say mm Bale
I spent a lot of time on a tractor in
Yes check your water every morning every evening meanwhile
They have
All this extra help
In the air
Yes
How many bats are out there you really don't know
Flying all around
The bats eat
The equivalent of 2/3 of their own weight
In insects
Every night
Wow
They eat all night long
All kind of bugs
A whole bunch of pets
That would otherwise be eating the car
Now a few years ago guy named John Westfall get a calculation
Came out to my farm and did this study he had some college girls at work for him and those girls were out there all
All hours of the night listening to what the bats were saying and each year the farmers
Collectively they make
About 45 million dollars off of
The farm
Question was how much of this is because of the bat
You know bats are natural pesticide spray
Figured out
Out of 45 million dollars it was around $700,000
That
You could describe to the bats
It's just beautiful
I mean it does make me sick
If you're those farmers
You should be compensating the bats
Yeah well yeah
It does give you a glimpse
The kind of scale of value economic value
That nature has that we generally just totally ignore but
We talked to a guy who didn't ignore
My name is Robert costanzo in fact he took this way of thinking to the app
Absolute limit
So the question was
What's the value of all of these ecosystem Services globally
All the services on Earth has bugs eating leaves worms turning the soil is chewing tree stump
Taking cities during storms everything
We tried to synthesize all of the studies that had been done around the country in the world
Like that bad study
Except I didn't just look at it
Cotton Farms they looked at tropical forest
Rivers and lakes
Corriere
Coastal Wetland Inland Wetland the ocean Woodlands temperate forest you know it goes on and on
Excel spreadsheet
It's it's kind of a Excel spreadsheet
From hell can get tricky so Costanza and his colleagues took all these different
Some of them together did a whole bunch of math and
Came up with a number
Which in today's dollars
Is 142.7
A trillion dollars
Pergear
Car services
That's more than
All of the
Gross national product
Of the world
That's how viable
The services of nature are
Masc guy get the I get the way this will work with a bat
Play bats eating the box but like how do you do it
With like
Would like a like a
Field or something like you just walk through and I guess that's
20 bucks
How do you figure out what the services are
Well are they they came up with a list
So
The list kind of depends
On the ecosystem you're talkin about
Does different ecosystems provide different services
For example
A
A salt marsh
And we are in the Waterfront
You're in the water
What is it with Sweets Salt marshes it like a Florida wetlands
I don't know what a salt marsh
Salt marshes are wetlands that are on the
Coast Guard water here we're quickly approaching high tide
We sent one of our producers simonelli to a nearby salt marsh
Parsley to Hazen your boots are much more water
Talk to this guy
My name is Adam Whelchel and I'm the director science
For The Nature Conservancy here in Connecticut and Adam gave Simon Atlantic inventory
/
Coastal salt marshes
The stream of goods and services
Invited over time
One of the things that does is
It takes water that's coming in
From Inland and it's Laden with all sorts of pollutant salsa
Start the bad stuff the salt marsh was trapped at water so the
Settle in and very often the Marsh Grass
Will suck up that water
Do the roots and
Clean it up
So you could ask Gary
How much would you have to
Suspend
To keep your water
That clean
There is one other study guide
Adam Whelchel said that scientists New England already figured that out
For flood control water supply protection pollution controls roughly about $31
Cars in $0.22
Per hectare per year then you got to add the value of all the plants that feed the fish that end up on our dinner play 338.
Been there the birdwatchers that by latte support the local economy
$90 per hectare and then there's habitat provisioning the list goes on and on and on
You get kind of obsessed with that you start like
You start becoming an accountant and writing down numbers
Seriously
And it gets you too
Think about nature
In a different way
Then you had before
Galling
Element over this aspect like when I first came across
This pointer producer Tim Howard jump into the interview in
You'll also hear Opera
Pretty sister on wheeler in
I do feel like in an example like the Salt March
Which cleans water that's all reliant on
People being there that need water so if you didn't have people there
Does that saltmarsh cica have any value but Tim haven't you ever had a conversation with somebody who just doesn't get
Like if you make the aesthetic art
Which is that nature
Should be should be preserved for its own sake
There's a whole category of humanity just doesn't respond to that argument
Is this becomes a way to
Talk across the aisle but it does still feel like Adam Oates something of infinite value
2 something of
Appeal evaluation really beat infinite value I mean would like a mother's love you don't take your mother's love is priceless I mean you know
Okay
II
Totally accept that there is
The Serta Priceless aspect of nature
But if you are
In the government in a very poor country
You have some tough choices to make
If somebody comes to you and says okay you got these lovely mangrove
How it turns out that
That the desert of
Setting with mangoes are is the perfect place
For shrimp aquaculture
Biggest shrimp Farms need lots of seawater so it makes sense to
But then we're going to put in these Farms are going to go shrimp
You are going to get millions and millions of dollars in tax revenue
If you're thinking about the welfare of all the people in your country
Many of them are starving
That might be a really powerful argument
Not into that kind of a discussion
You can bring in
The fact that these men grows
Are sitting there
Very quietly doing all sorts of incredibly valuable thing
In fact they've done these kind of calculation
And in some cases
The services that mangroves provide
AR
4 *
More valuable than what you could get out
With shrimp so it's stupid
It's just stupid
In a bit very basic sense
To wantonly replace lots of mangroves
With shrimp aquaculture
Is that a hypothetical situation know that's your ass
This is Glenn Marie Lang she's an environmental economist for the World Bank and she says very often
She finds herself in exactly this kind of conversation. You know I work for the world bank's or prime
Primary clients are our governments
Philippines Vietnam when you're talkin to a minister of finance and saying
You know what I know jobs are jobs but you need those Marsha
They have value don't say well yeah that's true but that means I'm going to have to reduce
The money that I put into the education budget
So you got to really make a strong argument about the benefits
That's really where the rubber hits the road
Well
I mean that's here's the counter-argument it comes from Doug McCauley and
The college's at Universal
City California
Santa Barbara the real danger is that we actually succeed that we
We convince people that nature is Viola cuz it makes money and then where
We're really in trouble in the minions is for a doesn't make us money
What do you do in a situation he says we're
Say a bunch of rivers are running dry
I am there
Quote depreciating in value you know by the same logic that you trained to think with
We should go out and liquidate these natural assets that makes me feel really uncomfortable he says it's just kind of a weird way to think
Nature proposal hearing
City California to make
Gay marriage law
And
Economist how to look at this legislation and said
This is
Expected to generate
163 million dollars annually
State of California
Well
It's good to know that
I appreciate having that information in front of me however when I'm making a
A decision on this legislation and I would say
It wouldn't many legislators
Voters average citizens are considering issues at hand
They're not thinking about whether they're going to make hundreds
60 million dollars
The state that thinking about a different set of values
On the other hand I want to say and this is based on my
Experience working in developing country
When you don't
Put a value on these services
Basically they don't get counted
They get implicitly assigned a value of 0
Queenie Glenn Murray
And as we were debating this going back and forth and back
We bumped into a story
About what happens when all of these value of nature ideas are
Are let loose into a world
Fruits
And trees
Human uncertainty
The parable of the bees
We heard this first from writer JB MacKinnon who says the Story begins
And now County in central China
Rural area fairly remote
Lush Green Mountains filled with apple orchards
And apple orchard in was
What is the main business
I'm going to JB in in the 1990s
The wild bees male County slowly started to
To disappear
There's a few different
Reasons given for that
It could have been the destruction of the habitat
The bees nest in
The heavy honey harvesting that wasn't leaving enough food for the bees but the
The prevailing Theory
He's actually a nikkah nama
Because Emma 1990s of China was shifting to a market-based
Apple producers are under pressure to produce
More apples
So they started spraying pesticide
Probably it was a constellation of
All of those things in a few others
End result is
Baby stopped buzzing in mouth County
Which if you are
Apple farmer
That's a disaster
Bees travel from flower to flower
Search of nectar they are over there
Dusted with
Pollen which is
The means by which flowers
Engage in sexual intercourse
So if you don't have the bees making the birds and the bees
On the blossoms
Then
Then you don't get fertile flowers
To turn into turn into fruit and obviously if you're a fruit farmer and you have no fruit to sell you have no income
So what are you do you're not performing you don't have these then you need to find some other way to pollinate the flowers
And I guess they concluded
What will have to add ourselves
Bai hat in Mandarin Chinese with Asian Gong Show
And so would be that means Emmanuel coronation
This is Harold Tebow in China for the French newspaper Le Monde a couple years ago
The Apple farmers in mouth
Lcounty so he flies to Chengdu and he in a friend Hopper
In the car and we drive for like five or six hours until we reach a disability International
Tiny little village
Few houses
And then we took your smaller
Rodenbach
The field
And we have to be so old that they wear
Lots of farmers
In the trees like on the apple trees
Rattling up and down these muffins
Thin and spindly branches
Men and women that have seen in in
Photos
Harold and his friend took pictures and if you look at those pictures you'll see the farmers holding little brats
Little pollen brush that they constructed using things like Chopsticks and chicken feathers and cigarette filter
I made have a little bottle filled with pollen and then what they do
They dip the brush into the Ballon a paint
Poem
Makeup airbrush Mac
Into the pollen
Make me the next flower
Canada
Begin again and I paint again
To make sure that that
All of the blossoms that they could possibly fertilized
Would be fertilized so that they would go on to produce fruit we're talking hundreds and hundreds
The flowers for
Missouri
Strange to see you
Are you human
The job of the bees
How would a pain in the ass
The image of this of these
Chinese orchardist standing up in these spindly trees
Traveled around the world through environmental circles
And it
The message that it seemed to send was that
This is what happens if you if you lose biodiversity you end up standing in the trees
Doing the job that the bees used to do on the win
For free
Those people are just like
Human beast in this guy
Yeah
Human Beast four years ago he travel to mail County to do
Economic analysis of just how much the loss of the bees
Is hurting the farmers amount County
But what he discovered weird
Was it the trees were producing more apples than ever
What production
This can be confirmed
Zelmore production
For hand pollination apple tree bee pollination for tree
Humans are more efficient
Really people were doing it better than the beasts I've been doing it
A lot better reproduction went up
30% that's what the farmers told you disenchant just kind of amazing
Amber amazing
Because I think hand pollination can pollinate
Maserati every flower
And bees don't pollinate a flower
These are a little bit
Yeah they're a little bit uneven when it comes to
I don't like it if it's damp
They don't like it if it's windy in all those cases bees often decide to stay indoors and just take
You send people out there and tell him to pollinate every damn block
And they're going to do it and there is the additional benefit of
The people that you paid
They go to the bar they buy groceries babe
Spend those earnings
In their local communities in a way that
Obviously
Bees never did
To hear you had this whole story that was supposed to be about
How important the bees are in the parable of biodiversity through that may be the lessons just the opposite
They're actually
We don't need bees
And maybe we never did
If we only measure things economically then we might conclude that
That some species are some ecological processes just aren't necessary in certain places
I or that we might
Even do better
To to take care of those
Processes ourselves right
So
Let me find My Notes app
Which is exactly but there's one more chapter
The story Harold the boat told us when he visited then Chen
Is there a 68
And he said in his opinion
Henry Nation
Night disappear in a few years
Apparently as China's economy has continued to grow workers have started demanding better pay
New wages are getting so high
Father welcomes that the farmers have to employ to help them basically it's not efficient
Economically
To do the information anymore
Now they're like
They thinking
Need a piece back right yeah
Problem is there are no Bees in those Villages anymore beekeepers in other parts of China
Not going to bring their bees
This area cuz they worry about the pesticide
At the pharmacy
That's what when wild bees might come back
Weather for this week
It's very hard to make a prediction
If you have the Farmer they like
What would you do I don't know
History of that
Story thieves me
It leaves me thinking that you can Amish is just not a good way
Putting an r value
Even though
Even up
Syson
Thoughtful value on a b
On the pound
It you do it and you think you're smart
But then the value changes the bees go from being worth a lot
To being worth nothing to be worth everything
What was in a few years this this is what markets do they swing back forth
And we pretend that we can play
But we never can
So you can't put the volume cuz you can always going to be wrong or right
Weather Cypress
Nowhere in the story did someone walk into the middle of
The proceedings
You know what these do have value here's the number
Text Carl we were talking to him told us you know they've been estimates that the value of pollination
When it comes from wild bees
Is 190 billion dollars
So that's globally right but still there was nobody in the room
Giving that kind of number to the bees were inherently valued at
Zero remember Beazer value to 0 only until humans get valued more than bees go down if he's going to have a lot of
Numbers in your head what I like about this idea is it
When you put a number on a bee or a bat
Are Marsh
It's like an attempt
2force
What kind of long-term thinking
You can just say don't do that mean something that like a conservation to say don't
But if you say don't do that
Here's the Valium so lost
Yeah here's the lost one that actually gives the whole
Precautionary don't sing some teeth
Except for this
That if you go
Businesses
And you're wrong
There are irreversibilities that's how environmental economist Glenn Marie Lange
This is one of the differences between natural ecosystems and what we produce
You smash your car hey someone can build a new one if you lose the bees
Many instances
You cannot bring them back
So the question we got to is
Is there another way to think about the value of nature
Show me the way that's not economic
And therefore short-sighted know about us but also
Not simply about
The Aesthetics in the beauty cuz I can be sore
Is there another way
The best I was able to do
Thinking about that
Writer JB MacKinnon
Was
When it struck me that
That in a way
All of this
Diversity that's out there all this biological diversity all these
Wonderful and amazing
And alien things that other species can do
Is like an extension of our own brains
There's so much imagination out there that we simply
Could not come up with
On our own
That
We can think of it as
As a pool
Of imagination
And creativity from which we
As humans are able to draw
And that when we draw down on that
On that pool of
Creativity and Imagination
We
We deeply impoverished ourselves
New innocence we are
We are doing harm
To our own ability to think
I didn't do and dream
JB MacKinnon book is called The Once and Future World he's written many but this one is my favorite thanks to Carl Zimmer
Reporting in the New York Times
On this topic is really what got us
Launch today
And what got us through this whole thing is Simon Adler whose production assistance was invaluable that was him
Freezing his ass off in the marsh I talked so long
How to spell awfully
Thank you and thank you guys for listening on Jedi
We'll see you next time
Hi Robert costanzo
Glenn Marie Lange
Adam Whelchel I'm calling in to read some credit show here we go
Radioactive
Produced by Chad Eva Braun
Our staff
Includes ellenhorn
Brenna Farrell
Guilty Adler
Simon Adler
And Claire tennis getter this episode
Goodbye Michelle Toronto
Special thanks to Rich
Oh my goodness
Rich
Dimeglio Lindblom quiz
Alma Flor graceful mm gun camera
Sally and reprieve
Expertise in Yemen
That's my best shot
And this message