Are you awake
Northern listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
Hey this is Chad from Radiolab so we were not planning on releasing a podcast
Cast today
But then
Friday app
The federal government tonight outlining and elaborate
Expensive and extraordinary assault on US democracy
Use of a massive effort
Unless you have been living under a rock for the past 3 days you probably heard that
Special counsel Robert Mueller
Guided
President Trump keeps accusing of being engaged in a Witch Hunt
He has handed down to indictments information Warfare
Against the United States
Create chaos
Going so far as to America traveling
Throughout nine states that you get from the indictment
Is it there was a sort of like
Shadowy network of Russian Nationals had infiltrated the country
It with the idea of sowing chaos in the run-up to the 2016 election
Very simply like who are these Russians
And who are these Americans that were manipulated how did it
How did it work
How do they feel about things
Now
So what we decided to do for this part
Just cuz we are curious
And just cuz you know
Fun for a podcast
Black Arts
You fast turnaround stuff on occasion
We decided to see what we can find
Producer Simon Adler takes affirm
Pay Charles are you there
I'm doing alright little sleepy better than that of
So not too long ago I got in touch with this a radio producer reporter based in Moscow by the name of
Charles Main
Yeah that be great I'm in a sort of my pajamas but yeah
Find the song
It was like 3 in the morning New York time at but but anyways I'm the reason I got in touch with him was to
Have him help facilitate and interpret an interview with this guy
My name is
I am from Russia, Saint Petersburg
I'm sorry I speak English oh no don't worry about it that's why you got Charles 4
I think of a child
Okay great
It was like
Where are you from originally I'm just curious like a little bit about who you are
Resume.
Vitaly bespalov is a kid from a small town in Siberia
Small town near kha'zix
And he said from an early age it was clear that he
Just really didn't fit in up there
Blue hair for a Time dressed like a goth
To be this kind of alternative character in Siberia is not an easy
Anything let me know
Which of these stories about walking down the street
I get some kind of tough guys with short haircuts or condom faget
When he gets a chance to to get out he does he moves to st. Petersburg considered one of the most liberal cities in Russia
And he moved they're not looking for just any job but
Specifically
To be a journalist
He really felt was his calling
Superheroes that refers to journalist as like supercar
Batman
If we had the same Petersburg and he
Thinks he's all set up he's got
A job with a local website
Editing for them
Writing
But right away with Within
Short order I believe the story is their business dried up and so did the newspaper in
And suddenly it Batali's out of
What's next
And so it's kind of a crisis moment
Muscle shirtless
He starts looking around and he's
As he describes he gets up every day start sending out all these resumes
Doing searches 2-speed find anybody to do anything that would let him
Use his writing skills just trying to find something to do with text
Until finally after almost a month of this
He comes across this one ad
That's
It's not really clear what their offering or
Who's offering it but it mentions that there's some
Copy editing to be done some writing
And
The pay scale seems a lot higher its if they're promising double the money is at the most people are offered for
The working in journalism in Russia
And then right away he just stopped
Weird but
Of course he's in
I'm how could he not be in so he
Places to call
Now it's worth noting everything that
Is about to happen vitally we weren't able to fact-check 100
But that being said it does lineup squarely with
What others have
Reported
Anyway
Fast forward a couple days he ends up having the interview and they offer him the job
I would she accept
Or the whale
Still not really knowing
What the heck it is he will be doing
Exactly
It's just not really clear what
What it is
Okay so tell me about that first day like
Popeyes
Entering into the foyer of the building
The entrance
The building itself is cement for story
Tall and the security is is oddly strip
Like when he went up to them they required him to hand over a bunch of document
It's like his
Passport
Just to get in that's his first term
Mythical man and his boss shows up this woman named Anna she walks
Halsey
He said the whole place had like the feel of a hospice
Long corridors with little rooms
Left and right
People behind
Keyboards working at computers
And it's almost completely silent
Except for the tapping of fingers on
Keys
Anyway eventually they they duck into a room on a shows his desk
This
Is finally when you get two cents
Of what exactly is going on
Anna sitting down says we're doing news about Ukraine
We just want you to write articles
20 articles a day you had to do sort of massage the text
4 but the thing is he didn't have to be brand new Arctic
But instead he was told since we take this article it's already been written
Somebody else's article
And
Or add to it and then change the contents of 70% original
So what's important to know here is this was 2014
And complain with in the early days of War
The apocalyptic
Scene in central Kiev tonight's morning Kiev again I woke to the sound of gunfire
A civil war that Russia wanted to influence the outcome
And to do so
They started experimenting with his new form of propaganda
That's right
What you saw was this Keno campaign it was going on two fronts
When on the one hand you had State media influencer program intermediate here broadcast from Russia
Ukraine
Spinning the narrative for those watching
But
Then you have a certain amount of the population that
Rastas in watch Dayton
And this is where you get into this effort
Chicago plug the holes in the story online
No no we have been hired to do
CO2 steel that storage
So
Yo
They told him to
Take an article that was
About Ukraine for example according to Vitaly there was an incident in which a group of
Pro-russian Rebels had taken over a school in Ukraine essentially holding the kids hostage
When the pro Ukrainian soldiers when they when they stormed the school
Children die
This actually happened and was covered by
Vibe Ukrainian media
But
Arnavut Ali's boss
Says your goal is to take this real news story and rewrite it leaving out the fact that there were
Ever any
Pro Russian troops there
Treating the impression that the pro Ukrainian troops had stormed the school in Massacre these children for
No reason at all
Brazil worship
And so once he had to be written this article made these small changes
Horse photography with create a website with a
The. UA ads
Ukraine address
Site that look like a local online Ukrainian news
Ostensibly written by ukrainians
4 Ukrainian audience
So he's being asked to write about Ukraine as if he was writing from you
Yeah exactly
Exactly the way he describes it while he's working on his newspapers
Evolving events in Ukraine pretending to be Ukrainian journalist
Deciding blogs
They're written
Extensively by ukrainians and he
Pretty sure that bloggers upstairs in the next level up inside this building a nest
Saint Petersburg
So it's a feedback loop
What end
So I'm presuming on day one
You shown up there
With these high-minded journalistic ideals
And you have to realize that you've gotten yourself into something
That
In no way lives up to
To those ID
How on Earth did that feel
Cancel
Go to Bistro
Important moment where he's trying to decide what to do
He says himself that he had cut
2 thoughts which is
Iau get
Out of there
And never come back
Orbi to go back and find out more what what's going on there
And it gets this idea that you know it
Maybe I've got a scoop here maybe I can do in bed
Navigation he sort of assign themselves
To become an undercover agent
Exactly
Okay just to to zoom out here for a second
The job that Vitaly had taken was with an organization known as the internet
Shadowy Russian organization Shreveport so much about in the past 72 hours
Private company established in 2013
Buy a Putin Ally name
Along with being the bearer of a rather strange nickname of President Vladimir Putin
Also one of the Russian Nationals mentioned in the Mueller indictment in the early days when Vitaly was working there
It was his impression that there were roughly a couple hundred people working
At the internet research agency but at its peak
Organization grew to a to employ as many as a thousand people for the annual budget of millions of dollars
Headed by a Management Group
And arranged into departments including graphics
Search engine optimization
Information technology and finance
Now as the Polly told us it was hard to know exactly what
Happened in this place
Because everyone was so silent but over his time there he was able to make sense of some of it
The first floor was filled with people just like Vitaly
Writing fake articles
Fake sites
Second floor was known as the social media department and the folks were responsible for pumping out knee
Like Hillary Clinton is shaking hands with the devil people writing fake
The same blog that the tollywood pull quotes from
On the 4th floor seat find the YouTube and Facebook, controls
Along with the cafeteria
What's the Bill of Rights
Are you 24/7 operation they never
Never stop making
News never spotted stops
Generating content
What and who are your co-workers
Lost quite a few people from other towns of Russia that moved to St Petersburg
They were some people he said we're frankly you know
Activists in the opposition
Are there alot of people there
You know like
You know they check in the checkout for work they just punch the clock
And yeah for them it was just like mopping a floor
Where are you know
Are taking out the trash did you feel some guilt
Or
Misgivings about what you were doing
What about really stressed out
Miss her. She was
You know on the one hand I suppose he's Gathering good
Material for
What will hopefully be some
Grand expose
Alright
The other hand he just felt like he was just living this lie
Eventually after three and a half months
Vitaly did quit
And if he tells it
He had enough
And just didn't feel like he could learn anything else
And so with his months of research
He went on to write an article in Russia that really didn't make a splash at all
In part because the internet research agency was
Already a pretty well-known organization in Russia at the
That time
Essentially other journalists had just beaten him to the punch
But then
In the wake of the 2016 election with accusations of Russian meddling beginning to swirl
Inside russian disinformation campaign
From twenty-six-year-old Vitaly best for the American Media took notice and
Vitaly got a call from NBC
This is the building
Yes yes yes
The troll Factory eyebrow piercing
Pink sweater on of Vitaly answer questions for this brief evening new II
Did you create
Fake accounts
Yes he says
Do you believe that this operation was backed by the Kremlin
He said
Still up and running
The Kremlin denies it
Suggesting reports the factory even existed
My feet face
NBC NBC The Bully
And from that moment on he really became the go-to guy if you wanted to
Talk to somebody who had worked inside
Journalists from all over the world started reaching out to him with nothing to you asking for interviews
Comments
Israel International
None of the Russian
Until one day not long after all
So he gets a call from this National
Tell television channel saying basic in an hour
We're going to run a story about you and we really want you to come on our talk show
Annie said look I'm busy I'm working and I you know I can't do it
And so now they run
I'm a donkey to the canal and Basin National Park
In the TV studio on the set that look like a cross between a
Family Feud and an evening news broadcast
The hosts just start taking Vitaly apart and flashing images of him on this
Giant screen behind them
P21 the garage of mine his online
Hanging out
Club making funny faces
Camera
What's Napoleon march to buy Super Sub Shop
Digging through his political views the fact that he's a supporter of the liberal opposition
C o n n n they just make him out to be this kind of free
And they're all laughing at him and
Yeah he said it's just it's just an absolute Publix login
Being a total public
Wow when he got caught in his own
Little misinformation
Loop
There at the end
Yeah yeah
That's right
Lepanto
Yeah the way he describes it is that
You know in some ways
When he was there
They were just trying to figure out the mechanism
It was getting more sophisticated
Educated
And as he's leaving
His time is ending at the internet research agency
She says
Just about this time he started seeing these posts
Four vacancies
In other languages
Including
English
Valdosta
Away he is for him is this morrissey's
The troll Farm the troll Factory
Suddenly
Turning out
Well now 3 years later
We know a bit more about this
English
Initiative
In 2014
The company established a translator project
Focused on the United States
In July 2016
More than 80 employees
Were assigned to the
Translator project
And many of those employees apparently took some of the moves from their Ukraine infowar Playbook
In Houston
When did the
At the US
Russian gospel recruited and paid real American
Do engage in political activities
Promote political campaigns
End-stage political rally
The defendants and their co-conspirators pretended
To be Grassroots active
In fact I spoke to one reporter who told me about this incident in Houston
When the
Two protests happening at the same time
The one side of the street a white nationalist protest
And on the other
A group of Americans for Muslims
Print out both Proto
Covertly organized by Russians connected
2B internet research age
According to the indictment
The Americans did not know
They were communicating with Russia
It was this phrase
Out of all of the Ludacris Revelations of the indictment
That really got it
Who were these annoying Americans
How did they end up at the fake protest in
How do they think about it now
Show producer Eddie McEwen and I we started calling around
We found three people at the center of one of the more
Famous
Fake protest mentioned Indian.
The so-called Florida flash mob will hear all about that
After the break this is Radiolab will continue in a moment
Hi there this is Kirsten recording from Orlando Florida Radiolab is supported in part by the
Alfred P Sloan Foundation enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloan at www. Sloan. Org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here I'm a producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
And I request for those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents
Aunts and uncles teachers
We're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments
Basically I want to hear about this
I kid you know did something
It just means you lean back and say
Well
Maybe it was the moment that our kids you've been reading to 4 month started reading
Back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of the musical score
Or maybe the kids in math
Music in the margin of their geometry
We're interested in the
Specific moments where
Kid does something super smart
It doesn't have anything to do with the test
If you have a story
Go to radiolab.org
Flash brilliance
Record short audio message
And that's radiolab.org
Flash Brewing
Thank you so much
This is Radiolab on Chatham Road so after those indictments came down
I guess the three Russian companies in 13 Rush
Nationals
I work use Aveeno creating fake
Protests across
The country are producers Simon Adler and Annie McEwen
Cottage City
Try and locate some people who had gone to these protests and maybe
Unwittingly
Took part in What was a covert Russian operation
They managed to find three people
Alright you can hear me yes I can hear you in fine for stop the woman named Anne-Marie Margaret Thomas
Who lives in Florida I live in Jupiter Florida currently and is in her 50s she works as a real estate agent and also
I long to see you
Beautiful
Very active on Twitter end in early August 2016
Just contacted first on Twitter then over the phone
My two guys Joshua and Matt
UCLA
They said they were
They were on
Working with
Hollywood producers
Matt and Josh needs R2
People from Hollywood browsing the film school right I don't know that they didn't give me that much
Information on the phone and thought Joshua's voice sounded
Familiar I better not I should say who I think it is
Who did you think it was come on just really curious
Who do I think it is
John Christopher
Yahoo John Crist
Fake name is Johnny
Yanni the musician
Wait this is Yanni the like Orchestra New Age piano god guy
Yeah yeah but I think she's just guessing like there's no actual evidence looking Yanni to any of this
What was the organization they were working with
This was the March for Trump
Group and they were Grassroots organization started in the United States Texas and California
They ask you what did they say when they contacted you
Well they were they said they were wanting to do
At a Hollywood people wanted to hire
Reactor
Want to play Trump
Want to play Bill Clinton and one play Hillary
Interesting
They basically told her that they want her to do this like performance arts theater protest outside
Now at the same time she was talking to these guys
On the other side of Palm Beach County
The name of Harry Miller
Someone in there but she also got contacts on Twitter and over the phone
There was a conversation about
The desire to put on a something like a flash mob or something
And supporting Donald Trump
I believe his name is Matt what did Matt say in his original sort of communication
This is it
Extremely paraphrase because I don't have a distinct memory of Oliver
And initially I was very suspect up and the reason I was so
Is because
A headache
Strong accent
And at the time it was a lot of commotion about Muslims
I thought he was some who is one of some kind I was trying to set something up
What did his voice sound like
It wasn't like you articulate it was
It was broken
What in Turkey
He said he wanted a flash mob and what did he
What did he say he wanted you to do it I he was asking me about making a trailer with a jail type of thing
It's actually the guy with the accent told him I want you to Stage an event
We have a cage
I'm going to need to build this cage
But you're going to have this Cajun at the event there will be a Hillary Clinton impersonator
Bill Clinton impersonator
I want you to put them in the cage
Like you're putting them in jail
And you should do this outside but lots of people can see you and they can chant lock her up lock her up and you should take lots of photos
Videos and you should send them to us
And I did eventually say yes because he had an elaborate wedding
But shiny told me his part of a big group of people
Being patriotic
It's dismantled according to the FBI now
I can't get a bigger
How did they end up paying for it
They sent
Me to 8
Check cashing place
How much money was it
That found an estimate
And I written estimate around $505 for it
But it did come from out of the country I do do recall that
Can you describe what this
Once the
Construction was complete
What your truck look like
I have an F-350 Ford
Pickup truck
Big truck
Yeah and
I build a
Chain link fence
Three sides
And then one side with a gate
Four Corners
I had the American flag
Of course
And there was a lot of talk about
Who is going to go in the cage
And hate hate
No one would play Trump
Answers the two quote UCLA guys suggested that she play Hillary
Angie Creed costume
I need the costume from a nurse's outfit and on the back instead inmate
I went to the store and I bought a full head mask of Hillary
And so what were they like you're told the
What were you told like show up and this place at this time at this date and you just
Did it in Palm Beach City Place
In front of Cheesecake Factories where this happen
Harry was told to show up August 20th 1 p.m. at the Cheesecake Factory
That's where this was going to go down
Kept asking about are you going to be there
Ecoroute who's going to watch
Where do I go
Switch shows up in for the Cheesecake Factory with his truck with the big K to build on the back
And sure enough there were people there
Including an dress up as Hillary Clinton
We were given a script
What were what were your lines do you remember
Let me see
Well we were supposed to talk about
My computer tablet in my emails
And then I was supposed to
I'm telling jokes
She was there with her very good friend Greg who she convinced to be the Bill Clinton impersonator
I sure needed the money at the time so what did you do to get
Prepare to play the part of
A Bill Clinton
I had to shave
Do you normally have like a mustache
I shave once back in the 70s
Then I shaved again
With when Jerry Garcia died
Am I saved
I had to play Bill Clinton
What you should do shaped like three times in your life that's bad hit how did it feel to
Be in this cage
Along with Annan be like this
Strange
Actor in this
Moving
Play
It was hot
And I was in bed and it was August and it's Florida so it's like 94°
And
All I could think of was
I wanted
Girl beer
I just wanted to be over so you didn't have very much fun
No just work
It was Annie having fun
Yeah I guess she was
Bill was supposed to
Find a lady in that would be in at like standing around like a news lady and try to flirt with her
Hey pal don't look now but I
Annie's bait shop
Cage for a while
What you see in the Facebook live video is a few dozen people in the parking lot outside the cheesecakes
And they're just standing around the cage with Annie inside of it
Who is pretending to be sad about being lost
Issues with a grudge exasperated
We spent the day doing that
Took a lot of pictures had a good time
Pictures of course ended up on social media and according to Harry
24-hour sale
You're aware that
Much of the much of the mainstream media at the moment is reporting that that this was a Russian
Like how did it make you feel that there's now that possibility that you were
I'm came here to talk to me about it
Okay when did when did you speak with the FBI
Yeah how long ago
Last week what did they ask you
Well
They discussed with me
Pretty much what you were discussing with me buddy
Not it's not in as much depth as you did
This video guy was kind of experience
Cute cuter than Christian Bale 2
Reach out to the FBI with no comment or are you concerned that you may be part like
Like that you may have been
Used as a puppet by people
In St Petersburg
No I wasn't using the puppet
But would you have done it had they not reached out to you in the first place
Well
I wanted to help Trump
But this is a situation where our own federal government is
Is telling you
That that this is
Essentially becoming an interstate console
Flexware Russia
Intentionally
Manipulated
People
Do you find that troubling
Stupid Howard Miller
And me and his wife
Veterans
No we're not that
Stupid you know this whole thing is being investigated and I'm like known as the unwitting
Real American
So she's referring to a word that Rod Rosenstein using a press conference meme now these indictments
Teacup puppies Russian
To communicate with unwitting
American
Quitting
I'm the one whose idea was to put the date of Benghazi
Prison games
And I'm not a Russian I'm an American and I decided that I didn't want to vote for Hillary
Yeah and I guess I'm not saying you're stupid at all like I think what's interesting here is
I don't think
You or Greg North or Harry Miller
I think that you all had really good intentions that you believed in this man and you wanted to go out and support him
And I think what gets complicated
Here now is we find out that
Even though you supported this
And maybe in the end of the day you you helped him win
That there was some nefarious
Work going on behind the scenes that led you to do this and I
I would have complicated feelings
I'm just trying to figure out if you do or don't
No because I do not believe that it be the case for the people that I dealt with I do not think it was a Russian movement
I've done article up here in front of me
And in the indictment
Are they refer to Matt skiba who is I think that the Hollywood man that you talk to
They refer to him as
From Texas and he went to UCLA
He was going home
Yeah I'm I'm looking at a document right here saying that Matt skiba isn't invented person
Well maybe that's invented name
He was a young guy ass
He sounds like what he said he was maybe he did give me a
Bogus name
But you don't believe he was working for Russia
Why don't know because if he lied about his name who knows
That's what he told me
He said his name was Matt
The email that I had
Was this
Josh
Josh Milton
I'll let you know that
Josh Milton they're saying is also a made-up
Nobody
On my TV
I'm not usually wrong
Puckett O'Leary's I really do
Because obviously what happened from what I gathered from this
If I was the one dealing with the Russians
How about that one
What do what do you think about that how does it make you feel
I don't think I'm stupid but I don't see a real motive here and how this could change
Heather claiming it disrupted the
The election
I don't know how that could be by really again had they not contact me I never my whole life
Been up there
Harry says he understands that book invisible men the other end of the phone seem to want but you create a visual stunts
One that they can take on the road they wanted me to go to New York
They didn't want you to bring the key to New York
And the whole thing to him was it just didn't matter if it were Russians or not
But the answering Craig
The guy who played Bill Clinton
He thinks about the whole thing very differently
And I known
That I was working for
Directions
I would have asked for a lot more money
But
I have never felt good
About the same because
I might have had a little bit
Of influence
Donald Trump
Being elected
And I think that was a mistake for America
And he doesn't feel like
But I do
Cities is the feeling almost assertive guilt
I'm not I don't feel guilty
I was being paid to do a job and I did
Goblins at the job
To the best of my ability
And people told me that I did the job well
How does it feel to know that you were sort of used
Nobody likes to be used
Irritating to me feels like a bit of a mild word
For how I might feel
Well
I don't know I'm thinking that this might be played on the radio so I can't really use the words that I would like to
UPS to ship
When it sounds like you and Ann have very different interpretations of whether Russia was involved or not
The second between your relation
You know I love money yes I do
Are very mature
Do we see eye-to-eye on everything
Now we don't
We all do crazy things
For love you can dress up like Bill Clinton shave our beards and
Go in a prison cage so I don't crave your attention that but
I feel
Astute
As an American
Not
By the Russians
But
Bye
My phone miracle
The Russians
Can't come here and vote
We voted the way we wanted to vote
I don't know if I'm making me something that sounds a little bit like you're saying that
What's frustrating is the fact
That
It wasn't actually Russia that
Started the fire
Fire they were just blowing on it and maybe making it a little worse
But the truly disheartening thing is
Accident
The fire was ignited here
Without
Yeah that's exactly what I'm trying to say
That mean
I can't
Talk about this anymore
Call back sometime
Just call back sometime
I got something to say about everything I'm old man
Black ragdoll cat thank you very much thank you by now
This piece was produced by Simon Adler and Anna McEwan
We had
Reporting assistance Rebecca Bressler and Charles Maines
Very special thanks to Katie Michelle and Laura isensee
And of course to Yanni
Thank you guys for listening
Mali Music from Phoenix Arizona
Radiolab was created by Jad appenrod
And is produced by Soren wheeler
Dylan Keith Sr director of sound design
Maria Meda sarkodie is our managing director
Our staff includes Simon Adler Becca Bressler Rachel Cusick
David Gable
Bethel Hoppity
Tracy hunt
Matt kielty Robert krulwich
Annie McEwen
Latif Nasser Melissa O'Donnell
Ariane wack
Pat Walters
And Molly Webster with help from Amanda around chick
Shima Olie
Nice views
Jay Carlo Niagara frattali and Phoebe
Is Michelle Harris