Are you awake
Listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
And NPR
Robert krulwich
This is Radiolab about the
The crazy Power of Words in particular 60 words
Is
It has
You can say defined America for the last 12 years
And
In a place to start
Is it difficult
This just saying you were looking at
Obviously a very
Disturbing life
September 11th 2001 8:46 a.m.
Has crashed into the World Trade Center we don't know anything more than that we don't
This is the day that anyone who is old enough to remember desert
Remember where we were
Who we were with
And
Course
We can remember how we felt
It is the worst attack ever on American soil
But
If you really want understand the world we live in now
You got a jump ahead one day to September 12th to a corner office in the white house where there's a lawyer sitting
Computer try to figure out how are we going to declare war
And one of the things that everybody realizes after sort of an initial discussion is yes we'd like to do
Declare war but we have no idea upon whom we should declare war that is Gregory Johnson the Michael Hastings now
National Security reporting fellow at BuzzFeed the reason this lawyer by the name of Timothy flan
The reason Flanagan is sitting at a computer in an office is because been President George Bush had to do something he had to
You didn't want to act alone you wanted Congressional approval right I mean technically in an emergency
Can defend the country is the commander-in-chief after all he doesn't have to go to Congress and say hey do I have author
Relation to use for an emergency that's been with us by the way senior fellow in governance studies at the Brookings
Magician but President Bush needed Congress on his side he felt it was important that we Project Unity
We're all standing together as one and second if this was an act of war the power to declare war in the car
Constitution is given to Congress not the executive when Congress declares war
Suddenly the president has a very clear and
Powerful mandate
Now the declaration of war is kind of a dead instrument of international law II mean nobody's declared war
Since World War II
But the modern incarnation of the declaration of war
Is
The authorization to use for
The authorization to use
Force What's called the authorization for the use of military force for as it's commonly refer to the AU
NF
Right so
Are lawyer in the White House
Flanagan
He's given a task
Go right in aumf to Congress contended
He really has no idea so he goes back to the last time
That the US did this
Last time Congress passed one of these things he does it quick
Sort of search on his computer
Find it 1991 Iraq
The Gulf War
Flanigan grabs attack
And then he copies that into a Word document
And that becomes his template he make some Cuts he makes
Some changes he delete some word men
He hit send
Are war on Terra adjustable
Reset emotions bewildering series of events are us drone strike in linked to Al-Qaeda
Madness that is basically the world we live in
15 members of a wedding reception who killed wife
If you like me even sadistic treatment feel like me and you find yourself flipping through the channels see the news
Ignoring it then every so often thinking
Terrorism Targets in Africa from Libya now the u.s. Air Force drone strike in southern Somalia
How are we doing this in all these different places
100 prisoners are on a hunger strike
Thank you for so long is it okay to do that
Witches who signed off on this you know
And it turns out
We all did because it was in that document
This is the legal foundation for everything that the US has done everything from Guantanamo Bay
Two drone strikes to secret rendition
To seal rate it's all been hung off the 60 words
And that's the crazy
Buy the body of the stock
The part that really matters
And the reason that when I was reading Gregory's reporting on this house
Like what
Is it it all goes back
2 1
Single sentence
60 words one cent
Can you read it
Absolutely
That the president is authorized to use all necessary and appropriate Force
Against those Nations
Organization
Or person
He determines planned
Authorized
Committed
Or aided the terrorist attacks
That occurred on September 11th
Or Harbor
Such organizations
Or person
In order to prevent
Any future ask
Of international terrorism
Against the United States
By such Nations
Organization
Or persons
60 words
Today a collaboration with BuzzFeed Adam with reporter Gregory johnsen
We're going to try to
Code those words
And ask where do those words
And how
Did they come to mean what they mean
It's not what you think
And how did they end up
Leading us into what is arguably the longest war in American history
And nobody saw it coming actually no but that's the weirdest part
Nobody - 1
Let's start
Linda Vista Barbara Lee
Write Berkeley is a congresswoman from right around Berkeley
California
Hello hello hello hi it's Barbara
And she is someone who has been in many ways a lifelong Act
Going all the way back to when she was 15 and High School
San Fernando Valley
Cuz I wanted to be a cheerleader
But you know since the early 60s
Have certain criteria like
At least weather was stated or not
Blond and blue eyes
For you I would figure and I was really hard so I went to the n-double-acp
She got them to pressure the
The school to change the rules
And she became the first black cheerleader
I'm at at her High School yeah yeah that's just my way of introduction fast forward many years to become a congresswoman
Gets elected to a second term
And on that day
There is smoke pouring out of the Pentagon she was at the capital no one knew where to go so the police officers just said run
Run run go go go attacking our country so I ran out of the capital of Pennsylvania
The Avenue
I remember looking back
It's a lot of smoke
Which was you know the Pentagon so clearly
The country is under attack clearly
People have died clearly
We've got a deal with whoever did this
Whatever it takes
Fast forward 2 days September 13th barbely's back of the capitol
To meet with
Her Democratic colleagues to review that document
The Flanagan Center
The mood in the room was very somber and very angry
Other thing we have to keep in mind when we're talking about this
Is all of this was done within 72 hours
After the worst terrorist
Attack
In United States history
And very
Confused
What would be the appropriate response
So is she and her colleagues read those 60 were
There was a lot of debate going on back and forth oh yeah
Oh yes from everyone
Because it's actually wasn't the first rap
Flanagan had sent one over the night
Before September 12th 2001 and that one was something that almost no one agreed
According to Gregory that early draft
Had a few extra lines in it
One gave the
The president
The power
To preempt
Any future acts of aggression against the United
Barbara Lee and her colleagues knew that look
So many things can be packed into this word
Aggression
That if we sign on today
That if we give the president
Does power
The president may never have to come back to Congress ever again
And request authorization for military force
Because he can say that anything is aggression
And we're also giving him the power to preamp
To the kicked back to the White House Flanagan took out those
And now they have this new draft
That the president
Is authorized to use all net
Siri inappropriate
Just what you heard
It's the one Barbara read that
Hats off racist
Glycol necessary
What does that even mean
I said this is too broad let's not
Definitive is open-ended and I she was speaking this is taking place in the basement of the Capitol building
She sees some of her Democratic colleagues start to nod
People we're not in people were not
Is everybody there knew the danger
You just have to go back 50 years
The Gulf of Tonkin
Gulf of Tonkin
Tonkin
Yes
To explain
My fellow American
At present
Commander in Chief
1964 LBJ announces that to American ships
Gulf of Tonkin off the coast of Vietnam were torpedoed by North Vietnamese boat people now
Now argue that one of these attacks never even happened
Nonetheless President Johnson won
Strike Back
So yes Congress
To pass a resolution
Which they did
Giving the power to quote
Take all necessary measures
To repel any armed attack
Against the forces of the United States
Inter prevent
Further aggression
Making it clear
That our government
Answer United
And its determination
To take all necessary measures
Import of freedom
10 in defense of Peace in Southeast Asia
Now it is the broad language of that.
Most people believe
It opened the door to the worst
Part of the Vietnam War
The Rangers and Marines took casualties mostly from Hitman sniper the thousands
Thousands of casualties atrocities
567 South Vietnamese civilians in March 1968
And in a television interview in 1969 when President Johnson was as to justify at all
I can't just blame him in August 1964
The new whatever maybe next
To the lessons of Gulf of Tonkin and Vietnam that was very much in the air
In that meeting on
September 13th
2001 several key leaders hope to avoid a repeat of the 1964 Tonkin Gulf resolution so is understanding
Barbara Lee stood up
Passage where colleagues she was worried about some of the slang
People are not a people were not
So there was a lot of uncertainty about what to do but
In the end those concerns were ultimately outweighed
Buy another
We've got to be unified with the present we can't show political division
Let's have the nation let's have Congress
Speaking with one voice
It was a time for Unity and borax
It's a walking out of that Democratic caucus
On the evening of September 13th Congressional leadership decided
The D60 words
This is the version there's no going back to the drawing board
And so
At 10:16 a.m. September 14th 2001
Session clerk will call the roll
Dashiell calls about
Mr. Alan's
There 98 Senators on the floor
Mister morning itch
All 98 event vote yay
So is asleep later in the day of the resolution we go to the house
Where Barbara Lee was
A representative
Dashiell XU Rush the vote
Do the Senate because the White House is called for a National Prayer meeting at the National Cathedral
For the victims of
That's supposed to start right at noon
And so right after the vote all the Senators
Pour out of the capital and get onto the buses I'm trying to get through the drizzle
There's actually raining that day
Know that moment
Barbara Lee
She hadn't decided how it is that she was going to vote I struggled with it for the previous two nights
Denver 12th and 13th
She stayed up late calling back to advisors
Friends in California we talk
Everyday
Including this guy this is Ron dellums
Alright serve for 27 years in the US House of Representatives Barber used to be his chief
Staff and when he resigned
She want his
Congressional seat you know she would say what what about this in
What do you think about that and we kind of talked through the
The emotional state of the country that we are feeling
Pain
Anger
We're shocked
Both Barbara and Ron were trained as psychiatric
Social worker
So they both knew
It when a person is feeling all of those things
Generally better to do nothing
Yes I called you one-on-one you don't
Make decisions when your morning
Afraid
On the other hand
I believe you know and unity to
I want to be unified with the president when the country is under attack
I understood he didn't tell me he didn't say which way I should vote but I did say two
Barber however you vote
I will always respect
You will always be friend
You will always be family
So that moment
With the memorial service about the
To start in a few hours to the houseboat
Barbara Lee was at the capital I was in the cloakroom and said she wasn't sure how she was going to vote she plan to skip the memorial
She wanted to stay she wanted to think and then
I don't know what it was
May have been the spirit moving me I don't know but at the very last minute she was drinking actually can of ginger ale at the
I think I'm going to go and I just ran out I probably was the last one on the bus I had the can of ginger ale in my hand and
Ran down the steps and got on the bus
She got to the cathedral the house buses arrived about
30 minutes or so before the opening
And so far for 30 minutes she's in the
Cathedral about halfway back listening to the Oregon
Thinking about
The families in those who were
There are people around her who are sort of whispering the pain and anguish
A few people who are crying
I said I got to pray over this
And she just wrestling with her boat
Her heart is say one thing this is too broad and her head is Saint Unity
How is it that you can be against the president
Does point
Speaking of the president eventually President Bush
Take the podium we are here in the
Middle hour of our grief
Just three days removed from these events
Americans
Do not yet have
The distance of History
But our responsibility to history
Is already clear
To answer these attacks
And rid the world of evil
And then as soon as President Bush
Steps down
Everyone in the congregation
Stands up and they they sing The Battle Hymn
Republic
Which is a very powerful
A very moving
Piece of music
But it's not the sort of thing that is typically sung at a memorial service since it's a very
Forward and almost aggressive sounding was the phrase terrible Swift
Sword
Yeah
Oh my God
It was
Not quite
What I expected in a memorial service
But
The second speaker
A reverend by the name of Nathan Baxter
Got up
He gave a reading from Jeremiah 31
Israel suffered
The excruciating pain on
Tragedy of militant aggression
And destruction here in that all over again takes me right back there and I remember
Korean drama
Lamenting and bitter weeping weeping
Rachel weeping for her children
Weeping
For her children
When he spoke
That's when two men
What is the Memorial
And then
He
He started
Pray for healing for grief-stricken hot
For the souls and sacred memory of those
Who have been love
And
He said something that really struck
Barbara Lee Divine wisdom
He said as we Act
We not become
Be evil
We deplore
That evil that we deplore
When he said that
Became very it was the sense of peace and calm came over me
And Barbara Lee says it was right then that you knew what you do
The clerk report the title house joint resolution 64 joint resolution to authorize the use
List of United States Army
Later that evening the house opens up at
Bait on the aumf
Speaker
Arise in support of this resolution which authorizes the president to use all Force necessary
Does aerating congressperson after congressperson speaker
Horizon supported this resolution tonight to fully endorse and authorise
The use of force
One after another
The doctor arrives in support of the authorization
16 in a row
Until Jalan from California is recognized for a minute and a half
We get to Barbara Lee
Mr. speaker members arrived today really with a very heavy heart
When did is filled with sorrow for the families and the loved ones who were killed and injured this week
Only the most foolish and the most cows without understand the grief
Are people and millions across the world
The I am agonized over this vote
Grips with it today
And I came to grips with opposing this resolution
During the very painful very beautiful memorial service
As a member of the clergy spoke eloquently said as we
The ACT let us not become the evil that we do
Deplore
Just after the boat Barbara Lee says she was
The cloakroom again
And she starts getting accosted by colleagues all of these friends are coming up to her and saying
You've got to go back you you cannot vote
Changing my boat one of them actually said
It hurt look you've done so much on HIV you've done so much on Aid
This boat is going to take you out
Think of the bigger picture
Are you saying you're dead
Giving president the authority to go to war we don't know what we're doing and you know the only Congress can declare war
Help me on this guy's the houseboat
Okay I was just now finished
That boat
And we see one
Novo during the final vote for the house was
We know what the Democrat we don't
Yet know who will figure that out
Barbara Lee was the only person
In the Senate
For the house
Cast a no vote
That must have been a very lonely moment to be perfectly honest with you I said some prayers
For my friend
This was the right thing to do
And you know votes like this
You have to be ready to pay the consequences over the next few weeks and months
Her office was inundated
Ladders
Barbara Lee your traitor and a disgrace to the office that you hold archive to Mills College
Weight on American society terrorist yourself
So much hatred
I don't know why you decided to place yourself into the camp of terrorist attacks came and they came and they came
Death run off to hell with you and Benedict Arnold one of these security day and night
Thanks for supporting the Taliban hey henway Barbara Lee
What are you
What do you believe in you go to Mills College in Oakland
What are there you will find 60000 letter
They're not all things
But most are
The congressman Lee says she never faltered
Because right after the boat
She's in her office my dad called me
Lieutenant Colonel retired in the army
He said I'm really proud of you you know my daddy been in Korea
And World War II
You see the way I see it
Cuz I really wasn't sure what he was saying cuz you know
I really wasn't sure
Chabad alright Daddy's proud of me
Now we should know that Barbara Lee is still a congresswoman
She did not pay the price
For that no vote
Whatever you think of of her VOC weather youth
I think it was the right thing to do with wrong thing to do what is interesting to me
Is that
As we're sitting here looking back on 12 years of war she was sitting there 12 years ago looking forward
And maybe she saw something about how this
Play out
But how these
These words say 60 words
Would start to grow
And expand
What's next
Gregory Johnson my name is Benjamin
Foundation and the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
More information about 12
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
About what we're calling tiny moments of brilliance
Basically I want to hear about those times when I did something
It just means you bring back and say whoa
Maybe it was the moment that I
I kid you been reading to 4 month started reading back
Do you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lesson
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of their musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed are ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the
Epic moments where
Kid does something super smart but doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story
T-shirt with us
Go to radiolab.org
Flash brilliance
Record short audio message
And that's radiolab.org / brilliant
Thank you so much
Hey I'm Jared I'm Robert krulwich should Radiolab in today 60 words
Is a collaboration with
BuzzFeed and
Reporter Gregory johnsen
Stories based
On a
An article that Gregory Road
About this
Simple word
It really defined American counter-terrorism
More than a decade
It's called the authorization for use of military force
That shorten to aumf and was passed by Congress
3 days after
September 11th
Here it is again read by Senator John
It says the president is authorized to use all necessary and appropriate Force against those Nations organization
Are persons he determines planned authorized committed or aided the terrorist attacks
That occurred on September 11 2001 or harbored such organizations or persons
In order to prevent any future acts of international terrorism against the United States
By such nations are organizations
He seems almost boards saying
Yeah he does
Can I just be honest with you for a second
I generally move to the world
With the
Assumption
Has been proven over and over again.
A truth that I don't know how the world
Like somehow I missed that day in school or something are you referring something in specific like a general sense
It somehow like Oz is out there behind the curtain pulling levers and I'm just
Always got me stuck on this
You know what motivates the show for me
I feel kind of stupid most
And these shows are a way to engage
Examine the word
Night
And when it comes to these matters of national
I really feel
Clueless
Until when I read Gregory's article
I felt like I understood something crucial
For the first time
By the way words actually operates in the world
Cuz like again this sentence this totally boring sentence this is the legal foundation for everything that the US has done
Everything from Guantanamo Bay to drone strikes
The secret Renditions
To seal rates it's all been hung off the 60 words one lawyer who is in the Bush Administration said look
This sentence is like a Christmas tree
All sorts of things have been hung off of
But how
Hotlix
Cuz you don't you read the thing and you don't
Seeing any mention of
Guantanamo Bay in those
60 words
Doesn't mention detention
It doesn't mention
Drone strikes it doesn't mention
Drone strikes
Against American citizen
That guy
Some of the first books
Recalled to help
What's the code this that's
That's John Bellinger I served as the legal advisor for the Nationals
Security Council from 2001 to 2005 and as the legal advisor for
The Department of State
2005 to 2009
You can't do any speed dating with an E with a credential like that cuz
The date will be over that's my congressional testimony voice
Attention isn't anywhere in the sockets how do you read detention from the sick
The argument with which I am
Purple as a legal matter
Is this he says if you go eight words into those 60 words and you get to the phrase all necessary and appropriate
Appropriate Force
Cesarean
Does resolve what is force
What does that mean
What are you out if I punch you in the face that's amusing for it that's one kind of morning use forced
To kill people but a lesser use of force is to detain them
Detention is simply lesser in
Excluded
IND use-of-force
It comes naturally in a military operation
It's like a subset
So if you're authorized to use Force to kill people you are also by default authorized to use Force
To detain them
I sent sheet to knock them out of the battle in other ways than that that forces both
Necessary
And it's
And the courts have upheld that
That one Workforce
That is how you justifying
Guantanamo Bay controversy surrounding Guantanamo Bay
Continue
The authorization to use military force act has
I've been the legal basis for the Detention of thousands of individuals
Numb about being charged words detention or never mentioned
Because that's attention if it gets even trickier if you go just a few words
Past illness is there any pro
GeForce
Do you get to the mention of the enemy who the force is supposed to be
And it seems to be
Very limited language
Give me maybe we can shoot everybody
Body or anybody know only the people who planned authorized committed or aided the Terrace
Attacks
It occurred on September 11th 2001 or Harbor touchdowns much more
Which is why a lot of congressmen and women voted for it
Joe Biden
On the day of the vote September 14th 2001
He says
Look people don't freak out about this language
Relates to the incident
And has broad Authority related incident
It does not relate to all terrorism every place cuz it just talking about Al-Qaeda who did this and the Taliban who have
Harbor Freight
Nope
Not necessarily
Gregory Johnson against overtime what happened is there's been this other sort of
Catch-all category
That has been read into b60 word even though it appears nowhere in these 60 words
In a catch-all category is associated Force
Associative
Yeah what we've been calling me 61st and 62nd
If you define the enemy as Al-Qaeda the Taliban and Associated forces
It's a whole different ball game
So you read those those all those words that did not include the phrase Associated forces is nowhere in the
So where does
So then why could people cite something it isn't in the back during mysteries of a bit
So the earliest example that we could
Find
Of those two words is in a 2004 Memo from
Deputy secretary of defense Paul wolfowitz
It defines of Mao Qaeda Taliban and Associated forces
The truth is
It may have just been there from the beginning
Play me is according to Ben Willis
From The Brookings institution there is a concept
In the laws of war
Called co-belligerent
It's the idea that if you're at war with personae
And person B is on person is side in the war
You're also legally at war with
Person B
Makes perfect sense if you think of it traditional War
We're at war with Germany
Italy joins our side so by default we're at war with Italy to write
So just transpose out here if we're
War with this group called
Al-Qaeda and a certain set of groups
There aren't them
Join the war on Al-Qaeda side when you are legally at war with them
You don't think about that too hard it is
Crystal clear
But then the question that has arisen over time
Is how broad
Do you make that
That Circle
Is the problem
BECU
We're not talking about nation-states any
Are we talking about group
So okay
How close does the linked to Al-Qaeda and the people who carried out September 11th have to be
So if you have someone who's connected to someone who's connected to someone who's connected to someone who is connected to September 11th is that a no
Or is it only three legs
Or can you be an associate in Minnesota
Now we can't exactly know how broadly the Obama and Bush administrations have
Define those words
We'll talk about why in a second
But you just have to look at the news
You could see that
Like we started with a war that was in Afghanistan and then it spread to
Gelato different places
Pakistan
Libya
Somalia Yemen yeah and there's a lot of debate in a lot of discussion
About like is this legal
Does this have anything to do with September 11th anymore cuz now the group in Yemen al-Qaeda in the Arabian put in
And so which is a group that that was first formed in 2009 they have their own hierarchy and their own structure and it's not
Not clear
How
In what
Fashion
They take orders
From
Either Osama Bin Laden why he was still alive or now I have another one
So does this make them and Associated force or does it make them part of al-Qaeda
Dancer leaps on
2011 MKT.
On your calendar December 30th 2011 seem to be yes when the US assassinated two members of the group
This is not confirmed yet but they could very well have been a US predator drone strike that is a US government
Attack to put all this in contact between 2002 and 2014 according to some estimates
They're going about 65 drone strikes in Yemen
Killing about 400 people
So much hinges on how you define those
So much is in the definition
I asked the Pentagon I said
Who
What are the list of associated forces to Al-Qaeda yes the u.s. is a war that's clear
What about the other
Al-shabaab
Buchheit in Iraq
Al-Qaeda in the Islamic maghreb armed Islamic group
Who are these groups who is the US at war with
In the Pentagon emailed me back and they said
The list is classified and offer
For public release
Wait so we
Who we are at war with any don't know
I see you saying
When you approached the Pentagon they said that they will not tell you the names of the people were at War again
Well maybe they shouldn't
Don't you want to know as a citizen of America
Fighting on the other hand do I want to know as
If the United States has determined
That I am dangerous to it
If it announced
Then that would give me a certain amount of
Notice
2D is this advantageous
United States
It could also though
Act as a disincentive for you to
To take action
Baby
But maybe not
Maybe they will just
Quieter
More dangerous
Mystery there might be reasons for
They have not wanted to provide a public list because they this is John Bellinger again
The group's move all the time and so if you say well
These were associated groups while then
Certain people just move
Group beta Group B
And they also want to leave these different groups guess
But it still raises democratic
Insurance if the America
Can people don't really know
Who the execu
Git branch believes is covered by the aumf
In the Democracy in a representative democracy
That has to be weighed out should the citizens of the United States
No
Who it is that the United States is targeting for Death Around the World who it is that the United States
Technically at war with
Should War be a decision that the citizens of a democracy of a representative democracy have a say it
Presented rameses you just said so I'm assuming that
Chairman of the house intelligence committee knows every item on
I'm not so sure morning everybody today to
Receive testimonial
The law of armed
Conflict one of the more interesting Senate hearings took place in early 2013
The 2001 authorization for the use of military force
The aumf
Who is the Senate armed services
Dyskinetic
Senator Carl Levin of Michigan chairman of the committee
Senator McCain is on the committee like you're welcome or whipped
Gregory says the Senators called a couple of Defense
Department official
Answer question members committee thank
The opportunity to testify
About the legal framework for the US military operations
Defend our nation
Cuz they want to know like
Now that we're 12 years into this war how are you using the stock
Does need to be changed
So the Department of Defense officials in there were four of them
Came and said look I believe that existing
Authorities are adequate
Disarm comfort
Don't revisit this sentence don't repeal it
This sentence is sufficiently gives us all the power that we need
And Associated forces are laying out their case
They say those two words
Associated Force
Associated forces over and over and Associated force and Associated forces
Shaded forces and their Associated forces Associated for an Associated forces instead of just nodding along a lot of the time
Others were like what
Dylan. I've only been here five months but this is the most astounding and most astoundingly disturbing hearing
That I've been to since I've been here you guys have essentially Rewritten the Constitution here today
That's Angus King independent senator from Maine and you keep using the term Associated forces you use it 13
18 * in your statement that is not in the aumf
And you said it one point it suits us very well I assume it does suit you very well because you're reading it
To cover everything
Who won the most striking moments of this hearing is when the head of the committee
Senator Carl Levin turns one of the dod officials and asks
Is there a list
Now there's an existing list
Two groups that are affiliated with Al-Qaeda
Senator I'm not sure there's a list per say I am very familiar with the organizations that we do consider
Right now are affiliated and I could provide you that with yes or we can do
When you add or subtract names from that list
Could you let us know
We can do that as well mister
IQ
Let me see if I understand what you just said at a Committee hearing
Say US senator asks specifically so who's on the list of people were allowed to
That suggested that the Senate armed services committee who had oversight
Really had no idea
Today's weather like all right if we don't have any idea who were at war with in the Senate armed services committee doesn't seem to have
And who does
One of the things that became clear to me as I was reporting on this
Story
Was that many of the people who are making these decisions
I never been elected by anyone
The any position
And they were the ones who were making the decision not the elected representatives and so who are they
I guess so yeah
So we rooting around for a while looking for an answer to that question until we found this guy
Daniel kleiman he's a journalist and I've covered National Security and counterterrorism for many years and
Based on hundreds of confidential interviews that became his book Killer capture
He was able to paint a picture for us
Who makes these decisions and how
He told us about these meetings you say it's the s
TV s meanings what are they who's in the room how did the events unfold these are they they call them
Civics meetings in the vernacular of
If your ochracea stands for secure
Video teleconference
Meetings described them as a sort of a massive top secret Google Hangout
Chat with literally hundreds of people
From throughout the National Security bureaucracy
Login to decide who's on the list
You should live
You should die
You should literally hundreds literally hundreds of people now many of them are backbenchers they're not participate
Heading out in the call but they're taking notes
Before they get together in this meeting many the folks at this meeting he says they're giving a little packets of information on each Target they called
Baseball
Sister look like it you got a picture and stats
Like Yogi Berra on one side and then you got his batting average in his hometown on the back of the terrorist equivalent of
Bald actor who is this person
Where does he Rank and what kinds of operations has he been involved in in the past
Eventually a general will come on the screen and say here's our Target objective Akron for some reason he says they was
For the targets by the name of American cities
Subjective Toledo
General might say Target is an overhead an opportunity to kill this person can we legally do it
In the fascinating thing although maybe it won't come as much
Surprises
People he's making this
Is Pitch 2
I got generals but
Lawyers
Are lawyers everywhere that is just a basic fact
Of Modern Warfare says John Bellinger
You know of lawyers on the ground with artillery units
Tank commander
Lawyers in Kevlar lures and helicopters are lawyers really almost behind every bomb
Just lawyers everywhere and that's a very good thing
That's Harold Koh he was at
The top lawyer at the state department
2009 to two
Because it means that we're not just
Shooting why people willy-nilly or
Because we're angry at them right there
Considered careful decision
No Harold kokori the den clivens reporting was
NOC
Tibbetts meetings and he would often be the one to answer the generals questions
Can we legally killed
So we asked him
If lawyers are now the ones deciding
True we are at war with Who We Are
How do you do it
Unfortunately for us
I don't think I'm good
Just call their mother
Audible methods but I'm
He said he couldn't comment on any of
Classified
But
Coco is a
Creative lawyer 40th and Clive
People familiar with
The process code in particular had a
A fascinating way
Determining who is and is not an associate
Another which we are or aren't at war with
And it seems to be less
About the groups as a whole and more about
Individuals within the
For example
I see you already
That was an important issue for Co if you're going to Target a guy he has to be
A senior member
A group like Al-Qaeda
Yes be able to give orders and he has to be unique within the organization you couldn't simply under Harrell Costa Rica
Go after say a driver or a cook
Who was in al-Qaeda or even
Foot soldiers
Because they were fungible
Meaning they could be easily
Another criteria was
Whether they were externally Orion
Forco if they were just participants in a civil war you couldn't Target
But if they were targeting westerners
Or Western interests
Then yes
So if you take Dan kleinman's account
Criteria as representative
And we first have no way of verifying
If you take that as the norm then maybe there is
Strong wedding
But I interviewed
Numerous people who
Participated in these meeting
Shenzhen one of the things that
I heard over and over again
Was it there was this
This kind of
Inexorable
Momentum
Toward killing
And that
At the military people in these meetings
Could speak with a kind of a tone of Do or Die origin see if Act 2 of the people
Who I quote in my book
Used exactly the same metaphor
Describe
That sense of momentum that was very good
Ultra zest
It was like
Standing
Train track with a
Train hurtling towards Hemet
A hundred miles an hour
Then I guess like
Play the important question for me is like how often do they say no
Well you should be 99 * yes and one time now or 50
2 times yes in 50 times know how many Noah's Ark
Well look I'd say I did not come across
Many many examples but he did tell us
About this one is
This is a
Meeting between the top lawyer at
The defense department in a man named Jay Johnson
And the top lawyer at the state department
Open todoist and parallel Harold Koh
Anacortes dansources Harold Cohen J Johnson worth
We're faced with
Determining the Fate
Aveda
40 year old man
Roughly 4
What are you named scaife wolfed are robo
I think that's the right but it's
I'm not sure he's a member of these Smalley group al-shabaab
And Picante
World Cup Celebrations of 10-2 tragedy in the Central African nation of Uganda
A few months before this conversation is in 2010
Al-shabaab bombed a rugby club and a restaurant
At the same time in Uganda
Killing 74 people
Broken chairs
Smash table
And the sounds of pain
As Rescuers search for the living
And the dead
So that just happen
And according to Dan Kleinman at this moment
Intelligencer
There was a debate raging
Weather al-shabaab should
Or should not be considered an
At the time their leader had sworn allegiance to Osama bin Laden
But their agenda was primarily a local
Agenda
Player never struck out
Against the United States
Sore against American interests
In the region
So you got the top lawyer at the state department and the top floor
Pentagon facing off
That's the weather this fellow robo
Al Shabaab
Should live or die
How does this work if somebody just like this someone pound the table or yes this was this was a very
Heated meeting Jay Johnson argued vehemently that
Robo was covered under the aumf
He was after all a founding member of
Carolco
Vehemently disagreed
Harold code conclusion based on the evidence
Any intelligence
Did he saw
Was it Robo was not externally focused
In fact he belong to a faction of al-shabaab that was arguing against attacking
Did the United States and other Western entry
Still going to climb in these two men went back and forth and back and forth until eventually Harold Co
Is Drew a hard mode
Look if you do this you need to know that you will be doing it over the unambiguous
Objections
Of the state Department's legal
The unambiguous movie that's very strong language
Which coming from a lawyer
And the signal that is sent
Tattoo the White House
Housewives
You will be taking
Military action even though
The top layer of the state finance said that this would be
Illegal a
Okay so what happened did they decide not to they did not do it
Academic
It's it's
Live
Depends on which way the decision goes
11 mm
Will continue tomorrow
Jim Donaghy
You from Fort Worth Texas
Radiolab is supported in part by the National Science Foundation
And by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding
Science and technology in the modern world
More information about Sloane @www.
What's loan.org
Hey I'm Jared I'm right by Robert Goulet this is Radiolab
Show to a single sentence
One sentence
60 words that's all
It's the 2001 authorization to use military
Dayforce sign in salons
September 18th
Together with BuzzFeed
Reporter Gregory johnsen we have
We have manhandled diesel
Yeah we have dissected we have by size
Second trifecta
Did you quadrisect it to the aumf as it's called
Yes and you know we've looked at how that these two sentences
Define flask
12 years
Counter-terrorism now
How would Define our future
General thank you for being here today this is
So we were thinking about that Senate armed services
This Committee hearing we ended up calling someone who sat on the
Tim Kaine senator from Virginia
Who is there
Yeah that what's up
That was a very
Kind of hair-raising day
And Senator Kaine told us that one of the most hair-raising moments for him was when one of his fellow Senators Lindsey Graham
Fast one of the Department of Defense
Officials Gear graywood with May the war against radical Islam or Tara whatever
Description like to provide
Will go on after the second term of President Obama
Another words
How long do you think this particular War
As declared in the section is going to go on
Leonard my judgment this is going to go on for quite a while and yes beyond the Turks
Second term of
The president & Beyond this term of congress
Yes sir I think it's at least 10 to 20 years
It was chilly
Cuz like this is already the longest war in history United States Vietnam
And now a DOD official as saying add-on 10 or 20 years so I said
The administration's position that you tell me if somebody is born after 9/11
Let's imagine in 2030 they join a group that is just become associated with Al-Qaeda
Is it the administration's position that the aumf would would cover them in those organization and without hesitation
Can the administration Witnesses said yes as long as they become an Associated Force Under
That's a legal standard that was set out it it's not limited in time
Not limited in geography
Really traveling
But you know I'm also trouble by another thing and then you know the iconic and it's a New York picture of the
VJ Day kiss in Times Square
August 14th 1945
Did there oughta be a day where those who have served in war
That you declare that the war is over and then you celebrate them
You can ask sometimes by service
Family sucks
Is going to end yours ever come up
Yes yes
He told us it's something like one and three people in his state of Virginia are connected to the military
So he does get that question a lot
And the truth is
We all want to be
Need
Inside 7 days after that Senate armed services Committee hearing
President Obama
It is a great honor
Give a speech
To return
The National Defense University
We seem to say basically
It's time for war
Like all wars
Mustang
That's what history advises
That is why I intend to engage Congress about the existing authorization to use military force
Where are you I'm at
Best Lionel says that he would like to get rid of those 60 words
And in this war
Yeah but Common Sense tells you
That these are
Different kind of enemy not a state or government they just they make war
It a different way Senator McCain has a great wind you guys look where in Ancient Warfare where the war isn't going to end with the signing of a peace
History on the deck of the Destroyer that's not how it happens these days there's no clear start and ending and yet the president
He wants to end the war
Set timer
Every war has come to an end he sees himself
As a person who came in
To a country fighting two Wars and he brought them all to an end and I think he wants
To have done that but how how do you how do you do that
How do you end a war
When the vast amount of people
But you're calling the enemy
Haven't stopped fighting so
What he does
In the maze
And it's extremely clever
And by the way
It's really well lawyer
Is he announces a set of rules
Going forward for drone strikes strikes to punish individual we act against Harris
Propose a continuing
An eminent
Threat to the American people that he's only going to use drone strike
When there's an imminent threat
Consuela understood
Who understands
The fit in the Constitution and also in international law
President allowed to act unilaterally
In self-defense
When there is an imminent
Threat
Meeting a surgeon
And you can't feasibly capture that
Ben fears that what President Obama was doing there
Thereby stressing that word
An eminent
Threat to the American people
Is it he was laying a New Foundation
You saying when the aumf and I wanted to end
I do have another way of justifying
All these things
Maybe they wouldn't change
The drone strikes in the raids with
Continue as long as you have a capacious enough understanding of what the word imminent means
You might be able to continue a whole lot of this stuff
And then you don't have to go to Congress at all and you can say you've ended the war
War and the human rights groups will cheer for you and
We're going to mysterious we find that there are a whole lot of imminent threats for free
Thank you very much everybody God bless you
May God bless the United States of America
And in the context of what happened to the 60 words you do have to wonder
What's going to happen to a word like Eminem
And all the while according to been witness and pretty much everyone we spoke with
Haven't really answered the big questions when do we want to attack the enemy who is
The enemy and if we're going to be fighting them even when we're not technically at war with them and what's
The difference between War and Peace
And that's why this whole subject is so unsettling if you don't know
The common sense definition any more of when you're at War and when you're at peace then how do you
How do you write rules
Yeah this was an attempt to begin a war
And so it has the usual beginning quick okay you who are you
Are you out there where
You for how long till you surrender another not going to like
All the usual
A business of warfare is it doesn't apply in this case so they have nothing in the house what do we do
Just like one long improvisation
Huge thanks this hour to BuzzFeed and
To their reporter Gregory johnsen checkout Gregory's piece
Radiolab.org it's on BuzzFeed as well it's called 60 words and a war Without End The Onion
Untold story of the most dangerous
That
Title right there
Also thanks to the great deal and keep original music and Glencoe Chief or music from his album Adventureland
Oh and also thank you to Beth fertig and the WNYC archives for the 911 tape
This hour was produced by Kelsey Padgett
And Matthew kielty
Myself
I'm Jedi runtime Robert krulwich
We'll see you next time
Play the message
Press 2
Start of message
Border Collie
I'm about
To you
The text of your credit
Hi this is Dan Clyde
And I'm going to read the credits
As I've been at
Radiolab is produced
By WNYC
And distributed by NPR
Radiolab is produced by Jad abumrad
Our staff includes
Alan horn
Doran wheeler
Tim Howard Brenna Farrell Molly Webster
Melissa O'Donnell Dylan key Jamie York Lynn Levy Andy Mills and Kelsey Patchett
With help from Arianne wack
Matt kielty
Simon Adler
And Crystal Store
Special thanks to Bruce Kane
Liz Mac
Steve Kendall
Ben Smith
And carry on
And this message