Are you awake
Listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
Hey I'm Jared I'm Robert krulwich Radiolab today we're going to start off with a building
Not just any building but a building that is
Heavy
With secret
Yeah it's building we first really learned about got a picture of
From the Seoul
Katie Engelhart I'm a reporter of Vice news in London
And Katie like now all of us
Is
Obsessed
Devastatingly obsessed
With this place called hanslope Park
Central Park is this
Huge
Sprawling complex in buckinghamshire near us
Hong Kong Milton Keynes
Which
Isn't too far from London and I'm pretty sure Jamie York
Happened to be in London on vacation so we asked him we'll watch describe your tape recorder
Go down there
Check it out
It's a bit of a drive from London
About an hour and a half on the M1
And do you approach this
Assertive beautiful
Town with adorable little
Posh Cottages in
Little Pub
Not from around here I'm looking for Antelope Park
I mean it's your sort of typical you old a British
Village
Security lights
Metaphor minute drive past that you'll the town you go to
Fieldcrest Overhill and there it is
This massive massive building surrounded by razor
To the archives
Are held in a purpose-built building from the 90s archives by the way from the largest Empire
Evernote
It's like if you were creating a movie set
For like
Secretive government compound where they
Keep secret files
You would literally just make this
Jamie Parker
Quarter mile away
Walk up to the gate
Big
Electrified
Through the gate
Pasties traffic spikes
Just as he barely stepped inside
Are you going to call
Call
Activity
I got grabbed them taken to a guard house
It's a microphone
And then
They walk him
Are you going to escort me all the way back to my car
The entire quarter-mile back to his car
Now we've heard it said that the files in that building if they were ever released could we write to
200 years of history no idea if that's true we just don't know
The one story that has so far away
The refined kind of startling
We shall see that there's some stuff coming up days
Graphic and disturbing
So if you're listening with kids
You might want to see
Although if you're not listening with kids don't skip it
Okay
Asturias of Kenya
Kenya was always that scene is historian David Anderson and it kind of sepia-tinted hey
Many years ago can wife end of Adventure
Who found the country beautiful
The climate kind of soil for tile
Bougainvillea Sunshine smiling happy seven
David says in the 1910s 20s 30s the British public
Was obsessed with Ken yet books eventually television programs was one of the crown jewels of the Empire and so yeah
You had all of these Brits
Leaving Britain and going to Kenya
Start a new life and many many more settlers who floated to Kenya
Lower middle classes
You could have a much better salary
And a much better living standard in Kenya than they ever could back at home
They stayed in founded the young colony
Women make their homes
Whether children are born taught them grow strong and healthy
Now it probably goes without saying this new life for the British citizen came at the expense of the Kenyan I was already living
Two problems that were always encountered in Africa and in general is colonization is the issue of land in the issue of Labor
That's Harvard historian Caroline Elkins play a big role in our story
Joan Kennedy Champlin Problem by simply alienating it and giving it to the white farmers
But that becomes a labor problem how do you force
Africans
Till Labor cheaply
On plantations
Write like in this case of tea and coffee
Love the way you do it is you create what I call native Reserves
We had them here for for Native American
Tracy says that the native Kenyans were forced off their land into slums where they could barely eke out a living and so the only off
They had
What's the word for the white people
And that's how it went for four decades
Until
The Second World War
Ask the question has started 1939 suddenly.
Thousands of men Canyon Manor forced into war
Came in contact with ideas of Independence and they anticipated when they return
Turn the day is Big Bear in Europe day after that
They would have access to land that the conditions will be getting better but
Nope
They may find their condition is not only
Not gotten better it's gotten worse
And so after the war a few of these vets
From the largest ethnic group in Kenya
Call the kikuyu
They get together
And they decide to take an oath
No Odin is traditional amongst
The kikuyu
So for example men
A hundred years ago or more would take an oath pledging allegiance to their ethnic group as they went to war with somebody else
This case they take an oath
Pledging themselves to kick all Europeans out of the colony
Then the earthquake today that I pledge to take all Europeans out of the colony out of Kenya and if I don't met this earth kill me
I pledged to take up arms against the Europeans if I don't buy this house kill me
No question last thing that was said always was if I reveal the contents of this Earth
May the South killed
She said the first thing they did
Was attack the settlers livestock
Doing things like hamstring cattle hamstringing cattle
They started destroying property duro's started to involve things like eyeballs Ram scrotums intestine
Blood things that absolutely repulse the local European settlers and put Terror into them
Why do they end up calling themselves the mammal that is much debated
But nobody quite agreeing on on how it
How it came to pass but the mailman hours
Many tickets
Swahili derivative of sort of more more that they would there be no some say it has to do with you peeing
And I don't play this
Overhearing what was the malos
Whatever the case in 1952 the colonial government
Is there the British Army in Kenya
Declares state of emergency
And those pajama agents timeout
They asked why they start going after the loyalists
The Chinese have been helping settlers
Destination after the next
In the British terrified this is the night of the Long Knives
Flights coming into reality and it's only about to get worse
And that happens on the night of January 24th
1953 which was the murder of the rock family
The Rocks were these very young lovely couple
Rothrock was a farmer as Miraak with a doctor
Flaxseed minister to the local population
And they had a little boy named Michael
Who is six
Just not date a little boy that falling off
Is Tony and his
One of their trusted servants
Querida backup
The house
Later that night a group of Mal Mal crept out of the forest
Lord Rodger Desmond rock out of the house
Kill them
And then the whole gang including that same servant that helped the boy
A March into the house go up to the little boy's room
And they hacked him to death
And there's a
Very famous
Photo of the young boy dead
Absolutely buddy
Which is in every major newspaper
And almost overnight
Mal Mal become synonymous
With pure evil
And our mind in children's vine Mom hour
Bigger than life
Darkest dark people
That you ever saw
An excess of reporting this story one of our producers lot of Nasser told us
About how his mom
Grew up next door to Kenya in
What is now called Tanzania
And to her and her friends
The Mal Mal were like a monster to children
The Boogeyman
That was sort of a
All the time. My mother especially prefer to if
If you don't drink your milk or if you don't sleep
Mama Wichita
I like the mama will come and get you
And how scared were you
You know what
Just the word Momo
Would make us run troll under the bed
I'm old enough
To be one of the people who thought
There were
Yes Theory like weird
Self-organizing terrorist
Yes the most Beast you a horrible awful Savage movement that I had ever hit the face the British Empire
Okay so here's our we get to the part of the story that is in deep
Flux after the
Murder of the rock family
The settlers demanded
That the colonial government do something
And they did they pursued the male Fighters
Supposedly
Small band of Fighters into the forest
There were skirmishes
The last
Four years Story Goes the Mal Mal movement never quite gained
Traction
And ultimately the British quell the Rebellion they handled it
Now that's for how they handle
For the longest time
People would look back it was this
Giant
Blank Spot
No one quite knew what
Happened
And here's why
Cody David Anderson
By the time the British finally decide to leave
By that time Kenya is around the 20th
Different Colony that Britain will leave
So it's about halfway down the list
So there's already in place
A protest
At the stadium the articles of Independence
The formal stage of powers they set off fireworks and then
The Ritz roll out of the woods daytrana smooth
And colorful and happy
Exit
And at some point in that well-worn exit process either right before the exit right afterwards there was
David calls it the weeding of document
I mean the British government
Conducted
Very very sophisticated Purge operations and all of its former colonies
Katie Engelhart again she says it everywhere you look Uganda Palestine Rhodesia Zanzibar Nigeria Jordan Malaya Hong Kong
Their stories of
Paper is being
Kind of tightly packed into boxes and drops it
See a lot of papers were burned as a joke
In Hmong engine historians
On the day that India treat its independence
When the celebrations were taking place in Delhi
You could hardly see what's going on on the podium
Does the wattage of smok playing across from the bone fires are burning.
All of which is to say that it was snow soon for 30 years that that Blank Spot
Aphmau emergency with just a blank in the story of the evil now or just continue
Because there were no documents to say otherwise
Then
We get to Caroline Elkins
How did you like a Once Upon a Time you are a curious
Young
Grad student or something
We'd have to go back further you know I'm dating myself at age 45 but the I have to go back to my aunt
Undergraduate years
Chucky 1990
I was at Princeton and when we work me that you do senior thesis there in Princeton was ahead of its time and
I got lots of funding and I went off to London and in Kenya
How old are you when you're taking a ship
So Carolina is working in Nairobi
And I'm doing research at the time I seen your pieces was looking at the kikuyu which is the largest ethnic group in Kenya
And
I was looking primarily at the shifting roles of women and in the ways in which they were impacted by Kanye West
So Carolina would wake up every morning and would walk
To this Old Colonial building right in Nairobi City Center call the National Archives
Louder
Dusty it's
You know sometimes you have to jump under the desk for several hours cuz there's a shootout at
Cross the street
Really
Yeah that was quite a Saturday
Long story short so one day she was at The Archives flipping through some files when I came across some fire
On
Detention camp
Kamichi detection kit
Committee
Kam adamary ITI
I just outside Nairobi
And
I said gosh you know
I know nothing about this
Sochi
Calls over the archives
Guy named Evenson
You said yeah let me take a look and then bring me some other files also related to akimichi
Bureaucratic files these Pages were filled with the with details and numbers of prisoners a lot of them
Were women well over a thousand because I would mention a hundred of this and
Honor to that
And at that point I saw it
What's going on
So short time later she gets back to Princeton and being the Goodwill undergraduate history major that I was I
I searched high and low about detention camps in Kenya
Nothing much ya no mention of
The center
There's nobody who done the systematic study of
And
That's what I was at
So without anything else to go on Caroline just started driving up country
The middle of nowhere Kenya
All these tiny little villages
It's in the central Province if you wanted to find middle of nowhere on the map I was in it I would just show up at somebody's little Sean Barr Farm one day
Garlic bread
Affordable Dental Care
Next thing you know I'm conducting an interview while working. How many
These are tapes recorded on a few of her trips she would speak to people through her research assistant Terry wairimu
1 4 hours then one interview be guess the next every time you finish an interview you say you don't you have somebody else who I could talk to her
Matteo yeah I've got my friend list three Bridges up in Four Hills over
Text you talk to that person
And then person they refer to
In person they refer to
This is what you did for like 5 years I want interviewed several hundred.
And what exactly are they telling you
Stories
If you can imagine
But the stories were
What does Dory have began to unravel
This is Darlene calling from Kampala Uganda
Radiolab is supported in part by the National Science Foundation
And by the Alfred
P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and
Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloan
Www.
. org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help this summer I'm hosting a show
And I request for those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teacher
We're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments childhood brilliance
Did something
It just means you lean back and say whoa how did they do that
Maybe it was the moment that our kids you've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons and you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed they're ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the
Epic moments where
A kid does something super smart but doesn't have anything to do with the test
If you have a story please share it with us
Go to radiolab.org brilliance
Record a short audio message
Again that's radiolab.org / brilliance
Thank you so much
Hey I'm Jared I'm run I'm rubber
Krobus Radiolab before we get to the stories that Caroline was referring to
We should say that as we were
Reporting the story we really kind of fell in deep
To the point where Jamie York
Put Oregon to London to get hassled by those guards at Hansel Park
He then decided to spend part of his vacation
In Kenya
Basically following in Caroline Elkins footsteps
Yes
And that's when he stumbled into something kind of surprising
So I got picked up early one morning in Nairobi
And driven about three hours into the countryside
And okay after what felt like
5 right turns 37 last we finally wind up in this completely replace it really
Just feel like the middle of nowhere
It's like a little village or something little cluster of houses in Rolling Hills in a county called me area
Got my stuff out of the car
Solitary
Yeah it arranged the trip
I am 41 years old
Same Terry who translated for Carolyn Elkins many years
Anyhow Crestview kids
And
Terry walks me to this little clay hut
There's a table in the center of the room there's a handful plastic chairs around it and eventually
People start showing up
Women
Hey
9 women
Who are all in their late eighties early nineties
Introductions
Honestly I'm a little bit disappointed because timeout
I thought
Wechat
Men
Spiders
I think these women I thought
Most of the men have died of old age so you thought you were going to meet anybody
Exactly
Curious
For myself
But I thought okay I'll
I just asked
How many of you identified is Malmo
Activity about to get with you
Instantaneously room put their hand up
All my people
Yeah
And then started to sort of chuckle
Because it's obvious you are supporting mom
They were like of course we were supporting the mama we were the mama
Like that
That was everybody
So interesting so it wasn't just like a small band of militants
It wasn't a small band of militants amongst the kikuyu it was
Almost everyone
This is one of the first things that caught Caroline Elkins attention made her really question that official narrative
Cuz when she was doing interviews 15 years ago
She said everyone she spoke to everyone
To a person
And we're talking hundreds of interviews
Started with I took the oath
On such and such a date
Very interesting
Seemed to her what you had here was not
A small Insurrection this was a mass move
And she would discover the British response to it
Was also massive
Shortly after the murder of the Rock Family the white settlers marched
Demand that the colonial government do something
Until what happened
Speak into the village Bazaar going to Villages across Kenya they rounded everybody up know each other
Slaughter cattle slaughter their goats burned down their Homestead
And put them into these
Prison Village
800 barbed wire Villages throughout
Central Province Kenya
The Village was like a concentration camp
The thing the thing to grasp. This is very carefully designed
I'm very
Practical
David said there was a very carefully planned system
Work the barbed wire Villages were primarily for women and children
Men were usually sent to these detention camps are true based
Prison
The logic of those camps
Was actually thought up by a group of British academics
Who met in 1953
Turn emergency meeting to discuss the quote mouth problem and they decided at that meeting
Clearly
The real reason the Mau Mau Rebellion was it that way
Captured by some kind of mental illness
Had nothing to do with the fact their land has been taken away from them know it was said they were temporarily crazy and the committee decided at
Must have something to do
With those
Host Machine by the British as a primitive way
Capturing a kikuyu mine
I'm making the person unreasonable and insensitive
The only way they all could you get rid of the oath
Was to convert the person back to sanity
Part of that involved a confession of what
I done
Once confessions were made
It would then be rewarded
Buy a better prison regime
Baby movement around the compound
Given privileges
Given better food
You moved along the system too cold for pipeline you would along the pipeline Until You released
But you first have to confess
To confess
This is get to walk hungari
Freedom fighter
I joined to the MoMA Freedom struggle
When I was 17 years of age
Quickly became an organizer
Recruiter
And therefore Target
They had to
Search for men
And they caught me
They put me into a detention camp
They want us to say loudly
And that wish for 6
The Momo struggle
Littlefield
Attack one man tell the story of how in one of the barbwire villages
Mo McRae
Every once in awhile would come to the edge of the forest
Just outside the villages fence
These were the fighters
Hadn't been captured yet they'd come right
The edge of the camp
Where a lot of the children
Would be fine
And go there
No grown-ups that states you don't understand anything about what was happening that country
The people in the village used to use the children
To take messages to the people in the for the fighters in the forest
Better day pass
Food and information to the fighters in a way kept things going
The point is Zachary David the inside the camps
Massive Resistance
It so many cases the British colonial soldiers
With double down
Warning the following is
Pretty graphic
Does BBC documentary called White
It has
Tons of these frightening Lee comments
Stories of abuse
From detainees
He told me I'm naked
Tidebuy speak to The Buzz
He was brutally beaten on the testicles with a stick
One of them is a man giving a tour of the
The prison cell he was kept in
Then they said his eyes with hot coals
They kept him that the 8 days
This another story of the Three Men Who were made
To strip naked
What element was made to put his head into a bucket of water
With a woman
Men the white officer held one of the prisoners legs a lot
Yamuna show
And another God brought some sand
Steak
Alternative putting in sand and water
Will the wild pushing the mixture in with a stick
FedEx still gives me nightmares to this day
Because that was something that should never be done to a human being with
And that.
Of course if violence
It lasted throughout the 1950s
I'm on my way back.
Listen there's nothing to excuse this kind of terrorism thought the kenning campaign was a sledgehammer
Hammer used to crack a note
There been a lot of different estimates to try to pin down the scale
Of the British campaign
They range from 160
Thousand people killed named torture detain
Too much much higher numbers Carolina consider own calculation
And according to her all the time it was done nearly the entire kikuyu population of a million
1/2 people
Retained
Tortured
Murdered
Systematized Force
Labor
And you have to look at scale
And if you are the balance sheet of this
How many Europeans died
Like why isn't this until everybody in the world now
In the event say of
The enslavement of the Hebrew people under the pharaoh
They were slaves in Egypt
The Pharaoh wouldn't let
Timeout
It becomes
The national story
Of the Hebrew people
In this situation
You have done working out of I believe is it
Kikuyu becoming the first
Why wouldn't I
He make this the national story
Well Kenyatta comes out of detention
And one of the first things he does
Is he denounces malmo
The same organization that accelerated Independence
She says the same movement scare the British
Scared him
He didn't want them suddenly organizing and taking his
Soap for
Decades
From 1948 until 2002 the ban on Mal Mal that have been put in place
By the British colonial government remained in place
Meaning it was illegal to even talk about it
But eventually in 2005 Caroline publishes her book
Imperial Reckoning concluded the hundreds of interviews
Picture of Justice systemic violence
The book was well-received which says
A lot of critics told her
Nice story
But
Now
This is an active fiction
Actor fiction
I made it up
But you had all these interviews
But one of them lines
Was that is all based upon oral test
Oral testimonies are usable
There is no story here
She said love that was
Blatant racism you know Africans makeup
Stories
But buried in there
Is sort of legitimate concern of memory is faulty we know that oral histories are notoriously unreliable
If you're going to rewrite entire history
You need to get Beyond personal anecdote
You need documents
Tequila straight improve-it Beyond.
As you mentioned that you found the documents
Didn't seem to exist
Nonetheless
Fast forward 2009
Caroline's Imperial Reckoning became the basis of a very large lawsuit
In June of 2009 5ml veterans representing over 5,000 Mouse
Flew to London
And filed a lawsuit against the British government the first time the British government had ever been sued by a former colonized population
Veterans want an apology
Some form of recompense for what happened are you at all nervous going into the court
I was not at all convinced that we're going to go anywhere but down that smart day he represented amount veterans in court
And the reason he was so sure that the case was going to go down in flames
Most same issue
You just didn't have the documents
All we had were stories
When exactly Rock Solid
Yeah that it was a nightmare
Old canyons in the late 70s 80s
Africans in my experience Van Dyke's extremely difficult
The people in that seventies night she's almost
And this is actually a huge problem because in the British system if you're going to bring forward an old
Old case
Like one that's more than 6 years old the key question to the judge is can you still get a fair trial the government
I can plausibly argue no
Too much time has passed
We really worried that the judge would say well look that count be a fair trial because
Actually these
Witness is a cell wall
So up and down just in Tim's that memory
It really that evidence is worth it right now
So to recap I wasn't really optimistic
But then
It's kind of a last-ditch effort
He contacted historian David Anderson
Tonight tonight to witness
Because David has written a book about African history that was chock-full of legal documents
And they approached me to ask
Whether that was material in the legal cases are dealt
That might
Be useful to
And that's what he told him something that
What ultimately lead
All of us back that scary building a secret he told them
For the past 20 years
He has had this hunch
Well so long before the my my
Trial came to court
I and my brother story ends
Believed
The documents being brought back from Kenya to Britain
David said in that same Nairobi archive where Caroline Elkins found the talking about the tension
Gosh you know what's going on in that same place somebody else who found another document that it also
This one is a simple packing slip listing of documents for transportation packing up and removed
Now it's for where those documents were moved to well
The ocean from 1997-98 99 like starving man with a single Pringle David kept.
I eventually bought documents from the national archives in Britain that confirmed the stuff from Kenya actually landed an error
Airport in Britain Independence
And then was able to find out who took them with Van they went in the car's registration number
Thought
That's in the trail went cold
Defile document request after document request that we get nowhere
Then
Something totally unexpected app
Do historians working on Southern Africa actually got access to Hounslow
They got inside
One of them was the former Colonial administrators Zoe
Networks and connections to get its way in any out
After work
He sent David Anderson a text message
Telling me the enhancement parking scene
Miles and miles of shelving
Of documents
From other colonies
Including Kenya
Was that a figure of speech miles or was that I think you meant it literally
Heat seat scene of vas a hanger is he
Describe it
With row upon row upon row of.
So when Martin de the lawyer contacted David Anderson and asked him can you help us with
Arcades David said
Yes I can do
I can actually give you any documents cuz I don't have any but I can outline for youth
The documents that I think
Might be out
The documents I believe
The bass, Whiting way
So he wrote a witness report for the judge summarizing everything he knew giving all the details I had
I didn't mention Huntsville Park I didn't say what I thought they were
I just said I knew they coming to Britain
I want to know what happened to the judge read that report and then basically asked the government
Do you have them or not look
If you can't answer this question
You'll be held in contempt of court
I will interpret this is you withheld information
I'm at basic means you lose the case
That decision was the turning point
Half a century on from Britain's withdrawal from Kenya documents detailing Yelich brutality employee
By the British colonial authorities
Have finally been released
I'm suddenly having spent years denying these documents existed but in 4 days they found them
Canyons will wasting in Nairobi today for the news from London
You can see the reaction of these people here today
I mean we're talking
We're talking something like
300 boxes of files
Tons of missing documents
15000 papers relevant to the case
This again is Katie Engelhart of Vice news she reported on the trial and the
Tencent number of
House of the government
100 linear feet I think those those files held
And it contained really really damning
Evidence of Britain's conduct in Kenya government in London did no
What was happening in Kenya there was specific documentation
A rounding up with Mama Fighters
It was even a memo about a Kenyan being roasted alive feeding letter written by detainees at then smuggled
Set up a cabinet
Hurry hurry hurry in order to save our souls I mean absolutely damning evidence
The government ultimately agreed to pay a bounty
20 million pound
List of people who brought this lawsuit
Which works out to roughly $4,600
Yes
He said I understand
Why would they even save those
Well
Looking through the collections of no emerged
It's quite clear to me
That
They want
Get to save documents that showed
Not all European stuff in Kenya
Hyping happy about compulsive Force
Who the letter written in 1953
By the colonies Attorney General
He observes that detention facilities in Kenya or quote
Distressingly reminiscent of conditions in Nazi Germany or communist Russia
So you think the people some of the British officers in Kenya save the files
Precisely because they were damn
Yes
They save stuff that would demonstrate
That we didn't like that
What are the reason why the memo case has become so much bigger than
Just amount
As soon as journalists and historians learn about the existence of those files they started to relentlessly poke
And request more documents and soon those 1500 8800 files
I meant 20,000 files and then
1.2 million files
And at the time the estimate was at the files occupied
About 15 miles
Floor-to-ceiling shelving
15 MI
The process that is being invoked
Biting my my case
Is going to have even wider repercussions than people yet
Realize
We got a little
Infloo laugh
When we're talking with a woman named Mandy Banton
A senior research fellow at London University national archives in London
And we call Hertz to help
Parse all this stuff and it one point I asked her if it's just a Kenya thing
And she said oh no no no
It's not it's not by any means
Explain the after the mammoth case the
Foreign Commonwealth office which is the technical name for the place
Holding those document
Almost immediately afterwards
It admitted that he actually had documents from 37 former
Colonist
Yes exactly
You mean that there could be dirty stuff from Malaysia dirty stuff from Palestine dirty stuff from
Cypresside Morgan Isaiah
Sofia Soto
Couple spots if you like I mean it's like a rewriting of history is that
I don't mean to run now Questlove to pay for
I'm looking at these you know comparatively newly-released records
Now both David and Katie
Cautioned us that the new stuff when it comes out might not be
White is revelatory as
All those Manuel files
I think their nuggets
I think their nuggets and I think
I mean I think historians will find them
For David Anderson one of those nuggets might be the documents about
The Cold War
Those could be historically really very very important
Fort Caroline Elkins israel-palestine that Malaysia
Singapore and I want to know what time does Hong Kong files there is over 250,000 documents on Hong Kong
Just Hong Kong
Which
Sort of brings us to the situation that we are in now
Just the most ridiculous ridiculous stupid situation imaginable
Which is that for the moment the British government's policy is that all documents must be reviewed
Aerodactyl
Did before release
So each file needs to be looked over by What's called the senior sensitivity review
Colloquially as weeders
Believe retired
Senior diplomat
If you can imagine you've got
15 miles of papers and you've got literally a couple of dozen
Tired
Diplomats I may sit in an office literally turning Pages trying to stay awake
Sitting here just imagine
And redact
All day long
Redact
At the rate
That we're going
The time these files finally see the light of day it will not be within my lifetime
It could literally be hundreds of years
I keep thinking about this two groups of elderly folks
Again producer Jamie York
The litigants in the Mama Cass are in their 80s and 90s
It just strikes me that
What a crazy lucky break for them that
In
The very final years
They're alive
Survived
To hear this apology
Numbers government acknowledgement
Shred-it been telling
For 50 years
Well
Thank you
Yeah thank you for putting it that way because I
I'm having
Got to know the plaintiff in the case
When they came to London
It was very clear to me that
What matter to these people Wars
Note
A financial settlement
But rather
Abnormal
Just
Simple of knowledge
That these things
Abington
So
Own the day
That the Barrister for the crime
Stand up in court I'm too old
Of our astonishment
Chad quite simply
The British government admits
Stitches
Once I gathered my Wix and looked right behind me in the cold
At 2
The plaintiff swearing tears
And
It brought home to me
What a traumatic
Hornet
Experience this evening for that
From start to finish
So yes I agree
For them to get that Triumph was wrong
But says I'm pretty sure Jamie York it was
Really remarkable only for somebody
So when I went to Kenya and I was talking to these people who would live through the emergency
Wanted to know about
What they thought of the settlement
And a lot of them are like
What settlement
The the hot
Rumors about the government
Britain Avenue
A green to apologize
Some of them and heard about it some of them hadn't but it doesn't
Really matter to them
To the people that got paid that's just
Tiny sliver of the vast majority of people who suffer
Who has you do good at whatever
What this one guy told me is that what he in
Most people what they what they want
Need
Isn't so much an acknowledgement it's it's
Take back what was taken from them
Nicole Eggert
Pieces of land
One can keep
Some go to
Ghost
That guy
So that he can do what any 18. Year old wants to do
Leave something behind
North Korea capital
Give their children in
Let's do dinner better
Special thanks to message Paula Schwartz for bringing us the story and to Martin Lovin Gina and to Faith a Lupe
Kenyan human rights
Mission Yakima U-Haul Kenda for the use of their music
3D painting a mini
For a production support
This story was produced by Matthew kielty
Racial music from Matthew kielty
A hell of a lot of travel and Reporting support from Jamie York
Omron arm rubber kovich
Thanks for listening
Hey this is Michael I'm calling from Culver City California
Radiolab
Is produced by Chad a perm rod or staff includes Brenna Pharrell ellenhorn David Gable Dylan Keith
Matt kielty animals Latif Nasser
Kelsey Padgett Arianne wack
Molly Webster
Soren wheeler
NJ New York
With help from the Murano marchetti Molly Jacobson
And Alexandra Lee Young
Are fact-checkers are Eva Dasher and Michelle Harris