Are you awake
Listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
3-2-1 hey I'm Jared I'm rubber
Delicious Radiolab for today
We're going to begin with a conversation we had actually
I I would benefit from a little bit of framing about kind of what we were like our goal of the session
Sure we can frame it
Make you blab a lot and then we added later
Right
It's a conversation we had with a reporter
She at the time was a New York Times
But is now the editorial director
Upworthy
So the start actually threw up
Personal interest lies in a relationship with milk
And I was very open about that
Talk about it with all my friends and we open with him
Yeah I mean I would say
He was in some denial and but yeah I was
I regularly would tell him hey like you have a problem with this
You know when he would be clear back
So you know if you're going to make me choose
Between me and vodka I'm going to choose vodka
So
And I was going to be young
But every night after 11 my life
Became
Without getting into a lot of detail there were
Fights
Arguments
A lot of rage
And I didn't know what to do and then felt really out of control and
And I've been to Al-Anon meetings and
Jesse Metcalfe
Terrible tragic problem that like a really smart cool person would turn really awful on you
But then one day Amy found herself in Barnes & Noble on Union Square
Union Square
Think I'm on the third floor and there was a
The table of mostly self-help books and there was this one called the end of my addiction
Fiction
She picked it up
This book was super fascinating it was the Memoir of a French cardiologist
This French Doctor Who had his life completely ruined by alcoholism
And I looked at it and I probably stood there like feet glued
To the floor and just like red
70%
The book described in very Vivid detail this successful doctor just sliding off the rails
Are detoxes and medical treatment facilities you know upwards of a half-dozen times
Is practicing falling off he was losing everything in his life
In the back of a taxi
Blood all over himself doesn't it was blood it is doesn't know where he's going
Used totally desperate
He kill himself was the next option
And then at one point he says that he had read this
Tiny nugget
And this is like the
Early 90
Barely eat some lacrosse the short piece about a guy who's been addicted to cocaine
Taking some muscle
And
Cravings for cocaine completely
You're just one guy one guy six
Eats all that and he basically just felt like
Well I might as well try it
I'm just going to experiment on myself
So he gets the drug
Start taking it and he slowly like doses up
More and more mount
The drug nothing happens nothing happens and then at one point he says the switch
And once the switch hit you just became absolutely indifferent.
Apparently this obsessive need for alcohol that it burdens him his entire life
Just went away
Total indifference
Baclofen
BAC
Clo Fe
Amy Says at this point
Standing there in the Barnes Noble
She was interested
Skeptical
But interested
Yeah so I found an email address
Like you do with reporter I Googled is every combination his name till I found some little. Fr
Email address
And emailed him and he wrote back
Right away
And they said
You know I'm already we haven't planned it Advanced Eye Care
Confirm it with him I'm all set up at my desk in New York and he picked up and I was like noon dr.amy send it how are you so good
Speak with you any
Music Amy Amy I'm so sorry I'm rescuing my girlfriend we are in the Alps I'm tearing her down a Mountainside
Can I call you back
Did you hear wind in the background and and the sound of no no
But he did seem like he was exerting himself to some extent
So you know we schedule a second appointment and
Recorded the phone call
Yesterday
Am I kind
To talk to you in the loop
I was rescuing my girlfriend I got a ticket like a hitch
Switzerland
So he launches into the mountain story and then
This kind of goes off
When Moses open the red
Make Matrix
I am who I wanted
Einstein
The Einstein was right and who is playing today
You like literally went on for 20 minutes
Before I got in
With a little
I read your book
They was off again
United States
Like literally was 20 minutes of on Fortner shared mission was to like save the world
Red flags going off left and right
And I sort of started to
Downshift
My
Thought of doing a story
And
Right about this time I reporting group got disbanded do it and due to an internal reorganization and so
I moved to a different desk and it was like okay
Maybe someday Radiolab will be interested
Kids will eat anything
No in all fairness dr. Mason to enforcing passed away a few years ago
May have been in the middle of a manic episode which doesn't necessarily negate his story with
Even after dropping the story Amy as a journalist is someone who can
Personally affected by alcoholism is incredibly torn
As a journalist
You have to be
Skeptical of everything but
At the same time like when it be great if we lived in a world where you could
Deal with this problem which you know tear it apart so many lives
Kill so many people create all kinds of pain and agony
With like a medication
That just seems
Great
A question for me
We often see addiction is like
Things that you've got them morally conqueror
Spiritual calamity
They've got some how we organize your entire being in order
Through
But what if it's not that way what if it's
What if it's simply a switch in your brain that got stuck in the on position
Can use a pill that
Just switch it right off
It would be nice
Now we were super skeptical of this idea but we also couldn't stop thinking about it
So recently
We start making some calls
Hi Santa Rosa Childress I'm all here
Dr. Anna Rose Childress is an addiction researcher at the University of Pennsylvania and Amy point of this to her because it was her
Work that actually inspired doctor me
I don't know if you mention throbbing pulsing desire States but somehow that comes to mind
That's our specialty
Throbbing pulsing desire States
Sounds great
She spoke with the prettiest Randy Mills and I in the studio and she's been studying that craving State and addiction
She's interview people about it what patients described
Tumi
Is it they would sometimes described as head of a wave of sensation
Just pulsates throughout your whole body
Their toes up to their head back down again
Okay one day in 1995 she's at a conference she bumps into a guy who tells her he has managed
To get some rats addicted to cocaine give them Baclofen and they totally lost interest in the
They were just interested for several hours
So I saw this and I thought
Well
So she began to give baclofen to people
Who are addicted to crack
Small doses
And initially there was a lot of disappointment
Results
Then she says one day she was sitting in the staff Lounge
Chilling
Macaulay Grant
Guy over
Hospital next door
And you know it was you got to talk to him
His name was Ed Coleman
Is a paraplegic
He had a drug deal gone wrong
Been shot in the neck
Paralyzed from the waist down so he was in a wheelchair taking Baclofen
Spasms in legs
He recounted this to me and actually have the tape of it doing low dose at first
And that was 10 mg 4 times a day
Tell me why you up the dose
Turn
Nintendo's
Does it take your muscles
I'm still beat up my legs are stingy
So I said well maybe if I take two
What did you notice
What Edward found was that when he doubled
His baclofen dose
Teens cocaine
No longer had the high
When I was taking it
Manhattan cream
Even when I'm to tell that when he stopped taking baclofen cuz he did stop for 2 days
I was having bad spasms the leg spasms came back
He could get the high again and the craving went through the ceiling
So Edward had been doing his own experiments did have the toast to see
What was the dose wake Stone, cocaine high but it hasn't wouldn't be driving him crazy
Wow so he's like a one-man study
This is actually the specific story that inspired Dr Mason to do his one-man studying to write that book
Which held Amy
Glute
To the floor in Barnes & Noble
Now even though none of this was
Rock Solid science by any means
Amy says that since then
People have begun
Quietly
Take this drug in some doctors if you going to prescribe it I talked to a guy who runs a halfway house in Youngstown Ohio
Who is using baclofen with people that were under his care there was a doctor
In Chicago who is prescribing it to a lot of people that Zoloft
Jobs in the book message boards
Hundreds of people on these boards swapping stories about how much they took when they took it
They were crowdsourcing their own cure in effect
The really surprising
Is it as we kept calling around we realized that Baclofen
Was just the tip of the iceberg
Yes yes there's another drug a can of procedure campral
And this other drug Gabapentin is Topiramate or Topamax
Disulfiram Chantix Suboxone
Naltrexone buprenorphine is a Doctor Mark willenbring
Addiction psychiatrist
Securian Saint Paul Minnesota
Others
Try to Target the high that you get a simple way to put it is this
It's a buzzkill
The bus schedule
Interesting seat drink but you don't get the milk at the happy warm feeling
Apparently takes all the fun out of
According to one journalist we talk to Gabrielle Glaser who does a ton of reporting about mental health and addiction
30 L but she tried one of these trucks during the course of reporting and
It honestly it made a second glass of wine same about as
Enjoyable as a
A glass of Dimetapp
It was it was just
It was like drinking water
Why what is the drug supposedly doing
Well
It blocks opioid receptors in the brain which is our pleasure sis
According to Dr dr. willenbring
Basically if you think of like if you think of a good Buzz as a
Has like a chemical handshake like you've got the alcohol molecules
I need to click in with the receptors in your brain and that's what creates ultimately the good feeling
What is what does category of drug
Do is they they get in the middle of the handshake they sort of like a blanket prevent the hands from shaking or muffled them
Search Bright
And if you're not getting as much enjoyment out of the drinks
Any ideas or not
I can drink as much
And these are home run
Drugs Eden things are drugs that you just don't
See
These kinds of effects
In medicine
And hardly any say
Mark Twain Addison Studies have been done in Finland
Are the Netherlands UK run a bunch of us
Hey look at this one particular drug called Naltrexone and show
It has a very high success rate
Like one particular study in Finland 150 people show that this truck has a 78% success rate
Helping
Very heavy drinker
Reduce their drinking to normal levels
Sprint
So are these rocks venues
No
Basically the pickup has been near zero
This is something over and over again
These trucks are out there that there's there is some evidence that they work
But they're kind of invisible yes that's Gabrielle Glaser again
Shear
About 1% of people who suffer from alcohol use disorder
Ever given the choice or an option to take any sort of medication
Set B1 2% of best
Yes
Which is particularly weird she says because that drug Naltrexone was using the Finish study that did well
It's been out for a while
This drug was approved by the FDA in 1994
I'm by the way the purpose of treating alcoholics
We never heard about it
That's so weird
Well that's a very complicated question should sort of hard to pin down but that there had basically just been this psychic
Barriers we've all had
To seeing addiction is something up
Pill
Can help I mean just look at med school
I think there are something around 240 Medical
Schools in the United
In only 14 medical schools
Was there a single
Course
In addiction medicine
That number has since gone up a little bit but not a lot and so we asked her why would that be
She said well
It's just that addiction treatment has never really been part of the rest of medicine it has been complete
Desegregated
It's been snowing self-contained world and
This actually goes back to how it was set up
The very beginning of fast I need to go back about 80 years we had in hospitals at the time in the late 19th
Recent early 1940s we had
Tuberculosis
TV Awards
But then
Funway
After World War II TB how to cure
You got better you didn't have to stay in the hospital in the sanitarium just
Tampa cover and suddenly these TV units were empty
And she says it was just a
A few years earlier
Data group
Of mostly man that got together
To form Alcoholics Anonymous
Doctors had no idea what
To do with alcohol
People they were called drunkards inebriate was another word that was commonly used
Of course the founders of a new this so when they saw all those empty TV War
They went to the hospital
Let's
Make
Those alcoholism units in your hospital
Family doctors
Okay we don't have an answer for these guys so we'll just let them let them do it and
Naspghan
80 years
Separation
And that's where we are now
Out of this physical separation according to Gabrielle Glaser you got a
Cultural separation 2
Very different ways of singing
Culture II what does that mean it's just like someone in the medical Sciences who might
Decline to see addiction as
Purely biologic
That's all
I will just fix it will just fix it
Play there's something deeply wrong here there's a
Something in the person in the spirit in the souls is a reflection of your inner broken self
Dressed at a higher level
The AA curriculum
I may have my facts wrong I believe
5 out of the 12 Steps mention God
Text you when we checked it
6 out of 12
Half and the big book which is the Bible of of Alcoholics Anonymous
There's a mention of God or him or your higher power
On almost every page
What is the recovery rate from the AA crap what many researchers say is that the success rate of AA
Pee is in the single-digit
One study show
That for every 100 people who show up in an AA meeting on January
Only five
Of those people will be sitting there on December 30th
Of the same year
You call that the dropout rate is
Is 95 /
Percent
I was really surprised to find that out
Not to be fair
I think we should be
We have to say that
Couple things like first of all AAA is it is a volunteer organizations
Support group doesn't claim to be a treat
And also when you start talking about success rates that gets really squishy I mean if a person doesn't show up
Today beating it doesn't necessarily mean that they're
Drinking and they may be doing just fine or perhaps they switched group they've moved him laugh really hard to sort
Find your terms here
Clearly AA is born
To a lot of people and that's something that actually Gabrielle Glaser found out last spring when she published an article
In the Atlantic
Get laid all this out
When that article came out I received
Thousands of emails
You are a horrible person you deserve to die I hope your kids get killed by drunk drivers
But so there was this article in the Atlantic in April
We talk to doctor willing Bryan Glazer mentioned in the article
Call somebody who believes more medication than 12 step
He said that when that article came out
Since then our phone is
Run off the hook
We got about half her calls from out-of-state
Is there anybody in North Carolina or in New York or in Texas or in California
Or where it is and they're desperate in the families are desperate
For an alternative and they can't find one
He says all this makes him think back about 30 years when I was a resident there was this debate raging
There was a big debate about depression whether people should be treated with antidepressants
Reset the debate completely shifted
Can we go
It comes to Prozac
When we got
Prozac prescribed Prozac
Suddenly had this drug that was a massive
Success Pond other drugs and in the process
Changed how people
Fundamentalist seed
And now most people
Male get treatment for anxiety or depression
With antidepressants
Compared to psychotherapy
Do you think we're heading in the same place with addiction
All We Are
We are there's no question
I do predict in 10 or 15 years will have a Prozac Moana
This is Jean Pelletier in Boston Massachusetts
Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology
In the modern world
More information about slowing it www.slha.org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
About what we're calling tiny moments
Brilliance
Basically I want to hear about those times when I kid you know did something
It just means you lean back and say wow how did they do that
Maybe it was the moment that I
Kids started reading back
Do you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lesson
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of their musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed they're writing music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the small specific moments where a kid does something super smart
Anything to do with the test
If you have a story
T-shirt with us
Go to radiolab.org
Brilliance
Record a short audio message for us
And that's where you live. Org / brilliance
Thank you so much
Very welcome back I'm Chad Roberts and if you know this music you already know it's the Brian Lehrer show on
WNYC good morning everyone this is the Brian Lehrer show at our own
Home station WNYC in New York very very popular
Yes
To explain
We wanted a gut check
Guess we've been hearing all these
Things from experts saying that we're undergoing a c chains and I want to know is that actually happening out there
There in the world and the world is our local world is
Who is Brian Lehrer listeners
It's your stories of What kinds of treatment you were offered and actually used for alcohol and substance
Abuse to ask the Brian Lehrer Timothy would help us out call us 221-2433
They helped us out
Radiolab hosts
And you believe we're in the midst of a cultural and medicinal shift for the way we both View and treat
People with addictions
Yeah we we bumped into a reporter a couple years ago who told us the story of a guy
Sort of summarized Amy O'Leary story about doctor Mason
He described a moment where the addiction just switched off
Goodnight sir to summarize what the experts
Hold us maybe something is happening we weren't sure it's not sure it's a
I were curious to hear from people who struggle with substance abuse
I'm wondering what sort of treatments they've been offered if they have they seen pills like an L tracks owner Baclofen
Have they use them have
Have they worked
What's been the experience
Show listeners
Just like that help Chad report this story
I'm calling from New Hampshire
There was an explosion of calls Ginger and male pack your on WNYC
I'm an alcoholic and an addict and I've been in recovery for 18 years
A lot of people who felt like this idea of a pill that can
Treat addiction was
Idiotic
Magical medication
Closest to physical disease
They're all be cured but we also heard from a lot of people who head
Just been offered these drugs
I was prescribed shampoo
Cut the Cravings Lincoln call
You just got prescribed addiction medicine
That morning
One way or another
He was excited as we're a lot of the colors in this category because
Kind of means that they're just sick
They're not bad people
Not something that people choose even though it seems that way
Tomorrow in Manhattan near on WNYC hello tomorrow
Hi-yah
One color called in
To say that
Her dad had a terrible time with Alka
What's the strongest
We were thinking about putting him in rehab or something but afraid of the stigma of it and my mom is a doctor squish
Is working in the hospital
He told me that one day she took matters into her own hands and
He gave him injection shots of
Voltaren
You know the way we say it is like mold during a muscle relaxant not too dissimilar from Baclofen
And it work
One day like everything was okay and he was over it I mean it wasn't something that was controlling our lives anymore
Let me ask you this
That's pretty strange emails again after the Brian Lehrer show we had so many calls
That he set up a Google voicemail and he talked with an additional 40 or so people
Eddie asked everyone do you feel that we're headed toward a sea-change where we're going to start
Treating addictions in the new way
I completely do you know you got a drug problem find a drug that fixes the drug problem
Is no pill that will make you want to put them drinks
Hello Billy
Today
Will you just introduce yourself tell me who you are
Yeah you can use my few can use my full name if you want my name is Billy Webb I am from Shaker Heights Ohio and Akron
Really live in St Paul Minnesota
Hey this is Andy so I'm talking to all those people on the phone Billy's
It was a story that I just kept thinking about over and over again until eventually we ended up getting him into the studio
Remember
What it was like
The first time
That you had alcohol it was
The summer that I turned 16
And
I was a quiet kid
It's kind of a
Nerd you might say I was into
Computer games but then it took the tide sort of swelling and I got into music and most
Specifically punk rock in
Sky
He says it was this time that he was
Coming out of the shell
Learn how to play the bass
Practicing all the time I made these new friends and they started the band we were horrible
But we're willing to put ourselves out there and we started playing gigs and
I have done my first girlfriend at that time and I was very excited
And nervous to see her
So
I figured why not why not losing myself up a little bit
So one day he breaks
Into his father's liquor cabinet
Takes a couple shots of Mount gay rum
To be honest with you and I finally felt like I was myself
And it just felt like I was on top of the world and I could do anything and I had all these creative ideas that came to me
I wanted to talk to people
That's when things started to take off
By the time Billy was $24 becoming an entrepreneur
He was running his own business
What is a storage facility that he plan to convert into art spaces where we would have shows and maybe even a little small
Record Shop
Thousand a relationship we had a dog
He was a new band that toured it was fun I can say that for sure I could even conduct business out of
The bar down the street
If I wanted to cuz the business line forwarded to my cell
But he said that it was also around this time
Have you started to wake up in the morning
With the shakes
But I remember
Drinking beer in the morning in the bathroom
How much do you think you were drinking
20 drinks a day 25 sometimes
They usually the night before
Before I
Passed out or went to sleep
I would say you know I'm going to turn it around in the morning I'm going to I'm going to get out of bed and workout eat a full meal
And that never ended up happening
What eventually
Did end up happening is that
Billy s
For help both his mom and sister the
Flew Billy up to Minnesota where he checked into one of the best rehab centers in the Midwest
And when I got there looks like a
Small college campus I mean is very serene
Sort of peaceful setting very welcoming
He started going to group meetings started working out and was like
Alright I was actually excited
I thought that things would turn around when I got back
But
Within just a day of being back in Cleveland
And it was right back to where I was
20 drinks a day 25 sometimes
So I ended up back in treatment
We figured you know I just didn't do it right the first time so if we go back we'll get it right this time
And
Once again
You know I
Crash and Burn
This time not even in Cleveland
I had realized at the airport
Even make it to Cleveland
And he said this is just how things went
It was just the same old story of In and Out In and Out in the span of about 4 years time Billy tree
7 different treatment centers detox centers lots of AA meetings I want 210 meetings in
70 days I went to 28 in one week one time nothing worked
He says there's a a sponsor's with tell him you can do this so get it right so we leave those meetings feeling positive
Another liquor store I just consider myself a failure at this point of time that
I was never going to get better
And that led to
More more drinking
He said that he lost his girlfriend pretty much all his friends
Got fired from his job
Due to drinking and my day is just consisted of
Walking to the liquor store
Find 2/5 and walking home
That's all I did I just laid in bed
And and drink tart even
Think about
Without being completely horrified that that's with
My life has turned into
And then
I woke up one day with severe severe pain in my abdomen and I couldn't move or walk
Or keep water down
And it was really scary and it was pancreatitis so I ended up
Checking myself into Hospital in Grand Rapids and
I saw these people and they said why we don't even we don't see
This condition until people are usually in there
Mid-forties
Billy was only 29 years old
When I got out I moved into a sober house
St Paul
And that's what I got hooked up with
The Altier Clinic
No at the altar Clinic which I should say really quick is run by dr. Mark willenbring we talked to earlier
Are there they do something that they call evidence-based treatment
So if a patient shows up looking for help
They are giving a therapist
Did any underlying mental health conditions that they may have in for everything connected to their addiction
They're given medication
Into his case they gave him when I took them out strike zone
I actually was able to limit my drinking to
2 to 6 drinks a night which was
Quite frankly
Felt like
The normal amount to me
He's able to drink
Yeah
Almost overnight
I was blown away
That's all I wanted was to be like everyone else who can
Write have a couple drinks in
Set it down what does that tell you that tells you that you are
Q word
I just felt like there was
There is no compulsion
Keep going and going
What was what was different than I did it did it not taste as good did it not as good
I can say that for sure especially if it was a microbrew or something like that
But
I didn't get that same brush in my head
And being able to drink without
That Rush
For a while
That made all the difference
Couple months I was okay you know now I can just have a couple
But
What happened was I
Was taking it and then on one weekend I just decided
You know what
You know what I'm not going to take it this weekend it's a long weekend
I don't need it
Listen to even though the urge to drink
Which was something that have been nagging at him for years even those that
Was now gone he told me that there was just some part of him that
Miss
Being drunk
If I wanted to
B2B intoxicated
Even with this medication that was
Who's helping you
You missed it
Yeah knowing all that it cost
Askew
What about it did you miss
I missed
Feeling like myself
I didn't I
Hey guys this is for the engine I hate to interrupt but we have to
The studios
Is being blocked
10 minutes of sorry guys
Poetically bad timing
We got
8 out of the studio
And this was this was several months back actually
And it took about another month and a half before we could all get back in the studio again Billy
Well yeah yeah
So I started by asking him so
When you said that
You didn't feel like yourself what would that mean
I didn't
Picture life being possible without alcohol that's the only person that I knew
And basically what he told me that if you
Think back to the beginning of the story
He came out of his shell
Alongside alcohol being creative writing music performing music
Alcohol's are his verse
Girlfriend alcohol
He's had drinking
Associated
Since puberty
With the best parts
Themself
Angelique you know how we all have this sense of
Like who we are inside
Again I have like giving your inner Jaguar like
People can think what they want about you and you got your Epic
Mutation
So you you know who you are.
Will his
It was all wrapped up
And alcohol
Do you take that alcohol away what was left was
An empty guy that I didn't know
Justice
Boyd
And filling up that boy he says was this
Onslaught of these
Terrible memories
Sequestered
Detox words and
Punitive treatment
All the people I've alienated
Over the years all the Lost opportunities
And all the failed attempt
He says that's what he would think about when he was sober
And you just wanted not
Last time we talked to Billy he was doing really well I had the job I had
The girl I had a band back
But he says that in the course
I'm just as month-and-a-half since the last time we talked
Elastigirl isolated want your friends and lost it
Good job that I wanted to keep for a while
Until I could get in the garage
It's cool so
Kind of having to start over now
Even just listening to your voice right now you sound so different
I know that I sound different because I was I was coming in here with more than
Positive spirit last time
I really was flying high last time
People were excited for me to come in and now they're they said are you sure are you sure you want to come in today and talk to them
I mean
The pit of people who
Even talk to me right now
So
It's hard to do a triple backflip
Didn't want to come in here crying or anything but you know
It's pretty sad
It's pretty sad but
At the same time I mean I feel hopeful that I can beat this
I believe still seeing a therapist he still going out here he's actually on this new medication out called
Gabapentin what she says has been helpful
And I know I was pretty staunchly against to the 12 Steps last time
But
I am actually
Going back to meetings
These days
Just to be with people who are in the same boat
Suicune buff
Yeah
I hear story like that and I say
Yeah I think we're ready to see Addiction in the new way
And we're definitely I think pills will be a big part of that seems me
But
The pills can't get all the way down
You know
Write the duck thing that makes addiction go is
Really deep
Retin A
This reminds me of when we were talking to Nora volkow spine and director of the National Institute of drug abuse at the NIH
She's at a point that is
The same idea in a really interesting way one of the questions that I've always got in my brain is
Why do we become a
Why is it that we can fall into a state where we actually
Become obsessed about something and compulsive
Despite the fact that
It can have negative consequences and
Romantic love
He's exactly that situation
Nora said that one thing that biologists
Snow in actually
I've known for a while is that
Drugs
Hijack systems in our brain that are there for other purposes
She says literally
Drugs will light up the same circuit in your brain
That are usually engaged
Take when you're in love
When you're hanging out with your friends when
Now you're being hugged by your kid
Since it's almost like randomness of chemistry that you have this chemical compounds
That can go directly and activities
Dissenters
So it hijacks the very things that make us
Casino
Good friends
Good parent
Correct
It's like a weakness point of a
The strength
Yeah and actually
According to Andrews children so we talked to her earlier
People with addictions ironically
They're the fittest of the step in evolutionary terms right
They're the people who would have been earliest for the the food earliest for the sexual partner
There's a deep down inside of them
Like
Level
They have the greatest sensitivity
They would be exquisitely attuned
To the promise of reward
And most of the time and for most of us
The Millennia all the priorities were on
Being
A good reward appreciators that that was our only job
But now
When a different environment where we got
Huge opportunities for many sexual encounters that carry
Viruses rather than just
Another possibility of survival if it is then we've got
You know
Origins meals that we can acquire without expending a calorie and see in almost every circumstance that you can think of
Except for the last
You know
50 years
Being on the side of being overly responsive to reward
Was probably mostly an advantage
You know
Hot sandwich I've never heard of
I said that way
And for patients
In some sense
They're the fittest of the fit
And think
Sounds like a terrible
And the
Terrible reality of that joke is something that just
Kept showing up on her voicemail
Over and over again
So yes this is Soca truth
Sing to the Brian Lehrer show
Way home from work today
Have a son who died of
Alcohol abuse last name
Kind of
Come to
My son
He was a creep
I think he just couldn't
See
How to be
In this world
It's really hard for him
How do you live your life
When do you have to be sober
The story was reported produced by mr. Andy Mills
Special thanks to Tim Howard and two of your Mitra Lee and Donegan Deborah Snyder John Kelly George koob
Andy and I wanted to say
To the dozens and dozens of people
Who willing to talk to me some of them
Hours
Mother recovery
Thank you
Very much
And a special thanks to the Brian Lehrer and Megan Ryan and that whole team and of course to Amy lyrics
Who started the whole thing off
Exactly
Thank you guys for listening
Replay the message press 2
Radiolab is produced by Jad abumrad our staff includes Brenna Farrell
David Gable Dylan Chief Mac tightly
Robert krulwich
Hayley Mills
Latest nature Kelsey Padgett Black Molly Webster
Lauren Wheeler and Jamie York
With help from Simon Adler Alexander Lee Young Abigail keil
Stephanie Pam and Michael loewinger are fact-checkers are either Dasher and the shell
End of mailbox