Are you weightless
Radio WNYC
Okay
Either
Bobert
Hello okay there you are
I'm jabbing Rod I'm rubber Coches is Radiolab yes sir and so okay we're going to continue with one more episode
Load from from the series on race
What you did for somebody else
I was kind of for somebody else but also for us at the same time
It always kind of squishy
To be honest
I've produced a four-part series along with Focus Features Stitcher eliminate house that was
About the history of conversion therapy in America
That's people who are gay who are being pushed to our ass to I want to be straight yes and sometimes it's a therapy
Type situation sciency sometimes it's a church type situation
Here's a few the funny thing Robert
You would think it's kind of
You think it doesn't happen a lot right
These days I would think certainly less
Certainly less than
Before well
There was a survey done recently
Bye
Buy a group of UCLA at the Williams Institute in conjunction with Gallup Gallup polling
They did a survey that looked at
Of the people in America who identify as LGBT
Kill which is about
4.5% broccoli
13 million people
How many of those people have gone through something like conversion therapy
And the number
Completely shocking
Shockingly small so I can
Well, almost 700,000 people
In the 1970's and 80's in Swan or also recently
Recently this is a survey is done in 2012
Actually give you a sense of scale
Okay
700000 people
That is the
Equivalent of the city of Boston
That's the number of people were talking about that's a lot of freaking adorable
No to your question
You would think it would be mostly older folks yes
From the days when it was
An Abomination and dial no longer really for many family it was actually
Equally prevalent in all age groups in the survey found that
Just as many young people
Champions
We're being put through these kind of programs
As people of older Generations
That is
The prevalence wasn't going down
You know if anything like just as lgbtq
People are being embraced
The Wider culture
There has been a kind of
Silently entrenchment
In certain communities America
It said that was part of the whole reason to do this project is that there's this thing happening that we're not really looking at and
History to it
Troubling but also kind of fascinating
So I want to play the final episode in the four-part series as it deals with
Well it deals with one of the
Central guys
In that history
This mean characters that you found
This is a really
Complex will you turn this thing
Well he
Oh
And then I don't know I don't know what your face will look like at the end of this
He has so um
Purchase a few things before we start this this whole project was done in conjunction with the Focus Features film boy erased which
Which is out now
And that film was based
On a wonderful Memoir by guy named Eric Conley
And this
Story
What's the story everybody told us we had to tell if we were going to do a series about conversion therapy in America
And it's about a guy named
Smith
News cameras started showing up
Bull horns came out
And all of a sudden I heard
John smid
We know you're in there
John smid we know you're here it was as though a torpedo
Adjust hit the side of her ship
The ship the John Smith captain
Before was torpedoed what's the largest ex-gay Ministry in America it's called
Call Doug loving action
For almost 25 years
1994 2008 if you are an Evangelical Christian
You had a gay son or daughter and you wanted to convert them to straight
You might have sent them to John
Maybe $7,000 he
Would run them through his program I want you to tell him how he is the guy in boy erased
The torment scary clown
Tell him how you hate it for the things that he's the way you sit down
Sit down but I'm not angry
I don't like my life to be painted as a villain
And that's kind of the way I feel about this movie it's like
I don't like it
It's uncomfortable
I don't like the movie I don't like the book I don't like what people are saying
I don't like hearing Garrett talk about it
I don't like it
It's uncomfortable
At the same time
There is
Ruth
In that I was a 4Runner
And a spokesperson and a national and international leader that said you must eradicate homosexuality for me
That's just
The price
These days John Smith is living a very different life
My life has been reinvented several times
Majorly reinvented he now lives in Paris Texas with his husband Larry
Andy makes furniture
Producer shemale holy and I paid him a visit
Corner of our house
John and Larry live in a tiny one story house bordering an enormous Horse Farm
So what you see is we watch the garage out of his house into the garage is
Rolling Hills in One Direction
Epic Texas Flatlands at another and a sky that is so big it kind of hurts your head the shop itself is it in here with the car
It's as if the divided shop okay the cars are in the next space John also collects and restores old cars
Oh wow look at this
I'm I'm a person that uses
Every scrap that I can I have a lot of used would old would like over there is a whole bunch of
These days
What does
Set of trying to eradicate homosexuality
John Willis spend his days
Taking are old copies of Reader's Digest books and
Carving them in the letters of the alphabet
This large band saw a really
That's a nice refined Edge there's no frayed edges
Or a he'll also and I'm going to router these out
Do carpentry work for local designers I know he'll make a call in
Paint it white
When you make it something what are you thinking about
The most the time
I'm I'm thinking about relationships I'm thinking about life
People
History future
Little Einsteins is processing painful things
You know difficult things
How to think about John smid
Is a difficult question he is undeniably warm and funny and honest
And engaging at the same time
Many people told us before we came
Don't forget this is a guy
Who ran a program
Where
People in the program tried to commit suicide
In some cases
And now that he's out himself and married to a man and vehement Lee opposed to the whole idea of conversion therapy
It does beg the question what do we do with that passed
How should we think about it
Is he allowed to just move on
Would you grow up
I was raised in Omaha Nebraska
It was 1959
Life was the 50s life was good
All the moms walked up and down the street in their Shirtwaist dresses and had coffee with each other I mean it was a stereo
Typical
50s
Suburban American neighborhood experience
And I remember
Feeling at 5 I remember sitting back in our backyard on a summer morning
School's Out
Sitting in the play sandbox
And feeling the warm sun
And I remember just feeling
Life's good
I was so at peace
This is one moment of calm he says
Or he didn't have to worry about who he was
Know the story as it goes from here
Of John becoming
And then Unbecoming the
Elvis of the ex-gay movement
Is complicated to say the least
You could start the story in the 4th grade
I remember in fourth grade
Having an emotional affair
With Steve I wanted to carry his books he had a broken arm
I wanted to hold his hand cause I was a gay boy
But I didn't know how to work that through or what is a little boy in that situation say to myself I didn't have words
Then there was fifth grade
For the first time in school gets a male teacher all my teachers were females
And all of a sudden this male teacher
Remember just
I just
Fantasizing
Just looking at him being drawn to him being attracted to his maleness
Not knowing what to do with that
Jumping forward a bit dated
Several girls in high school end up marrying a girl named Chris
I was 17 16
Like him
Chantel family light alcoholic father parents are divorced
Healthiest kind of got each other
And we
Created to children
And then you get to the first in a series of
Violent shifts
In John Smith's life
Many years later when he was like firmly embedded in the ex-gay movement end up preaching against homosexuality
He would give a sermon that's her
Talked about this moment
I just want to share a little bit about my personal story so you know who I am and where I'm coming from
And I describes of being 23 newly married with kids
And then falling into the
Funk like suddenly be very uncertain about his marriage
About the future
At the time he was working in a department store and that he meets a guy named Leonard
How the enemy Works in our lives and he works in those
Does intimate times of Darkness
A secrecy it's not in the light it's not above board It's Always Somewhere Sinister that he sneeze
610 and 1 Friday night
9:30 at night my wife was bowling I was taking care of the kids Leonard call me I'm at the bar
Why don't you come over and we can talk
Well my head strategically placed himself at a bar right across the street from where I live
And I found out later that
He was already surmising what I was looking for what I was curious about where I was headed in his mine
I want to cross the street that evening ended up in a very
Mutually seductive homosexual encounter
I came home from that
4 in the morning which is again something I never did I never ever went out and stayed out
Of course my wife wasn't
Stupid she knew that
Why was he out so late what was going on
So she began to ask me questions what went on and immediately went to her and I said
Chris I'ma
I'm gay
You see how quick that identity got stuck
I had one sexual encounter
Outside of
Marital sex which was the only other experience I've ever had sexually
One sexual encounter
And I'm Signed Sealed Delivered
I'm gay and I want a divorce
What what do you think when you hear that now
My first thought was my verbage
And the way I described that story
And the way I would describe it if today would be so violently different
Those terms for inflammatory I mean I I filtered that story
Through
My
Theology at that time
I walked away from that marriage abandon my children in homosexual adultery
And drove into headlong
Full force
The homosexual subculture
I live in an apartment building free for the gay businesses
Anyone who wasn't familiar with or didn't like my homosexuality
I just crossed him off the list
In a later TV interview John would say that during this. He even became the guy
That young gay men who are new in town would call
Assertive
Get initiate I had taken people to the gay bars for their first time I was instrumental in helping people involve
Call themselves for years I lived in that lifestyle four years of active Pursuit and all along
Thinking in my head I'm looking for monogamy
I'm looking for a life partner
I'm looking for that one person that can satisfy all my needs and never let me down
What makes John's backstory
So
Interesting and also difficult to wrap your head around
Are these wildly different polls
He travels between in one life I mean he starts off living the sort of 50s American Suburban dream wife two kids
Swings into the gay subculture as he calls it
And then
As he puts it what happened was he started to get his heart broke
A lot the first guy that I lived with
I mean I just
I just really loved him as a 20-something year old.can
He came home one day and he says I can't be with you I'm a size queen and you don't measure up
Galaxy told him you're not enough of a man down there for me that was a shocking
Deeply deeply wounding moment
He said he struggled with his confidence
And he got into a series of
A very bad dysfunctional relationships
Began to feel like something was wrong with him
And it was at that point
With this
4 year experience in the gay culture
Where a girl I worked with
The time he was working for the railroad as a clerk
She was an Evangelical Christian
Started talking with me about Jesus in the Bible
And she was very open about her own struggles very vulnerable with me in
She invited me to church
And kept inviting me to church then eventually I went
It was a Christian Revival is church services the kind where people speak in tongues talk about the devil a lot
So I went and sure enough I was sitting in a few and this guy was speaking and I don't know what the heck was talking about
Because God was too busy speaking to me personally
I was sitting back in this. I'll never forget God said
John
You don't have to live this way any longer
Who was attempted mean
This is always the last John like what
How does explain that moment now
Because I mean that follows really flows from that moment it is honest as I can be about it
Because I
I don't really understand it myself either but
As much as I can process it it was built on
The hope of
Not the
Spirits of
He told me later that no
The conversion of it that God's voice in his head that he can't
Explain but
All the moments after suddenly having this whole new belief system
Reframed everything
First of all he was Reborn
To literally everything before that point was no longer important it was only about what comes after
And also he now had this book
Which seemed to say that the way he just was with a sin
Wish you would think
Would want to hear but
He said it was actually a relief to hear that
Cuz he can now take all of those really
Hard questions about himself and who he was a man and he can now put it into a box called sin
And say to himself oh
That's why I was feeling so bad
Because I was committing sin
It was
What I was doing it's not necessarily who I am it was my behavior and that
Can change
Believe
That all this pain
Jesus
Could heal
And he could bring meaning and sense and comfort and peace
Into my life
And so in another violent shift
John Smith becomes
Really only one of two people I've ever heard of to come out of the closet
Then go back in
That's going to the church regularly I felt free iFit liberated
Tell him that
Are clown minutes yeah I was a clown I became a clown you are clown yes
I was rainbow the Clown
How do you say that so matter-of-factly yeah well we were we were with it it was it you was it you
Christian song yes
In my clownstick was I was walking with an umbrella
Because I was high I was underneath the clouds of life in the rain
And my had a trick umbrella that when I would shake it it would fall
And it put it down in the rainbow would come out the promises of God's future it was my testimony kind of a story
Of how I came out from under the rain clouds and found the Sun
I made all the wigs for the clowns and I made the props and it was really a significant
Two and a half years
Of my life when I didn't have any outside pressures
Said it was a little bit like that moment when he was 4 he was totally at peace super happy but then
Starts getting lonely
I needed a companion
Side dated a couple of girls and those things didn't succeed and finally I met Valene
And we started kind of dating and I fell
He said initially things were going well and he felt like I'll maybe I can change
Maybe I have
But then as he describes it
That funk return
What does old feelings but even more unspoken than that this is the kind of panic would come up and I started feeling
I'm really really scared
While I was in that place
Today on family talk I heard
A radio program welcome everyone to this edition of family talk
Focus on the family James Dobson
GameStops in by the way is maybe one of the most influential Evangelical voices of last 50 years
SN
Hugely popular radio show today we're addressing the tough subject of same-sex attraction which affects Mill
Millions of people and their families
And the guest on the guest on the radio program was Barbara Johnson
Barbara Johnson was a mom of a gay son at the end of that program
Can and do
They offered information sheets on ex-gay Ministry
John says they basically said
For all you who are struggling with same-sex feelings there's a program out there
They can help you first time I've ever heard gay anything in the context of Christian anything
So I said focus on the family a letter
And to make a long story short he ends up getting connected with
The guy who many people sort of believed to be the father
The spiritual Godfather of the X game with
I had just given up on the church
We talked about it a bit in episode 1 like John
Frank Worthen was a guy who had been in the closet
Come out of the closet but then at a low Point Heard a Voice from God God say I want your back
They went back in the closet 1973
Right in the middle of
Jesus movement
Frank starts going to church and after service one day after church
Three young men came to visit me
And they were all gay
And they said that I heard you made a recommitment
Price that you're leaving the gay lifestyle and we would like to leave at 2
And so that kind of
You know within three days we have little group going
Has Frank Worthen tells it that's how the ex-gay movement began casually one day after church
Well the members named at love and action we did feel that it was
God's answer to the APA saying homosexuality is normal
And God is saying
Not really
What is referring to their is sort of the beginning of the scientific Community washing their hands of the whole idea
Deification which we talked about in the last episode but we're not Christian they don't know what they're saying
John's at the time that
That really spooked a lot of evangelicals this scientific communities were accepting homosexuality and they were saying that it's
It's not a disorder anymore they were removing it from the DSM 3 which is why we need
To do what we're doing
It was very explicit in your mind oh yeah
Indicates John and Frank Rosen and Frank's wife Anita were then they started corresponding and I said I was capable
I was trustworthy
They could count on me
Can you help me what do you have
And so need to call me she says we
Are hiring
A house leader for one of our houses
We are now if you want to apply for it
So John goes out to San Rafael California volunteered for love and action
And so
Begins a
Very bizarre very dramatic
25 year Odyssey to try and Stamp Out homosexuality
Christian men everywhere
And especially himself that's after the break unerased will continue on Radiolab and just ammo
Hi this is Jack from Peralta New Mexico
Radiolab is supported in part by
Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloan at
Wwww
Sloan. Org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here I'm a producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help this summer I'm hosting a series of Stories on the show and I've request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
About what we're calling tiny moments childhood Brilliance basically I want to hear about this
So did something
It just means you read back and say whoa how did they do that maybe it was the moment that a kid
Did you been reading to 4 month started reading back to you or maybe the kid was a piano lessons and you
Suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of their musical score or maybe the kids in math class you noticed there
Reading music in the margin of their geometry homework were interested in the
Does something super smart but doesn't have anything to do with the test if you have a story please share it with us
Go to radiolab.org Brilliance and record a short audio message for us again that's
Radiolab.org Brilliance thank you so much
This is Radiolab listening to episode 4 of unerased on Radiolab
Let's get back to the story of John Smith at this point in the story
John is searching for a way to rid himself of
Gay attractions
To make himself attracted to his
Wife is second wife
It does end up marrying a second time
He goes to San Rafael California to volunteer for new ministry
Find by Frank Anita Worthen
That promise is a solution they loved me I was became an office manager I managed all kinds of stuff I became senior housing
Manager decides to go to the Philippines on sort of a missionary trip
And
John takes over the ministry
The one he left
We completely redecorated moved everything around changed everything I mean like
I'm in the moment Frank flew out
Which was a symbol of this is now mine
And here's where John's story
Morphs into something quite different
Something much bigger
Any darker than just one man's
Journey towards
Accepting who he is
As John tells it
The moment he showed up
Love and action
Car wind
Program 6 months after I got there
Which is insane
Start appearing on
Fairies talk shows
Homosexuality from my experience that stand out of a need to know I was okay as a man
And he very quickly realized his story
Was like Rocket Fuel I had a phenomenal
Miraculous
Testimony
What's the name of that phone interview I mean I was one of those people
Who had a dramatic trance
Information from where I was one day I'm sleeping with my gay partner
And the next day I'm 100% sold out to God committed baseball so people
Saw my life
As
The dark vs the light it was almost like Saint Paul on the road to Damascus
He said people would come up to me Christian conference isn't and say that they were actually jealous of
I want to see all the power in his own story
We became much more extroverted as a minister
Perhaps as a result
Love and action started to gain Converse
By the week to the point where they could no longer fit in the small Church in San Rafael and so
They go off in search of a bigger Church
We got to Memphis Memphis Tennessee
Big church large community they hire staff at this point John is flying high and love an action
Who was advertising this is daggering success rates was something they heard from Garrard Conley
7% success rate of conversion from gay to straight I internally
Underneath It All while I couldn't verbalize it
I had to admit somewhere in me that we were not seeing success
We were not winning
They were successful why they were in the program
As soon as they leave bone
Bad Fallen
I knew it wasn't working but I couldn't admit that so the only way I could have knowledge that would be to
. something new that might work better
So when he got to Memphis he decided to go a totally different route
He figured if people were quote relapsing
Which they were let me draw inspiration from other modality
They also have to deal with the problem of people relapsing
And so
He ended up visiting a
Local drug and Rehab Center
It's called second chance
It's a drug and alcohol rehab for teenagers
Wonderful success rate so we all talked about it as a staff and we sat down and we said we really think they have something.
Valuable we adopted their philosophy
They decided they would Define homosexuality sexuality
And maybe they can just treat it with something like 12 step the 12-step seemingly were they the best way
To rid people of drug and alcohol abuse and had
A track record
And I'm thinking well maybe that'll if if homosexuality is an addiction
We need to remove the homosexual
Drug
Long enough for these people to detox
From it
It's so starting in 1994 and going through his whole 14-year stint at the Memphis Clinic John basically
Implemented this system where young men women would come in anything that they had
That could be remotely construed as
Which we call deaf eyes Falls images
There homosexual
Look
There homosexual books there homosexual Concepts friends people associations
Drug and alcohol recovery centers have seen these things as contraband
And it has to be removed
You big can't come here with that
They have to be separated from its so they can
Think without it
Because it's their coping mechanisms
It's their addiction
After they were then separated from their
Homosexual paraphernalia or what have you
Clients within go through
You know endless rounds of
Pseudo-scientific
Talk therapy
And so it became this elaborate 12-step program where we had to write down
Every week
Three different sexual experiences that we had
In Our Lifetime
And do a moral inventory about it
Each one
Mrs Peterson Toscano we heard of it from him in episode 1 he did to stencil of a notch
Would be
Well beyond just
Physically having sex with someone but a fantasy
An obsession over someone a romantic
Crush that you had
An encounter you may have had with an inanimate object this very varied like
Strange language to talk about the stuff and some of it was like we talking about and they were like you know
You know did you ever use shaving cream
When you masturbate it would like I was like no but now I'm thinking of that thank you for that
You're writing about these
Really intense sexual encounters and it becomes like a butterfly
Can vinegar Patrice played out in your analyzing at and dissecting it and tearing it apart
Peterson also told us that there were times when this these kind of techniques
Tipton to just
Abject
Cruelty
Sometimes they would be asked to confess
Some of these stories directly to
Two parents on friends and family night
He told us about a mock
Funeral that was stage 4 young man named Erin oprea Lee Peterson remembers candles I'm not sure if I remember that or not but maybe there were
It it's one of these
Pretty traumatic things that I didn't ever really want to
Bring back to the light
This is Erin because I'm up he says he is okay talking about it now
Special senses
Scene in the boy erased film besides see what happens if Aaron had
Vegas relapse
Fallen or whatever with someone outside of the program again
This is how they stay today
So they asked him to lie on a table closes eyes they brought end
That's some pretty Gotti
Flowers and their office
John Smith going to laugh at me for saying that but I did not like the flower arrangements so that anyway but I do
You know that I was on a table
I got my eyes Riverside
And then they wanted
All the people in the program to say their goodbyes to me
Wow
Yeah
Come on
Really
This is what he said directive by the professional counselor that was our Consulting psychologist
They made this up
And he said you should do that he said the reason we're doing this is because
This man
Has had a pattern of
Destructive Behavior he says it was just something that was suggested then by an actual counselor who used to he said this is called
Stop therapy
He said the guy suggested it they did it and it also just seemed like another one of those things I could borrow from dropping and Rehab
Clinics that apparently do this sometimes if somebody's
Using drugs in it
I dying
Be Scared Straight
I don't know when we were
Chastised
4 Hour rules
Which we
And I was
And I have been
I know I understand that now
But we were chastised for it
And we would internally say
We are not doing anything different than the local successful drug rehab
John says he knew
That some of these techniques were confrontational maybe even traumatic but it's a
Time
I believe that the time
That a temporary pain
To rid your life of the horror of homosexuality
Is worth it
He gets me upset thinking about it too just
How
Crazy some of us got there this is Peterson Toscano against XE him in a film made by director Moore
Fox
Who is nice enough to let us use the footage
One of my closest friends there
Attempted suicide and dumb
I found his truck at the end of the driveway
With all these photographs of his children
And he had on this note
He had this noted just about what a horrible person he was and
He gave up with any such a bad person
We took all these pills and went off
To the fields to die
Peterson told me he knows at least five students
11 action who at one point either in the program or afterwards attempted suicide
Smith himself
Offered a story of going with a colleague to a Christian Conference in California looking on the wall
Sing a plaque
With the name of a former student this room dedicated in the memory of David bilbrey bilbrey King
I said Allen
What happened
Citi credit suicide
5 years ago
I asked John about a letter that he wrote
In mm
10 where he
I know this is jumping for just a bit but where he ultimately
Apologizes for everything he's done
And below that written apology a comment or said
I don't accept your apology
And then they listed a series of names
In-Shape
17 committed suicide
Dominic Crouch 15 jump
Tua stats from the six-story building
Billy Lucas 15 hung himself in his family's Farm
Asher Brown 13 shot himself with his father's gun
Seth Walsh
Hang himself from a tree in his backyard didn't die immediately
You've taken to the hospital where he placed on life support. 9 days later
Jeanine Blanchette 21 pills
Tyrell Williams 1700 self in his bedroom closet
About 20 suicides no not all of them happened at 11
What are you
How do you hold that
How do you
The only thing I could say to that is in in all honesty
In some levels of this process I have to
Use some denial
I have to
I don't mean denial it didn't happen
Denial of my feelings
There been many times
Through life experience where I have perceived
If I truly
Felt everything that there is in there
I would die
And I also
I also have to release
People
To their own process
And I cannot
Take responsibility for their process
I can't
All I can do is acknowledge
And release the rest
Jonathan told me something that
Kutztown defensive
Actually I think is a truth that needs to be acknowledged
The idea that he
Was selling it love an action or perhaps that he bought into
Ultimately goes Way Beyond him
The sources of all that shame are as much the families
Of those kids
Peer groups
The schools were they went to this early the churches
The society at large that creates the conditions for love and action to exist
He says he cannot take responsibility for all that
I think that's right
This
Is an album that
The guys in the program actually made for me
And it has pictures
With statements from
Each one of those clients
Why we were there John showed us a kind of yearbook of the love and action class of 1993
These are these are students are wow
First picture was a kid who's maybe 18 husky thick black hair
This guy here you know you've been an inspiration to me from the first year I met you
I learned from you that you have to face life and death and then go through it
You're a good leader and a shepherd and I'm so grateful to the Lord for you I love you
And this is a guy
That today
He's married to his husband
Anna and we are in contact
Regularly and
As a very affirming and positive relationship
This man I was in contact with
Call thin blonde hair but this is one of the one of the circumstances were this meant
He died of a drug overdose
About 2 years ago
They didn't believe it was suicide
But
He
He's no longer with us
Just see
Here's one for this guy he says Smitty they called me Smitty that can
So much of my heart has gone into preparing this Keepsake for you each time you look upon it may you know my love for you
He looks like early twenties tall thin Adam's apple
Can bushy black hair big smile
He doesn't completely accept necessarily where I am today
But he's very warm and friendly he doesn't accept where you were
He doesn't completely embrace
Someone being gay and being married so he's not openly gay or is he talks about being gay but he
He's married
Till woman
And he has a family
I've not had communication with him
I have had communication with him
American guy Freckles but he actually continued
Working for a very anti-gay organization
And
It got to the point where
I just was
Was just in turmoil when I would see things you would post on Facebook or things you would say and so I really chose to
The kind of not be
Affected by that
This is a guy
Sandy are radiant smile he was a guy that was HIV positive
When it came in the program and
3 years later he died
In California there were
People that were in our program or in our support group Ministry in California the years I was there 22
Two of those people died from HIV
Are you in touch with all these people
I have had communication with
Him yes
Yes
In the last five years since he's been high and drive love and action John says he has made it
His mission
To reach out to everyone he can to try and engage with them
Sport them if they want to be supported
If that's what they want
For him
His sort of
Clean break
Really began in 2005
June 6th
We moved in and that was our first day
They just upgraded their headquarters a second time hired more staff
Do we had just started a new group of
Teenagers
Everybody was there we were excited
8:30 in the morning
Our office manager came running in my office and said John there are protesters outside
I was horrified
Horrified oh my gosh
What has happened how did they know this is when the torpedo struck young kid
Kid in the program named Zach
I posted a message to Myspace saying his parents had put him in this straight Camp it was like a boot camp
Wooden trees going to make it news camera started showing up
Three of them
And all the sudden I heard John smid ween
You know you're in there John smid we know you're here
Connections new recovery Treatment Center in Raleigh over there in the morning and the night
From the protest I started entering into an absolute days just just a cloud
I I I don't even know the protest lasted for eight solid weeks International media started
Coming in there's so much attention that the state of Tennessee actually started cracking down performing in space
Directions John Schmitt ends of counter suing the state I was so desperate to make this work and he says now looking back with the maze
How long it took him to wake up how
All throughout his mind with contorted self to push away doubt I'd I would drive through the protesters
And I remember them saying we love you we love you to meet he says amazingly he interpreter
Did that in that moment as God speaking to him I know you're here and I knew you were here
And I didn't want you to hide
I wanted to celebrate you being here
And I did it through these protesters
That's the way I interpreted it has some mental gymnastics
Yes
It is
The honest truth is what brought John into the light
What needed to happen before he
BLC light
Is it his organization collapse
Protesters created division in a staff one of his managers tried to
Force Mount you didn't know what to do eventually
He resigns
And so when I resigned
I sat in my
Newly designed home office
And I said God
I have no idea what you have in store for me for the
Surprise me
From that point forward
He says it was like
Slowly sobering up after you've been drunk for 25 years
This time it wasn't a violent shift
Is the series of
Tiny micros
Like one day he's sitting in his computer and decides
Click on gay p***
For the first time in his life
Immediately feel horrible react with shame decides got to go tell his wife who he was still married to at the time by the way
But anything's
No
Not going to tell her
A short while after that
Is it a Christian Conference
Any announces
To the audience that he John Smith the Elvis of the ex-gay movement
Was in fact not cured
Vocally said I'm a gay man
I'm a gay man
And
I'm in a mixed-orientation marriage
Mixed-orientation by the way means a marriage between a homosexual and heterosexual
I told term you sometimes here in this world
But that process that slow gradual Awakening
John says it is still happening yes the whole creative
In the car he told us even about the shoes he was wearing it so that brought it up I have bright blue tennis shoes on today
I bought those a month ago
I love bright colors I've always loved bright colors I stood in the store for 20 minutes
Looking at gray or turquoise blue shoes are identical
And I made the decision the conscious decision and I feel very emotional about this crazy
Table tennis shoes but I had to make the decision to buy the blue tennis shoes because I love turquoise
Blue and it's that it's it's still, I'm still coming out I'm still having to open my
Self up
To the reality
Of who I am and who I was wired to be from the moment I was born
It just there's his constant battle within me to deny to push away to surgically cut
A major component of who I am and so even though I was a I was an ex-gay leader
And one of the one of the instruments of abuse
I'm also a person it was subjected to ex-gay Ministry for 25 years
And so I have the same kinds of anger in the same kinds of wounds the same kind of pain
And that complicated this about John Smith
He is both the instrument of abuse
And also
A subject himself of that same abuse it might color how you see the Final Chapter
In his journey
From
Straight to gay 2x k2xx gay
Pets do this guy I grew up about
8 miles west
Avisca
Community call Maxi Tech
Is Larry McQueen John's husband
He works in the engineering department of a company that manufactures pipes for oil rigs third-generation Pentecostal
Come to a very religious family and so before he and John to Connected about 5 years ago
He had never been with a man
He tried dating women it didn't work knew he was attracted to men push those thoughts away up to that point I had lived
My life alone
And
In fact I had come to the point where I was crying myself
Because I was so lonely
And that's what I actually led me to say look Larry you know
You're 40 something years old you're lonely
I don't think God really wants me to be this way
The first night they were together which initially wasn't romantic it was they've gotten together as friends to do some Home Improvement projects
Talk about this on the radio
For now I fight
What okay so so I walked we went out to dinner came back and we just
We just really had a
Comfortable time
And Larry
Came to an amazing awareness at that point
He said you know
What I'm feeling with you
Really confirms to me that I'm gay
Any sitting by the way we're sleeping in separate beds
Next morning Larry walks into John's room
Lays down beside me on the bed
Puts his arm around and he just put his arms around me and I was reading an email he had his arms around me and I
Just started to sob uncontrollably
You know I had never in my life ever cried with another human being
It for me
It was like almost a physical sensation inside me
That
As if there were cogs
That never were quite aligned proper
But that weekend I felt
Within my body
These cogs coming into place and click
And I felt whole for the first
I was Larry's first kiss
Wow
52 years old
A few months after that weekend John got a divorce from his second wife Bolin
John Larry got married in 2014 and these days they sing in their church choir
Is the only openly gay couple in their Church
And they continue to nudge to church
Urgently
To take a stand
Support of gay marriage
The end of the day it's still difficult to know how to reconcile John Smith's past with his present
Whether he's taken enough responsibility for his actions or not
We spoke to people who are all over the map on that question
John would say
How do you feel
The lesson from his life is that
Recently people can change humans are teachable
Human mind is infinite
Robert I wanted to offer once I know to the story
In the time
That we were working on this series like something like four states
I mean that number wrong outlawed conversion therapy for minors and if you looked us or more broadly in the last
Few years
There's been this wave of legislation is trying to stamp this out yeah on what theory
That's cool I mean that special your talk about offering to minors
So I think
Something like 37 municipalities in the last few years have have outlawed conversion therapy for minors
And at the same time you have a lot of debate about the sort of expanding idea of religious freedom
Back protection that's written into the First Amendment
And a lot of these groups are arguing successfully * that
They have the Conn
Institutional right
To offer these broke
It's a really interesting and confusing moment right now
This episode of Radiolab was drawn from unerased
The Untold History of conversion therapy in America a series that I worked on with Focus Features
Stitcher and luminas in conjunction with a feature film boy erased
Huge thanks to the production team Shamaley Ikat Aaron Alice Quinlan Michael assessor David Craig Garrard Conley
To Anonymous content for their support of unerased if you want to hear the entire series I hope you will
You can find on race in all the usual podcast
Okay well I guess we should go
Yes that's what we can buy