Northern listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
Can I tell you a story
I don't have a choice do I have
Jack Kennedy John F Kennedy was the president
Penny Annie's
Very good
You really use on television was fun to watch and he would he would he would go to mass in my neighborhood in New York when you come
Anthony York
Kygo
Do a particular Church all the time and just out of enthusiasm some of my friends and I would go and stand there and watch him just walk up the staff so you can
Can you see the president
Of the United States in
Wife has multiple too many times yes
Because he we were big fans
And then
One day
We went to do that
And I can't remember whether he's Zip by or zipped in but anyway we missed it
I and my friend John.
But he was a New York ID so he thought they would be interested he knew that the place where presently was damaged
Famous hotel on Madison Avenue
He came up with this crazy plan that he was going to ask for his aunt
We walk in the lobby for the Secret Service wouldn't have to worry about us
So we go to the hotel
Cow he does the thing where in the law
Bobby
And then crazily the elevator door opens and there is
President Kennedy steps out of the oven with Jackie well she's immediately grabbed by these reporters in there asking her something and he's
Nothing to do so he's a politician he glances around
And I am standing behind
Potted plant
Staring at him
Anthony steps towards the bush and he reaches over the bridge of hello young man or something like that
And I couldn't speak because there was so much phlegm coming flooding into my throat that I thought I might drown standing up but
I took his hand
And I shook
And then
He believed he went off to something else and I was just
Staring at my hands
Completed that day I said
My sister
I shook
President Kennedy's hand
And
I guess I'm not going to wash it
Like two days
Two weeks maybe
What did she say to you
I don't remember what she said but
But that's a funny
Thing to say when 50 years later your science reporter
Google
Huh
Because at the moment I thought
Kennedy Honors Robert I didn't I didn't know that was true it was like a dream
I think of celebrities I do
But now
It turns out we can examine the question
Scientifically there's no science
That can do that
What do you mean
Well
First of all we all know this was covered with germs
But what I did realize that there are
Scientist who say
The bacteria honest they claimed was almost like for life
So you can be identified
By your microbes
And these are now making the Bold claim
Did they can check those Mike up to solve crimes to detect diseases
Do Public Health kind of things
Put them to the test
Serious
I know after this small little up
Personal history
So I decided to to reproduce the John F Kennedy Robert krulwich handshake
We could have I could find somebody who would be President Kennedy who would shake my hand and we would measure
In calculating C
So I got a team of producers on a WNYC show only human
To help me doing this and we found
A scientist
Is director of the microbiome Center the University of
Taco
I don't have President Kennedy around anymore so I got myself you going to be president
Substitute President Kennedy
Can you do JFK by Nation
Good for the man on the moon
SafeLink
This is Neil deGrasse Tyson director of the Hayden planetarium with the American Museum of Natural History here in New York
You ever been have you ever had your hand shaking by a person who you
Let that you feel
Like you'd like to have his or her
Steps to stain
Yeah I'm not that
Weird or creepy
I just want to know if you got Carl Sagan
Underwear would you keep called phagans underwear
No
But I have
I have come to
Love and embrace
All bacteria that want a part of my body
You are you are awesome
Am I your man for this
Pick up food that fell on the floor and need me to
I don't even wait five seconds
No one exactly knows the answer was
But if a person shakes another person's hand
N4a ordinary injury
Then the question is
How much a person a
Lands on person be and how much a person
Can a stays on person be
But most crucially for how long
Presumably
Exchange
Yes so we're nicking off
You Dragonborn or Miss hands on that I'm looking
Yeah it's I know when I try to find gloves it doesn't work so it's
3XL
XOXO
Just so you can get it
The fact that you are
Carrying all these microbes
On you
Bring up where are they
Gastrointestinal tract all the way down your skin
Young fingernails you urogenital tract
Every part of you that's your butt
Your butt
Especially your butt
He's covered in bacteria
I'm just sitting here you're actually releasing
Into the air around you think pigpen from the Peanuts cartoon member
About 36 million bacterial cells an hour
For every minute
How do they come up with me
They are leaving off on the on the surface of your skin cells or shedding I'm very old respirations coming out
Okay
So they
Lawton on they dry out on the surface
I'm making literally just drift office dusk the the
The anatomy of the room
All over this room on the door knob on the table surface on his
Hands
On the desk
And on the chairs
There's Neil everywhere
Colonic
Writes a lot in my cheek coming out of his
Out of your pants right and there they are on the steps.
The chair in the deposit
We we I think we understand what you mean
So now
Time question real quick
Subjective
20 minutes
To do
Breast of the sands
By the way producer
Why do we why do we start experiment now
Are what you going to do
So what we going to do is we we have little
My butthole is burning it doesn't mean I'm offering you my boo
Gut microbes
70 minutes
Absolutely sir we have these little star all chiefs reach tubes little green
Tube has a sterile swab in it with a with a completely sterile tip
We're going to open that up on very quickly rub
Birth photography
Each of your hand so your palm the inside of your finger
I'm going to do that very big Racine and put it as quickly as possible
Sister control sample
I got to shake hands with the young man over that was Robert
And we're going to definitely I trying to see how many you have received from Neil and how many
Neil is received from Robert Leahy is swabbing your hands
Before you hand shakes so that he can figure out what's the Baseline that you got them both your hands prehension
And he sure you're going to have different bacteria on your on your hands
You and you
So this is where it gets very interesting so you have very specific types
Bacteria and he has very
Types of bacteria that are unique
I mean I guess like I mean like if I just think about her second like the
Two of you had different days you arrived in this
You probably touched
Places you eating different things okay maybe a little bit of difference
But in general
You are
Those men
Living in New York City breathing the same air ride in the same Subway's exactly so why would you be
That
Different from one of
Well because there's one very important difference
Between us
Okay
We have different mothers
Have you been told anything like what this is
Dr. Siobhan Dolan
Assist as well we brought her in because she knows more than most when it comes to moms and babies
Stream my training years
Delivered a hundred babies ourselves about 500 babies centers in private practice at Yale New Haven Hospital for a bunch of you
And I probably delivered another couple hundred and I have three kids myself
Other side as well
And she says as a fetus
Before your born
You know exposed to what's in the amniotic fluid but it's a pretty
Clean
Set up in utero but
Then you go to the vagina and the vagina is just a host of bacteria and
You know heaston
Amniotic fluid there's blood or bacterial
Right exactly
Because at this point you're this pristine unadulterated hunk of biomass
The bacteria
Give me a ride I'm going to jump on it cuz that's what
Bacteria to
Finally
When
The baby's born
The doctors they take it to make sure that stable breathing
And then right up on tomorrow
Start to immediately promote the bonding and skin to skin
In your own case if
If you can remember
I quit what happens
What I remember is describing for him like you're mine and I've been waiting nine months to meet you and
Here you are and like just kind of embracing him and looking in his eyes and soap
There's a sort of bonding there that I will never forget the same moment
You're going to get some micro bonding to I'm it's a it's a very dynamic
Hot and bacterial. They leap from the mom's skin on to the baby
I did this for both my children night I took both of the month my bed chest at Beth and what you wanted to compete
Against your wife
Absolutely maybe a little bit daddy was a helpful thing you know who knows
Sorry yeah is that that was the reason I did it and the thing is.
Strains of bacteria that we get in those
First few hours
Give me a ride to a lesser degree the bacteria that we meet later in the first year of our life when
Stick weird things in our mouths at the dog comes by those strains of bacteria stick with us
Ready Set forever
Lorena Bobbitt
As much as possible even the bacteria that Jack will find a tickle
Nils hand
My hand fingering in between
Are descendants of those first moments of contact
And crazily enough even if you try to get rid of your bacterial inheritance
Get rid of all your skin back to you
Take lots of antibiotics to get rid of all your tummy bacteria
And then move to some completely different part of the world where the food is different than the temperature different still
The bacteria you got from your mom will come
Creeping back
Why why would the why would that be
Well there's something in ecology cooled
The founder effect
Whereby the first organisms
To get there and to be successful in an environment
Ulta the trajectory
Free of the rest of the ecosystem in
Change how it develops right
So you know if a tree
Species and type of tree lines on an island and becomes dominant
Then it will support the types of beds in the types of monkeys in the types of insects
Love that type of tree
The same is true in in the microbiome so you know you have a lifelong partnership
The bacteria you Interactive
So we know that Neil and I each have a unique mix of microbes almost to the point where they like a
Fingerprint
But if we shake hands the mirror
How much of his is going to get on me how much a mine is going to get on him and most importantly
Is how long will you
Strange microbial
Last
So you guys got to shake hands I want you shake hands like just as if you were meeting and holding you would like
Hey Neil or Hey Brother nice to meet you and just shake hands
Okay
Not like
Fanfic about how to actually shake at work
Okay now it was my hand go
Just made my index finger too cuz you got a little
Didn't didn't touch
And so every 5 minutes for the next 20 minutes
Jack's LaBeouf at my hand
Bacteria but no checking to see if any bacteria moved
And for how long
Joy what happened did you did your wife what happened
Well
Why would I tell you now
When we have the advantage of a short break
We'll be right back
Listen to call
From Corning New York
Supported in part by the Alfred p
Peacebone sound
Lansing public
Understanding of sine
Technology in
More information about slow
A
I hate everybody Pat Walters here I'm a producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of
Timer kits
Parents
Aunts and uncles teachers were looking for stories about what we're calling
Tiny moments
Brilliant
Basically I want to hear about this
Times when a kid you know did something
It just means you lean back and say
Well
How did they do
Maybe it was the moment that I
Kids started reading back
To you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lesson
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of their music
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed are ready music in the margin of their geometry
We're interested in the
Epic moments where
Kid does something super smart
It doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story
T-shirt
Go to radiolab.org
Splash Brillion
Amber Court
Short audio
And that's radiolab.org
Slash brilliant
Thank you so much
Jad Robert Radiolab
Okay just for winter break
Robert Neal
Just shaking hands and Jack
Gilbert was going to swap those
Sans write 1 minutes off the handshake
Then around every 5 minutes for about 25 min
Bacteria back to the lab and he identified are bacteria by their DNA
That means
Well yes it is a holy signs it's
Signs that's on The Cutting Edge
Rena Ware still researching and developing
And it will take many years before we're ready for Primetime but Jack says they are now at the phase where they can look into all kind
Kinds of different applications for this new microbiome detecting
Take me to Tampa forensic
Imagine if somebody comes into a room and doesn't evil deed
Right now we know that when somebody interrupts
Without space.
15 minutes
They leave behind enough of the signature
2 Frost builds text
30 minutes later
If I had to pick between 3 people or full people that would break into a room
There's a good possibility that I could detect which one of them had broken into that room and they're only going to get better in bed
Do you think maybe one day you'll be able to track somebody like outside moving moving around
Shirley on the base in the bacteria that they leave behind back exactly what we're investigating
He also says being able to identify bacteria in a town sewer system
Be a really useful in helping us to predict a potential outbreak
By noticing that there's a disease-causing bacteria right in the sewage so you can go to town
And before anyone begins to show symptoms you can say to my way to second we got a quarantine vaccinate we got to do something here
Nip it in the bud if you will before it becomes
A problem
And as you may have heard this plenty of research
Looking at the microbiome
Inside
Is revolutionising better
I mean we already have evidence that we can
Determine whether somebody will have a bad response
Stewart rug
Based on the bacteria that oppress
Inside them so we can screen them
Using the microbiome to
To determine if they have that like the outcome
But for now
Back to this absolutely crucial
And breath
Taking a spare so let me just quickly remind you of the situation we left
Do you and I talked a couple of weeks later
We got the result
Quotes from Jack and so I decided to go to Neil
To deliver
And just to set up expectations here Jack told us
What he expected was immediately after a handshake a little bit of me would be on Neil
A little bit of deal would be on me and that
Pretty fast the bacteria would die
And be gone
However
I am very happy to say
That
Is not
What happened what percentage change
Yes
You caused
On me of me on you
10%
I can't imagine it
I would say 1% 10%
But not much less than 1%
What was less than 10
When they came back
It was significantly less than 10
Okay
It was
What can it be below there whatever is this
Actually found a teeny number back here but they die
Nothing
From the
Nothing it's just it's just
Should I put it that way
I mean
That was quite shocking
I we were expecting that to be a lot more bacteria
Being transferred
Change
So that you know that one person picks up the other person picks up 10/12 bacteria
I think you might have washed your hand immediately
No there's no no no sabotage running
I hate antibacterial
I don't use what he called a
Purell
Yeah I never use any of
So for reasons that are at this moment totally unknown Neil's bacteria simply failed
Completely
Affect my hands
The other side of this equation is
What would you guess the present
Might microbes on you
Okay what I know from physics
Surfaces
Is
If they have approximately the same
Coefficient of friction
Then it's a it's a
Complete two-way street
If I gave you nothing you would have given me nothing
Is my
Guess
Here's what happened he
Definitely picked up bacteria from you and that led to quite substantial disruption it turns out
Hi
Your hand
You tell me you were
Skank nasty
I came on today funky the percentage
Before the handshake was that you and I was six
50%
The same 40% differ
Post Shake
You are more than 75
Scarlet
You made him more You by 15% at least I was swerving all over again
Slightly proud and control all the time
Staying and staying and stink
Every time
I was still there
6 minutes later at 12. Nasty
Could have been an hour later might still be on his hand like yeah I mean there's no indication that they were in 2K
When I left you were covered with
Let the record show he beat his chest in that moment it looks like there is a possibility that some of them could have gone
I think tonight you think that I might stay on him
I want a what I think is that there's a high probability
But some of those organisms once they set up shop on his hand in those initial 20 minutes
Could stay on his hand
What you mean like forever like
Forever and ever
If there is a possibility
There's a possibility
Versace
Do you have any idea where they're what we've just described is typical of a common handshake experience
This is a typical
I'll be because they may be old outcompeting
Directions to understand his house
Strange this result is think about it this way
Two hands coming together
It's like taking a rainforest from Bolivia Anixter and dumping it on top of the rainforest in Brazil
I was wondering whether any of the trees from the Bolivian rainforest will take roots and you know an adapt and become pretty
You all
Bacteria have home-field advantage
They are abundant in the dominant tonight in Parma
Then we would generally suspected
Very quickly the invading microbes. To die
The killed off
I'm pissed off
And I hope they just becoming a
It's always happens and it's over and nobody wins
Versace
Best mutual decay
So am I now successful invasive species on his hand
Some of your microbes are successful invasive species that yeah absolutely
How are you
Spleen mice
Success what we think actually happened is that something disrupted nilsy Coast
Right
I'm with think
Based on the analysis that there was a stripped
Secaucus
Which is usually quite rare but that doesn't sound so good step 2
Well their loss of species
Streptococcus
No tolls in the pathogenic
So there was a stripper
The caucus that was very abundant on your hand the beginning
That was transferred to Niels how do we see that transfer caring
I'm not streptococcus somehow
I'm disrupted music
System and allowed for a greater trend
Bacteria
From your hand to his hand
Oh man
That's like a little band of like murderous little bacteria
And it cleared away the forest
And then let's sit at the rest of you could come in and colonize I don't know I don't think anybody knows the answer that question all I know is that I'm
Name all over them
Out of my soul Robert
Slaughtered on my body that's fine
Don t feel any defensiveness
Towards the fact that he managed to
Conquer your microbiome and yet yours
Was unable to do the same to him
That by the way is producer Simon Adler
So
The word conquer in that context I would
Reword this sentence and say
My microbiome was perfectly content staying where it is
Apparently Roberts
Microbiome
Can't wait to get the hell off his body
Men
I came here thinking I would find out how long president
Kennedy stayed on me
Now there's suddenly a new question
Cuz if he's a cool cucumber
It's all on you stayed on him
Yeah
I believe
Maybe you were the anomaly
You're the creepy sweaty man with
Wet Palms
That's what you came here for
When did
Big big things to astrophysicist and author Neil deGrasse Tyson
For a
Putting up with this
Shenanigans I can go 5 days without a shower
And you wouldn't know it
Lemon smelling his armpits
I just don't
Smell
If you're on the way to smelling bad
This story was produced by Simon
Big thanks to Jared myself digital of the technical work the lab work that gave us our microbial analysis
Also to the Montefiore Medical Center
Also to science writer and author whose book I contain multitudes as a primer on all things
Microbiotic and he was talking to Ed
And then when things really got going that's when the team at WNYC is only human kicked-in that's Amanda around
Elaine Chen Kenny Malone Julie Weinberger
These are the ones who work
Who were with me all the way
Stuck with this
Baby things with a
Schwab's in whatever and speaking of which
ISO
The whole JFK situation that robber just did what you can kind of do it to this company called the ubiome
Has offered the chance
4000 hours to get on your hand
What is enough
Envelope I assume and then mail it back they will sequence it and then tell you all the stuff that's on your hand
And you can start that whole process by going to our website radiolab.org or only human
And after next week they're putting on their own show which involves
A microbial robbery that is can you catch the robber it all you can see you the microbe
Believe your house speakers into
A robbery in my home
Yes and also go to my website with only human we are putting up a very short animation
Of the handshake situation done by Nate Milton
Which is a
It's just
Glorious
Definitely weird
Kelly quick reminder you can listen to Radiolab anytime on Spotify
Hey Dad I would shake your hand but I
Keep your distance
To play the message press 2
To go to the next message
Breadsticks
Message
Who knew from phone number
Xiamen just I should
If the text to read out for the
I got the message to on Cullen and Reed
Text him I apologize
Lai Thai
So anyway
Here's the text
For me to read
Radiolab is produced by dad
Senior editor Jamie York is a senior producer
David Guetta
It's not cloudy
Annie McEwen Melissa
Emily West
Fontina
Beauty Wang
I'm Katie Ferguson
Michelle Harris
End of mailbox