Are you awake
Northern listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
That lime doesn't cut it very much I guess you really powerful
It's basically straight rum this is a very traditional guadalupian drink
Call Dad
People
As in punch
Doesn't punch
Ready Radiolab today we're going to go
Off to an island
Yes small little corner of the globe which it is very
Surprising way is trying to figure out how to
Understand itself
Buffett itself and
Pregnancy
Tickets The Winds of The Wider world
Reporter
Simon Adler
So
I went to Guadalupe a couple a couple weeks back
This French overseas Department
Physically a territory of Guadalupe
Guadalupe is a series of islands in the Caribbean
Did east of Puerto Rico and 400 miles north of Venezuela or less
Okay so I just landed the runway we landed on here was that one was just ordered on boats
Side body super lush green Walls of a floor I've no idea what they were in the story I want to tell Alexa
Sleep starts
On a watermelon
It's okay if I park here
Owned by this couple Sully and Louis
Thank you so much for being willing to do this
They look to be in their late 40s
How many
Souly had on a pair of glasses t-shirt and cut off blue jeans on Justin
My wife and Louis
Nice to meet you is wearing one of those
Floppy hat
Synthetic rubber boots
OK Google
Are you you were born during what
Yeah it was
I was born in Pawtucket
So after growing up in Guadalupe and graduating Sully decided to to get off the island for a bit when overseas
Fees for working gaetana's is lowest
And fell in love
True
Then I
Came back to Guadeloupe 20 years ago
Establish myself in the family area
Actually I didn't buy it but I was in the family for a long time okay
So I decided just to give them
And then we ended up staying saulino
It wasn't planned that you would be eventually they
Kind of fell in love with Farm we enjoyed so it's a it's a new a different way of living
60 acres of land
Rolling Hills bordered by the ocean filled with their crops
Tomatoes sweet peppers pumpkins
And watermelon
Watermelon Zellman Court
So cellular took me out to their actual Farm
Deserve what
We have to have it still
And there in this field I was surrounded by Jets
Hundreds and hundreds of these enormous water
Adidas huge like
Yes the way about 20 to 25 lb in this is there because
These watermelon in this field for the past 15 years
I've been under attack
Is this one this one is
Another one that was punctured in
This one is fresh oh man okay this day they've been here recently yes last night
Bill Rancic still fresh
Golf ball size
Cool poured into the side of it
And in the watermelon itself had just been emptied out it's incredible it's like they
Play football
Glittered with Halo water
This this is the worst attack we've had in about three years that I said it did it specially because you were coming
I'd like to ask this cuz I think it's time or what is doing
Raccoons raccoons
Raccoon
Rec
Yes those masked Bandits with the with the
Little tiny hands and adorable adorable at all
I don't know there's so not cute no knowing no horrible you have to give
Even if they are clever they were sneaking into Sully and Lois's field at night finding the big
Biggest rapist
Watermelon in the patch
Boring a tiny hole into it's creeping out the juicy innards digiscope adults and chowing down
It's a fiesta and Brazilian Louis this was a huge problem
Yoobi stuff
You able to to lose a third of it
A third of the Watermelon Crop adjuster
Yes meaning could go up to 20% of Revenue yahshua
Thousands of dollars
Saw
We couldn't stand
This loss is too much
We have to do something
We have to fight
So what do they do with a 15 years ago at Sully and Louis declare war
Meaning what the start with we puts an electric fence around our field that will keep them away
Pretty quick in note to put the branch and walk on the branch can get into your feel any way they built the Florida Bridge
Walk over the branches
So then they're going to try something new
This time they're like we have to be there at 9 she sings black music at them
We'll run around reply to sad music at one point even us
Stoop to just throwing rocks at the raccoons
He picked up a Rock on YouTube
I'm a good picture
But you can stay in the field all night long
So next thing I decide to try is okay let's put some traps out in
We tried to trap some
But there are smart
The big metal sword a tripwire
But the one day there was no trap
We found the trapper in the woods and it was all bent up
We did they run away with the truth
The raccoons were actually destroying that sometimes we just
I decided okay
Had to try the dogs guard dog put their dogs in the field
By the next day when we came it was it was it was it was
The raccoons killed one of your dog exactly
All of his intestines were outside so it was a jewel to the death
So you know what kind of animal dealing with
This confirmed every feeling I have about raccoons
They're not just clever they're fierce
Good and bad in everyone of these are obviously not very nice raccoons and if I were
Lewiston Sally's position eichorst
I wish you something I thought that if anybody would be on
I'm bored with
With some sort of eradication
Campaign I
But when I floated this idea by them
If I was you I would want to kill those raccoon
They just kind of looked at me funny
Killing them
It's a little love
A little harsh
Attacking your livelihood I'm trying to understand how you
I'm stranger because I myself putting myself in your position I would find it strange to
It's just may be sentimental
Treating you know
Wait what why environmental feeling
What does that mean
Well
Here's the thing
The people of Guadeloupe acknowledge that these raccoons
Are super
Destructive
They know that they are attacking not only watermelon Farms but
But goat farms
And chicken farms that they're going in tipping over trash cans in downtown quota Pete
But yet simultaneously
They adore them
Michael Jackson love is so lovely
Of course we love the raccoon they put them on their postcard we just think it's so cute driving down there mean
Highways uuc billboard
Where people logos for their advertisements for their for their Tire Company
Is a raccoon
Everywhere
There is a statue of a raccoon at the zoo with benvenue Zoo de Guadalupe there the number one
Xzibit here they are the first thing you see when you walk in and have many in the trees
Thank you
And on the way out of the zoo
When you walk into the gift shop got a coffee cup with the raccoon on it
A snow globe with a raccoon in it
Keychains of those
People people are raccoon crazy on this island
Why well it's it's really complicated it is it has to do with their history of the island it has to do with who
Who came to the island when and who gets to say what happens on the island is it has to do with it with power like who
Raccoon that steals all of these problems and ideas are are inside
The raccoons tails
Tell the tale of the raccoon and the tale about the raccoons yeah
Explain this a little better
Will a
The trouble all started
Would you be the meaning of saw in 1911 with his guy
Is a scientist working at the
National museum in DC
See this by the way is blunting chemo
What is the hours for the Wildlife police
Spoke to my interpreter salary sign in
One day Miller was just hanging out in his office when a box turtle
Guadalupe
And he opened it up and found very much dead raccoon
Misshapen
Skin I like in a company's called This is a kristofer Helgen curator of mammals at the national museum of natural
Drunk History part of the Smithsonian
Douching actually has the same job that Miller had back in 1911
Anyway
This raccoon that Miller had in front of him looks a lot like the North American raccoon
But it was small
And
Different in
Quite subtle ways
And so
We left large Miller baptized Olympian raccoon existing species
Scientific name
Brazilian Miner
Guadalupe and Recker
Putting a name on it and recognizing it is a new species implied a deep history
Of
The presence of raccoons in Guadeloupe hundreds of thousands if not millions of years
Have it over these Millennia these raccoons have evolved into their own distinct species
Found nowhere else
So is that
When do the Guadalupe is begin to love raccoons when they realize they had their own
No one and only yeah but it took awhile to catch on I mean
This discovery was with initially only being talked about in these
Arcane academic scientific journals
It's not like this discovery was on the width on the front page of the guadalupian x or anyting
But then in the 1980s
Conservation really came into its own
Scientist started worrying about us
How about species disappearing from the planet
Any particular
I started worrying about
This raccoon these raccoons and I were being recognized as
Potentially endanger
F****** their only on these islands there
Probably aren't that many of them
Like we got a
Hectic
Sza
Sol de Guadeloupe is an overseas French Department France
Decided to do just that
February 17th 1989 legislation was created to
Detective raccoon
Shortly after the passage of this law Guadalupe open
Pittsburgh National Park
And the raccoon became the mascot
The symbol of the National Party
Animal sympathy
And as the mascot of this new National Park became that symbol of
Protected species
It was a celebrated
More like okay nice wheel of the raccoon
In more than just a symbol of the importance of
Protecting the natural environment of Guadalupe
Overtime the raccoon became in a way
A symbol of Guadalupe
Itself
Who is it that it's really that simple for people like
You can definitely see it as the Bold evil in the US
Aside from raccoons
You didn't really have
Hardly any other mammals that are native to these islands apart from bats
And so if the raccoon is the one furry Critter running around that everyone can point to and say this is something
Special
No this is not the same as a raccoon you'll find anywhere else
That is an exciting thing is a powerful thing and
A point of pride
I mean we're not
Suck it
Did not and I
Very good
Meet you how are you
Wasabi large now in Spanish
Age doesn't healthy
This is Nama Regis
You you were born here in Guadalupe
We yes
Yes indeed
She's an older woman may be in her 70s wearing this
Pink floral
That's her house was right on the highway with
Westfield in
And that
She says is a
Is where the raccoons would hang
I presume there was a whole bunch of them just like chilling in the area because oldest
Behind the house was
Sugarcane
They actually came and fed them to sugar
Choo sale or open place you only work out there I love seeing that I mean it was always sometimes
Pleasure in
Time in like seeing those raccoons out there to put cheetah
And at some point there was one that
We really became acquainted
At that point she scooter chair over and end picked up this black and white photo that was that was sitting on her dining room table
And inspect
When can I see the photo that you have here
Crystal Lovato photo
EBay Chevy donut bun
Basically what's on the picture is
Sophie
And I'm feeding her red
That I didn't to milk
Sophie was a pet raccoon
I had
Back in the late 8th
And she talked about Sophie
If she were her child
Baby baby make away green Fellowship
If you're making the gesture of like cradling of babies
Sophie
Can you come to us
Sophia Sophia
She would run around and leg
Everytime I called her name and everything like she would just like Come Running
Sophie I was really close to heaven like
When other people came to visit they could see that I had to
Is rare wild animal
With me
Anyone playing
She got she got really quiet
In grass the photo type
Sophie
You're holding it to your heart
SFO
When he died died I cried
Friday's name
Who's really really painful time for me
Ascacibar Appleton Appleton
To have something of your own
I almost got the sense that having this raccoon
As its national animal was away for Guadalupe to distinguish itself from fridge
Guadalupe is always been pushing against friends trying to declare some sort of
A cultural or national Independence
In fact just a couple years before this
This law was passed
A group called The
Guadalupe
This group that was fighting for independence from France
Look up a section of Guadeloupe airport studio in the government own TV station
Even a Chanel fashion perfume store
In central Paris
Windows and doors
Racks of hi-fi
Clothing
And it fell to me
Like in some small way
The raccoon had become a way for the guadalupian
Dulce de France
This is an hour
Not your
And because of that it also became a point of
Tension between France
Guadalupe
Yeah what are you waiting for
The morning after I met up with na
I went to the police station
Good to see you
To talk to these police officers
Do you mind saying your name for me
Read David David attorney Anthony Johnson
Explain government
As well as a couple others
All of them but one were white and French they were stationed here in Guadalupe
And they they took us up into this sort of war room which was that
The second story of the
This Bungalow type building out in the middle of the junk
New China Buffet
Genius
Everybody was sitting around this
Makeshift boardroom table
And
Okay pretty quick after the meeting started they've been booted up this PowerPoint
How to get a PowerPoint up with a picture of a raccoon
Display.
This image
Of a raccoon
Crouch down in this chicken wire cage what is going on here
Well they're planning a raid to liberate this raccoon
In fact they had the location where it was being held mapped out with
With entry points designated
At the even had the license plate number of the man believed to be holding the raccoon and when why exactly doing this
Will because as Anthony grow yo the the leader of this whole operation
Ming tombs
Espressi for the law passed in France back in 1989 declaring the Raccoon as a
Protected species
It specifically outline
Killing raccoons transporting raccoons
And even
Portability
Having raccoons
For pleasure
You Can't Raise A Raccoon as your own
Chick-fil-A peekadoodle
But you friends with the losses
They can't be held
And as a police officer in here I'm speaking as a police officer
I have to be here between 4th July
.
No question
Zast
And so
What's the breathing was over
They headed outside strap their pistols to their belts through the rest of the gear in the back of his head
SUVs
Intercom
Everyone is growing out where in three vehicles and 20 minutes later
We arrived
At the top of this hill peering down into this
Lush
Dense
Jungle
Driveway
We get halfway down the hill
And I
I'm here
Clearing we spot this man
He doesn't see us
Guy in a red shirt with a
Camouflage hat on
He's got his hand behind his back
The cops tell us it's too dangerous you guys can't go any further
Sally and I ducked behind some trees
And then Simone and Anthony
Wearing wireless microphone
Rush into the clearing
To confront
Set up a little bit
Lee Williams
Ask him if he knew about the law
Study did the guac Escondido
Even though I was like 30 yards away I could see that the guy just see
Confused
Pretty harmless
All good here
He's cooperating
Right away
Wait key told them where the raccoon was
There is in this chicken wire cage behind this giant tree
Cute little guy
This rough-looking raccoon
Nicolette toolbox
Wire cutters raccoon and grabbing The Wirecutter like it. It was play time or dinner time
Cut open the cage reached into it these thick leather gloves
MMA grab it by the neck and
Threw it into this
Kind of dog
Jerry Orbach
And
Commission is
Cycle Gear
Scenery can get
I got to see this whole thing sounds a little
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
This summer
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents
Aunts and uncles teachers were looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments
Brilliant
Basically I want to hear about this
It just means you lean back and say
Well
How do they do that
Maybe it was the moment that our kids you've been reading to 4 months
Started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of their musical score
Or maybe the kids in math
Music in the margin of their geometry
We're interested in the
Specific moments where
A kid does something super smart
It doesn't have anything to do with the test
If you have a story please share it with us
Go to radiolab.org
Flash brilliance
And record a short audio message
Again that's radiolab.org
Flash Brewing
Thank you so much
I know
For this feature
Releasing a pet no greed
But we're going to go
Later that morning we went on the 2nd
What are we expecting from
Furnace
Scenario in the seriousness
Clicked into place
Korea difference
Setting
We walked into this Courtyard surrounded by maybe 10 houses many of them made of sheet metal and do we know where the rack
A queen is supposed to be
I daren't
Chipotle lettuce
Pile of trash thrown in this enormous white
Cage there inside was it
Golden looking raccoon the amazing pool.
Pablo on pookie
The dirt how is his all-round to Winter
See who is really in charge
But before the officers could do anything
Free IT Crowd started
No no no woman has just arrived
Basically what's going on
Three or four people showed up head started poking out of Windows
And Sally overheard one of them saying
Someone snitched
That there was a raccoon in the air
And I suddenly realized it when I
All of the officers were very on it
Going to live
Why can't we just just take the raccoon
For safety reasons
Don't want to
Sit here to
And
We got out of it
Tell me what was going on in that second situation cuz I have a lot of it was over my head
I mean he's really understanding the context of the setting
I mean
This is not just a police I mean it's
Why police
Horses
Coming into and overwhelmingly black and poor neighborhood
That has a lot of
Pino significance
Discount
Highway in fact
When I was talking to Nana about this the night before
I know know know she said that if police officers had ever come to try to take Sophie
I mean they would have had to
Take me in as well
I would have taken my my husband's gone and I would have
You know I would have shot
When we come back from break the tail thickens
We'll be right back
This is Timothy franczyk calling from Stillwater Minnesota
Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of
Science and Technology
In the modern world more information about Sloan @www.
Loan
. org
This is Radiolab and we're back with reporter Simon Adler
The story of the
Guadalupian raccoon witch
As we just heard for the people of Guadalupe
Is both the point of pride
We are in the back room
Explorer of the museum have to go to the Smithsonian Museum of Natural History
Here in the US
With mammalogist Christopher help where we are now is What's called the type
Collection the world's largest
Library essentially of
Dead mammals
I have to say for such a grand play Fitz it's a little visually underwhelming basically just a bunch of locks White
But that said
The behind-the-scenes area
Where are the real Treasures are store
Can we take a quick detour
So I can explain what he means by that
Okay so scientist
Taxonomists their job is to name and differentiate species writing so how did they do that well
Let's let's talk about sharks
Because sharks are kind of cool animals Brighton
Imagine there's a shark species it's swimming around its having a great time and
At some point
Half of the sharks in this shark population decide to leave
To go somewhere else
I don't know they go to deeper waters or to a different ocean
Get cut off from the their previous shark family they don't see him for a long time and over thousands
Or maybe a million years they actually start evolving on their own as third of a new a new type of shark
Become different enough that they've become a new species
That's what the scientists come in and try to figure out
How do they make a determination basically it's a comparison game
They compare him to the old trucks do they look
The same are there
Dorsal fins taller or shorter
They look at how they how they behave in the water how they move through the world is that different
Now it is all even just do genetic
If they decide it is a new species of shark
At that point they do this sort of wacky thing that I had no idea about what they've decided that this
The shark is a new species scientist will go and kill one of the
They will stuff it
Put it in a box
And then they will store it in a locked cabinet in a natural history museum
Because
Ever After
For hundreds of years
That specimen becomes
Kind of a gold standard
The definition
Of that species
There's a difference
Key
Four types another
Every kind of
Moth or might
Smallest mammal in Ivory Oak
Free
Every kind of zebra somewhere in the world
There is a museum cabinet
We're locked down there is a
Physical specimen of that organism
That's so it's like it literally is like the Natural Museum history of the world are like the library the card
Life life
In the room that are that Helgen took me into
I'm in the sixth floor of the
Smithsonian
Cabinet upper cabinet after cabinet upper cabinet
Filled with these type specimen
Including the Guadeloupe raccoon
Type specimen
Be very specimen Miller inspected back in 1911
So here we go
Pelican bend down and open this one particular cap
I'm pulling out of
Big metal drawer
And inside
This is it right here
Here it is right in front of you
This sort of Ratty looking taxidermied raccoon
Is maybe not the most pretty
The ears are a little bit broken and bitten off
Some of the stuffing was coming out of the belly butt
That's probably how it arrived Helgen foresaw this raccoon back in 2000
One of the first things he did was
Start it over looked at it in this small maybe like a 18in long like that that just like Miller had reported
But then he popped open this little white box that had the skull
And
Take a look what do you see here
Keep Collective fine white lines
Crisscrossing the dough
These are open sutures
Which show that this girl still growing
In other words
It's not an adult
Who's the Helgen with a big D
Deal
Because ever since being a kid he was suspicious of the guadalupian
It didn't it didn't add up to
I just had a suspicion of Anneliese Tribune raccoon didn't make sense
He said if you look at islands that usually don't have just one native mammal species walking around Guadalupe
I'm going to put it on this tray the fact that this thing was a kid
It meant that there was nothing special at least
About its size
End
No by the time I I laid my hands on this one and looked at the
The skin and skull I'd seen
So many raccoons in museum collections at 9 to their skulls and teeth really well
So when I saw this
And one of the first things I noticed this
There's just nothing that looked any different to me from the common raccoon in the North American raccoon and soap Haugen decided to do
Some genetic work
She compared the DNA of these guadalupian raccoons against North America
Did the math we made the comparisons and
Are clear answer came
Not only are these
Not very different they are just simply North American right now
You mean Guadalupe in raccoons are the same ones that come in and and torment my garbage cans
Common
Literally garden-variety raccoon that we have in our own backyard scientists and conservationists
It is a real turnabout you know it goes from being distinct special endemic
McKenna found nowhere else
To just the opposite
Invasive
Sewing Helgen started publishing papers on the Raccoon in 2002
Conservationist
Worksite because raccoons
They can have real impacts they will do things like eat
Sea turtles
Bird's nest
Bird eggs including of some that are potentially endangered
Today they weren't they were hurting actual endangered
Yeah it's so now that now that they have
Proof now that they are certain that this raccoon doesn't belong here
Then they feel finally we're going to be able to go out and start doing something about this
Protect the actually special one
Get rid of this one sort of faker
But
Putting conservation aside
What you've got is is this
Native to the island national icon
Animal
That has suddenly become
An interloper
Brought there within the last
Got 200 years
Probably
Just on a boat
Will giving everything that you've told us about the colonial history
How did the Guadalupe Ian's react to this
Well well we went down in 2004 Pelican and his mentor
To Guadalupe
And
We talked to some people associated with the zoo and with the government management of the park
And it was just a very brief conversation
She made sure that they had heard the news
Why is this
Raccoon that's found only in your country
It's not
What you thought it was and it doesn't belong here
And
I remember that
The message that came back to us was
Essentially thank you very much
But
We're going to we're going to hold on to a raccoon
Yep meaning according to Blanding chemo communication campaign
Held on to make sure the population knew that there was a change inside of the government never really told
And when someone did say something like Gerard Berry
Long-time conservation
Music.
I was interviewed by a reporter and I told him what I knew for
And everyone was just saying you know Off With His Head
Head some of my friends were like how can you possibly say this you should not
Have sended
This is this bad
And soap for over a decade now
Nothing is changed
The laws haven't been amended
And
Because the government
Cut this so hush-hush
Many people on these islands
Still don't know the truth
My understanding of the story is
For many many years
There is this
In fact I
Guadalupe accidentally broke
The news
Tanakh
Recently it was discovered that no in fact
It's it's the same species that lives in the United States
Is that
The change your feelings about Sophie or about the the guadalupian raccoon in general
Marshall University
African find it in the United States
Is it possible that maybe it was
Brought to the United States
The scientists say that it was brought here
From the United States
Watch Yokai Yokai Watch
It is kind of sad for me to know that it's not in that me to Guadalupe I mean
I wish
It would have been so
To be honest
And then
I had to even less enviable task
I'm informing not
That just this past
Bu past
Dysregulation
We recognize that we cannot act on all the time basically
A black list of invasive species
What's negative impacts concerned or european
Union
The thing is of particularly in Germany the raccoon is terribly invasive
Directions to actually been called Nazi raccoons as they
Spread from Germany throughout the contest
And so
The raccoon made the list
And that means that
That member states like France and us
Very likely overseas agencies like Guadalupe
Will have to start managing
Or even
Erratic
From the folks I've spoken with
There's a good possibility that in the next year
The raccoon is going to change from being a protected species
To being a species that can be hunted
Trapped
And killed
Steven Jesse Boykins best computer chassis
No no no I hope I
Opatija Tibet
Michelle Murphy Malaysia
It kills me some Method Man kills me
The stop that
You know
People could start hunting raccoons like
We have to protect the
No no no no no no no
It's not a specific specie
Yeah okay
But
I just don't care
Angelique Charlotte
Owner of the Guadalupe
You don't care I don't care if it's just the raccoon
But it's kind of a name
Crafter isn't it a kind of trick
That's responsible of the person saying it was another specie
People making era he didn't do anything
You must respect her
The animal you know of
Even Sully Louis
The watermelon Farmers from the beginning of the story
Said
At the end of the day if let's say
They say okay as of this date the raccoons are no longer whatever I don't see myself taking a rifle running today
The feeling just lying in wait
Play shoot them no
It's just that we have a oshun
Type of Wildlife
No no snake nothing so it all
Is
The bigger ones bf1
So people adopted it as a national animal
That's it
It's one of those if you can't be with the one you love
Love the One You're With texted
Have a good one
So
As a pragmatic person
I know it's anybody's fishing today I know it
But I know also I think he's cute
And I think I like it
So
What is the best balance to find
You see I don't know
An interesting that
We need a miracle of the bald eagle
A kind of Richard bird that steals other people's Nest Anderson generally of vulgar animal
Actually but
We never think of it that way
Because we've given it Majesty
Let me give it yo its Talons there you see you both
Peace and War
It has been
We have dressed it in America
Every time a nation chooses
To identify with some wild thing it mostly really about
People identify
Now.
The animal
I totally agree but I see like this like there's that you have this fact right there is a fact.
That the raccoons didn't show up a million years ago or whatever
It was probably more like to hunt
Your stats
Most
Probably a fact
But then there's the stuff on top of that which is like
Are they not
Troll are they invasive
Do they belong here though still feel like fax those who like judgment so can like who gets to make those
The scientist
I don't know I certainly didn't realize the extent that this was a deep-seated cultural battle in which I was entering
Again Christopher Helga it's just the same information you know different responses and
I think the one of the deep questions of that
Of this story lives in that
Which is like
You you came to a scientific truth
In
The question becomes should that scientific
Truth
Win the day
I mean
As a scientist you know I would say yes
There is a conservation biologist I would say yes it's important to shows us that
Taxonomy really matters this animal didn't belong and
Really perhaps it should be
Remote from the aisle
But
At the same time
It's really a question for Guadalupe
This is our Island
These are there animals running around on it and
I can be very challenging for
Scientists like myself
Come to terms
But
That's how the world works
One more thought before we before we go alright
Before Helgen officially sang
Or dethroned
Guadalupian raccoon
There's actually another guy with a similar
Hunch
This Parisian mammalogist named ijm
Pons
I did one of those papers he wrote that
Even if it can be proven
That the guadalupian raccoon is no different from the Northam
Raccoon
Did the best answer might not be its reclassification
Or eradication
But it's dead
Is isolate
He wrote that it's quote
Insular distribution prevents Gene exchange with the mainland and is likely to Warrant different select
The pressures that should favor short-term genetic differentiation that may lead to a long-term speciation
Process we was that mean meaning if they were able to keep these North American raccoons on Guadalupe
Isolated long enough
Maybe someday
They could be reclassified yet again
This time
Ezreal
Guadalupe Inn
What's your response to that pawns said that but
And I like it
But
I'd say going to be waiting a long time
That's going to take over
Do you want to give super super things to Sally stand ye who was our translator and got Simon everywhere he needed to go
And make sure that it all worked out
Andrew Ali Pannell here in New York who helped us make sense of the holding before we left so so
You are huge that they are very manual
David Xavier Albert Lawrence Baptist Alamo
Ann Florian
Kirchner a jabroni beating meal
And most especially
Thanks to Simon Adler who reported in produce the whole story
Real quick before we go about what cuz he know how we were arguing about whether the raccoon is a good
Featuring Immortal creature and I was looking for ammunition on the internet to find September
It's been a Blog called the truth about raccoons
Andesitic contains a paragraph
I wish I'm pretty sure is not true
Pecos and I quote raccoons are one of the only land mammals who can also walk on the bottom of river
Dad's holding their breath for up to an hour
They eat both live prey and carrion be consumed after
20 lb of raw meat at a time then go without food for a week
Their skeletal structure is found in no other animal
And that combined with their ferocity and complete lack of moral fiber
Make them perhaps
Are most dangerous
Anime
I rest my case
That was no chick stuff to propagate
Message run hi my name is Callie singing
I'm summoning the staff credits right now
Radiolab
Killing kisses art director sound design
CERN Willard senior editor
Play New York their senior producer our staff includes Simon Adler
Jennifer ehle the devil
Not guilty
Robert Goulet Annie McEwen
Laughing their beliefs O'Donnell Aryan Latin Molly Webster
Without some crazy hunt
Valentina baldini
Seaway bank and Katie Ferguson
But that picture is Michelle Harris
All right that's it thank you
And this message