Are you awake
Listening to Radiolab
Radiolab WNYC
And NPR
Peter I'm Simon Simon how are you I'm doing well and yourself
Okay who's who
Peter is a DJ Peter Rosenberg from Hot 97 Simon Adler the journalist rpal Andrew Marantz from the New York
Worker is also in the room and Robert and I are in the back
Goodwill
We have all gathered here today to
To talk about the wonderful world of
Professional wrestling my favorite world
So yes we're going to talk about freshman wrestling for the first half
The show we realize it's a lot of you out there listening right now for like
Seriously eyes there people like
35 years old you love wrestling I get this lot if I'm tweeting about a lot I get two weeks ago
You know it's fake right
It's like well do I write you that when you tweet about your favorite movie
It's Entertainment
The awesome thing about wrestling is
Is that there are these random things that are a little bit real
And sometimes those moments realistic and
They can change everything now if you're like me and you grew up in the 80s
Might remember wrestling is like you know Hulk Hogan versus Andre the Giant
Epic
Matchups are kind of great but also sort of ridiculous
Cartoonish
According to Peter Rosenberg
There was a moment where wrestling started to sort of Tinker
With reality in a much more nuanced
And
Fascinating what you could argue
That pro wrestling became a real estate Association of the Baroque movement of the 16th
CenturyLink postmodern
I know people that would
You're going to meet him
I'm Jared I'm Robert
Is his Radiolab Ed
According to Peter this
Whole thing's
This whole thing
Goes back to this moment called the Montreal screwjob the Montreal screwjob was
Above anything else that ever happened there that will ever probably ever happen again because it was
Order reality transpiring right there in the
I mean it was real life just came in for whole
In the fiction
That guy just heard is David Shoemaker I write about professional wrestling for Grantland and the guy you're about to hear is journalist
Simon Adler
He will take the story for
Okay so the moment in question really centers around this one guy name
Brett Bret The Hitman
Bret Hart is seen by many to be the greatest in-ring performer of all time
She was one of the good guys the best there is the best there was
In the business they call him a Babyface
Is that what you call the good guys
A good guy in wrestling as a baby
He was my favorite wrestlers a kid I didn't understand why at the time but now I do
It's because he did everything so well
And in that era
The mid-to-late eighties when I fell in love with him
So many guys would miss big and Hawking in a little bit clumsy
But Brett did the kind of work that you could show to someone who's
Who's never watch wrestling
I think they could see the art
And I think they could see how it's
It's like ballet
Or a million other art forms
What do you mean Zin
You can kind of see this when you watch old Bret Hart matches on YouTube
Gliding through the air
Bouncing off the mat off the ropes keep tell stories brilliantly
Within the way he
Executes a match the wrestling is scripted but there's a lot of improv going on there the set beads
She knew how to take those moments in
In that Improv
Make you
Think so shoot he's about to lose and then
He was a natural-born wrestler
You know that his father was up with the legendary wrestler of his brother Owen
Legendary wrestler
He comes from
This Canadian wrestling royalty me is a
The kid growing up by
Have the ability to watch the weather
Fortune watch these
Very dressing Styles and techniques
That Bret Hart in an interview in 2000 on fresh air and he says it's some of his earliest memories as a kid
These massive
Dude showing up to his house and hanging out in his basement with his dad
Who is teaching them how to be wrestlers
He would pull on these old Bowie tights
And that he would
Wrestle with these guys
He would literally
Women wrestling holds these submission wrestling hold
Obsession and
Torture these big huge football player
Hours and they wouldn't scream
Literally this hype
It screams of terrifying I'll be upstairs in the room above it and as I got older I would go down and actually Venture into the room and sit on the bench
And watch
He would sometimes these wrestlers would run out
When my dad finally let them go that actually run out
Tear out of the
Out the doorway in out the
Outside sometimes in the snow and run out with Ann in their bare feet and you and even see them again I mean there's a legendary so many legendary stories about
The Hart family but you
You know my favorite among many is
The bear that lived in their backyard during Summers
Because at the time
Wrestling a bear was a thing that would actually happen from time to time no really
And
Brett tells a story in his
Is book
About you're just sitting there and letting the Bear lick his toes
Something like this is this is a life that they that he lived and he was
He was so in so ingrained in him
In the early 80s Brett was working for his dad's company
And well that's going on in Canada there's this guy Vince McMahon
Back in the US who is building kind of Des wrestling Empire
It basically he's buying up all of these small promoters
Acrostic
Country and eventually goes up into Canada
Advise out Brett's dad's company I bought it 1984
They paid him a certain amount of money to stop running
Can I go out of business
And then they took on
Is better wrestlers
At the time which
Christmas elf
Couple brother-in-law's
Shortly thereafter
The WWF
Tums
Under Fire
Hulk Hogan Another World Wrestling Federation stars of taking the offensive against accusations that many have been still
Monster mentality led to widespread
Steroid abuse in the World Wrestling Federation so there's a
Steroid crisis Vince
Have to deal with all of this litigation and he kind of needs to Rebrand
His organization he needs a new good guy
A new Champion a new baby face
And
Books to read for that
For a couple of weeks
According to David Shoemake one
Is that he's a traditionalist
Sort of a throwback to an earlier time
You got that big so when you see him you don't think
Sterilite. Definitely have road rage
And so he saw that and Bret Hart
During the 90s
Vince makes Brett a really big star
The new face of the company I mean he was on The Simpsons
He was a really really big stock you know they're people who criticize Brett for saying he wasn't that fun or took himself too seriously
But he was a serious worker he took wrestling very seriously myself really fighting hard to
Actually surviving come out of it can actually come out of the wrestling profession someday soon
A wrestling tragedy
Which is what so many of them turn out
Okay so fast forward to night
95-99
6 at the time a major rivalry was starting between the WWF Vince McMahon
And the WC.
Which was Ted Turner's
What company head-turner multi-millionaire and one of his big tactics is I'm just going to start buying all of
All the wrestlers
From the WWF
From Vince McMahon's organization so he's offering them
More money use offer
Bring them longer contracts music
It's like flooding it with money to steal all the stars from WWF and then in late 1996
Brett got an offer
Turn it really went in for the kill
From WCW that was huge
2.8 million dollars
We have to show some common sense me on first or UPS in this right for your family
But I mean how much money do you need sometime
I found myself torn between trying to do the right thing for my family and at the same time
Show my loyalty
That the clip of Brett talking in a documentary that was being filmed at the time
Call wrestling with shadows which is fantastic filmmaker Paul J was nice enough to let us play some
Connecticut
Brett gets this offer
He's got kind of this
Terrible decisions
Because
Vince gave him a lot you know you really gave him his life and initially Beretta side there's no way
I'm going to leave
Not like my relationship with
With Vince McMahon was always sort of like a father
And I sort of Saw myself if I left
It would have been a little bit like leaving my dad
Especially when the chips are down
He really did see
Vince as a father
Sabrett goes to Vincent
Basically says convince me to stay it went back and forth conversation about him signing a long-term deal at 1
Your deal with WWF
Not for as much money but for guarantee
Security
Vince
Said
I can't afford to pay you that
Stock events
In the documentary Brett and his wife there sitting at the kitchen table
Received
Because nobody wants Bret Hart more than
NYC letting you go
Compete with turn
Turner's hell-bent on trying to put them out of business
I got to think about everything
Color
Shut this off now for a little while
Ultimately
It became clear that Brett would have to go
Take the money
I can't help it feel really
And disappointed that dumb
Did I left this company
So this really gets to the heart of
Once
Brett decides he's going to
They have to figure out how
How
Are they going to make
This is really the pivotal question
Behind all of this
Get yo it's a very very delicate situation
That's Vince Russo and this was sort of his problem to solve because he work for Vincent
And you could say I was his right-hand man because I was writing the show
She was part of the team that scripted who would win who would lose
How would happen you know I mean I was literally putting the show on paper
Oh yeah once a week
Weight-wise it's a hard question I mean can you just pick up and leave because he's the champion
He has the belt
The physical belt the giant golden black belt buckle thing
And that belt is the symbol of the company
And everybody in it that everybody working behind the scenes everybody was trying to support their family
That belt was a representation of
All that the worst thing that can happen is your Champion walking away with the belt to the new company
Holding up the championship from The Old Company
Where they can just defile it
If they wanted to
That was not an option for Vince McMahon
This is an imperfect comparison but the closest thing I come up to in my mind
Is it would be like LeBron James
Quitting
His contract with Nike
And then showing up
In Adidas commercial
And taking a piss
Into a pair of Nike
So you know Vince at the end of the day he just had to get that belt off of bread
So their initial thought their first plan
Was probably the simplest.
There was a match coming up this big event a Pay-Per-View event
In Montreal
Bread being the champion of the company
He just lose to the number two guy
Shawn Michaels
Vince
Love Sean
I mean really thought Sean was a Megastar what you was right about
Clearly Sean was next in line
So they pitched this idea of breath
And Brett was like I can do that
For 1
Keeping Sean's an idiot
Shut this Primadonna personality
He's better than everyone else
There's something very arrogant and obnoxious the bottom
Because he was he was a showman he would hump
The ring
Just like do ridiculous things in like to Bret Shawn with the Triumph of
Style over substance
Also
You're asking bread
The wrap up his career in the WWE
With a loss in Montreal
In Canada
Where he is a national hero
Describe the events I just assumed
Blow my brains out
The same
What you're asking
To do from
Character standpoint that's what I would
Bret the Hitman Hart with bullets
Makeup
The whole thing's
Day of the match
Still nothing has been decided as to how the match is going to end
Brett is backstage in
Eventually he goes to Vince
Have a conversation
The documentary crew filming all of this
And at this point then says no I don't want any cameras in here get those out of here
Red actually end up wearing a wire
To document the conversation that's about to happen
I never ever want to leave here with any kind of bad feeling good this week has been a bad week for me I feel kind of betrayed a little bit
Well I do to a little bit and again while we're talking about really is Ted Turner between you and me
Appreciative I will always pay for everything you've done I didn't want to leave
It all has no other choice but to go the way this whole thing is been depicted it's really hard for me that you're
Come up short this weekend
What would you want to do today then I'm up and I think what I'd like to do is get through today I think tomorrow I should just
When do mice
Sabrett suggest that the send
Lynda
Usually what that means something called Ashmont
Typically in a small the ring is just flooded with a bunch of wrestlers and Chaos ensues
The referee usually is thrown out of the ring and ends in some sort of draw
Brett would that appear on Monday Night Raw the next day
Introverted
That is what he planned on doing
So that way you could turn over the belt but not lose exactly
Eventually events
Okay fine
Coming up
It all goes wrong
Radiolab will continue in a moment
This is Jim Donahue from Fort Worth Texas
Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation enhancing public understanding of science
Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloan
Www.
Sloan. Org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
We're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments
Brilliance
Basically I want to hear about this
Times when a kid you know did something
It just means you lean back and say
Wow
How did they do that
Maybe it was the moment that I
Kids started reading back
To you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lesson
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of their musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed are ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the specific moments where a kid does something super smart
But it doesn't have anything to do with the test
If you have a story
T-shirt
Go to radiolab.org
Brilliance
Record a short Audiomack
Again that's radiolab.org / brilliance
Thank you so much
This is Radiolab with skip back to Simon Adler story of the moment that changed wrestling forever
Viola
So you're Peter Rosenberg
Hot 97
As well eat the first
Pick up the action
Weather
Olympic match
What we've all been waiting
Okay. So Survivor Series 1997 Montreal
Who is the drama
So around 9:20 p.m. 20,000 people in the stand countless television screens across the country
Shawn Michaels
And he comes out singing
Sing his own theme song
I think I'm cute I know I'm sexy
Singing karaoke style if re-recorded
That's an approach
He's got his hair in a ponytail he's wearing his trademark black
Spandex pants with hearts all over them like
He is the manifestation of everything
Set breakfast
And then outcomes Bret Hart
Waving
The Canadian flag
Can you walk
Into the ring
Get the intake off a championship belt has it to the rap
And before the match
Even officially begin
Sean flies at bread and just started wailing
Sean and Brett they're going at each other with a sort of like real for real
Pretty quick there outside the
Ring picks up
Sean checks him over the sea
Security railings
Then there's this
Read Pick Sean up to that Sean's legs are straight up in the air and then Brett
Just slam them on his back
In all of this is scripted
Everything I know about it is like
They're following the The Narrative art but like they know okay we're going to fight
Outside the ring for a while and then
XYZ will happen
And So eventually
Retro Sean back into the ring and then you get
Make appointment the mattress feels very early in the match
Where Brett
Climbs onto the turnbuckle
Which is the corner post of the Ring
Get up on top of that catapults himself off the turnbuckle
Through the air
Chords
Shawn Michaels
Super dramatic is kind of floating in the air there for a moment
And then what Sean does ripe
Before bread is about to come and hit him he pulls the referee
In between bread
And Sean
A human shield
Hit the referee the referee hit Sean and all three men
Are lying
On the map
Is that a disqualification
Here we are right this could this could be the moment
But no
Before the referee can get up
Sean
Whatever the brat
And then
Shawn puts rat in the Sharpshooter
Which is Brett's signature finishing move
Basically xian pretzels up Brett's legs and sit and within seconds
The bell rings
Sean slides out of the rain grab the belt
Runs to the back takes off
Things work a certain way in wrestling match
Is right like
No one gets the first pick in the second match starts
And no one put someone in submission hold and they instantly submit a special agent did not appear like the time the mattress opposed
The crowd is kind of
Shocked
It's strangely quiet
And
There's just one moment where the camera Zooms in on Brett face while he's lying
Shut down
On the map looking up
And there is just as bizarre
Amazing looking
Confusion
Is an emotion that almost never exist in pro wrestling
There's a cartoon confusion of like everything's crazy in your arms are going like wild your eyeballs pop out of your head
The real confusion is one of the most compelling emotions of all
That's what you see on his face in its most
Pure form
Genuine confusion
And then a Brett gets up puts his arms on the Rope looks down sees Vince McMahon
And
Spits right in Vince's face
Event proceeds to get out of the ring
And basically destroy everything in
Because over the announcers table starts ripping it
He destroys the monitors
The headphones
Krowd
Eagles pretty nut
And maybe the moment
That truly
Made you go what is happy
Brett gets back into the ring
He takes his hand in the air
And draws with his finger
In the air as big as he can
W
See
Which is where he was going to be leaving
To go work w
See
W
It keeps doing
Walking across the ring the signal
W
See
WW2 the crowd
After the match
Brett head back into the locker room looking for bench
Wavy
Tells the camera to shut off
And then
To make a long story short
Pepsi clocks vintage
Noxzema
Now the WWF has a real proud
Vince has a black eye
And the fourth wall has just been torn down and they need to figure out
How or if they're going to build it back up
And dumb
The next day
This again with the head writer at the time Vince
We had a television taping right after that you know you have Roar on Monday you know you do you have paper
Review on Sunday you have Roar on Monday
They all had a little room to discuss their off
And Vince says that everybody in that
The first knee-jerk reaction is what we going to sweep this under the rug and not even talk about it I mean that that was almost
Just assumed because you have to understand there's this old principal in wrestling called Casey
And basically what this
Is is this loss
Of the wrestling god passed down
Since time eternal
That says
You don't talk about the fact
That it's fake
Everyone knows
That is scripted and that it's fake
But you damn well better not mention
Because everybody has a better time
When everyone is under the spell of it
And I was like wait a minute
Vince is walking around with a black eye
The boss has a black eye and one of the boys punch them in the face
Russo is saying I understand kayfabe but we have to address that we can't not acknowledged
And that doesn't have to be a problem
I can be an opportunity for
I mean it like I hate to say this but
Like it doesn't get any better than this Rousseau says this discussion got very
It was
Passion-filled
And
Indian
Nobody really knew what Vince McMahon was going to do
By the time Bret Hart steps Center Stage for his match up with Sean Monday mentally
Vince McMahon decide
I'm going to break with caffe
Now keep in mind
He's always been the owner of the organization but
Very few people actually knew that
Fans of professional wrestling
He was just in an ounce
That night
On his own TV show he comes out not as Vince McMahon the ringside announcer but
Is Vince McMahon
The owner of the company
Let's get right to the chase
7 days ago at the Survivor series
Did you or did you not
Screw
Bret Hart
Some would say
I screwed Bret Hart
Bret Hart
But definitely tell you
Ice
I'll look at it from a different standpoint
I'll look at it
From the standpoint of
The referee did not screw Bret Hart
Shawn Michael certainly did not screw Bret Hart
Nor did Vince McMahon
I truly believe that Bret Hart
Screwed
Bret Hart
You can look in the mirror
And know that
I'm sure in some parts of country right now there's a collective groan that you orchestrated
The situation
And the fact that people are not going to understand
What you mean by Bret Hart
Screwed Bret Hart so
What do you mean by that
There's a time-honored tradition
In the wrestling
Someone is
Leaving
They show the right amount of
Respect
To the WWF superstars in this case
Who helped make you
That's super
You show the proper respect to the organization
Help you
Become
Who you are today
Time-honored tradition
And Bret Hart
Didn't want to honor
Mapreduce
I know that's that was breast
Decision
Brett
Screwed
And
Everything changed from that point on
And according to Peter
After the Montreal screwjob and after this speech
The writers of the WWF
Started blurring the line on a different level
Vince McMahon the chairman of the WWE
He became mr. McMahon
The character the number one villain
In the company
There were no more ridiculous you know
Stupid unbelievable childish ignorant immature characters
Every character we had was basically
An extension of themselves
Cold Steve Austin was Steve Austin
1000 times magnified you know The Rock was Rocky made
My BF 100
X magnified and as a result that was the beginning
Of the biggest boom in the history of the wrestling business
As far as business goes this was
Huge for the WWF and Vince McMahon
They came roaring back in the ratings were they destroyed
Ted Turner in the WCW
The one
And if you ask Vince Russo
Tell why this approach this new aesthetic was so
Successful
He said simply
The truth
That was great TV
Plain and simple
The fans just want something true just tell the fans
What
Happen
But Peter says
Things one and it's way more complicated
That is not just about
You still have
These writers who are scripting the show and wrestlers who are getting that
And following it
So it's not like
It's now a true world
I think it's something more like
There are these tiny injections of Truth
Into this world
In really unexpected Moana
What that does
Is it put everyone on high alert all the time
For those milk
And when everyone is on high alert for this moment all the time
Every moment has the potential to be
True
Has the potential to have a little bit of an injection into it
And when you are watching for those injections
It completely changes how you are engaging
With the Arts
With the entertainment
And that creates an entirely new type of fan
What they call a smart fan
A smart Marcus Mark as they're known
People who love the
Wrestling business but really love the behind the scenes of the business
Smart bar
Here's where you can get a little lingo
The lingo part of wrestling is a huge huge part of it and a mark is someone
Who doesn't know that wrestling is fake
Or
Using other
Piece of jogging here that it is a war
Yes of work is anything that's not real okay as opposed to a shoot
Which is something that's real
Like the Montreal screwjob yes
Deschutes
By Def
In the ring
Oh shoot you never happened
But
Then there's something called of course I'll work shoot
Emmett something that does happen once that where you
Scripted to seem like a
It's totally unscripted
And it may even be real life they're injecting into it but it was plan
Rosedale all discuss that this is what would happen
And so watching wrestling becomes this game
Of hunting for the truth
According to David Schumer
Any truth but the authentic
Even if you know that it's fake
There's some point where the guys are really going at it in the ring
That you're just like
Well maybe
It's real just that right there
And that's
What makes wrestling so powerful
What's the NeverEnding search for the reality
Within.
The fact that we get to blend these things together I mean
Another example that just fantastic
In the early 2000s
The edge
Matt Hardy
And a girl named Lolita
Lita
And Matt Hardy
Were legitimately in love
Dating for years
Edge and Matt Hardy were legitimately best for
And then
Ended up with weed
Took his Best Friend's Girl
Something that unfortunately
Happens in life sometimes
Lego WWE
And it was turned into a storyline
Manifold over women since the beginning of time and we haven't got to see an epic battle over one right now I find
Credible
That you could
Go out into the rank and pretend
To beat the hell
Out of someone you want to beat the hell out
To know that you have to go out there
Work really hard against someone you legitimately hate
And also absolutely have to protect
How can we not find that fast again
That's awesome that incredipets like watching Fleetwood Mac Go on tour
Exactly
That's what I was going to say next
That's Andrew Marantz
The New Yorker and play all their songs cuz all their songs they all had these love quadrangles they all were married in
Left each other and wrote songs about I'm so pissed off at you because you left me for the guy to standing right there
And they go out on tour
And Lindsey Buckingham is standing right next to Stevie Nicks playing the song that he wrote
About you betrayed me I hate you so much
Crazy
It right after 9
Super fascinating
Yeah I just think there's a part of the
Human brain that wants
To be
Confused
Between those boundaries that wants to be
Slipping in between what's real what's fake to feel that confusion
I feel like that's why Jimmy Fallon was so successful on Saturday Night Live now because he was the greatest
Sketch comedian that because he broke
A lot and you eat you can't do that in wrestling cuz those moments are the best
You have to save them
You have to say it
When people acknowledge a moment
And you can tell they look around at the crowd and their knowledge in like this is
Or someone says one line
That everyone kind of knows like whoa
Well that's kind of real
Those moments are special
And you have to save them
Hey what's up
He's on the way I'll be leaving
Sargazo Usher awake
Well that's where the interesting thing is that after the Montreal screwjob
I'm a few weeks later Brett showed up on WCW television
And never really worked out for bread
In 1999
Just two years into his contract with WCW
During a match he got kicked in the head
And suffered a severe
And it was the beginning of the end
That same year
Ladies and gentlemen something has gone terribly wrong
Brett's brother
Owen Hart
Who was
Wrestling for the WWF
During one of his entrances
To the match
Entering from the ceiling
And
Something with the stunt went terribly wrong
And he
She fell
50 ft
Into the ring
And then he died
This is not a part of the show
This is real life
Owen Hart is being attended to right now by host
I went through
Right away I said I could
I don't think I can ever go bad
Bret Hart spoke with Terry Gross about a year after this incident single all these sort of contrived storylines of the
Maven wrestling
You know this guy's going to come in and going to do that
He's going to say this about you earlier
I just thought everything you can possibly imagine is so
Ethically meaningless when you relate to
To the the real life horror would happen
My brother
He would retire
Shortly after
You're saying that
So thank you to
Assignment
I would we decide his wrestling name was
Xiamen
Simon the growling gruyere
Seth Curry
Because he's from Wisconsin
So you have to be like a few
Cheese
And thank you also
The fresh air
For letting us are there
And thank you also DePaul J for allowing us
Play some clips from here
Documentary wrestling with shadows
Pancetta
Radiolab will continue in a moment
Here is Peter Rosenberg and I'm going to try to do my best to do this
Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world
VW. Sloan. Org
Radiolab is produced by WNYC and distributed by NPR hope that works later guys
We're back
Blue tell us who you are I am
Bruce burningham and where do you teach
Illinois State University this is Radiolab on I'm Robert
Joe Bruce
Hefei
Hey scholar language professor and i called him up because you disagree
Friendly one
We're having an argument here I said
That when you get the hip hop in the wrestling
Novels about you getting a sort of a moment
Contemporary MoMA
People are fascinated by authenticity
And then Jack my princess
I don't know maybe people always been interested in Oregon does it end
This is just comes with being human is nothing about now it's it just about us I mean that's that's
Latest new in the sense
That
This generation of which we belong
Has become very interested in these kind of question
But Bruce told me this preoccupation it's not really new in fact at least in book form
It goes
Back way longer than you.
Well before wrestling on before Fleetwood Mac at before Jimmy Fallon begin laughing at his own jokes
There was Miguel Cervantes his book
Don Quixote the first book really is
About authenticity from the from the get-go you open this book
Find me the right way the narrator says I'm going to tell you a story which I actually gathered from other office
A bunch of different
Historical document so I'm not really the author
He says things like while some books a the first
Adventure was this sin some statements that
Sweden from the start you have a very unreliable narrator to tell the story of a very unreliable
I completely Crazy Character Don Quixote
Who is dry
Which
Capricious
In constant sorrow
Choke Don Quixote believe
City has been set on Earth
To rescue widows
Princesses
Mtnb kindorf he's like a delusion
Cuddly deleuze right he is he's essentially a guy who's who's
Read too many Zane Grey novels and decides he needs to be a cowboy
You think herds of sheep are attacking Army she thinks windmills are Giants at the same time he has this savvy
Assistance Sancho Panza who seems to know what's really going on and they're constantly arguing about what's real and what's not and then
In chapter 8
Something really
Spring-trap
One day
Don Quixote and Sancho Panza
Traveling down the road at me see a carriage
With a woman in
Just an ordinary woman doing
Meet her husband
Donkey xote whoever for no reason at all
Decides that she is a woman in distress needs
To be rescued and he spies this man standing right next to the
Cheese is a basque
Guy sees this guy and he decides
That he's a he's an enemy who needs to be confronted and so they start fighting
And the best was waiting for the sword also raised and in mid-swing when both swords are in the air than areas
Gator stops and says
And I don't know where this goes from there
I've run out of material
You just rest stops near me
And this is what six
Steno something 1605
The book stop
Just stopping at the end of the well know so you turn the page and you're in a new chapter and now the narrator's just telling you how
Crazily enough he's out of business
Shopping
NEC this pile of old papers and books together in a basket of these rifling through it
Dom quixote de la Mancha
Apparently a real historical account in which the stupendous
Is concluded the problem was
He was an Arab
And so then he hires a local marisco who is a christianized more
To translate it for
I see you now got a guy
Who's writing a book from historical sources he's run out of one he's found another but now that one has to be translated and on
Happy that you frequently inserts commentary about the translation and we'll say stuff like
Well city of netty says this
But we all know that Arabs can't be trusted so
You don't take that for what that's worth
The meeting and I'm picking weight
This was written in 6
Pino
What do people make of a book that didn't seem to have any author I had author of him also, feel like where they
What time the book was a bestseller
It was huge lollipop
Apparently people found all these layers annies ambiguities a laugh
They gobbled rapidly leftists as hard as they could
This is Howard mancing Ristorante Skyler at Purdue was translated into English in 1612 in
Two French in 1614 into Italian and 1622 everybody with it
Including in the New World by the way how many copies of the first edition of Don Quixote
Worshipped
To The Colony
So the book is a worldwide bestseller maybe the first of the
Time in ten years later
10 years
Waiter Cervantes write
Sequel
Which kicks up this narrative weirdness to a completely new
In part 2/2
He introduces a new character named Samson Carrasco
He actually visits don't Quixote and son
Don't you tell them that
Part 1 exist
It's a bestseller
In the very early chapters of part 2 donkey healthiest would be like walking up the Huckleberry Finn to know by the way you living here in Hannibal
But you're now a famous boy
Everybody he meets knows who he is because they've read part 1
And now it gets even stranger because in real life
During that 10 years that it took Cervantes to write his second book of person who goes by the pseudonym of Alonso Fernando
Disable you neither
Published his own second part of Don Quixote before
Cervantes could get his own psyche
Wait so this is this is an unofficial
Part 2 today we recognize it as a sort of fanfiction or
Or somebody attempting to steal George Lucas's idea and come up with their own Star Wars
Installment so there's this unauthorized part 2
Floating around Miguel Cervantes he's very annoyed by it I'm assuming
In here
Official sequel to Don Quixote
There's this scene where
Donkey xote is that man in any overhears a character talking about his relationship with with
This
Supposed donquixote wait for this guy this guy
At Simon Adler deciding on the interview with me this guy
Existed in the
A Quixote number two
Is it character in that and is now appearing in the real
Tell Jennifer to Cervantes Cervantes steals him
If you steal my character I'll steal yours
Now you got the real donkey or that he's bumping into a character
Stolen from a fake
Book of Don Quixote so so why don't you decide to confront this
Images right up to the guy thing says
Unfortunate
The climax of that scene which is just wonderful is he
He
Forces this other character who has stolen from the unauthorized seek
To admit that the donkey xote he knows from the unauthorized sequel is not the real one
And that the one he's currently talking to is the real one
For the sake of what you owe to your being a gentleman
Please make a statement to the forces him to sign an affidavit
3 bus Sim
In-N-Out
But you got a story about a guy that then becomes a part 2
Dory
About the story about the guy including false guys inside the story about the
Guys from another book
So why even bother
If there's anything like this come before they know he's really sort of inventing this whole meta-narrative
Game that it is so Poppy
Meta-narrative what
What is
What up until that point most
Stories are
Simply
They purport to be what they are I'm telling you a
But donkey xote
Pretends to be something other than what it is it really is the start of modernity
Our modern sense of the world
CU CHI with Chad Bennett this is like this is this is not
Waxed and waned this particular ear
Don Quixote has been read by different generations for different breeds
Bruce says he thinks the people who were reading the book original
Time of survivors they actually reveled in in the the multi levels of fiction
During the romantic. And and well into the early 20th century people were less interested in all these narrative layers
They were more just
Thrilled by the Romantic Don Quixote or the dreamer Don Quixote this generation of which we belong
Has become very interested in this
Terrain that Cervantes charted a long time ago
See it in the cinema of the late 90s kid movies like The Matrix and then later at a patient about inception
Exploring the concept of a dream
See it in Seinfeld
Who's going to be on TV the following
Is this comedian Jerry Seinfeld who's playing a character that happens to be called Jerry Seinfeld
Who's making a show
Within the show
Black octopus
Who's Jerry Seinfeld answer you have
Reality nest
3 *
But I guess I'm interested in this idea of why is
How is this happening again and why is it happy
But my sense of things is
That
Both of these moments are moments of intellectual crisis
Back in Cervantes time
Coming out of the Renaissance
You have all this new scientific knowledge
That is calling into question the foundation
That everybody was building their life
Suddenly the Earth is no longer the center of the universe
It's now just one planet among several orbiting the Sun
So you have people coming to terms with
A worldview that they can no longer sustain
An astronaut's now in the last hundred years
You have Darwinism you have relativity you have quantum physics
Any cognitive scientists are telling us that we have no free will because they cancel
Chart
The chemical reaction that happens milliseconds
Before we we think we decide to do something
All of these things tell us that the world that we think we see is not what it is
And I think that inspires people to then start asking these questions
If what I'm seeing is not real
What is
I who am I
An enticing to a great extended its
It's a reaction to a moment of intellectual crime
Wait but okay let's say that I like professional wrestling a lot
I don't know anything about any of the research you're telling me about why the hell do I like professional wrestling in why did I lie
Like it more when they started blurring these lines
Hard question
Well I would say
Humans
Are humans and one of the things that we do is
Is it as opposed to as far as we know what other animals on this planet do is
We are aware of our own contingency
Meaning we can imagine
Radically different possibilities we can imagine a world where we don't exist
Or maybe we only think we exist I can remember being a child's 4 and 5 years old
And
Going to a fabric store with my mother and there were two mirrors set against opposite walls and I was just fascinated
Standing in between them and watching the infinite regress
Go in each Direction
You know when I have not even started kindergarten yet so I think
I think humans have this
Fascination with infinite regress and with embeddedness and with the questions that it forces you to consider
Like weird is everything
Begin Again
Where does it all come from
Me the question at the heart of
Donkey xote realizing that he's a character in a novel is
Who stands above you
The author
Stands above you until that author has a kind of Godlike relationship to you
But that very question starts
To make you ask who stands above that author
And if you start asking that question it goes on forever in every direction
Thank you to Rupert Boyd for coming and playing the Spanish
Guitar for us
These are very short notice and to recorded books for giving us permission to use
George melies is wonderful
Read a book
He's really good
Okay
Well I guess we should go then we should go by goodbye
Writer for Grantland Bruce burningham editor of the Journal of the Cervantes Society of America
And these are the credits
Include ellenhorn Thorne wheeler and Howard
Sarah Lally Webster O'Donnell Dylan Keith Dunleavy and email Kelsey Padgett
Matt kielty area wac and lots of semester with help from Simon Adler David Asher Damiano marchetti
Kelly Prime and Danny Lewis
Special thanks to the legendary gem David Shoemaker that's me and Paul J the director of wrestling with shadows
But you should see
Thanks
Fight
And this message