Are you weightless
You're listening to Radiolab from WNYC
Richest are the beginning how did the series
I know the ancient history for you already but how did it come about what was the sort of spark for it I remember
Sing the word know just written down on the page
And immediately be like
Oh my God I have so much to say
About that word here this is Radiolab
Today we're going to be airing work from Radio maker Kaitlin Prest
Because we're going to play for you today sent all of us here on quite a journey Caitlin.
Is a fellow traveler she just released a show through the CBC called the Shadows apparently it involves puppets
You should definitely check it out but before that she was the host and creator of a podcast called the heart
Here's what happened about a year ago
But for five different
People on my staff
Seemingly all at once were like you've got to hear this series from the heart
It was made
Creamy tube now they're in me to you stop what you're doing
Listen to the series to four-part thing it's called no
I personally
I've always had a complicated relationship
With saying no
In any context
But especially within a sexual context and one of the people in our crew
Wanted to make she just said I want to make something
About like
No like just
No
That when I finally listened to the series
I was like
Damn
I've never heard anything like this
Like really and truly
And so what we're going to do
It's kind of construct for you the journey that we went on at soda starts with Caitlin
Work
So today we're going to play you excerpts from
First series that she produced for the heart
Then over the next few weeks
We're going to dive deeper into some of the issues that she raises in her series because like I said
When I heard it and we started talking about it internally it sent us on a whole thing
Series of conversations that went all over the place and we'll play you some of that in the next two episodes right now
What play you excerpts from Caitlin series end
Just as a warning
There are scenes in what you're about to hear that are
Sexual explicit
Very much so at times and
Strong language probably not the kind of thing that you want to listen to with kids
Anywhere nearby
Anyhow
We're going to start with an excerpt from the second episode of Caitlin series no for the heart
This episode she titled inheritance
Hello and welcome to this month's edition of audio smut
I'm in my twenties I left my tiny little town for the big city
I live in NYC now
Chinese slippers
I make an artsy feminist sex radio show
Sex positive feminism tells me that I was onto something back in my teens adopting the same ruthless
Sexual posturing the boys are encouraged to would allow me to wheel some of their power if we f*****
Without feelings we too could be free having slept Pride with cebert the double standard
That would force the world to recognize that women sexual pleasure is real
The only problem is that I hate casual sex
Make up for it I masturbate with abandon and tell the world about it
Switch low medium or high vibration pain
Become an expert at advocating for my own pleasure I know what I want
I feel entitled to it I really wanted to sleep over but just FYI I'm not
Tupac. Cool
After all these years I've mastered the art of saying no
Stretch yourself out from downward dog into play
No
I know now that what I'm looking for is love even though I know it's corny
Thunder
Not a big brown couch wrapped up in the arms by friend
Jay
Songs are really
Do my best not to like this more than a friendship with the appropriate a little
Yeah
Okay cool
Go get it
But of course I can't stop myself from wondering this friendship is the Friendship the right under your nose
That whole time
Kind of friendship
Been friends j48 years like my oldest
How did it go Jan I've always kept it in your pants
Masculine way to this perfect friendly intimacy we call each other babe and boo liebich about oral
Relationship dramas have extensive Gchat conversations into the night and always sign off with the word love spelled in full
If I hate my current relationship
And that's good night night love you with that being the case there are as I think there are like
Great great hookups that are just
One night stand so
I've always thought it was hot it looks a little bit like my cousin Robert I had a forbidden crush on when I was a kid
Boyfriend 4th of July
Play 1130
I want to come over for a snuggle party
Hey
What's happening
Put on some music and sit on the bed woman she's so cool and she kind of had this thing in common where
Arabella
Billy time in people and we're talking about how like she's not really used to making the move
The. She sort of create the conditions in which I move can be made
Why
Because
Looks like some weird power into
That like submissive role that I just don't think is really there
Are you serious
Really you're going to
I feel like I'm kind of nervous
Yeah
That's cute
Too quick
He says yeah but you keep going not reading me
I Don't Wanna Miss a Thing
Define whatever
Sorry I just have to pause the scene for a second
Give you some information
So what you're hearing right now if you hadn't already noticed
Is a reenactment
Hugo ya do it
Hey
This is an actor
The name is Tommy and then I'll be like hey like
Can you connect slow down a little bit
Curing yes
He was pretty like
Progressive
Yeah the making of the story I called the real Jay to verify what happened that night
I also asked him if he wanted to write and re-enact the whole story with me
But
Are you guys still friends
We started being friends again since I
Call them and ask him if he would do an interview about like you're going to hear more from the real Jay
Later
But what I need you to know right now in this moment is that what you're hearing isn't the real thing
I built this scene so that it sounds as close to the way that I remember it as possible will kiss again and
Kind of intense again
And then say it again
And then you get kind of pissed
At that moment
You say
Pine
Astera the overhead
Headlight
I look at the clock
Almost 1 a.m.
The air is tense
I feel like it's my fault
I know better than that
Go
But I don't
Frozen I can't move
He's back at the zipper of my jeans with my hand on a dick
If you have a wreck
This is
What if you just like
Go to the bathroom and
Just like
Come back
What
Cuz I'm we can just make out and be fine
Just do it come on
Touch it come on
Dude
What
On the outside act like everything's fine on the inside I give up
And the way that feels so familiar to me
I make myself, in front of him so he can make himself come
We can go back to having a nice night I feel defeated but the same
Sometime I'm getting off I'm really good at masturbating so it's not hard for it to feel good
Perfume moments I forget that I feel like s***
I'm sad when I leave
Angry until days afterwards July 5th
2013 I had the most vile experience
And then I'm so angry I can barely write about it my diary too angry to the big Scrabble
I'm angry at so many things
Performed for him ever form to play kaisa wanted him to be happy more than I wanted myself to be forgot about my
She forgot about me supposed to be my friend my defenses were down to f*** thought this was a dumb High School dude that college dude
I thought I was past this s*** I thought I'd practice avoiding this s*** f****** 27
True he didn't force me to do anything
But I'm on the last felt like I had no choice
Why
That on me
Where's that on him
I begin to wonder if having sex I don't want is something I've absorbed from Generations past
If it's something I've inherited from my foremothers
How do you say no that's rude or that's not
Bellator
Cuz my mom why are you saying know you're hurting the guy is feeling
Friend with someone who you're interested in if you say no are they going to just give up and walk away
And then you're going okay should I just go along with it so I don't lose that he could have been a great guy
Heart rate of a guy right balance that out but I think that is where the
But if you been just walks away
Another friend of ours I mean it's subtle because you know on the one hand you're having attention I mean
I was brought up as a female to
To want male attention you know that that was
A status symbol actually you know if you are
Attractive enough woman that you could
Get attention from man that was considered an important thing that was how you were maybe going to end up finding a husband and
Having children and doing that really conventional stuff so those ideas they don't defy come
I'm up all of a sudden you know you're you're surrounded by that grow your whole upbringing
When was the first time that you've had an experience where you felt like you were allowed to
Change gears
I was
In my late 40s and he stopped
And asked are you sure this is what you want
I had never ever ever been asked that before and I was like shocked I didn't
Speechless in responding to him because I never had been asked that before
At this point in my life I felt
Strongly that I was different for my foremothers My Generation would be different
I talk to people my age
I hear the same attitudes same feelings
He kept telling me that the reasons I was saying no we're stupid that was drunk and crying
A drunk crying girl generally wants to be consoled to some extent but not with sex
I told him he couldn't f****** and then his dick wasn't me you know and then I was like oh my God for having sex
I thought we talked about this
And even then the whole night was nice
That part was just sucked a how
Do I give him what he wants in a way that's not terrible for me but
Nike deal with
It's like your gut instinct will tell you what no I don't want that since they know and cute way and then say no to 4
And then there was a point where you just like
It's like I literally just gave up
Let's just let him have this now because I fought enough and like I don't want to make a scene I don't want to wake up anyone and like
My roommate sleeping and she's going to get me like I slept on the couch and like it was like his mental gymnastics that
You do to not tell yourself that you're not putting your needs first but that like all these people up matter
So much
Talk to my 20 year old cousin
She's almost a decade younger than me
Like my first boyfriend
I just wanted to please because I didn't know what I was doing
So
I was just going for it and trying stuff and leave
Not asking questions
And I've been getting it so I want that person to like me
I want this to be fun for that person
Not thinking about yourself and just be like I'm trying stuff
Makes me think of something that my best friend Laura said I was talking about being a people-pleaser
I like how
And you said that that's habitats how women survive I think women survived by
Being aware and reading social cues and
We know when someone's going to be angry we know when someone might lash out we know when someone's
The Frayed we know when somebody is sad we know when some of these
Happy ending and
We know when when we're safe and we know when we're not safe and
You know there's the element of using sex as a social currency to stay safe and
Using sex as a social currency to
Belong in
The group even if the group is just you and one other person
Start to wonder if this is how anyone who has historically been on the Shady Side of the power dynamic
Learn how to move through the world
How important it can be
To be liked
Someone who has your fate in their hands
Sometime after the Jay night I discovered something
He brought me answers
It sounds Hotel
Llama sound like
It was a recording
Not a re-enactment
An actual recording
I made this recording two years before the day night
When I was 25
In this recording I'm sitting in a windowless bedroom with a guy named Raul
I'm doing an interview about intuition for the show
Well the times for me intuition just means getting your mind out of the way and being observant
This guy Raul and I dated for a while
I smiled at him in a coffee shop and he ran down the street after me asking if he could take me out sometime
I was Charmed by him
But after a few weeks he totally ghosted me
By the time of this recording it's been months since we last spoken
I did that dumb thing where I needed an interview for the show and I was like oh my God
To be perfect
So
Here we are
When the interview ends
I leave the tape rolling because just good radio practice
Often the most intimate parts of the interview happen after it's officially over
So we're just sitting on his bed
I know beyond a shadow of a doubt
They don't want to have sex with him or anything along those lines
That were flirting a little bit
And I'm enjoying it
Mama by Fela
Massage
Okay
I'm down I'm down for that but
On my back
You can try to seduce me
But I want you to
Touch me in sexy places
Upromise
Oppressor off
Definitely
Booty belt
Under breast
Under breast is okay
But you have to be very like
Aware
Use your intuition
But even if it seems like I want you to you have to be nice and good
Okay
Massage to me is as intimate as a handshake
But I know that's not the case for everyone
So
I start to try to vocalize my boundaries and make sure that what's going on is cool for everyone here
Can you to feel like you can do it like you can touch a woman without like
Having
Like feeling like you need to
Soccer
I don't know I mean like so for example
For example right now the way that you're touching me makes me feel like
Later I'm going to have to tell you that I don't have sex with you
Tiananmen
And I just wonder like
If it's possible
Like
Is it possible for men to feel like
Cotuit to genuinely enjoy like
But but do you get off on my trying to change someone's mind
Girlfriend
This is the sound of me and Raul having sex
When I listen to this recording I hear myself say no again
Presumably when he tries to escalate to full on penetration
Show camera
I feel a little bit like
Are you
I mean I feel good but
S7 want to
Are we just retarded when it comes to
What we want
How do we know what we want
What part of you knows that you want cuz he was taking analytical mind that knows that you want
No how could it be
I mean it doesn't make any sense is analogical
We can only
Trigasm
After the post-coital cigarette
I didn't stay over
Which is really unlike me
I walked home through a gray Bushwick Warehouse land
Angry
Raul for ignoring everything I said
At myself for totally folding when he push my line
And at my body
For betraying me
For enjoying the sex
I got to go to the interview part of the recording we did produce the intuition show
Unless it's recording silent in the archives
4 years
Until one shitty night just like it
I've been to me on the 4th of July
With an old friend
Jay
In the months after the Jay night I dug up this recording
And I listened closely to myself
I listen to the way that I actually sound
In A Night Like This
My boundaries are crossed
My best friend Laura listen to this
She said it definitely sounded like I wanted to f*** this guy
If you take away the words and just listen to the sounds
This is probably exactly the way that I found it
When I was with j
Say no in the sweet seductive tone
I'm trying so hard to be nice and not hurt anybody's feelings that
I know basically sounds like f******
But on the other hand
I wonder how many people sound just like this when they are getting hot and heavy with someone and they're trying to draw a line
Express what they want in a way that doesn't break the flirtatious vibe
But doesn't negate the possibility of doing other things
I wonder how many people sound just like this when they're scared
I think this is why the definition of consent has evolved
To me more than no means no or even Yes means yes
Consent is about knowing that someone is excited about what's going on
It's about knowing that both people are on the same page
And it's knowing that knowing that is really complicated
Not just because communication is hard and sex that is awful
But also because there are invisible social and historical context that play in these intimate moments
Contacts that
Impact
How entitled we feel to our own comfort
How likely we are to put someone else's needs first
These contacts could be historical like race or class or gender
Or they could be super situational
Like when one person is a little bit in love with you and you are in love with them and you can totally sense that they'll do what
Whatever you want
When things are uneven in this way
It's important to take extra care
To create an emotional environment that allows for a no
I didn't feel like I had that space and either of these encounters
But on the other hand I should have been stronger and advocating for myself
I'm bummed because I thought I was over this s***
But it seems like I'm going to be struggling with this
My entire life
And after all this contemplating
The anger that I have it myself
Slowly
Dissipates
I start getting angry at J
I was not angry at rule because we weren't that close
Vagina work clothes
I expected so much more from him
Expected him to care more about the way I felt
In the same way that I had cared about the way he felt
I knew that the strong thing to do
Would be to talk all this out with him
2 days after the night
PG chatted me
I ended up sleeping all day
And then two days later
A month later on my birthday
Happy birthday
Thanks darling
How are you babe
Two weeks after that
5 days later
Same day
What's up
Thank God you answered I was getting worried you were active
Totally ignoring me
How are you
I say home every time I friends get together and I know he'll be there
I tried to tell her friends what happened
But when I say it out loud it does sound like almost nothing
I'm a surface we had which day would later call
Drunken night of masturbation failure
No big deal
Problem is that
We don't have a vocabulary around emotion that would let me describe with any sense of legitimacy
The totally invisible things that happened between us that night
Can we come back from break
Going to hear from the other side of the aisle from guy's point of views DJ
Listen to Radiolab we will continue in a moment I'm Ryan and I'm
Calling from Lake Tahoe California
Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloan at www. Sloan. Org
I'm Jedi boom Rod this is Radiolab in the no part 1 in collaboration with Kaitlin Prest
So we're starting things off with excerpts
From a series of stories Caitlin produced for show she hosted and created called the heart
Series called no
We just heard a chunk from episode 2 of her series when she calls in herons
In the third
She explores things from the man's point of view where I was like I knew that I wanted to interview men
And I just interview the people who had access to which are my best friends my exes
And I was like oh well interview men
Interview people who have
I perpetrate like you have pushed
On the other side
And so I just yeah I realize that almost all the all of my close friends had a story in the same way
That all my clothes women friends had a story about pushing and knowing that they pushed too far
And that's actually what you hear in episode 3 of the series called answers were going to play you some excerpts of that now starting a few
Few minutes into it
Just as I unknowingly into the disappointment of my parents absorb certain ideas about how I was supposed to be a
Girl in this world
Boise the disappointment of their parents
Absorb ideas to
Feeling the need to girls
Try to get some that was the plan
13 year old boy and his friends create an elaborate plan to get the girls to do sex stuff
Beer and making the move like that was like the magic answer they learn from older boys
Men's magazines that getting girls drunk is crucial to the goal of getting girls to do sex stuff
Cheating in a construction site after 3 beers
Why does hand underneath the lip of Genesis pants she sits up straight
So I'll try a little more take as hand away he puts it back
That's what you're supposed to do right takes it away he puts it back
15 year old boy leans back in his chair
Cutting his knees rest on the back of the chair in front of him leaning up against whatever girls but is in the seat
Sitting behind the girl who I was attracted to you that I would spend a lot of time reading back in This Not That unnatural but not
That natural leader position and not at guys
Change it
A 26 year-old boy invites his good friend over to his house late at night
And playfully ignores her when she says she doesn't want to do anything below the belt
When she asks him to jerk off in the bathroom he laughs
And they resolved to jerk off beside each other instead
After that night I don't talk to or cj4 years
In that time
I searched for answers elsewhere
Become obsessed with the topic of consent okay so the idea about the episode is that
I want to hear about a time where I like someone said no and you pushed
It became
Clear you both wanted to consent inherent to you like when you were young or did you have to like
Unlearn things that you
Women that I know
Almost every woman in queer I know has a story about being pressured or coerced into sex by a dude
Let me wonder
Does that mean that
Every man I know has a story
About pressuring or coercing someone into sex
I start out by talking to the men in my life that I trust the most
Shall we go to remain nameless or what
Well it's hard cuz you're my dad do you know what I mean
It's fine whatever okay so tell me the story
Long story was I had a real crush on this girl
She got
Pretty drunk
So I went down and
Snuggle.
And I was rubbing her sides and then we kissed a little bit but that was the extent of it
You know nothing to too serious by today's standards but by then that was a big deal
But
At that time
What was the big deal
Leonardo's
Yeah
Yas and enjoying that plus she was ferret wearing h
Free sweater which was really nice and I still remember it anyway
It was not it was not usual self
When did you know that she was upset about it
The day after we heard through the grapevine we didn't have
Texting your Facebook fan but you heard pretty quick Through the Grapevine yeah that it
He was very unhappy about what it happened
And felt
I've used or taken advantage of
My relationship was never the same after that I went and apologized but that was there is no
Coming back from that and so I felt regretful and paid for it because we were no longer friends after that
This is a best friend of mine
As soon as I knew that sex wasn't an option I became a bit of a dick
I
Got kind of cold
And like
Not really communicative
Or
Yeah I just became like a stereotypical
Dick
And I became like grumpy
Had this really like f*** this attitude like you all if I'm not getting what I what I came here for
Dead Like Me
I guess I'm lucky that I got this is like
Really intense
Detailed email from her
You know breaking down what I did why was bad how much it hurt her how it affected her for like days
Is after
And and I'm not going to lie
I also had that
Reaction which you've described
Dislike initial reaction of like a here like over exaggerating
This is my first love
Well I remember you told me the story of the this one night that you had with this woman
Can you tell me that story I can tell you that story so
We were dancing we were drinking she not getting really drunk
And her friends are like
Definitely putting down
The collective foot
Saying that no I shouldn't sleep with her tonight that she was too drunk
She's like I want you to come over
Went over to her place and
Is in bed with her and we're making out and it was getting heavy
She could feel that I was
Like moving in
She kind of like
Like no no
Just kind of like a whisper
Like I know keeping it
Sexy but like
Saying like now you know
I felt kind of confused
Because that night like
You know we are out and she invited me over to her house
And for me that's like a message that she wants to hookup that like she wants something to happen
Otherwise like why invite the person you've been making out with all night over to your place at like
4 in the morning
LSi
You're looking
I like
Fool around a bit more
And
So like I remember
Getting off of her
Just lying there for a bit feeling kind of disappointed
Then like started making out again
Going around again in the sky like the same process it happened and
Like after doing that for I don't know maybe 20 minutes like
I like got back on top and
Was kind of making the same moves and
She didn't say no
It wasn't that point of interjection where she like said no before
And like
So I just went for it cuz I was like
Stupid in young and I feel like it's wrong now you know
Like I feel like
Chad said no before and like I should just been really vocal
About like communicating boundaries and like seeing what she wanted for the night you know
But do you think that there was a moment where you stop thinking about what she wanted and was focusing mostly on what you wanted
Yeah I mean I feel like probably the entire encounter
I was thinking what I wanted as opposed to what she wanted
I mean I thought that it would she wanted was the same thing as what I want in
And
You know what it wasn't that way I felt like
I was trying to make it that way
In this episode Caitlin goes on to
Speak to a whole collection of other guys who
All describe different flavors of the same experience of gently pushing
Sometimes not so gently
Pass that
Personnel
We're going to skip over some of that and engine for a few minutes because eventually Caitlin does end up
Convincing Jay to speak with her on tape
You want to start
Me
Yeah
Yeah I mean what were you thinking
But you should start yeah that's what I was thinking too
But when you gave me the option I was like was there an alternative I mean I would love an alternative
Not starting would be the alternative
This is Jay
The real one
No reenactment snow actors
It's been three years since we had that shity hook up that inspired this entire series
I knew that after interviewing all of these men
He was the one I really needed to talk to
I procrastinated calling him for months
He definitely knows that I was upset
But I don't think he knows exactly why
Olympics interview
I have to tell him why
I'm afraid I'm afraid of the same thing I was afraid of that night
Afraid of silencing myself
To avoid uncomfortable moment
I'm afraid that he's going to convince me that my feelings are illegitimate and I'm afraid that you'll be a jerk
Over the years Jay has become kind of a monster in my head
Stereotype has morphed into a combination of every man I've ever felt sexually coerced by
Become the poster boy
I think they're feminists because it took some courses in college and really love women
Friend Jay is gone
Even know who that person is anymore
But a part of my heart opens
He says yes to doing this interview
I can tell that he doesn't really want to do it
I can tell that he's doing it because he wants to help me out
He could sense how much I really wanted him to say yes
So
What if I don't know why don't you
I mean should we do the hard part first or the easy part first
Nervous about talking about
Like me and you and stuff you know
I know why do you have to make that face is that face cuz you feel like it's stupid or is that face like
No it's not stupid it's of course it's valid it's like it's legit
But I just
Doesn't it feel like such a small
But see that I think that that's the thing is that it feels so much bigger to me than it does to you I think
I really knew you were going to say that isn't what you want
I just saw it coming
I also just don't feel like
Me just rehashing every it's just so much work
Can't we just
Can we just move on like really is it really that big a deal like honestly I mean
The thing is it's not in your daily life like can this really follow you around
I mean
There's like the honest answer to that question and then there is the answer to that question which is like
Me really wanting to not make you feel bad do you know what I mean
To my thinking it's just like
In all of our friendship
Knowing what you know about me
Don't I get a pass
For one infraction of this line
I just
Stupid I just wasn't shrunken school like
Lake pushed over
All syringes made such a big mistake and I get that it was a big mistake but it was a mistake and it was like wow
Wantonly
You know
Would it be so bad I'm not asking you to get over it
But just like in the abstract
If you think about other like another friendship not hours
Would it be so bad to just get over that one thing you know
Like doesn't really warrant becoming
Baggage for so many years
Yeah that could also just be me since I'm the one who f***** up
But I also think you f****** overreacted so you know
I don't know I mean
And you're also like haven't talked to me for years until now you need something right
My giggling tells me that I'm nervous
But I know that in this moment I'm also relieved that we're getting right into it
Looking him in the eye for the computer
Singing to his bedroom
Watching angle the camera so that the lights flattering
The Dubrow monster melts away
I'm just chilling with my friend Jay
About to have
Pretty intimate conversation
Can a nice
Not
Scared of him anymore
I'm scared of is that I won't have the courage to say what I need to say
But
Start
Yeah that's true that's true
Farpoint but I have to say that like I didn't remember you ever saying sorry or like acknowledging my feelings about
Or even just saying sorry like I just didn't remember you saying sorry like I felt like
I really trusted you as a friend
And that like
I said I don't really want to touch Jon's and then you kept trying to
Junk touching
I'm putting my hand on your junk and stuff like that you know what I mean and telling me to touch your junk and like
And I kept trying to sort of like push
At this point I talked for about 10 minutes straight
I tell him all of it
He just listens
When sitting here and there
And tell him what he did how it made me feel
I tell him about Trevor Smalls and a b****** in the basement
I tell him that he said and did things that I brought me back there
I tell him he made me feel like a means to an end
Yeah okay
I don't I guess that I don't know what else to say
It would have been nice to have had this conversation then right
After
It happened because
Like you said to its
Sleep timer
Reject offer
In front of each other
And I was like yeah I was like a super pushy drunk
Hookup guy
But that's all I want I wasn't
Basement
Guy I know but I understand
I heard everything you said
That you just said
I heard it all
I guess it was frustrating it is like the fact that there is
Trauma
The den compound
That's like a fact but it'll be
Nice to know
Which specific ones
We're getting added to it to me
Cuz like I know I pushed you back there
But then those things that you experience
And not what happened this is Sarah like I don't ya
I mean I think that like it's
It's whether it's not even much of a difference
But that's the thing I guess it did feel like
Write me off
Where do I get to do you know what that's not me like I'm not all those other
People I'm sorry that this had that like we got drunk together and that I tried to do hand stuff and you didn't want to
And then it ended up with us doing heads up next one another
And I'm sorry that still drunkenly I was a dick
And I'm sorry that drunkenly I said a bad thing and you know I'm sorry of for all that but it's like
How bad do I have to feel
One thing is like parsing out where I end and like all the other terrible dudes in the world begin
Which is a frustrating thing for a young man to deal with
F*** man also like how can I done my time like do I really have to feel like I haven't gotten to talk to you
You for years now because of it
Play how much guilt do I really have to have
See you making me feel bad
Okay no I just want to know okay
You're making me feel bad okay
No I don't think that you
That I don't think I asked
Westfield Corporation
And then the only reason I asked that but it is an isolated incident in our friendship it is
We talked for about an hour and a half total I'll spare you all the details mostly we just kept circling back
Back around the same point why it shouldn't be that big of a deal
Family I realize that I never got a chance to ask what is inner monologue was that night
Or what larger personal and social context might have been a play
But
I wasn't silent
Did my ground
I fought for the we didn't receive my feelings but I felt like you missed some of my Q you were
Most women are dealing with some degree of sexual trauma is like the right thing to look at it through the lens
Of being a free about isolating specific sexual activity
Worse than that one friend of mine says that they're upset that my first reaction is to be like oh my god what the f*** did I do I'm so sore
Sorry X suddenly to you I was just like a means to an end
It still makes me angry that I had to fight so hard for legitimacy of my feelings
In the first place
I want to start cutting the interview
Start to hear
Accusatory his voice sounds instead of talking about why
Why he was drunk that night we talked about why I'm a jerk for being upset about it
Hear how each of his apologies were paired the rebuttal of the entire premise of the conversation
Play this is not what an apology sounds like
I was a dick and you know I'm sorry up for all that but it's like
How bad do I have to feel this is what an apology sounds like
Kaitlyn
So sorry
I mean I
That's f***** up that's Tommy the actor who played Jay in the last episode I hired Tommy
I feel like to do more than just explain myself
Politely that actually but to actually get angry it was your fault
I'm realizing that now that you know why it was your fault I'm going to tell you why
You're f****** a******
Hurt your feelings I would feel like s*** about nothing feel like s*** about treating me like a f****** Barbie. I was taught from birth
You want for what I want f****** job to be sensitive to that masculinity really f****** wife
Great job. And I hate you for up all the f****** privilege card you're acting like
I f****** hate you and your client
Wow okay so you made that
That
Documentary that we just heard a big excerpt of that was that was a few years ago at this point
Have you spoken with Jason Centerview Revisited that that conversation at all
I wish I mean like
I why wouldn't I would love I would love to have a kind of like a closing out conversation
Done with him I did check in with him over the course of the whole production and I sent him the cuts before they went
And I just keep right reaching out to him saying do you want to talk
He doesn't want to talk he's not answering
So Caitlin's stories for the heart which we would encourage you to listen to
You can find the whole thing really play bits and pieces of it you can find the entire series well worth a listen at
The heart radio. Org colossal link you to it from radiolab.org
Sing is that Caitlin made that series well before me too and actually listened
Set it up like having a bunch of questions like where are things at now conversations
Round consent in the moment of consent the aftermath conversations like the one she had with Jay or how are those half
Happening or not happening now and we took all these questions and we walk them around
A little bit talk to series of academics at makers BDSM practitioners many men
Play room folds of college-age men and women and in the next two episodes we're going to bring you in on some of those cam
Conversations Caitlin will also join us for some of them want to sincerely thank her for allowing us to share her
Work definitely check out her new podcast called the Shadows Caitlin's team that helped her producing the
No series for the heart Caitlin wrote and directed what you heard us she also had help from editor Sharon mashihi and
Assistant producers REO Han and Phoebe Wang & Associates sound design a music composition from
Shiny Abra okay we will be back next week with more delenn I'm Jedi
Thanks for listening
I'm Kaitlyn
It's Caitlin
Hello
Radiolab was created by God album Rod and is produced by Sean wheeler
Maria Montessori the managing director
Dolphin cruise Simon Adler Becca Bressler Rachel Cusick David devil
Hohhot
Her
Kasie hunt at Chelsea Robert krulwich and Amy kissing the peace Nasir Nasir
Not fair Melissa O'Donnell Arianne wack at Walters
And Molly Webster with help from FEMA only
Glassboro
MO
Elmo
Michelle Harris
The end
And this message