Are you awake
Northern listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
We're going to
Starts with a conversation that I had with Jad a few weeks ago
So
I like medical stories about you through this you know
And so I read this website
Cups that news.com
Mariah is sort of really it's like a new weather Boston
Collection of really amazing like medical reporters
And
I will click on surveys that look interesting
And there was one about
We've just grown embryos
Human embryos for a long time in the lab and
That was when I read the phrase
The 14-day rule for the first time
It was that
Apparently there's this thing that you can't grow an embryo in a lab
Pass 14 days
Which I didn't even know you could grow in embryonal Abbott all right
Or the people were
Or that
I mean I guess I knew IVF
Happened sure like tattoo babies how long is the average IVF situation how long is an embryo in a dishwasher
Then I realized I didn't actually even know that either so then I just spun out so like the whole article is just interesting to me cuz I was like
I don't know about any of this
Emily Webster this is radio from today on Radiolab
I'm hole into another universe and Robert you're coming with me tell me about the universe
You're going to want to buy a ticket because in this universe are twins and souls and mice and something called the
Primitive streak and they're all gathered together around a certain rule
Well you can fertilize an egg to get fertilized
And then the egg is fertilized egg it multiplies X cell divides so scientists could take it
To watch it grow to learn about human development
But then I have to stop
Fa14
That's the rule
Is this a medical kind of thing or science
Limitations Medical Science in there
But philosophy and ethics
Obviously religion and
Shebang I have water
I'll take a sip
Okay are we going to begin with this guy Leroy Walters
Okay he was an ethicist at Georgetown University now retired
And to me he started the father of the 14-day rule
I never thought of myself
As the father
14 day
He totally is well
We shouldn't forget the context of
Alright so 1973 Leroy has recently graduated with doctorate in ethics
From Yale University and he's settling into his job and it's a Time medicine and ethics
Sort of Collision Course
Yes
Good evening
January 8th 1973
Happens is clearly
That a
Unborn
Within the meaning of the Constitution but just six months after that decision be issued
Go research became of Hot Topic
Name of a testimony
Even an instance of decapitating fetuses and then around the same time
Guinea pigs the research involving human being
Civil studies that were done on African American men without their knowledge
Paralyzed without their informed
Women with intellectual disabilities
You have all these questions swirling about like
How we feel about the human body whether or not we want to experiment on it what are we protecting what don't we protect
It just sort of this to Whirlwind and
You are about to see a historic but most relevant for our story
July 25th 1978
UK wear now
Incising the uterus itself
Produced
A child with the aid of in-vitro
Fertilization
The first baby that was born from an embryo that was grown inside of tube
Babies not open her eyes yet
Everyone in the World list
FastMed
But there were people
Who predicted Doom
What was the Doom
In vitro fertilization would lead to
Reproduction is
Form of manufacturer
So the government was grappling with
We need more regulations or we need as a country to think about like what are ethical guidelines are
The department of health education and Welfare
Put together and then call the ethics Advisory Board
Doctors Lehman academic
Even a Jesuit priests who consider moral and ethical questions
Human fertilization
It's meetings and discussions open today
Now as part of those meetings the Border colonies expert Witnesses and one of those Witnesses was our Boy Leroy
Write the staff director Leroy like
Ethically tell us what we should be thinking about when it comes to embryos we are to regard them
And he says well there's a spectrum and on the one side You could argue human embryo should be
Protected from the time of fertilization
Forward
We shouldn't even be growing embryos in a lab at all but then there's the other side
Possession was that
Research could be done until about 8 weeks fetus at about 8 weeks
Can have a reflex
Response
To a stimulus
And then
At some point
A Committee Member turns to Leroy and she says
Where would you draw the line
A+
He says well
I would say for me
14 days
Y 14
Well Leroy had a couple different arguments
1 before 14 days 50%
Overly human embryos are simply
Laughter
They just sort of Shed from the woman's uterus
And don't develop further if we are already losing 50% of them naturally
We don't have strong moral obligation
Toward early human embryo
You can even posted as the
Metaphysical
The question
If these are important beings why do 50
8% of them
Disappear
And we never have any knowledge of
Argument number two
Splatoon 2
As in Twin embryos can recombine
And a one embryo
Right right before 14 days and embryo doesn't know if one embryo or vasectomy one person or two people
So is leer I put it it doesn't have a
And that happened around 14 days argument number 3
The Primitives
Streak
Appears
Primitive
Streak the perimeters
Is the
First indication of a
An axis
Of the future body
People see it as I got the body starting to organize
You might say it's
The outline of the spinal cord that will develop later on the first hint of like
Shape
All of those seem to kind of
Converge
Around
14 days
Eventually the committee decides to take Leroy suggestion and recommend that all research on human embryos be stopped
Get 14 days
With
High expectations
Since we submitted the report
The Secretary of health education and Welfare
Joseph califano
On May 4th
1970s
And on July 19th
1979 before he could be
Respond
Secretary kalifano was fired
By president
Jimmy Carter
It was part of a whole cabinet shake-up
And so
The report has been sitting on shelves
Gathering
Dust
And there has never been
For Maurice
It did end up becoming a guideline in the US It's actually an international guideline but we never actually needed it
Because 14 days that was so far beyond
The capacity of researchers
The culture early embryos that it also seemed like
Safe
Marker safe
Foundry
Because and this is the interesting thing with IVF
We're familiar with 0 1 2 3 4 5
Which is about the time they put the embryo into the mother
So nobody is ever really seen how an embryo develops from day 7 through 14
So interesting you can't
Photograph it through the body for like various reasons
For one No One Ever Knows they're pregnant that are really like
When did you and your wife realize your pregnant looks like a month after the fertilization
Yeah it's funny it's like when she ain't you even if you're trying you don't actually know for weeks until
Yeah
And it's so small that even if you did know the way it attaches to the uterus it start
Burrows in and
Kind of can't see it
At the same time scientists are pretty sure that this is a very important moment in development
They just can't get to it
Wait wait
Life Magazine 50 years ago published these gorgeous pictures of
Of a fertilized cell
And then
Beautiful little baby with eyes you just
Yeah but this is a that they have
Pictures of sperms and eggs
Then there's a blank spot until at least three and a half weeks
So that Magazine spread
Didn't show
The first Pew II
In the development of the human being that no scientist has seen
Ever know
Yeah so this is this kind of. Which in the textbook who would find described as a black box which
Brings us
The Magdalena at the University of Cambridge in UK
Cheat for years have been trying to figure out how to grow embryos during this period
But if we're Joseph Spider-Man the problem was at this point the embryo is beginning to attach
To the mother's uterus and so just need certain things from the mother and if
You try and grow it in
A dish
It just shrivels up and dies
Yes yes so that the time we were trying critias scratch our heads and come up with that Mustang
Enrichment environment we could imagine
Like maybe I can make a recreate that really warm cozy
Home
Put in a dish without the mom interesting so so experimented like what is the right
Bath
At the growing embryo needs it needs
Yeah and they decided that while they're still trying to figure it out they would just do it on my sombreros first and Sochi
Started essentially just
Coming up with like chemistry concoctions
They started with the gel which was of particular elasticity and then they
Made from Human placentas added some hormones like progesterone along with fiber
Escrow factors like someone would sell this is
Looks like a face cream or something
Play even tried serum from that's what I sent us that actually really didn't work.
For five years they put stuff in everything
I ended up with something at least on my seem to work really well so they thought okay
Maybe it's time we try this with human embryos
We took two Andres just two human
Blastocyst
Put them in a dish with their chemical concoction and
Amazing Grace
It works
One of them
Ditch maker
213 days
The other one didn't but it's right
Suddenly they have an embryo that was growing heffle into date
Deny
Big Ten
And they were able to see all of these moments in human development that
No one had ever seen before
And and guess what Robert
I got to see them too
Do you want to come of course I want to come okay good Alicia go right now I mean we are going to go
But we're good actually have to take a break first
So we'll be back in a bit
Hi this is
Does Lizzy from Arlington
Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology
In the modern world
More information about Sloan
At www.slha.org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here I'm a producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
And I request
For those of you who
Who spend a lot of time with kids parents
Aunts and uncles teachers we're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments of childhood brilliance
Basically I want to hear about this
When a kid you know did something
It just means you lean back and say
How do they do that
Maybe it was the moment that I
A kid you've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of their musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class
Music in the margin of their geometry
We're interested in the
Epic moments where
Kid does something super smart
It doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story
Go to radiolab.org
Flash brilliance
And record a short audio message
Again that's radiolab.org
Slash brilliant
Thank you so much
Okay we're back I am Robert krulwich
I Molly Webster
He is really 11 today the 14-day rule
Last we left you we had just met a woman who managed to grow a human embryo in a lab write up to the 14-day line
Now we get to see it right after you promised
Yes
When your phone on when your phone off
Good luck
Lucky enough for me there is in embryology lab right here in New York Rockefeller University
How are you
Run by this guy
Fake being a scientist
Ollie's team building off of magdalena's work
Today we're also going human embryos in the lab
The 40-day mark
So he invited me up to see them seeing something that
No other human beings has ever seen
Except the group in Islam
And obviously might just laugh
How many people are in this lab that you think so.
I think we're so total 25
So then I'll be like 26
So Ali has to step out of the room
I'm excited but thank you Ali and he passes me off to the guy that runs like the human embryology
You research at the lab
Craft and a lab technician
Chichirya Pellegrino
To Julia Pellegrini
Okay
We go into the lab
Benches microscopes and people pipetting and
So
There's a little sticky on the fridge that says
Experiment 27 embryos here
Entity Leah pulls out like a plastic
Box that has a blue bottom and like a white opaque top
So they just came off and inside there was kind of like a microscope slide and the embryos were
Attached to that
There's condensation on us we have to wait like 10 minutes
Weirdly nerves but eventually they like look down into this like
Little
Square well
10 millimeters by 10 mm and I have a little bit of liquid in it
And then inside that liquid
Offices
Human embryo
How big is it how big is an embryo
In my mind I do imagine
A tiny little
Human isn't even human like at that point
Tiny. Right there no is just a little white
.
Really small
I took a grain of sand
And it looks like I kept also thinking that it look like if you took
Sheet of typing paper and you took
Pin
Poked a hole in the paper and a little pinpoint of light came through
That's what it looks like that
I cannot believe that goes into a
Five foot nine tall human being
So that was a day 12 Andrea we were looking at with our naked eye but gets into chili also
Badass microscope
What do I don't want to break anything
So we could look at a bunch of images and see the development of an embryo day by day
Starting with
Day 8
Right here like you have the embryo man
What are you
What is it look like
It's
Tewksbury lunar 2
Blown-out Grace
Sphere that has like modeled surfaces
But inside of it are hundreds and hundreds and hundreds of cells are primitive endoderm and there's a happy glass
There were like three different types of cells but to me it like looks like a simple structure
And then
This is the same embryo the next looks totally different so starts to get a little more complex
Now we can see nuclei there's a nucleus
Make me switch from 9 to 10 so what are those
Droplets now there are these like spiritual balls around the edges and that could be any number of things
Just think they might be fat and the embryo it starts
Warming like the asymmetry like you see things move to different areas of the cell
Inside
And then your inner gut cavity that starts to form and solve
A new cell type would never stand the yolk Sac Rebecca Graham cell
So it's totally new type of cell no one's ever seen before so we don't know where it comes from and neither does anyone else
Damn excited every time you open one of them locate a 11
They'll abandon really like looks at different to me
School Daze thirteeners all this brightness at the bottom in the upper left-hand corner
Remind me again the last is that is the cell type from which the entire body
Eventually emerges
Guest says those are the cells that all of the body comes from like all the other stuff is mostly just support
So it's like that it's like the Primal like
Primordial
Yeah
So actually got there on day 13 of the experiment so all of the embryos were just sort of
Waiting to get today 14 and
That was it
And then I was just sort of
Spit back out into the real world
Are they learning fantastically new amazing things based on this so they're like the the the big take
Play the both of the groups had
Why is that
This embryo glue for another week without any maternal input
And it grew basically as it should have
Which was mind-blowing to me into all of my colleagues
That the human embryo
Will behave in a self-organizing manner
In the complete absence of maternal input
At least for 14 days
Like I think they always thought
Even if they got the chemistry right there be some sort of system breakdown because it wasn't getting imp
From the mall
Interesting ways I keep thinking of it is like the anti Mother's Day message
Camera doesn't need you happy Mother's day but the edges the one pro promo
Saying is by the way by the end
In between day like 12
14 and became
Clear that it started meeting
The Eternal Empire
Well so they always cool was like they saw that the embryo start
Deforming
Tunnels and Pathways for the mom to like
Infiltrate but there were little tubes and Pathways of foreign war like nerve attachment could happen
And like circulation
Sewage pipe repairs itself in this week
The mom and the connection really cool it's like
Play cooking itself up to the network
I know it's funny as I coming online is like a human being
The cool thing was
Guess told me that right around Dayton along the edges of the embryo
This hormone shows up that your body had doesn't have before it's called like a gonadotropin
Do you know when you take a pregnancy test
The thing is reading is that hormone
Is that
He thinks like
The embryo Broadcasting
Cyclone boom boom mic out to the rest of the body
Like I'm here I'm here look at this hormone
Wow that's super cool
What is it like to look through a microscope and see
Day 8
When we've been stopped at day 7 since
The 1970s or day 9 or 10
It's hard to describe it
When people receive
The digital image of the Hubble telescope
First uri's
Who are getting it in the screens
I guess it has to be something but he seemed enough for that
When I look inside
409a attorney at the time where
Nobody knows
Even exist
Is the same as
Looking at dimensions
Never imagined
Whatever see because we didn't even know they exist
But then at day 14 you have
To essentially embalming
You like, I can make it stop growing and
Freeze in the place it's at
They caught fixing but if they wanted to we could they go past 14 days
Maybe but
Ali he said that as I got closer to day 14 they noticed
Changes in the embryo that made it
Clear that it started needing more than just a current Bassett it was in
Okay
Like embreeville Lou says it's 2 in Magdalena says it's like everyday feels like an accomplishment
Oh my gosh I grew another day and then you start like
Sharing it on
Another day another day oh my gosh here to 12
Becomes like your life
Champion
And then you're like
Stop you're done and I felt like when I was standing there was like oh that's a bra
Because
I wanted it to grow grow grow grow grow
But he said don't want it to grow grow grow too far
So is like
Curry 15 16 when does the joy of my voice stop
Eventually
That's uncomfortable this is something that
Touches Us in The Roots
Overtone definition
So far being in existence and individuality
Tecumseh like a Pandora box
So
Yes you would open it but you have to be ready
To see what's in it
If technology has no moved it a whole nother week so we can go for 14 days
Maybe it's pretty soon you can go a whole nother week and then home other week
Does that mean the rules going to have to change
That is a conversation that's happening right now
This research was published there were commentaries and articles and columns
Songs about what do we do about the 14-day Rule and there's
Conferences are competent Boston that's happening in the fall
Like you could choose
Could do any number of things it depends on where you sort of throw down a biological or moral marker that you feel come
Comfortable with like you can keep it at 14 days instead of keep it around like this idea of twinning and The Primitives
You could move it a week out to say the day 21 when there's interesting sort of neural phone
Folds in divisions that are starting to happen in the brain
You could go to 8 weeks
But it could also go back to zero
There's no consensus on the scientists are the first to say like
They don't want to make this decision
They just think maybe we should have this conversation as a group so the
Society decides not us
So yeah and then we'll just like if you say that like this amazing is like the Hubble telescope how did it feel
When you're like I've gotten this far and now I have to end it
So that's the toughest question you can ask me today
For me for sure
Who was important
Stop the experiment
Where there was still a message that you could convey
That would not offend people
This is more than just saying
What is the
British an engine
Reproductive biology especially in human reproductive biology
To make sure that you don't know fans
People sensitive
Identity dignity
Religion
So Ali he finds himself
Trying to keep all of these different perspectives in his head
All at once
So. Lifted the Catholic point of view is
Human Origins perception then I have to respect also the Jewish point of view
That's just you know what is a harpy
Also
Respect the Muslim point of view about the origin of human life
Which surprisingly for one seems to be similar than the Jewish point of view is also heart piece
I wish I could respect the Buddhist point of view
And what about the Hindus
The booty says if you don't cut the umbilical cord when you're not independent you're not a human being called an organic human being
Asian deuces
I don't know what you guys are talking about
There is no
Origin or ends
What are circles within circles within circles
On the butterfly today
I'm going to die and come back as a tiger I'm going to die and come back as a human then come back
What origin
A circle does not have an origin
I am for the progress of science
I am four
Gaining knowledge is my job
It's the way I'm wired
As a human being I said his final sense of curiosity
And there's nothing more to use to me tomorrow Norwich
So then that would be like you would love to know like what happens on day 21
Absolutely and
I like to think that
Before I die
Who would know
What happens on day 21
This episode was produced by Annie McEwen with help from Matt kielty and
Brenna Farrell and Simon Adler and diarrhea
Add something to do with this episode so
Thanks guys
And I want to thank the research library at Georgetown University
Thank you for the
See you later
To play the message press 2
I'm a retired faculty member from Georgetown University
But I was part of the Kennedy Institute of ethics and the philosophy Department
Radiolab is produced by Chad
Open rod
Dylan
Chief is our director of sound design
Corrine wheeler is senior editor
Jamie York
Is there senior producer
Our staff includes
Simon Adler
Brenna Farrell
David people
Matt kielty
Robert krulwich
Annie McEwen
Capiche
Master
Melissa O'Donnell
Ariane wack
Send Molly Webster
With help from naggar fatali
Alexandra B Young
Charu Sinha
First shift Berlin
W Harry Fortuna
Perfect checkers
Are Eva Dasher
And Michelle Harris
Beckett
Text Buy
And this message