Are you awake
Listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
Hey I'm Jared I'm Ron I Molly Webster this is Radiolab
Robert krulwich will be back with us soon
Today a story for you well I guess I was just thinking I should probably tell you just
Morgan and I back
Story of how I heard about the story so Morgan and I went to grad school together at NYU
So I guess I've known her for almost 11 years
Okay and where were were holed up in my apartment
I don't know this is like no last November something
Comes over
Sitting on the giant I've big floor pillow like a Turkish floor pillow
Course you do
Sitting on the floor pillow
And then she is like
Already hear the story
And I said yeah and she's like okay need you take the battery out of your phone
Really yeah and I actually said that
I can't take the battery out of it and she goes
Okay I need you to power down and put it in another room under a pillow
What
I was like what is going on in shoe and then if I disappoint she's taking the battery out of her phone so I
I do it I put it in the in my bedroom and I put it under pillows I
Turned it off I came back and sat down
And then she starts telling me essentially about the ceremony
About going to the launch of this new
Currency
Which involved her flying across the country to live in a hotel room for a number of days
A bunch of strangers and then something happened because she came back seemingly paranoid
At least she was hiding phones under pillows
It takes a few steps to start with step one which is
Which is Morgan
I Morgen pek
How would you identify yourself
Professionally
Professionally I'm a freelance journalist
And my eyes Morgan has become like
The historian of the world of digital money I started reading about neuroscience
I quickly found out about Bitcoin about a year into my writing
2011 and has pretty much been running ever since
Now yes a lot of people when they hear about digital money they think
650 Euros paid in Bitcoin currency
Obviously it has become associated with cybercrime
Stephen Morgan
What attracted her to this whole world of meter go my God this thing is amazing
She's like pulled in by the idealism of it there was an extremely active community of people who were talking
About
You know
Completely subverting the financial system at a time
When the financial system was
Not trusted and was clapping
Because Morgan says the birth of Bitcoin goes back to
Well
Never 2008 boom was the big
Implosion in September the stock market crashed the banks bailed
Bears are standing there watching in amazement I don't blame him I'm believable
This shakes your trust in American institutions
And then just a few months later 2009 January the Hot Topic
Digital money
Call Nick Quinn showed up after the big collapse
It was after and it was very much response to that definitely
Cuz he was as currency that was decentralized
Which means it's Ron and monitored by all the people who use it which means you don't need a federal
Is there a Uso at the beginning a lot of people sell Bitcoin is a way to sort of
Take the power back from The Big Bang so I had just everybody over Libertarians were really into it they thought that
It was going to
Rash that it was going to crumble The Columns of
Every Power structure in you know
The world obviously that didn't happen it did not take down the worlds
But Bitcoin is not going away it's been a decade it still around
But if you talk to people on the inside
Will tell you one of the things that has dog Bitcoin from the beginning
Is this issue of privacy
The weight of the
Technology works
Is that
It tracks every single transaction
Does ever
Maid on the network
Anytime anyone with a Bitcoin buys
Coffee
Start pound of heroin
That transaction is capital
In something called the public Ledger Bitcoin is a ledger public Ledger
It's out there for anyone to see
Really every single transaction has ever been done
Private at all
But people thought it was Private beginning because over using these pseudonyms another words in The Ledger you never see anyone's actual
There no names on in the car
Like I wouldn't be my only had bt9 572 problem is it
Well
There are no names attached
The behavior is out there
For anyone to see
Turns out
It's really not that hard to match
Dislike string of characters
With the person that it represents out in the real world
You could just kind of Google it on the internet see if it pops up anywhere else what is associated with
And then you got to figure out who the person is
And then you can go back into the Bitcoin Ledger and search their entire history can figure out all their big
Business dealings all their personal dealings who they know who they don't know possibly who their bank is
And you know people have tried to solve this problem with big
But companies now
And actually specialize in doing a network analysis of the Bitcoin blockchain and they do it for companies who want to
Make sure that they're not transacting with you know criminals people who have had
Delete trying to D Anonymous people
Wow
And so one of the puzzles that
All the internet people think about
Is
Is there a way to get the best of both worlds can you have the decentralization that comes with
Digital money
But can you also get privacy
Almost like cash a dollar bill out of my pocket I walk down the street I give it to someone they give to some
Can trace that money
Can you get the decentralization that comes with digital money and can you wrap that up with
The Privacy that you get with paper money not question
Testing testing
Brings up to this guy zooko Wilcox
Zuko and I'm in a different room
He is our master of
The ceremony I have to say you do
Everyone's like pretty excited on talking to a guy named Zuko like
It's just a good name Zuko
Zuko
Zuko is digital currencies for extremely dry
Is a charismatic leader type of thing
Yes but I was concerned about the Privacy applications because he's a pretty hardcore
It's like worlds upon worlds are opening for a cypherpunks
People that care deeply about
How to make the internet more private human right and that it's
Necessary condition
For the exercise of a free choice
Morality and of political participation
And of everything that's of intimacy everything that's most important as humans
So this whole thing with Bitcoin in the Privacy problem
Right up his alley
So I went out of my way to study the Bitcoin source code and
Contributed some
Suggestions and
Yes I immediately started
Fantasizing about what could be better
So then he
Being like the Privacy security cypherpunk
Gorilla becomes the leader of something called zika
NZ cash
Really it's mean
Contribution to this ecosystem is privacy
So there's this thing called zero knowledge proof
Okay and it's a mathematical invention that
Mathematicians who come up with it requires something called the Z snark parameters to be baked in
Into the protocol
I asked
Hours of questions
And it got me into conversation about circles and graphs
Send the shape of numbers is the shape of what's a possibility of
Was that
It allows you to prove that something is true
Without revealing anything about the thing you're trying to prove is true
Well you just
Take van to run Computer Science and Mathematics start
Overlapping to Wizardry here
All you need to know is it's zcash promises to give you decentralisation with the psych
Buffet at 5
Messi
Zcash has its own flocked unfortunate vulnerability in the math
In order to create the currency of zcash you have to first create a number certain
Enormous number and then you use that number to do a
Bunch of math and then like boom
You have the currency
But it all starts
With this number this key
Problem with that
In this system
If somebody got a hold of the private key they could counterfeit C CashPoints
They could counterfeit money just making it
Millions and millions and millions of newpointe that's a really big problem
You have a Anonymous currency cuz no one would ever know
Bitcoin and it's a public Ledger you can actually see if there's any funny business going on that
Actually why they keep it open right the lack of privacy and Bitcoin is a security measure but you're no one would ever know
So the challenges how do you get people to buy into a system that has this like
Major vulnerability
I'll be at just right at the very beginning there's this one moment where
You know you have to trust people
In a way that's
Completely
Existentially defining of the currency
So this is what zukas up again
How do I
If I want super privacy what she does
Generate this number in such a way
That
No one steals it not me not anyone else and how do I
To all of the people that might want to use zcash later than in the
Tiny little window of
Of creation nothing untoward has happened.
That the number is never been tampered with it
Human eyes have never been laid upon if you know that the entire creation of the system remains
Pure
Is it this is very much like an Immaculate Conception
You're like
No humans can have sex to make this baby but I need to be a baby
Examine the act of sex to make sure that there is no physical contact
Is it like that that's so good okay so here we are
Zuko designs
Will have
Ceremony
Most secure most sophisticated cryptographic ceremony that's ever been performed
Okay
Here's the thing while it's trivial to make your own currency
It is not trivial to inspire
That's what money is is the agreement between people to use it
And honor that
Yourself a contract and the creation of value to me that's like Alchemy
And at the moment of creation walking down the street
Near you Mali Greenpoint
And I get a text message on Signal
A private messenger app from Zuko that's like
Pay we want you to be want you to
Be there
Since you're so excited
Is chosen did you even know what you were being invited to now I had no I
No idea but I was like I have to do this I mean
I cannot miss this
Even if zcash doesn't make it even if you know it collapses
It seems like a historical
Moments
Suzuka basically said just
Wait for our back call
So about two weeks later
The back call come to the coffee store in Boulder
Soap Morgan gets on a flight to Denver Rent-A-Car to Boulder and go to the coffee shop goes there
Standing next to the Barista counter and actually
He has a huge
Paper map
With him
Spread all over like the Baristas area he's like up in their Grill
And this other guy not showed up who was going to film it up
Was that was that for you you wanted everything recorded
And it was
To serve as a security mechanism
And documentation for the public
More on that in a sec
And then
Okay
Okay they leave the coffee shop go over to Matt's van he makes us both up I told him they can make me up
Then we're going to turn off all of our cell phones
So that if there were any hackers
They would be able to track
Where we work physically
I'm trying to think if I have to say goodbye to anyone
We're like okay now we got the van we got our cell phones turned off
The next thing we need to do where we're going to the
Computer store acquire a computer
Because like if there was some hacker who is planning to steal the
They could have already planted some malware or tracking device on zukas personal laptop
Before we even started
So we all piled into the van to get a clean computer
He's decided to go to Denver for this but he doesn't want to use this phone
Because what if somebody is like cracking what he's looking at that is due
During much of his recording while he's driving do you have like a black hoodie over you like his
Bella style so they're driving for a little bit
All of a sudden they make this Pit Stop we were like
Hey there's a costume store in imperfect.
Wizard hat wizard hat
Can I see your wizard hat section
So they walk through this big costume store pass
Witches hats Tiaras what is the wizard that you settled on
It was a Gandalf hat Gandalf hat
Play I love the Gandalf hat that is appropriate the greatest wizard of all
And then back to the mission at hand stands Denver computer
We drove down using our paper map with our cell phones off to the computer store
They get their walk in a little computer shopping
Different ones
The computer is sacred i7 6700
Which henceforth is given a new name called the compute node
And why is it sacred
Well because this
Is the computer that will hold the secret number the number that will give birth to an entirely new
Currency so
And drove to an area that has hotels that we knew of
Hotels near going around to like the hotels in Boulder
Or they don't have an ethernet connection
He wasn't clear on the notion of ethernet
If you don't know what you're going to do
They don't know what they're going to do
I see this is actually your security measure I guess you're totally in the dark about what you're doing
Then some hackers they can't they can't mount an attack
It's foolproof but
Eventually has rooms and hotel
Zuko actually Hazmat book the hotel room for two nights
Do you have a key
We all check into one room from floor
It's not particularly
Fancy you got your two beds
Then they set up
We're well organized machine
Bad to chill out on concentrate on
Uncareful observing what we did was we stripped the room of all of the
Lamps and the telephone everything on all counters gets
Shop somewhere over that stuff bearded way into the closet
Or the bathtub in addition we didn't want like the television
For example which could be remotely controlled by an adversary
Television
Grab that table where they're going to set up the compute node explain again while you're keeping it away from the wall
There's a teeny tiny chance that a team of spies rented the room next door and set up a giant antenna
The other side of this wall this is like the dopest attacks atsuko is planning against
Called side-channel attacks by which you could use an antenna
Phone to figure out what a computer is doing for example with some crazy microphone you can listen into the computer
Desert if you heard something like
Oh that's a Diffie Hellman key exchange
Or
Oh yeah this is obviously figured out the full 4096 bit RSA decryption key
Hey that's a new babies video
Or whatever so please don't
Put anything on this desk from here on out
Just pulled away from the wall about
5 ft
Just in case there's somebody set up
Next door and then started loading and all the
Cameras and Equipment battery pack
Junk food but then there was also a whole security camera setup
They don't have a radio
For security cameras which word from the 80s before security cameras came with Wi-Fi
Which means
We had to buy antique
Security cameras in their night vision security cameras
And they said those up
So that we could see the other cameras from the first camera so you could sell that new
Did just snuck in there in like tampered with one of the cameras during the process either
And this security camera setup with one of the key points in trying to
Create
When Morgan was talking about earlier
The Alchemy
Faith Trust
Whatever
So the security mechanism this was this was going to
Catch any
Shenanigans
Inuzuka was going to post the security footage to the Internet so
Security Experts
Scan it and make up their minds could the ceremony be
Trusted
Hold on where are you going to sleep tonight
We could all cannabis sleep anywhere
So we said all that stuff up
It's like 9 now at 10 it was late
And
I took the computer that we used so-called compute node
And it from that moment forward I kept that thing
Like within Arm's Reach
48 hours or so oh my God it was
A little bit exhausting trying to be paranoid and it was exhausting trying to be paranoid
Yeah like I slept with it at night
My bed
UTEP my
Cut my arm around it
Goodnight sweet prince
And flights of Angels Sing thee to thy rest
Coming up
This is Enrique Romero from the Border Town of Laredo Texas
Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation enhancing public understanding of scientific
Knowledge in the modern world more information about Sloan at www.starone.org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here I'm a producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help this summer I'm hosting
And I request for those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
We're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments
Brilliance basically I want to hear about those times when I did something
It just means you lean back and say wow how did they do that maybe it was the moment that I kids
You've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons and you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed they're writing music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the specific moments where a kid does something super smart but doesn't have
Have anything to do with a test
If you have a story please share with us
Go to radiolab.org Brilliance and record a short audio message for us
And that's where you're at. Org / brilliance
Thank you so much
Chad Molly Radiolab
Back to Boulder
Sorry I can open the door that would be helping you
So it's the next morning
Zuko sits down at his personal computer and he starts making all these
Hello
Video chat calls
He calls up a guy in DC a guy in Texas
Tell you you sound like Tom Hardy also
Florida
Really appreciate your help
Slovenia
Drop it by another guy in California
And then there was this mysterious one has ready that was only referred to as February
Didn't know where he was
I didn't find out until afterwards
He was actually driving from Vancouver across
British Columbia
Who are all these guys sofra Zuko it's it's very unacceptable he wants to take as much of the
Trust me you got to trust me out of it as possible
And that's what I tried to do
It's so
Even though zukas can record all this footage put it up online later someone is going to be watching that could be like
This was a trick
It's all smoke and mirrors Magic Mike sure you say you recorded everything but maybe you manipulated the footage
You didn't even set the cameras up the way you said you did
And so
So I decided to do was get in touch with all these guys all over the world and try and decentralized distrust
So there were six stations security camera setup
Ready to help Zuko make
This big random number the private key so
Each of the six stations was actually creating one
Piece of the ski
That way they'll be no one person that makes the entire key it'll just be these little pieces that actually won't
Ever come in contact with one another the idea was nobody will actually have
The kids up
Hope this works
So everyone's got their compute node power down
And then
The ceremony begins
It's top secret Park
There's a special box
Here to make sure that nobody can
Gasser read this Secret
Zuko closes the blinds
And so
I'm going to cover my keyboard
With the special box
Do I take a cardboard box that one of the computer to come in
Sawed in half so that it was
Half of a cardboard box
He put it over the keyboard of the compute node
Freddy
And then I slid my hands under the cardboard box
And then
He starts punching in all these random letters and numbers into the computer node
Cat walking across the computer
Okay
And once he's done an auction on eBay
You know does it takes all those random characters and it combines it with more random characters that are generated like inside
By the computer
Until finally it creates
Part of the key to the other five participants had to do the same thing
DC made their piece of the Key Florida
Texas
Slovenia
Canada
Okay so you got one key broken into six pieces and the next
Step is to get all of those pieces to work together to
Create one thing which is zcash
And you want to do this in such a way that those pieces never touch
Each other that they remain hidden
So that
No person could ever get their hand on the power of the whole key
So thank God there's convoluted math to save the day I think it's a good time to just say what was happening
3-2-1 so
First things first the guy in California gets on the horn
Play like the batting order and then
He sent a message, but go message to station one
Station one guy and his computer know do some math on his piece of the key
If you know spits out a number and then Burns it onto DVD
Why DVD
Because all the guys at the station to ripped out the Wi-Fi in their compute node we don't want her to be able to package because
This by the way has a pretty cool name
You have a protective field basically around the computer that holds the secret
I feel
Anyway once the computer is done burning to the DVD the guy station one takes in wanted to another computer
Cuter
Uploaded to the internet and then the gas station to Peter van valkenburgh
So what happens is the software I run on my connected computer
I take the DVD out of the connected computer walk across the air gap if you will
Mini compute node takes that little answer combined it with Peters piece of the key and then
Math
Sonos it Computing again you answer a bigger ass
Answer and then I write on a different DVD answered
Takes it out of the computer network computer uploads
Station 3 grab that can find him a little bit more of an answer than Station 4
It's the same thing
Get a little bit more the answer and just rinse wash repeat station 5-6 back to the
Top of the order
And throughout this entire process the individual shards of the key are kept separate
And Secret
Get together they're doing the math it's getting closer and closer and closer
Do the final key that will launch zcash
Was there a like a
Peter in the air
No
I mean it really is
Tttt tttt
You better bring a deck of cards
Brunch Oakland
Cool
I can juggle 3 balls
Because the thing is every one of those Mass steps
Took about an hour
Have they had to do like
3 full rotations through this order
So most of the weekend was just kind of sitting around
Waiting
And waiting
Who's this
So yeah we're hanging out
Good to know
Zuko has brought along some
Pork rinds
And sour cream but he's tipping his dipping pork rinds into sour cream
Also
Napping
Which is the only sleeping this happen like
There's like
You know an hour here
Are there
End is the hours Roll by things are going really well people are getting their math done their passing along these answers
Getting closer to having their key
Maybe halfway into the process
Think it
Strange
The reach lying in their beds just
Kind of chilling out Morgan was just waking zuka was playing on a tablet
What
I groaned City to do
Dorit
Suzuka gets up
You start stalking which is
Well with my voice echoing back at me back
Feedback
Started
Equity
You don't like me
Incongruous noise
Make it stop
Commuting all my mics I don't know where it's being back from
He like turns off the mic
It was like okay
Macy's down
At the Google Hangout
Computer
A
Tester
If this Echo comes back
If you look at the video you see
He like just
Freezes
And then just
Turn his head to the left
Looking off camera
Play out over there now
At this point everyone in the room to start a false silent and is looking around
I start
Like pinpointing it to like the the part of the room that has a security cameras
Monitor test test test test
I start listening to that and I got to get skyrover here again
Stop wait a minute
What what is playing out
Over
Their test test
And I looked in the direction
Morgan's
Bet can I turn around
I pick up my phone
IPhone
And The Echoes coming out of my speaker
Is coming out of your phone coming out of my phone
Why is your phone
Playing out
Google stop
It's playing up in this way
He zeroes in on this mic that's on the corner of the computer that's doing the Google Hangouts
Pictures onto this hang on
He leans over to that
Start fiddling with it
Is there a way he stands he said
Whois
It's coming for it's not coming from this way
It's coming from
The Google Hangout cuz I just muted it and software
Now it's gone
So my voice Google Hangout let's hear Peter's voice
Beer
I want to test
Audio coming from you say some stuff
Allwood Manor okay
And then I think Suka says something like
Google Hangout
Why is our chat coming through your phone
Oh wait
So the audio coming out of her phone is not
Originating from in the room it's
It's somehow the Google
Hangout chat
That's coming through phone yes
So weird very weird
It was like
Your cat had just turned into a monster or dad started talking to you or like just turned on
Can you
So
I'm kneeling on the bed with it
And I look at it
And I think that's when I just like
Through it
Threw It On The Bed
Revulsion so
Can you turn on the screen
He picks up the phone from the end of her bed and hands it to her and is like can you pull up
The screen
Well what all apps running on this phone
I don't run any app
Is that doing video
I'm recording
At this point the cameras have like swiveled
So they're focused on the phone
Okay
Switzerland River
Can you use this Android
How do you manually get a list of apps running late by swiping down from the top or something
I think I don't know
I'm sorry I don't
How about that give me swipe down there's that sing this next to the thing
What about that thing
With
Yes
But just give me a second
I don't see a Hangouts app running
Idaho
Well
I didn't
Test run a hangout
I think it's talk you listen to it
Test test test
Bestop hasn't
Suddenly the phone stop doing the weird thing it was doing audio player
It went it went away which field hackery the hackers have been had
Just realized
Yeah that's what I think there was an attacker
And they screwed up and accidentally turned on the speaker
Yeah it's weird is it
Creepy
What do you mean packed what kind of active in
Define doubted
Private
Messages someone's been had access to them
Or is it people have been
Sending
Messages spoof
To be from you
To your friends or colleagues
Can a horrible
So eventually
They just decide to turn off her phone
Now it becomes a more civilized conversation of
What are we going to do
And then Google said to me
It's like I think I'd rather donate my body
No
Well
What would it take for you to donate your phone to science
Like in the current state of it right now
Without without like
Yeah that's a problem no way
Like that has so much
Is my work on it
And my
Okay life
I just think that
Oh I don't think I have to justify
Why
That's right you don't have to justify it
But
Do you have a Leah pictures
And some pictures but not much
I-chaya put myself in your position I would have been like
I feel okay I don't know I start
But you were very immediately like the opposite
That's a no to me why
Tumi
My responsibility is not to
Just to myself you know privacy is a shared
Resource associated with a share it's something we share with each other
I will say this is one of the first stories where I
Get
What privacy and data protection like means
Like I remember when Morgan was telling me the story thinking if someone had hacked into Morgan
Phone
How long have you been hacked in for
I charge Morgan all the time
I was kind of hat
You know and then it's like
We who else did you talk to her tell your dad was kind of crappy exchange those text messages that weren't on
Signal that person was kind of hat
Randomly just dawned on me duh like
Her privacy isn't just hers
The things that are on my phone that are private or not only private from either private for for anyone I was talking to an
Almost feel like I don't even have a right to give over that phone
If I haven't
Talk to the people that
Then that would be exposing like that's not fair like sometimes people insist on privacy can feel
Selfish
Yeah then you realize like no like
One person doesn't insist on privacy
Kind of like a chink in the armor
And like something they were all vulnerable
For about an hour Morgan and Zuko go back and forth about what to do with her phone
But they don't really reach a conclusion
Need to walk around
Is anything going to happen if I go take a little walk
Yeah you're not going to miss much
Planner schedule
I'm so sorry for no good reason I can't think of any reason for you not to take a walk
Risk of freaked out
Okay
Yeah
What
I said be safe out there
Enjoy
Do you think I meant
Do you think I'm a
Secret agent
I wasn't thinking that
I was thinking
Was afraid for you
I'm not afraid
Yeah I'm not either I was just feeling that way
I'm going to take a walk so I feel really close
So then
I had to decide
What should we do
Shall we
Abort ceremony
Focus our attention on some sort of Investigation of Morgan's phone
What should we do
Here's a decision here's what we're going to do
You get more out of here and otherwise
No change
He figured this these people have hacked into Morgan's phone we have
So many security measures in place that
We can keep going
Don't breathe us out later
So basically what happens is like
Morgan comes back from our walk
Brewery
I still have another full day of the ceremony last
Okay
And then
It gets to a point where
They finally have the final key
Everybody
The big step
Is there a high five
Unplugged
No we're done
And then
To sort of top it off I mean if you want to use the angle grinder
Everybody takes their compute node
And destroy that
Because
In the case of the computer holds like
Ghostie fingerprint of that like original piece of the key
I just wanted
Dawn saw the computer into pieces
I missed smash the pieces with a hammer
And dropped
The crushed pieces into a giant bonfire
And that was that
And now they were sort of
The moment
Weather like okay well we actually did the technological
Thing which was we created the system
And now the bigger question was did they
Create the Alchemy
Did they needed to inspire trust like we're all the protocols in the video footage and all that stuff
Was it all enough
Especially now that they have this phone thing happened the phone thing
Why did we do what we needed to do to show the world that they want to buy into this thing
So five days after the ceremony ended the currency begin
To an insane
Fanfare
Really it was
Crazy because she's a cryptocurrency built on bitcoin
It is dedicated to protecting your privacy but I think it went up like $4,000
21 zcash coin and that is
The Bitcoin High
At the time is like
Around 1400 so that's insane
Inspire
A community
To then use it it seems like it has it has done that
People continue to point back at this phone moment and wonderin speculate
Some
Yeah people of people want me to they want to know like
Power results
And how does it resolve them and did you give him your phone
So what actually happened was we went to this bonfire
And then by the end of it
Did everybody was sort of rushing off I was rushing to the to the airport and
Just like game iPhone does he go
I was like
We'll talk about it
I trust you
Don't do anything
But I haven't agreed to
So you ended in the in the in the in the spirit of the whole Endeavor in some way
Molly Webster
But you have to go through all of this again so
We have to do it again
Because
We're upgrading
Liquor tography and zcash
Good God man what have you started
We're going to do ceremony.
Deploy Nerf
Photography wheat will keep thinking of
HGTV
50ddd please
This piece was produced by Molly Webster and Matt King
Guilty Denver ceremony station recordings were created by media maker and Nathaniel Kramer thanks Nat
And also thanks to his assistant Daniel Cooper
And Leslie very special thanks to Morgan pack her reporting on the ceremony
Odyssey wizard the anchor for our peace and you can find her article at IEEE Spectrum
We will link you to it from radiolab.org
Okay we will be back in Robert will be back with me
I weeks I'm Jedi boom Run Webster
Thanks for listening
Hi this will zogbaum I'm calling from Sunny Seattle Washington
Radiolab is produced by jet album Rock
Don't keep is our director of sound design Soren wheeler a senior editor
Staff includes Simon Adler David Gable Tracy hunt
Not guilty Robert krulwich
Annie McEwen Latif Nasser
Melissa O'Donnell
Ariane whack and Molly Webster
Help from
So empower
Rebecca chiasson Niger fatalii Phoebe Wang and
Katie Ferguson
A fact checker
Is Michelle Harris