Are you awake
Northern listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
I'm rubber colon
And I'm left with Nasser
And today on Radiolab Robert I am going to make you wrestle
With
Your most cherished ideal
American democracy
OIC okay wait a second
That's troubling of the offense now I haven't okay
Okay great
Start things off by introducing you to
To Yasha
Yascha mounk
I'm a lecture on government at
David studies policy
What was what I was going to say maybe we just start with where you grew up
Yeah so I was
So I was born on a T2i
Punjabi movie
Toronto
Best friend Germany as a kid
And then went to college in England
Cambridge in mm
End
I love studying politics I was a history major so Joshua studying politics are you studying
Hit in the past so he was looking at you know going all the way back to the
Cradle of democracy in Ancient Greece and then
How democracy came to thrive around the world
But has he was studying that
He was noticing you know when the news you would see in certain countries like
France or Austria
You know there would be this
Parties
Far-right
Ultra-nationalist anti-immigrant parties
That word
Starting again
Traction
And for Yasha I saw some of this
This was a little bit
Because my family is being in the wrong place wrong time for bed for generation
His great-grandparents perished during the Holocaust my grandparents
Betty survived
The Soviet Union map
Hands clapping
Poland
And was thrown out of the car
Country Inn
Anti-semitic wave 9
68th and South
The idea of a system the TV
Disabled Emoji piece for my son Newton
Breakfast
And even violent
Do something but I suppose I always had symptom awareness off even as a kid
So I remember being quite worried by this and having friends were quite worried about it we were worried about it as
Is weed bad thing with going on
I didn't think we asked
Deformed fat
These people might win
Jump to the early 2010s
8 * 20
For the first time Elena fan will have us
Parliament
Along with seven others from her far right
Party in France they start to gain
Power and it is not just there but you swaps of Europe is also happening
Elsewhere
Similar right wing party start rising up in Italy Greece
The Netherlands Poland Hungary and identity crisis for the entire European continent
And it's not just Europe you have India turkey
And what
Started off as
United States
Impossible is now real
Basically there's this wave of politicians whose message was
People and we listening to you
Your government has failed you
Trust me
I would speak for people
I'm going to fix everything
And to Yasha this was
You know this is like a wake-up call
And not just because of
Immigration policy or right unless meanings of certain politicians
But even more deeply than that I was quite worried about the way in which these political movement
Perhaps pretended to have
Some allegiance to democratic mechanisms
But actually we were enemies.
Like there's this one guy the leader of the Austrian Freedom Party
Glorified
Besides rice
Mission Valley Raceway
Add Weehawken back to the country
Fastest pass in a positive way
That wasn't
DePauw fat
I mean
A huge number of the world's dictators have penal exit
Democratic
At some point
And then they move against Democratic institutions in such a way that
Yukon displacement
So for yahshua who made this point was a lecture at Harvard he
You know kept seeing this and Country after country after country he saw these
Citizens
Willingly electees wannabe dictators into power
And so she started wondering
What is making the citizens do this
Do they do they feel like their current leaders don't get them do they
Are they already riled up about some issue of the day like refugees or income inequality
Or
Is this a sign that they're upset
About something even more Foundation
The prison system
Itself
Like are they actually angry
With democracy itself
Anti sat down with
The friend and colleague
To figure it out and it's Brenda turns out worked on something called the world values
Ambitious attempt to try and get a public
Wikipedia around the world
Basically just a bunch of social scientist who asked a whole bunch of very standard questions
To a whole bunch of people all over the world
What's actually look scrutinize what
What's the setting hear about your mockery
And when we actually
Look at the numbers
You're honestly flabbergasted
Okay so
Exactly three questions in particular
That he got interested in poker
Start with
How do you feel about a strong ruler
Who doesn't have to bother with
Parliament
Who doesn't have to bother with Parliament or election
Yep okay
They also asked this of Americans just instead of doesn't have to bother with
Parliament it was does not to bother with Congress
So in 1995
24% of all Americans
Endorsed
That kind of strongman leader
24 / so you know one out of every four
Yeah but in the last several years that number is jump from 24
232 purse
So now it's a third almost
That sucks
Say it strong leader who doesn't have to deal with Congress or elections
Is
Either a very good or fairly good
Well that's surprising
It's it's kind of even more striking in Europe so is it in Germany
One in six people
Used to like that idea but now I'm free
Poor in Germany
Where they
Should know better in France United Kingdom
It was one in for 20 years
Is it go
And now it's 1 and 2
Half
Yeah so every second written Frenchman's Asia
The idea of a strong ruler who doesn't have to Bubble Parliament elections
Vest.
It's not appealing to me that is not appealing to me
Yeah who would say that they like the not be involved in a democracy
Which is about being involved
Okay well if you think that's pretty here come question number two
Flatout simple straightforward
How important is it to live in a democracy on a scale of 1 to 10
And when you look at
The Americans born in 1940
1940s
Two-thirds of a give
Baha'i Temple
Living
We might be with
12232 Little Star
To make sure
But I'm wrong
American spoon since 1980
It's less than 1/3
Less than 1/3
Consider it essential to live in a democracy
Stove a hundred people a hundred young people
3230 3025 it say I love democracy is very important arrest
What's a red state
It's not
It's not the most important thing for them
Deciding where to live
Okay well then if if you want if this is
Good where would you like to like what would you prefer
Would you like to be living that's a good Segway to the next
Question final question
Was about
Emiru
So do you think would amirul is a good system of God
I'm evil
So we're not with this is no civilians anymore
Soldiers running the government still just following orders soldiers giving orders
So
20 years ago
About
1 + 6
16 Americans photos good system of government
In the most recent poll a couple of years ago
It was 1 and 6
Among young and affluent Americans
Is actually
Sedona from 6
Send
235 bus
In America
What you got one in three
Young Apple in American Military was a wonderful thing
That's what you think
Exact
Yeah that's
Misguided
Or tragic
I don't know which said something he was like I didn't think of a cuddles to go there tomorrow
Once I can say this is wonderful but it does
Show
A deep lack of attachment to a control system and visit of sense of
You know what
I mean try something
How backflip
You must watch the movie
Here's the here's the thing that gets to be
Let's imagine
A well-intentioned but totally authoritarian dictator
Who takes over gets used to
Power and then
As dictators do chooses
Is to remain in place
Forever
The adventure of democracy
Is it admit
That nothing is ever right
We always have to fix it and the system
Has built in it
Impermanence
Every
6 years you are
The senator over again every two years you will like
The congressman over again every 4 years you can have the option to switch presidents presidents can't serve Beyond a particular
It will be checked
They will be balanced as they will be protection but the whole thing
Admit
But there's always change
And always the ability
And this trip that you just read me says we don't believe in it anymore that's dangerous to me
Scary to me I think my response is if that's the case and I don't argue
Happy people happy zipping
If that's the case then let's fix it
Let's not throw it out
Let's repair it in some way
That's
But that's what seems like a moment like this called
Basically you're saying
Let's fix it
Yeah
Yeah well
Eminem is theirs
Corporate money and
Special interest lobbyist and gerrymandering and minority groups don't get a voice and active voter suppression in a lot of
Places the weirdest of the Electoral College to two-party system in general where it seems like they have nothing to do except for haitani
Each other but the thing is
So just focusing like
I take this very specific week this week that we are talking about this there is a midterm election coming up
And so I figured let's like let's just focus on one thing
Baoding
Like is there a way to just
Weakness
Fundamental part of democracy like can we change the way we vote
Svet people don't
Feel as many people now do that they're throwing their vote away that they did their vote doesn't count that their vote
Is wasted
Okay so
What would you
You suggest
So
What I got is a
Kind of an alternate universe it's it's
It's a different way of doing elections
Vet
Could have
Founder effect on the way or tomorrow
Eddie can you hear me
Yes there we are good
Okay cool and we're going to start off with producer Simon Adler
Yeah so in search of democratic inspiration
I called across the ocean to the Emerald Isle to talk to this
So my name is ABC open Bowman
Attorney work for orgy radio one on the DriveTime program is a radio producer reporter for Ireland
Equivalent to the BBC known as RTE
Eddie's a self-described election nerd
Okay so
Just wanna start from the start the way I would look at this is
American democracy is
One of the oldest democracies in the world it kind of like a laptop from 1985 at the time every
Everybody was like oh my God this is incredible it's so fast it's so responsive units so much stuff done with this
You did
But you've got to keep updating your operating system otherwise pretty soon your democracy is struggling to deal with things like
Facebook news feed on Twitter and leave the cell phones being hacked by Russia
In Ireland we got our democracy little bit later
The 1920s
Okay and I thought Point democracy had moved on from
The 1770s 1780s when you guys are boring your democracy
And we adopted this
What was the important modern voting system PRS TV
TV exact
It sounds a bit like an STD
It does sound quite like a sexual transmitted infection it does yes
Other things like dead in the water
Canelo versus multi cprs TV that's really sounds like an STI it's not one more time
Say it again multi-seat
PRS
TV stands for multi-season
Portional representation
Buy single transferable vote
I have no idea what that mean
Weird as it might sound this is a system of voting.
Unlock hours
I can make every voter feel hurt
Candidate to best reflect the collective interest of the people
And it make sure no one ever feels like they're throwing their vote away
You don't have you don't have to believe impossible feet
I'm walking to the lower part of Dublin Central
Let's just put this in Concord
Great
2016 there's an election
For the national parliament in the Dublin Central.
Blocks
Brick
Row houses
Punctuated by these
Brightly colored pink or purple or yellow doors you can think of it like an election districts in Ireland
It's what's known as it considers
Couple adult stores low-rise White
Public housing unit
Working class
Kitchen sink with a lot of difficulties this is Maureen O'Sullivan a longtime resident of the constituency with
Shock white hair anime always been involved with youth clubs
Doing volunteer work
I've been teaching
In communities in the DC area
And so back in February 26th
This area of Dublin
Along with the rest of the country what was holding their parliamentary election
Elections for what they called
TD
Wait water TDS
Right okay but Gigi is the Irish Gaelic for
Chucky's daughter
Which translates into remember Parliament
At that time Dublin Central had three of these TD seats
Three people representative
Parliament
One of them
I was elected in 2009 was Marie
And I would be I am
Independent
Not allied with any party
And going in about 2016 election things were looking pretty uncertain for
A principal there was a field of 15 candidates running for the
And worse
Seat 1 and 2
We're expecting to be snagged quite easily by these two high-profile major-party can
Yeah this again is a T-bone and who actually covered this 24
16 election
They're they're not locked down but these are people who look like they are going to get Alexa
What that means is you've got this wide-open field of folks all fighting against Marine for that third and five
Who's are contenders
So we're going to focus in on two of them
Can I see a picture to introduce yourself
Yes so I married
Fitzpatrick we got Mary Fitzpatrick
On the spectrum of American politics
Do you know where you fall
You just a few parts
She's pretty liberal been around Irish politics
For while you interview me already
Secondary down hoody young community worker this Brash guy with red stubble on
His face quite interesting quote of hantik want to watch because he's representing this brand-new Politico
Floki outside Lincoln City, or anything like
Yes know what an amazing slogan it was very simple
And I was just the one word
If
Completely from fable about when the Macedonian army was marching
And defend Sparta a message saying that if we win we were born Sparta to Brown we will enslave your
Women and kill your children
What's 5% back one word message just saying
If
Like I said
Brash and then you put other voices to her last winning or environmentalist or or others
All right things actually work over in Ireland
Voting is underway in the Republic of Ireland
When does the country Alexa
New members
So day of the election comes
As a as in Irish
Citizen you walk into the voting booth and it's a very very long bowel
Because it has all of the
All 15 of them
Their photo their name and then align
Okay it in this palette is a key component
Of that updated Irish laptop of
Because instead of just feeling in the circle next to one of those two
15 you say my number one choice is this guy
My number two choices this lady my number three choices this person and you can go all the way down the ballast giving preferences
With many different people as you like
You write in a number next to eat
Each candidate about one man one vote
Well it's still one man one vote. Which can't you know it is it is it is it is
At the end of the day your vote will only have counted for one person
However in the voting process
What you're not just measuring what everyone's First Choice it looks
You might have a favor choice
But you're not totally equal but the other three choices
I'm with this system allows us to do is to reflect
It allows you to say how you feel about the rest of the
And
If your first choice doesn't make it
If he or she is way down the list
Stand out of the running
Then your boat lives on in the form of your second
So for as long as there's a viable candidate with your number on it
Your vote will stay alive in the system
Is it is it too early for me to raise a
Off of winning Thursday when wait I may ignore it but let's see it or hear it
The commitment that people make
Devoting
It's light
Most of us
Oriental lunch Sports
Work I didn't
Baby on the day of a boat they have their best friend so you got to vote for Sally
Like they know one they they're not even in 07
Yeah soap the first
It would take us more time than we want
And we might walk away from this exercise because we don't feel
Pair
You can engage with this on whatever level you'd like Robert if you only know one candidate's name you can just put your one
Next to that person and hand in your ballot and you're done or let's say there's a candidate on there you really really don't like
You can please some of the Polish entirely your ranking
Your preference
It's very simple
Fairly good answer
So let me walk you through how this
Polls close at
10 p.m. on Friday
February 26
And then
Then all hell broke
General election 2016 on RTE Radio 1 with Rachel English and Schoenherr real action begins
Going to be a tray of drama shocks and surprises so what happens is
We vote on the Friday
On Saturday morning the votes actually get counted
Dublin Central Dublin Central get stranded in one central location which is b or d s that's
Vista to Ireland's largest Concentra trt
Society
Big vault
Feeling big big hole
Huge amount of noise
No I'm joking I see with the doors open
I arrived
This what's wrong arriving
It's now Mel monkeyboo the campaign worker for our endangered incumbent Maureen
Sullivan
And on the morning of the count as he pushed his way through these
Heavy wooden doors
We would have seen with the cavernous Hall filled with
People knowing about everybody's got clipboard this
People with twins
Club sandwiches
Is made
Tea and coffee in abundance and everybody's really excited
Shortly after 9
All the boxes
Coming giant metal boxes of ballots to the boxes are open
Listen International
And there is a Cascade and a spelling of
All this paper because it's golden by paper voting
Wait what
Yeah
We tried electronic voting in this country and we didn't like it
Because it was very fast
And I think we realized that the dram of an election
And and also be
The ritual of democracy gets everybody engage and gets people watching
It's like watching a sport sports game you don't want to be up in 5 min
Dara
And soap I'm now for our life update I have to warn as we always do at this time on this day we're talk
Hawking tallies first of all which obviously can skew the results not just at the RDS and not just for Dublin Central but
All across the country both cancers are dumping boxes of boats and going through the prism of the stacks first
Intercounty is Justin McCarthy new in no particular order
Play here and they include elderly on here the counters are just trying to get a handle on how many First Choice boats
Each candidate is gay
I'm Calvin ultracarbon 100% of the boxes are open as well the ballot counters are doing this
Initial count
There's another group of people standing next to them in their own unofficial
Calculation
Yes definitely the tally man
There are several of them put forward by each candidate and they're just looking over the railing
Waiting for you to point of olive branch upstart Gary Gannon again today can cello name of the prison that got the number one
China number 1
What they're counting is number one yes they're shouting out in tallying the First Choice labeled on each ballot
So you haven't found them why they are at the races are not
Which it seems like Gary what
We have a 98% Holly are there is a growing belief here. The third seat will be between Kerrigan and getting a lot of birth prep
So I walked in a cup filled over but one of our national newspaper to do an interview
It's too early to be saying you over the line but you're going well until
All the radio researchers are coming over grab them and bring them over to speak on the radio if there's a bunch of you've done 9% as well so
And we could be in for another dogfight there Absolutely I'll cancel my weekend plans with ankle
Real no sense of excitement
Knox
Forever
So that morning I was at home doing different things again this is incumbent Mourinho set
What did you do did you make breakfast did you go for a walk
White fluffy and dog
Dry brushing for walk
Are you listening to the radio
You're totally disconnected pretty much
I left my
Campaigners clover
Vitaly
Campaigners
It's starting to hurt
Including Mouse
So what in what in the first hour from someone
The townies that we were seeing
You don't make me do not like Marius and isn't picking up
Enough votes
Sao I hope this is not going to be an early day
Where does no need for you to hang around
Cuz nobody's in the rice any longer
And I'm then I think I was driving when I got the first call
From my
Campaigners over ended the country saying it's not looking good
Alexa let's go back to the busiest to Mary Wilson and the
Rachel thank you very much
The first count
Eminence We Believe here
In Dublin Central
Meanwhile the calories take all those ballots
Now officially started by first prep
And they pick up the stack
For each candidate on the table and then walk that stack back to its wooden shelving unit again
American Dad behind the table in the center
This giant sword
Cubby
Pigeonhole
Just like light flimsy wooden box
And this is the sacred Shrine of Irish democracy on this day
The cubby
Absolutely
Because
The first preference votes in the mall in their respective cubbies
There's a whole should not part of of the Arena
And
The returning officer stands up on a stage with a microphone
And goes
Following is the result of chemical bond
Here is the first time for the constituency all double Central
Steelcase
Six six and a readout of every candidate how many number one votes did they get
20 Honda first off the bar at the end of the first
First and second are pretty much locked down with the two people everybody expected to it
In third place
Unexpectedly is Mary Fitzpatrick
To be in third position on the
First time
Now with our system of voting at this point
You're done
The election's over
To Frontrunner candidates would have each won a seat and then Mary Fitzpatrick
Wouldn't want to see
Gary and Maureen baby out
Done but
In Ireland not so
In Ireland
They're just getting started
So back to the race
And remember at this moment
Mary Fitzpatrick is in 3rd Gary is in 5th and in 7th
At that stage I was listening to the radio and I knew what they were saying about Dublin Center
Is incumbent Mourinho cell
And it appears almost certain to
Joe Costello and Maureen O'Sullivan are set to lose at
I had some
Because of the numbers I think the feeling was I was too far down that first preference
To come back
But I've been looking at the early results coming in from around the country like I said
It's not over yet so the way the most Progressive
The sheriff are the presiding officer
Start to eliminate
Candidate the first elimination
Is the bottom three candidates
Those candidacies are gone and in the band
Since Gary's in fifth and Marines in 7th are safe
For now
But the bottom three candidates
They're gone
Y3 because they are so far out that mathematically they could never
Come back
Between the three of them they've only got like a hundred fifty
So we get rid of all three of them and redistribute those
So if you voted for those people they just go okay
Who did you vote for as your second
And
The point is your vote is still alive and still part of the select
Enso
150 votes
150 ballots
They begin to do this sort of ballet
Baluster Lindy's pigeonholes
Everything is visible vote counters walk back to that Shrine to that cubby and pulled the ballot
From the cubby hole for the
3 *
Then March this ballad back to it to the front table and sort them then into bundles of
Second preference on the bottle
So now you've got
Stacks for every candidate that was listed as a second
And we distribute them they take them back to the Cubby where they are then added to the remaining candidates
First Pres
Okay okay so what they want is
Everybody who voted to the degree that it is possible
Should maybe be participating in letting somebody to go out
Exactly
Alright what time is it now we're probably middle of the afternoon at this
MLB start
We started at 9 in the morning
Point taken people are hacking by doing no no no no
I'm not watching this program for 5 hours
Is that a long time I will challenge your statement that just because a competition
Unfold
Slowly
That it is without
Drama
Or suspense
All right
I'm sorry that we making this so hard for you
That's fine if you are not making it easy for us
Anyway back to the scene has reduced to three seats
So I'm looking at this going okay
Mary Patrick Star candidate in 3rd after
The first count has 2500 votes
Gary Gannon / Liane V behind her
And my instinct is he's going to be more transfer friendly he's going to get more second choice votes than her
I think you could ever take her
Am I start watching where the transfer to going
And
I start to be proven rice
Knife pocket only getting two countries the whole process repeats knock somebody out to the ballet ballet redistribute
Transfers Gary gulman pics of 60 votes
And I could possibly pick up stuff so he's gaining on her already to talk about me asking who is this going where is he going from
All these things and then look at my phone call Mary stock is falling well Gary their right is that Mary stuck is saying stop
You know we were struggling to transfer stuff that was the issue
And the others are gaining on
It painting
Undermined you still got other people taking up both their little pickups
Nautilus for moving ahead slowly
Hounds, you have for again
The time around really not much changes
Then come 5
The next person going I just got a hundred bucks
31 of them but Maddie Fitzpatrick but also 190 of them go to go to Gary Gannon
All the people in his ability to pick up transfers from
Gary gulman
Jumped into fourth place
We got quite a fight now in her hands B standings as they are still at the place of Mary Fitzpatrick in third place
Just barely holding on in 4th
Hot on her heels is Gary Gannon and then way at the back of the pack still in 7th is incumbent Maureen O'Sullivan
Play it had five or six
Cuz he'll we're back
This is where two two big things happened
What are the frontrunners expected to take
It's over the line and also
Gary Gano jumps into third place it was pushing Mary Fitzpatrick out of a winning spot
It was on the transfers I got cost never recaptured
The woman who under our system would have worn off the bat
Cheap locked out
Yellow
Still hanging on in second-to-last but but also disheartened is our incumbent Mourinho cell
Who's expecting to
And I suppose maybe seven
People started to arrive
She actually invited her campaign staff and volunteers back to her place
For a concession
And I said when people came in
I don't want to know anything about the elections
I got you tomorrow
Unknown to me because I was busy with the T in the Dream Center food
Some of them in the house
Still in contact with those over in the RGS
Constituency into a reporter Damien Omar development
One of those guys still over in the IDF
Was Mel
My dudes
Iverson
Looking at the numbers and saying when
Okay
Bus
If
Then maybe
Does the chance
It was just a thought to have
All day the media have been saying that Marine without going to be
Might be eliminated seven something starts to happen
Priefert coming around the bend down and looks like he's in Pole Position
But I was certainly wouldn't reallocating people second preferences ever toured preferences
We got the stage where we're reallocating people's toward fifth and sixth preferences cuz keep in mind most people
Boats are still flashing around the
Little Point not only has their Top Choice been knocked out but their second and third as well as their vote
It is now being capped for their fourth fifth or sixth place choice and a lot of those
They are going to Maury so even people
Number one number two number three their votes were still carrying pasta for dinner
Boys I'm just small neon those transferred
Massive jump
Boating her
The head of two opponents into 4th Place
Now just a couple hundred vote-buying Gary
And they decided not to tell me
Doctor raised my hopes
The candy axe
They redistributor boats
It's it's coming down it's coming down to it when I count up those transfers
Lucky to be elected or what's the situation there Marine get some 300 more transfers than Gary
Meaning suddenly
Oh my God I did Nazi that coming
Cheaper than eight votes
Quarter to ten but Maureen mean while it is still convinced she's going to lose
She's actually heading down to the count Center to
Concede the race
I said to myself I should go over and concede so and can most into the car and as I'm driving over
To concede
I was just at the traffic lights I can picture it
I'm at that stage
The phone call comes
She looked at her phone and it's one of her campaign staff
I I don't know why they'd just hurting me up to get over whatever but in fact they were calling because
Central Roofing
Just as I mentioned your name brand for going to dump in Sanford
This is the results of the 11th
For Dublin
Central
I like dim the following candidate to be Alexa
Are they are
Maureen O'Sullivan
In her car Maureen did eventually pick up
Where are you you're about to be like
You're going to be Alexis
She put down the phone drove to the count Center
And when she arrived
Grace God's grace hugs and kisses so it was just
Explosion of
Feeding
Warm feelings
Towards me from everybody
Maureen O'Sullivan congratulations
Thank you very much relieved woman
I'm assumed woman I was home reconciled to a new life outside of politics and then suddenly I'm back in the frame
We had felt that we were too far behind
I know what Lancer is felt like
Kind of moments
What song is this the story of a
Multi-seat
Proportional representation by single transferable vote
Working out
Exactly as it is meant to or is this sort of a pro version of the Sith
No it absolutely is it woke that they will tell you exactly a single transferable vote was meant to do
One Last Time be gracious Gary
Everybody got their cut everybody got their saying everybody got their vote don't get me wrong
It is
2829 Dan Lake of the u.s. sense of like
Will show you
Lego movie back
So
Single transferable vote on. They work against me
Reno
I think it worked out perfectly
Perfectly
I mean let me just see if I get this right
There's this woman
Maureen
Who
Hardly anybody loves she's hot
Scores almost no
Boots at the favor
She's just everybody's beer
No AA 4th 5th 6th I'll choose
Marine
And yet because the votes to keep getting shuffled and shoveled and shoveled
It's missing that who becomes
The winner
But she's she's chosen because a lot of people
Don't
Heater
Yeah what's up
Here's what it makes me think
Right and I had this moment where I was just
Imagining
If we had been using this at various
Crucial moments in our
Very recent history
Things could have gone an entirely different way
Take the American presidential election of 2016
Okay between Hillary and Donald Trump
Hillary Clinton but also
Gary Johnson and Jill Stein
Hardly hardly anybody that number of hardly anybody
That was that's a sizable enough number
That they
Could have swung the election one way or the other if you look at
Veliki state
The deciding States
If you presume
Gary Johnson votes were split and if you presume all of Jill Stein votes went to Hillary Clinton Hillary Clinton would have
Pennsylvania
Michigan
And Wisconsin
And the whole kitten Kaboodle
Well that's
Interesting
Another weird thing is you can just keep playing this game and and it'll drive you crazy but you can keep playing until if you go back to
2016 Republican primaries where Donald Trump emerged
Victorious right over 10 people or something
Over 10 people
But there was a sizable number of people in those primaries
Two word never Trumper
If those people had been able to block their votes together they might have been able to
Rally behind a candidate who is not
Donald Trump
It and then rewind even further back
The 2000 election where
The number of books that Ralph Nader. In Florida more than the difference between Bush got and Gore got no elected elect
The Republic
Can you okay so it's so go back
To rust
Wright's George HW Bush was running against Bill Clinton in 1992
Ross Perot it's
Very controversial whether he really was a spoiler in that election but
I mean if you ask them to Bush People they say definitely was
If the perimeters went to Bush's that been
Like Bill Clinton would have just being a historical footnote he wouldn't have being the president
Like it's like a
Huge
Huge seismic difference in
In world history
So
When we come back
We're not going to be looking at my own imaginative math we're going to look at what is ranked choice
Actually look like
It was in the United States
Because it is in the United
That's about to happen
When we come back
Hi my name is Corey and I'm from Minneapolis Minnesota
Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world
More information about Stallone at www.slha.org
Welcome back on
Acrylic I'm lot of Nasser in this is Radiolab
And we're trying to fix them up
Alice Topix
Little bits and pieces
We have been
Talking about this and thinking about this around the office for
For a little while
At some point as we were as we were
Become meditating on this dwindling faith in democracy one of our
Fellow producers that our sister show more perfect
Sarkari
She just took me and Simon great
Rates and just drag us into his suit
Okay so
We've been having this
Conversation about
Whether our democracy is broken for like a
A few months now and like
Every meeting that we've had I've been the one in the room being like
Guys are democracies finally have you seen other places
This is crazy like who are these people that
Think like
Our democracy is broken like they don't know what
They're talking about and you know why I like where where where is that feeling coming from
Well okay can you tell me your name
And who are you probably because of this woman I was
I was over you in relation to me
Oh I'm your mom my mom is
And both of my parents actually
Grew up in Pakistan that is the
Fixing 25 years of my life that I spent and I
Field which is
A pretty young country and its
It's just struggled so
Much too
Keep its democracy alive and healthy
And
I saw and the consequences of
Not getting the full demo democracy
There in Pakistan
Soda
That then after living 25 years of next 25 years of my life in America
I really found out the value
Off for democracy
As an individual and as a group also
So that I can differentiate now
Maryville
Getting to the store
So
That's kind of how I've always understood our
Button Simon I listened to your Ireland story with
All of the
Does ranked-choice voting stuff in and that's the first moment when I was like
Like maybe
Maybe our way of doing things is
Broken leg
Maybe we do need a nap
Okay okay
What about it
Make made you
Switch teams
Because
Maybe suddenly aware of the fact that in our system Candice
Don't
Actually need a majority of the votes to win
You have canvas who then make that calculation where they say
I only really have to win the votes
People who are in my base
If that's
If those if my base is bigger than everybody else's base
Then like screw everyone else
It is seems like in a democracy
People should vote for the
Person who win
Not just that the person who wins is going to have the biggest
Bass
Bigger base that everybody else
Like it should be that most people are in some way and some preference
Supporting the first in Utah
Yeah exactly and it's funny like
When I heard about ranked-choice voting I was like
Oh like this system is so cool because it
I feel like it addresses that exact
Problem
And so I totally got sucked into it and I
I started looking around
And it turns out there are a bunch of people who think that this
Could be used here in the US
And not only that it already is
And when I asked around
A number of people appointed to this moment in
Mm with the election when
Bush loses the popular election but he wins
Because he wins in Florida
And so people look at the the results in Florida and see that
A bunch of votes that
Might have gone to Al Gore
They go instead to Ralph Nader
Who then becomes
You know sort of notorious as the spoiler that
That maybe
Ruin the election
Infer Al Gore
And after 2000 at that point you do see some cities that
Start to adopt ranked-choice voting
At the local level
And so what I did is
My phone
I grabbed let this and we kind of did this
Cross country ranch Choice voting tour
End
The first place we're going to start with
Hello San Francisco
Is San Francisco
Is it Dominic
Yes this is Dominic what's up
What's up
So this is
Dominic fracassa
He used to do radio pipes for it Dominic hey let me know if you need me add spot
So we can get right to it
But he order at the San Francisco Chronicle
City Hall reporter for the chronicle
Yeah so the very first ranked-choice election in Sanford
Francisco happened in 2000
But it was actually a ranked-choice voting became
I guess the cities method or the city
System if you will back in 2002 where there was a a ballot and it
It's that was passed by voters
That said like this is going to be the system that that we're going to implement going forward
So the vast majority of local elected office
Is are are chosen with with ranked
So city council supervisor
School Board
Assessor-recorder
One very specific election
In the mayor's race
The case
In the mirror
Okay great
I can't believe this was just that a few months ago
It seems like a long time ago
Okay so early 2018
The San Francisco mayor's race
Kicked off
And when it really kicked into gear if there were
Three leading
You had
Hi I'm bored
London breed
You had
Hello
Former San Francisco supervisor Mark Leno
And you had
A current supervisor I Jane Kim
And these aren't these are all Democrats
The field of candidates
Set down
Okay
So out of the gate San Francisco
London breed
This camp
Pain
Is a winning campaign
He was the more moderate more established Kansas
She's getting one heck of a bounce in the polls
And she had a fairly strong lead in a lot of wind in her sails
The closest rival
Mark Leno
And as a campaign has made its way to election day
We are winners
It was almost like
Sure there are three names on the ballot
But today was more like London breed London breed
And London breed
The favorite in the recent polls heading into
Tuesday's election
But then
Right before the election
Something happened that you basically never see
In American politics
Never believe that
In the very last few weeks
Before election day
The two underdogs Jane Kim and Mark Leno
They held a press conference on the steps of City Hall
Mark and I are
They stood outside City Hall literally join hands and said
Porter
Wait a second
So what you think of me but also vote for
This
Guilin running again
Yeah exactly
Vote for me first
Vote for James II
Vote for me first and vote for marks
So like if one of us were to come in last
Like what they Mark comes in
If all the people who voted for him ranked Jane as their second choice
Then all those votes would go to her
And vice versa
That way
They actually have a better chance
Of beating the front runner
London breed
And that made it
A lot of sense they were both quote-unquote more Progressive
If candidates and you know
Saw each other at least the rhetoric goes
Add
The person that they'd like to
To see as marriage
If not them still
Was that was that a surprise move to you as you were covering it did you see that coming
No I think that was it
A surprise to a lot of
Supporting both
Jim and Mark
Vermeer
After that press conference
Jane Kim
Started appearing in campaign ads
Campaigning
For one another
UShip
Is it basically the whole campaign is like if you don't vote for me first and at least feel for me II
Kpix 5 Joe Vasquez is with the London breed
Campaign we're just MoMA
Reed address
The crowd Joe so
On Election night
London breed has a
Pretty commanding lead
As the poles are coming to a close
Basically she's trying to get up to this marker of
50% of the vote
Plus one
That's a majority
And if she can get to that
Then she went there's no rank choice
Runoff there's no vote swapping
And as the night goes on declaring victory
But this crowd is celebrating
She's got like a double-digit z
Like things are looking pretty good
They are celebrating the person they believe could be the next mayor of San Francisco
Holy smoke she's beating Mark Landau by 10
Percentage points
And she's beating Jane came by
So we're getting to midnight I'm completely bleary-eyed staring at my laptop
Refreshing the Department of Elections
State every few sec
When
12:30 at night
It happen
She came in
Just shy 50% all of a sudden
This entire race has changed
Okay so the rankings have been
Lemon tree number one
Mark Leno number two
But when Kim got eliminated a huge chunk
Herberger's
About three out of four went to linode
Because their second choice
Razor thin margin
Jim leonhard strategy
Head come to fruition .8
4%
Women
The mayor's race is still too close to call
The race would actually drag on for days as more ballots get counted
Thousands of outstanding balance
We didn't have a mare chosen until I think eight days later
When in a gymnasium packets
Screaming supporters
Outlet
The new mayor of San Francisco
Yes
Mark Leno came up
Chester
He came within 1.1% or a
A little over 2500 votes
Oh man
So I mean
Okay it didn't work in that he didn't win but you can't say that it was
Is completely ineffective
And so so ultimately what did people think of
This hole like Mark
Leonard Gene Kim coming together
Strategy as
Xgaming the
As saying look
They are doing this
In order to keep London breed
And that would never got your paper right
Right that was that at
I mean people do feel that
That it was this
Strategy
Especially when
42 *
Who saw a teaming up a piling on and in this I mean just to kind of
Zoom out all the way I think people just
Find that weird in
A country
In which
Politics ends up being a
A zero-sum game
In which you are you know relentlessly
We attacking you
Bloodsport
Yeah exactly
Exactly
But
At the same time that's very much
Either might be some people at my own newspaper that.
Disagree with me but I think that's
Very much in the
Spirit of what rank Choice voting invites
Coalition-building
Dominic wanted to be clear the
In the case of the mayor's race
This coming together of opponent
I don't want to make it sound like it was just some kind of Kumbaya.
You know because that rude that was
But
At the very next stop on Archer
We actually fell
The Kumbaya
Hey Curtis are you there
Which
Also on the line we have let this
Hi how you doing
Hey what's up
We heard about
From this guy
Curtis Gilbert and I'm a reporter at American public media
But I used to be a reporter in Minnesota
What radio
So Curtis told us
In Minneapolis they actually started using ranked-choice voting in 2009
But getting much more interesting since the
Sew in
2013 was the first time Minneapolis actually had like a competitive mayor's race
Under ranked-choice voting
Rent-A-Wreck
Record-breaking number of Canada
Minneapolis mayor RT Rybak
Who's stepping down
The end of this year
35 candidates
Signed up to run to replace him
Yeah
Curtis Gilbert covers
Minneapolis politics
He joins me in studio
Are you back in I mean there were so many
1035 cannabis is a lot
Unlike the racing San Francisco the Mayoral race in Minneapolis
People say aren't you the Republican
Did have
More diverse
Kansas Republican party and I also stand
Fiercely
For marriage equality always have
There was
A Republican and independent a bunch of Democrats it was a wide-open free-for-all race and it was real
Really it was really interesting that
Despite all that
They were
Very
Civil
Thank you very much it's nice to see you're not
Utterly infallible
Ohio
Very very
Gentle to each other
We won't be rude with each other
What doesn't benefit us to be rude
And this is one thing that you know The Advocates of ranked-choice voting serve look at as a pot
You know voters voters are turned off by negative
And there's a
Theory
That goes that if you're hoping to get like second and third choice votes
You'll be much nicer to your opponent so you don't alienate their supporters so maybe you get a second or third choice vote
And it did seem
Like
There is an element of that playing out
I'm in in the race
I will
Talk more about
All the issue
Cuz I think I've run out of
Thank you at work there was like
Some light ribbing
Tencent
They were polite
Stage Logistics
Getting out of that chair is a little challenging
So we may want to
The microphone around
And
Plenty of
Yeah I mean
The most remarkable one of all
What's the final two
I was there and it was in it
Church in Downtown Minneapolis with the church was
And at the
The end of the debate
The candidates and I think there were eight of them
All
Kind of put their arms around each other and one of them suggested that they all sing timer but I am I was
Kumbaya
No
After the debate after the debate
That's going on Instagram
So it's like I mean it's almost like a cartoon right like the Kumbaya it's really
Funny
Right but it's also
It's
It's also I think for a lot of people right now that
Feels like a relief
If you'll take a relief to hear politicians not biting each other
Heads off
And that
That's something that comes from ranked-choice voting you fine
Consensus you find Coalition you find
Commonalities
Difference
But
That also
Flattens everyone out if everyone ends up running to the middle
And then you just
Have kind of a
A bland consensus
Yes or no one's saying bold things
And everybody is just
Kind of
Middle
So in a way when you make this Choice your choosing
Do this carefully
What is careful
I wondered about that cuz I'm thinking maybe don't do this carefully
Maybe have a country that can be dynamic level right now
Yeah
We are that is in deep in a deep way that's what's being asked him like what do we
What do we actually want
Do we want a system where
You know you are lined up behind your Alpha Dog who's going to who's going to argue for all of the things you want
Want an end and maybe you can get them but maybe you're also going to lose them all or
Or do you want it do you know being a system where you know your
We're all kind of
Started begrudgingly bought into
Irr second-place person who get behind but like
Definitely wasn't
He knows how to write deal and I think that's a question
That's like a soul-searching kind of a question
Michael what do you want and what we want this country to be and for that reason
Like I don't know how I feel
Just going to be perfect I think it's really interesting is what seemed sort of mechanical
And
Technical
It does
The tone
Your country and history so the world we've got is the function
How we vote
Change this
System.of always vote
Can I get a very different world
What different what different we're different food China different scary different good different
You don't know
Well we might actually know soon
Because I actually have one more stop
Cross country ranked Choice voting tour the Great
State of Maine
Super politically diverse
Fiercely independent like a lot of independent voters
An infected in 2016 there was this
Coalition of Independence and Democrat
That Minister get this
Ballot initiative
That would change all Statewide elections to ranked-choice voting
Statewide
Yeah
And Rachel's voting was
Adopted into
16 according to Maine public radio reporter Steve mistler
It passed
The past however
With a major flaw
BM
Undermine the Integrity of our election process
The state
Senate
Was under Republican
Control at
The time
Picked up on
Is constitutional conflict
Within a conflict within the state
Constitutionality is we're not happy with it
Like my post
The main Constitution literally says you have to use a plurality vote the word plurality is actually written
In the Constitution as opposed to a majority
Correct
And ultimately the Maine legislature
Past
Oh law
That delayed implementing
Ranked-choice voting
This is one more example
Of where
Yeah politician
Ark standing against
And it set off this whole fight where where people rallied against the state legislature and held another vote
In June
Literally this
This past June at the Statehouse this
Morning to get around the delay
Nature through what
Was billed as a people's veto
That passed
I almost the exact same margin
If not slightly more
In what it passed originally in 20
At some point the main Supreme Court gets involved
And really the details of this are all kind of a mess but
What it boils down to is
Any upcoming election
Like the midterms that are happening now
Maine will use
Ranked-choice voting
For its Congressional races
We have three of them this year
We have a first congressional
District race
It'll be used in that contest and also in Maine's 2nd congressional district
Which is a swing C1
You know what dozen or so nationally AK one of the districts that everybody's going to be watching in the midterms
And on top of that they're going to use
Ranked-choice voting for the Senate US Senate
Campaign will be using that contest
4 position in the federal government
Yeah no other state has ever done it but
At the same time because of their state constitutions not being used
In the gubernatorial race
So does the ballot just like look in
Same like
Part of it is like
Ranked-choice voting thing and
And part of it is
Isn't like they're just suck
So they're separate ballots for the federal races and then there's a separate one for the Statewide ones
I haven't actually seen how many ballots that voters are
So this is really going to happen now like like
This week yeah oh yeah
Two main claims of ranked-choice voting or being put to the test
In the very first and it's very first
Roll out in Maine
Voters in Maine will head to the polls later this month can work for
A third party or independent candidates
But is also a test case
About whether or not
It does what it promises
You just told another big
Right in front of everybody
You're lying about my roaches reproduce
Scorched-earth campaign
Slide
21 *
Also
I guess I'd I just wonder if
The people of Maine are going to come out of
This election
Feeling
A little bit more like
Like democracy is working for them
Wouldn't it be interesting
If
In Maine somebody who was you know everybody's 8
Choice
Gets elected to congress
This Radiolab was reported by lots of assert Simon Adler and Susie lechtenberg sarkari Tracy hunt
Produced by Simon Adler Matt kielty sarkari choose lechtenberg our story on PRS TV
Was produced with support from RTE DriveTime huge thank you to them as a people making that possible
Rob Richey at fairvote John sorry Diana leygerman 52 on Alderman and the rest of the team at the variety
Use of democracy Institute in Sweden as well as Carolyn Tolbert Bobby Ag and Edward still
And thanks for listening
And go fo what the hell right
Hi this is Jenna calderoni calling from Raleigh North Carolina
Radiolab was created by Jad abumrad and is produced by Soren wheeler
Dylan Keith is our director of sound design
Maria Manchester Padilla is our managing director our staff includes Simon Adler Becca Bressler
Rachel Cusick David Gamble
Bethel happy Tracy hunt Matt kielty Robert krulwich Annie McEwen
Lots of Master Melissa O'Donnell
Aryan whack Pat Walters and Molly Webster
With help from FEMA Ali Ali Bo and mo at the BMO are fact checker
Is Michelle Harris