Are you awake
Northern listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
And NPR
Hey I'm Jared I'm Rod this is Radiolab Roberts traveling
Today so it's just me
And today we have a very different kind of story than we've ever done I'd comes from
A journalist and filmmaker named Lou Estrellas
Interesting thing going to happen as we were reporting this
Sounds pretty clear
Yeah
That got to be a landline
Louis and I one of our producers Tim Howard had to call up
This guy Vladimir saballos
Who is
Filmic himself
Cuban guy exile
The interview that happened to be just a few hours after Obama had made that big announcement
Today
The United States
In the most
Can changes
In our policy
More than 50 years
That happened just before the interview hello is this
According to how you doing
This is Tim in New York and we also have Lewis
High-blood it's a increase
How are we screwed good news now
Yeah meeting news ready
Really
Yeah what's crying man
First of all
You know I've been here in the United States
20 years
I never
Interesting.
I was going to see the state you know
Will begin
To normalize
Because
He says being 50-50
G 53 GR
Since the United States
You know bro the relationship with
Diplomatic relationship with
Nothing happening to you
You know everything's the same
Now
Everything is going to change
Today at
Collaboration with fantastic program radio ambulante Louis strass comes to us from them
This is a story that
Predates the stuff you've been hearing the news in many ways it's maybe
Tiny dark
Preamble
To all of that stuff to story about Cuba
Power of music
Who decide to opt
Out
In this crazy way that when Louis strass told us about it we almost couldn't believe
So the reason we called up Ladi is that we wanted to hear
The backstory of all of this
I was boring
Pinar Del Rio 1964
Tell me about
What what it was like for you to be a kid
I was happy
Because
Nqr we didn't have any information
We don't have any communication with anybody outside Cuba
Anybody seen that we receive
You watch the you know the news that the government want to give us to us
He remembers listening to endless fuelcaster
Beaches on the radio
When I was a key then
Elementary School
All the time they were
Teaching us.
Russia
What's the big
Country in the world the big economy on ABC now
Easter be like then
It was a given that
She would
Getting line every year to get high
A story you know I only got 3 toys every year
Because of rationing exactly and then every week
He and his folks
Wake up they would go to the nearest nearest church to trolex
Eye discharge
Building throw a cause we believe in God the government
They didn't believe in God you know
That's that's how you showed you were good revolutionary and
Vladimir was
Just being a good boy
But when he turns 14
There comes a day when
Friend takes him aside
It shows him a video of
Led Zeppelin
I remember that day I remember like it
Remember what Led Zeppelin song it was
Costume
Cashmere oh yeah yeah cartoon
What's my first time
Rock and roll music
How did how did it make you feel
When you hurt Cashmere
Well
Different
You know you sear on a plane
Can you see Jimmy Page with those long hair on
The movies that they have
Thing that they say
What's the difference
Ketosis diet
Complete the chain
Computer tray my life
Not sure why
But in that moment I eat I went from inclusive song
What is the weather
So free keys are what Cubans call the mostest
Stream Metalhead
Hard Rock
Punk rockers with Tire waving Musical
Clothes with holes
A long hair
Problem what
If you want me to rub your station didn't put any rock music
Download Remember When
I was 19 years old 20 years old
My father give me Russian radio
I was a good after I'm we wouldn't do that to the roof or some friends because
And those roofs you can listen to the station from Florida
Lumine wearisome drawing Stone
A sympathy with the Devil
Hello baby girl
That I didn't like another
I came from there in English was good you know
Because I don't know
What kind of music
Give us
Another
Not door
So glad he's walking around with
Ripped jeans long hair and
That's fine
The normal youth Rebellion
In the late 80s
Everything chain
Mr. Gorbachev
Open this gate
Gorbachev tear down this wall
The Wolves went down
Indian reaction
Burlington nacionalismo
That is slogan is painted freshly all over Havana Socialism or death
Suddenly music you listen to became very ideological and if you listen to rock you were listening to the enemy
Of the Cuban state do United States government create in every neighborhood every 5 blocks
Vladimir says this is the police found when you have long hair that beat us keep us send you away from
Work putting sugar cane in the cane fields in school they don't cut your hair against your will
He was abused
And just jump and disappoint the story where things take a very
No way to say it a very punk rock turn because into this cultural War that's a guy name
Bubble we naming and Pop-A-Lock Pop-A-Lock Bella
Male Papa the bullet
I really want to say that he tried to embody that
That's kind of bullet to your brain that
Wake up
That's robbery I know he's a professor at Southern Oregon University
Be wet several times in the 90s to Cuba to interview Bible who he calls to Kurt Cobain of the freaky
Yeah he looked very intense
He was Cocky and Confident and just charismatic
Super tall skinny
Your wig where are American flag
Bandana
Jesus Diaz and Luis Hernandez who is also about Native his
Cuando abren Alyssa. Miami cast
So Lewis remembers the first time he met Popple and it was
On a night
That
Communist Party meeting was taking place right outside
Outside the building I'm going
When Papa is coming
He's coming in bicycle
We he's here
Aeroflot United States flag
I need head
Yeah my father
My father
Going
A second deal with the American flag
Musically
How do I do crazy taking you fly
All you had
The Bible say why
Why on everyone
Outside the building
Silence
Papa was
It was a weird guy
Tagaytay
For were you interviewed Papo and some of the other
And that documentary Papa talks about growing up
Poor father is an alcoholic
Mother abandonment
The broiler Solana Beach 14 he's in the streets
And a few years later he makes
Decision
It's really at the heart of the story
So that you can understand
Context
What happened was that
1989 I think 1990 somewhere around Erica Cuban government is fighting
In Angola it's backing a leftist Liberation movement and it's kind of a proxy war with the United States
And in the ladies
Cuban soldiers
Start coming back home some soldiers from the Cuban army they wearing in Africa
They came with with HIV
HIV positive because of that the government has
All the people who are tested with HIV virus group you are test
They went to the
Do you place a word they went to your bottom and they went to the school that went to
Everybody
I remembered it wouldn't do it to my warranty test everybody over there and their value station
50 people's over there
Give me your bro give me your bro give me your bro give me the blood bloody says they would come in
Take your blood and if they found that you were positive the police game
You in there in the police car
I go straight to the Sun
They just like you are
Yeah I remember
I remember one day I was talking to him Papa and his wife
Look
I want to live free
Look they're kicking me out there beating me all they don't they don't want me to leave
Like a Rokia
They are
Doing a lot of things to me
I'm going to do a lot of thing today
He told me look I went to this District counseling via Clara Papa told him
These other Rock
Chris Stewart
A+
I went and took a
Syringe
Do some blood from their arm and
I put
Bonito in my own arm
Can I get my service HIV
Gimme Shelter
Global
Contaminated with
Wechat
HIV you know
Look at me
Do you know what you did
You know what you doing
Going to Diamond
I said to me
I don't care
That's crazy that's crazy
Heat he knew for sure that when he did that that he
Did that was a death sentence
Porzingis
He knows
Vladimir is not quite sure that the others that came after Papo
Really knew what they were New England
But but Papa new remember
Someone say that
Supposed to meaning
That is a door
When you don't have any more doors to open death is a door
Coming up
That door gets wider
Others walkthrough
At least something besides that something quite the opposite
Message
Hi my name is sweet and Radiolab
Wooden park by the office Bistro foundation and happy public understanding Science and Technology
The modern world more information about www.
Loan. Org
Radiolab is produced by WNYC and distributed by NPR
And this message
Okay I'm jeroboam Rod this is Radiolab
One two one two
Check that's Luis Reyes of radio ambulante is back to his story about Cuba and music in the late eighties and nineties and
Sofara dude
Has made a crazy 2
Dude named Papo
To inject himself with HIV
Would you call a protest
I think
Papa would have called it a protest
The guys that came out
This is at a moment when there was a cultural work happening between the Castro government and anyone had deemed antisocial
Could include the kids with long hair to listen to rock and was also a moment where if you
Were found to be hiv-positive in Cuba
You were forcibly
Quarantine
So Papa injects himself and he gets
Sent to the Sanitarium
And can you describe the place like what did he find
Well he found a beautiful place in the middle of the
Pinar Del Rio Countryside
Full of
Palm trees
Dairy Queen Berry Lush
Farm animals
Roaming In
Any weather
Yes yes I wish I was there
I was there and there are still
How far am I
Couple of cows and
Chickens it's it's like
Kind of an idea
So I went there to visit the last two rockers that still remain in the place your son go away on his way
Honda
And they're kind of like
The keepers
Of all that went down in there
The memory
Couple dates with them and they
And it's cool like these blue
Housing units
And you're saying this place is idyllic even back then
Pearson and John are walking through it and they're like okay so we would be walking around here 10 years ago and
Nirvana would be coming out of here
NE Bana
Single Metallica
NC Symphony
No kidding
Yeah so it was like Headbangers ball and
How come they were able to have the
That freedom in the sanatorium but not outside initially the sanitarium system
What's under the military
And
It was
More of a gulag
But in the late 80s early 90s
The Sanitarium
Went from
The military being in charge
To the ministry of
Health and Medicine
And
These were by all accounts
Very Progressive doctors
Are you concerned about their patients
They gave them all the
Food and medicine they needed
And they were like
You want to rock how it go ahead and so is like a prison but is also kind of a little bubble of freedom
Yeah
Strangely enough to be soon found out that
Steven
Had
Power
How are they didn't have before Larry told me this
Story
Patience is at the sanitarium to go out
Every 21 days
Four-day trip and some of the freakiest would go out and just buy flashing their ID cards that said they were
4/8 patients
Movies with leave them alone I remember
Dollar Tree location.
The boys getting up after sitting
One of them
Hey
Getting
A syringe syringe
And he says the guy
Took out the blood and waved it
The police I said
You want to come to me
Into me
And they were friends.
It's so weird TNT
Read about what life is like inside
Scentarium
And you have to keep in mind that outside
Cuba was falling apart hard Economic Times in Cuba the government has a Titan red rash
And raise egg prices it blamed delays in Soviet shipping
What's the Cuba almost overnight after the fall of the Soviet Union
Cuba was left without
Massive subsidies that used to get
That meant long lines for bread
We're suffering
Latimer survivors who never actually lived inside the sanitarium pieces that people outside we're going hungry
He himself I was waiting like
100 pounds
Lele pons
Oh my God
And
Things just keep getting worse
Escape on a raft and make it to the Florida Keys
These days more Cubans than ever
Taking the risk
I was a big crisis you know the king Tom Lehrer
But if you were in the sanatorium
You are fine
Yeah just being able to get milk
End
Beans laureano says that that was
Big motivation for lot of kids yes I'm not going to be harassed yes I'm free
And yes I also get
Meals
And
It went
From being a couple of self injectors a couple of dozen self injectors
Being
Hundreds
When did the government know this is happening
Cuando Murio Swedish documentary from the time it's called SoCal
Worth it and any threats this
Bishop Cabana
Opportunity
And he says that he met some of the kids that were injecting themselves with AIDS
And
That at a state dinner he approached Fidel
I told him
DB skid steer after injecting themselves in infidel
Complete right now
And then after that
The pharmacy
They don't sell sireesh anymore
They put aloe
Duffy Julie injured inside with HIV you want to spend eight years in prison
But
It didn't matter what sneaking movement
What's Niki Moon
Son you have all these bands forming crusty Island in different Sanitarium
In the biggest one of the mall in Santiago de la Vega Los Cocos which is like a half hour 45 minutes
Yep first group that that gets worms called the Yachats translate to Chinese
But then in center of the island is down coat Santa Clara you had the Cuban punk band the score yet
And Korea translate since come right escoria
And according to Bob if you look back to the 80s who were fleeing Cuba that about Settles
The Raptors
One of the responses of the Cuban government where Billboards that's at camp
Let the scum leave
So to call yourself escoria
Call yourself scam that is punk rock
And with these bands a big outside the sanatorium to I mean you can't talk about keeping Punk
I mean it's cool it's like
To the tapes got out
Yeah
Totally it would have its next meeting these bands are forming kids are self-injecting does it just keep growing and growing
Yoga Pod
There's tape of her Salon Yolanda saying
That it got to be so fashionable that
Kids diet
Think that in order to be freaky
You have to have a
Like it was
Witches
And the kids were saying that if you really wanted to be a rocker in that time you had to have a
It's like
Did the factory went from 10 or 20 to 200 or more
It was
Obviously they could this kind of just
Joyner phenomenon
I'd like that so cool I'm going to do it too
91 mph in km
There was even talk among some of the young people I met of thinking that I'll eventually Fidel and those guys will find a cure
Going to find a cure for
Cute with the one of the best health
Care Systems in the Western Hemisphere
Everything start to change when
The first of the night
According to bloody the first kid that died in Philadelphia was a guy named Manuel
Apus last name
Ice Age
On the second die
I want the third eye
Everything
At one point in Freddy's documentary with just made in 1994 sister in 2 years
About 18 people died
SMS app
They start seeing how you die
Because you don't die like
Normal person when had a heart attack
A lot of them went blind
Then they went insane
They started getting opportunistic diseases you know how its Works seen that this time thinking about what they did
Did kids start saying
They wish they hadn't done this documentary and and that Swedish documentary association with the
Juice made in 1995
You
Definitely see the kids having
Deep regrets
You have one of them saying
X
Well
I don't I never heard Papa
Ever
Question that he had done it
I didn't that Swedish documentary there's a scene towards the end where you see Papo and he's clearly sick
Real thin
Swollen
MGM stepping into an Evangelical Church
He's wearing a Nirvana T-shirt
But he's become
A fervent Christian he's found his community
Of Evangelical Christians that accepts AIDS patients who still taunting the government
Because he says
Still a rocker and that he thinks
Crysis 2
Perfect communist
More Communists were like
Christian
That would be perfect
It's interesting though because in that last video we also
See him taking English classes
Money
I knew he saying like you know
Sick like me
Rock out till the early morning
But I'm like
Fix my life
Toyota certified
To the end
CLA
And a few months later
Cursing
Apple started to
Redoubt
Now he would do it online today to download
And I
Forget embarrassing Reserve
He had a parasite
Can you sprain
Came
Violet
He died
That disease
Apartment Hunters like is this strong and fierce or is it
Dumb
It may be fierce also I can't figure out a field
Yeah well I think it can be all those things right it was dumb and stupid and immature and it was also
Nihilistic
In an arcade
It had any impact
Well
That's that's hot.
Say
It must have
Giselle Lewis puts it not even 5 years after Papa died
Things did start to shift in Cuba
Make it what you will but December 8th 2000
Castro unveils statue of John Lennon
The same here
Bob Mariano in a bunch of rock musicians
Including will Oldham David pajo permission to play a bunch of Rock shows in Cuba out in the open
One of those shows in Pinar Del Rio
Announce listen we're going to
Send out this next number to Papa La Bala
And the freakies
End
Everyone sing along
Now it would be impossible to draw any kind of cost
Affected say one thing led to another that would be ridiculous but
Lewis says the back
When this
Freaky's were streaming into the sanatorium wasn't changing back
They started
Change precisely
Because of
100 gestures big and small
He says around Cuba that moment there are all of these tiny mostly silent protest
Taking hold and then you have the money for NASA
Which was like
First serious
Civil Disobedience that Castro had in in 94
The mob
In Havana Rose upbeat
If they were so tired of
Power outages Stewart
Angry at their poor living conditions they were leading the the city in raft
By the thousands by the hundred
Castro literally had to
Come down to the Cuban La locanda beautiful
Seaside road that circles around Atlanta
And he literally had
To talk the mob down
So at this moment
The late eighties early nineties
Justice
Breeding ground of
Discontent
All over Cuba and I think the
Self
Injector movement
Best crystallization we have a black
It's like the city of a thousand points
The blight and this is the brightest point
Right by the darkest Point Franklin
Right exact
Huge thank you to
Louis Tres
Of radio ambulante we were thrilled
To collaborate with radio ambulante and thank you to Daniel Alarcon for making that collaboration possible if you don't
No radio ambulante
Check them out
Radio ambulante. Org they tell these
Incredible stories
I'm around the Spanish speaking world in Spanish
Some very hard today
King stories radio ambulante. Org Wallace appointed to them at radiolab.org
Also they are
Created a Spanish version Spanish language version of this story
Into Lewis's visit to Cuba
And the story of God sending you a Honda the last two
Remaining self infect
Get free keys
They just put that story in a podcast feed
Spanish speakers out there who
We want to hear their story
Thank you to Vladimir ceballos and Barbara Jana for use of their documentaries
This story was produced by Tim Howard
I'm very sad to say is leaving us
This week I had it right.
Take
First-year hat
Tim we love you we wish you the best
We have production support for Matt kielty and Andy Mills
Original music
From Elio die and the Cuban punk bands HIV and escoria
Broward College will be back next podcast I'm Jenn I'm running
Thanks for listening
And I just say
You have two new messages message
Fun from lovely Talent Oregon
Radiolab is produced by
A boomerang our staff includes parallel and corned beef
Matt
Guilty men Levi and the mill rabbit Snapper Melissa O'Donnell Kelsey packet
Molly Webster store in Wheeler and Jamie York could help from Danny Lewis and Kelly Prime
Record for this episode was Michelle Harris
TV channel SVT for use of the documentary socialismo
Walmart
And of course
Discredits wouldn't be complete without a crate amazing shout out
Doodle crate
Tim Howard
And this message