Are you awake
Northern listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
And NPR
Hey I'm Jared I'm rod iron Robert krulwich Radiolab in today
Begin on a plane
Thank you Brooke which carried our newly married producer Tim Howard
To the Galapagos
So I took the plane from
Keto we just finished our honeymoon that morning me and Brooke
They make announcements the certain point the flight attendants
Open up all of the overhead bins and they walk up and down
Spraying some sort of insecticide for what for a like invasive
Whatever bugs might have been stuck on the plane by this point I'm getting super excited
And I'm thinking about Darwin
And I start reading
Voyage of the beagle his book on this note that I bought
Trip
But then my power supply didn't work in my Nook.
Come into sight
What is the color of the Pacific Ocean
Lookout
The plane window
This totally wild like I'm nursing like
This
Storybook blue green
Iridescent aquamarine
I'm thinking
Wow
This is going to be like dropping into another world like nature in its purest form my version was
It is my dream of what I would like
Did you land on and it sort of like
Lowe's
Grassy knoll
An enormous turd comes by
The one that you could sit on the top of and it wouldn't notice that you were there
Just going to meet you at the airport just wondering cuz it's very similar to what I was
Picturing
But can we take a 40 minute bus ride to Puerto Vallarta
Webster Highway
Where are you are you are you are a Toyota
Which turned out to be kind of a big town
Tons of people live there
Fishing Village
Conn's no it's way bigger than a fishing Village
And just let me say that my first hours in Galapagos were totally different than I was expecting
Sort of the first thing that
Where the hell am I
I
I'm walking through the town's kind of weight starting to set
I'm actually walking down Charles Darwin Avenue
Just kind of getting the lay of the land
When
All of a sudden
This line of cars comes around the corner
Honking
Endless honking
And they're waving flag blue flag the first I didn't know what that was happening but turned out it was an election
And I was just really blown away that this
Continue
This procession
For like 15 minutes
And I remember asking one guy
Who's your candidate in there like
I didn't know where the guy was but turns out he was the incumbent
And I'm like
Is it going to win
In this guy he doesn't even say anything he just kind of points
Spypoint
The car is in front and behind
As if like dude
Seriously you see how many of us there are
But then it a certain point
I noticed that one guy
By himself standing on the sidewalk
Wearing a white shirt and jeans he's waving a flag
But his flag has a different color
Is why
And it's really loud but I go up to him
And I yell at him who's your candidate
He said
I am a candidate
I'm like what
Are you seriously
So his name is Leon need
Journey apparel
For Toyota Center
He is a naturalist guide
You actually end up meeting a lot of people employed that way in Galapagos
And he tells me so outsider
Political politically speaking he's an outsider
And of course I'm wondering why he's standing there by himself waving the flag at this entire parade of people who died
Don't support him at all
They tells me
CL memento
If a party in power now that the front runner
If they get elected
Can I see a dark and uncertain future
Grand Hotel
More big hotels
More of these enormous boats more
People
If things keep going this way
Who's going to stand up for nature
This is Radiolab and we are dedicating the entire hour to
This little set of islands and
To that question
As the world is
Filling up with more and more and more people is it inevitable that even the most sacred
Pristine places on the planet will eventually
Get swallowed up
How far are we willing to go
Return to play
To what it was
Before we got there
And more importantly
Can we
Okay so this is Linda
Linda Kao currently the science advisor for Galapagos Conservancy I began my working Galapagos
In 1981 who first came to study tortoise
Back then
Galapagos was really isil
Barely any cars super limited electricity all I remember is having a smile on my face
All the time
Because you know as a biologist going to Galapagos is like going to Mecca
She said you have islands with massive volcanoes
Tree ferns that grow
In a well above a human's height
Man grows back lava flows in
Pink flamingos
This is Matias Espinosa naturalist guide in the Galapagos like Linda
He says that when he first got to the Galapagos in the 80s
He couldn't believe that the place was real breasts taken
You visit an island called
Edina
First things ISO
Was lava fluid was moving
Is it what's what's going on you know no that's not like 1,000
See iguanas taking a sunbath
He said he would go on these Dives
Can you imagine schools of hammerhead sharks.
508 ended
Passing in front of you
Like tuna
Losartan
It shows you the power
Choose yours Revolution
There is revolutions very strong
Okay so
Quick contacts Galapagos Island cluster island off the coast of Ecuador in the Pacific 19
Bigger island bunch of smaller one
And this is a place of course where Darwin landed in 1835
And
As he went Island to Island
He started noticing that there were all these creatures that were really similar to each other
But also a little bit different the tortoises had different shells depending on the kind of Island
I lived on the finches look similar but their beaks were always a little bit different and it's got some thinking what if it isn't the
The way that everybody always says
What if God didn't create every single species in the beginning and leave them unchanged what if in life
Is purely change what if everything has been changing all the time
Darwin's bye weeks on Galapagos pushing to develop his theory of evolution and that's also why
When we think of evolution we think of the Galapagos in particular
We think of two iconic creatures
The tortoise
And the fence
Let me start by telling you about the tortoise
Bright is such a perfect day for
Tortoise hunting
You're not hunting but looking for
4th day I was there
I went to the island of floreana which Darwin visited and they're up in the highlands basically in the
The middle of this yard oh my God
33 massive tortoises
Does clustered together under a tree
Wow that is freaking amazing
Describe them what they look like is there such alien-looking creatures there like the size of
Json even know what they're massive
They look like they would crush you to death
How many years has it been here for
They can live for over 150 years
Is a tortoise trying to get over branch
Who is that that is a sound of a tortoise breathing
That's cool
So Linda when she first went to Galapagos to study these tortoises about 30 years ago
I did a trip where we backpacked around the Caldera
She took a trip to this island called Isabella hike up the side of a volcano and looked at all the tortoise country
And it was an impenetrable Forest
Basically tortoise heaven and what makes it so perf
Pek for tortoises
Is in the dry season in Galapagos
Comes onto the island
It rolls over this Forest
And it
Patches in the branches of the
The water that drips down from the top of the trees down to the ground
Creating what we called drip
Pools
Which provides
Tortoises with
Water during the dry season and they like to rest in water
And so they're under the trees you have these Pawn
With dozens of tortoise domes
Rising out of the water
So that was my first experience
It was a magical magical area and then
I actually didn't get back there for maybe fifteen years from when I was there the first time
And when I returned
That Forest
Was
100% gone
The drip pools were just dry
Dust bowls
There was no shade tortoises with with
Sitting out in the sun oil
Crowded around a couple of storks that was still there
This is Carl Campbell I went Valley conservation and I'm based here in the Galapagos Islands Charles actually the guide
You showed me those tortoise
Time it was just a
Yeah I was a Barren landscape
Baron Brown
What happened to the forest
Goats
That was definitely not what I thought
I thought you said people was kind of collaboration
So here's a story
Goats were originally sent abroad to the Galapagos probably Pirates and Wireless
Back in the 1500s
Tony sellers making these days long voyages across the Pacific and Galapagos was the the naijapal
On the whaling Road
Where
Yeah you come and get fresh water but you also come in and pick up tortoises
Land tortoises
And yet but to take away several hundred of them often and turn them upside down and I can laugh
Year-and-a-half
And all the s*** like lying there upside down
Liner upside down
In order to make space for the tortoises The Wailers and Pirates would often take goats that they brought with them
And throw them onto the island
That way when they're on their way back and sick of eating tortoises
They could grab those goats
So Wailers Buccaneers
Introduce goats to Galapagos
Put on islands like Isabella
Which is this Massive Attack
Size of Rhode Island
The goods were actually penned into just a little part of it
Because there was this black lava rock that ran across the island dreamly rough lava that's extremely
Play difficult to walk
12 miles of
So that had acted as a barrier
Basically with goats on one side tortoises on the other
But according to Linda sometime in the late 1970s
The goat Scott braids
We were probably talking just a few goats but
By the 1990s
Those few goats the population had exploded to about a hundred thousand votes
And
If you think of hundred thousand
Eating everything in their path
Every sort of plant
Even the bark off of trees they destroy the forest
So now they had a dilemma on the one hand
Tortoises needed help
On the other hand
You had all of these goats
I didn't choose to be on the island and it wasn't their fault and the goats that were out there were gorgeous
You know they had curled horns different colored
Just beautiful animal
And they been there for 500 years
Some people would concern you with
Goats have their own set of if you will write to be there those arguments came out frequently which car would respond
Yeah we going to let tortoises go extinct
Yeah this thousands of
Islands around the world that have goats on
These tortoises are only found here so way2go values lie
And so in 1994
What we called the tortoise Summit in England and that was where we started
The discussions about what are we going to do
Experts came from all over the world
Linda says we want to get rid of hiccups
And many of them thought we were nuts and then it was impossible
There's a hundred thousand of them
So many doubters
Carl says he even heard the idea why don't you put lines
Yeah they eat in Africa yo why don't you get Lions on that and those yeah really interesting ideas but
At some point they're going to get hungry and they're going to start eating all the other things that yeah you treasure
By the occasional terrorist
Mini case after endless
Planning meeting took 8 years
I think they come in
Project Isabella
To the helicopters we use that cool. Indy 500 small helicopter
Messengers one part single turbo on spotlights this is Frazier
2004 through 2006 almost every day during that time Fraser would fly over Isabela Island
Two guys with two Shooters are the sort of the helicopter
One guy that ran away to join his friends
Circle reloj
And then we start picking off the goats
One by one by one video where you see these packs
Goats
Running for their lives
And then dropping to the ground
The last goat or two might
Start of run into a area where it's impossible to reach
And what would those with funnel acacian as close as we could have run on top of the cab
Drop out one of the two shooters that was in the helicopter and he physically go into the cave
Shoe the guy chapped
Oh shoot them on sight
And then you go on and actually in under year through this aerial attack
The end of wiping out 90% of the goats on Isabella
But to give example the nature of his business that's Josh Tomlin he runs an NGO that was involved in Project
It's relatively easy
To remove 90% of
Agra population
Confirm an island but as it become rare and rare there harder and harder to detect to go to become quote
Educated learning that this sound
Mean
So the goat start hiding in the bushes they want Move To Learn to stand under tree holding their breath
And so you end up flying around in expensive helicopter
Not finding any good
Now the way we deal with that
Interesting when we use a technique called Judas goats
Yeah you disguise
Initially was Carl suggestion gregarious and like being in groups
And so
The technique that we would use was
You would fire helicopter to fly around 5 to go see kids
Then come back back to Basecamp offload then
And
He put a radio collar on
Any thrown back on the island
And then you wait
Instinctively that
Longo
We'll go and find out the gut
Week 2 weeks go by
Fire up the helicopter they get back over the island with his
Little device
It's a directional antenna
Start tracking the Judas goat
Till they spotted with some other goats and then
Everyone gets shot
Except the Judas go
Tell her to go find more friends
And then
Everyone gets shot
Except the Judas go
And then you do it again
Everyone gets shot except the Judas goat
And
You do that every two weeks for a year
That is how they go from 90% Go free to 91 to 92 to 93 to 94
It sounds like having a program on you over and over and over again
It gets worse as a good Judas go
Until
It gets pregnant
Cuz then it doesn't want to be social anymore
It goes off and
Has his kid and is very salty
Which is the last thing you want when you're trying to get goats off Island
So Carl kept mulling this problem what would it take to buy Saline MI
The the perfect guy
That ideal Judas goat if you will is it got that wood
Search for Andy search for
And it would never get pregnant
Soco Campbell figured I'd technique
Where we could sterilize them in the field got the goat start them in a matter of minutes
Smith's net
Did you do this
Yeah well I I stood next to call and watch him do it
And
Call take it one step further
Any actually
Gave these females
Hormone implants
That's basically put them in the heat for an extended duration normally female goat would be in heat for a couple days
These females are gopher
Bowling 290 days
And wherever they went they would lure the male goes out of their caves
So that you know
All in all over the course of the two-year program we had
Hundreds of Judas go without using those boots they were able to go from 94% Go free to 96
7th and 98th NYC when you have only Judas goats mating up with other Judas goats than you
And say the goats have been eliminated you done
Point they got to at least on Isabella in mid-2006
This kind of eradication program was Far Beyond
On anything that anyone had ever done anywhere in the world
Because it turns out they were just doing this on Isabela Island
Over the course of about 7 years they eliminate over 250000
So you you complete that with Isabella
And
Did it work
Yeah the results of this way absolutely impressive
Plants re-emerging at trees growing back I didn't really show. Of time and this allowed for those important drip pools
And tortoises
They basically got their home back
This is a real thing
Tortoise
Walking around
Increible
So they did it they got all the guts
Not all the goats
The Judas goats
They kept them around
That would have shot them first it's out of
Pay for them
They needed to goats because
Well
There was a problem
Of people
Because during the 90s these demonstrations started to happen
Demonstrations of outrage violent activity
Constant conflict
To explain
Villa peschke this is Agustin Lopez longtime fisherman and he told me that the 70s and 80s
All year round
No restrictions and the fisherman started making a killing fishing sea cucumber
Because if there was a huge the man
But then the national park comes in
Same group that doing the go to radication
They sell the fisherman there overfishing the sea cucumber they've got to limit their cats in the fishermen are like who are you to tell me
That I can't feed my family
So they lash out the March down Charles Darwin Avenue they would come down there
Street
Throwing rocks and sticks and everything in a Shepherd conservation Society
He was their counter for testing and he says that at one point they went after National Park built
And they were attacking the ranger stations with Molotov cocktails did Road they literally drove the Rangers out
National Park headquarters and took it over on Isabella they burn down a building kidnap some people including some of my
My crew
And they even killed dozens of tortoises
Slitting their throats
According to some accounts maven hung them
Trees
Not only that but according to Linda those goats couple islands where they've been eliminated Fishman to put them back
Really
Oh yeah
Until what they decided to do is
Leave the Judas goat on various Islands
Where they can live out their sterilize days
Jumping on grass
Sharing War Stories
Until such time
As it might be needed again
It is the is the war between the greens and the
The fisherman and such
Still hot
Difficult
Still
Killing tortoise
They're not that the fisherman
They seem to have
Stop
You know taking over National Park and then killing tortoises did a y
It's a combination of reasons on the one hand
Fishermen have started to participate in the actual
Fisheries management more cuz it seems like they realize
If they're going to keep their livelihood they cancerous
Fish everything out
But then at the same time the tourism economy has been taking off
And so all of these fishermen they find that it's easier for them to actually survive
By using their boats
To take tourists around island island so they're all kind of converting over into the tourism economy
Going to take a short break
Radiolab will be back
Check with Bruce rittenour.
And this hour on Galapagos
Hi
This is Linda Kyle
Foundation
Information about monat www.org
And this message
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents
Aunts and uncles teachers about what we're calling
Tiny moments of brilliance
Basically I want to hear about those times when I kids you know did something
It just means you bring back and say whoa
Maybe it was the moment that I
I kid you've been reading to 4 month started reading back
To you
Or maybe the kid was a piano
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of their musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed are ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the
Epic moments where
A kid does something super smart
It doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story
T-shirt with us
Go to radiolab.org
Flash brilliance
Record short audio message
And that's radiolab.org
Brilliance
Thank you so much
I'm Jared I'm running Robert, which is Radiolab in this our honeymoon is over
This is the place where Darwin began to develop
Theory of evolution and it's
The place a hundred seventy year how many 180 years later where are producer
Tim Howard landed
Wearing fishnets in a Bad Brains t-shirt
To find a very different
Landscape then what Darwin saw
We just told you a story about how far humans are willing to go to
Check something this next part
It's about how far we're willing to go to get something back
We've already lost
Service store
A place in a creature to
Do it quote wild state
The story unfolds on 106 most northern islands with else had to get ready
Goats
Called Pinta was a very special place this is James Gibbs
Professor of conservation biology at the State University of New York
It's a one of those islands it's not part of any tourist visitation site so there are no people there
And
When you set foot first on Penta you
Immediately sense
Sheer abundance
Puppy insect life
Hubbard
Problem is on Pinna things were spinning out of control
Vegetation was growing wild
The forest was getting overgrown with the wrong kind of plan
And the whole ecosystem was just teetering out of balance
And one of the reasons for this
According to Linda coyote is that we had an island with no tortoise
Because tortoises are are sore like the lawn mower
You know they they
Plow down vegetation disperse seeds but for centuries they've been hunted by those Wailers and in about ninety
The Pinta tortoise
Went
1906 yeah little over a hundred years ago they don't know the exact date
But then
One evening in March of 1972
Santa Cruz Island having dinner with some friends
Yeah I was recently on Pandora Island collecting snails
And I saw this
And I thought do you know what you have done
Livedo tortoises a hundred years
He International Park Rangers erase out to Pinta
And there it was
This beautiful told us
One male tortoise
Maybe 50 years old they weren't sure
They'd eventually named him
Lonesome George
But at the time the immediate question was other anymore because
If they can find a female for George
Then they could maybe the extinct
The species
Like poke around in the areas where we got the one
And I found
Michelle
All the female
Hey
Dead animal
What happened what how had that how had this female tortoise died
Someone chopped in half
No it was just
I felt
Violet
I want you to borrow someone's gun
I'm going to chill with us
Everyone hold out hopes for just finding more tortoises back and says it kept going back
Calming the island sniffing dogs
But in the end they're just George
Nothing shifted the focus on now what do we do
We then went to a wolf volcano
Island next door and collected two females through females that sort of looks like George but weren't quite the same species
To see if we could get him to breed
He never did was an intro
So they thought
Maybe he needs a pinto
So Cal course there are no female tortoises on Pinto but they thought you know maybe a zoo somewhere Private Collection has one cuz you really never know
So they called around offered huge cash rewards people sending dozens of tortoises
But Linda took one look at them and was like
No no
No intentes
So then I thought we've got to take matters
Indoor on hands
Basically what you do is you sit at the back of the tortoise and first you have to get to where they'll allow you
You to touch them
And eventually you start
You know fondling their their legs and Tails and red
Hoping to get them to ejaculate
Plate and petal volunteer working with me her name was favorite grigioni
She worked with him every other day or so for a few months
And was never
We were
Really starting to get
Kind of
Desperate about options in Jane says anyway it was a paradox
Because on the one hand
Awesome we have an actual living pinta island tortoise
But on the other hand
He might have actually been like the worst possible candidate for last
It was kind he seemed to really like to keep to himself he never really liked other tortoises much he didn't seem to like you
Humans and maybe that's why he survived he wasn't curious
Jane Says
A lot of tortoises footsteps they raise their heads they come out to see what's going on and then they get whacked
Yeah
In any case for about 40 years scientists tried everything humanly possible to get Lonesome George to mate with another tortoise today
Resurrect the species
And bring Pinta Island back to its original state
Nothing worth
Until
One day in July 2008 George turns to the two female tortoises that he had been ignoring
The year
And he said
Inexplicably he just suddenly decides to mate with both of them they eat
Play eggs laid in his garage and the scientists are like George guitar hope so
Dramatically, but they ultimately were infertile
Mother
Mid eighties they were having a meeting about this that's conservation is Josh Tomlin against a bunch of herpetologists were out there
There and some Island conservationists and they're talking about what to do Pinta and they can't get Lonesome George
Reproduce with sugar hoping to do cuz it make a bill to paint the population and put it on Pinterest
10 so for sure I spoke with
Biology
Cornell University
Said that at this meeting there was one guy who just couldn't take it
Geese that they're getting more and more and more frustrated
Linda finally just blurted out
Tortoise
Quit wasting our time
Because it hissed you this
The single individual was holding up
Is huge conservation opportune intercourse the shock was
There was a wave went around the room when he said
I recall seeing service second wave as a Spanish translation
I passed
Around the room
Really what that guy was specifically saying was don't be precious the tortoise is a tortoise is a tortoise
Let's just take some tortoises
From a nearby Island I put them back on pint
But there's a much bigger question here
Which is basically like what is the right way
To protect nature now
People are
Right now
Throwing gears
Each other
Around what is rice
Josh says that they're basically two camps right now
On the one side you got this classic like what you might call edin
Conservation biology
Is foundation is this idea pristine wilderness
From the very beginning I think all of us
Other people but but you always have this idea of
Wanting to get it
Back
To some kind of
Human Condition real human being the operative word
And if you think about it we all have this we all have this
This picture of what we want to bring it all back 2
To you know what might be like group Des Plaines just
Covered with Buffalo or maybe the Serengeti desert
Lions and elephants are maybe 10,000 hammerhead sharks but whatever the scene is it just doesn't have any pee
What is carrying that idea those pictures your head even like
Useful anymore it's like so sad but it just seems so unrealistic
Right but I mean at the bigger picture you can make the argument of humans now effect
Every square meter
Of the Earth
There's no place no matter how remote would get
You can go to the North Pole it's been affected by human activity
You can go
I don't know the depth of the
Impenetrable
Jungle it's been affected by human activity that's how they dream is she's an environmental law professor at the Berkeley School of Law in
In California are radically remaking
The world
And the question is
What are responsibilities
Second school of thought
Which in its most extreme version
Go something like this
We're God we might as well get good at
And we're going to have to
Create the zika
Based on
Our best science
And you could argue we're going to have to get a whole lot better
At making some very very difficult decision
Climate change
Seems to me
That's a lot of
Species
AR
Pretty much
30% 40% 50
2% of the species
Now on the planet
Two decades Maybe
Disappearing
If this is what I think it's really tough Quest
Now
If we can see
That we can't
Any longer
Save all the
Then does that put us in the situation of having
To the side
Which one
Will save in which
Won't and do we have any base
So you saying that that that the
But let's go back to when it was good
Let's go back to a better time
That's just
Silly
I didn't say it was silly
Impossible
This might not be silly they might not be stupid idea
But we still might not be
Do them
Okay so here's a
Applewood
Plaque
It says
Lonesome George is the last survivor of the dynasty of land tortoises
And in fact
In 2012 after Decades of trying to get him to
Debride
Lonesome George
Dies
Rip
24th of June 2012
And the Pinta tortoise went extinct
Sedam case-in-point I guess
No Going Back
Yeah I know that's what I thought
But then I spoke with this woman
Hello just how did you hear me
Who kind of scrambled everything up for me
Can I get you to introduce yourself
Yes
My name is Giselle Acuna
I am a senior research scientist
Rul University come up with kind of a radical idea
I call it the Phoenix
Here's the backstory in the mid-90s we started in 94 to sell and some books from their Club
National Park they began taking a census of all the tortoises in the
I have a population of tortoises on all the islands are going to do this big population study so they went Island by Island took a little
A bit of blood from all these different tortoise
Is genetic analysis and apply
Found something they never expect
A group of tortoises
Not on Pinterest
That had
A lot of pain to DNA remember very clearly.
Somebody already exciting it's like yes look at this
I was on another
I was at a
We don't think it was natural to sell it thinks it might have been The Wailers
Neither The Wailers or the Pirates talked about in the 1780s
Whalers become along grab a bunch of tortoises
Put them on the ship and then they would hunt for whales
Sometimes when they were done in this
The sherpas
Filled with oil products
They throw a few extra tortoises overboard say a few from pizza maybe those
Tortoises swim with occurrence to that nearby Island set up a little expat community
Started breeding with the local
That's our working hypothesis
Which brings us to
Her idea
Do you know on average 50% of your genome comes from your mom and 50% from your dad but
It's an average
So just tell it.
Just by chance some of these tortoises are going to have a little bit more Pinta DNA from their Pinta ancestors
And others yes
Those tortoises
And read them together collect them for the Next Generation so you can give a push
Crosses she says if we keep doing that taking the babies with the most Pinta DNA breeding them together
Shirley in for Generations you can have 90% of the painter Gino restored
Yeah but that's
Four generations of
Which means at least a hundred years
But
In the meantime the vegetation on Pinta is growing out of control
So in 2009 they come up with
Stop Gap
You take 39 tortoises raised in captivity and they use them as placeholders
They sterilize them
In Pokemon Pinsir
Yeah but these are very
Purest Serta Vision Bugatti the lawn mowers
They're not exactly they put them on Pinterest
And they are just
Chomping away right now they're living out their lives really happily on Pinta
You know until the originals are ready
Now Linda says in the end you don't actually need to do the full aggressive for Generation breeding thing
You can just take the best Pinterest
Tortoises you fine
And put those on Pinto
And
You know over the next
200000 years
They will evolve into a pinta tortoise setup could be a bit different than the past Pinta tortoise because evolution of Mewtwo
Vacation and all that
Doesn't occur the same
But eventually
Nature's going to take over
And they will evolve into tortoises
Is this the way that
Everybody who works in the tortoises thinks about it this kind of
Deep time
I don't know
I'm not sure many other people think
About that
SWAT Pakistan newspaper that says 72 hours left in the Electoral campaign
And still flying
Everywhere
Unless
But we will be there
Miami weather
Hi this is Emily calling from rainy Vancouver wash
Radiolab is supported in part by the National Science Foundation
And by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloane @www.
Sloan. Org
Anjana barad I'm rubber clovehitch this is Radiolab today a whole hour on the Galapagos Islands that place that
Inspired Charles Darwin to create his
Theory of evolution was basic ingredients
Lots of time
Isolation
And then
Constant
Darwin didn't consider this
What if
Connie's Island
Thousands of tourists arrive everyday caring fruits and chocolate
And souvenirs jumping from Island
Now the Galapagos government spends millions of dollars checking all the goods
Come in and out
Quarantine the one that might have
Have things that are problem
But what if
Simply putting your foot
On the ground
Can completely
Formal place
Actor-producer Tim Allen
So I met this woman named Frank Yeager
Who is like a plant science
What time the restoration ecologist
Said that Charles Darwin Foundation
You are in love
We were going to look at these incredible craters called Louis and Melo
And as we were walking along the path
She's like oh wait look at
Right here she points just the right of the path
Look at this
Species here
Small leafy green thing they call that young 10 in Spanish it is
In
Santiago
I think in the US they call it the was it the wrench of the white men
The rent of the white man
What's actually the footprint of the white
Doesn't matter point is an introduced
Species is introduced
Found in Europe North Africa
Shouldn't be here and you have this one
Here
Pointright next
Call Titus County Jail between green and white lie
Has a terrible common name and then there's I'm not going to say it
Wandering Jew
Basic houseplant you can buy it at Home Depot
But there it is in the Galapagos along this path
Just looking to the right and the left
And then
She just start counting the number of envy
Species at 1 to 3 as you can see here it's only right next
Set the trial
But not so much for then you'll see that they're only there for this border of about 5
10 inch along the edge of that hat
Why are you happy because
Like I said what happens is it
Taurus
They'll be back in their home country they'll be walking around in
Garden or park and it'll be filled with tiny seeds the seeds stick to
Tissues and suck sense
Trousers they wear the trousers on the plane and then they wear them when they come here and then people walk and then just
Distribute
Who dispersed the seeds along the trail
Panama City's plants are actually probably harmless
And you know like you said
Blockers National Park
They spend tons of money tons of time trying to keep invasive out
But fact is there's only so much you can do
And every once in awhile
One of these hitchhikers
Slips under the radar
And just reeks
Havoc
You just grabbed it just like that you just put your hands around
But that's the only possible the first day
So while we were in the highlands of Santa Cruz Frankie took me through the woods
To meet this guy named Arnold my name is Arnold from the University of Vienna and shortly after
We walked up
He reach out into this tree and he grabbed the
Tiny little baby Finch right off the branch
He's adorable he's there
Oh my God he said he he looks a little bit
Furry almost really tiny vulnerable Fletchling of a warbler Finch
The Darwin finches
Nexium pulsing kind of a deep breathing
Soap Darwin's finches
Ensure
Darwin when he visited Galapagos
He collected a lot of specimens of finches
Took them back to England
And eventually he realized that
The beaks had all adapted they were all little bit different depending on which island to finches lived
With a B
A bit adapter to what whatever the food they were eating
1 Islands
Finches had literally like the beak would be shape sort of a long
And then the next Island it would look almost the same but much shorter
I just became one of the
One of the most important pieces of evidence that
You know when
Animals would move from one place to another they would begin to differentiate based on what
But speaking of beak
That Finch that Arnold was holding
The Fred
Did you see the
50 Cent
Extremely
Yu-Gi-Oh
The nostrils
Have have big holes
I apologized something at gotten inside this little finches Nas
Drill these holes
And it was not eating the Flesh on the inside of the birds nostril
Scientists first began to see this in 1997 when they started to find nest
Full of dead baby finches
At first nobody had any idea what kind of creature it was so
Baby Jenna frantically studying
How to get a bed actually visited one of the main reason
Gay. In Congo
She showed me her laugh
I'm turning by shells and on the shelves are these tiny little plastic cups
That are filled with
Vice
This is the villain
Paris is solo concerto
People the most a little black fly looks like every other fly
Is it policy
In fact B. Says regular house fly
But it's actually a botfly called
The Lord has downsy
Future spell fullness down Z
Yats
Phil I can't see
Spell Lor Lor NIS
Down SI
Pelonis actually means but loving that's Charlotte cost into the researcher
The Charles Darwin Foundation she says there's actually very little known about the
The fly
They're not sure where it came from or quite how it got here but here's what they do now
The adult fly seems to be harmless
It feeds on flowers and
We think decomposing fruits
Baby flies
They're not vegetarian
Chocolate
And
What happens is that as soon as I start laying eggs
On the basis
Set the nest
Sort of underneath the finch a
Once the eggs hatch
The eggs hatch
Applies as well in the lobby
Wriggling little larvae will crawl out in the bottom of the nest
Ulta finches body
Intuit be
Mega Man 2 the the
Nose isn't
Baby finches
And just start eating
You know they're basically
Feed on the blood of that the baby bed
How did these
Google
For my babies
No that's a that's a very specific trip today
Question
We're still trying to figure that out
I'm going to assume that it was carbon dioxide carbon dioxide
From the breathing
Yeah
Box of some of the birds that
Little bean sonus
Licentious
Oh God
It's annoying normal
PA.
Showed me
This tiny little dead Finch
Why there's a little hole into the brain of this little Finch
Oh my God
Waco and Ariel Espinoza
They ate the whole bag of this little Finch
How big a problem is it
Well I talked to one scientist Sonia kleindorfer I'm professor in animal behavior at Flinders University
Australian researchers recently did a survey of Finch nests
Four different species on two islands
And all research groups found about 95
Percent mortality in the nest
95% of the babies were dead
Yeah
And Arnold told me that this year small tree finches so far we have only two nest with fledglings
And all the others with it
Switzerland
But even worse so far we found following us on 13 Islands
The Flies spreading
Island to Island
Is there any primeskill obituary by like are these finches disappearing
Very fat
Very slowly
Depends on the species
We have at least
5 species that are known to be facing extinction
And another six
In serious decline
These five species
Does that mean that they
May go extinct in the next
5 years in the next
50 years
I hope Knoxville
You know we have the case of the mangrove Finch we have C
6280 individuals left
Wow it's a Race Against Time
So
For starters
They put up all these Travis took me aside to show me where the traps are hanging from a tree here
You see them actually Oliver Santa Cruz is bright yellow trapped
Una mosca
And this is to control the fly population
Millions of drops every few feet to do that business just
Grab a few flies take them back to the lab and study him
So they can learn how to fight him
Charlotte and beer. Fantasy is at the Flies use a fireman
To attract
Syria
Fantastical
Lovely if we could find something like that
Cuz if they could find that chemical
That love chemical that the Flies use to attract each other they could disrupt it
Confuse the Flies and screw up their mating
Another
Possibility is
Sternum inside
Sterilized male flies and introduce them back into the wild
Set the female
A mates with a stare-off lion obviously
Doesn't produce fertile eggs if they can't make babies a population will crash and in some cases you can
Successfully eradicated species this is very much like the mosquitoes
Apple podcast
Ray but here's the problem
It's a going to release their livemail 5 into the wild they have to be able to raise
Inclusive a million a billion
Mystica song
Guinness your idea
Trying like crazy showing me all of the alarms that
Hats today and he talks with me for baby flies it had just hatched
Chinese little cup
But she told me that these for flies
Will probably die because they always die right now we have
Huge problems trying to refine Wellness in captivity which is ironic
Given
You know how abundant disease in the wild
Philadelphia tourism video
When I was there
Piedad told me that so far they're only successfully raised three three. Flies
When you're singing in millions
Yeah
And meanwhile the finch populations are just getting decimated
Charlotte says it there
Trying to respond
Ornithologist have started to notice some new Behavior
Reference in setup
Taking the Lafayette to the nostrils of of the baby beds and what we're starting to see if they're beginning to consume them
You need to fly larvae
Yeah which 15 years ago they would never do
Tried feeding the finches some fly larvae
If ever there were a look of disgust on a finch face that was it
I think there's been a change there also seemed baby finches
Climbing up over each other
Just struggling to get away from the larvae on the bottom of the nest I mean they'll even start standing on the nest room just to avoid being
But when I asked Charlotte what she makes of all of these changes
She said
I think probably too little too late
But then someone told me something
Really surprising very unexpected discovery
Takes a couple steps to get there
Justice ended up back in 2000 she was on floreana island for the first time
I started studying Darwin's finches
In particular
Three tree Finch species
He's too small to medium in the large and we went out and we we set up our Miss Nets and we caught the birds and we measured
Even though these are our three different
Species
They're actually really hard to tell apart
Visually
So she would end up relying on their songs their mating call
Skip do you remember the song types could you whistle them for me yes it's very simple song
The small tree Finch goes something like
2 2 2 2 2 2 2
That's a small tree Finch
The medium tree finches just a bit
Slower for the meeting
For the Lord
Teeth
Wow it's like a soprano saxophone and Alto and tenor or something like that
So we we just meet us at the 4 somewhere and we would always quiz each other what's that what's that we all agreed because the calls are really
Distinct
Easy to tell apart but
The interesting thing was from year to year it got more difficult each time to go into the field
The song sounded like they were starting to blur together
Then when I showed up after a few years again I was truly even more perplexed
Should I gather why can't I tell these finches apart
It was very confusing am I losing my touch but that shouldn't really happened you should actually get better
With experience. Worse and that's where I thought all something's changed in the system
I'd like to think of it as a kind of Darwin Finch you know sluicing Adventure
So when your team rounded up some of the Birds attack
We collected genetic samples
Got some DNA brought all the stuff into the lab
Terrible realization
That the large tree Finch is now extinct
Totally gone from guilin
So you really only had two species
Small tree finches and the medium
And based on that genetic data
The
Small tree finches
Not doing great but compared to the medium tree finches they are because of me and proof inches were on
On the brink of Extinction
Like a large
But then she sees something
Amazing
She's a small group of birds
Who have mixed up jeans
Hybrid cluster
Some jeans from the small tree finches and some from The Medium tree
What is that mean what it means that these two
Different finches had started having babies together which should never actually happen because these are totally separate species
That's really the classical definition of a species is like a biological rule
About who you're not going to make a baby with
So they they choose not to breed even if I could
Troll that boundary I've got my thing over here
You got your thing over there
But then Along come the Flies
And all the sudden like over maybe 20 years
The medium tree finches they start to
Break their own biggest Rule and they start to mate
Outside of their own kind
Annie's hybrid finches are they doing
Better against flies well there's there's a couple Cruise it's a maybe
Yeah for example when you look in the neck
They seem to have
Pure parasite
And they seem to have more babies that survive 15%
Wow where is the numbers were very small for the medium tree Finch and smaller for the small tree Finch
Wow I daresay that sounds kind of hopeful
It does
Yeah no
The jury is still very much out on what will have
But if the hybrids do you have
Disadvantage and if they survive
We may be witnessing in hyperspeed
The creation of an entirely new
Species
Possibly be
One of the first vertebrates
Examples of speciation in real time
That we can observe
So
Talking to the story of these finches
Is the story of Galapagos
Same exact story The Darwin saw these processes that he described
They just never
Ever stop
It's this
Unpause
Ending
Struggle
Wellness my last night there
I went to meet up with that guy Leonidas was running for mayor I met him at this pizza place
Election that happened the night before and did he win no Bocelli the incumbent one
So we go outside
Turns out he speaks in English
So we can we do this interview in English and I'm I'm almost embarrassed that I wanted to
To talk to him because I think the food is
It's going to be
So down and out
Exactly the opposite he was so joyful
That's what I thought you're not sad and he's like friend this is a field
A for the other three of money behind them and you see their flags all over Santa Cruz
I just came in second
The guy who wins
He spent $500,000 I spent what two grand
Eating
Avenue a new future for the Galapagos Island
We are ascending we keep keep we have our dreams up
The Nature has a boys now
Brazilian has a voice
The penguin everywhere
So something is happening that exactly how we see this interview
Pretty certain hour before we close very special thanks to Matthew Judas kiltie
Would have been crushed just by the sheer amount of tape
Indeed
How to make saddles key for regional music thanks to Chris Doleman and Screen siren pictures Alex gallifant Matthias
Espinoza the naturals guy from the first chapter who wrote this song is also well-known musician in
Galapagos turtle
Thanks to the Galapagos National Park Charles Darwin Foundation Island conservation and the Galapagos Conservancy
Run by Robert Goulet thanks for listening
Hi this is James Gibbs going from Syracuse New York my name is
University and I have be enough to leave a message for the credits
Radiolab is produced by WNYC NPR
Radiolab is produced by Jad abumrad
Our staff includes ellenhorn sternwheeler
Molly Webster Melissa O'Donnell ceiling caves
Sammy York slim Levi
Andy Mills
And Kelsey Padgett
With help from Ariana wack
Special things to Katie Hopkins
Henry Nichols Jason koebler
Carolyn Bessette
Robert Lamb and crystalline
Goodness
Okay I hope that was okay thanks bye
Thanks for the opportunity
And this message