Are you awake
Northern listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
Hi I'm Robert Goulet
This is Radiolab and this week we're going to do something a little unusual I don't know how many of you
Know the earlier this year we launched a spectacular success
So I should say
Spin-off from Radiolab
Shaun Robbins Farm was a correspondent on the show I was yeah it was called is called more
More perfect
Is a podcast about the Supreme Court of the United States and what about the
Court of the United States all of it race class gender sex money power religion how the how the institution deal
Deals with these issues that that sometimes divide this nation
It's also filled with people stories in judges
Just pays one way
Chili went out of his mind anyway
By the way since so many people have been writing all the time about what's going to happen to the market
Do you want more more perfect music are there going to be any more I can in fact confirm there will be more more
You can't expect details
They should be coming out in the spring of 2017 probably met
Okay until then we would recommend if you haven't heard all the ones we did this year
Go to radiolab.org
And there are other waiting for you I know we put a few of these more perfect on our podcast feed for this is the first time for this one on read
One of my favorites so here it is from my podcast more perfect
Abject
Anyway
Which you want
United States
Let's do it
Hey I'm Jared I'm Rod this is more perfect miniseries about
And today story from a reporter Sean up your last name can you say it rhymes from rum
Confirm
Cinemark place
Set table for you we live in a representative democracy
What does that actually mean practically speaking when do we come in contact
52 places seems to me
One when we vote
Right yeah you asking me
I was deep in thought
If you vote if you've always too I know like
College-educated super Progressive human beings were like why would I ever voted to the UN
Just don't even care about the world makes my point like voting is the first way in for a lot of people
Entirely optional the second way is not you will be fine if you don't do it
And I mean
Serving on a jury
This is where I like We the People decide
Who goes to jail who gets free who lives who dies which is where we actually do
Democracy
Today we start with the story of a guy who
Spring who is Supreme Court famous
Would you say yeah he's in the books he's like a chapter one the most important names you've never heard up because he's at the center of this ongoing
Battle about
Who gets to serve on juries
And his name
Finding out who you are either symbolizes the best parts of American democracy
Or the most cynical
Just his name
Yeah go for
James Batts
James Kirkland bath
Hello
James
I went to his house in Louisville
Tell me your full name and tell me where you're from
About that James Batson Louisville Kentucky
James Batson his name just kept coming up over and over again what I was looking for the history of jury selection America so I called
And I was like hey
Israel airport in New York City and I'm really interested in your case
Because there's other
For the Cartwright app
Can I come talk to you
Okay make sure my full name and City
Call
She's built like a fridge
He's a black man Bernal drove Truck local in Cross Country
Orthopedics 15 hours one way
Florida
As a kid he was
Is a student
Graduated from Aaron
Technical High School
Q's and I'd like a vocational school specializing in life
Engineering industrial electricity
Do you think
Popular
But
Shortly after that
I'm like the bottom fell out
13 bats and grew up in the West End of Louisville in the 1970s and the West End was super rough
The people selling dope
Prostitution
Does everything have to do with fast money
Young age
Fast money was like
The American dream
I mean it's pretty hard when a lot of people around you got a nice things and they got them because they're doing
Doing something illegal
You keep coming up rabbit ears
You shaking your head like you know what rabbit ears are what a rabbit is
Pupil mobile pockets
Can I let him neither one of them
He said also when he was 10 he wanted pair of shoes he couldn't afford them trailer
Well when they first came out if you didn't have a pair of those you had on 4th
Call Buddy
Everybody
Cheap tennis shoes
Annie's brother asked his mom
Romani and they
She gave them some money but not enough
How to make up the difference they went out and they
Stole people's empty soda bottle
And turn them in for like
The deposit
Reset on nickel apiece
Don't wanna pop bottles
That was my first
Experience with
Feel like money
Don't pop bottle
Joe everything else is there
Fast forward a couple years James has more grown up he starts doing some petty crime and he starts breaking into house
They actually gave me a name call me pants pocket burglar
When crime would happen burglar would take only
Stop Gap in his pocket
Big purses and jewelry no merchandise didn't fit in his pocket he wouldn't take it
That was you
I'm not admitting that was me
Possible deniability
Pokemon Sumo names
Vibramycin
Gothic V
James start stealing bigger things and he starts getting arrested
Tattooing in and out of the Courts
And then one of those small in that cases
Became I think
American legal
They got me out of car
92 cops pulling over
Pull me out the car they say you have the right to remain silent anything and went through that little
Protocol whatever
They tell him some burglars that happening at area
I think they said I did them
William
Yeah I would
The time I've been doing some margaritas or whatever but anyway
James said he didn't do this one
And if they didn't have the proof
He was driving around in his car
And they pick them up when they arrested me I'm thinking they didn't really have a case against me they didn't catch me breaking into a house
You got me out of car
An old fingerprints nowhere
He thinks he can win
Okay so I'm not going to jury trial
And
The mere fact that you and I are talking about
James Batson
Case 30 plus years later
Is amazing
That's the prosecutor about Joe Gutman
I'm from Louisville Kentucky
Gripped and loyal raised in Louisville
Wanna be a lawyer since he was a kid my parents would through a divorce when I was very young and I wanted to go to law school to help
Kids in divorces
Become a lawyer James's case was in the first 6 months
That I was in the prosecutor's office
Pretty impressive first year
Starting out
I lost my first date trials
Really
Batson's case you know this low-level burglary of breaking of a house in a purse being stolen he was a go
Maybe this'll be my Wendy evidence
Disappeared that he was guilty of the crime
James was
Accuse not data Fighters the one is having done it
Eyewitnesses they're saying James these Witnesses photos of him before
Because
Do you need naps
So
To come to the case
It goes to trial
And
Had a hung jury
They end up being a hung jury
Hip hip hooray
It means they can come to unanimous.
James gets off
Why is it a hung jury in Kentucky you have to have unanimous
So the defense is looking for that one juror that keeps from convicting
There is apparently one jar
Who just didn't buy it then by the evidence and thought James was legit
It was a black
One black lady came to visit me
After Drew's over
She said I really really don't think you're guilty the rest of
The jury
Was trying to make me say that you
Guilty and I was saying not guilty
So end up being a hung jury at was
Disappointed
At that point I was
Having sex
Thoughts about
Is this the right career for me
SoJO gottman
He says imma try this case one more time it was pretty close to guilty
I have this one Drew hung it up
Tell me two or more time and it does something this time
A little differently
Just a setup as you know when you get a jury summons you go in you're on a jury pool
At the beginning of a trial
Jury selection
Maybe ask you touching your call if we're both side the prosecution the defense sometimes the judge they get jurors into a room and they start
Asking lots of questions is there anyone here who has been the victim of a crime
Victims of crime
To figure out which jurors do we want
Member of a church pictures do we want to get rid of
And that's the more important part of this process which jurors do we want to toss off history pool
So what are the rules to get rid of jurors
There's two ways to get rid of jurors to get down to that group of 12 in this
And the first way is called striking
Cause this type of move to excuse him for causing this time
Tracking for cause is like when they ask you can you be fair in this case if you say you know Noah
I really can't I really strong feelings about the people or the subject matter
That's a strike for cause or it's like hey that lady who's sitting in the chair of the defendant
That's some
That's my cousin
We grew up together
Don't like conflict Venture Lane, that's my boss
We go out every Saturday for brunch whatever it is
You're too close to this
You can't be fair
Got it so that one's cause
That's pretty much common sense it makes sense to everyone but the second way is
The heart of this whole matter
This whole story
It's called a peremptory challenge
Preempt rear entry
Peremptory
That's a word depending on how you punch it into Google
It'll be like that's a type of a son what does it mean what is peremptory mean sound means you get a certain number of straw
Just to get rid of people you think might not be
Fair to you
But you can really use them anyway you want and
But these strikes
You want to give any reason
How many days do you get
So it varies from state-to-state in some states
20 in other states
It's for
In Kentucky then and now each side gets
88 juror
That they just get to put the Exxon and say you're not going to sit on this trial
Hooker crook anything and this isn't just some
Weird legal rules we made up
Like 20 years ago this is something
That has been around
It's older than America
Goes back to England in the 11th 12th century
And before that some say he goes back to like
104 BC Roman times really really
And the idea is I feel like the visualization is like
Like a seesaw
Like okay
We need to get to this perfect group of 12 people and
You know there's going to be people who are biased either side so each side gets the eliminate people you get three you get
You get for you get for and then we'll
Come to this balance
Send the jury
A group of people
Port going to be fair
Tilted their way from other side
The thinking of the land up balanced yet and also the thinking was that this would give both sides more faith in the process and
At the same time
Protect both sides
From
Tyranny of a trial judge
Too much power
Got you okay
What happens in this case is the second trial begins
Take me to the
Imagine early
Yeah that's that's the first thing that happens
Set a scene from a well
The only people that were in the courtroom
Were some family members of mr. Batson his attorney a detective
And me
And the jury
So the reason we're talking about this case and Joe gottman and James Batson
Is because the next thing that happens is Joe Gutman gets up there
He scans the jury pool and at this point he says there are 13 people left
For that were black
9 that were white and he uses his peremptory challenges
The strike of 1
Black jurors
They're all gone
Leaving all white
Do you remember striking
For minority
Do I specifically remember
The reason for each
No I don't
I asked Joe was the reason because they were
In fact
Black no
I can see that they were not stricken
Because of race
And I remember
Specifically that one of the jurors lived in the neighborhood
Is exactly remember what his reasons were for all four black chairs but
What's important for our story is to know that James Batson is sitting there in the room
As all of this is happening
Just completely destroyed
Jury pool
Damn right I told my lawyer
Objective that you know
Voices violet object
James said because
Not fair
He should know it's a long-standing rule he's allowed to do that
Describe what we want
Was he loyal white or what
Hughes wife
He was white inside nose for people that have just been struck off the journey there by the courtroom was white
So again
Jo Malone YouTube chicken again
What you mean you can't you work for me you do what I say you just check anyway
I don't care this long-standing rule
And he did
And it all came behind that one objection
What happened
Is after the jury was select
Dugdale
James Attorney
Said
Judge our I want to make an objection
We went up to the bench
He said
Your honor you can see there's an all-white jury
I would like for him to explain his strikes
But before I could get another word out of my mouth
Judge Ryan
Said Mr gottman does not have to
Explain his rights
It's not the law
Let's move on
Move on
So they moved on with an all-white jury
I got found guilty
I got 20 years
Yes
Sebastian goes to prison
Danville Court
And he said his first move when he got there
Appeal immediately
And ultimately his appeal ends up in the hands of the sky David niehaus
Jefferson County public
Defenders
Office
Anyhow decide to do something
Ambitious
What we did is
We call it taking
A tour of the jurisdiction
Washington
Khalid
Healing takes illegal road trip
Sesame house and his team start looking at other states looking at other regions to find out what this is
The problem
Elsewhere is this just something
Limited to the South or is it
Something else
You mean like our people in other places doing what Joe got midday
French braids
And what he found is that this was happening pretty much everywhere
So
The following appeal
Which worked its way up through the courts
And in December 1985
Thank you gentlemen the cases submitted to hear arguments next year in Kentucky
Case arrives at the
Supreme Court of the United States
I get a call one day
From the Associated Press that showed up
How do you feel about the
Supreme Court accepting
The case of James Kirkland Batson and I was almost speechless and
I did
Go just to observe and learn
Mister chief justice and may please the court
So here's an ultimately went down
Bat inside my house
He argues that these strikes were being used take black people off
Jerry's and this is happening everywhere able to list some 25
Jurisdictions and
Practice violated the 14th Amendment which is equal protection
And the 6th Amendment
Which is the right to a jury of your peers as representative of the community as possible
So if Lewisville is like 17% black
Detroit probably be about
17% black
And
The prosecutor shouldn't be like
Askew that without having to give a reason
First of all
Kentucky's response to report
We Believe
The historical nature and function of the device itself to Kentucky saying
We shouldn't have to justify these strikes the court has told us that again and again
Is always been unsettled enough controlled by the court
Unexplained and his practice
Centuries and
Yes and maybe some of uses but this is a tool that lawyers need
Thank you gentlemen McKay's this semester
4 months later the court delivers
Its verdict
And in a seven to two decision
Batten wood
The court found that the prosecutor's actions for sure violated the 14th Amendment
They said racial discrimination of any kind in jury selection
Is not allowed
Que Dan Rather Bhai courtroom today it is illegal totes illegal even on a Grand Prix challenge it is
Is it illegal for a lawyer to reject a juror on the basis of race
James Batson sentence with immediately vacate
Can you send describe them
If you were in prison and you know your sentence is being
Take it away
Talk to break every now and then
Discount fishing come up
Just be hanging out playing chess
I got a law in the logbooks Batson rule
And that was the biggest deal
Of all this
The headline
This new
Rett syndrome named after him
Justices put new limits
What is called freedom to re-challenge the Baton Rouge the Bat signal is an echo of what James did in court that day
You see people minorities getting booted off of a jury you can say your honor I think that's an option violation
In the other side B of the defense of the prosecution
Pastor provide non-racial reasons
For why they eliminated that you're in for a lot of people this is a break
This is like finally we figured out how to do this right
There was a system in place to protect everyone and that system was even extended to civil cases and eventually the women is
It was a big deal when the case was decided and the initial elation
Was quickly
Tempered
With a strong dose of reality
This is Jeff Robinson he's a director of the ACLU Center for chest
Because what bats and prevents is
Deliberate
Racial
Discrimination
And I almost immediately
All over the country
Prosecutors started training each other teaching
Each other on how to get around Batson
That's fine Simpson he's the director of the Equal justice initiative
In Montgomery Alabama
Are there a train is all across the country
Do some of these are on video
And I found one
Music on YouTube you got to stay these basic rules this is one of those videos this one
In the Philadelphia prosecutor named Jack man lecturing to a room full of young prosecutors on how to pick a jury
Selecting black
You don't want the real educated ones and my experience black women young black women are very bad there's a
Antagonism I guess maybe cuz they're dancing to respect women and their black sand
So there are downtrodden to areas and they somehow want to take it out on somebody and you don't want it to be you
The crazy thing about this video is that it was film just a few months after the Batson decision
Batson vs Kentucky I'm sure you've all become aware that case
Jack man basically tells his prosecutors look we got this new rule
Here's how you break it you strike the black person off the jury but just say it's for another reason
Because that's what Batson required
This is a racially neutral reason
When you do have a black shirt you question them at like and
Honest Little Chute that you have Mark something down that you can articulate later time if something happened
Black
Start with first three people write it down right then and there I'd rather ride in my little box there you know the woman had a kid
About the same age as defending and I thought you'd be sympathetic to a more
She's unemployed and I just don't like unemployed people because I find enough today before this is almost this training to create
Catalog of reasons
Put on the face where race-neutral just say you're excluding them because they are too tall
Are there two old that person was wearing a black sweater things like well he lives in a bad neighborhood
Person would maintain eye contact body language or they belong to a church
Tattoos
What are a nurse
Any of those reasons have a markdown
As long as a prosecutor doesn't say I excused that person because they're black
Batson says it's completely okay
I was actually working on a case this is lawyer Bryan Stevenson
My office said the time was called the southern Christmas defense with Jesus and I was in Atlanta Georgia
Before I move track
Alabama and when was this
This is 1986
And we were defending someone down in Swainsboro Georgia
Guy by the name of Gamble
And the bathroom decision
Qingdao
I and objections were made with the prosecutor used his peremptory strikes
Exclude all of the African-American
And we said wait a minute you're on if there's a new decision Batson vs Kentucky
Which means that the prosecutor can't do this
And the courts at while I read baton. What this means is that the prosecutor has to give race-neutral Visa
I've got my race-neutral Visa
Is Weis truck this woman
Because she looks just like the defendant there was an African American man to wait a minute what is that
No she doesn't
He said he did
What struck this man because he lives in South Winnsboro
And that's where the defendant
And we record the sale of all the black people live in South Waynesboro
All the way to
That's not a reason to reason. You know that is a recent movie
Pizza Hut stock one person
Because this man was in the military and he was discharged
After 5 years in the military
And in my experience your honor
You only get discharged honorably after an even number of years
What a juror was put back on the Stanley Cup
Were you discharged from the military honorably yes I was I was actually decorated
I got this medal I got this award I got these things
Well I still accept the Prosecco
Just waiting for excluding that
My personal favorite was
The prosecutor said it gets better
This man because he testified
That he was a mason
And he said you're on I just don't want anybody who's a member of a masonic lodge
All my jewelry they have their own code their own rituals are all culture
I don't want that
The jury was put back on the stand we acid or are you a member of the Masonic Lodge
Watching the tree said no I'm not he said I'm a brick mason
And the judge says I still know what you mean I'll let you exclude that person right
And so almost from the very beginning there was this
Cynicism this gameplay I used to tell people
Bath is not going to eliminate racial bias in jury selection
But it will make the jury selection process a lot more entertaining
Y'all should come to court and just watch the show
So you not only did Batson
Not change anything but that's in made things worse
As one lawyer Steven breit put to me what bad son is really is basically
Set of procedures to sorta legitimize and cover up the race discrimination that's going
Going on
You had this
Smelly putrid problem of racial discrimination in jury selection
And instead of
Tossing it out
We just
Sprayed Febreeze
He just kind of perfumed it vaguely she cologne it's still there
Begley hidden
And now with the Batson rule
If you think the prosecution or the defense
Is striking people off because of race
You have to call them out and then you have to
Somehow
Try and prove that the reason they're providing is a lie
And that's
Really really tough
Since
1986 Ford xample in the state of Washington
There been
Probably 4748 challenges on Batson issues where people have been convicted make sad waiting
The prosecutors were excusing
People of color from the jury
Because they were people of color
Out of those 46 250 challenges there's been one
River
The state of Tennessee has not reversed a single case
Under Batson
And the 30 years for it it's inside the Baton decision came out
As a result
He says there still many counties in America where the diversity of the jury is not increase
Very much at all
So for example in one Louisiana Parish they looked a felony cases
Is over an eight-year period
And found it nearly half the black jurors
Worst truck
Houston County Alabama
Over a five-year period
Data stops at 80% of the African Americans qualify for jury service
Restaurant
80% 80% and that's in debt
Panda cases cell
I mean if you think about that like a big percent of time Deezer
Lawyers who are
Going around the Baton Rouge going on the law
Corn on the cob
Tuition to get these all-white juries
Who are then oftentimes pudding
Black
Mint
To death
And
That reminds you some pretty dark
Super basic
I mean
That video
Training video
The assumption that video is it
Having black
People on the tree
It would hurt that guy
Would hurt the
Yeah
Show me Justice
Assume that or is there any
Any data that would say that's even remotely
Betru the hardest thing about looking at this stuff
Analytically
The juries are like
Black Box
They don't let
Journalist
Akademiks
In off
Study
What's going on
The jury is kind of sacred.
Yeah but
The few times we've gotten data like that is
This group called the capital jury project that looks at
Data speed
SafeLink application
Because that's where the stuff ends up
Living life or death
So they looked at data in
Like 350 cases in 14 States
Over a number of years and they found that
White man
Are more likely to go for the death penalty than black men
When you get to sentencing that number that the difference between white and black it's really exaggerated like
White men are
Are seven times more likely to want the death penalty
Black person
There's another study that was done in Florida
Amazon look at felony cases over like 10 years and
They found them
All-white jury pools
In Florida convicted black defendants
Percent
More often
Okay but was really interesting like that that cap was practically eliminated one at least one member of the jury pool is black
Interstate but one black person
And that difference
Catastrophes
Why I mean
Oxycodone cases
Usually involve cops and reason is often cited as
That nope black
Jurors are less like
To believe
Cops
Bikers are more likely to
Insert some sense of
Suspicion
Into
The Estates are the Commonwealth or whatever is testim
And almost everyone talked to
Gave me a version of this
That that you know when you're blocked going to jury to deliberate more
And that black people are less likely to trust law enforcement especially
Jack McMahon
Who was the guy we heard from in that video
Anybody knows me knows I am
Anti-racist
Person that
Could ever imagine
Stone Cold liberal
To the nth degree but I was talking about practicality
Jewelry box
I still stand by that
If you're prosecute
Let me ask you this
And you're trying to drug test
And the defendant is going to claim that the
And you're the project
What
Demographic
The group has had more
Bossier
The police live
Then
Minority
They have seen
Police
Lima believe police
Live more than
Some white guy lives in a rich area believes that police officer every guy everything he says
And so is the prosecutor you're trying to win the case
And that person is not going to be
The person is going to
Questioning
Witnesses
And you're given the Opera
Opportunity
True peremptory challenges to strike them why wouldn't you
Give me a full mattress
Well I guess
I see the argument that you know use your peremptory challenges
Is to get the best year you can to win but doesn't eliminating a black
Jerry because you believe they might have certain biases against app
Police officer versus a white juror
In some way violate
The equal protection clauses
The 14th
I don't think so
Not at all because it's not because of
The color of their skin
Cause of there
Demographic
And where
Kool-Aid
Societal demographic
The fact of life
I think those Facts of Life in those societies
Demographical Concepts
All stem from the color of
Their skin
Maybe a deeper issue that we can't deal with
But you're right
But the reality is
The reality is that that that that's what this
Situation is so
So you're saying that if you're the prosecutor you
You should take out for this guy probably worse
For me he probably
I believe those cops are line but I'm going to take him because I want to uphold the
There is no prosecutor in the country
I want to I want to show my altruism
And I'm going to keep this guy on my
Jewelry who made this
Believe my
Because I want to be altruistic
The way life is
How to solve a problem like Batson
More perfect will continue
This is Albert Einstein College
Sylvania
Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world more information about Sloane at the W
Wwd
Sloan. Org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
And I've requests
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
We're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments
Childhood brilliance
Basically I want to hear about this
Times when a kid you know did something
It just means you lean back and say whoa
Maybe it was the moment that our kids you've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed they're ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the specific moments where a kid does something super smart
Have anything to do with the test
If you have a story with us
Go to radiolab.org brilliance
Record short audio message
Message press
Again that's radiolab.org / brilliance
Thank you so much
This is more perfect miniseries about
Explain how we got into this whole morass
It's about
Racial bias in juries
I think we should
It's because of a case that was in front of the Supreme Court this term in case 1483
Foster versus Chapman
So basic facts this is a murder case in Georgia
A younger black
Man kills an elderly white woman the prosecutors dismiss
A bunch of black jurors
Is and the defense having this new Batson rule says hold up
Can't do that
And prosecutors give these race-neutral reasons and the judge says
That looks good to me
Years later something sort of incredible happens through like one of those Freedom of Information Act
Type
Things
The defense
Actually gets
See
The notes
The process
Can had
During the
Trial the notes they kept during jury
This is one of those rare times when we pull back the curtain and we find out what the prosecutors were doing
This is lawyer Steven breit he actually argued Faust
After case in from the Supreme Court late last year
And he says what you saw these notes was that the process
Xcution they literally wrote
A little B next to the name of
Each and every black juror B1 B2 B3
Highlighting all the black sand in in green on the list of all the people summoned for jury
Racial discrimination is really hard to prove
This is actual physical proof
Violin the state like this is the Smoking Gun
We've been waiting for so what are the what are the prosecutor how did the prosecution argue this in front of pink car
Once an ultrasound they said
We were just running those bees because we wanted to make sure we noticed
The black Jersey you want to keep
Track them
4 months
Prior to trial defense counsel
We're filing a bat
That's the lawyer representing Georgia Beth Burton
And she saying of course we're going to notice race this is the post Batson world end
We're going to no trace and we're going to write it down
I would be more surprised quite frankly if there wasn't some sort of highlighting or
Is that is that the reason he highlighted
Actors in green he being the original prosecutor
Was because he was preparing defense in case
Correct. Justice Breyer asking well why didn't you make that
Argument
Like
When the case was actually happening the years and years ago
What isn't surprising
But he never thought of it
Didn't tell anybody
I would say that's on
The good news is that
In a 7 to 1 decision the Supreme Court agreed
That this prosecutors reasons War
Utterly ridiculous
I'm just going to ask you is in this is clear that's in violation
That's Justice Kagan
Is that
This case was in front of supreme court at all
Good at to get appealed up to the highest court in the land
Before someone said
Oh yeah that's about annihilation
That's how hard it is
And the Supreme Court so it made a force
Full
Decision 7 out of 8
They didn't make a new rule
This is not work
They didn't offer up but that's in 2.0 or they didn't double down or throw it out or do some new rule
No they said
This is really wrong but
Didn't go as far to say
Oculus doesn't work
So we still got bad
So okay if we want to diverse juries and we know that bad
Doesn't really work
What do we do
So I asked
Everyone I talked to
That question
Got a lot of different answers
But this was the
One and done agency
Margaret is a professor of law
IIT should
Chicago-kent College of Law
What I'd like the court to do
Is eliminate
Peremptory challenges
Again steambrite is a lawyer we have to
Supreme Court gives you these rules
Appropriate challenges
And it says
What weight am I
Don't just break people
Even Jack McMahon the guy from that
Training video he was over
We've had 30 years of experiment with Batson and it's not working
We now have to go the route
That Justice Marshall suggested back in Batson
So in the bathroom decision you've got Thurgood Marshall like the most
Important attorney in the Civil Rights Movement turn the first black Supreme Court Justice
Key in the same paragraph
Call the Baton decision
Historic
And then said this isn't going to work
This decision isn't going to do anything
It he was basically a fortune teller he said both those things in the same breath
In one paragraph he starts about going this decision today
Historic by the end of the paragraph
You're never going to fix this until you get rid of print through challenge
Set an alarm for 9 breakfast just do away with from three strikes
Constitution
Both sides are denied
Peremptory challenge
Challenges
You will have discrimination
What surprised me most in reporting this story is that like I talk to people
On the left side of the criminal desk
On the right side of the Criminal Justice System ACLU types
Law professors academics conservative
Secure is all of these people when you say
Guys we got to get rid of printer towns right almost every single one will say no
No
That's a crucially important to let you know it's an easy solution just get rid of
Peremptory snow helmet
Italian style are legal editor law professor sunwolf from Santa Clara University and lawyer David niehaus again
And here's
One of the arguments
I heard if you take these things away all the decisions about striking jurors would be made by the judge
On the question whether Jerrika be fair and impartial and for that to work
I thought you have to have a fair judge
And
There are an awful lot of judges
Who aren't there
Here's another argument I heard from Jackie Robinson
Sing from the ACLU
And this is based on my
Experience of 34 years in the criminal justice
Jeff Robinson says if you can find some way to take race
Out of the equation for entries are
Super useful
Annie told me about this one k
Very high-profile homicide
Case in the state of Washington
This case was incredibly complicated and also
Potentially involved
A course
Confession
Buy some undercover cop
Sand
There's a police officer
Surrounded your iPad
He says
I can be fair
I know the police officers that investigated this
Pyside worked with him before
I think they're really good people but don't worry
I can be fair
Everything about his back
Was saying
I do not want this man to serve on this
But he was saying
I can be fair
I could not exclude him
Moana challenge
Call
Why not
Because he said he could be fair the fact that he's a police officer doesn't mean he can't be fair it isn't saying I'm
I know some of these people involved in this case enough to get him dismissed for cause it's enough to get more questioning but how well do
You know I'm not very well
So you saying that case if you said okay. I like to dismiss jurors 17-4 cause the judge would say there's not a wreck
I don't think any judge in this country
What dismiss that juror for cause
And so a peremptory challenge is important
So
Watched more jury selection videos on YouTube than any person
Evershed
And
It's this amazing thing where you see these people but not necessarily use
To being in a courtroom
There's certainly not used to being grilled in public
500 people in suits
Take it up there to the jury panel
And they got to ask these questions in the trial
Over and over
Can you return a partial
Yes sir you're like a blank slate you just got to listen to the evidence can you do all that
Nobody says no
Everyone feels like
Yes I can be fair
I'm thinking I could I can be totally unbiased
And I think some of them believe that they can actually do this nearly impossible task
And others they know they can't but they might say yes anyway anyone who tries the case
Believe me
Knows the bias Jersey
Comment they don't reveal things they lie about things for people that when you're crushing them in a jury that you know they're lying to you
Trying to get onto jewelry or trying to get off the jury bias people are being allowed to serve
So any tools that can help reduce the number of biased yours and yours
Is essential to just
So yeah if you got a really
Crappie outlook on chores and humans then maybe you need more friend through challenges but the way Jeffrey Robinson put it to me was that if you're using friends WeChat
Challenge the right way
It forces you to be like
Equal opportunity
Suspicious
Suspicious of
Everyone
And that's
The only way to be fair
My parents
We're both active in the civil rights movement in Memphis Tennessee
Is active as two people you could ever want to meet
Both black
I would never let my mother
Set on a criminal defense jury
Because my mother's view about black defendants was
You're the reason I have to lock the door in my neighborhood
You're the reason that I get disrespected when I go out into the
Community
And I'm going to take it out on
My father's position would be
I wouldn't believe a police officer if he told me it was raining and the water was coming down on my head
And so what this is about
Is
Actually
Putting into effect what the rules say
Talk to jurors and find out what they think
But what about Thurgood Marshall's idea that
You know if you have learned through challenges if you give people a way to discriminate they will discriminate
Well
I was born in 1956
It's on 1954 Thurgood Marshall argued Brown versus the Board of Education
Which
Had
A significant impact on my life
Thurgood Marshall was someone that I
I have respected and someone I admired virtually my entire life
But I can't agree with him that I want all peremptory challenges eliminate
And why do you think Thurgood Marshall Justice Marshall went straight to
No print I think Justice Marshall concluded that
He did not have faith in America
To be able
To make these kind of decision
And I understand why you concluded that
And you do you have that face
I still do
And how long that will last I don't know
But I still do right now
Robinson says that
To give up on this
Parentheses is like giving up on who we might be one day
Because of who we are right now
That's conceding
That we are so divided by race that we will never be able
To try and fix it
And I'm not prepared to conceive
Okay one last thing for my trip to Louisville
What's up Shane
All right
Thunder blew me away
Banjo getting it I'm a teacher at Central High School
Also an attorney at law
I'm James Batson truck driver in
Construction worker amongst other things
I probably should add that on the
Former prosecutor of mr. bathrooms case
Joe gottman and James Batson those two people whose conflict in a courtroom back in 1983 gave us the bat
Rock and roll
They are now in 2016
Prince
I'll talk to him about time you have to
Yep we're friends now
How often is it that a prosecutor becomes friends with someone
Helps convey
Not not often I mean retired from a
Prosecuting Austin 2001
Hit Cena
Too many awful things
To make a long story short it was time for me to do something else
And starts teaching at a high school in Louisville
80% black
Where do we
Posing drug testing covered
Jackson
Well drug testing in schools
Seems like a good idea but in actuality
Tell the day I visited Joe gottman's classroom which is like a full-on Mach
Courtroom in
Classroom
He's doing his mock trials with a
I'll be allowed in schools and public schools cuz if no funding
When it's all said and done
I would prefer to be known
More 4
The accomplishments in this classroom
Jennifer Batson
As for James at the batting cages
Eventually
Illegal
Activities
Andy Roebuck
War on jail
Concept
Me trying to get people
Stop doing crime
And the books actually you how these two sort of met up again
One day a few years ago James came to Jose school to give him a copy
He gave me a copy of his book and asked me if I'd look over it I wanted his opinion on it I read the book that night actually
50 books into the school system
Where is Jefferson County now
What happened in the past is in the past
30 years ago he did what he did I did what I did
Let It Go
As far as a legacy the Batson challenge goes it's really interesting to hear them talk about it
Especially because
In the eyes of a lot of people who know these issues
Joe was a villain that was always
Painful part about
Decision in Batson
Is the label of being a racist prostitute
Well that was a horrible lie
Yeah I mean so horrible
But that's in started
I needed discussion and I need a change
On jury selection in America
Can maybe I was just
They're Weatherby
Fate or whatever
But this was the start
Change
Take it for what it's worth
Maybe if Robinson's right we can look at all this
And
Have a little
Tiny Buddha
I think
Baby.
Sean rameswaram
More perfect actually Shawn Kemp more perfect
Tobin low
Kelsey Padgett
Andy Mills
With
Soren wheeler Elie mystal David Herman Alex overington Karen Duffin Sean rameswaram Catherine wells-burr
Michelle Harris
Special thanks to
Email client
D Charles
Sarah
Supreme Court audio is from
We love project
Collaboration with the Legal Information Institute at Cornell more perfect is funded in part by the William and Flora Hewlett Foundation
He Charles Evans Hughes Memorial foundation and the joist