Are you awake
Listening to Radiolab
Radiolab
From WNYC
And NPR
Hey I'm Jared I'm running Robert Radiolab the podcast
Actually brought a list okay let what it was 22
Share with me your list
This is Andrew Moran
He's a writer and editor at the New Yorker magazine
I might have gotten lost to occasionally pops on do I show
Maybe you were mugged
Here it is
And he recently got obsessed with a the list of measure
Base units are called
Ver SI basic
System international
Who did this way you ever wondered
How long an inch
I'm exactly
I know I took a ruler but how do you know that your ruler in my ruler do I have the
The same amount of each
He's worried that someone in China that their inches are inches your engine is
I haven't really thought about it but I'm just a
Assume that there's like a master
Strange somewhere
How do I say in French
That is what was on this listing and you was looking at its a list of standard measures
For everything we have around how big something is
Bar something in hot something
It's all in the
Okay
So when you go down the list of the
Sistema Internacional do you need
Here's what you got a meter
A meter is
A fraction of a second of the distance traveled by light in a vacuum okay
Is
How much radiation corresponds to the transition between two hyperfine levels of the ground
State of the cesium 133 atom that's the definition of a second is a particular atom jiggle yeah
An ampere which measures electric current you know
Is
Constant current which has maintained in two straight parallel conductors of infinite length would produce between these conductors
The force is equal to 2 x 10 to the negative 7th Newtons per meter of length
I have no idea what that
See that's the thing if you look at the actual definition
There is one
Standard on the list
It is unique
Fritz simplicity
The definition of the standard unit of measurement that is a kilogram
Is no man no numbers it is a
Sing
A particular thing
Plum-sized
Sing
It is the only
We used to measure things
Six the last one standing you'll
Physical standard lab why is it the last
Hawaii weather is it what wait what
Let me just take you back to the beginning of the story
Like I must admit that I I expected this
Story to be
A lot more boring that I found it's like an epic
Story
That is Latif Nasser science historian regular on our show he says if you go all the way back to the very first farmers back in
All of the earliest measurements were super intuitive
And he says a lot of them came from the body
As in that bunny is coming close to the net
How close dad two hands
But it's not just like hands and feet but it was also
So many other kinds of measurements like you would say oh something is as far as you know my voice
Skin care
Something is as far as
I can see
Sitting on the top of a camel
Or something is as far as
I can throw a stone
That would be like saying okay I'm going to build
A
Farm here
And I'm going to do it
Three throw rocks
Across the way I read about it was like Travelers like if you're a Saharan traveler you know
Junior you need to know where the next
Watering Hole is
Measurement yeah they would say it
Cinema 3 throw rocks away or it's time for a Rockaway
But you know that there might be some built-in uncertainty there because you ask Achilles
It could be to throw rocks
This way but he asked me it would be like 78 exactly the problem
System
Annie's problems kind of came to a head
In the 1700
It's the eve of the of the French
In a little town called Paris Cosmopolitan place which means that people are coming from different places and they all have their own
Measure
Approximately 250,000 different units of measurement and regular you a hundred and fifty thousand
Commodity has its own measures do you have green wine oil salt hay for wood fabric everything
Ordinarily
Confusing
Not to mention it's
Extraordinarily bad for
I came to you and I said miss you I have video
Of cloth
You would say
How much luck you got
Do Urology
What's a yard
Amelia
Is this March
Is this
And that you can see that it's frustrating it was frustrating and making matters worse 1780s
Was a real family
So there was a shortage of grain
And people were
Hungry and people were angry
Which I am going to
Call audit they were hangry
They were hungry were very hangry
Studebakers at the time they knew that if they raise the price of bread like an angry mob would basically
But they also knew that with no absolute standard it was no way to be sure that what you were getting is what you were getting and so
What they started doing
Was he started
Just lightening their bread loaves by Jess
So as the fam and got worse
People would be waiting in longer and longer lines
To pay the same amount of money
For smaller and
Smaller load
So they were getting hungrier and hang
And so one of the things that
People are like crying out for is that they want
Standardized weights and measures
If I go to the bakery
Can I buy a loaf of bread I want a whole loaf of bread
Don't short me on
Serious
Well you you know what happens now
The Bastille
Stormed in
The king is under house arrest in
Then under the
Guillotine and as soon as the Revolutionary government
All right
Okay this is one of our first priority is we are going to make a new stand
But not based on something arbitrary like
Kik
Why don't we
Drawn some kind of totally
The authority of nature
Of nature
So long story short they took the circumference of the earth they took a quarter of that circumference divided that by 10 million and they got
The meter the mirror they then / 10 cubed it filled the cube with water to the mass of the water into the cylinder
Metal with that mass and why
They created the world
First
The idea of this
Was if we make this thing that is so beautiful and perfect
Everybody can
I see it that way
Then not only will France use it
But the whole world will use it
Then goods and ideas can be exchanged
Everywhere by all people and it will be
They wanted something that would be Eternal and unchanging for everybody
For all time
So now I guess you want to see it though
Yeah okay
Okay so it's in here
We ended up visiting the National Institute of
Standards and Technology
This is where we'll be going in but we're going to go in for this guy was our guide
They took us three stories down into the Bedrock of the
State of Maryland
Could they want things down here
Totally
Still just gone through one Dumbledore
Here comes another Dumbledore
Let me step into the Vault of the room
Kinnaird was
What we're looking at Fan is
A glass jar with a handle on top and then inside that is another glass jar with a lid
Little handle on top
And inside that is is the thing do you think it's
Kind of
Who is this really
The shiniest loosens you ever seen
Very small and it looks very clean
Hard to tell where the like Russian doll glass jar stop because it's over
Reflective
This might be crazy question but can we hold a kilogram that's a producer the levy
It feels like we've been talking about it so they are very careful with
The real
The original of the original of the original
Original gong
Caught
As they call it leaves in a basement
In France you can't get anywhere near.
Are you cooking I can get all Tom Cruise on that die trying
Here's how it works
The international prototype is Laguna that's the one used to calibrate 6
Identical Platinum sellers what they call witnesses for tomorrow
In French those Witnesses are then used to calibrate another set of cylinders which are then used to calibrate the u.s. standard Witchwood
Esau and that one is used to calibrate all kinds of things
The weight of your lemons the scale in your bathroom
Every time somebody loses a pound of that TV show Biggest Loser
You can actually Trace that like a bloodline if you will or an unbroken chain
Back
To the international prototype kilogram
Grab to a single object in a basement in France the holy of holies
What is the Killer
But you're telling me that when something is weighed in the world often it goes
All the way back
One hunk of metal or something which was why the next part of the story
Is so
Disconcerting
What happened in 1989
Is that according to Andrew the folks who take care of the official kilogram a big k
He took it out
Jars they put it in a steam bath
Hit it with the steam
The prince is everything
Wait for it to dry
Then
They commenced a ceremonial way
How do you weigh the thing that is the standard of weight while you weigh it against the copy
Like the US copy
Beef example so they get one of those and they put it on one side
Okay on the other end
Vipk the logo on car the one
Is light
What
It doesn't how many how many how much
Lighters invented
Roughly the
Mass of a grain of
Sugar
So was that gigantic tits measurable but how do they know that it was light and not the other ones
Heavy right well they didn't
So they used the second sister copy still light and
The third sister copies
Still late in the fourth
5th and second comes the man from Germany from Canada light in comes the man from Spain
Which led them to the troubling possibility that the international standard for weight
Was losing weight
Well we think that we think the big guy
As far as how it lost that weight
Really knowing us one possibilities about cleaned too much and maybe some of it.
Scraped away although
It's disputed whether cleaning it more would make it lose weight or gain weight
The other theory is outgassing like maybe a little hydrogen is seeping out of the metal and then there was one thing I read that
Foul Play cannot be ruled out I was thinking maybe
Malaysian here we got a hunk of metal losing weight and yet because it easily standard it still weighs exactly a killer
Write up the definition of a kilogram is
The mass of the international prototype kilogram
Whatever happens when you put that thing on the scale that's a kilogram
You can't do that and then everything else in the world is wrong
Doesn't sit right that's like something that like the North Korean government would do
Just feel like no more cash
Like that we can't just go around capriciously doing so
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help this summer I'm hosting a show
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
About what we're calling tiny moments of childhood brilliance
Basically I want to hear about those times when I did something
It just means you lean back and say wow
How do they do that
Maybe it was the moment that our kids you've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of the musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed are ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the
Specific moments where
A kid does something super smart but it doesn't have anything to do with the test
If you have a story please share it with us
Go to radiolab.org
Flash brilliance
Record short audio message
Again that's radiolab.org / Brillion
Thank you so much
Rights of the standard of weight is
As you're saying losing weight so how do you fix
Well
I'm getting 0 cell phone reception down here it means we're really do
When we were down in that underground room in Maryland we met a guy
Oh there is
Okay his name is John Pratt I'm the leader of the fundamental electrical measurements group at the National Institute of Standards and Technology
Analogy
John wants us to even more high security doors
Gloomy walked into this by God
Amazing Race
It's big it is big
Three stories tall
Take a silver room
It has a silver gray floor at silver shiny wall
And your hair is on the Silvery side
Very much so
I don't even know how to do
It looks
Like a wheel turned on its side with the thing itself
Looks sort of just like a like a massive
Round metal cauldron more like big metal
Pot
But then there are all these weird little gizmos and part in and all these coiled up wires and just a stunning machine
But it's all just for the benefit of the one
1 measure 1 kilogram extremely
Extremely sensitive balance
An equal arm balance
Basically like a seesaw
Our a teeter totter
And
Usually you would set that up so that you would literally put
Kid on one side of the teeter-totter kid on the other side of the teeter-totter now you've been in a playground so you know how this goes but what they've done here is
One side of the teeter-totter they've.
The kilogram like the ground guy
Number one
On the other side
Gattu will have
Highly variable magnet
Now here's the thing the magnet won't be touching that side of the scale it'll be exerting a force
An invisible force
It'll produce a force
And
We could use that
To hold the balance
And of course he takes
Hold up the balance that of course is to
Same as the weight
Cosseting
And if you can convert that Force into a number that everybody agrees to Wawa
You have just redefined the kilogram you have wrenched
Get from the world of things
Has become attached
The fundamental forces of the universe
Depth even grasp the gist of it
You want to see that happen
Have a great now I can show you this
With our Lego version of the watt balance
If I can fire it up Lego Lego one will see that the big one was being tested or something so
So they took us
Over to look at the little one
Okay so
We have hello scale disturb the balance and it's
El chikilin around a little hitch free-floating
Hey so you're now going with your tweezers and your pucking a titty bitty
What's this tiny little symbol thing on the Mountain hours going to East
To levitate
Now it seems he promised me Macon Macon
You know I'm going to put the Macon
And
When do we see the levitation
That was it I didn't I missed it do it again it was floating
It is floating
Sitting on the balance
That's a different idea of levitation
Now the truth is that once I finally figured out what this guy was doing it was actually sort of cool he had taken a little metal way
Play he put it on one side of the
On the other side of the scale
Empty baguette
The thing didn't
Skip over because the empty
I actually had a magnetic force equivalent
To the metal
Holding
Perfectly still
Dark Souls II able to do that does that mean that the grand Cay
Is rain is
Not yet no because first of all week that you have to get straight with a lot of man MC squared new work back
Backwards / eaten by Amazon to be filled
Let's go and you're watching your Planck's constant classical Bohr model of atoms and stuff anyway
It is actually way more complicated
This whole thing that I
Prank people ever
Understand but here's where we are at
You got all these different teams around the world you got John's team in Maryland with his seesaw you got another lab a couple of them
Have their seesaws you got a third level
Literally counting the atoms are all doing experiments comparing numbers trying to get the numbers to agree so that by
I would ever rude everybody agreed on exactly what a kilogram is
Right now they're closed their they're in agreement out to about 6
Decimal
Places and that's not good enough they want the numbers to be at the 8
Decimals
Play see if they can do that
And only then
Will the grand Cape be no more
Yeah
Because instead of defining the kilogram as
Whatever is equal to the ground k
Now you have a new death
The new definition of the kilogram to kilogram
Is the SI unit of mass its magnitude is set by fixing the numerical value of Planck constant speed equal to exactly
6.6 26069
Do we have X's cuz we haven't all agreed with the final
Does the missing decimals
When is expressed in the unit fractions Joule seconds which is
A meter squared kilogram per second
That'll be such a simple definition
No u
What will happen to the Grand Cay when the new definition goes into effect
When I saw this is the
Looks like a tree
Is the church where the
The ground Kami eventually end up in a in a place like this
That's a big deal with so many standard
I've gone to die
This is the Music These are they mature
In Paris
Beginning
Suzhou tour guide
What is this
Elite controllers the original leader
Kimberly thermometer
Who wrote the show Des Peres this was the infallible
Absolute
Standard
From 18
1 -
It's in a wooden box with a velvet
And it's got
Ribbons at either end
And it's just a very beautiful looking Silver Rod
No matching like the thing the grand thing being in this place
Seeing the Pope in short
Or something
Uncomfortable
Special thanks to
And
And also to
We want to forget
Richard Davis
Michael
And sign
Thank you to our math Angel soprano
Also big props to reporter Andrew Marantz latinaass Iran
Ooo-ooo-ooo also you should go to radiolab.org
The Show by clicking the sport button but also to check out a collaboration video that we did with
Henry Rice from minute physics
You can see it radiolab.org are also
Youtube.com
Minutephysics
Yet another meditation
On what things
Run things
I'm Jared I'm right I'm Robert krulwich
Thanks for listening