Northern listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
Who's iPad is this
But it was mine
Oh my gosh best for your handwriting
Your handwriting is not awful it's actually very elegant
Is it legible not so much
But elegant
Generous Radiolab so not too long ago Robert and our producer Bethel habte has a nice lean-to
To it pulled me into the studio to walk me through this
Story that they've been working on together for
Everybody
Yes so what are you doing
You guys are just going to tell me the story or could rather tell you a riddle okay
Once Upon a Time Birds evolve
They evolve from dinosaurs
So they was originally scary things in the scales turn to feathers in the
Feathery things began to fly we call those things Birds
But they haven't lately I just I'm going to just ask this to you out of the blue because it's a basic appendage
How many birds
Have
Penis
Oh oh oh can I buy before you answer
There are like 10 to 20 thousand different kinds of birds button by modern time
So again how many of those
Have penis
At what percentage of currently existing bird bird species have in the mail
With the penises as we would identify like a hangout
Is it making weird penis
Zolman Tire
Do you know how many times we said penises are there in 27 and 4 minutes
Birds have penis
Well
I have
Absolutely no frame of reference answer this question I don't know I mean
Lower
Dead
10 lower
Lower
One three
3%
Yeah 97% of birds
Don't have penis
Wow yeah
So we learned this little fact from a scientist named Patty Brennan
So weird about birds is precisely the fact that they they lost a penis
Will you just said
You just use an interesting. So that you say the birds lost the penis is so does that mean that
Earlier editions of birds it have them
That's right yes of penises are widespread traits of old
Vertebrates right except for you know some amphibians
And fish
And according to Patty if you go back 200 million years or so
Birds were like all those other creature
Yeah like basically 100% of them had penises sexy right over time
Vast majority of birds apenas was then lost
Now
Well that's the question how do you lose a penis like
It seems like a pretty handy thing to have when you want to put your sperm close to female eggs to the 97%
Don't have a penis now what do they have David kind of hold the mail and the females have these holes in the shirt
Open up anime line them up yeah it's called a cloaca
Play Commander MTG and that's it that's it and it works just fine but if you're thinking about the engineering what appendages
Is going to work best for you to make babies
Penis is the one because it gets your sperm closer to female eggs
So far all of these penises to just vanish like she says that evolutionarily that just doesn't make any
Acquired you lose a thing
What's so useful for there to be selection for the penis to to go away
There's going to be a very important reason
What's the reason
Well there's a few possibilities
Number one people have speculated for example that you might have been sexually transmitted diseases
You're putting this Pinos way deep into the female and then you're pulling your penis back into your click I like that could be potentially
Easy Exchange of of sexually transmitted
Cuz you're like digging the germs deeper I guess exactly yeah yeah yeah so even though the penis has its advantages obviously
Maybe it's only one way because the birds that had the penises just kept getting these inspections that's
But so far nobody's found a link between penises and STDs so then the other possibility that's really intriguing actually
Is the babies because
Penises are heavy
Number to start flying
And getting rid of the penos would have been an easy thing for lowering your body weight
Maybe they lost him so they could fly further items
I mean I think that's
Unlikely to have Phoenix strong enough selection
Because ducks for example are among the most long-distance migrants
And they still have penises Theron to 3% and sometimes they have penises that are bigger than
Theron body
So
Patriots to my god you watch a penis go by with wings
Oh my God yes I think the record is a male that had a 43c
Centimeter long penis
And this is a male that was only about 40 centimeters long himself
So apparently you going to be pretty large penis and fly just
The Ducks are also sort of the key to a third Theory
Pretty disappearance of the penis so yeah so I was going to say my favorite
This is some this idea that actually had to do with female choice
Against
Males that controls Ripper.
To explain Patty actually thinks that the original bird penises
Might have been a lot like the modern-day
Duck penis
Which is essentially
A weapon
I'm so one of the things that we learned when we were studying the Ducks is that
Do males have a bolt Direction mechanism that is
Crazy they have Annex
Close his erection mechanism
What that means is that the male actually efforts his penis and ejaculates in a third of a cell
Basically a a a pistol
Penis looking mushroom yeah it just goes between yes
Wow what what does though is that it allows these males
To forcefully inseminate females even when females don't want to be inseminated right safety smell
Is anywhere near a female is just going to go and push right through
And so as you can imagine that's not
You know
That's not something you Starley desirable for female
Often times with females will be
Struggling
They're trying to get away from these
Emails that are trying to forcibly copulate
So Patty thinks that will might have happened here is that female Birds trying to get away from males with
Large penises and
He's really violent ways of
Approaching reproduction
Begin systematically choosing gentler and smaller males with smaller penises right so so if females
Closest are selecting males that are less
Violently sexually violent did that my
Lead to the disappearance
But I think you just said is
Overtime because the ladies were
The ladies were just comforted
The gentleman
Changed
And lost their penis
You got it
She think that that's females essentially castrated males well is a slower process
Castration / time
Yes I suppose
Now what meme
What makes you what what evidence is there for such a thing
So no I mean
Norman in a way because we're talking about penises which are soft tissue
And they don't fossilize so even if we went back into the fossil record
It would be really hard to fight
Find evidence of Wadsworth have
So that's the part that is difficult you know it's kind of like a wonderful story
That that I think makes a lot of sense given what we know about the way these penises work now
We can only
Speculate
I like this idea
But is this just a one-off I mean
What about Gorillas in Moose who fighting
Clash their horns I mean there's so many species where it just seems like the females have zero choice
So I know they there are a lot of cases like that of bedbugs are especially horrifying Google it
Talk about bed bugs but
There are actually a lot of cases where
When the females do get to choose
Bape shoes in ways that
Completely change
What we see in nature are we found a group of scientist who now are
Cute but if you look around nature you will see females driving evolution in ways that I certainly didn't expect
And when they get into the details of how this actually works I think it's going to
Flip your ideas about evolution
In a way that you are totally unprepared for
Do they have evidence for this idea cuz I got to say to you haven't yet convinced me of the first thing they said
That females have
Evolve the penises away
I guess that was a guess
I will introduce you to a bird called a bowerbird
That I think will spell it speaks for itself in these regards
And it's also his penis list
They're really
They have
Beautiful plumage the satin bowerbird is a
Beautiful iridescent blue with a
Violet blue eyes this is Gail Gail patricelli and I'm a professor of evolution at a and ecology at
UC Davis
Well I say that again without stuttering on and
No no
Anyway so the Bower birds what makes them
Most amazing is that they build
Bowers
So about our
Listings of birds
Build
Basically a structure made out of
Text which can be up to 3 feet tall and it repeats
Loving it in some of these things now
Yeah and
It looks like an s
But it's really a kind of Seduction theater with one seat
And that nms for her this is Richard from of Yale University sat biology
Is there any system on and around this bow
The mail will a real whole bunch of
Down.
Precious objects
Beautiful
Parrot feathers and berries and flowers and leaves stuff that the bird gathers from the forest episode East
Structures can be very ornamented and elaborate every species has its own
Style and some species of all be blue everything
Blue feathers
Blue flowers and then of course blue trash like drinking straws and bottle caps
In the mail by bird
Basically dedicate this whole life learning how to build these structures
What take the satin bowerbird they take 7 years before they reach sexual maturity and during that. Of time they look
Just like females
An elephant fly around the valley and get
Courted by adult males
So they play the role of the female
And learn how courtship works from other males
In the valley and then when they get a little older that's teenagers
All-Star building practice
Court each other and eventually once about a bird figures out how to make a really good stuff
Female has arrived
SLL fly down to the bower and now often check out the bower itself
Symmetrical like a well-built
And if she likes what she sees
Slender the Bower
This is where things get interesting
Because the bower has a very particular
Purposeful architecture
So it's two parallel walls
Styx
It better close to one another
And the female sits between them
Three different variations on the basic design but in all cases the female is in a protector
Did position
There's always some kind of barrier or wall between her and the mail so the male wants to try
Try to force himself on her for whatever reason
He has to run around the back and she can just fly away out the front
Even as he's trying to win her attention completely he's built a building that keeps her out of disk
Absolutely the bower is like
Insurance against date rape
For the female
It allows the female to observe him at an intimate close distance for as long as she likes
While still maintaining our freedom of choice
So the female if she likes
The Bower
So settle into this protected space
Where she can back out whenever she likes
And then time to begin the show
So he'll start out with his own
His own displays many of them
Very loud electronic sound sounds
They do they do imitations of kookaburra
Cockatoos
Then along singing
Didn't they pop up on a run vigorously back and forth right in front of
The female and she's standing between the walls of the
So the female watches all this from her seat
Spot for as long as she likes and she can decide
She would like
To meet with this guy or
Not good enough
Stop and fly away
For the female
The moment
Pisco
That was particularly interesting here is a gale has done studies
You said show
Windmill
A very close attention to the female like when the male really watches her body position
The way that she's like pastured that can actually signal whether she's interested or not the males that respond to most of those signals are
Are the most successful in mating
In other words if the male makes his move too early and too aggressively
She's gone
And that mail doesn't have any babies
But it also seems like the females are
Have toying with the males like seeing what they're willing to
Do for them like
If you if you watch a video of this
You can see in one bowerbird
She comes in he like
A list of his wing with
Kate and then just like sort of rotates his wing like this like
It's so funny like a like a like a like a matador and then
Right after that
She like
Picks up
A blueberry
From the ground
Henan
She drops the blueberry and then he does the Matador thing with the blueberry in his mouth
Good vibe
Seems to be all about her
May I see what you mean
Yeah I did females are definitely driving driving the bus
And when you start to really think about the implications of this about it being all about her
That can lead you to a fairly deep rethink of the very basic rules of how evolution
Really
Normally the classical argument with credit like the reason this male bird is so color
Apple so red or whatever
The reason the peacock has the gigantic and
Beautiful feathers on its tail
Is sort of a signal
That the mail is sending to the female of Fitness look at me
I am healthy to have a tail like this I don't have parasites I'm strong
I be a great mate
Play survival of the fittest
Right but let me ask you if you just heard about bird story you have these females with these
Ouija
He's like this one
Likes
Gulou
Only blue
And this one likes iridescent shells
So it shall sell sell sell sell than this one likes green leave but they have to be right side up and never ripen upside down
Fitness signals or is this more like
Art
Maybe she just likes
Blue
Or she just
Likes
Shell
What you're saying that
These birds evolve based on on whims and tastes well or Rick
And there's other
Smells like him save absolutely yes it's about beauty I'm really focusing in on aesthetic
Choices
Choices that are based on what it is the animal likes
Where's at the whole darwinian
Thought
Was
Will you okay there might be Beauty there but on some level the logic behind those beautiful
Things is
Survival survival of the fittest that does not sound very darwinian
Well since you dropped the name I propose at my view is
The legitimately authentically Darwin interview
Darn he had an idea about beauty
Oh yeah he he actually
Okay
Page 397
Descent of Man
Stripes and marks
And ornamental appendages have
Alban indirectly gained through the influence of
Love love
Jealousy
Through the appreciation of the beautiful
Enter the exertion of a choice
How interesting
So you saying
That is love jealousy and beauty
Choice
Yeah Android
Yeah that's definitely not what I learned
So it's
Over a hundred thirty years later and I'm still pissed
You think there was some kind of plot
To reduce
Darwin's idea into
Does something smaller
And eventually
Eliminated in tire
I would like to go historical let's go out with Darwin
Let's go Wallace said
And then let's go
Did the 20th century and where we got so screwed up
Charles Darwin spent 20 years working on his theory of natural selection
He was not particularly noisy about it
Because you knew it would
Very much
Disturb his wife was quite religious and other people in his church so during the twenty years while Darwin was working away
This other guy comes on
His name is Alfred Russel Wallace
Kind of skinny in scrapy and self-taught 14 years younger than Charles Darwin
Went around the world collecting specimens and he also
Came up with a theory of natural selection
Independent
What was the relationship
To each other I mean today where they friends were they collaborators were they
Hope you know they were
Close
Collaborators first they kind of both got credit
For the idea
But
A little later Darwin rocket it out his book into interpress
What he publishes On the Origin of Species
Very popular book Darwin got the Lion's Share of the credit as I think rightly so
Has he been working on the idea for literally for decades
In 20 years later Darwin dies
Meanwhile Wallace lived in until the dawn of War
I drink if I'm this is Rick's argument after Darwin die
Wallace kept saying over and over and over again
Then when it came to female Choice animals
I didn't have the sensory and cognitive capacity to make aesthetic judgments and nature so these is love
Amber decorations and be artistic
Behaviors can only evolve if it communicates
Information about
Vigor
Quality and general fitness to survive
And Rick would say that because Darwin wasn't around to argue back
Wallace may have lost
The the battle
Over
Credit
For the
Discovery of adaptation by natural selection
What do you want the war over what evolutionary biology would become in the 20 Century
We have inherited both the science and the culture of flattened dumbed-down and ideologically purify
White version of Darwin's
Actual richest
Fighting words
About UC Rick is pretty fired up about
This and he's written a book
Evolution of beauty
Where he argues that ever since Alfred Russel Wallace scientist have been trying to squeeze everything
AC in these male patterns male dancers male songs male blue images
It was single explanation
Can a dogmatic category
Cult Fitness net female choice they claim is always
Always about Fitness Bethesda
Erica is now you know that is
That's a stretch
Is no way to boil down all this variety Into Fitness
I'm not saying that the emperor wears no clothes
I'm saying that the emperor
Is wearing a loincloth
What I mean by that is that that humble garment
Covers about the same percentage of the human body
As the idea of a adaptive mate choice
Covers all the ornaments
Sexual ornaments in the world what you just said is that most
Or most of what you see most of what you see in the world you think is
Who is desire
The desire between creatures expressed in in beautiful for absolutely not
Not that oh that
She's just looking at him thinking he's strong he's genetically
Trustworthy none of those just
I love him
Yeah
Yes it would he say most
Most of the time when you see the ornaments that
Not Fitness at all that's what he said most
Is Big Time on most
Why would you even
Know that I mean it as a human how would you ever even know the inner workings of another creatures mind
To know enough to say what it isn't this driving or not I got this very quiet I didn't know I asked a very question
$20 just came by
Right isn't it
Possible for you as a human being than any ID
Dear what
A lady animal monster
To see in a guy if
That lady animal is
A peahen what you aren't
Or
A trollop I'm ready to answer this I hope
Here it is
I don't know what she wants now
But I know historically she's wanted exactly what you see in those males
The peahen has wanted that big ol tail
She's wanted the show
She's wanted the blue chest she has
At some time or another in the last
I don't know how many thousands of years
She has wanted everything you see on him from the Fancy Feathers
To the white skin around his eye to the
Iridescent blue the shaking
That's what she has wanted in the past
How do you do that
Because it's there
Seriously what is a lawyer in the room
Where are biceps
Yeah so you just happened to have this like
Define nanostructured
Iridescent colors in your feather because like 42 interacting genes across five different chromosomes came to
Together to give you iridescent blue
The way you get iridescent blue says Kim is you start small
You give your female a bunch of choices which are the males
Interblock so imagine the female bird surrounded by a bunch of males who are all just boring or gray or black or what
Whatever then totally randomly
Email servers up
Who just happens to have
A little bit of blue on them
And she noticed
When the sun glints off of his black plumage there's just a little answer blue in that black
Glossy
Shiny blue black
I like that
I like that that
It's a little different than everybody else and I like it
Who knows why
It could be totally random to
But for whatever reason she decides to meet with the blue guy I like that and because he's passing on his genes
Her sons are likely going to be a little bit blue to her offspring are going to have those beautiful jeans
And we already know that the females chose him because he was attractive and so she's going to have attractive
And her daughters are going to also find
Those traits attractive
And so what you can
Our generations and generations of females you say
And then it goes you're you're creating your ear evolving the mail
To please the female end it all starts
With I like that
But I like that
Doesn't feel to me
Opposite of Fitness like I like that could be
A desire that is
Driven by in
And couldn't like the walls person walk in and be like
Yeah she likes that because she was designed to like that
She's not thinking about the
Did the why there she's just having a desire but behind that desire is
Maybe a drive to get her to leave mail that is the best
Like it could be the same with us too with people
Like what we find sexy
Might have
Maybe in the end of the bout Fitness that's a perfectly reason
Edible objection but what if I told you about an animal who has a fierce desire
SHOW beauty
And this particular desire for beauty is
So strong
That Fitness is
Out of the picture
As a bird
It's another
Fix fries I know
Take a break take a break
And afterward we'll come back with
Third bird
Hi this is Sarah calling from
Scarsdale New York
Radiolab
What is supported in part by the alpha
Teaspoon
Enhancing public understanding of Science Fiction
Technology
In the modern world
More information about Sloan
Www.
Turn. Org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
And I request
For those of you who
We spend a lot of
What type of kits parents
Aunts and uncles teachers we're looking for stories about what we're calling
Tiny moment
Brilliant
Basically I want to hear about this
Did something
It just means you read back and say
Well
How to make
Maybe it was the moment that I
I kid you've been reading to 4 month started reading back
Do you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lesson
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of the musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class
You noticed they're ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the
Epic moments where
Kid does something super smart
But it doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story
T-shirt with us
Go to radiolab.org
Flash brilliance
And record
Short audio
And that's radiolab.org
Flash brilliance
Thank you so much
Dad Robert battle Radiolab we're back mid battle between
Beauty and Fitness
Bird battle battle and introduce our third
Bird
Yeah you want me to go
So there's a bird out there called
The club winged Manakin
And this mannequin live
In the jungles of
I forgot where she was somewhere in the jungles
South America South America Colombia well okay so the the
The club winged Manakin has a very small range in Colombian Ecuador
Is it big
Tiny Bird the males the Mills are mostly red bright red hair Auburn body
And black and white wings with little flecks
Pics of yellow underneath them boobies are small bird lots of color and female
Raise the babies on her own because she doesn't need guys except for the physical sexual act
He doesn't have to provide for her he just has to attract
So to that end
This is what are little red Romeo will do
Hilton Sedona branch
In the Indian jungle
And he'll wait awhile
Until females
And then when she does he has a courtship display and he
Bounces back and forth on The Purge
And while he's bouncing around every so often stops
Boar's Head
Sticks his butt up in the air wings all position and Heat
Rosa
Behind his back and then
Vibrate
Shivers he Shivers his wings together so that the only things that touch
Are those feathers across the back the tips of those funny feathers are going knock knock knock knock knock knock knock knock
They not 39 times in a row
It takes about a third of a second for those 39 Knox
Their wings vibrate
So fast
But they make the sound
Can you make a can you make the sound
No it's impossible for humans to make with their voice
Is that serious
It's like a truck backing up
Exactly
So he's not using his voice that it's just as Wings kids got this instrument
Yeah it's like it's
She called Street relation
So this is a cricket winged Manakin would be a perfectly good name for the spark
In any case something about that sound that specific
Sound
Excites the female
We don't know why but when it started but somewhere in the birds
Past a female decided she likes that sound and so the mail just started to make it
But here's the thing
In order to make that sound yeah they
Really have paid
They have they have paid
Because
To vibrate your wings that fast
107 times per second you need
A rigid Wing phone that you can really control
And so the club winged Manakin has done something unheard of
Their wingbonz went solid
Just like a rock inside there
This is a big deal because
Flying birds
Have Halloween
Actually can fly
Actually even Velociraptor and T-Rex
Chav Halo
So this is a feature that predates the origin of birds and the origin of
What this guy has given this up
In order to make
These
Extraordinary wingsong
What does not hurt your ability to fly vs
Set yes
They are slow
Heavy
Unable to LEAP buildings in a single bound cost of doing business
A display right
Think about that you're in a crowded Forest
Lots of competitors. The Predators trying to eat you
And you've made yourself
Slower
More vulnerable
And it gets worse
Because
Mannequins
How to start this process of building these hard bones really early
Like when they're very very tiny
In the embryo for the embryo has become either male or female
So you got an embryo that can go either way and they're already making the big bones and some of them are going to be mailed
But some of them are going to be female
So by choosing males with weird Wing Bones because they make great songs
The female also has daughters
With distorted
And inferior Wing Bar
That they will never use
Both the females and the males
Skip these thick bones
So she is choosing to hear that sent
And has designed him to produce that
But
In the bargain
He comes out with heavier bonsai
I can fly last
And weirdly enough
She comes out with heavier bones
I can file EX
So both of them
Are hurting
Their chances
Just survive
For the chance
I hear the beautiful tone
She wants to hear that he wants to give her
Wait so
So she has every buns to
But she doesn't use them know Rick's Auto mediately like
I think all this is where the females got the bumps on her bones too and he's like
Like what
I can females have it but they don't use it she's bearing the cost
Of her own choices decadence
This is like
20 years ago
What did he mean so everybody in the population be
Becomes worse off because females are so choosy and shoes
Beauty
So from Rick's point of view you got a contest going on here
Two Primal drives
And on the one hand there's the desire to survive
Survival of the fittest right
And according to that logic
The mannequin should go for the things that make him
Swift and powerful and agile
But on the other hand lyrics
A second Drive
Or in this case to hear something
They like
Something Beautiful
And
In this case
That second Drive is so strong that it's winning
It's
It's pushing the birds
Away from Fitness
So so we've gone we've gone through the math
And others have as well and there is nothing in theory nothing to prevent
Discard process
From leading to Extinction
Oh my God
Right you just you just turned what I totally think of evolution on its head
Like we've always been taught
That what these animals are doing is they're adopting as best as they can to new and changing conditions and
Getting
Better
But here you say that they are so
Hung up on desire and beauty that they even are going to get worse
Write what you know
That's why this example is
Checkmate but there are biologists
Eminently
Hello
You want to be sucking a lollipop whatever you're doing it again
Like Jerry Queen of the University of Chicago
What is it is it a lollipop
Orange cough drops
So Jerry redrix book and there's not not convinced
By his acumen
Well I think it's a good book
But it's not a great book it's good because
It has really great
Stories about mating behavior which are accurate stories as far as I know and they're quite absorbent
Promise a good writer
The recent side great book is that it's tendentious that is as written to promote a Cause
Which is of course that males with
Beautiful ornaments are shaped by female sense of beauty
Not Fitness
I think that the word Fitness is a huge problem
And I don't use it anymore
That you can't just say that and have it accepted by scientists unless you can test it
And that is
Ruggeri when it comes to the stories that we just heard like the bowerbird or the mannequin he thinks that more is going on
I'm here then what
Richard says in his book
You know take the female bowerbirds preference for Bowers at keep her apart
From mail
I mean Richard
Explanation that
It allows the female
More
Time to choose it doesn't freak her out because she feels protected that might be the right right explanation
But we don't know how many could be that females have an innate preference
It's for being sheltered
Because it gives them a sense of
Social Security
Like cats
Cats like to beatbox
This right because
They feel sheltered and they feel safe and it could be that female bowerbirds
The same way
And that would lead to exactly the same situation but with a
Completely different explanation and it's not just
A random aesthetic
Or he says maybe some female bowerbirds like blue so much because
Blueberries are really good for them and
Is there an 8 we drawn to blue because of
Or that let go to the American Tail
What that no 1500 Hearthstone Rick says that
Simply Delights the female's butt
Suppose that the females prefer males
They have a certain freak
Seawing beating
Because they were attuned to that frequency perhaps
Because it indicates
Something in their environment
It's useful to unlike the presence of a predator
Could be anything really
Sound of some romantic and friendly animal or the
Protective animal maybe the
Although they were babies baby chicks and so they just have their nervous system innately tune
Set frequency
See that's called sensory bias
Another theory
So they carry doesn't dispute the fact of female birds like
Bowers
Or that they like
Beautiful tone
He just think that there might be a reason behind their liking and that reason could include
Fitness
Correct but are you are you hoping I guess is that the right word hoping that there might be
A parasite signals involved here like you don't know you just want to know I don't know I mean that's my whole point
And that's why I don't think I don't propose my own theory of special selection I'm not sure which one is
Doesn't count for these mannequins with the heavy bones we just don't know
Oh my God this can't just keep this conversation we're having keeps ending up in the same place which is we just don't know
The difference between me and Doctor promise I have been I don't know
The suggestion here is it Rick is clinging to a
Faith in one explanation for
Wallace it was Fitness
The Rickey
It's Beauty but still that
Dogmatic insistence I just think that adaptation by natural selection is is
Pretty boring
You know we've been going to 150 years in week
Whip-whip that pony quite a bit and we made a whole bunch of progress but you know what there's this huge world
Trinity in the static evolution
Bet that has been missed
In fact Rick would say
Of essential beauty is it can be
Many many different
It is
Gangnam beauty is fundamentally subjective
So the aesthetic model requires that we put the subjective experience desire itself at the center
Of our of our scientific explanation
But can you even have it a science
The basement
Experience
IFixit
Data science of subjective experience
It's not only
A good idea it's necessary
To understand the natural world
Yeah
There is idiosyncrasy
Again ornithologist kimbap
You can't take the individuals out of it
So you don't
Is that science or is that just
Okay it really comes down to
She's a Carp Lakes with that male carp has she the worm lights with the worm has she the bird like what the bird has
You have a trillion explanation each one different depending upon the lady didn't want to see you go
Where are you at that so-called Beauty and desire a category of an explanation as to not
Tell you very much
That doesn't worry me at all
II doesn't worry me at all
You
All of us we are individuals we have unique
History
And life on this planet has a unique history
Science has a hard time dealing with unique instances
But biology is it just in your face with it
There are individual females making choices if that individual female had not made that choice history might have been.
Different in the species might look different
And that
Is true
That's just
True
In in physics
Conceit that but a scientist
Supposed to do is take
Clueless
Variety that you see in front of you and say look
I can boil this down to a rule
Which is always true
Yeah we usually had one rule
Everything
So what did John of science usually is this
Find some kind of Oneness inside the Menace
But now we've got
Nature and living thing
And they have this crazy spec
Tacular variety
Now you've got a group of people who say you don't Maybe
We shouldn't even try
To explain all this
With one
Laurel or one
Paradise
But you know I wonder
If
If that's
Still science
Or
Or is it more like
History
What if every species or every animal
Comes with its own store in Century
Once upon a time and then
Once Upon a Time
Once
What time
Once Upon a Time
Once upon
Is this was reported by you have a crow witch
And Bethel hobday and Bethel
Produced story
Bethel
Sure thing
And special thanks also to Jessa. Skeet for her work on peacocks and Mikayla Gunther
African hyenas
We didn't mention the peacocks in the hyenas in which repeat that but we are very grateful
Both of you
Goodbye goodbye
Well I'm not done with you
Thanks for listening
Hi this is Kim Bostwick calling from Trumansburg New York
Radiolab was created by Jed abendroth
And is produced by Soren wheeler
Director of sound design
Suzie lechtenberg is RA
Executive producer
Includes Simon Adler
Becca Bressler
Rachel kusick David Gable
Kasie hunt
Max guilty
Robert krulwich
Julia Longoria
Annemieke Yuan
Blackish Master Melissa O'Donnell
Kelly Price
Sarkari
Ariana wax pet Walter
And Molly Webster
With help from FEMA
And Neil
Tunisia
Are fact checker
Michelle Harris
If I can verify that Michelle Harris
Thank you and this mess