Hey this is Dad so
A couple of us here have been working really hard for
Last few months on a
On a new spin-off
Radio apps for spinoff
Called more perfect
It is a miniseries about the Supreme Court
Working on it for months and months
We just released our first episode last
Next week we're super proud of it
And I'm talking to you now
Cuz I want you to see
Describe the Spy
I think you will really like
If you like Radiolab you will like this
So I'm asking to do one better I don't know where she going to feature a couple of
Episodes of Maury
Perfect on this pot
On Radiolab
Cuz we know if we really
I think you'll like it
And that we hope you'll go to iTunes or Google or whatever it is you get your podcast and you subscribe
And you'll spread the word
The people listen to this thing
Maybe we'll keep doing it
Alright so
What you're about to hear is episode
2 of March
Perfect
Are you spending
Supreme Court
Episode one is already out
The Voice you're going to hear is Suzie lechtenberg
Who is my main
Collaborator on the project
Choose long-time executive producer
Freakonomics
Shinar
Cooking up this project
So
Here it is episode 2
I think we should start the story on June 25th 1969
Urmc
I'm jazz
I'm ride this is more perfect okay so why
Why 220 when was it
June 25th 1969
Supreme Court chief justice Earl Warren is retiring or a Warren of the Warren Court
Isn't that a big Court
Yeah that's what I think of you think of legendary
Supreme Court judge
Says he's probably in
Top five
So he was one of the mount Olympians he's a big deal
Right now he's retiring so he's retiring he's been on the court for 16 years
And he's in an interview in his ass
Would you list Master Chief Justice of the Supreme Court's most important decision you're 16 years here
Is kind of astounding
Not only of state legislatures by Porsche before you hear the answer
I think that you need to know that he could have said all kinds of cases he was the chief justice
During
Miranda
Remain silent
Or Gideon versus Wainwright
Beauty
Harvey Specter
Athens Big Bore Brown versus Board of Education
Mad when I know that one
He doesn't say any of those
What is issei
He says this little case called
Scarface
Baker vs. Carr
The Batcave
Is perhaps the most important case that who that
Since I've been on the court
He thought that case whatever it is is more important than the case that desegregated the school
He did
So what the hell is it
Exactly
No really what is it
It's this case that was so dramatic and so dramatic
But it apparently
Broke to Justice
There was an instance in which
My
Brother found my father going upstairs
To get a shotgun
Supreme Court of the United States
United States
United States and this honorable Court
Is this more perfect miniseries about the Supreme Court just a frame the story we're about to hear first
Second
As we were putting the show together
We we hosted a panel discussion
A couple of us were on stage and a woman in the audience asked the following question
Address what I see is the
Increasing politicization of the Court the apotheosis of which I guess was
You know voting
Electing Bush to be our
President always been this way is this just my perception that it's becoming more popular
Size
I didn't know this until City started looking into it but there was a moment
When the Pandora's Box
Just got ripped off
So I think they understand that moment and this story you have to get to know three care
These aren't necessarily the three most important justices of all time because of that time you had chief justice Earl
Warren
And William Brennan on the court in these are kind of giants
Supreme Court judge
But for this story
These three guys are
One of them is on the right
One of them is on the left
And one of them is just stuck right in the middle
Tragically in the middle
On the conservative side
Oliviana expression or action by the state
You had a guy named Felix Frankfurter
Did Justice Frankfurter was one of the most sweetest name is really Frankfurter
One of the most
Influential Justice
Of all time I bet taragrove she teaches constitutional law at William and Mary Law School
A very influential scholar at Harvard Law
School before he became adjust
With a close adviser to Franklin Delano Roosevelt
He was extremely smart
Towering figure
But as a person
Justice
Justice Frankfurter
He wasn't necessarily the nicest
Person
I heard that from everyone else
I always call him a Bantam rooster
He was a difficult Krusty figure this short
A little bit of a pouch on
Was one of the most
He was a tough cut
When a when a clerk would come to the u.s. Supreme Court Chambers to deliver a message
In the person of the door
Tried to hand Justice Frankfurter the paper
Frankfurter would inevitably Let It Drop to the ground
So the person had to bend down and
Pick it up
Two handed to him again
Dude that's a
And by the way the voices you heard besides Tara Grover professors Mike seidman Georgetown University
Girlfriend won't School Craig Smith California University of Pennsylvania Supreme Court Clerk
Elenco involuntario hn okay so Frankfurter is on one side of the aisle and his nemesis
Is a gentleman on the other side of the aisle illiberal named William O Douglas
He was Justice Douglas now in the Supreme Court chamber
This is a recording from a 1957 interview with Justice Douglas
Looks very well as faces 10 rubbing his eyes sparkle
Mountain climbing environmentalist
Big and civil liberties
I think this this song coming generation is more aware of the importance of civil liberties and crashed biking
Generation Y unlike Justice Frankfurter
Douglas was a prick
To everybody around him everybody hated
All those same adjective
Applied
Here's how the New York Times described them
Habitual Drinker and uncaring parents Douglas was married four times
Killing on each of his first three wives with her
This is footage from his last marriage to his wife Kathleen
He was 67
She was 23
So yes
Yes that it that is William Douglas
See how these two guys Frankfurter the Bantam rooster Douglas
The prick and
As you can imagine vacature
They just despise
The Frankfurter had this habit of monologuing and while he would go on and on Douglas would just pull out a book right in front of them
Start reading you know he was just opening his the same for Frankfurter I actually found a series of interviews
We're done with Douglas in the early sixties where he basically calls Frankfurter names
Time
Wow
Why they hate each other so much
According to Mike seidman some of that comes
From maybe there
Difference in background Frankfurter was
A Jewish immigrant from Austria
A Douglas was a western
But according to him
Or of their hatred
Actually was ideological reflected
I really important split
Over how powerful the court should be
Quartz just want not to intervene and he believed that many matter should be left up to the political process
And the courts should stay out of those issues
Courts want to intervene to protect for example minority groups Free Speech rights things of that sort
Do you have this personal Feud going you had this
Ideological war that was brewing in the court and into the middle of all of this
Walks Charles Whitaker
You might call him the Swing Vote
Okay this is Alan Cohen Supreme Court
Clerk for justice Whitaker
From 1957
Whitaker grew up in a small town in Kansas
Just called Troy
Antithesis of flashy
This is his granddaughter
It's kind of a one-room schoolhouse overview Little Red Schoolhouse work on the farm but he
He he determined that was not the life for him
Kate says when he was around sixteen he became obsessed with the idea of becoming a lawyer and she says he would actually practice law
To the animals
Can you imagine you know pushing
The plow along in the fields and them lecturing and arguing cases to the cows or to the horses or whatever
I hear that he was lecturing yes
Oh and on the side he was he would hunt he would hunt the squirrels opossum raccoon
I need sell the pelts for a few dollars I think $700 would that money put himself through loss
My understanding is that he simultaneously went to law school and high school
What which is just mind-boggling but yeah apparently he went to the head of the law school in Kansas City and he's like I don't
High school diploma but you need to let me in
The dean just saw how ambitious he was and he was impressed means like Alright you're in
I love this guy
He's like Mr bootstrap
Totaling any how to make a long story short the top lawyer and Alan Cohen says that because he would
Do better than all of his opponents he would outwork them out prepare the great attention to detail
Great
Presents before a jury
And then he becomes a judge for a federal district judge and then an appeals court judge
And in February of 1957
Gets the call so I recall it was in the evening and asked if he could be in Washington
Nginx
Morning this is Kent Whitaker
Charles Whitaker
He should certainly but my best blue suit is at the cleaners tonight
What did he wear
As a matter of fact
My mother or someone else got the cleaners open up at night
In the first allegation
Tending to show data corporation's right of exercise of Free Will at them
This is one of the first time that Whitaker spoke on the bench and he innergex with a question for the attorney and he is Midwestern
What I have
The thing is crazy to me is it
He walked into the highest court in the land in
He didn't even go to college
I think it's important to understand
That he had no formal education real
Another way she never took history
Political science or social science
But do you love the law my father was not an ideologue
He expected
The court to be
An arena in which there were Lively arguments on legal issues
And that's what he enjoyed what
What's really good at
What what are you love
Has Kent Whitaker puts it
His dad was kind of the walking embodiment of that thing that
Chief Justice John Roberts said back in 2005
During his confirmation hearing for chairman I come before the committee with no agenda
He was sort of a blank slate my job to call balls and Strikes
And not the pitch
Or bat
My father was not interested in advancing a cause or a
Siri but frankly that's adjusted
Should be that you are approaching it without a political agenda and that you're deciding it I think
Exactly right
But
In practice
So many of their case
There is no law
To turn to to decide those cases
Ken says that his dad quickly discovered that law that Supreme Court is never clean cut
Cases make it there precisely because the lot isn't clear my name
These are just
Without pressure in those cases
You have must
Care of your ideology
As a
As a starting
And the fact that he didn't have an ideology
That was invulnerable he was definitely getting lobbied
From both sides
Sprinkler on one side Douglas on the other
You were the new kid on the Block and was being pulled by
Each one like
The way the judges bowling for votes within his first three months he found himself in the middle of a death penalty
She was found in her bedroom by fireman
Take a note
Turn that after 4 now
A guy I've been tried for arson and murder and Douglas and liberals wanted to intervene to help them
They feel like you've been treated unfairly by the lower courts
But Frankford when the conservatives thought that the Supreme Court should be
They should honor president according to Justice Douglas
Justice Whittaker was undecided all
Douglas would tell him one thing
That seems right and then just
Something else
I think there was some thought that you
You might
Shein
The guy who talked with him last
You know
He ends up being so undecided on this death penalty case that he forces the court
To delay the vote until the next
In the world series of cases like
Read aloud be fuzzy ideologies would Harden and Whitaker he would be right in the middle
The physical depictions of him in that first year from people who saw him
Describe somebody who was
Restless
Terribly unhappy
I had lost a lot of weight nervous
With agitated most
The time
It was a lot of stress.
Whitaker that in normal Cortana California procedures and butt over the next week
Here's your fences back you find this week
His production increase
Eventually
Third-year his fourth year and part of his V
He wrote as many opinions that is any other judge
He wrote as many dissenting opinions as any other judge
He was one of the nine it was
Fully employed
And he wrote some very important opinions during that
Period of time
Along came a bigger versus
Scar
And it's broken
Hi this is Shireen from
Sunrise Florida Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world more information about Sloan
Www
. Sloane. Org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help this summer I'm hosting a show
And I request for those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
We're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments
Brilliance basically I want to hear about those times when I kid you know did something
It just means you lean back and say wow how did they do that
Maybe it was the moment that our kids you've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the musical score or maybe the kids in math class
Notice their writing music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the small specific moments where a kid does something super smart
Have anything to do with the test
If you have a story please share it with us
Go to radiolab.org brilliance
Record a short audio message for us
Again that's radiolab.org / brilliance
Thank you so much
Avis more perfect I'm Jedi from riding a story from Suzie lechtenberg
But the case that broke to Jessie
Number
123 Charles W Baker at Alcatel appellant versus Josie car
Okay so it's April 19th 1961
The Supreme Court is hearing Baker vs. Carr
Does an individual
Voting rights
11 qualified voters in the state of Tennessee
Not on the surface Baker vs. Carr was about districts and how people are counted in this country and this is why
One of the most basic ways that political power gets assigned in America
That growth should be reflected in the number of Congress people that are representing them but at that time in 10
Has he hadn't changed its legislative districts
Since 1901 which was 60 years earlier will this created big problems
For urban areas like Memphis because in those 60 years
People move to the cities in droves and rural areas were getting smaller and put the Tennessee State Legislature
Had refused to update account and it was still giving more representation to those rural areas
In Tennessee
The figure was 23.
NYU Law Professor Sam is that girl
For people that don't understand how does it actually delete your vote well
This is very
You have one District that has
One person in it
And you have another District
Trick that has 23
The district that has one person gives all the power to the
The district at
Has 23 people
Spread it out over
Ultimate
T3
What are you think of it this way
At that time a person in the city in Tennessee
Had one 23rd as much of a voice in the legislature as a person living in the countryside and
Here's sort of the Insidious underbelly of that
It just so happened that the people living in the countryside or mostly White
And a large percentage of the people living in the city were black
Underlying all of the reapportionment litigation leasing South was
White supremacy
That's Doug Smith
Historian in the author of on democracy's doorstep this is deeply tied to whites
Supremacy in the maintenance of Jim Crow was a method of making sure that rural
A white legislators continue to control the power structure
So you had the situation he says we're a small minority was choking the majority
Suburban areas from any sort of any sorts of funds cities couldn't get the money they needed for Rhodes education Social Services soda
The question at the Supreme Court was and they actually tackle this in two separate things
What should they do about
And here's where you get to the ideological Smackdown liberals on the court like Douglas
Basically agree with the plaintiff when they argue
Liberals are like yeah this is clearly an injustice people in the cities are getting screwed
Their voting rights have been diluted in the basement
But conservatives are like yes people are getting hurt
But we're not going to do anything
We can't Frankfurter
Firstly said we cannot get involved that as bad as it says it was not an issue that the court should get involved in right now
Unique situation
If we end up doing this in Tennessee pretty soon we'll be intervening in California South Carolina
Will be rewriting entire us legislative map
Tennessee
This is the United States not
Yes so
Basically he felt like this would force the courts to get involved in politics
And he really believe that the court should never ever get involved in politics
This is a this is an idea that goes way back to something called
Political question Doctrine
The political question Doctrine says
No federal court can decide this issue at all
Quartz simply had no business
Getting into what were considered to be fundamentally political
Questions and what could be more fun in my life political than the makeup of the legislature it's a philosophy
To feed rooted in the notion that unelected lifetime judges should not be substitute
Shooting their will
For the will of the people's elected representatives
Frankfort like even if you have a terrible political situation if the justices stepped in and overruled the legislature
That would be worse than doing nothing at all because it would be fundamentally undemocratic
I'm he viewed
He view the political question Doctrine
Is a crucial limitation on the Federal Judicial power
And he wasn't alone the courts at follow this guideline for about a hundred and fifty years
And even with the current case in Tennessee federal court that first heard the case
Recognized
The situation actually referred to it as in evil
But this is the decision that this is a political question
Malapportionment is a political question and only the political branches can handle this
They have no power
Anything about
Protecting and enforcing
Voting rights
So
When the lawyer for Tennessee got up there
Play jokes
He didn't try to defend her Tennessee was counting or not counting its people he basically said yeah what we're doing is bad
But it's nobody's job but hours to fix
Is it worth
The legislature of Tennessee
Not
The real Porsha
Or is it
Warriors
Federal District Court
Violate
He basically said if you step in you're going to screw up the balance of power in America the power
I want America comes from we the people not the courts
So this matter should be left up to the people of Tennessee and their elected representatives if the whole problem
Is that you don't have a voice in The Ledges
So then how can you suddenly
Have a voice
In legislature
I mean either way to change it would be SC legislature itself where to give up power and why would they do that
Can of course once elected officials are in
Power
They have a vested interest
And keeping their districts exactly as they are because
Those are the districts that elected them and fundamentally
Electoral Representatives knew that if they redrew the lines and they would be
Voting themselves out of political power
ASCII Charles Professor Duke Law School
Not to do anything
So for the Liberals on the court they felt like this was a fundamental flaw in our democracy that needed to be fixed
And nobody was going to fix it if they didn't fix
Frankfurter he's like if you fix this one you're going to fix that one and that one and that one and that one and where's it going to stop
If you do this
There is no way out the Court's going to get stuck and what he called political Thicket
The political Thicket the court must not enter the political Thicket
Karina Street Last Words the imagery of the thicket is that you know the deer very
Proudly with his new horn
Goes into the
The thicket
Gets entangled
Never get out
Frankfurt
Volume was
Once the courts are in there will be nothing Beyond
Bonded and someday
The courts will be
Forced to declare winners and losers a very high-profile action
Okay so after the oral arguments are over in Baker vs. Carr the justices Head Inn
The conference that's a meeting with just an EIN
Right down the middle and Charles Whitaker
He was a potential Swing Vote was deeply torn
He been leaning frankfurters way
But
Clear constitutional
Right
Finish this for the first argument he asked a number of questions that suggested a great deal of sympathy with
When is the knot
Power
In the course
Constitutional right there's a lot of thought that he might actually come down on the side of
Of the plaintiffs medication I threw a Frankfurter really
Really buganda to rip into him
Right after the first real argument
Drake on
Even 90 minutes speech
Search Oxford
90 +
Straight minutes
Darting around the room pulling books off the shelves
Pulling books off the shelf reading
From prior cases gesticulating wildly
To make his point and the whole time looking directly at Whitaker
There was one account that I heard where Frankfurter went on for 4 hours
4 hours really lecturing Whitaker really really belittling him
Yes it was it was horribly intimidating
At one point one of the justices on the liberal side
Justice Hugo Black
It took Whitaker side was trying to make
Can feel better and black said to Charles Whitaker just remember we're all boys grown tall
We're not the gods who sit on high and dispense Justice
But it's very difficult not to see yourself in that role
Particularly if your vote might be the vote that decides everything
This started weigh heavily on Whitaker's mind
He was disturbed by the by having the weight of Spring Court on his shoulders
According to his family Kate and Ken's my mother tells me that he
At that time was under a lot of
Stress and spoke as though he were dictated spoke his punctuation
Hello Judas, it's very nice to meet you could clearly thinking about everything that he
Might say being recorded
I remember his
Stating that he felt like
All the words that he ordered were being chiseled in stone as a result of Leaky Shed
You don't talk much
So after they heard the case the first time wudaokou couldn't make up his mind
And actually incidentally there is another Justice Justice Stewart
Who was the other Swing Vote in the case
Who also couldn't make up his mind
The court decided to hear the case again in the fall
Just because they needed more time
And over the summer remain deeply divided that he actually
Written memos on both sides of the issue
Doug Smith says Whitaker wrote both and opinion for intervening and Baker vs. Carr and Addison tag in
Intervening in Baker vs. Carr
At the same time as he circulates
60 page memo explaining how this was a political question that should not be decided by the chords
He's God
A fire in his belly
He's not going to let this
Number 6
Charles W Baker at Alice Cullen
Monday
October 9th
It's 10 a.m. and the court is back in session
Lawyer arguing the case against the Tennessee legislature begins to talk
Frankfurter stood quietly for about 5 minutes listening
Without the lights
And then he starts
You gave a minute ago
Of course.
Frankfurter hammers the attorneys with questions
During the course of oral arguments
He speaks approximately 170 * 170 + 70
Charles Whitaker
Have some
For the allocation
Amish legislatures to districts
17 *
Well
After nearly four hours of oral arguments
The justice is recess
And going to conference
Frankfurter needed
Desperate
He had a gun
And he would
Kept asking
Like a
Dog after a bone
Trying to persuade him
And that
Harassing a guy. I have to make a point
It was a nightmare
And I saw the night
How so
Describe it to me well
He was
A nervous wreck and like
Cat on a Hot Tin Roof I found out I don't know if he told me or his wife told me
He was on tranquilizers
Overcome
What he thought was just work-related
Stress will clearly
Something was taking
Hold of him
Who had trouble concentrating
Highway fraud I would characterize
Here's eventual breakdown
It's something of a slow descent
By the early spring after the court had returned from
Winter recess
Whitaker was absent from the
Court
You mean like he just didn't either getting chill for work one day
Apparently so Splurge didn't know where he was
The other justices
Didn't
Know his whereabouts
He just
Appeared
Really in the middle
Of what's going to become one of the
Your Monumental decisions of the 20th century
He disappeared
She had to it
Escape
Where'd you go
Well
He went to really what would be a cabin in the woods
In the middle of Wisconsin
And he called up one of his former law says he's in Kansas City to come up and join him
And according to Craig Smith
He in the sky whose name was Sam Milby
They would just
Set there
On the bank of the lake
In silence
They would sit for hours on end not talking to each other
Just waiting for the justice
Speak
We have no way of knowing what he was thinking at that moment but
I imagine he was just
Sitting there and he was thinking about these two realities that could unfold like
On the one hand
If a court stepped into politics
They can protect people
But on the other hand
President with the set
Would it make the court too powerful
How much case
W bush do to protect the people
Imagines mine went back and forth and back and forth
And when Whitaker decided he really had to get back to work than this
Protege would say to him
No just relax
Did you just take it easy and
Get yourself together before you decide to go back
After 3 weeks
Justice Whittaker returns to DC
Back to worship
For a few days
But can't again his son
We found my father to be
Really in extremis
And debate and end I think I'm borderline suicidal
When you said that he was suicidal what do you mean
There was an instance in which my
Brother found my father going upstairs to get a shotgun
A few days later
Charles Whitaker checks himself into a hospital
There is
Some evidence that it was really Justice Douglas Who convinced Whitaker
Go to the hospital
That's Justice William Douglas again
Hospital
A few weeks later March 29th 1962 the presidential press conference
From the new state department Auditorium
Washington DC
Several announcements to make
It is with extreme regret
That I announce the retirement of associate justices
Supreme Court
Charles Evans Whittaker
Effective April 1st
Justice Whittaker
Remember the Supreme Court for nearly five years
Have the federal judiciary
Beignets
Is retiring at the direction of his position
Reasons of disability
I know that the bench in the bar
Of the entire nation
Join me in commending this to Justice Whitaker
First devoted service to his country
During a critical period and its history
Text I want to take this opportunity to stress again the importance
The tax bill now before the House of Representatives
Wow
Whatever happened with the case with Bakery card
Whitaker didn't vote on Baker vs. Carr
So you could say that this
Case that
Essentially broken
His vote didn't count
Around the time that he was in the hospital they were sort of the liberal coup at the court where Frankfurter lost a couple of other
So in the end the decision actually wasn't very close at all
What was it
It was 6
Brennan wrote the majority opinion and he says that this whole kind of cluster we've been fighting over of how
How States in Tennessee Count Their voters
But this is something the court can and should look at
So another words I decided to
Lower their arms and go into the thicket
Oh yeah they did
And just one or two final questions of what happened to Justice Frankfurter
The thing that I find
Crabs most extraordinary
Is it less than two weeks after decision in Baker versus car came down
Felix Frankfurter was working at his desk at the Supreme Court
And
Frankfurter secretary found him
Sprawled on the floor of his office
From a stroke
He suffered a massive stroke
And the never return to service
And while he was in the hospital solicitor-general Archibald
Cox
Visit a Frankfurter
And Frankfurter
He was in a wheelchair
I could barely speak
But he
Apparently convey John Archibald
Wilcox
That the decision
Baker vs. Carr had essentially caused
Stroke
He felt
So passionate
The court should
Stay out of the
McKay's
Statkey physically
Physically deteriorated
After the court
Gone the other way
After Baker vs. Carr President Kennedy essentially had to Supreme Court vacancies to fill
Now Whitaker seat he filled with a guy who turned out to be a moderate
Frankfurters vacancy that second vacancy
That vacancy
See
That will lead to the appointment of a man named Arthur Goldberg
That is the fifth vote
That
The four liberals
What are regarded as the four liberals that becomes the fifth vote that they need
Really to create what has come to be regarded as the Warren Court Revolution
This is when the Supreme Court basically became an agent for social change
Begins with a 1962 term that's the revolution that is going to change
One man one vote in a political boundaries
Confession the way we think of Criminal Justice
The way we treat 1st Amendment religious and obscenity issues
That's the Warren court that people run
Member
And that's the court that came into existence when Felix Frankfurter left
And so just thinking about that question that that woman asked all the way at the beginning of the story
Could you
Address what I see is the
Increasing politicization
Of the corriere papios is of which I guess was
Yoona voting
OLX Ching Bush to be
President you can
Kind of draw a line from this moment in Baker versus car
All the way to December 9th
Mm
The polls in six new states have just closed and the lead story at this hour is
The state
Florida is to
Close
I think feel transported would have said
See
That's what I told you that's what would happen
Is that eventually you will you will be deciding a
Autism
Which
Presidential candidate
Essentially received the most
Boat
For those who
Felt themselves on the losing side of bush V Gore
This was just
Does frankfurters
This was the moment
Bad Baker
Car head
When I teach this to students
And particularly in the decade.
Ricoh R1
The Descent sent to Ben
Sentiments about this
Still quite Raw
I would say to them well
Is this
Was Frankfurter right
And I remember a student in the
Who said
In class I never thought I would
I would say this
But
Because I hated the outcome and
Bush V Gore I was
So angry
Proceeded
But if
Bush V Gore
The price we have to pay
The courts make
In the overall
System
Work
Somewhat more tolerable
Play properly
It's a price I'm willing
If we totally sign off what
The Douglas Weiser lost track of time so after Baker vs. Carr was decided he went on to be a Supreme Court Justice for
13 more years and to this day he actually holds the record for being the longest-serving justice of all time 30
Frankfurter so Baker vs. Carr was the last case that he ever heard
And he died a few years afterwards recover
After Whitaker retired from the court he moved back to Kansas City with his family and his son said that it took them about
About two years to get better from his nervous breakdown but he did get better and eventually he got a job as counsel
Open General Motors but
He never returned the benching never was a judge again
Okay more perfect produced by me Chatham rod
Susie lechtenberg Tobin low and Kelsey Padgett go Kelsey wheeler Elie mystal David Herman Alex over
Sean rameswaram Katherine Wells Barry Finkel Andy Mills and Michelle Harris
Special thanks to Ian Riley
Archival interviews with Justice William O Douglas come for the Department of rare books and special collections at Princeton University Library
Supreme Court audio is from free law project in collaboration with the league
Information Institute at Cornell
More perfect is funded in part by the William and Flora Hewlett Foundation The Charles Evans Hughes Memorial foundation and the
Joyce Foundation