Hey folks just a quick note this story that you're about to hear
Has in it an interview that contains
Threats of violence might not be appropriate for
Sensitive listeners Young
Are you awake
Listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
Now for some reason
The speakerphone doesn't ever want to go off
Can you guys call me right back and I won't put it on
Okay sorry about that
Hey I'm Jared I'm Robert krulwich this Radiolab and today
Today we have a story about something that
You might not know that you have but you definitely do have an answer to the crazy
Maybe even scary
Secret
Crazy scary secret hello
Power hey sorry
It comes to us from a producer's Tracy hunt
The story for us got started with this woman Laura
I am a freelance internet marketer she's from Colorado and in the mid-90s
Something happened to Laura that hadn't happened to anyone in
Centuries
It's over it's over
When to take a second 1996
The day you got your jury summons that very first one that was the day of jury duty I had to I had totally forgotten about
The jury summons until the day of
And I picked it up
And I read the back of the summons and it said
Something about 6 months in jail if you don't show up
And so I didn't have a ride to the
The courthouse
And so I called the
Court
And ask them if I really had to show up since I didn't have a ride and they're like yeah yeah you have to show up then I said well
I'll have to hitchhike then
And if something happens to me I said to them my blood is on your hands I wanted to make them
I feel guilty about making me show up but that didn't work she said I had to show up anyway that whenever
The point is Lori did get the current in Gilpin County in Colorado and when she got there she walked into the seats
I think there's about 40 jurors in the pool of jurors and Thursday fill up the box with 12
Soldiers and then they
Ask them questions about themselves but were you hoping to get booted off oh yeah I was hoping to get food
Of course
Any any good red-blooded American was hoping to hot crazy in the jury selection I was I was one
The last ones to be selected
So the next day Laura and eleven other jurors
Showed up to hear the case and the case was for this nineteen-year-old girl and she was charged
With possession of methamphetamine
What happened was that she was up in Central City which is a gambling town
And that day she was driving in her van with a boyfriend and eventually the two of them drove this casino or boyfriend jumped out
Out of the van he went to the casino and then she kept driving and then the police pulled her over
They just for whatever reason pull her over pulled over for
But she got out and put her purse on the hood of the car and then
Made a lunging movement towards it
Which they said give them probable cause to search your purse cuz now they're thinking o the table
Answer the police open up her purse and they start kind of rifling through it I wish they found this one ounce of meth m
Amphetamine
And so one of the questions before the jury was
Is this young woman guilty of possession of methamphetamine
Beyond A Reasonable Doubt
So at the end of the trial
Laura and the other eleven jurors got up and went to the
The Jury Room to deliberate
Until we talked about a lot of things one of the things I remember we talked about was whether or not the police were
We're lying about you know her lunging towards her purse and things like that
There is also the fact that she did have this mess
But it was unclear whether it was actually hers or not because according to the girl when her boyfriend got out of the van
Can you put something in her purse she said without her knowledge this girl saying the meth might be his but it's
Definitely not hers
I mean to me that
The whole thing that's
Element number one of the possession charges that they have to knowingly
Is that soap for Laura if she said she didn't know she had it
And
Could be her boyfriends and she's not guilty
It it seemed to her that it was just like
Pretty big hole in the prosecution's
I mean to me I just couldn't get beyond that
It's a law return to the other jurors and I said to him I was like well isn't that enough Reasonable Doubt for you to
A quitter and they were all
Like no she had it in her first she knew it was there it's almost 5 we need to go to Victory and go home
But Laura wouldn't budge
She just couldn't get herself the go along and so
She held out
And that night when she went home
She just kept turning this case
Over and over in her mind
And she started wondering
What's the girl was looking at
As far as
Sentence right but that's not technically what adder
Supposed to do
In this case and generally the judge had told them you know like I'm the one that gets to decide the sentence
You just have to find out whether she's guilty or not guilty
But I was worried about some sentence you know you have is 20 rager
You have somebody's Liberty in your hand
It's a loris at dad on her computer she got online
And she found this criminal statute and to her understanding this girl was looking at 2 to 6 years
Like what that is just feels so out of
Lamp that doesn't feel right also it's a felony charge you know you can't erase that
So the second day of deliberations you know we just went back and forth where the police line yes we think the police are lying
Is that Reasonable Doubt no it's not reasonable.
After all my arguments about Reasonable Doubt we're exhausted
That's one Law return to the other jurors and try this
Completely different tact
She looked it up and she was like look
Even if you think she's guilty we didn't have to convictor for any reason that we could let her go
The even if she broke a lot we can say
We don't agree with the law
You know we we are here
We're here to be the conscience of the community that's what I told them
You don't have to convictor
But wait. Seems like I
And I would imagine some people might be like what are you talking about of course we do we're supposed to just
Say whether she broke the law or not that's what a jury does
Fred
Right well that's where everything broke down
Because as it turns out when I started making this argument
A whole series of events
Set into motion
One of the jurors apparently they wrote a note saying Laura's inherit she's talking about sentences
She's saying that she's only going to quit this girl got sent to the judge
And apparently the judge exploded
And call this all back in and declared a mistrial
Sheriff showed up at my house with a summons for contempt of court
And suddenly Laura Story caught fire
First juror in 400 years that was actually punished for their verdict prosecuted
6 years
Point is when Laura told those other jurors they could essentially ignore the law that they could disregard the facts if they disagree
Read with a lot of she had tiptoed
This very bizarre
Pull up some kind of people see as a trapdoor to an
Anarchy and on other side people see it as like
When is the
Foundational bedrocks of what it means to be in a democracy
It is something called jury nullification
Jury nullification
Actually the first time I heard about jury nullification I Googled it
And the first thing that came up with this YouTube video that was like a little
Explainer thing with an animation
And I think it was like the
First thing is sad on the
Front undercut
Frozen screen of the YouTube video has
You can get arrested for talking about this
Really
And I was like
Oh okay I'm hitting play on that let's go you can get arrested
You're talking about
Get well that ends up being a
Sort of
It also did not
Which is what makes it a loophole
Thank you
Yeah just this way
Anyway as we dug into it we figured you know we are going to need some help
But understanding this thing
So I was thinking that would start with a little bit.
What's your notification is
Yeah
So we call the favorite legal expert
Elie mystal an editor of above the law and the legal editor of more perfect on WNYC
What perfect what is that that sounds amazing what is that it will it will
You know what it's not worth much
Anyway
Elite season 2
Anyway when we were talking to Ellie the first thing that we asked him what do you know what just give us
The pure uncut version
So pure aspect of jury nullification would be
Let's see I am the defendant I am accused of stealing a car
I absolutely stole that car everybody saw
They had me dead to rights all you have to have me on video
My mama said
No Reasonable Doubt
But I stole the car because my kid was sick and I needed to get to the hospital
Take him to the hospital
I had no other option
It's why I smashed the windows to somebody else
Car hot wired it
Put Mike in the back I drove to the hospital
Save to save my save my kids
Now I'm up for child from the
The guy who has the Audi
Rochester
The guy who asked me out
It's like he stole my car
Which is true
Imagery says yeah
Now we're just going to
The jury would nullify that clear
Bat clear illegality
Clear crime that I committed so it's like
Yes he took the car but
The law by the way it's written doesn't
Account for the fact
That in this particular case
That's okay with us
So that's
That that's kind of
Sure
Version
And that's kind of the most
Kind of Happy clappy
It's a very happy version
I could have stolen Justin Bieber's car
I probably couldn't get convicted in a court
For that
The nobody likes him nobody likes him
So they could be saying the laws not nuanced enough they could be saying the punishment is
Off they could be saying
In this case the
Victims are deserved it
Or they could be saying
We disagree with this
Right away
It's something I understand is like
It's so here we have a situation where Laura says she doesn't do with
Descendants
What does she or any of the other jurors have like
A'right
To do this is there is there like something written in the Constitution
It says they can do that no there's nothing in the Constitution that
The direct
Explicitly says
Yes you have the right to completely ignore the law and let off whenever you want to
That's not a constitutional right
Okay
Crying because Ellie says a jury is told to do what they think is
Best if they think their best is nullifying
Aloha
That's also not exactly illegal
Which disc get back to Laura first second is why the court never actually charged
Perfectdry notification
Instead they found her guilty for not answering questions directly during the jury question process
Eventually that conviction was overturned on appeal because
In general the things that are said in a jury room are protected
Their private so it's not
Right it's not a crime
What it is is a power
And so I think of it kind of like
Wolverine
Power
Is Keaton
She can be patched
Deal
Adamantium claws
That's just a
Back of Wolverine's wife
He has the ability to do that
It's his power
Now
Is it alright for him to have claws shooting out of it and no
Absolutely not is it illegal for him to have claws shooting out of
Well
Not really
It's illegal for him to use them in certain ways
Rights to Wolverine comes into your house
And scratches you on the face that's assault we have a law against
Wolverine has the power
To just
Walk around as he is
With these claws in his hands
Built into the nature of his being
Real quick to the people who care about
Superhero Powers we know that Wolverine's Powers apps
United heal
But at least point
Don't hold
Wait a second
The tree like it
Claws
To the jury has this
Claw
Whatever
But these simple point is
That
Jury nullification is as fundamental to juries
As having
Klaus is the Wolverine
That's just
A fact of their existence
But they still get in trouble if they use it
Lorded but then how did we end up in this weird
Place where you can
Do it you don't have the right to do it but you can do it but if you do it
Or even
Talk about it you might get in trouble
That question because it gives me a chance to update Matt are you back there can you queue some like English jaunty
1700s type music
Coming right up
All right now we're in the mood
Fluorite
Explain yeah so I ended up finding this guy Jeffrey Abramson of Law & government the University of Texas at
Johnston told me you don't have to do with the sort of battle over who has the power to decide
What the law is
And he says the opening shots of that battle go all the way back to William Penn trial in 16:7
Any which is really the birth of religious liberty
I guess we can also use some sounds of horses
Cobblestone streets and
Sister Sister
So much better thank you okay so it's 1670 London England we've got a guy William Penn
I'm with a young man he was a Quaker
And one day he walking through the Streets of London hold a prayer meeting and Grace Church meeting Chapel
Welcome to the chapel door
But
Define deadlock by the authorities
And the reason the doors were locked up because there was actually this century-old law on the books it made it a crime to
Essentially to be a Quaker
But what pain does
Hey
That
Okay one both of you two
Pain starts
Calling everybody together in the street and as more people start to gather
Wrong like three or four hundred people show up
Come on come on so it's already seized the occasion to
Arrest him for breach of the Peace
And eventually
And get thrown in jail and he gets a jury trial
This follows that William
Of London now the government became he was pretty much just charging pin for being a Quaker
But the authorities
Thought they could go underneath the table and just
Prosecute him for what was
Common law crime of breach of the Peace
Are you guilty as you stand indicted in matter and form as for said or not guilty
I plead not guilty
Matter and form
The case is pretty open-and-shut I mean
Gathered hundreds of people in the middle of the street according to law and the evidence he is guilty
But
His
Defense is
Show me what law in England makes it a crime
To worship God in my own way
Stop the dream went out to the Jury Room
The jurors come back several times and say we cannot agree
What was their hang up well don't know how inside the heads of those people you can get but it seems like they just
Didn't feel like
Locking him up for that was the right thing to do even though it's technically against the law
And so the judge says to the jurors I am telling you
That is
The evidence shows
The 10 preach
What's wrong
On a public thoroughfare
And he clearly did I have to find him guilty of the crime of breach of the Peace
And then the judge lock them up in the Jury Room
Without food tobacco or rest facilities for a quote
Considerable amount of time
And quote and then finally they come back
Hancock
Quit vim
The judge accepts the acquittal
And then orders that yours too
Jail for perjury with the whole jury in jail I got locked up
Not cool
So that guy end up filing a
An appeal it went to the highest courts in the realm all the way to the king's court in the Chief Justice
Rule that it
Henceforth would be illegal
To prosecute jurors for a not guilty verdict
So this becomes the start of jury nullification
And
I really was was
The birth of
Bubble this
Connected space called The Jury Room
That
Can't
Punish anybody for what they do in the Jury Room
So that notion crosses
The Atlantic Ocean and becomes a part of the American tradition of law so that when the colonies are coming up
They have trial by jury and they have juries and
Smartdeblur writing things about how the jury is the place where the people get to
Decide
What happens when we die
Forecast.
Punish them for what they do and so you get people like
Adams and Jefferson making Grand arguments about the role of the jury
And actually Jeffrey says one of the things that we get from injury is
Freedom of the press
In the 1700's this newspaper guy New York
Supposedly
Libel the king or the crown
Into the jury in that case it was
Pretty clear that you did
But they decide that the law itself is unjust
And boom there you go bring the Preston
This ideas her baked into our nation's beginning of trusting Ordinary People to do the work
Injustice themselves
Ordinary People
White Manna
But then
In the mid 1800
That's hard to change because of two things
One more laws are being written and it just more complex and complicated and it is harder for people understand
Number two
The legal world is becoming way more professional more more people are getting legal training even judges who before didn't have
Necessarily have legal training to become a judge
They're getting legal training
And so it so now judges are seen as the experts in the law
And then what happens is that you seem or just would have take
Bath
The power to decide what the lot is from the jury in the United States Supreme Court
In a decision in 1895
I know
Responsibility for
Deciding
Whether to enforce the law question number
Or what the law
Properly interpreted was
Number two
And from this you get the sort of
Judge's instructions that are given to the jury and we still have this sort of instruction today
Ladies and gentlemen of the jury the case is now upon you
It is your job to find the fact
But it is my job to instruct you on the law
Now it didn't it wasn't exactly that jury nullification bikini legal and more like just the court kind of
Pushed it
Down made it at start of unspoken thing
And over the next hundred years or so
It does I mean certainly there
Times when jurors refused convicted
Famous cases are like during prohibition and then some arguments during the Civil Rights movement in the in the Vietnam War
Or but really
The explicit idea of jury nullification the idea that this is really
A role for the jury
Stays mostly Underground
Until
Claws come out
That's after the break
This is Albert in State College
Sylvania
Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of
Science and technology in the modern world more information about Sloan @www.
Sloan. Org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here I'm a producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
And I request
For those of you who
We spend a lot of time with kids parents
Aunts and uncles teachers we're looking for stories about what we're calling
Tiny moments of brilliance
Basically I want to hear about those times when I kids you know did something
It just means you lean back and say
Well
How do they do that
Maybe it was the moment that I
A kid you've been reading to 4 month started reading back
To you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lesson
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of their musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed are ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the
Epic moments where
Kid does something super smart
It doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story
T-shirt with
Go to radiolab.org
Flash brilliance
Record a short audio message
Again that's radiolab.org
Slash brilliant
Thank you so much
Jad Robert Radiolab
So we're talk about jury nullification the power of juries to perhaps ignore the law
Tracy hunt and Soren wheeler
Reported
And
You guys are saying it was underground for a while
The 92nd
It was a perfect storm of
Two events both of them California
Have the Rodney King trial where you have this video tape we've all seen the pictures of Los Angeles police officers
Beating a man that had just pulled over
In this video you see Rodney King he's on the ground and police are surrounding him and there
Kicking him and beating him with the ponds repeatedly most reasonable of service that there was severe please
Hospitality again
An unarmed black man
For Los Angeles police office
Charged independently the trial was supposed to be held in Los Angeles but
Because of concerns about media exposure
Neighboring Ventura County where the jury is almost all white
And after a month-long trial
And weeks
Jury deliberations
Majority in the Rodney King case has delivered its verdict you can't
An acquittal de equip the officers
Of the four police officers seen on video tape beating with the King a year ago he is guilty of using excessive force table
Woman found not guilty and of course it happened in La after that
5 days of right
Bottles various things going at cars School Bus 60 people were killed
You can see a white plume of smoke and it's not a billion dollars worth of damages
I'm in this area I must say
I'm scared
We all saw what happened
And and it looks very much
Two African Americans in Los Angeles
Betty's white people in Simi Valley California
Race rather than evidence to acquit
I'm 43 years old
I have witnessed this for 43 years of my life
Injustice
I cannot even compare to you the hurt
So according to Jeffrey that was round one and then just three years later
What car you get round to believe that this is the police Simpsons
White Ford Bronco there you see the police car
OJ Simpson in connection with the brutal slaying of his ex-wife Nicole in 25 year old Ron Goldie Reese
Is blood a massive DNA evidence
Up to and inside the house in his bedroom and yet a predominantly black jury
Boxing title action find a defendant or Owens All James Simpson not guilty of a crime of murder
You heard the verdict can we can we ask you reaction so well
How many black people table a white jury to ignore the law in the Rodney King case
Many white people felt a largely black cherry
Done the same thing in acquitting OJ
He's guilty
According to Jeffrey these two cases
Together they sparked a national conversation
About Journal
The day after
The OJ Simpson
Furtick The Wall Street Journal writing the first page story
Essentially
Arguing that in
Inner cities throughout the
Country
Black jurors were
Remarkably
Acquittal
Another words according to the article there was a spike
In acquittals among black jurors in cases where the
Defendant was also black
And the most likely explanation
Is
Kind of jury revolt
No Jeffrey actually argues that this idea of a jury Revolt was
Stated in Part B
Because
He said you can never really know if it's yours actually
Hawaii
But sometimes
Will prosecutors would persuade a jury Beyond A Reasonable Doubt
But the drawers would still
Find immaculate
Georgetown law professor
Paul Butler who was
The prosecutor in DC the time says
That's exactly what
Did that feel wrong
Only because
You know like
Every prosecutor I wanted another notch in my belt
So yeah it took me off but the reason they were doing this is because they didn't want to send another young black
Black men to jail
Which Paul says was mostly what his job was
If you go to Criminal Court in DC you would think that white people
Don't commit crimes
They're just out early absence
From the criminal court
Obviously that's not a reflection of the real world
And over the years day today
Locking up black people it takes a psychic toll
Paul says he started
Ask himself should I go to law school to put black people in prison
And for me
The answer became no
Well now a black law professor is urging black juries to use nullification
In their fight for racial Justice that let me smell only understand
What these African-American troops were doing in DC letting cases of non-violent crimes
20 Dwarfs
Did you let a guilty defendant off isn't that the same as really taking the Law into your own hands
Did absolutely is the same as taking the Law in your own hands
Political protest
Tilia MN
That one sort of seems to grow directly out of the racial
Mix of things that we're going on in both Rodney King and in the OJ case
As this was all bubbling up there is a group called the fully informed yours Association that started actually
In this tiny
Butt hole of a town in Montana
With these like super libertarian
Allowed
Say that
And they started this
Group that was app that was basically advocating for jury nullification writing up pamphlets
Yeah sending out things eventually the internet comes along and attention to jury nullification just can't go through
There's claims that jurors in Atlanta in the mid-1990s started
Quitting sports like bookmaker
People defendants on a regular basis
Even though like in the past those cases it serves her missing a slam dunks and in the post-trial interviews jurors were saying that they
Basalt
The reason was a Sigh No moral difference between betting on sports and playing like the Georgia Lottery
By the time you get medical marijuana initiatives around 1996
All sudden
It's become much more difficult for prosecutors to convince Teresa convicted in marijuana cases
So prosecutors are deciding not even to file
Charges in those cases
It comes up in gun right cases during that time so you have like this
Spasm of Interest
Largely because of these
Two kind of race-related Trials and then suddenly you have
It's kind of
Spreading
Serving all safe places near
Brochure butchered rewrites
And in fact today what you're seeing is this kind of
Rising activism
Around getting the word out about jury nullification
What is happening at courthouses all across the United States in Philadelphia and Florida
Name and who you are what you
What You Do lyrics Easton
A reporter to Denver to talk to this guy
My name is Mark
Teyana Taylor you spell that last name ianni
C e l l i
I am with an activist
For jury nullification
3 days a week old cold very hot rain or shine Mike would show up at the courthouse
And he's in other people
And they would just
Standard steps of the Court
And hand out these
Pamphlet that basically say
Is your right as a juror to vote
Not guilty it's a bad law designed by bad politician
You know you have the right to vote
Conscience to represent the conscious
The community had the right to judge the law
Right that's perfectly legal and that's how you get rid of bad law
None of these people various sorts
Looks like they are very sore
You'll get the kind of guns rights people you get the Libertarians out west of occupy Denver
Like occupiers like Mark and you might get some like a racial Justice people who think they're not too many brown people in jail
Big tents
Is he a prosecutor he's got the LL Bean tote bag
Twin Rivers.
But then the thing is here as we get to the getting in trouble for it guys like Mark we got arrested here
Who handle this
And what's in front of courthouses
They sometimes get arrested
We will distribute the information and they came down
When they got seven of these right here from the fully informed jury Association
And we were handing them out to everybody
I get arrested for 7 class 5 felony is looking at 21 years in prison
Under what grounds
Almost always
Never says no once again
Json is A Canticle cuz obviously
Not until they get usually get arrested for
For jury tampering
But then these cases of go and go get it
Appealed and eventually
I don't think we found a case where this isn't true every single case
The brought the charges against thrown out because
Free speech
We are now in a
1st Amendment
Free speech
War
OK Google can you hear me
This is Julian haikal and he became kind of a jury nullification activist hero of sorts when he was arrested
Today in 2010 at the federal district court hearing
Well I made 9 appearances at this courthouse and was arrested five times and he was about 78 years old
At this point he was just handing out flyers
Yeah yeah you have like a deck
They're like a table set-up or are you not an information
And I just
As I got at bacova I I just
Pass out this one-page flyer people come up to you when they see Jerry information like are there.
More of the runaway
And he said show up at court houses like
Oliver place like a new jersey yet in Pennsylvania and like in Philadelphia and in Florida actually when we talked
He was in Orlando staying with his friend Mark and they were heading down to the local courthouse
The following Monday to urge people to know if I lost it on agree with basically because they see notification is a kind of a check on
On times when the government or a law goes
Interview
Too far we have many cases like this that have shown it
When the slaves when the slaves were escaping from the south and going up north
People were running them up into Canada
And they were told that they had to return them after all the slaves were property
What that were guilty I was theft
When they didn't return these slaves probably the most
Famous
Example of jury nullification cases
Square northern Jersey
Even though they knew someone had harbored a slave and was
For guilty
They would just
Refuse to commit
They don't do it that's how that's actually the most important
Jury nullification case that this country probably ever had
Is a just left us life I just heard about the Canada
Violating the law out now
That's the point of having a jury
In fact Thomas Jefferson made the statement
The only thing that will save this country is the jury
The only thing
Hey by the way if you need to stop and take a drink of water don't
Don't hesitate to stop and cry a little
Anyway let's go
You don't mind if I cry while we talk about this
Just touches me pretty much
I mean what is it
Of course I don't mind if you cry I'm guess I'm curious what
What is it that's hitting you
In that way emotionally
I'm sorry I think about these cases that I just can't believe what's happening this country
I can't believe how corrupt this country has become
And you're seeing that corruption in people being locked away put away for things they shouldn't be put away for it
Web for drugs
Do you know that
We now are the number one prison state in the world we have the highest percentage of prisoners in any country in the world
That's the United States of America
And of course 40% of the people are in there for a drug violation
Why does the government have any right to tell you what you can do with your body
It's the same thing for prostitution
Why should the government be able to tell you whether you can have sex
Or what you can't have sex
Or why you can smoke a cigarette or why you can't smoke a cigarette
Now I understand why the government tells you you can't shoot somebody else
Give me that make sense
But if you want to shoot yourself
Guess you're busy
Anyway and I'll tell you something
We're going to the car it's even though
To pass out this literature on Monday in Orlando that's why I'm down here
And
Then contact with a judge and he's been in contact with me yet he's informed me that if I show up I'll be arrested
What application are they probably have 50 or a hundred people
Omaha
I hope along with me
Do you think I mean is that what you're doing at the courthouse are you going to be passing out the the jury pamphlet
That's exactly right
And the
Judge has promised us that will be arrested
He said he's asking all my people to come with guns and shoot the cops to come after
You're not serious about that are you
I am serious
Why me too baby. That would be the thing that you just said you understand why the government
Stop someone for Jimmy.
Crosses a line. Comes a time when you got to stop
And I think that time as much as December 5th
It's got to be ended
You got to start killing the
The police and the guards and hopefully the judges
Until they learn how to behave
That's not Justice either
The point is we've tried now for years
It doesn't seem to sink into them that is their job
To uphold a lot
Not to keep throwing people in prison
470 years I've been doing this
And this is the first time it ever occurred to me
That I would ever have to do such a thing
But
I can't help it
I have a hard time to reason why I should be arrested and taken away
After going to try and do it
I want them killed
But you realize couple
I have a hard time believing that you believe that that
Desserts
Killing a quart
Clarku
Has a family
They've been warned that I've sent them the letter I told him anybody that comes within 15 ft to me that's an officer of the Court
Where are the party of the Court
That there.
Be removed one way or the other
I've come to the conclusion that it has to be ended
Well I think that if you're in a position that ended on December 5th
I think that if you're in a
Position of
Considering doing what you've just said you were considering doing
That that's that this to do anything it's only if they do so
Well
Okay no matter what we have to do it's not going to happen again
Julian I'm going to interrupt you there in just say you know I think
I think we're probably best off just ending the conversation
Letting our microphone person go home and letting me in
It's not only my opinion.
My attention
Yeah we hear you we got it
Okay thank you very much for having me
Okay thank you
Bye-bye
Holy
Do you have to take stickers number
What happened
After that interview
Are the talented and
Esso after we hung up
We thought we had an obligation to
Call law enforcement down there because he
It sounded very much like he was making a direct threat with a time and a place
Until that Monday
He and his friend Mark
Did show up neither of them are armed
Need a hammer Market
Been wanting to show
No it was just that nobody else showed up
And
The police say that
Somebody who works at the court
And she told him that he had to leave that he was trespassing
He refused to leave
A police officer didn't also came
He was
Shouting things about
Shooting police officers at one point apparently he attempted to hit
But the court worker
But yeah
She didn't and
He was charged with threatening public workers
Assault
And
Trespassing
So what happened
So the charge for
Threatening public workers
That was
Drop the prosecutors drop that charge
But he is still facing two misdemeanor charges of assault and trespassing
Did
It when you're sitting there in that interview did that change
In any way you are
Feelings
One way or the other about
Jury nullification
Cuz I kind of feel like it did for me little bit
My answer be really short
No
Okay
Wino
I think he's just sort of
Sounds like a
Angry frustrated
Person
He's angry about
People not letting him
Talk about what he wants to talk about in front of a courthouse
I guess not I mean I did hear
When I was talking to him
Lemon party
Because I was I've been thinking about jury nullification
What started the most heroic
Term just like this
Chance to
Stand up against an unjust law
This conversation just made me realize they can also it also like
Can I guess
Posted up with this really
Deeply anti-government
Idea
You know like you talk to these people and you here
Arguments that sound like Burn It Down
That's the end of my problem
Burn it down instinct
That's my would always serve at a distance
It felt this much much
Closer
Yeah that's kind of my head when I hear that tape
That's the strain and that's the kind of thinking that you bump into a lot
That I find
One of the most frightening things
I find it more frightening than almost any
What but what
That idea that like we the people should should be should be triumphant over everything
Like that if I find that to be a really scary
Ideas pops up I think like Tracy has a checks and balance kind of thing like of his system
We have a legislative branch passes laws so yeah the laws are
What are you looking to see you tour
Or circumstance
Change
Are you find out a consequence of the law if you know people in One race are constantly going to jail during race on it or getting electrocuted
And then you get these
You get these ordinary people walking into these participation points and you know what
Doesn't feel right
It's just wrong
And that's like
If you don't have that then the legislators don't get that little creek
In their little bubble
Totally hear you I mean I've never advocate for going along with a bad law
I think you are
Yeah right with that loss
But there's something
Potentially corrosive about saying to a person
You can judge
Just negate the law
Think about all them times when white juries in the South refused
To convict
People of
Horrible thing
You know it
It's like that
I mean that's that's absolutely jury nullification and that's like that is that is the history of life
Like post-reconstruction
South you know
Yeah but you can make those same arguments on the other side
Think about what yours did during the Civil Rights Movement
This is Supreme Court Justice Sonia Sotomayor speaking at NYU in
10 mm
If it weren't for jury nullification
We would have many civil rights
Individuals who would be convicted felons or otherwise
Four things that today we think
Are protected by
The First Amendment
There is a place
I think
Forgery notification finding the balance of that
And the role that a judge should or should not play
Our forefathers did not believe
The tree is necessarily always got it right
But it was I think what they believe is that
The jury getting wrong
Was better than the Crown getting it
It goes at some fundamental level 2
How we want as a people to be governor
Do we want to be governed by experts we want to be governed by each other
What power do we want
Each of us to have over the other one
This is what this question really comes down
This is once again I'll install legal editor at the WIC show more
The older I get the more comfortable I become with the idea
Of
An unelected
White man
Sitting in judicial robes
Deciding
As opposed to
12 random
Jerk-off from the
And I say that knowing full well that that is a horribly elitist
Terrible for that reason
Listen to the
We have it so puts hand in concentrate power in
Mostly white hands
It cost to get into the system
When
We're saying that one of the only benefits of jury nullification
Is to be a check on the side
If you look at it only from the perspective
Then
Jury nullification
Seems like
A great way to protest
But I'm kind of I've I've started to look at things more From perspective
Which victims are getting Justice in which victims are
I'm not
What I see is
Juries nullifying
Cases
When the victim is of color
Or when the victim is a woman
I try bringing rape case
Try bringing a date rape
Try it
It's really hard
And what reasons why sweetheart is the jury
Is the jury sitting there is talk about
She was asking for it talk about what was she wearing talk about
How why was he out that late any damn way right
Jury
Doing that to the woman as much as any as any other
Part of the system
So when I think about it from the perspective of the victim
And how is
What are the Avenues of Justice
For the Vic
If you're a person of color if you're a minority if you're an other
I feel like the jury makes it very hard for you as the victim to get
I feel better about the judge not
Hearing if the people that you shot happened to be white or blue
A jury cares
If you can't connect the cop when you know we did it when you saw him doing you can't convict
The cop who shot Walter Scott you can't convict
Can't even indict the cop
Who choked Eric Garner to death in broad daylight
That
Tatsumi
Requires a much more dress
Stick wreath
That's how we do things in this
Anthony the
First people to go
Have to be these
Gdb
I find that really persuade
I don't
And a nice
You know maybe that's because I served on a bunch of juries I've been on them
6 now and
Time and again been amazed at one time I was in a murder case
Some men have been accused of stabbing a woman
22 * she died on the staircase
And
The four women in any New York they just picked a person who speaks first becomes the
The four the four person
She came
And she sat down to look
How many of you noticed like the
Defendant's lawyer was asleep a lot of
Every hand when I seen this
Here's what I want you to do
Let's
Let's go back over everything that we know
Essentially retry the case
We we we actually
We went we went
Together to every bit of it looking for some damned out somewhere
We staged the stabbing we went back over the distances where the pack with the guy have gotten from here to there and data
I'm out of time I live in the neighborhood I don't think you can maybe you can maybe can't
We basically
Did the job of the court all over again ourselves and when we were done
So Calif
Vote now
And when it became clear to the four women that we were going to connect
Cuz she was counting the votes in
And finally the 12th vote
To convey
She
Just shorter than her
Her chair so
When she got off at your sexy
What's smaller than when you're sitting right
She asked us all the hold hands
We just spent five days we've been sequestered in a hole
Hotel
Each of us have
Policeman guarding us because we was
Violence
So we all standing on TV she has to hold hands and then she looks up at the
Ceiling
It's one of those ordinary rooms
And she's addresses
The
Cu
One who's killed
And she says
She says we have spent the last few days
Trying to do something that is just
And we know you were there you died
His hands or didn't
We decided that you did
And we hope
And we pray
Physicist
It works
When you are getting just
She said God bless
Bless America
That's amazing
Even though I think you're you're expressing that kind of faith in democracy that it's
I think it's in shorts
Supply right now
I know
Big thanks to producers Soren wheeler and Tracy I know we should say a couple things to first fall of Jeffrey Abramson
His book is called we the jury
And also Judge Fred B Rogers
Colorado Nancy murder law professor at chicago-kent college of law professor of law
Cornell Law School, Hannaford the national Center for state courts
And Robert Lewis
WNYC Newsroom for helping me out with some public records.
And one more quick note
Lord kreho the woman
In the beginning of the story the juror who got punished
She actually passed away
Earlier this year and we just want to say what a pleasure it was
Talk to her and Hell
Lucky we feel they've been able to tell her story
History of produced by Matt kielty and Tracy hunt
Dumb jeroboam run
Acrylic
Thanks for listening
It says Emily Crockett calling from Washington DC
Radiolab is produced by Jad appenrod
Dylan Keith is our director of sound design Soren wheeler is senior editor
Jimmy York is our senior producer our staff includes Simon Adler David Gable Tracy hunt Matt kielty robber
McCraw which anemic Yuan lots of Nasir
What's up with Donald Ariane wack
And Molly Webb
With help from Valentina Bonine
Agar Vitaly
Katie Wang and Katie Ferguson
Are fact-checkers Michelle Harris