Are you weightless
Radio WNYC
Everybody Chad here this is Radiolab
Happy holidays
This is the first of two releases we're going to drop this week
Both come from the same dude
The irrepressible life of Nasser
Lots of has been working with Radiolab for about 9 years
First as a contributor and then we brought him on staff full-time
And he has
Told you stories about
The racial barriers in professional ice skating badminton
We brought you the three-part border trilogy
Story about
Nuclear chain of command
Working on something really cool for 2019 which
Bring you soon
Get rid of to La tips for you
For you
This week couple days were going to actually send you a conversation that lots of had
About how he finds the weird
Peculiar
Stories that he
Seems to always find
He has a really interesting set of techniques
There he goes
Throughout
You at this article about it went sort of viral so we're going to bring you a conversation
Our he goes through some of that stuff
Abba today
I thought play the very first story lot of did for us
This goes back aways
The time he was a grad student at Harvard
He written us an email saying hey are you guys into Old robots
Like robots that are few hundred years old
And then he had a whole list of them
Like for example picking up
The story
Heard
Rumors whispered by Soren mostly about a pooping duck
Ippudo to the pooping duck is really famous
The duck was really eating and pooping but they had like a store of like
Pre pre poops
I don't know what it was looks like duck poop maybe and you would see this robot duck and then watch it actually poop
She sort of this in this out and they believe that people thought this was this was a pooping duck
And we talked about a bunch of these ancient robots it kind of funny
About one in particular
It was
Actually was
Hannah Honda
It's not poop at all
So the year is
450 years
Not so long after Columbus
Ferdinand and Isabella of Denton has a new king of Spain
Phillip Phillips
The seventeen-year-old
Crown Prince
His name is Don Carlos
One day he's in the Royal lodgings
I was walking down a flight of stairs
Trips
He falls
Bashes head
Against a door near the bottom of the sea
Is the Crown Prince Hussein Crown Prince of
So this is a national Calamity The Heir Apparent
Doesn't look like it such a bad injury still conscious
But then his head starts to
Swell to this kind of crazy size
He becomes delirious and fever issues struck blind
And so at this point the the king comes
Tribe is King Philip
Second so he is at this time he's the most
Powerful man in the world
Right so you basically control
The Mall of the Americas he controls much of Europe the Philippines is named after him he was tight with the
Hope that this time the Pope in the king were kind of like
You know
BFF to the Holt Spanish Court
I'm across the country people are
Seeing this reading this as a kind of sign that
The gods very angry
Until they're there fasting they're doing this
Prayer possessions things like
According a lot if the king
Calls all the best doctors near me
Come
To Spain to help his son and these doctors are trying everything they are drilling a hole in skull
To relieve the pressure to relieve the pressure they are
Leaving him and blistering him and they are purging him to the extent that he has like
20 bowel movements within just like a certain few hours
They're like
Smearing all over the wound there they're smearing like turpentine and honey and for Don Carlos
Even after all of this
They look at each other they look at him and it's kind of like
This is
He's going to die
So he's dying
He's basically on his
So at this point getting a lot
Peking
Goes to the Sun
Legend goes between meals
Beside
What is Sun son's death bed
And it makes a pack
God
The Pact is if you help me if you heal my son if you do this miracle for me
I'll do a miracle for you
Palace Pets
Quite
Heuristic
Of a human being to say to God the most powerful men in the world
World is he is a God among men really yeah this is this is what he says okay
All of a sudden
His son
Just
Get better
Within a week he can see again
Within a month
Mississippi didn't fall at all
He just pops right back up yeah
I'm King Philip must have felt
Oh my God this is
Is that means my God probably exactly what you.
When is sun
Can finally speak he says to him
Dad
And the weirdest thing happened when I was out
I had this dream that's a great story
This is Elizabeth King artist and professor in the sculpture department at Virginia Commonwealth
University
She's actually the one that lot of fun the story there are documents of Don Carlo next
Morning
Saying that had a dream
This vision
Dead of the figure in a in a Franciscan habit
Knows this marvelous smoke
Entered his room
Approach
His Deathbed
Holding a cross
And basically told him
You're going to be fine and that's quite well documented
Apparently there was a witness in the room in the sitcom with an at night
Talking to a ghost hoodie mumbling things
In his delirium
So Don Carlos has a
Stream
Suddenly he's fine
In the natural question people are asking is
Who is Mark yeah yeah music just a generic manga or is it somebody specific sum
Messenger from God and from his description
Habit piercing eyes even if kind of crosses using everybody in town
The king everyone was like
Oh yeah we know exactly
Can only really big one guy at a local Friar who died a hundred years before
Name.
Diego de Alcala Diego de Alcala
Who's he he is
At a local holy figure
Corpse was associated with a number of documented miracles
He's like the sky was so holy in this town is a bit of trivia ever
To San Diego
California is in the Padres
Was it the same guy he was the patron saint of the people who founded San Diego
Still holy in this town the people believe his corpse his 100-year dead corpse
Had
Healing powers
Shenzhen people
They're different stories but some people say that even they are these
But unbeknownst to Don Carlos
That night that he had the dream the priesthood and the King himself According to some stories went and they got
Corpse
Out of the church
Out of the crypt
They carried it through the streets they brought it to the bedroom name
Snuck it in bed
With John Carlos
Instagram in bed with his bones
There's different report if there's a picture of him in this Engraving
Youku
You probably can't see it but
Look at this picture right here
She had a a copy of 1/16 roughly a 16th century woodcut
Show me the scene where you could kind of see
I'll wait till the two men in bed together
One guy who's alive barely and another guy's been dead a hundred years
Caught in the middle. Philip II
Who has asked God for miracle God came through
Do the smog
Now fill the second is like
I got to deliver King Philip II always got a miracle
That Miracle after the break
Hey this is Brian in Red Bluff California
Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world
Information about Sloan at www.slha.org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
This summer
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
About what we're calling tiny moments of Brilliance basically I want to hear about those times when a kid
So did something
It just means you lean back and say wow how did they do that maybe it was the moment that a kid
Did you been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons and you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed are ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the specific moments where a kid does something super smart
It doesn't have anything to do with a test if you have a story
T-shirt with us
Go to radiolab.org brilliance
Record a short audio message for us
And that's radiolab.org brilliance
Thank you so much
I'm Jedi boom Rod this is Radiolab let's return outdoor story from lots of Nasser where we left off
It is 1562 in
King Philip is on the hook
He knows he owes God a miracle
Acutely aware of this
Really
Renowned
Clockmaker
Yep names of juanelo turriano
A huge bear
A big box of a man described as always being filthy and blustery
And not a lot of fun to be around
Butter great great clockmaker
Certainly among the best
In Spain
So the King goes to the sky
And he says like I want you to make
A mechanical version
I'm Diego.
What a mechanical version of this 100-year dead
Holy priest
Like a mechanical mod
A robotic Padre
Yeah which
And this I did not
Expect
Still exists now the most bodies in the Smithsonian perfect working order no way
The first time I saw this figure
I was
Drawn to it and then repel
That's Carlene Stephens she is a curator at the Smithsonian in DC about a week after a lot of nice
I spoke
We ended up in DC meeting with her and she showed us
The Monk
Who lives in a little glass case
What we have here
Is an otamatone
Over foreign
Is this the first robot that we know of
Ancient Greek
Things that
Could be considered
Robot
Okay back to our story 450 some odd years ago
Clockmaker
What's his name of Toriano he goes into his shop and he does whatever he does next one gear to another to another
Hours weeks months
No idea how long it takes and I don't think anybody does City emerges one day
Into the bright sunshine
Waze
A robotic Padre
Yeah it's a 15 inch high
Figure
Made of wood and iron has dinosaur tablet has the sandals has the rosary has
And poking out of the top of the Habit is a little
Mall
Hairless
Head
Sharp nose
Like a like
A razor and the rather ferocious
I
Like Intense or like that
Doing business like
Unfocused
Like maybe I'm only 15 in tall but I am focused on something much bigger than you you human
So did you like
Turn it on or push something
And why would I get on a train and go for 3 hours just
Usher Yeah
Okay do it
So Carling takes us out to the hall can we sit down on the floor
Skip slatoff
A little brass key
He sticks it into the secret slot in the months
Side
Counterclockwise you would tend to want to do it
And lots of
Wines of the month
Turning it
Counterclockwise and it's
Surprisingly
I'm so if you sort of wind out this receipt
Spring
Alright I'm going
I'm going put it on the ground
Let him go walk very slowly
One foot after the other coming out from under the casa can factors actually little wheels under there
Coming out
It is turning from right to left
The eyes are rolling in the head the mouth is opening and closing if it's heard of muttering
Prayer
The arms are in motion
One arm is Raising and lowering cost
The other arm is beating the chat
A symbolic gesture to a Catholic
It called the Maricopa after three or four steps
The arm holding a cross though something new
It moves to different new directions to bring the cross to the mouth
And the figure
Kisses across
Oddly mesmerizing
The next thing is doing is it at
Learning
And moving in a different direction and then walking its paces and kissing across
As we watched it it turn once then twice then three times
4 * let it go back to where it started imagining tables the number of people sitting around
Probably it's going to start up
At one point or another head for you
And then turn away and head for someone else and turn away
Why would the king of
Spain
How who could have you know
I will build a church
Taking a crusade to Jerusalem done something new because of anything why
Commemorate his son's Revival by making a little
Automatic.
What was that for
Yeah lots of what was he thinking it's a good quote That's The $64,000 Question 2 grade question
The truth is there's really no way to know for sure
They got to rely on the vacuum
And it's not a whole lot of that in this case one interpretation
Certainly could be that
Yeah the king had this amazing miraculous
Thing happened to his son and now we had a way of sharing that
With his subjects
He's got this device worth it's a it's an illusion like the Machinery of it is completely him there's no visible
One of the craziest
Sports that it's all sort of hidden underneath the the robes at when he put it down on a table or in a
Courtyard
People have seen it move on its own
It would have been amazed
As we were
And you could have said look here is the miracle
Look what God did
For a country God like Spaniards what God did for Spain
Which would have been a useful thing for a king to Beyonce right
That's that's one
The other is it just on a more utilitarian level
This was a machine
That was built to pray and this was a period when you could buy
Prayer repetition so if you had the money you could get someone to pray for you
While you go do something else
Are those over here when you're covered you're covered
If you think about it from Philips perspective he needs to say thank you to God
And he had this thing that if you wound up
Was an automated thank you machine
Thank you thank you thank you thank you thank you thank you thank you or could be
I love you I love you I love you and I'm sorry I'm sorry I'm sorry
Please please please please
But if you need
But if you think about it more expensively
Salata
What did it mean at that time to be a Catholic
What it really mean
What a nice robot
With maybe the best Catholic you could ever hope to be counted his prayer was was
Was quite specific
In the sense that if you say the right things and and do the right actions
In the right order in the right time and in the right place
That's
Prayer that's when God notices about method
It's about method it's about
Maybe this monkey says was like method embodied that's a good one
I mean why not
It is in fact
Perfect
It repeats itself over and over and over
Replicates the idea
Is a little a little teaching object
Where is how you do it
This is the perfect prayer
Perfect
Price of doing it the perfect way every time and I because I'm I'm just in a lowly imperfect
Human
I'm not I can only aspire to this
Perfect piety
Are you making this up or do you think this might the month might have actually been seen this way, true I don't think I feel crazy
Especially if you think about what was happening
At that moment mrs. counter-reformation Spain right not so long after Luther eunos nailing Theses on
Has big debate raging about how actually do you get closer to God you have the kind of protest
With Luther were saying it's not about you know works it's not about saying something this many times it's about whether you feel
And then you have the Catholic argument which is to say
You do these rituals
Because these are the ritual
I'm using the way you get this is the way to get close to God
How's the way to pray
You pray like this thing
Just like this thing
If your Catholic can
Gods of Catholic
I hope he is
If you're Philip II
You look at the sky
And you say God
You and me or Square
There it is early lots of Nasser
Thanks to him
And you guys for listening information 2018
Year that as tumultuous as it was
Still contains a lot to be grateful for
And listen we're raising money to produce Radiolab
2019 CBR most ambitious year
We have a ton of new things planned new series that we're going to be bringing you but we need help getting them funded
So if you did Radiolab if you want more of it
Go to radiolab.org click that donate button
4 text the word Radiolab no space
270 101
At the word Radiolab 70101 thank you
I can't do this without you just a couple days we're going to send you another latte
Situation
Conversation that he and
Lisa Rachel Cusick hat
But how lots of find stories
What's the techniques that I think we can all
Use in our lives even if you're not doing the thing that we're doing
But you just kind of want to have more newness more interesting this in your life
That's coming up soon
Until then
I'm Jad abumrad
Thanks
Transporting show
By the time I'm calling from Seattle Washington
Direct
Director
Staffing address
Bethel happy
Tracy hunt
PennyMac
Molly Webster withheld from
Cast Lazlo
Are fact checker
Yzma