Are you awake
Northern listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
Good
Is your mic on
I'm getting
Nervous
Maybe I should get my EpiPen
Allergic
To radio greatness
That I know of iPhones been really exposed to that yet anyway let's go
Rio Roma
Okay
I'm Robert krulwich this is Radio 11 today we're going to begin with a conversation between Dan pashman okay
Host of the podcast hear WNYC called the spork
Speck food
AnimeBroMii
A digital producer here at the station who likes food and the conversation they had
It was about something that happened to Amy would she never expected certainly didn't want and yet it could happen to any of us
At any
So years ago for any this happened to you
Just tell me what was your relationship
With meat
My relationship with meat
Yeah
You know how when you're little and your mom is like
You can have any special dinner for your birthday my dinner was
Meatballs
And she was like
Except meatballs are so hard to make soy sauce
What's pot roast
And then
Peter Levine on Peter Luger Brooklyn
I used to go there quite often and I live there and I have a Peter Luger credit card
So hard to get
You know I don't I don't know how they give them out but nobody seems to have one I don't think they give them out anymore but I mean
I was very into I was living in Williamsburg
And
Adjust
An open at like 1 everyday
We could just walk in at 1 that had an amazing bar there's no tablecloths on the table these old German Waiters
Play bring out your porterhouse for 3 they put a little plate upside down and then put the big platter on top of suits
Tell that in all the juice runs to the end
And then they like have the special double spoon thing that they somehow like scoop
Juice on TV
Steak and
So good
And also like
Smell of burning fat from hamburger
Learning logs
Oh my God I love hot dogs so much
When you bite into them and they're like
Snap
End
Like having a Weenie Roast
Out in the open air is just stats like that
Anyway I
I was always
Very intimate
What changed
Oh my God it was terrible it was what happened was
I was having this beautiful it was Springtime I was having a beautiful leg of lamb with some neighbors and
We might put it on the grill and
It was just a delicious beautiful dinner and I had
Serve with add some ramps that I foraged in my moms
Yard by the way is just a wild onion
And so
So we had this delicious meal and then you know I went home and was going to sleep at like
Midnight Life
A few hours later
And I just
Felt weird I was like
Something's wrong I feel like really
Anxiously
Like something's wrong with me
I went to the bathroom and I like look in the mirror and my face was like all weird looking and I was like
I kept the laying down be like I'll just sleep it off whatever it is but everytime I lay down I feel like I was going to faint so I was like
Prop myself up and I was
7 terrible like
Stomach cramps just like a weird feeling of
Impending doom you know but just like anybody
Just getting this site
Sleep that's a path I like Splash a little water on my face
I mean tell him everything that's what I thought like
Maybe a
Now
Tiny snail was on one of the ramps
That I ate
And it was like poisoning me somehow
You know snails I mean
They probably put
Poisonous
So
I called my friends in the morning I was like hey how you guys doing how was dinner
They were like us
So great
Like really so great nothing weird
And they were like so lovely thank you so much and again Barbara
I was like wow I really had a rough night
And but I didn't think anything up and then I went on with my life you know just like whatever
And then about a week or two later I made
Some
Cheeseburger
And I
Apus cheeseburger
And that was watching
Goodbye mr. chips
Really tear-jerking movie and a good book tattoo
About a couple hours after I ate I was like started to feel really weird again I was like feeling like I was like
Stand up I was like I think I'm going to faint I feel really light-headed I can't catch my breath I feel like
Really woozy but if any time I lay down I really felt like I was going to say it so I was like trying to say
Sitting up right now so I can
I got this is very similar I've ran into the bathroom and I was like looking in the mirror and Loans all that hives all over me
My stomach and
Then they started coming out of my hands and I was like oh my God something's happening
And at one point I did get up and unlock my door because I did feel like
I have passed out
Con ambulance and then I could be able to get in so I mean I was
A little bit
Ephrata.
And when I woke up in the morning the first thing I did was Google
Sudden meat allergy
Sounds like this seems like an allergy and the only thing that was a
The same was me
And I'm going through like the second thing that came up was this article that was like
Florida man
Pasta and meat allergy I was like oh my God I think it's a possible I could have this and so I made an appointment with my doctor
Write an article and like I had to be this person but I can do it
Had the article my pocket
You know the person who goes there doctor was something I found on the internet so I brought the
The article
It was in my pocket and Mike
I got to the whole like check up
I was checking out went when I was paying the receptionist I pulled it out and gave it to the receptionist
And I was like
Could you kisses to the doctor
So
That was
The best I could do and then I did
Call my doctor and had a conversation with him on the phone asking him if I could
Tessa news like now there's no such thing as a meat allergy Baba
Some people think allergies are just like
In your head
This is science writer Peter Smith we got in touch with him after we heard Amy story
Because Peter is an investigator many things including
Strange allergy
And people are like
Mushrooms hurt them or they think WiFi hurts them
When I got into the studio and we talkin about Amy story
You said
All right
Exactly
Who you need to
Yeah High
Thomas platts-mills
Genesis Thomas
Plattsmouth that's right
How are you I'm very well
Doctor platts-mills is down at the University of Virginia in Charlottesville he's a professor and he
Allergy clinic with constantly shifting through stories which not only you don't believe
But I actually nonsense
And he told us in the last
10 years or so
So he started hearing lots of stories
Just liking
Somebody shows up at the office convinced that they're allergic
All of a sudden for no apparent
To read me the first time I heard it
Was probably as early as 2000
And every single time he heard
You would tell the patient
Exactly what they mean
I told her no no way
No no no it's not possible
Right
So what was wrong with these complaints
Orthodox Medical
Oh everything I don't
Don't become allergic to something they've eaten for
40 years
Out of the blue and suddenly not read me this page
I think you must be making this up
Because I can
I don't I don't use language like that
I said I say that bad that I was I was trying to give you your energy
So you don't want to know what
Doctors are thinking in the invoices and are you often think in the middle of interview is it possible but he's gay
Got you know some
Goslee disease
When is the when he hear a story like Amy's
He just didn't believe
But then
Everything change
Thanks
This new cancer drug called cetuximab
In New York
Today Martha Stewart was in
Indicted on Criminal
This is the very drug that got Martha
Stuart in all that trouble for insider trading
Remember that I went to jail for 6 months
Anyway very promising
Exciting new drug
But then
Doctors were giving people this injection
And
And just like end up on the floor of the doctor's office
In shock
Yeah that would be an anaphylactic shock
Their hearts would start beating faster that get shorter
Breath and get stomach cramps
Their immune system would start to overreact to something new and alien
Came in with the drug
Basically a classic
Allergic
So
Dentistry lands on Thomas platts-mills desk
Yes so we were honest to look at cetuximab to see if they could figure out what was causing it
And it has two groups of blood
A control sample and then people that have this allergy
Any quick easy rodian on a particular molecule
It was part of the drug
This sugar
Galactose Alpha 1 3 galactose
Alpha gal Alpha gal
As in a
Particularly great lady
Better than the beta or gamma gamma alpha male to female didn't quite have a ring to it
Anyway
It seemed like alpha-gal was the Copa
Yeah and if you told me four years earlier
That there's a whole lot of people out there who are allergic
To this sugar
I'd have thought you would
Smoking
You know vaping again because not only does this sugar alpha-gal show up in the cancer drug
This is where you get back to Amy
It also shows up in the blood of mammals
All non-primate mammals
So every time you eat lamb or beef goat
Camel even try
4pics kidneys
You're also eating alpha-gal
Some reading this article and it says like
This thing called Alpha the lactase are alpha-gal or what
Don't make no sense that someone like Amy who been eating meat all her life
Allergic
I just was like this was so stupid also
It's getting to be BBQ season I usually have like
Couple of barbecue soraida
Just do a whole
Parkplatz
And the brisket and likes hang out all day doing it and I was
Chuck Berry wanted to do that
And I was like
Not eat meat and not even know so I was like forget it my doctor will test me I'm going to
That's myself
So I was like going to be very careful I got a thing of Benadryl
And I was like I'm not going to do it alone I'll do it with my mom
I went up to my mom's and she's like really into food too so she was
Exciting I got to porterhouse steaks and salad
Explain to her what you adjusting yeah I did cuz I had talked a little bit about it with her
So
Fire up the grill do the porterhouse I even think I'd like Instagram that has a joke like hahaha
This might be the last time you hear from me but
So
You know we're having a nice summer day just me and my mom having our stake I only ate like a couple bites cuz I
Slightly nervous and
I was like sitting in the grass with my dog and reading a book and trying to think like do I feel normal
Try it folks
Hard
To figure out yourself
Do I feel normal
Does this
Am I breathing
Stomach hurts something wrong and I was like after why I was like
I feel
Pretty good
And the neighbor came over and was like chatting with us and
It was in the middle of that conversation where I was like
Kind of
Can I have to go to bathroom but maybe I just have to go the bathroom so I went to the bathroom while sitting there I was like
Got something feels
And then I was like
I definitely
This is not right something's wrong and I went in
To get the Benadryl and I took two Benadryl and I won my bad and
And the guest room at my mom's house like sitting on there and I was like
Be alright
Maybe I just take a deep breath I'll just stand up
Maybe I just put my hands over my head like this
Oh that does feel slightly better I think I think we should go to the hospital and I
Went out
Side eyes like Mom
I think you have to drive me to the hospital
Like talking to her neighbor like what oh my God how did it work
Let me go change my clothes
Change my clothes like Mom you know she's not wearing the hospital level clothes
So am I okay hurry up Mom Mom are you ready mom and then I was like
Wash U change your clothes I suddenly was like oh my God got my wallet out of my cell phone and I flex through it towards my mom
Bedroom door
And I was like my insurance card to call an ambulance and I just like hit the floor
Eventually the ambulance arrives and
I got stabilized I was strapped to the thing I was in the emergency room like they were
Shooting Me Fallout I don't know what epinephrine and adrenaline and
A little like 12 year olds emergency room doctor runs in and he was like
I looked it up on the internet alpha-gal fascinated what
I've never heard of that could be true yes it's true
When I went back to my doctor after that and I was like hey I just got out of the emergency room cuz they tested me for alpha-gal diamond
Allergic to meat
So this is an allergy so all of a sudden you're looking at the
Quote crazy
And they're not so quote crazy anymore I absolutely we suddenly had a blood test
And of course turned out is all these patients who been telling us this story
Alpha-gal
But but is still like a mystery
Right there
Thomas platts-mills couldn't figure out
Why people like Amy who has lived for 40 years
Eating porterhouse steaks at Peter lugers with a credit
Why would she suddenly develop an allergy
That is some kind of trigger
Yes we were looking for
Could explain it
It could be a mole that could be a nematode worm
Or a fungus
But then he looked at
Again and noticed that all the people who have bad reactions to the cancer
They were in a particular area of the country
West Virginia North Carolina Southern Missouri has no cases in Salt Lake City no case
Denver smatterings down the West
So he turned to his technician J
I said you got a Google every map you can find and say what matches that are
Creatures or diseases that appear wherever the allergy appears
Show Jake starts
Googling Googling Googling Googling and eventually
He comes across a map
That matches where the cases are very beautiful
The maximum area for Rocky Mountain
Spotted fever so he met this little map and it's like the
Shaded dark areas of the country are places with Rocky Mountain spotted fever and then there's like some Stars
I swear
This allergy had appeared yeah and they they overlap
Very interesting
And then all the sudden
It clicks
Rocky Mountain spotted fever is a tick-borne disease
This is the distribution of a lone star tick
And actually just a little before this it turns out an allergist down in Australia
Carol Vance unit
The Noonan v i n n n n u n e end
And I'm from The Tick induced allergies research and Wellness Center in Sydney Australia
She said she was now being visited by all kinds of P
People who claim suddenly
To be allergic to meat and whenever I take a history so if example at Austin was their family history of brown eyes
The 6-month asthma
A stinging insect allergy nice a label being bitten by ticks
When we started asking patients
We suddenly heard the stories
Just out
Kazoo
But at this point Dr platts-mills all he has
Is a map
Some stories
Anaheim
Right so
So what does he do
Well
Maybe I'll just do this to myself
He does what he decides to test it on himself
Oh my God he's our like denies that he did it intentionally I know I had no intention me
I think you also likes to walk and amble and
Think about things right so he does for a long walk along the Blue Ridge
Mountain man I knew I wanted to be off trial because
I'm actually rather allergic to humans
So he's walking and walking and walking along the way he bumps into a whole bunch of
And if you walk into a nest of those things only
If it sounds like a nightmare absolutely 200C ticks and then
In November that year I was taking out to dinner and lamb chops with particular deliciousness
The French wine was delicious
And 6 hours later I woke up covered in hives
He's got an allergy to red meat
All just because of a
Tick by tick bite that's right
The bite you right back
Hi this is Sarah calling from Asheville North Carolina Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan fan
Enhancing public understanding
Science and technology in the modern world
More information about Sloane @www.
Sloan. Org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
And I request
For those of you who
We spend a lot of
What type of kits parents
Aunts and uncles teachers we're looking for stories about what we're calling
Tiny moment
Brilliant
Basically I want to hear about this
Did something
It just means you read back and say
Well
How to make
Maybe it was the moment that I
I kid you've been reading to 4 month started reading back
Do you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lesson
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of the musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class
You noticed they're ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the
Epic moments where
Kid does something super smart
But it doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story
T-shirt with us
Go to radiolab.org
Flash brilliance
And record
Short audio
And that's radiolab.org
Flash brilliance
Thank you so much
I'm Roberto which this is Radiolab now we go back to Amy
Just when she's discovered
That the allergy to meat that she's developed comes from
A tick bite
Tick bite
Like a few weeks before all this started happening
As I said I was foraging for
Ramps my mom's backyard
And I had a tick
My on my arm no turns out that Not only was that tick bite
Terrible thing for Amy
It was a kind of double chine
Amongst the trees
And I think it's only right at this point backup is it
And consider the story from Atticus point of view
Okay so I'm Grandpa clean
I'm a wildlife disease ecologist at the University of Tennessee
So I was wondering if you could help us
Tell the story of
Lonestar
Lipedema
Oh yeah sure
So they start off
Little pile of eggs
Perhaps a massive
2000 eggs
Under the leaves
The proud mom just
At that point she's just a kind of a withered husk
Mean that
Anyway few weeks later those pigs
And this massive 2000 baby ticks
Emerge from underbelly
Could I see them with my naked eye if you ran into a mass of them all up together
Would feel like you got a little smudge of good
An image of Scott Walker
Climb up and potentially will be on the same leave for the same tweet
Looking for something to feet
Now 110
Is that they dry out so when they come up from under the sea
Steve's they come up briefly and then they go back down
Come back up
Thirsty go back down and rehydrate
And we refer to the behaviorist Quest
So if you were one of these little baby ticks up questing for food while you're up there
Yuan
Century Velcro
Because each one of your little legs you have little kind of
Like
Structures inside of your
Flat against
Believe in the air with your two front legs
Second attempt
CO2
Heat movie
Let's say one day you're sitting there on your leaf and you pick
The scent of a nearby Mouse
Potato chips vegan
Maybe you might be about to have your very first meal
So you best stand up
Stretch out all your little legs and do a tick.
So it's kind of interpretive dance why you waiting for that mounts to come just us enough
Rabbit
Suck your dancing your way
You're dancing in you
Reading
And you're dancing
And you're waiting
And you're
Dancing
To be honest you are probably going to
Wait your entire life
And die unfulfilled
Because
There are two thousand to be starting off
And a stable Tech population
Is Ernie going to be
Two of you that survived
Oh my gosh
So 1998 little baby ticks are born and then that's it
Let's say that you're one of the lucky
And one sunny day there you are hanging up on your little leaf when
You detect
Two incoming mammals what is a 40 year old
The other is her daughter
Wave detector
And saved you waving your dancing and you're hoping and dancing in your opinion no waiting in your dancing in your home
Grab
Any
And survive
The reason that
Tech ended up on me
Was
I slept in bed with my dog naked
I mean she's always make it but I was also thinking that's not gross I don't
That sound weird
But what button
How do you know that's when it happened because I know that like I did a good tick check on myself and I took a shower
Power and everything
And then
In the middle of the night I woke up
What's up itching sensation and I went to the bathroom and I couldn't really see what was like
Something was on the back of my arm and it was a
Protec so as the tick is biting into a me
What is it giving Amy that's going to make your allergic
Two meatballs I need to stop to that Robert
That's Peter Smith and rejoining us is shoveled in the scientist.
Circulation we don't really know
But here's a theory
Normally when you eat a piece of meat you put alpha-gal in your stomach and your stomach digestion is in your body
But the tick cunningly drilling injects its saliva
A football that text that takes pit
Into at the victims
Straight into its victim largest
Organ the skin and thick spit as an anti-clotting
Anesthetic anti-inflammatory compounds and we think the alpha-gal
That Peter says the thing about the skin
Is the skin is like this enormous like
Surveillance
It's always on the look
Gottfried Invader so
Wind me up y'all comes
Through your skin
Covered by owner
Bad bad ticks pits
Stop that's going to really like
Set off your means
Immune system
Freaks out like
The alpha-gal covered now in bad spit almost
Sort of by mistake
Gets labeled bad
And now it's on the bad guy watch list
So before the next time you eat meat meat comes in and then
The body unleashes wave upon wave upon wave of chemical
Do battle against this
Alfred and his reaction gets way out of here
And you got so many antibodies both
Making you
Aimee-ffion
Right I mean
It's very weird that sounds like a science fiction movie
It sounds like
The beginning of a science-fiction at least
Kidz Bop let's not go to movie but like
It's
It's just
Strange
Which all goes to say this
Really is
The kind of double tragedy
For Amy and
Yeah cuz
Xidan evolved
Bite humans
Right we're a mistake
Like we have opposable thumbs going to pull them off I actually woke my mom up and she helped get it off
Play drop off the gun to drop off another
Airport terminal
Walmart High pile shag carpet
End end the dirt
And for us while we lose something
That historically anyway is a big part of Who We Are
Yeah
Because we have
We we adapted in the
Grand evolutionary
Schema things
Flash
Yeah
I mean I'm actually sitting here picturing
Steak
But actually the saying I mean hot dogs
Like
Wrap ramps around a weenie in Rust
That's a good my mouth water
Weenies weenies and ramps
Yeah but I am going my allergist tomorrow cuz I did
You know I was reading about this allergy a lot when I first got it and I read that for some people the allergy can fade away
So I'm going to get a blood test to see what my blood level of alpha-gal is
So I'm a little hoping for tomorrow
I want to be normal
Again
That was the end of the Dan and Amy conversation she was going to go to the doctor
Tested
Find out whatever
Define I would happen
So I actually did get an appointment with my allergist
Dr. Korn
Dr corn
She's really nice
So I got a plan I got the blood draw whatever and a few days later my doctor called me and she
Said that my numbers were still really high
And I was like wow
How high are they
And she was like
And I was like three that's not high and she's like they're supposed to be like 1 or something
So they had gone down
But they were still
You know many times more than they should be so when you left
And we're waiting for the call will you waiting with the hope
That what that you would soon be
Eating a bit of hot dog I mean honestly I was hoping
No no no I don't wish that you are you are the beat the great you you never knew I was afraid that she
He would be like oh my God your numbers are so low I think you could probably eat meat let's do a food challenge I'll be like
Cuz like
That's such a scary memory
I don't
You know actually just the other
Night I was eating an Indian place and I was eating vegetarian but like
I felt something and I pulled it out and in the dim light of an Indian restaurant like why are they all it like that
I was like
Was this bacon
And I suddenly you know that you just get those drop in your stomach and I'm like
What time is it
4 hours from now if I did cuz it's there something about it being delayed
That makes it so difficult it just says like
Make a suspense movie
With you it's like it could happen in the next 3 hours or maybe not I don't know
I mean honestly the only thing that
The real reason I want to be able to eat meat
It's so that I will be prepared
To eat at in case of emergency
I mean
I
When on a canoe trip in Adirondacks and I was like what what happens if I get stranded out here in like what if I have to
But I can't even eat meat out I have to hunt fish but then when the lake freezes over what would I eat I can't survive something
Wrong with me
Byfield evolutionarily challenge
What is what I think about before I go to bed every night when I be able to survive if I had just what's on me right now a pen
Underwear
My daughter
And so yeah I mean that's a real issue is like
That's not a real issue obviously it's never going to happen in live in Brooklyn but
I do for some reason I always think like
I want to be prepared in case
But
Yeah you know
I don't think I would go back to eating meat necessarily
Like you are still more
Morphe
Frightened and game
How to speak
Well
Also like
I wish I could be a vegetarian for ethical reasons because it's
Not so much just eating me but just like you know the the factory farming and I kind of stuff so
I feel like morally Superior now I can be like why I don't eat red meat
Course I'm forcing not even put at the same time
I would if I had the if I had the willpower I probably go that way anyway and then also
I think it's great it's like we're all evolving to be on this planet which is
Getting harder to be Anand
We know that
Meat takes a lot of resources and like
Now I don't know I'm not doing that so like the tickets helping me evolve into a better human being
Xo1 could
Instead of thinking of the tick
As
Your teeny weeny
Irritating enemy
You can think of it as a Guiding Light
Making the world safe for to share
With your followers
So you may have lost a relationship with me
But
At least you have your moral superiority
Yeah I mean
I am Superior
So huge thanks to Amy Pearl
For telling a story which never stop
Stop being scary and
And to the fellow who brought her into the room Dan pashman
Who's podcast
The sporkful is
It's all about
Food in every conceivable way
Eating it preparing it
Worrying about it as you heard getting sick from it getting fat from it whatever
And you can find his show
On iTunes or Stitcher or the internet at the sporkful. Com
And the story was produced by Annie McEwen and Matt kielty with recording
Help from Latif Nasser
See you next time
Received
Thursday
At 9:50
P.m.
This is Dan pashman from the sporkful podcast
This is Amy Pearl I'm allergic to meat and I'm
Is Devon Eggers Amy Pearl's mom
Radiolab is produced by Chad
Apple ride
Sr director of sound design
Jamie Jamison York is our senior producer
Maxfield Annie McEwen
Mary Ann wacker
Wang P Ferguson Alexandra Lee Young
Percy of Berlin Berlin Berlin
All the apps that come up with
I got that one
Bye bye bye in this message
Baguette like
Cut off from the group when I'm out on a
Tour of the woods or something and I have to sleep overnight and
I could eat like a frog
A bug
But I couldn't eat like
Squirrel
Emmaus
I guess I could eat bird I mean I don't know
Like
What
Kill myself
I know
Sound like
A champ Burger
Not a baby
I think even more darker
A human another human baby
I don't know if I'm going to go for it
Turkey meatballs
An awesome