Are you awake
Radio WNYC
I'm Robert krulwich Emily Webster this is Radiolab and today today we've got a guy asking
A pretty common question yeah but the way he tries to solve this question is it first
Thrilled
Instructor-led puzzle
It comes to us from producer Andy Mills
Story is about David Weinberg
A buddy of mine and it starts off right around the time you get that high school yeah I graduated from high school and tooth
Mm and then
Went directly to University and then
I got kicked out
Somewhere the beginning of the second semester
And then left that town that I was living in a move to the town where all my friends were going to college and
He moves into the group house it was a party house and a bunch of his friends there was a giant
Cross in the front yard and my friends had found while tripping on acid and put in a shopping cart and they put in the front yard
Are fact-checker actually found out they were tripping on mushrooms not acid but anyway a lot of drinking a lot of partying
David is like for a while it was
Goodbye I'm hanging out with like the people that I care about most in the world I feel
Incredibly free because I don't live at home anymore and then I
There it just started to get old for 1
Every day when his friends would go off to class
David would have to go to work during the day I was working as a janitor at the University where my friends went
And during the evenings I would deliver pizzas
Put on like this for years
You know day after day they would party but then in the morning when his friends would go to class he would go and clean
Toilets and then deliver pizzas
I'll do sophomore year they would go to class he would clean toilets
Andover Pizza
Junior year class
Toilets
Pizzas and like I think looking back on it now I think
There was this rage that started to build up inside
Inside me because
I mean I was really sick of cleaning the toilets of kids in the dorms who
I resent but are also but I also recognize are able to do something that I
Wasn't able to do and you know all my friends were at that University and they were about to graduate and
So I think I was also worried that like
Well they're all going to go off and live these lies and I'm going to be stuck here cleaning toilets in the top of that by the time
Most of David's friends for seniors
He was spending his weekends in jail for driving on a suspended license
To my life at that point was like
Cleaning toilets in the morning delivering pizzas in the evening and then every weekend I was in jail
And
It was kind of this
Breaking Point
One thing one thing we did a lot of like we listen to all the punk music my friends were in punk bands
And we would just like to get really drunk and like yell into the speakers
I like three or four nights a week in up
And one night we were doing that it was me and my friend Danny and my friend Mark and something just snapped inside me
I got lost it
Just started like grabbing chairs and hurling them for Windows and just like
Smashed out all the windows in our house
You couldn't see the floor cuz there was just like wreckage everywhere and I was all bloody
And I was just like
Present tense it was
I don't think it hit me until the next morning
When I saw what it look like
Like a hurricane a black rip through the house
Yeah and all his friends
IPhone just went to stun their sort of like
What's going on
And then you know when you when you confront
A reality like that
Everything just sort of gets Stripped Away and you're just left with this question that's like
Who am I
And what am I doing with my life
Around that time
David was driving around delivering pizzas
Listen to the radio and WBEZ Chicago This American Life
Ameriglass heard the story
Vistacare story couple test
I was hired to interview men and women in the state of Utah who receive Medicaid support for treatment of men
Mental illnesses
Generally
And it just like
Stop me in my tracks I saw the stories by a guy named Scott
Carrier the frequent contributor of This American Life in
It's basically about how he gets his new job he gets this job
Driving around the state of Utah interviewing schizophrenic people
Giving them this test
I took the job because I had no other
I took the job because I just quit my steady job my profession
And this is happening at a point where Scott's life is falling apart
What I wanted more than anything was to put my boss on the floor
Stand on his throat
Watching guy talks about how he hates his boss and my wife moved out
Took the kids and everything's wife had just left him so I took the job and did the job
And my life will never be the same
And David says
As soon as he heard that story I remember thinking like
I need to figure out how to become a radio producer that's what I need to do
Why why does he
Well
I think first off
Scott carrier is
Really good at what he does is something about him that is magnetic
Right it gets people thinking I want to do that
But maybe more importantly
In the story
Scott is
Stuck
Not too dissimilar from
Where David finds himself and
Scott does he turns his stuckness into a story
And in doing so kind of
Gives it meaning
It's getting its Rising above your situation sort of
David hears everything's like
Maybe I can do that to make sense yeah it was like okay
This is my
Ticket
Soap that summer he lined up a job at this camp this summer camp in Upstate New York
And I bought this minidisc recorder shirt
10th he and his buddy Mark who had just graduated
They left Colorado and headed to Upstate New York my idea was like okay I'll just go around and
Kelly's recordings and then I'll write these stories about what it all means and
They want
Sole on the road but with
Recordings
He recorded the kids at the camp this bar fight one night when he was out
Can a counselors
What good animes are keyboard
Listen for this is the coolest thing in the world
Put these on
Is that cool
It's a live recording what's happening right now and yes I distinctly remember just being in
Delete all of hearing recordings that I had made
When nothing is happening
The idea that I can make a recording and listen to it
It was like
Like early man
She's a mirror you know and just can't stop staring at it
Yeah
Yeah he wasn't it
Interviewing
People are anything like that he'd sort of decided
That he wanted to record moments
As they happen
Any figured
The best way to do that was to record
Secretly
I had cut a small hole in all of the pants and shorts that had in the pocket
So I could get up in the morning
Put the
Minidisc recorder in my pocket and then I'd run the cord down my shirt
And anytime
Something interesting was happening I would slip my
Figure my pocket in just press record with at first just some moments here and there
Possible little scenes for a story Maybe
Abraham
Then
He and his buddy Mark to go to New York City
Everything
So he's reporting more and more upper little dude
40 day
After New York he and mark hitchhiked across Europe together
Karen David
At this point David is recording people that pick him up
He and Mark and their other buddy down on the side of the road on the highway is
Even it sounds almost like waves on the ocean
Run up to
Stand next to and record
Just
Everything
And you're still thinking to yourself like
Man I'm just getting gold
Yeah I was like yeah this is love this is the raw material for my first great story you know and I think I tried
Separated myself from
It's like it's kind of cliche like a new backpack around Europe and it's like one of those people like
Actually making a
Grands documentary like I'm a
Imma imma somebody you know I'm not just like everybody else
Yeah
Meanwhile David is accumulating hundreds and hundreds of hours of tape and one thing that you'll hear a few minutes to live
Through all of it
Or most of it as I did it's just him hanging out with his buddy Mark like we became
Instant
Friends the moment we met
Marco's year older than David he was really into music
Sound Engineering that's Mark scene
We have this like perfect Dynamic where Mark had like enough Talent like you could actually play music
And like a Christie's funny songs on the spot
I swear like brought the wrong Suzy azzam to it
And the two of them together the Wii
Would just end up in these crazy places
Oh yeah I remember this recording yeah I remember that
We were in Croatia
Then we ended up with this huge amazing party was like in this old abandoned cabins building which is
Beautiful Croatian people
Cuz it's a great day
But then
French fries veggies or applesauce Mark came back to the States Mark when I was able to record an album with his band
And and David I got a job waiting tables at Applebee's
Dinner salad or soup
Before the meal
Magnus Hometown living in his parents basement
And if you guys are taking
Taking money out of your pocket
You're taking money out your pocket
You're taking money out of my
This kid that hung out with the most that I work with was this meth addict I would go to a place after
Working like
Drink beer and play video games and he would get high and it was like really depressing
Hard time
Shity
And David has all of this tape
Tons and tons
And tons of tape
From X with Mark in New York in
Europe
But he has
No idea what to do with it
So you just keep hitting record
Yes
All right
Yeah I mean I just I just needed that more I think I needed the recording in a wire more than any time in my life been with it
But that was a true but I needed the why the most
This sucks
Like I'm going to I'm going to get through this I'm going to end this will be a chapter in the story
It's been a lot of my time with my finger
Gently resting on the mini disc player I could feel the disc spinning
When it was recording
It was just very satisfying comforting
You know like a pulse
Anyway yeah yeah
Still going yeah
No we should get one of those bells
Some bartenders
Does he have a story I'm not so sure he's cut when I tell well
Hang on to the break
I think you'll think you'll hear an answer
This is Neva Bartram from Encinitas California
Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation enhancing public understanding
Science and technology in the modern world get more information about Sloan at
Www.
Sloan. Org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help this summer I'm hosting a show
And I request for those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
We're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments
Brilliance basically I want to hear about those times when I kid you know did something
It just means you lean back and say wow how did they do that maybe it was the moment that a kid
You've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons and you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of their music
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed are ready music in the margin of their geometry homework were interested in the
Epic moments where kid does something super smart but it doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story please share it with us
Go to radiolab.org Brilliance and record a short audio message for us
Again that's radiolab.org / brilliance
Thank you so much
I'm rubber, which I Molly Webster and we're back
And today we're out we're in the middle of a story
But David Weinberg who is recording almost every day of his life and last we left him
He was in Applebee's
Working as a waiter and living in his parents basement
Right but he did eventually save up enough money to travel again I went to Alaska things like that
And he says that
Win 10
Bad like at Applebee's you needed these recordings to make his life feel like it had
Meaning when times were good
He couldn't stop recording because he was worried that he was going to miss some
Yeah occasionally like something would go wrong like I lost
Three or four recorders they broke down over the course of the years has recording
And whenever our quarter broke that would be a. Where I have to wait for the new recorder to come and I just
Felt like
On edge all the time you know like I need to be a missing I'm missing out you don't like in this weird Twisted way like I feel like I was Miss
Missing out on life
Because I wasn't recording it so when you would get the recorder it would be like a relief oh yeah I was like thank God I can you know
Is pressure would be releasing I can go back to recording
And I would just feel like myself again you know
But then
Hey guys ride ahead of you or behind David ended up down in Seattle where he met back up with Mark
And
Mark and I got in some big arguments in Seattle before I left
What is a woman
He just told me when I depart
Hate the fact that you record me all the time
And
It always recording
Text conversation to
I don't know why and he just laid it all out for me
You know like he was someone who spent
His day all day in a recording studio meticulously laying down perfect tracks you know that
That was his life
And so to him that idea that you would just sort of like record everything it was wrong for a lot of reasons
One of which was he just didn't think that the experience is worn to that
And then he had like philosophical objections to it
That like
What makes life
Great and worth living is that it is this bleeding thing at
Temporary hem
And when you are trying to constantly record it and capture it
Georgia
Taken away from that
Aspect of life
Play don't keep trying to capture like the essence of this thing just
Be in the essence of a thing
David
Saying that
You know he's recording all the time as to not miss anything and Marcus saying that no by recording all the time
You are missing everything
Yeah
If you're missing the important things
And the doctor finally she
Said he didn't want to be recorded anymore and it was like really getting away by friendship cuz like
What puts a ceiling on where your relationship can go when someone
Feels like
They can't open up to you in that way it just puts this wedge between you and the way that's just like awful did you stay
Stop recording at this point for well I couldn't stop I got that fire just like
I don't know whether it was OCD or whatever was like I was just like I couldn't stop recording and so I was always recording and
The recording was like
Almost like a uniform for this
Person that I wanted to be was like
It's like you're on in a play
And
You think you're living this life and then when the disc stops suddenly like the lights go up in your realize
It's all fake
Do you like face a dude like
You just drifting
At this point David has around
2000 hours of tape
Because he keeps on recording is not really hanging out with Mark anymore or any ends up just
Drifting down to New Orleans
This is not
Grey long after Hurricane Katrina
And it's like you know like
You know I don't answer with a flood and is like
I'd like to listen to people like heroin Journeys
And then like all this Injustice is that they face
So we decided
To do something that he never really done before
And started interviewing
People have an assisted living in New Orleans East
Telling their stories
That wasn't changed
Change that much since Katrina
With their permission not recording them secretly
So what did you leave those stories on too
New Orleans Public Radio Station wwoz Street Talk
Stories of New Orleans cultural rebuilding
I'm telling you man I appreciate that discipline
Cuz I have growing up man I was growing up
Just terrible
Then at night he go home and
And he would listen to audio from The Wire
Tape of like me and some bar and
I think
Super drunk and it's like
What did I think this matter
Get out like
Why
Yeah
And then also dislike
Dynamic started to change my mind
We're like
It's one thing to record your own life
And then he asked me before I was also recording other people but it was always framed around me
And everyone else was just sort of like supporting characters
Then I was like
This is not about me it's about other people and like
Suddenly it did start to feel dirty to record
People that was like all of that so we can go ahead and I just felt worse and worse about recording
And
And then I just stopped as I don't want to I don't want to do this anymore
What about that feeling you were talking about just moments ago or wear without
The recorder
Recording what's happening
You felt as if you were missing out
That experience was kind of wasted
Because you hadn't got the chance to record it
I mean I didn't go away that definitely didn't go away
I mean I feel like that's still to this day
I sometimes feel like man I wish I was recording this you know
But
Force me to really think hard about what moments in life
We're worth capturing 120
He doesn't like it if you do try to
Capture a moment
Then
You're kind of
Out of them
But if you don't
Then
It's gotten
Recording has the potential to be lost
Right I think that yeah we all can relate to this idea
But for David
The Crux of that
Pension do it or not to do it like
That became really difficult after him in part because of what happens next
Few months after he had quit recording are you starting to mark
Who I am so back from Seattle is very
Happy to hear the David wasn't recording anymore
And some are decided to go down to New Orleans and visit David and their buddy Danny was down there too
And
And this is hard cuz I haven't really
Hold the real story about half with Mark I'm trying to think
I'll tell you the real story and
Dan and Danny and Mark and I were really close the three of us
And one thing we do
A couple times a year we would all go out to the mountains together and just have this
Great trip together like as friends
And so
We are going to do that in New Orleans and so
Garner bikes and we wrote down to the river
And
Set along the river for a while and then we took the ferry over to the
Westbank the other side of the river
New Orleans is like glittering across the water got stoned and it was just
Magical like that for a long time to talking like having those who deep
Philosophical conversations for the first time in a long time that was not recording wasn't worried about capturing the moment
So my mind was free to not think about the recording
Pinot and then I was actually
More present in some way you know
And it just felt like
It always did when we were close back in the mountains in Colorado you know it was like a great
Moment
And I wanted to keep hanging out there
And
Markers are getting kind of answer you wanted to go explore the city you know you want to go exploring and I was just like
Didn't really feel like I was just sort of like
Didn't want to be one of the people I was happy to be there with them and then Mark
Just jumped up and took off like
Bridget away and we were like well that was
Weird uncle's very strange
David says that
Mark said something in them on the butt
Can't
I can't remember exactly what and so we like God on our bikes and we're only a
Maybe I don't know maybe a hundred yards 200 yards from the
Very it was park there
And
By the time we got
To the bridge that connects the land
Fairy I saw that my bike was laying on its side
On the ramp
I was like well that's weird you know my mind and my life take it back about it I feel like I'm having very slowly why is ma
Mark cycling down why
All those people shouting they're looking
End of The River Why are they looking over and then I look in there over and there's mark
Annies
Swimming in the Mississippi and he shouting something and I can't figure out what he's saying and I was just like
Holyshit like
This is really bad
And I got really really scared I look Danny and Danny looked
Totally terrified
And
She started again I was going Downriver I was just the river and so there was a point
I could see
Off the distance there was a boat like a rescue boat or something and gotten in the water
And Mark started to drift around bent and he disappeared out of you
How to walk up and down
The river
Looking for Mark
They couldn't find him
Then it gets dark
And then he might just head home
And wait for news there
The next morning
Still no news
Few days later
Authorities 8 they gave up their official search for Mark and in assume that he was dead
And a week or so later
They found his body
Get drowned
And I should just add
But there is
No reason to suspect that this was a suicide
Yeah I'm sorry the mark
Batman tits
Sensitive story to hear
Thinking about this is Allen's of like you being with someone who has a
Compulsion and Obsession that is now under control but still
Losing you
Is there
I still is there a part of you that
Wishes you had been recording that day
I the thing is David says
You're not long after my cat died he started going through a lot of his old recordings
And sometimes you would hear on the these great
Moments what you got two of them
But a lot of times he says it
Almost like
You could hear that ceiling
Platypus
According to put on his friendship with more
Man I want to f****** take a boat down the coast man so bad
I was acting
Different than I would have if I had been recording you know like I was conscious that I was on tape all the time
I also hear my cell phone's recordings often
Like stepping over him like
He'll say something and then I'll jump in in in in just like
Clearly I'm just like you
I'm on my own black train of thought and I'm not really listening to him and that bothers me a lot
I'm glad I don't have
I think I'm glad that I
It's just a hard cuz I'm on 100 glad that I don't have to
Live with that Taping that it doesn't exist
But at the same time David says
I feel like
Maybe I missed something and maybe there's some part of what happened the night that I can't
That I missed
All I Know It
Is that
He just said let's get out of here and I jumped up and like
I don't remember exactly how he put it I just remember all said he was gone
If I had a recording maybe I could make sense of it and maybe something would be more clear about it
I think about that a lot then I also think what would have Mark what would Market wanted and
You know what
That probably
Trump's whatever
Clarity I don't know I don't know ya but I still think about it a lot
So think about
What I would get from his recordings if I had them
Random
I don't
A big thank you to David Weinberg for opening up his audio archive and sharing it all with us and sharing the story
And thank you also produce the whole
And listen to all of his hours
Bad here a little update on David he's actually a producer at KCRW he's got this
Series that you should all checkout called below the 10 and if you want to know more about that and maybe you'll
Listen to a lot of the time
It's a series about people like very one-of-a-kind interesting people who live in LA
Couple of the 10
Do you want to hear it I find links to it
Or hear little Snippets from the archive
You can find all that on our website
Nothing you could do I don't know if that's the thing we should say which is radiolab.org that's it that's it still it
Start of message
Radiolab
By God album don't keep it by director sound design
Start wheeler is senior editor
Jamie York is a senior producer
Staff includes Simon Adler
Brenda Farrell
David Gable
Matt Kuechly
Robert krulwich Eddie McCune
Andy Mills
Beastmaster
Melissa O'Donnell
Chelsea Padgett
Arianne wack and Molly Webster hotel from Alexandra Lee Young
Stephanie Pam and Michael Owen shirt
Checkers are either
Dr. Michelle Harris
And this message