What is it
Lab ktoo
And two homosexuals
So funny hilarious that you were like before you listen to this
Need to sit down we care about how you feel
When are boss at different times I feel like we talk about you I'm as I concerned parents sometime
I think Chad lately is he eating
It's soaked before we launched into the show today was going to introduce you to a couple of bucks and I'm Tobin
We are the co-hosts of a new show from WNYC Studios called Nancy
Why did you call Nancy is that code for something that someone's mom
It's whatever you want it to be
Stop it Nancy is like a real old-school term for a gay man
Thanks for the back in the day someone might be called a Nancy boy
I like such an answer
Okay so Nancy as you can probably gather is a show about
Very interested in LGBT stories
All the stuff that comes with it in the stories run the gamut he's a very quick preview one of the stories I'm working on which will be
Early in the season is a search for the first asian pornstar
Until then says at one point he was talking to the director who claims to have discovered this guy she she LaRue
If you ever try to have a conversation about racism in p***
With a p*** director
Fascinating because really it just inspires them to pitch more movie
Black girl get black eyebrow Burial at guy income panda bear
Don't you have the that just the
Polar bear as the wife oh my God
You create created right now I'm just like my wheels are turning in my head
In one of the episodes you have this incredible conversation with your mom can you talk about that
So
I keep coming out to my mom
And then we
Do the classic thing of
We don't talk about it anymore because it's uncomfortable for her so
I guess coming out to your mom to come yeah I keep bringing it up because I wanted to be a normal thing for us
This is how I feel why did you become this way
Why did you choose this
I don't know
Humane Society
Tulsa museums it because your family influenced you
Why you whine you tell me why do you think this way
Wisin y
It's not something you choose
You just are
I don't have the capability
A falling in love with men
Do you know what that means
Pasadena
Compositi
It's not possible
For me to fall in love
With men
I don't know
Desert
The world of gay Republicans which right now is rapidly changing under President Trump you hear a truly incredible
Conversation between hiv-positive man of different Generations
And the whole thing is driven by A really lovely curiosity that we must know everything there is to be about
We are because we are
You know how we are queer
But the reality is like
There's so much about other people that I don't know within the community and I think the show provides an opportunity to
To have this conversation
This is as much about you guys learning as it is about you guys
Nancy's first season is 12 episodes Atlanta April 9th
But you can subscribe right now
If you go to iTunes or wherever you get podcasts
And I hope you do cuz I think it is going to be
Great
Are you awake
Listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
At your name again is
February I'm going to write that down
So how can you hear me get high okay
I'm Robert Coolidge is Radio app
What is the story about a guy my name is Harold herring
I use the middle initial L for Lewis and honor of my father who asked a question
A simple question maybe a dangerous question just the beer asking
A vacuum at ruin the man's life never got answered but today on Radiolab we are going to re-ask Harold's question
This time
We get an answer
And let it Master takes it from here so our main guy Herald
He's former military and he's 81 years old
Staying pretty active I'm competing at the national and World level or do a salon compass
Location
Right off the bat this is the kind of guy you could tell he just does not give up
I've really I'm not supposed to be competing because I've had both knees replaced but anyway
When is Tiny Town Called Brown's Illinois from up where family is the eldest of 11 kids
Planes going up
He would always here
Air Force planes flying overhead and that's why I from when he was very young he always wanted to be an
Air Force pilot
So
How do you spell a little bit about your military background
Well most of my career was with the air rescue service
This is in Southeast Asia during the Vietnam war if an Airforce pilot went down got shot down
Whatever Carol Dennison would jump into their helicopters kudroli green heavy lift helicopters
Hover over the survivors on the ground lowering the voice cable and their pararescuemen climb down
On the fourth floor find the injured Soldier and attached to cables
Hold the helicopter steady you had to hold his hover and a lot of time
The enemy would wait until that process started before they open fire
I've had some wonderful experiences that probably Chief among them with my crew and I
We picked up a pilot ejected in the North Sea at night in the winter time
Hundred miles out to see if we picked him up and
Brought him back
Super high-risk high-adrenaline kind of job and I hadn't
Outstanding record
And then well well he got
Old how old were you around this time
Bye-bye by 39 old
Pilot to my age and with my experience were put into desk jobs
And
Wanted to be on the front line if I could
This was 1973 middle of the Cold War
Harold decided that the way for him to be on the front lines without actually having to be on the front lines you know cuz
Couldn't anymore
With to go into training to become a missileer
Missile launch officer those are the people who sit in a underground bunker and
Just wait to get an order to turn the turkey
And unleash a nuclear attack in trading Hemmings just the information
Remember just virtually Brooke verbatim
Bears that eat
Methodological offer
Has under his Direct Control more Firepower than
Can all Generals in all wars in the history of warfare
And so
Started his training at the Vandenberg Air Force Base in California Nixon was president
At the time and at the time the prospect of nuclear war
Felt very real
And a lot of responsibility there and there's no room for error
Until in Harold's training we were very small class he learned all about the technical stuff you know all them
Mechanical stuff and emergency procedures that were involved all the nitty-gritty details of our missile actually
You want Shannon part of time we had classroom instruction where he learned about the chain of command and all the difference
Safeguards in check so I imagine that he gets an order to Launch
That order has to be decoded so he would decode the order and then his partner with the order and it would verify it with one another
One guy would be like okay I got the order alpha bravo 1 to 4
I confirm
Alpha bravo 1 to 4 and then they launched
So neither of them
Has the power to launch on his or her own and
Both of you are and do you carry a sidearm with you
Why
Well you know it's serious business if you had someone that was
You know if if they threaten your life if one of the officers wanted to just go Rogue you had a sidearm
I took my gun and pointed against return the key Harlow I may go down but I
Be drawn my weapon at least keep have to be turned simultaneously so if I shoot you
Turn my key then Rover get your key and turn your key is too late right after you simultaneously
To the whole point is the system is designed so that no one person
Can launch a nuclear attack
I was very pleased very satisfied with a checks and balances that the crew member levels the bottom worth
They're turning the keys I was not concerned about that at all
But then a few weeks into training there was a
Some discussion about
Preemptive strike
Real quick
Obviously if someone launched a nuclear attack against the us we would be able to strike back
Their pre-emptive strike would be where we for whatever reason
Decided to strike
First
And that raise the hair on the back of my neck a little bit you know I just
I thought we're receiving all of this information about all these elaborate checks and balances
Within the system but they never got any information about how things worked at the presidential level
There's a complete void or blackout at the level that the order is in
Initiated
When you had this thought that you say to the other classmates it wasn't my intent to try to create
Racine by involving other people students whatever so Harold weeks until the end of class
What's up with the front of the room and asks the instructor
A question the very reasonable question he's like just checking up there's a safety net in place at the present
Is making a crazy decision right I want her to find out more
About checks and balances at the
A top-level instructor pauses
Looks at him
Can you put that in writing please
Okay and so he did let me find it first
You do your best to have everything ready to go
Oh here it is
Okay
There is presently a degree of doubt my mind as to whether I might someday be called upon the lawn
Nuclear weapons as a result of an invalid unlawful order is it part of the letter that Harold wrote explaining his
Question I ask myself
How Will I Know
Or can I be sure
I'm I am participating in a justifiable act if you were ordered to turn his keys
He would absolutely do so
But
Because you're not being told what the checks and balances are for the president
He would be doing so
With a conflict of conscience
Picture of underline
I would be required to assign Blind Faith values to my judgment of one man
The present
Values which could ultimately include
Hello
Personality
And political considerations
This just should not be
Okay there's a lot of
Sex on me but who is checking the president
Kind of serious question
Because right now we have a president President Trump
Google
Is clearly interested in nuclear weapons
He talks about it constantly you got the thing with North Korea escalating tensions of North Korea Syria for chrissakes
Student makes you stop and think like
Okay if and when these decisions get made how are they made
Is there someone else in the room
If the president is determine if he if he's ready to go is there somebody there and turn to the president
That is a great question
This is historian Alex wellerstein he's the one who introduces Harold he wrote an article in the Washington Post
Post about this very topic am I at the right place I want to be just like a fists length away
Yeah yeah he has spent
So much time in the archives behind microfilm readers and foiling documents and doing all kinds
Different things
To figure out the history of our relationship to this
Uniquely destructive weapon and what he found was a kind of tug of war
Between the military and the president
That is gone.
More than 70 years
Good morning by President Roosevelt's death
Harry S Truman becomes president
Woman learned how to bomb the day that Roosevelt died
This is April 1945 at this point America has been at war with Japan for over 3 years
It was impressed upon Truman that this was
Not just another weapon that this was something that could be bigger and better than any other weapon before
But there's no
Point with somebody says
Hey mr. president sure we bomb Japan with this bump
Assumed
Of course you're going to do it you have the bomb
You have the enemy and in fact nobody ever goes to Truman and says should we do this they go
Go to Hammond they say we are doing this
The Truman write in his journal
We're going to use the atomic bomb but we will not use it on a civilian Target we will use it on a purely military Target
That's the term
Shirley
That we can't get into his head to know exactly what I was thinking but that is what he wrote in his journal at the time and then he says we will not be
Killing women and chill
The first atomic bomb
Is going to be dropped by a President
Thinks he's dropping it on soldiers only he's
Someone congratulating himself on the no women and children will be killed in this attack
Atomic bomb was dropped on Hiroshima
Men's announcement after they dropped the bomb the day after they get casualty estimates from the Japanese and he realizes
This is not purely a military base
Approximately the size of Memphis or Seattle or Rochester New York no longer exist
The total death toll was almost 200 thousand
So there's a real switch that happens between Truman talking about the bomb and also everything he says about the bomb before he hears with a k
Casualties on both the greatest thing ever and this is the greatest day in history and he's so proud and so happy and then here's
About the casualties in tears about the women and children and suddenly it becomes a burden
Now what happen
Japan August 10th he gets a message from General Groves
Just three days after Hiroshima dropped two bombs
Alberta have a third one in a week
Just FYI
And it's not clear
The Truman new the two bombs are going to be drop so soon
He is
Just learn the Hiroshima is a city
When he just wanted another city
He is not in control
And he has immediately written back
To that massage
Stop knock it off
You are not going to drop another bomb without express permission of the president of the United States
Soak the major theme of Truman's approach to nuclear weapons
If they keep them out of the hands of the millet
Why he believes that the military if you give them a new weapon they will use it
It's not a crazy idea to design and build these bombs to make sure the military can't launch them on
The nuclear parts of the bomb have to be in the possession of the civilians the Nuclear So the
The plutonium the plutonium core nearly bombs allowed to do that the fronts of them actually open up and allow you to stick
Krikorian and close it back up so the civilians walk into the room with the explosive part the soldiers open
Lid
The civilians put the explosive part in close the door now you have an active Bomb by putting a battery or something else
Biking to your Walkman why do I have that analogy in my eighty-year-old where does it put the nuclear
They have their own faults with their own guys but their own gums and their job is to shoot anybody who
Tries to take
A core without presidential authorization for the rest of his presidential term Truman doesn't
Budge the nuclear power is his
And he's alone but the technology starts to make it trickier to do this
If you want a very small atomic bomb you can't
Separate the pin out from that is just not going to happen it's physically like glued to the explosives and things like that
So it's 1953 just a few years before held enter the military
Returns to Fort Benning Georgia
President Eisenhower comes to power and he's a former General right exactly is a little bit less concerned about
Who has control over these nuclear weapons so he
Eases up a little bit in his administration
I'm Potomac weapons small ones are to be treated as basically any other kind of weapon
Awesome this is archival footage from 1960 when President Eisenhower is getting a first look at some of the newest addition to the new
Nuclear Arsenal
Binoculars to watch helicopters
At that time they were really creative with their new nuclear weapon
Does he
Continue to maintain authority over the bigger bombs he allows them to be transferred to the military but he said
Says Don't drop them without my permission but there are some cases in which she says
Under really bad circumstances you can use some of these weapons without my permission compared to Truman he's really shifting that
PowerBack
Does the military
Yes but by the time Kennedy is the president
Harold has 24 his Pilot in the Air Force
Are the two in the most danger of Devastation Soviet capabilities are greatly increased so
Can you get rid of anxiety
Some of these anxieties bubble-up and popular these are these are kind of out there
How to drop the bomb on popular culture is
In nuclear fear
Mueller building bomb shelters kids in classrooms are practicing hiding under their desks
This distance the Heatwave is sufficient to cause melting the upturned eyeball
You have bombers flying from the United States and on these routes to take them near the so
Soviet borders
And the problem is you put up a lot of bombers only a matter of time before they'll expect one.
Cracker of a malfunction
B-52 carrying hydrogen Munitions and so indeed there are a bunch of accidents
Bombers crash with hydrogen bombs on board a crashed in Spain and drop hydrogen bombs
One of us gets dropped in Greenland
Play crash in the United States numerous times there's one in the South for a bomb basically land on somebody's house in the comic book
Atomic atomic bomb landed on someone's house
B-47 jet Over Florence South Carolina
Thomas tomorrow
On the water
That would be the most terrifying thing imagine you're just brushing your teeth and then
And there's a knock on the door is excuse me we going to remove this
So does all these accidents and on top of that America is keeping a bunch of its bombs and bases all over the world
And I start to worry that some of these bases are are not American bases and there aren't that many Americans on them
Nukes are kept at a base in Turkey turkey's our friend not a problem but they're like
Two American guys guarding these things they have the keys to turn these missiles on
What do you need to do if Turkey wants to become a nuclear power over the head with a hammer and take the keys
Now turkey is a nuclear power yeah this is more or less what Kennedy says
Waxing Instinct The Truman that he issues a directive which says no weapons can be kept overseas unless they have
Have locks on them
In the first versions of these are very crude they're like literally combination locks we like bikes yeah they're pretty simple
So you're you're doing this technological enabling of this kind of
Vast political metaphor that the president is in control of these nuclear weapons at all times
Truman wanted it
Close
To the chest
And then Eisenhower wanted it out there and then Kennedy now is pulling it back in right exactly
At the time this felt safe
Who better to trust in the
President with something so powerful to get in the world
And even after Kennedy the laws around this solidify the power stays
With the president yes
But then
You got this guy
People have got to know whether or not their President Richard milhous Nixon
And this feeling of safety and really
All trust in the presidency
Starts to a road
So in the last days of his presidency the Watergate break-in they're all the investigations
Nixon was drinking more than the president perhaps ought to
He was under intense amount of
Stress
He did a few things that made people uncomfortable the most infamous Moment Like This happened in the summer
Yes when all the Watergate stuff was really coming to a hat p was talking with two congressmen
And he was trying to impress upon them what a waste of time this quote little burglary was and
Give an example of
A minor this was he explain that
His responsibilities were huge if he wanted to he could go into the other room pick up a telephone in 20 minutes
60 million people would be dead
Wow he said that he said this
And that's exactly the kind of situation Harold was thinking about when he asked his question like
Since I'm the guy with my hand on the he just kind of curious here
Is there a system for making sure a president doesn't just walk into the other room pick up the phone and order me to kill six
A million people
There is presently a degree of doubt in my mind
So he asks this question first
Out loud then he does it in writing and then I was pulled out of training unequal survival
6 days before graduation that leads to a series of meetings with Superior officers
Tell him that I need to have more faith in our leaders know not to question him
And I was told I didn't have a need to know that leads to a trial
Where he has this one meeting with this military judge you basically here I have your question in my hand I will tear it up
And we will can all forget this ever happened but I still wanted to question answered and then that leads to appeal
And he's writing letters I would spend days and nights virtually continuously writing to congressman
Writing and writing to the president but it really didn't matter at all what I had to say
He's basically like okay fine I I don't
Want to be a launch officer anymore I asked to be you no real sign if they weren't going to give the info
Cremation but instead of reassigning him my
Promote Lieutenant Colonel with withheld
I was removed from flight status so I no longer would get flight pay
I was thin permanently disqualified from the human reliability program
Along with that my
Top secret security
Clarence was taken away from me
And once you have a security clearance remove and your permanent disqualify there's no hope
For your career
I pursued every Avenue available to me
To have my military record corrected
And to have the findings reversed
And to Romanian Air Force
Only after I exhausted
All of my Appeals
Was I ordered
Kirby
Retired
What
I don't why why a man knows it like the whole military thing you got to stay in your lane you don't question your spear
Why would they
What's the question why why would they why what's wrong with him asking the question why is it such a
Well I'll tell you right after we take a break
This is Timothy franczyk calling from Stillwater Minnesota Radiolab is supported in part by the
The Alfred P Sloan Foundation enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology
In the modern world
More information about Sloan at www. Sloan
. org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help this summer I'm hosting
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
About what we're calling tiny moments of Brilliance basically I want to hear about those times
So did something
It just means you lean back and say wow how did they do that maybe it was the moment that I can
Kids you've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons and you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of the musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed are ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the specific moments where a kid does something super smart
Don't have anything to do with the test if you have a story please share it with us
Go to radiolab.org brilliance
Record a short audio message for us
Again that's radiolab.org / Brilliance thank you so much
Hey I'm Jared I'm wrought iron Robert krulwich Radiolab until lots of why was Harold question such a threat
Here's how it was put to me. The other side has to know the only reason the only way that a phrase with this
The whole the whole premise is deterrence not has been our founding philosophy
Since we develop these things this is dr. Sonya McMullen and I'm a former Air Force missileer
She had her hand on the nuclear keys from 1997 to 2001
She means Arizona
Countries from nuking us
Will Newcomb
Right back
But if the other side doesn't believe that you will respond in kind
Then it doesn't work you have to believe my thread is legit I have to be credible so if you're the guy who's hand is on
Kaneki when the order comes down to launch there can't be any doubt that you will do what you were ordered to do exactly
So the problem with somebody like Carol is it you're in if you start allowing people to at the bottom to start making up their mind
Then it's not a credible threat cuz I want to understand in your own mind why they had to have a
Committee to sit in judgment on him and review
Some sort of
Factory I don't know what
I'm I'm in Plano I haven't seen their side of it I'm
Filing
To get access to that side we'll see how that goes
So I found this actually just we got this morning so we actually ended up finding a statement by the
Commander in Chief of Strategic Air Command
At General Russ Doherty
I don't know if you have
CNET Harold but it's going to be fair we thought we should let Harold respond to what do you know about
No but he would see us
Think that Commander cheapest teaching her come in right right right until let me just read to you what he said sure
Demetrius hesitation initiated extensive hearings and administrative procedures
Later he professed that he really would turn keys and that is hesitation and be misunderstood
Examine the record thoroughly and discovered that for a fact
Kid repeated several times in the record that he would readily turn keys
Each instance is affirmative assertion was followed immediately by a personal
Subjective qualification
Yes he would turn Keys upon receipt of an authentic order from proper Authority
If he thought the order was legal
If he thought the circumstances necessitated an ICBM launch
If he was convinced that it was irrational moral necessity and so on
Every affirmative answer was qualified by a subjective condition
I did not say that anywhere
Nowhere did I say that
Nowhere did I use those words
And
I'm sorry but
That's just
Dutchess Falls
That doesn't surprise me according to Harold he never wanted to doubt an order coming from the president
Moon
Let there had to be
Some
Sort of check and balance
So that one man
Couldn't just
On a whim
Order the launch of nuclear weapons just wanted to be told that something like that existed so that
He and his fellow officers
Would not have to have a conflict of conscience and that we not put anybody in a position
Horror
They're just following orders
I'm throwing our conscious to the for when I think it's an affront
To play the game of you don't have the need to know
Someone that's doing one of the most serious
Grave jobs that there is
Any armed forces
Ento
Harold never got an answer to his question
We decided to make it
Our question where where do you get somebody who's allowed to question the president because we know
I know that my time you get to the bottom there's no way that's possible so what about the guy above that let's say there's an officer who's one more up to
Is he going to question me order well I don't know he's getting it from the general to coordinate all of the nuclear attacks but if it
I got the ham it must be a legitimate order right maybe those top-level major heads of the military branches
Maybe they get to I don't know and so my question is where if anywhere if the president issues an order
Tammy will they say no
After a lot of digging around Alex says that he thinks my guess is you're not allowed to question the president
More than a couple steps down from the very top if you're allowed to question the present at all maybe we can do it and when we talk
To Sonya McMullen
Element lyrics
She also thought that the Secretary of Defense could
Probably provide a check
The Secretary of defense's that is the first person to say
Hey let's let's think about this
I think about this in detail
All right
We're ready
Okay
This is Bill Perry
Formally Secretary of Defense 1960 defense of the United States
So we decided to ask an actual Secretary of Defense
William Perry served under President Clinton
Up from 1994 to 1997
Yeah let's just pretend for a moment that the president issues you an order that you disagree with
Because you don't think the president is of right mind or
Sober
Or whatever
What Authority do you have a secretary of defense avanee
The system is set up
So that only the president has the authority to order a nuclear war
Nobody has the right
The countermand that decision
Team I choose
To call the secretary defense or the Secretary of State
Or the chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff
To get his advice was counseled
But he even if it does that you may or may not accept that counsel
If you as Secretary of Defense say to the president he says let's
Go and you say let's not
Can you vote if he calls me and then if I say that mr. president that would be a very serious mistake don't do
Do that he might or might not accept my advice
Are you necessary to launch like
Suppose
Everybody in the room thought that it was a bad idea would he still be able to do it yes
He has the exact call directly to the Strategic Air Command to do the launching
End
They will respond to his orders they don't call the sexual defense
For the children's sake should I do this
They do it
Yeah so in our training we are conditioned
Almost like
Pavlovian tok this is Doctor Bruce Blair he was a missile launch officer
At the exact time that Harold was training to become one and ever since then he basically spent the whole rest of his career
We are studying nuclear command-and-control and I wrote studies
So classified that the Pentagon demanded that I not be allowed to read them anymore
We asked him like why does it work like this why would we give one person that much power it's always
It's always been set up that way and it came out of the
Cold War
You know in the 1960s
I don't know what
By the 1960s the US and the Soviet Union were building icbm's which of these nuclear missiles they could
Go from a silo in one country
To Target in the other in the matter of minutes
So if the Soviets ever launched their missiles at us for under a missile attack
There's very little time to assess the attack
To brief the president on his
Options
Because the Assumption was that the Soviets would Target our missiles are icbms
And they would be the first to go into the office for the president
Has to decide whether to launch ICBM
Before the other metros land for
Any incoming missiles could destroy
Command and control system
In
That horses
The present to make a decision on how to respond immediately because missiles are flying in it
4 miles per second is about 6 or 7 minutes
To make that decision
Sex with a decision process
Is too short
For any kind of
Thoughtful or serious deliberation and the pressure is intense
And there I think you
Would find that
Different presidents would respond differently
And their character their temperament
Are they thinking people
Where are they intuitive people
Coopers Pond instinctively in ISO
See a lot of variation in the way
Presidents
React to a nuclear emergency
If the president United States now for
50 years is followed at all times twenty-four hours a day by a military aid
Current football this is Van Vice President Dick Cheney also up former Secretary of Defense
Talking on Fox News Sunday back in 2008
He could watch the kind of a devastating attack the world's member saying he doesn't have to check with anybody he doesn't have to go
Call the Congress he doesn't have to check with the court he has that Authority because of the nature of the world we live in
It bothers me
Immensely that the only area that there is not a checking balance
Is a 1
Zack and literally result in the end of the world
They seem strange to me
Have you thought about this at all and wondered whether there's a better way to do this yes I have and what would you suggest
I have a
Specifically proposing to continue to propose unsuccessfully again former secretary defense William Perry
Louis phase-out are icbms and to the extent we have to have a nuclear deterrence
We limited the submarines in airplanes because
They don't have to lunch
In 5 minutes or 6 minutes for 7 minutes and when it comes to preemptive strikes
He says how we have before the Congress now a bill making a modification
Which has the less
Ellesse United States
Has been verifiably attacked
Then the president
Hash before you
Yvonne Chisholm nuclear weapons
Has to go to Congress
Full commission
So far our bill is very simple this is congressman Ted lieu and he and Senator Ed Markey are the guys who off
After the Bell Jessie says
Before the president can launch a nuclear first strike the president must first get a declaration of war from Congress
I believe that you introduced this
Bill
Before the elect
Sarah Wright
Absolutely
Senator Mark I believe we need a structural fix We Believe actually Hillary Clinton was going to be president
Is Bill
I would have replied to her
And that's because
The fate of humanity in our world should not rest on one person
And so are you seeing this as just as you sizing the stop is this a systemic problem or is this a
Problem with one person who
Just happened to have the office right now it's actually a systemic problem
And it's also a problem with the current person in the office
Who's the president
But you can see future President right could be elected with
Judgment or temperament issues or maybe
They simply go to Advanced age and get
Alzheimer's right or or some other
I sort of issue
That's why we can't
Have a system queer
There's so little checks and balances do you know about this bill or
Have you heard from now actually down
That's that's interesting
That is a very interesting bill
.
Let me let me say this way
On one hand I agree
Because of God I always like to have checks and balances
On the other hand
I also think that it
It it says to a potential adversary
Enid
Now there's doubt
So there to sort of values here
1 is
Your Humane interest in making sure that
The end of the world if it comes to that
Is happening for good reason
LOL just reason it's best you can define it
And
The ongoing hope that by making this
Art system
Credible that they will never have end of the world
So my question to you is like how do you weigh those together
Well
It's
That's the Dilemma
Yeah
You know that's the Dilemma
So after the military force Harold to retire
He became a truck driver
And once I got that job I made up my mind
But I was going to devote my time
I'm making a living for my family into that company
Then I wasn't going to be off dealing with this subject anymore
Eventually he started doing Addiction Counseling at the Salvation Army mostly with homeless
How how what's your sort of
Emotional state around all this right now like how often is this something you still think about it how
What do you how do you feel right now
Hell I'm
I'm just
I just I think that
Common sense I think
The
Goodness in human beings
Babes
A resolution dance
I just think it's nothing need
For that
Is
At least as great now as it
Ever been in the history of our Republic
And I might add on a personal level that
When I was really
Committed
To the military to the Air Force
Volunteered several times in 02
To do my duty with respect the Vietnam War and
I just felt
That I had asked a very reasonable question
That deserved
An answer and
And it was not
For me alone
Activist for all of us
Maya Western Hemisphere
Keep thinking about the six minutes
Not a long time
Big props to reporter lots of Nasser
This story was produced by Annie McEwen with production help from Simon Adler
And a big thank you to historian and reporter Ron Rosenbaum Force research be relied on
Some part for the story and to our special Consulting researcher Alex wellerstein who is by day
A nuclear historian at the Stevens Institute of Technology
New Jersey to US Air Force to Captain Chris mesnard and to Carla Pantheon to turn tester Willette
Andrew Lieutenant Veronica Perez also thanks to Elaine Scarry Ryan Pettigrew at the Nixon Presidential Library Ryan
Camp Robin Berry and Lisa Berry Tom Woodruff during the broom and Ray Peter and finally the temp
The Bay Times
Who we work for the past two years on the previous two episodes we put out about police violence
Their project
Called why cops shoot is now online definitely definitely check it out at Tampa Bay
Babe.com why cops shoot at tampabay.com why cops shoot
I'm Jared I'm Robert krulwich thanks for listening
Start of message
Simon Adler Brenda Pharrell
Melissa O'Donnell
Vitaly and Katie Ferguson
Bill Harris in this message
I'll be happy to share whatever
I remember remember this
To place early in the morning of March 1st 1954 search been a while
Tell a couple weeks back the writers Sam Keen put us in touch with this guy
But was quite traumatic and then hard to forget
How old are you on that day
In 1954 I was 9 years old 9 years old
His name is Tony De Brum he is an ambassador for the Marshall Islands in the North Pacific
He tells a story about a particular moment that happened
When he was nine
One a day very early in the morning
At that moment is that the early one morning hours I was out fishing with my grandfather
It was customary we lived in
Two to go net fishing
Throw net fishing for scad
Tony says he and his grandpa were out on the beach
Before the sun has risen
And they waited through the water tossing their net
Pulling a back
Tough it out
Pulling it back
Natalie done that for a while the settlers took beginning to rise from the East
And I was carrying the basket he was throwing the net
Turn the flashlight off
We are temporarily blinded by the Flash
It was as if someone had walked up to you with a with a flash camera and and
Nnn took a shot writing inches from your eyes
I cannot
With any certainty tell you how many seconds past
But
I felt the shock it was like the real
Heavy burst of wind going through real and it turned away from the light and back
Towards the shore where you can see the the vegetation moved
It's Indescribable I thought it was the end of the world
But Tony didn't know is it 300 miles away the US had just test
Did a bomb they called Castle Bravo it was a hydrogen bomb but a thousand times
Strong as the bomb that dropped on Hiroshima and then the
The rumble and Roar and the Thunder of the the sound of the explosion
This was not one big explosion that goes just boom and that's it the Chain Reaction caused it to
222 roll like thunder and then
He says the sky erupted everything turn red the sky 2
Turn red ocean was red the sand was red my grandfather was threatened
Fish report for rent so holds that the whole atmosphere the whole hemisphere
The effect was like you're standing under a glass bowl and somebody put blood over
We we were terrified
That explosion in the many others like it
Would poison the Marshall Islands poisonous people
But in that moment Tony says
His grandpa just stood there
Listening to the explosions
And staring at the Blood Red Sky it seemed to have lasted for what
What seemed like hours I am Nas
72 years old and every time I speak about this my My Skin So cross night
I still get goosebumps