Are you awake
Northern listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
Hey I'm Jared
McCulloch versus Radiolab and today my name is
We're going to start
With a cry for help
I know 90
10 years old
And I'm unable
How to get a driver's license
Good job
Go to college
Can a plane get a bank account or boat
This is the
The story of a woman who became sort of famous
Wish myself
I don't know how
Invisible
For having no identity whatsoever
If you've been through a similar situation or know anyone who can
Please contact me
Story comes to us
Our reporter Alexandria
And the young woman at the Centre of the story
I was born in Texas is Alecia Faith Pennington
Cuz by faith
In
Brian Houston and then we moved to Kerrville
When I was real little like I don't even remember Houston at all she grew up in a really small town about 45 minutes outside of Santa
Antonio and it's kind of country we live right outside of Kerrville actually
So it was even more
In a country that Kerrville is
These parents were very conservative very religious
And they had created a place for their family that was
Separate from
The rest of the world
Well hi there
Welcome to the Pennington point
I'm Lisa
I just wanted to
How to say a quick hello
His mom Lisa actually kept a video blog of life in the Pennington family
Birds are singing
So peaceful out here in the country so we had like like 5 acres of land
This is our front porch we bought this old farmhouse
About 10 years ago
We had a little home Farm
We had
Goats chickens
We had rabbits at one point
A cow that we would like raise
You know we butcher it and then freeze it all to me and then heated over the year
I just sort of approaching self-sufficiency or was it was it
Reach that self-sufficient point
But they also we wanted to give you something their kids
Duties and responsibilities
We had a chart
The kid's name
How many of those how many of you were there
9 children Grace
Jacob
Hope faith patience don't Adam Legend Levi
Got that done.
Where were you in the
Pecking order
4th in the middle
Middle child syndrome
And Herb
Parents
Is Faith a word
Kind
But very
Farm
Very strict lot of rules for how you're supposed to dress and how you're supposed to look high school
Educate yourself what were some of those rules
For the girls you had to wear dresses
Was super high collars we always wear sleeves no sleeveless
Kind of Amish but not like that conservatives
And
We all had a really really really long hair we didn't cut her hair and we just didn't have a lot of access to things that they didn't want us to have access to
I'm going to turn into like you were like 18 and could get on the allowed on internet for like limited
Sight and stuff
What about television did you guys have that no other kids watch television
Electronic
Satan 2
Not have as much of a passion for Learning and working
And their Bible reading
I didn't get to watch a lot of movies growing up they only listen to Christian music
Cool or what how did that
All home-schooled
Every single one
Does that mean that you were like
Always on the
On the property or
Go to church off and on
Various times so
We go out for that custofab
Super rarely like we did
I love the time you were with your family
I was just kind of a moral thing like
We are trying to
Keep you
Holy
I think
They
Just
Wanted to
Keep playing
The things that they thought were like
Sinful in the world
Away from their kids
And try to keep them safe and everything so if you said I want this they would say no and they win
Yeah arguing was not allowed but face actually
Should I just kind of
Pushing that line just a little bit I am definitely a lot more stubborn and a lot more free-spirited and
Right around her 18th birthday ideas
I don't know I reached a point like a Breaking Point
With brushing like a little family meeting and I was
4 oldest
Siblings of my parents were kind of supposed to discuss things and then
My oldest sister asked my mom she was considering getting a job and kind of asking advice or permission
If she couldn't
The Rings are too much outside influence but she was 23
Yeah
And then my brother said he wanted more internet because he was doing work for a church
And they're like I'm sorry we can't do that you know you could be looking at things online you know we just need to shut it off
Github
The one that's right next to me to 21 mm for a phone my parents are like
No telephone
And so I was just like wow
And I'm looking at my other siblings and they have nothing ahead of them
When I allowed to get jobs
I like to go to school
They have no life except living here on this little farm
They have no future
After that night I decided I couldn't live like that
I couldn't
I was not going out like that
So
I had an iPod
And
I went on my parents room and I snuck
My mom wasn't there and I snuck my grandpa's phone number in Cincy an iPhone I could text him over Wi-Fi from
My iPods
I did and I said hey when y'all come visit next weekend
I want to go back with you
I need help I need to get away from here can you take me back
Home with you and
He said he would
So Grandma is not a bone of the same mind as your folks
They weren't really on board with how my parents did things
But they always kept coming to see us
That's why I knew that they cared about me
And so I felt safe
To reach out to them
So the next week
Her Grandpa and her grandma show up
Farm and
What week
Bolt how you going to do this
Expendables
I don't want to go
But my grandpa was like
You need to ask them first need to ask permission
So I did and then
They
Said no you can't go with them
And then so I was like okay
Could I couldn't argue
And then
I said
Are they approached my grandparents broken necks and you still want to go or
And if I decide that I did
As far as you know you're the only one so far in this family has
It might
Dyrdek
On this is convect
I know it
Everton
Anything like that in
Our family before
So
Text morning
September 24th 2014
My mom was on her morning run and my dad was in his office he said was always there working in the morning
In the house
To my grandparents have to buy the rest of the kids and I just walked out the door with them
Luggage rack
What's your weakness one suitcase
My my grandpa texted my mom and was like we're taking Faith with us just wanted you to know
And then my mom texted and said don't go anywhere yet I'm coming back
She texted my dad and then they they both came and
Tried to get me to get out of the car
They're like you have to have the car as I don't have to like what yeah you have to cuz we're telling you to Mike Will
So they got in
And
Thanks yes my grandparents to get out
They're like can you get out of the car and we'll get in so we can talk to her
So you were alone in the car with your parents then that's then all the all the safety goes away right here
The only thing I had on my thighs that I was buckled in the
Car and refuse to get out
I think they were just kind of
Shocked
I was so torn
I I mean I felt like I was just
Melting
What was it that kept you in
I think I was just telling myself over and over that I knew it was the right thing to do
Even though I didn't feel like it
I
Had to take
Control my life
And Amber wildee
Migraine pressure like we have to go like we need to leave out and sew
They left
Just drove away
So this world like this is
This is what 8 people that you ate + 2
10 people that you are
Reminder world
Like
Yeah
I was astonished that she had the boldness to
Carry out that plan
This is Jenny L&S face and her mother's sister who like her grandparents didn't really subscribe to the Pennington
10 worlds you
But she would visit them from time to time at the Farm Heroes
For face
It's even more than just
The boldness of leaving her family
She believed she was walking into this world that was bad.
Potentially going to
Harm her
So that first night she gets to my parents house my grandparents said you can sleep in this room and there's a TV
The guest room Tulsa remote and leave her alone and said whatever you want
She never been allowed to
Kicker on TV shows and Sochi
She turns it on
You looking for
Full sun and she said it was like a
Gardening show or a Home Improvement show or something and she's sitting there thinking I don't know if this is bad
Exactly
Portland Water
Chevy watching this cuz that's kind of my parents did their what they would come dictate was right I was wrong and I went somewhere distant okay that's wrong
That's right
And now that moral compass
Was gone
She suddenly wasn't sure what was going to want
What about anymore
I am so tired
Tired of the way we
And 19 is a tough place to step into the world being that naive
Yeah she's asking me about sex
How do you learn what are you I don't know anything
I thought I knew
What kind of man
I didn't know anything
Even the most basic social norms supposed to act
When she's hanging out with her cousin or other people her own age I don't know what I'm supposed to talk about I didn't catch most like the reference
Do they make all these other
Teenagers would be talking about shows music
Movies school face
I had no idea
She wanted to join this world we all live in an even in the most simple ways she wanted to get a job
When to drive have an apartment
But
She couldn't
She didn't have course have a driver's license
No plus she didn't have it
Social security number
Have the birth certificate will you were born when you were born didn't they say okay was just the hospital will
The hospital Saul home birth
They specifically sought out midwives
That would
Agree to file no Wrecker
Why would you want to do that
There's two
Hole
Kind of way of thinking is called
What's it called
Sovereignty to take some of these documents as they exist
I've got hooks in them
So as I dug into the story I actually talked to a bunch of people who the birth certificate seemed like
Like a paper of ownership
Political or religious or just privacy reasons don't want this kind of documentation from the gov
Definitely been used for the measure of control
Face parents who actually wouldn't talk to me for the story they're not supposed to be a part of that movement but my dad
Some of those ideas
That
The government should not have a number assigned about they purposefully raised faith and her eight siblings to be
Outside of the system and that's
Probably something they thought of as a gift
I guess the thinking is that face would be
Free from the rules of
Society really my parents
Stay but they did it out of like
The best they thought they
To do so I mean I'm not going to
Emagine buddy for doing what
They think they should do
But to face it didn't feel like Freedom it actually felt like prison
And this is where face Journey really began
Bass and her aunt or Grandma they went online started poking around and you realize
Was it the first thing you need is a birth certificate yes
She's applied to the Bureau of Vital Statistics government office where they keep track of like births deaths
Marriages adoption in the Bureau of Vital Statistics does a search not only a vet name but if any light
Django babies born in that area and make sure that you weren't stolen at Birth from some of their parents or something like
But they couldn't find anything so they said the next step is to go to court so my mom can't
Text the court and they wanted three pieces of information proving her birth facts
Well there was a sworn affidavit by my mother a swearing that she was at her birth we got that one
So they needed two more documents she could get a doctor's records
But
She doesn't have any government Hospital
They said she's never been that sick never even had an accident and they're better than us
Records I never even set foot inside of school savings account
Bank account without a social what about immunizations my dad was super against all that one of the
Court Clerk's asked if she'd ever been baptized cuz the certificate that you get when you're baptized in a lot of churches can
Work as one of the three pieces of evidence
Okay but it turns out the baptismal record didn't have her birthday on it so it didn't count
Did you ever go to the library and get a library card you can get library card without an ID
Did you ever get an email address to your name at your parents house
Yes
But it was all in your handwritten stuff
It doesn't count
So you have to go to the judge and say what what do you say to the judge
Well the judge won't listen he just said we're not going to hear the case because you don't have enough to even for me to even consider cuz you have to
I have some kind of Records you don't have enough proof
So you're sitting there the table there's a lawyer sitting there opposite and you and you sing so so
I know I was
I believe that I am this age
I was born
In my
House
Add second section address
Now what do we do
He looks at you and says what she looks even says
I've never seen this before she seemed people undocumented but not
Someone born in this country and visible to the states in the federal government
Whip It Up
If you're born in America you are not automatically a citizen so shouldn't that I mean it's not like when you're born there's like this hey
Halo floating over your house just letting everyone know
You have to prove it
Where they could she get a
An immigration attorney that won't no not really because when an immigrant comes here from another country they
They have this country of origin
And for face in the eyes of the government she has no country of origin
They just think of her as being from nowhere
So I wasn't just like I was stuck
That's weird he called everyone we could not
Get help and we get like a little bit of allelic mean it as a work
We go up we talk to somebody or we fill out a paper we mail something every call somebody or something
And just like you rejected every time
You know it just looked hopeless is made me feel like
SNF
Happen you know it got to the point where when she was at parties or just talking to people about her
Situation what are you do I say how I don't exist
What kind of start this like weird conversation and it would actually start a lot of Commerce
Games for other people
And it would kind of help me to like
Navigate stop
And so I actually kind of
Help me figure out how to
Socialize
This funny little things you could say
But when she was alone
It wasn't funny at all
I went through a really dark time during that I went through a lot of depression
Depression manifest in you what
Happened to you
I was not self harmful but I was
Having a lot of suicide
My tomatoes are now almost like I don't even now
It's just
Felt like I was
Just floating in life
In the middle of just
See if there's so much stuff
You know I didn't know who I was
I have like I didn't exist at all
We're going to take a quick break and we'll be right back
Hello this is Ricardo from beautiful Monroe New York
Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology of the modern world more information about
Sloan @www. Sloan
. org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here I'm a producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
And I request for those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents
Aunts and uncles teachers
We're looking for stories about what we're calling
Basically I want to hear about this
I kid you know did something
It just means you lean back and say
Wow
Maybe it was the moment that our kids you've been reading to 4 month
Started reading
Back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of their musical score
Or maybe the kids in math
Music in the margin of their geometry
We're interested in the
Specific moments where
Kid does something super smart
It doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story
Go to radiolab.org
Flash brilliance
Record a short audio message
And that's radiolab.org
Flash Brewing
Thank you so much
Hey I'm Jared I'm Robert krulwich Radiolab today the story of a woman who became famous for
Being intimately invisible
So
She decided that the only solution
My name is Alecia Faith Pennington
And I'm US citizen by birth to make this video I was bored at home
And my parents neglected to file breaker 2
Advocate for birth record of any kind
She just figured I was homeschooled my entire life
But have no school records
Maybe there's somebody out there that has no done this before so I was like well
Give a shot I want
Travel I want to get
I want to just be a phone
American
But I can't until I can play
If you've been through a similar situation or know anyone who can help
Please contact
She put it up on YouTube and
Then
That was it
Expect anyone to watch it
But
My phone was just like notification after notification it was like
Ding a ding a ding
In the first week at over 1.2 million views like
I hadn't even like been on YouTube before that let alone like
Posted a video so it was crazy it went up on Reddit Twitter the friend of
Snapchat daily
People just couldn't believe it they were like can this seriously happen it just
Took off and then she just starts getting all these
Email it was
Is saying I was getting literally two emails every single second that's not an exaggeration
I couldn't keep up with it like I could not read all of them coming from like Germany and Israel Africa
Worldwide
And what were people saying what did they email you about
Oh all kinds like I was not only touched by your screen presence but I'm also very infuriating frustrated by the circuit
I actually sat down with faith while she read through bunch of these emails
Hello I'm very intrigued by your story book really 23 from homeschoolers Louisiana my name is Jose from the children
Turn up immigrants who felt like a scent
Solidarity I commend you for that but a lot of it was and I pray that you were able to get the documents
You need some kind of encouragement saying I don't know how to help you but I just want you to know I'm rooting for you
Like don't give up
What did it look like today
To have eyes on you in that way
It was
Really empowering
I didn't
It was a very confident in who I was
So Jess
To have
So many people be like we're behind you. It felt really good
To be recognized
A little bit
But at the same time it
Kind of made her
More famously that woman who doesn't
Exist the girl with no identity
And it didn't even solve her problem because when people did offer advice
Didn't really help start working on not paying taxes I'll come to you I got people who just had them ideas of what to do
So you can gain citizenship many of them more marriage proposals
Actually that will help
Some of them not so
Set alarm
Also inside of those emails in comments
There was a conversation about whether what her parents did was right on his from like the opposite perspective
David says her parents didn't quote neglect anything they stood on an exercise their rights and wisely so
What they did was in her best interest she just doesn't understand it because she is young and she's led a protective life a lot of these folks
Spelt like Faith was blowing this
Gifts that her parents
Giving her
From my perspective if you take some of these documents as they exist
I've got hooks in them
This is Alfred Addis
Who blogs about sovereignty and sovereign state
Kristoff
Mystic give you a little bit of a
Evidence that maybe I'm not crazy
There's a case called Chisholm vs. Georgia
41793 they're talking about European jurisprudence
Distinction between the prince
And the subject
And the distinction is that the prince gets his rights from Ghana that's when they say the king is Anointed
Happy message ideas obtained he
Hear meaning within the United States of America after revolution
The sovereignty devolved on the people
And they
Are the truth sovereign
And the word sovereigns is
Alexandra how do you deal with the opening phrase
Raisin in the Constitution which is
We and people not I the person one by one
But we
When it says we the people it means we the sovereign
Are not a collective
You are an idiot we ended up getting into the the little tussle over the world
Government disability
And the car
Tuition but eventually we got back to face
Once you have been recognized as a sovereign
How do you avoid it's like in Redondo long just I want
Judge I don't want blue eyes anymore
If you must part of you must go out and feel a little sorry for her right like she she's got it she has
A
She has a a will to become something other than cousin will to become a subject subject
Yes
So you going to but I don't hear you condemning her
Oh you are condemning her that little bit
Is making a choice
There's Proviso in the Bible where people in the Old Testament if you wanted to remain you could be you could volunteer to be a slave for some guy
Some people don't want to be sovereign
It's not an email I just want a job if you want to work for a living
There are consequences for her abandoning her status as a free woman
Here's the weird irony
Because she has no birth certificate because she has no passport
The state of Texas in the government United States Sabo we can't figure out how to make you visible again
They may not be able to
But then
Face grandmother lives in my district in Sun City and she the government stepped in my grandma was able to
Get in touch with Marsha Farney Marsha Farney state representative
I have house district
She's a republican member of the Texas House of Representatives we would get together I do with my staff and say what are the cause of headache
I come in this week
And this one will really
Caught our attention
So she heard about it she said when you do something about this
And she did
This pill
Is anesthesia
To get
A birth certificate
Around a month after face video went viral Marsha Farney put together a bill and brought it before the House of Representatives in
Standard committee
Already read
About this bill and Bear
Keenly aware
So the bill does a couple things it makes the process logistically easier
Expanded
Where a someone could apply for a delayed birth certificate it was
Punishments for the parents so in the case of Faith right if she asked her parents
For documentation and they refuse then it's punishable by up to a year in jail and up
$4,000 of a fine or a combination of both
Germano bail for Witnesses here who want to testify on this bill during the kind of way
That the various sides High
I'm Lucy Southworth live in Georgetown Texas
And so faith and her aunt and her grandma all went to test
If I face is my granddaughter in my namesake
I was in the room the day she was born
Unfortunate
Her grandma filled in the state reps on what they've been doing the last six months we went to the DPS to get her a driver's license and
They said no they said go to the social
Security people security people said no go to the voter registration p
Meetings and dead-ends and rejection go to the DPS
We were stuck in a do Loop
Well I wasn't going to quit their for goodness sake she's a text
So Marsha Farney has offered us
Our only hope we have had since this started
I just hired you to pass this
Spell
Take face out of limbo
Give her the life she
My view was just like we would not allow a parent
The physically handicapped a child
We should not allow a parent to handicap a child
Where they can't operate and function in society
Although You Seen Her Standing
Anon person
Chicken Walk
Off the face of the Earth
And legally nobody would know
She was gone
I think the bills a little misguided that's James Pennington face dad he came out to the hearing and ended up on the
The Fox 7 news cast
And unfortunately this is the only bit of tape we have of him
Fees for prostitute already there
There are six other
Children seem a little
I think I don't disagree with that does the State of Texas want to put start putting
Aaron's in
Well the bill gives the judge some leeway based on what the circumstances are for the parents
But we we felt there was a need for some teeth to this bill
Duke and it turns out that the Texas
State house and state senate agreed so we were able to get it through the house and the Senate
The bill ended up passing Republicans voted for it Democrats voted for it there's actually only one no vote
But the next time Marshall funny was up for re-election she actually lost in the primaries
And according to the Texas Observer who actually did a really nice podcast if a story
There's this lobbying group called the Texas homeschool Coalition who donated a bunch of money to find his primary opponent
Parental Revenge
Okay well then what's the weirdest videos that leafy
Well because of the bill Faith was able to take her case to a different Court a higher Court
And it seems like the bill allowed the judge to consider different kinds of evidence so in the end Faith with Abel
Will use an old orthodontist record and a piece of paper
From her uncle a doctor
Who had treated her toe back when she was a kid
And in just a couple weeks
This is
Certificate
Sometimes I just take it out and look at it
Sometimes randomly
I know it sucks it's so dumb it's like
I have one too
Can you read it to me a little bit like what's up what information is on here
It has my name at the top and it has like my description
My sex
Where I was born
County
Counting to the singer
I'm hoping that the physical papers
Can like mirror
The emotional thing that she's going through cuz I feel like
It's like a she's getting the papers she's appearing
So that by the time she gets that last one she will know who she is and then she will be that person whoever that is
She's working so hard for it
I'm hoping that
Adjust
That will have developed in her something that she feels like it's more than a piece
You know
I'm hoping
So now Faith
She was actually able to get a driver's license
But she still doesn't have her social security number
Which means you can't get a real job she can't open up a bank account still really
But she can't get health insurance she might not be able to go to college
So
I don't know what's going to happen to her
I remember asking her this question like when this is all over
Do you know who you're going to be
You know
Cuz now this is who you are you're the girl with no identity
And
She was
A little concerned that she wouldn't know who she was going to be
If your if your aunt ask you that same question again like
Who do who do you think you are now who Do You Think You Are
What how would you answer that now
I don't know like
I just feel like me
Like
I'm just
You take to report a producer Alexander young is pieces also produced by Brenna Farrell and Andy Mills and we had
A lot of help from a lot of Texans
I should say
I think I must be texting Savannah Escobar Rachel Coleman David Glenn Chris Van Dusen
Russell Whelen Liberty consultant Nick read the group homeschool alumni reaching out and
The Lake Travis
Zipline Adventure
Speaking of that last one I should say when I went to go visit face in Austin
She's got green hair now she's got
A nose ring and a tattoo when she goes home from time to time and actually visited with her mom on Mother's Day
But when I was there she wanted to do something with me that she's never done before
I'm so excited you guys
So we decided to go zipline
Zippysack
And this one just
Happen to be called
The leap of faith
Davis Jack one last thing before we close
I wanted to let you know that this fall I'm actually going to be
Doing something that I haven't done in the
14 years
I've been working on radio
I'm gonna take a little time off
So you will not hear me
Prisoner hosting this podcast
Through the fall I will be back
Early January
And yeah the reason is very simply that you know
In creating this show and then
Building up and then going
4life
Tours and then most recently creating the spin-off
Hyperspin up more
Perfect a
Just need it's all been incredible by Celine a moment
Catch My Breath
And
To reacquaint my
With my children so I'm going to be doing that
But the great thing is that you know as much as Radiolab
This thing that I started with
Medellin
It's now as you know home to a huge lie
Talented amazing group of people
Ah-So
You'll be hearing more of that mean Robert
My partner-in-crime will be holding it down
But you'll be hearing a lot more Molly Webster
Soarin a lot of
Simon and
The whole crew will be doing stories
Can I have another some pretty amazing stuff coming down the pike and I for one am really excited to be able to listen to it
From the outside
The first time
So yeah
Now we making a few appearances here and there so if you find yourself in like Missoula Montana or
Sydney or Melbourne Australia
Come say hey
Otherwise I will see you in the new year
You have two new messages
Supposed to read some credit I this is Jenny
I'm not sure if
Supposed to leave a message with
Where you at is produced by Dad aboumrad giving teachers are directors
Thorne wheeler is senior editor in New York and a senior producer
I Staffing please
Simon Adler Brenna Farrell David devil not guilty
Robert
Coolidge
Any mcgoohan an email but she's not there Melissa O'Donnell Kelsey Padgett Aryan whack
And Molly Webster Alexandra Lyon
Jackson Road
Hro
I thought Checkers are evil doctor and Michelle Harris
And this message