Hey Radiolab it's Molly Webster
Before you start the episode I have a question for you
Somewhat impolite probably wouldn't ask you this in person question
And that question is
Are you trying
To have a kid
Because if you are
I want to hear from you
So if you are trying
And you be interested in talking to us totally confidentially
You can email us at
Trying
At radiolab.org
And will tell you more
That's trying at radiolab.org
Thanks
Are you awake
Start listening to Radiolab
Radiolab WNYC
Testing one two this the headphones safe
Robert
Radiolab
How could I say
Because I let you go so give me another 20 minutes do I get to talk
Is there a little while back I had a rather live a little less conversation with these two guys first of all like who are you
I'm Larry Bell and I'm Avenue Bell
So you are related in your both in the plumbing business
Are we related
Yes we are related but we are in the home inspection business
Yeah they're father and son at the family business we are the
Principles
Of accurate building inspectors
Brooklyn New York and I've been in the construction in to see evidence I'm about 16 years old I'm 84
Okay I'm not giving my age
I wanted to talk to them because
As building inspectors date there's something they see over and over and over all the time
That is actually a clue
In what turns out to be
Deep mystery
The way that you just what exactly
Well let us say you have a yard in front of your house
You're just back your
Doesn't make in front and right in the middle of the yard is a tree and the tree happens to be
Weeping willow just for example and not too far away from this tree underground there is a water pipe perfectly
Good pipe connecting your house to the main city water line that's in the middle of the street the roots of this tree of course
Can go anyway they want to go then go north south east west whatever
What do you Bells have noticed that even if a tree is
Hand
420 30 yards away from the water pipe
For some reason the tree roots creep
With uncanny regularity straight toward
The water pipe the tree will wrap its roots around that pipe around around around
Doing of spaghetti like almost and each one of those lines of spaghetti
Squeezing
Little bit each one announce announce announce announce announce and eventually over a p
People crack the pipe
Like a nutcracker
You don't see this happening all the time coming up through the pipe into the house
It's amazing that you happen to be the magnolia tree outside of our house got into the sewer pipes
Reached its tentacles into our house
What's the sewage pipe you just happens to a lot of people it's almost as if these plants it's almost as if they know
Where are pipes
I see what's happening
Are you bringing the plant parade again is that what is that what this is crush on you because
The Roots under the ground all connected into a whole Hive you have problems with
Everytime I close my eyes you're coming out of whatever Direction I do I do at the plant parade in a plant biologist
I prayed she's done three experiments
I think I tell you about what she has done you even you
Will be provoked into thinking the plants can do stuff you didn't imagine dream they could
I know I know you I know you
Let's go to the first this is the
Plant and pipe Miss
Hello hello hello you might
Think that the plant sends out roots in every direction one of the richest
Happens to bump into a water pipe and says to send a signal to come over here
Is the water
But that scientist I mentioned my name is Monica research associate professor
The University of Sydney out of the garden
Into her lap
Yeah tasted in my life
That restricted the route so they can only go to one of just two directions
Order water pipe
Or away from the water pipe
What kind of pot is it kind of shaped like the letter Y but upside down
Or the to the right
Got the plants if they were truly dumb they goes if you hit a real friend
But after 5 days
She found that 80% of the time the plants went well maybe chose
To head toward the dry pipe that has water in it so the question is
Appliance that is quite far away from the actual pipe
How does it know which way to turn and grow its roots
So that he can find a warsat
My hypothesis is that what happens in
Where can I can I have a few minutes you got somewhere to go
You got somewhere to go
No good
If she's going to do this experiment
Most likely she's going to use cold water
She's not going to use hot water
Cuz you don't want
Cook your plants
You know
And it's more expensive why waste hot water
How do I establish is it a fact that you're okay but you want to confess
That
The cold water pipe
Causes
Even
Small amount of water to condense
On the pipe itself
On the outside but I kind of like a cold glass sitting on your desk
And it's always a puddle at the bottom of the glass is not broken it's not a leaking water still in there so there is
Some water outside of the pipe is condensation
Right you what they're saying even if you totally seal the pipe so there's no leak
The difference in temperature will create some condensation on the outside
Little bit of moisture that the plant was somehow sense if you look at a root under a microscope
What you see is
Movie Fountains of feelers like hairs on your head
Looking for water every one of them
And all of a sudden one of them I found them and then all the other one direction
Be sensitive hands he argues would probably be able to
Keelback tiny different yes
But Monica says absolutely not
I purposely removed
The chance for most degrading
She made sure that the dirt
Didn't get wet
Because she actually fast in the water pipe
Do the outside of the Potter wasn't touching the dirt at always so the
This branching pot thing
The part where the water pipe was over the pipe is on the outside of the pots right outside
And the plants still went
To the place where the pipe
Was not even in the dark
Estranged
Let me get the vibration of the pie
That's making it go toward it they would have to have no you got some kind of signal different
Traveling through the soil
Monica thought about that and designed a different experiment
Again if you mentioned it depart my experiment to post with the fort
Very different options for our plant
On one side
Instead of a pipe with water she attaches
An MP3 player with a little speaker playing the recording
Sound of water
And then on the other side Monica has another
MP3 player with speaker but this one
Plays
Nothing
So she's got her plants in the pot and we're going to now wait to see what happens remember that the roots of these
These plants can either go
One Direction towards the sound of water in the pipe
Or
The other direction to the sound of
On the fifth day they take a look and discover most
Other routes of majority lyrics were hitting
Chord the sound of water
Exactly
So they just went right for the
MP3
Fake water not even the actual water just the sound of it just the sound
Stetson
I want to plant
Ears
Something
Like they don't have ears
Or a brain or anything like
They couldn't hear like we hear
Well
Baby
They definitely don't have a brain
No questionnaire
But
They do have root hairs
This is Jennifer Frazier vlogger of The Artful amoeba at Scientific American
Possibility that plants can
Do something like here so
What do we have in our ears
That we use
To hear sound
Right
And if you go to too many rock concerts you can break
Keith Harris and that leads to permanent hearing loss
Too bad
So maybe
Root hairs which are always down
Right at the growing tips
A plant root
Maybe plant roots
AR
Like little ears Maybe
Which route is is like a little year for the plant I don't know
That is cool
That is definitely cool
Okay good thing I don't get is is in any animals the hairs inner ear are sending the signals to a boy
Brain and that is what chooses what to do that's true
If a plant doesn't have a brain what is
Choosing where to go think Monica knows the answer to that
But she does believe
Let me know that we humans a little obsessed
Weed the brain
And so we
Oranda decompression oil I would say the conviction
That the brain is the center of the universe
And and if you have a brain and nervous system yuan
Good and you can do amazing stuff
And if you don't run by default you can do much
General okay it's a very biased
View
Humans have in particular
Two words others
But still I mean
To say that a plant
Choosing a Direction
I don't know I mean it
La quina planta
It bends toward sunlight we've all seen houseplants
Would you say that the plant is
Seeing the sun now I mean it's just it's it's
Reacting to things and there's a series of mechanical
Behaviors inside the plant that are just
Bending in the direction to meet couldn't it just be like that
Fair and I think if I move on to the next experiment from Monica
You're going to find it a little bit
Harder to objective we need to take a break first but when we come back the parade that I want you to join will come and see
Swoop you up
The carry you along in
Floating Visio
Hi this
This is Ashley Harding
St John's Newfoundland Canada
Reason lab is supported in part by the elf
Four-piece loans
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology
In the modern world
More information about Sloane @www
Sloan.
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents
Aunts and uncles teachers about what we're calling
Tiny moments of brilliance
Basically I want to hear about those times when I kids you know did something
It just means you bring back and say whoa
Maybe it was the moment that I
I kid you've been reading to 4 month started reading back
To you
Or maybe the kid was a piano
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of their musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed are ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the
Epic moments where
A kid does something super smart
It doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story
T-shirt with us
Go to radiolab.org
Flash brilliance
Record short audio message
And that's radiolab.org
Splash brilliant
Thank you so much
321 Chad Robert Radiolab so today we have a triptych of experiments about plants that apparently
Jury still out
Are going to make me rethink my stance on Plants experiment to now
Are we now that is correct
So
We are going to meet
A beautiful little plant called a mimosa pudica with a perfectly symmetrical plant with
With leaves on either side of a central stem
Eggplant I get so many signs
Centuries
Because
Peculiar plant has a surprising little
A reflex
An anti
Predator reaction
Like a defensive mechanism as soon as it senses that are grazing animal is nearby
If a nosey deer happens to bump into it the mimosa plant
Sleeves
Curls all its leaves up against its stem
The whole thing immediately closes up and makes it look like
There's no plans here
Justin
Boring set of twigs
Nothing delicious
At all
So do you like a Nobel
Nevermind
Right
And you can actually see this happen so
So
Mimosa pudica
Can get anybody can get one of these pants on and we did
And if you just
Patrick even just one leaf that
You can actually watch this Kaskade
Believe closing
Yeah sort of
Startling to see
ETSU UT
So that voice belongs to a Tish Bachelorette who is with Princeton University's Council on science and technology
We should one of these plans to him and a couple of his colleague Sharon Dela Cruz
And Peter landegren
Because he wanted them to help us
Recreate Monica's neck
Experiment
Okay
Could you just described it just briefly just what you did
Well I created these
Horrible
Contraption apparently she built some sort of apparatus
I guess you could call it a
Mimosa plant
Dropbox
Picture one of those parachute drops if they have it there
State fairs or amusement parks where your who stood up to the top except in this case
Instead of a chair
They got a little
Plant size box
Into which she put these sensitive plants
Monica
Drop them
Just about you
Seven or eight in London very comfortably
Padded face made of foam
So no plans with actually hurt
Cindy's experiment
But the drop was just shocking and sudden enough for the little plant do
Close all
Leaves
What's reflex defense
Ben Monica oyster plant back up again and dumps it again
And again
Allegan
And after not all who want to drop
The plant
She noticed
Stop
Closing its leaves
So after the first few the plants already realized that that was not necessary
The plants
The plant stop
What is it.
Hope they stop folding up
She thinks that they somehow remembered all those drops and it never hurt so they didn't pull up anymore they've learned some
Exactly which is pretty amazing
You couldn't just be at
An entirely different interpretation here
Like what the plants
Have to keep pulling the leaves up and they just
Retired
They run out of energy exactly it's a costly process for
But
Figured out they weren't
Because after dropping them 60 times
She then
Left right
It would close up so
It's not that it couldn't. It's just during the dropping it learned
Let it didn't need to
Yeah
That's a
Learning is something I didn't think plants could do
They do
Hi-Tech
So we pick him up if it's this easy and this matter of fact we should be able to do this ourselves and see it for ourselves
So
That's really split the scientist from Princeton come in theaters Sheridan
They design from scratch
Parachute drop in
Blue translucent Lego pieces
Plant rapper and we can move it up
And we can drop it
Don't we just wrapped in our mimosa plant little she felt for him
Down and then
Account
And then we Let It Rock
Dropped
Five four
3 and we dropped it once and twice
Again
And again
We waiting for the
Restraint
Stop both we drop
We drop
You didn't happen
It was curling every time when it every time it just kept curly and curly
So you can replicate what you saw it happened so we went back to my life as you know built
Your elevator
We did what happened to you didn't happen to a. Can you can you imagine what
We did wrong
Example my plants role in environment control room switch
Is Not A Minor Details then the no experience in extra changes oil
For example I don't know if that was the case for your plan
No I doubt I'll be kept switching room cuz we weren't sure whether you wanted to be in the Highlight or week later
One light or no light it was my baby too much
The Wizard of Oz
The movie the plants correctly responded by not opening
Because something really mad what's happening around it and it's like
This place is not safe
Atlantic on this point
She's got a
CiCi's right one time the plant literally flew out of the pot and upended with r
Roots Exposed on humanitarian
The be kind of proved our point we were so inconsistent so clumsy that the plants were smart
To keep playing it safe
Can closing themselves up
That's a very successful your experiments you found exactly what the plans would do under your shirt
Circumstances
Cardinal saib more
Tumultuous the mine
And she goes on to argue that we've been a little bit more steady and little bit more consistent
The plants would have
And would have remembered the last
Because what she does next 3 days later she takes these plants back into the lab
Just to see like
The difference between the first time you learned something in the next time they figured out faster this time or maybe
Slower
So she takes a plan
She puts them into the parachute
She drops
And she says this time they relaxed almost immediate
They'd remember straight away straight away
All of them
No ready what to do
They remember what it happened three days before the dropping dinner that they didn't have to fold up
So they didn't
And then she waited a few more days I came back they still remember
Yeah
Few more days
Yeah and it was almost like
Eventually she came back after
Unidays 28 days
Yes and they still remain
Are they still did not close when she dropping that's what she says
What was your reaction when you saw this happen that's pretty sure
Retention of
Of knowledge my reaction was
That was my reaction
Because the only reason why this perriman
Turn out to be 28 days it's because I ran out of time
So did they might remember even
How much longer time than 28 days
So she saying they remembered for almost a month
Can you remember what you were doing now I actually like even this morning I'm at that's already gone
Supposing that she's right
Where would the aloe plant even store a memory
That's what I asked her I do want to go back there too
Support for something like learning
Like I don't understand
Learning as far as I understand it is something that involves memory and
Storage but I do that in my brain that's the place where I can remember thing
In my brain
Yes I do is a bro I think
Is your daughter came to my house
Picasso and I forgot now
Sorry
Actually Monica's dog leaves
Perfectly into her third experiment which
Again will be with a plant but it was originally done with with
IDOC so Pavlov
Started by getting some dogs
And some meat Annabelle
The kind of the standard
And his idea was to see if he could
Condition needs
To associate
That food would be coming
From sound of a bell
So he brought them some meat
And then eat the meat then
He would bring them to meet and he would ring a bell
And again drooling eating
And he would repeat this
Ring
Meet
Eat
Ring
Meat eater
Ring meat
Finally
One time
He did not bring the meat but he rang the bell
Turn off the dogs begin to droop they had learned to associate the sound of the Bell Witch
Nothing to do with me when they actually saw and smelled and 8B
Exactly
Animals do this experiment but
It got Monica thank you
Buddha plant
The same plant learn to associate something totally random like a bell
With something
It wanted like food
Are you like aggressively looking around for like you wake up in the mornings and now what can I get a plan to do that rhyme
Reminds me of my dog reminds me of a bear
Reminds me of Abby
No really
Lucifer I feel I feel this is the kind of good
Society
I don't do that
But Monica says what she does do is move around the world with a general feeling of
What if
So she decided to conduct lyrics
Pretty much like at the concept of Pablo with
He's dog applied but instead of dogs she had pea plants in the dark
And for the meat substitutes you gave each planned
Little bit of food in this case of little blue
LED light
Light is obviously representing dinner if you if you shine light on the plant you're like feeding it
Real I'd like to know that
I need light to grow so
Otherwise account
So for three days three times a day she would Chinese little blue lights
The plants
From upper to
Particular direction
And she noticed that unsurprisingly the plants would always grow towards the light
Endo knows that the salivation equivalent was
The tilt of the plant except
And then I needed
The difficult
August of this payment was
To find something
Being that will be
Quite irrelevant
And really meant
Nothing
To the plant
To start with
Liza Bell for the dog
So after much trial and error with
Clicks and hums and buzzes
Randomness
That the one stimulus that would be
The perfect was
A fan
A little fan the same one that are used in
Computers light
Yunnan very tiny
She determined that you can pick a little computer finkelman
But we're going to keep them for pretty much ever
Utterly indifferent to the whole
The plants don't replace the fan right next
So that
Coming from the
Same Direct
These two stimuli she put the plants
Little pea plant
What's 2 a kind of training
Little fan goes on
Light goes on of aiming at the people from the same direction and the people and leans toward
Then she takes a little light and the little fan and move them to the other side of the plant turns the fan on
Betway
Light after Fender moved around always matched in the same way
Together fan by Clean
Fanfight Lee fan lightning
Same as the type of the beldam eating the television
The doggo you do not play the stand for
For the plant
We know now for the dogs the dogs
He's expecting
Predicting something to arrive
If it was only the fan
Would the plant anticipate the light and lean toward it
Be going random
After three days of this training regime it is now time
The plants with
Justify
No light
Chuck Monica moves the fans
The new place where
On
And the pea plants are left alone
Quiet
Darkroom
Feeling the breeze
And then
The next day
Are the uni on a Sunday afternoon goes into that
Darken room with all the people at
So you know I mean the dark she's got a little red headlamp
Yeah she moves about the room
Tearing down
Plants under the red glow over head lamp
And then I
Stop
The these little plants
My Little Pony
Indeed
Turn and move
Toward the fans catching up their little leaves as if they were sure that if any moment now light would arrive
A scooter was Sunday and I remember it was Sunday because I study
Discriminant
Stop my plants
There's no one here on Sunday afternoon
How can spin my head off your phone
Oh my God
These guys are at
She doing it so course that was the only the beginning then
We actually had to run four months of Trials to make sure that you know that what we were seeing
Was not one p doing out two piece but it was actually a majority
So you just
Did what problems did to a plant you got the
Plant tours
Associated
Fan with food
Yeah
But once again I kind of wondered
Since the plant doesn't have a brain or even neurons
To connect the idea of light and wind or whatever that weird would they put that information
How can a plant
How do you do that
I don't know
I don't know yet
But what I do know is that defensive line doesn't have a brain descendants
Doesn't
A priori
Today's date
The plants can do something
Dependent humans do it enough
It doesn't mean that everyone needs to do it in that way to be able to do it in the first
Multiple ways of doing one thing
So we're really like this is
We're really at the very beginning of this
Yeah I know
This weather is often more questions than answers
This part of the
Define as well
Monica's work is actually gotten quite a bit of attention
The mother plant
Yes and some of them this is Lincoln taste
Professor emeritus
Biology at UC Santa Cruz stay there very curious but want to see these experiments with
Repeat it's very interesting experiment
I really want to see whether it's correct or not lead us to
He's got lots of questions about her research methods but really his major complaint is
Is her language are use of metaphor
Write example words
Like hearing or learning behavior and this is not a huge fan
Yes if you get
Too wrapped up in your poetic metaphor you're very likely
To be misled
And to over interpret the data
It's a kind of Romanticism I think you know
It goes back to
Anthropomorphizing
Plant Behavior
I wonder if
Her using these metaphors
Is
Perhaps a very creative way of looking at
Looking at a plant and therefore leaves her to make
Make up these experiments that those who wouldn't think the way she would whatever makeup and therefore she might
Indian see something that no one else would
What sea is it
Pictures of metaphors letting in the light as opposed to shutting down the volume
Just started like going off the deep end their butt
Maybe it makes her sort of more open-minded than
And then somebody just looking at a note
I think you could be open-minded but
Still objective
I think there's something to that I I think
There are some cases
Swear
Romanticizing something could possibly
Lead you
Some interesting results to your like a a metaphor cop with a Milky
Yes that would be an interesting.
How much longer cuz I have an appoint
Home inspectors Alvin and Larry ubell
We thought maybe we should run this metaphor idea by then
There's on the science side there's a real suspicion of anything that's anthropomorphizing it
I just don't like
To hear words like mine or hear or see or taste for a plan because it's too animal into
Too Human
And the classic case of this is what you go back up
A few centuries ago someone
Notice that plants have sex
Oh yes that there was a kind of a moral objection to thinking of this
And I'm wondering whether
Monica is going to run into as she tries to make plants more animal-like
Whether she's just going to run into this malice
From the scientific
You sure any of them know I don't
Because
She may come up against the
People who think that
Intelligence is unique to humans
And so I don't have a problem with that I've been looking around lately and I know that intelligence
Is not unique to humans okay
So I don't have an issue with that
And everyday that goes wanna have less of an issue from the day before
So I don't have a problem.
The problem is
Is
With plants what they may have this
Intelligent
Maybe we just not smart enough
Figure it out
Well okay that's a Pareto
Let's
Do it
Big things to ask your sponsor to Sharon Dela Cruz and to Peter Lander going to Princeton University Council on science and
Allergy
Also thanks to Christy Melville and emerald O'Brien and Andres O'Hara and to summer rain
You thinking Summer Rae
Did the plants need that one in
The summer is a real person and her last name
To be spelled a y n e
This story was nurtured and fed and ultimately produced by Annie McEwen she actually trained the story and rather elaborate Express
Middle set up
To move away from the light
A light Breeze
Against
Thinx
I want nothing thanks to Jennifer Frazier help us make sense of all this you should definitely go out and check out her Blog The Artful amoeba
Especially to the post the forlorn one
About plants
Plants
Are really
Underrated
When I write a blog post
My post
They get the least traffic guaranteed are the plant pose
No matter how amazing I think that the results are
For some reason people just don't think plants
Are interest
And
Timmy
It's your three more reasons that you can say no really
Plants are amazing
And this world is amazing and that living creatures have this ability
4 reasons why
Don't understand can't comprehend yet
That's amazing and fantastic
Does it change my place in the world is it
Retina eye
Sense of myself
My place is a human that a plant can do this no does it threaten your sense of humanity
That you depend for pretty much every single calorie you can eat on them
So you think that this
You think this is a hubris correct
What so they can't move
Well
Some of them can first of all and
Big deal
Can you make your own food
Play the message press to start of message
My name is Jennifer Fraser
Are you Belvin Avenue valve accurate building inspector
Sound design
Maria
Attessa
Maria Madison
David gamble the Bell
Gable
David gamble happy
Tracy hunt not guilty
Annie McEwen
Amanda ironic
A friendly reminder have you hugged your husband today
And this message