Quick note this story contains some profanity
Junior couple
No just know that before we get going
Are you awake
Listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
Hey I'm Jared I'm Robert Radiolab and today we are going to start with a producer
Let's just go back to San Francisco on a particular day at a particular time
Killer Women hello is this Sarah Jane
Yes it is woman named Sara Jane Moore Sarah Jane
What day was September 22nd the particular time 1975
It's a Monday morning was a nice day I don't remember anything different so I assumed it was a nice day
You know in my own head
Surgeon
Not on this Monday morning
She wakes up early drops or nine-year-old off at school runs a few errands
Then she drives downtown to this
This big fancy hotel what was the name of the hotel
I'm 87 years old don't expect
But at any rate you know I parked in a parking garage across
Right across from the hotel is a park but there's a
Parking garage underneath
Walk every walk across the street that there were sidewalks on both sides of the street
There were people on both sidewalks
She joins the crowd across the street from the hotel was very crowded couple thousand people it's like a big scene and there was
Barrier a rope barrier right
Keeping us back on the sidewalk
And my plan has always been to be back in the crown
You know what I was dressed like every other middle-aged woman that was there so I don't remember what you were wearing
Temperature there
Older pictures of it yes I was wearing I was wearing slacks that was
That was at the beginning of winter
Natural for women to wear slacks
I had a coat on
And I was carrying a purse and I went back into the middle of the crowd
I had planned to do anyway
I thought a man come up against man
Socializes I wasn't that day and time I spun around to Slappy's face
She see this guy there big strong guy blond hair look at him and realize that it was
He had not done anything out of the ordinary that
I turn back around
And I went on about my business
I was in pushed up
Crowd pressure was such I tried to stay back in the ground
But I got pushed up almost on to the ropes in the front
Write up on the curb of the sidewalk
Why do I not plan to be
And he apparently was still right behind me
So maybe he was pushed out by the crowd also
And so Sarah Jane is just crammed into the
Crowd and she's just standing there
Going about doing what I set out to do
So
She waits
And she waits
And an hour goes by and two and three and then finally
Out of the hotel comes none other than the president of the United
United States Gerald Ford that he has
Police and Secret Service they're all coming to walking out of the hotel to get in his car which was parked there on the street
But he sees the crowd Sarah Jane actually says he looks directly at her
And
Waves
He waves to the crowd and everyone starts
Applauding and cheering
Now
Right at that moment
Sarah Jane
Regis her right hand
Into her purse and
Pulled a gun out of my purse
A 38 caliber revolver
Cox it and then she takes aim right at Gerald Ford's head
And then
Mr. Ford did not fall
For chips the wall behind him Ford
Freezes in place Sara Jean never plan to take a second shot
And still in the air holding the gun looking over the smoking barrel of the gun and she's got enough time if you wanted
But before she can take that second shot the blond man behind her lunges
Grabs her gun arm pulls it down and deflect it for just that crucial second
50 police officers nearby need to get to her the tackle her they take our guns and the pentagram
So I couldn't move and buy that points the secret service has whisked off the president into the limousine and I was in
Immediately picked up and carried across the street
Into the hotel
Arrested
And eventually
Cheap went to prison and she served 32 years in prison and then
And then after that was released on parole
And then we talked to her
Weihai
God prepared
To be told the first-person narrative from the perspective of someone who's about to be president that was not what I was expecting
I was hoping that weight can you explain know why it is she decided to shoot the night
Never fully explained that and when I asked her what this is not
She was like I'm not going there this is not an interview about
What was driving me or about what I did or why did it this is an interview about mr. simple
Sipple Oliver Sipple the random blonde guy who just happened to be
Standing next to Sara Jane Moore that date the guy who grabbed her arm and save the president's life and T-Pain
Dearly for that I actually called up Sarah Jane and had her tell that whole story because I was actually interested in what
What happened to Oliver Sipple after that because had he not
Reached out and put his hand on my arm
None of this would have happened to him
Wait what happened to him
So Oliver Sipple actually died in 1989 but
Before we go to destroy I just want to give you a picture of the guy
So
Just Google search Oliver Sipple Ford or something
Wait okay wait I see the picture
Muscular guy kind of blond hair he's at he's at
He's a
He's a handsome guy yeah he's a he's a little bit James Dean
And Marlon Brando had a baby, or something all American
We're bringing in another All-American for the story Daniel Lutzer editor at
Oxford University press
And a few years ago
Probably more than 5 years ago I wrote
An article
About Oliver Sipple
Anyway to get back on track September 22nd 1975
Sara Jane Moore fire snapshot Oliver Sipple grabbed her arm the police
Russell Moore to the ground in a police actually grab Oliver to pull them inside the hotel the question is
Initially some confusion about what he was doing there and some thought that you know he might have been a suspect
So he's in this hotel trying to light a cigarette but
He just couldn't do it because he was shaking so hard
Oliver had served very rough tours in Vietnam
Loud noises Woods would make him very unhappy I think this is the sort of thing we might call poster
Traumatic stress disorder now
But when eventually Oliver started to calm down the Secret Service were like
What are you even doing here it's kind of hard to answer because it's like didn't even really knows like
And I just bumped into this
Huge crowd of people asked what was going on people like oh like Gerald Ford is going to be here any other the president is going to
So he said he thought I might as well see him
And then he was standing there for a couple hours until he saw a flash of metal realized it was a gun reacted quickly
Instinctively and then
You guys all put me in here
Can you be here
So cute question for 3 hours he goes home
Don't is 4th floor walk-up
And there's a reporter that waiting for him
My butt
He just wants to
Serta be left alone and he told this reporter quote
I'm a coward I don't know why I did it it was the thing to do at the time
And isn't even after that he just keeps getting phone calls from reporters and then some of them
Learned that he was a marine until they would ask him questions like oh was it your
You know what that your training is that why you did this heroic thing but he said like
Oh you know listen don't mention of any of that stuff about the Marines you know I got to keep that Under Wraps
I'm no hero or nothing
But
The next day after day
Contra game deflected by an ex-marine
Vietnam veteran named Oliver Sipple television
Ex-marine to flex weapon is woman shoots
That's the LA Times Chicago Tribune
Sero tells how we deflected woman's arm and
Despite his best efforts Oliver becomes a national hero for a day
Appears that he sort of thought that would be yes
Maybe his friends would give him a pat on the back like I'm a couple rounds and then you know over the next couple days at all
Ulcerative like Ripple out of control
Because that very same day that Oliver was being painted as a hero this guy named herb Kane the long
Long time San Francisco
Columnist walked into his office and on his answering machine
Work to message
Saying
Hey that guy Oliver Sipple the hero who saved the president's life
Is gay
Was he
Was he out what he was sort of out and
Sort of Na
What does it mean
Well 2
Explain you got understand this
Particular time and place
So let's
Just
Take a Magic Carpet Ride
Close your eyes
And
Let the sound take you away
Tolerated that's why San Francisco sometimes labeled with a slide caption Queen City of the West
San Francisco was one of the first cities in America have a gay pride
My Parade in the 70s boys go to bed with boys and girls are better than girls and
Forget people San Francisco was like this Shelter From The Storm many of us were immigrants from somewhere
10 male long time San Francisco resident
Kansas
Escaped from Kansas
Because
What the West
Offered was the Ethereal promise if you will of reinvention
You could cross the line in which your past
Stay behind you
It was a place where you could be out but to the people you left behind you can still be in
So a super Oliver you know he came from Michigan from a working-class family I had a lot of brothers and sister
Can use one of the eight children
And he was perfectly open about his sexual orientation and would tell anybody who asked that he was a gay man
But you know you never told his family
Until Oliver lived like a lot of gay people is a time this
Double life and do we know that this is the reason why I said mechanic San Francisco or was there a difference
Harvey Milk is there
The Harvey Milk you know famous gay activist
San Francisco politician he was friends with Harvey Milk
A New York
An immigrant from New York turns out Oliver had actually met Harvey a decade earlier New York
I just want to mention this because it's so cool the time they actually dated the same guy who was the
The inspiration for Sugar Plum Fairy sugar
In Lou Reed Walk on the Wild Side
Just a fun fact just a fun fact
That's it but
Oliver Harvey they were pretty good friends
They correspond it's in touch when they lived in different places in the country IP Harvey even loans Oliver money sometimes cuz
Oliver didn't have a job
You know Collective disability from his time in the Marines but
Anyway
By the beginning of the 70s
When Oliver got to San Francisco reconnected with an old friend Harvey was shall we say evolving into the hue
Huge figure their butt gay public figure
I'm just thinking like one of the things we were talking about on the phone was about sort of the
The kind of two different
Schools are no different the Segway to that
Other I would say older but other generation
Okay
Mostly men
Was that
They were content to go to tea with the mayor or public official of some kind
Wearing jackets and ties really weren't
Shall we say
Activist
Because according to Ken the activism came
When in the late sixties early seventies that young gay men and women who came out of the
Vietnam War protests
Into the world
Take a look around
Discomfort or fear
The police are still rating bars
One of them and said we're faget we're going to beat the s*** out of you sending that affect how we going to kill you
Violently in
And non-violent
They knock me down and
Started beating me with their hands in their feet their elbows
Try to muffle my screams
And
After a while a body of people get to a point where they just
Will not take
Depression anymore
So in came the activist like harbin ponytail mustache
Banker turned hippy you know you lying you know you're changing the statements around he was very outspoken
Behind it very militant to Harvey
A person should have the right to say gay people with living in a half life opportunity
I am gay that is a part of society. Not being able to be who they were
Must
Does it is you must tell your immediate family
You must tell your relatives
You must tell your friends if indeed they are your friends you must tell your neighbors you must tell them
People your work with you must tell the people in the stories you shopping
Once you do you will feel so much better
And so
Cut back to September 22nd 1975
In a blink of an eye Oliver civil becomes this
Hero
And that same night Oliver spread Harvey
Sears about all this news
And
Consensus
Wait maybe there's an opportunity
So he picks up the phone and calls
Columnist herb Kane
A very very well-known well-loved
Gossip columnist isn't there so milk leaves a message on his answering machine
And he basically says what
I'm
A friend of Oliver symbols I've known him for years Oliver Sipple worked on my
Campaign for supervisor
So basically with without
Sipple's consent
Harvey outage
Milk out of them
What was Harvey Milk thinking that you do this
Well for Harvey
Stereotypes the lies the innuendos of gay people as limp-wristed and drag queens and stuff
Distortions
Okay people to travel us
Ears
True gay hero us square-jawed heroic Marine seem to be
Sort of like regular like red-blooded American
I'm so hard reset and this was written down by his biographer of coding
It's too good an opportunity
For once we can show that days do heroic things
Not just all that caca about molesting children and hanging out in bathroom
What's the difference between no no no no you got to ask the guy for you can just do that
Harvey just did it
Really
Yeah he just did it
Chicane
The next morning Kane arrives at his office
He listens to the message
Teen tries to call simple but he can't reach him
But there was another guy who is a gay activist his name was
The Reverend Ray broshears
He was the head of what's called what was called the lavender Panthers
And he also independently
Called
Herb team to say
Oh that guy Oliver Sipple ever I'm talking about on the news
Yeah so you got to
Independence vs both of people who said that they were
Friends with Cybill
And that he
Was gay
And
Can I think this was juicy
This was a juicy thing
And
He
Go back and get this
So two days after the assassination attempt
Canes call him comes out and the way that he wrote it up this is the precise paragraph
What are the heroes of the day Oliver Billy Sipple the ex-marine who grabbed Sarah Jane Moore's arm processor gun was fire
Tired and thereby may have saved the president's life
Was the center of midnight attention at the Red Lantern a Golden Gate Avenue Bar he favors
Reverend Ray broshears
Head of Helping Hand Center and gay Politico Harvey Milk
Who claimed to be among simple close friends
Describe themselves as
Proud maybe this will help break the stereotype
And then that day this guy named Darryl Lemke
Left
Lembke these hurricanes column
The office of the Los Angeles Times
I was a reporter for the LA Times in San Francisco and
So
My office told me
Got an interview with Oliver Sipple
But really quickly before we get there
We actually managed to find a recording of this very specific interview
In the Allie X collection at the Huntington Library in Los Angeles and M
It's the reason they hung onto it was cuz it was
Controversial
So the night that came this article comes out Daryl goes to Oliver's house
Oliver's there are two reporters from The Sentinel were there also
That right there is Daryl
Venezuela
The girl sitting in Oliver's living room and end with the reporters are wondering is
Have you heard from the president before husband doesn't bother to thank him at that point
Present an award
What they call
Medals of freedom
Top streaming apps
Arthur
Never have me brought back to the White House
Would you like to meet me
Voice right there
That's
Oliver
You didn't have time to meet you back
Have you heard from the mayor
I'm at the number
I heard only from the press and porters and
Reporters and pressing that should have been hard
You have access
Okay can we go on background
Yeah
For some reason
San Francisco Police Department
Is now
Inquiries about you
The sex crimes
Gmail
Something Oliver should know because
This is against at a time when these sumption was that all gay men were just
Pedophiles
Pervert
I want to set background this is information that cannot be sent
Oh God Colin Kaepernick
Daryl actually asked if he can call somebody and ask about it
No I don't want
What you want
Ask you why the number
Who's the guy to talk to
Lochmere Sullivan
Or
Daryl called local authorities but he can't get ahold of anyone
Robinson
Do you have any sex crimes on your record
Never had a sex event in mind that either been arrested mugshot would being drunk a couple
Is number in Rhode Island
Are there casinos
Recorder goes off
Comes back on
Well who do I call with some Authority
Police depart
And now all of his on the phone with the police department
Detective Allen
Yeah well my name is Oliver Sipple
I'd like to know why I've been turned over to your department sex crimes and missing person
This is my yes
Best director
Yes I'd like to know
Bunch of breast came over without a bunch of
This afternoon
And they said they were trying to get some information about
Police Department
And I was turned over
Sexy
What the hell is going on
OIC
God I mean I said what the hell is going on
I tried to call the mayor's office just now and I tried to call the chief of police office just now
What the Sam hell is going on
Okay thanks a lot.
Yeah
Just the opposite.
With the assassination
Assassination
In that department that's all
That's why
Stop making sense
You got me really shut up young man
Just about to go downtown and whip some ass somewhere
We find out
Now
The reason is Tampa so controversial is because according to Oliver before the interview began before the you know
Recorder started rolling
He had said to the reporters from The Sentinel
Okay I'm going to talk to you guys about my sexuality
But then she had said to Daryl
I don't want you to write anything about that
I don't I don't want that International Paper
Daryl says he doesn't remember that
But then
Right here in this interview
This thing happens where Darryl says
I'll make one more try on the gate
You don't want to change
You don't want to change your mind on that
No
I just don't want to change them
Very popular saying homosexuality has nothing to do with it
I'm calling and saying that
If I were a homosexual I was not even cook me or not
It doesn't make me any less of a man than what I
But I think they have nothing to do
React
Rancho
So I don't think you took anything
Eventually
Okay
Interview ends and
Daryl says
Is that when he left that interview he felt like when I came to all of her sexuality don't want to be quoted
That was it like just don't
Quote me on it
But still I was trying to report from all sides about us
The big side for me was
That he was a hero on this
The president of States was very slow on the take
I'm psyching him for saving his life
Darryl thought that
Oliver sexuality the fact that he was gay might have something to do with that because
Just seven months earlier
On March 6th Sergeant Leonard matlovich disclosed to a supervising officer at Langley Air Force Base in Virginia
That he was a homosexual
I wanted to stay in the Air Force
Is Air Force Sergeant named Leonard matlovich
Who had the Purple Heart had the Bronze Star he comes out that he's gay
Annie's kicked out of the Air Force
In conversation
My account
Minority group
No more America
And now you've got this former Marine saved the president's life and it's
2 days later he still hasn't heard from the president
Tilt for Darrell even though Oliver had said don't make this about my sexuality I still thought it was it was a no
National story and it was
Pretty hard to ignore it after a hurricane and started the ball rolling
So that night after the interview Darrell calls in his
Story to the LA Times office
And he uses this
Raise
He said to Oliver's of former Marine who was quote
Prominent figure in the gay community
Put it down always the story with the rewrite guy put it in the lead really made it the big thing
And so
3 days after the assassination attempt
Ble X run the story with the headline
No call from president
0 in Ford shooting active among SFGate
And the only times
New service
And so Daryl story it goes
I mean it goes everywhere
Another strange twist to the story headlines are like
Score
Homosexual hero been reported that the ex-marine who deflected misses more shot on Monday
Is well known in San Francisco is gay activist circles
And so it was not just running in Los Angeles it's also running in Chicago it's raining in Dallas
It's running in Indianapolis and it's running
You know of all places
In
Oliver Sipple hometown
In Detroit
I guess what I'm wondering is if you have a guy who says
Please don't talk about this it has nothing to do with what I did yesterday
Shouldn't that play some role in what you decided to write or not to be
Well
You don't know your news sources
Are always
Reluctant to talk
So I guess I
Took it as much
Duty
Pick up that angled specially such as Bob the president of the United States
Right
But if you were to do it all over again would you do anything differently
I don't know
Taken into
Call baby
The potential harm
Second
I don't know if I do it over again or not
But
Not able to turn back the clock for something like that
Clock marches
Forward after the break
My name is jazz Adam
I'm calling from Los Angeles
Radiolab is
Supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloane @www.
Slovo.org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help this summer I'm hosting
And I request for those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
We're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments
Brilliance basically I want to hear about those times when I kid you know did something
It just means you lean back and say whoa how did they do that
Maybe it was the moment that our kids you've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons and you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin
Maybe the kids in math class you noticed are ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the
Specific moments where
A kid does something super smart but it doesn't have anything to do with the test
If you have a story please share it with us
Go to radiolab.org Brilliance and record a short audio message for us
And that's where you're at. Org / brilliance
Thank you so much
This is Radiolab
We're back with the story of Oliver Sipple from reporter producers lot of Nasser
Saudi assassination attempt was on Monday
And on Thursday
Simple and his lawyer
Call a Preston
Well I think you all know this is Oliver Sipple and saved the president's life and he has a prepared statement on a subject that's
Appeared
Rest
Today
In the past few days I have been asked many questions having to do with my sexual
Preferences too wet
I've been asked whether or not I am gay or homosexual
This is
There is
This is my reply
To the line in question
First reason
You are
Interested in my In Me Is
The Shack
The woman who tried to shoot the president
Play I'm sorry I'm so nervous excuse me
This is a handwritten statement and he's having a little difficulty rockstad in order to get it to you
Afternoon
Using your interest
The fact that I
Oh okay I couldn't get the words
Drink
My sexual orientation has nothing at all to do with
Saving the president's life
Just as the color of my eyes
Or my race has nothing to do with what happened in front of the Saint Francis Hotel on Tuesday
Bisexual
Bisexuality
Is a part of mine
Private life
And I have not I have no
And has no
And has no bearing on my
Response
Do the ACT
Of a person
Take me to take the life of another
I'm first and foremost a human being who enjoys
And respect life
I feel that
A person
Person
Worth is
Determined by how
He or she
Response to the world
In which they live
Not on how or what
Or with whom a private life
Is Cher
He basically says like stop stop
Macy's canvas simple as that
Makes the whole thing I mean so much more
Personal
Finally actually was the very reason that Oliver
Call the press conference in the first place
I want you to know that my mother
Told me today
But she could not walk
Out of her front door or even go to church
Because of the pressures
He fails because of the press
Stories
Concerning my sexual orientation
Actually I never
Anticipated
Interference with my family's
Relationship when she died
When I supposedly say the president's life Oliver would later say that when he was talking on the phone with his mother
She said to him
I don't
Want to speak to you ever again
And she hung up on him
And also hung up
Did you call him uncle uncle Oliver
Yes I called the macabre
Yep this is George Sipple Junior all of his nephew
She told me that
Look at all these families stayed in Detroit
Albers two brothers and his dad work together in an auto plant
They all work for General Motors in the stories that I've heard is that
Today after Oliver saved the life of President Ford they walked in and everyone wanted to like buy them a beer
You know everybody on the factory floor
Was congratulating them patting them on the back you know your brother's hero your son's a hero
When you know when they would take their their shift break and this is the old days right they take a shift break and they go to the bar and
Everybody wanted to like buy them a round of drinks
So then the news comes out at whatever I did couple of days later that
Adhesive
Gay Marine
And
There's teasing on the
On the factory floor
Yeah
Yeah and George says
What happened is reporters back in Detroit
Sort of descended on Oliver parent
To get more of the story until they kept
Knocking on my granny
Other store
And she apparently told them to go away
I guess neighbors were harassing her she thought the media was harassing her
My grandmother just said I don't want to deal with it and so don't don't come knock on the door leave us alone
They just wanted to go away and we'll go back to their
Reno private lives
No one of the things that I found
Actually after talking to George wear these interviews done with all of her family after the news broke that Oliver was gay
And there's just
Call I just want to read you this one particular Passage
Have you talked to any other members this is from George F Sipple Whois
Oliver Sipple brother
Have you talked to any other members of your family since September 1975 about Oliver
I mentioned it once to my father
Question and what was his response what did he say
If you can remember
I was on afternoons. And I had seen him because I had come in early
Mention the fact
Did the next person that even said he had a son named Oliver
He was going to literally break their dam neck
Wow so his dad was like
His brother talking about his dad's react
And he told me quite clearly in two letter words
Just forget you got a brother
And I let him alone
Never
Anticipated such
Interference with my family's
Relationship with chine
When I supposed to be saved the president's life
This is all I have to say on this subject
Thank you very much ladies and gentlemen any questions and go to
Minister to my lawyer
Like asking a question like this
What would you what would you like to see
I don't know I'm just embarrassed
I know you have to go and see a doctor over this and I'm very emotional
I feel very sorry for my family too.
Can you tell us the story of the letter I wish I would have brought it
I do have it but I didn't bring it today
The same day is that press conference
Which is 3 days after the assassination attempt Gerald Ford actually did write a letter
To Oliver Sipple which was then released publicly its a nice letter it's White House stationery White House envelope
It's basically
Ford telling my uncle that
You know he's
Thankful to him for this
Heroic deed and
He signed it Jerry Ford witch
I've been told that Gerald Ford
Sign
Different ways
So if you signed Jerry Ford
It meant something it was like a personal touch
Listen to other chapter where your uncle
Says
Set to the president I guess rights found it we found a letter we found a letter in the Gerald
Ford Library it's from your uncle to the president
Wowhead
Yeah
I did not I did not know about that letter
Really I have a letter right now so it's it's it's in the date on it is September 30th 1975
So here's what it says
Dermstore
It was Wednesday September 30th 1975 so that would be a couple days after you got the letter from Ford
So obviously
At the same
He got my grandmother must have hung up on him right
And then he wrote the letter
Cookie cake
Yeah yeah yeah
That's really interesting. Me anytime if you have thoughts
Grandparents
Dear mr. president
Thank you for taking the time to write to me
View of some of the events since the unfortunate attempt on your life on Monday September 22nd I really appreciate
You're publicly thanking me
As you probably know
There have been a number of stories concerning my personal sexual orientation in the news media
These stories have caused Great anguish
To my parents
And to the rest of my family I am sure
My mother hung up on me when I first called her after the stories begin to be
I know you are concerned with very many matters which are two important and pressing for you to be concerned with the details of my pride
Private life
However the unexpected
And glaring publicity which is being given to my private life
Has very seriously disrupted my family relationships
Mr. president it is a very hard thing
Tab your mother
And family
Not want to have any contact
With you
I know that your schedule is heavily occupied
But I respectfully request
That you take the time
See my family or at least call my family
The telephone number is 3
Z-ro I love my family and I do not want to be separated from their love and companionship
Your help will be gratefully appreciated
Respectfully Oliver W Sipple
That said
Saturday think that nothing came of it
You know
Yeah
We tried really hard to find out if
Ford ever made that call the
The archivist at the Ford Library they went through his call logs and there was no evidence that he ever made that call
ONN
We talked to George Junior and he talks
You know everybody knows family and they don't remember it either it anyway you can't say for sure but
As far as we can tell
That call never happy
But we did find out
That the same day that Oliver sent that letter
He and his lawyer filed a 15 million dollar lawsuit against
Depress
Really
Saying same what
That the newspapers
When they publicize that he was gay
Without his consent
They violated his privacy
Okay walking out of civic center Bart
Honda Civic Center in San Francisco it's just one of those cases where it pulls your head in One Direction
And it pulls your heart in the exact opposite direction
Until
So we wanted to get into the legal case files and we could not find them we look and look and look
And then we found them you found that we found where do you find them
Cast of the clerk's offices
I guess not surprisingly right off City Hall they were at this
Court in San Francisco and we recruited this guy this researcher historian of the gay movement
A great name Joey plaster and he
Okay so I'm going to need your ID okay
Went and got the files for us and then
When we turned out there were thousands and thousands upon thousands of pages and everything
So the issue
You know it's it's a very fundamental issue for those of us in journalism and to help us make sense of the arguments
In a lurking in those pages
What is privacy in what is invasion of privacy we talked to Dan morain editorial page editor of the
The Sacramento Bee actually first heard about the case in journalism school and also wrote about Oliver Sipple way back in
1980s
Anyway okay so here's the first page of the file
The lawsuit was against a Chronicle Oliver W Sipple
Plaintiff vs
Is the chronicle Publishing Company
LA times Des Moines Register the Chicago Sun-Times a denverpost Indianapolis Star and a San Antonio
Express 180 said this is the deposition of Oliver w
Simple
See the one of the arguments the lawyers for the newspapers were making is that all of her sexuality was not actually
Chile private
Lawyer were there any people that you knew in San Francisco's and say September 1975
Who knew that you were homosexual
Simple yes
Lawyer approximately how many people
Simple I have no idea
More than 10 yes
When it's 50 yes
More than a hundred
Yes there were people in New York who knew he was gay there were people in Dallas who knew he was gay
The settle in the like in the hundred
Did you tell anybody before and September of 1975 that you were homosexual
If I were asked
I am asking you
I don't know what you were asked
And they make the argument the newspapers lawyers that hey this was already
Somewhat public a fact but his
Personal business was his personal business I've never attempted to obtain publicity for the
Fact that I'm gay or predominantly homosexual in my sexual orientation private citizen and made my home app rocks
Ultimately 1800 miles away from home
But my parents and my family so that I could move so much freely in the gay community without the fact of my sexual orientation getting fat
To my parents and family
And it goes on
But the newspapers need another argument it was like okay
Whether or not you're living a double life whether or not you wanted to or whether or not you had to
There's something here that's bigger than that that's bigger than you which was he was a private citizen who thrust himself
Self as anybody would hope they would do he ran toward the he went toward Danger
And when he did
He also thrust himself into the public eye and a journalist when you're in the public eye
You become something else entirely you become a public
Ticketmaster
When that happened to Oliver
Lost his right to privacy I'll make one more try on the game
The music was argued when it came to all of her sexuality
It is was and it all printed times has been my judgment that Mr sipple's activities in the gay community
Are highly significant and newsworthy for two important reason
First smartphone
He was a homosexual
You had this big story about the u.s. Air Force trying to kick this guy Leonard matlovich out because he was gay
Oliver has heard nothing from the president
Present leader said that he thought had nothing to do with all of her being gay
But the people at the time the suggestion that the president's expression of gratitude to Sybil might have been affected by rumors
Activities in the gay community
Has not yet personally thank them
Second lies the innuendos the public display of heroism in saving the life of the president
United States
Okay people travel esters
Presented an image
The gay people are like everybody else that
They're Heroes image certainly contrary to The Stereotype of persons associated with the gay community as we can done
Heroic figures
Which is to say this is newsworthy this is worth knowing and it is something that the whole country wants to know
And and the value of that is more than the value of
You know this individual person's privacy do they make sure to put it in terms of the public
Benefit outweighs the private privacy
So Oliver ski
It dragged on for 9 years
So from 1975 to 1984
But this is
I'm quoting the judgment
The record shows that the Publications were not motivated by morbid and Sensational prying into
To apologize private life
But rather were prompted by a legitimate political concerns
Ie
To dispel the boss public opinion that gays were timid we can done heroic figures
And to raise the equally important political question
Whether the president of the United States entertained a discriminatory attitude or bias against a minority group such as home
Bisexuals
So
The court
Cost Oliver's case out
He lost
Didn't get it.
Everything about it is weird that
A journalist can just take a person's most private details
And then if it feels relevant
If they can make that argument they just
Put it out there if we did we were to go silent because somebody said don't say that about
Then and the government backs him up it is if it's meaningful than the person
Out of which the meaning is being pulled painfully
Had nothing to say about it that's just because it's really hard and I was thinking about this like even on the train coming
Over here Daniel Lutz
And it's like
The thing that like mixed
Journalism law so complicated in the things that make
An invasion of privacy discussions so difficult is that like
What makes something not an invasion of privacy is not that it's okay it's that it's
Politically you know releve
So like this with the fact that the story that affected the
Private details of his life
AR
Politically relevant
Memes
That it's not an invasion of privacy
You know it doesn't mean that it isn't rude or that it doesn't hurt
It means
That it's
Inappropriate
Story 2 video
Publix
But I do think like why should the journalist be the only ones to decide what is newsworthy it's not like
Why is it that then
Journalist you
You just pick up a notepad and pencil and all the sudden you have so much more power to say what say of
Then than anybody else
Well I mean we have a long tradition of that in the United States I mean like that's
Like what the first amendment is
I mean
I don't know means like yeah sure like it's like why do journalist get to decide that will like
Who would you rather have decided
It's not a perfect system but it's
You know
It kind of works
So so is Oliver just like this this is Tracy hunt it was in on the interview somebody who
Life is basically kind of sacrifice to the altar of the First Amendment and it's like
Sad way
Yes
Yeah
I feel like he was sacrificed from all sides
It it feels like there's just one kind of man in the middle and then they're all these
Forces around him these like
These larger-than-life forces like
The White House there's the gay movement
Freedom of the press
NN all these people are our sort of batting around all these all these enormous and important abstractions and then
In the middle of it
This guy that just
Is trampled by all of them and so what ends up happening to him in the end
Apparently some people in the gay community
During and after the lawsuit
Tell that he was trying to go back in the closet so they sort of
Turn their backs on him
Surprisingly he was friends with Harvey Milk till till the ends like
When Harvey Milk was assassinated
Oliver Sipple went to his funeral
He did have one brother George senior who stuck by him throughout but but his parents
Did not
And they never fully accepted the fact that he was gay and end
To when his mom died
It was so bad that
Oliver suppose father didn't let him go to the funeral
And because he he sort of
He had so far
So few people I guess at the end and because there weren't
You know a lot of news articles about him and
Cuz a lot of people in the gay community from that time have died because of the AIDS
Craigslist
It was really hard to find out what
Happened to Oliver Sipple nose last
5 years of his life
And
The only way we could was because
When you were talking to Daniel Lutz already mentioned this interview that he did with this guy named Dwayne Friday
He was a friend of Oliver
Wing Friday was sort of like a
Pillar of the community in San Francisco like a pillar of the gay community and then also has heard of
Political figure and he was like
Coffin you know he was he was at Heathrow
Fingers in every pie
All kind of thing
Wayne died last year but Daniel still had the transcript of their conversation about Oliver Sipple
Last days until
We found it after
Very gifted Gordon pinsent
And we had him read it for
Okay let me have a go
I forget was 1975 the Sarah Jane Morris
Yeah but I miss him around 73
He was a Swamper I like gay bar, Coughlin
Swampert is used to clean the bars at night
Set the bar low for the next bartender in the morning
Do it three different bars he was always at the bar
Unsane
We actually became friends because we discovered we were both from Michigan
There was a good guy
It was just so f****** alcoholic I made against disability check once a month
How do you go down one of the bars in the tenderloin but I used to hang out with cough Queen Mary's Pub
He told the other day got his check
Swear to God
Hit hit spend this whole fucken Jack on everybody
How do you get broke the rest of the month they just couldn't control himself
And he was a little bit of a blowhard that I always e
Get drunk and loud Guitar Center bars
I used to drive me home
Hidden department on Van Ness
Had a little Studio.
I want bedroom on the first floor at about Turk
He drunk I'm going to have at the bar and I driving home so I always knew where you live
And that's why this thing was forwarded really f***** his mind.
Broken guy after that the whole thing work.
The publicity of them all
The fact that everyone knew he was a faget dinner
He said to be a couple of times
I went to the Marine Corps and I got hurt and now what am I known for being a faget
And I said no you're not
You're known for saving the president's life
She won't be known for what you did in bed for Christ's sake
But he would get drunk and then stop bemoaning that
I just talked to him about it amen
It is what it is
But he was just
He was just
Down to nothing
This thing happen
Andrew overcame him
Too much for him to handle
And I think he got the feeling sorry for himself
Annies family
Many a night I would sit in the bar with build simple and he's crying your shoulder and you'd say Okay symbol
It's time to go home
And then I drive home now
I remember it was raining
It was pouring f****** rain
Bruce called me at my office over at the DA's office and said when
Will you do a well-being check on simple for me and I said why
How do you say nobody's saying the dude
You haven't been around for awhile
So we go out there together and it was raining
And I'm ringing the bell ringing the bell ring
He doesn't answer
I noticed on his door there with these little stick'em things posted
Elliot Big Friend of this little old lady
Who lived next door they kind of looked after each other
And she left all these notes Bill call me I can't get a hold of you
So I rang the managers Bell
And with little Filipino guy
I showed him my badge and I said you got to let me in
And so he did
And the door opened and I know what was going on
It's the smell
It's a smell
You never forget
It's a sickening sweet
Smell
Bill was sitting in the chair
He was bluffing
Is bloating a real big
Yeti bottle of Jack Daniels sitting there
And the television was still on
The coroner told me he'd been dead
About 10 days
As near as I can figure
God I didn't know he was only 47
I thought he was older than that
Anyway
I got the guy to open the door for me
Adam energy did I said
Troponin
And then I had to stand there
Android for the car
I remembered it was over here at the Campbell funeral home at Market
Straight
And then we buried him out in Golden Gate National Cemetery in San Bruno
And I remember
Is very small
Casket wasn't open
The funeral was just
I'm in
There were more millionaires
I seen them buy drinks for more people than we're at that funeral
He could have been buried in Arlington if they made an issue out
I mean shut that he was this National icon a gay whatever
It was just a few people
Out there
The funeral
I believe in human life
And I think that this country stands for human
Diets
Including life and freedom
I'm first and foremost a human being who enjoys
And
Respect life
Fifield
I feel that
A person
Worth is
Determined by how
He or she
Response to the world
In which they live not on how or what
Or was home a private life is Cher
This song is my words and their my feeling
This is all I have to say on this subject
Thank you very much ladies and gentlemen
This story was reported by lots of Nasser and Tracy hunt
Who is produced by Matt kielty and anime with lots of Tracy
Thanks to Bruce th Burke to Stacy Davis at the Gerald Ford Presidential Library to the glbt Historical Society
Eddie Stephanie Arias at the Huntington Library
James Clemens is Gordon pinsent agent in as long as we're on the subject of Gordon the actor you heard just ending the peace wow
Wow just
Wow yeah thank you to Gordon special thanks also to Alan Jones Danny Meyer
And Floyd Abrams thank you all
Weird original music in the story he's a lot of music from a guy named Patrick Cowley
Music I grew up in Buffalo move to San Francisco in the 70s like Oliver Sipple
He died of AIDS
This music was released posthumously by the label dark entries were super grateful to them
And Patrick Cowley wherever he is
Four uses music
And Glassell at least before we close we just want to say a very sort of special
Belated goodbye to our senior producer Jamie York who did a little of the legal research in the store trying
Appropriately DP to get the legal files thank you Jamie for doing that and forever forever
Guiding so many of our stories and our whole team for the last few years tell me we will we will really miss you
We even do eat this very moment I miss you
Play the message
Cresco
I'm calling in this is Joey Pastor in New Haven Connecticut
Hi this is Dan Marino to record
Credit fraud and is produced by storm wheeler
So
Starting now
David Gable Bethel have the Tracy hunt not guilty
Lots of Nasser Alyssa O'Donnell and Molly Webster without from Amanda run
Shema Shema Shema
Playing and Katie Ferguson tractor is Michelle Harris
Happy to record it again but I think that should work fine with you know how to conduct
And this message