Hi I'm Robert krulwich Radiolab is supported by Audible
As we explore this story of obsession creativity and symmetry
Check out this is your brain on music both a cutting-edge study and a tribute to the beauty of music
Go to audible.com radio or text
Radiolab to 500 500 for a free 30-day trial and a free
Audiobook
Hi I'm Robert krulwich Radiolab is supported by Casper
As we continue this episode on creativity and symmetry check out the Casper or the wave mattress
Support system
That mirrors your body shape to get $50 towards select mattresses by visiting casper.com Radiolab
How do using Code Radiolab at checkout
Terms and conditions apply
This is Dad
Before we start I would like to let you know about a new podcast
Is out there in the world that is aimed at
Drum roll please
Kids
MSM protocol excited about this cuz my kids just discovered podcasting it's the things we can do together
This particular one just called this podcast has fleas
Tells the story of a dog
In a cat
Who live in the same house and have competing podcast
Hi everybody I'm waffles this is a dog talk a podcast by a dog we both are podcast
Everybody else podcast
These days why would Patsy different
Lili Ortiz
A small soups all of what you can expect from the series
This is my weapon waffles the dog walks into the mud room discovers that
She is not
The only pet in the house
Podcast
The cat is sitting in his litter box
Big electronic beanie with a lot but podcast
I don't care
Schlitterbahn
Cat lovers
This is laughing a little box name Jones the cat
Downloading my hip new single featuring in last week
Episode
Let's hear a little bit of it now
Who invented the napkin who sometimes has on his toes
Jay Pharoah
Saturday Night Live Alum played The Cat
Emilylynne Place dog
Baldwin plays a goldfish
If you have kids if you don't check it out it's called this podcast has fleas from WNYC Studios
Whenever you get your podcast you're pretty good at that Daddy and I just love your show
It's an inspiration you show your not a cat
Yeah
Are you awake
Radio WNYC
Anjana barad I'm Robert Goulet Radiolab
So okay so this one
This one I think you weren't around for the first time I wasn't I was going for Blackberry that I listened after
Which you had listened
I hate liars
I hate that something then
As is often the case
Reluctantly became Eli course
This one is a its
You know me then I'm a music nerd
Right you are
This is story about
The weirdest
Creativity in a piece of music
Did Frankie add study in school
But which
Unites
Two people across space and time in a really bizarre way
Kind of rhyme
First Story begins in the 1980s in Vancouver British Columbia with a woman named and Adams
Who by all accounts was a brilliant cell biology
Oh yes and was highly articulate
That's her husband Robert Adams you know extremely capable with language
She did cancer research he actually develop the cell line
That I believe still exist
So she was very sharp
He says that as a scientist she was a natural but then
Rather Suddenly at the age of 46
And kind of did a 180
Something happened in 86 which change the course of her life
It all started when their third son Alex gets into a really bad car accident
We were told that he would probably never ever walk again
And decided she's going to take some time off to help him recover and he does he does learn to walk again
The wild home
She just decides to quit
Quit science
And become a painter
Dan
Made up her mind then and there
That she was going to
Take apart
Full-time
Had she ever painted for well she did a fair amount of it when she was in high school
Which is a very long time ago so the whole thing struck him is kind of out of the blue but he rolled with it and
Within a short. Of time she converted a room in their house into a studio and she
Painting houses
And buildings
Little churches
Simple at first but after that brightly colored versions of what you see when you look down the barrel
A microscope Neo cells bacteria after that strawberries
A series of paintings involving these Blazing Red strawberries
A water faucet
A note of what would becoming a stream of strawberries
Play there was things called strawberry Universe where the strawberries have rings around them like Saturn and I don't
I think there was something like 35 or 36
Strawberry painting
But then she would switch to something else even after their son had fully recovered even through Waze crutches
Went back to school
And kept on painting and she would work
All day long
10 hours a day making these paintings that got bigger and bigger and more abstract and there were times he says
When he was like
Wow
Because for someone who hadn't painted since high school
She was suddenly so prolific
And it's entirely possible
There's something was happening to her even then
Way below the surface I mean on the surface she was painting it was working
People buying the painting she's having solo shows she was becoming a successful artist
Then in 1994
She decided I don't know what gave her this idea
I never knew what gave her any of her ideas
But time she decided she was going to do a painting
Well
Best
Valero
Bolero
Yeah bowlero
Robert says he's not quite sure how it happened but it's
Some point that year and heard this famous piece by Maurice Ravel
Became
Set
Couldn't stop listening to it
Then playing it on the piano
Deconstructing it mapping every pitch in the melody in the bass
To color yours
Here's one page
It's just very long just have her notes she's got a silver a flat copper
B
Leaf Green
B flat
Metallic
Green eventually the paintings
Quite a large work to panel side by side
Barry Electric colors a blizzard
Symbols
Triangles
Tooth type things with marks on the middle mean something and rectangles marching back and forth across the first pen
There was a triangle in the bottom of each one of the rectangle and the
Height of the rectangle
Represented the loudness
It's an incredibly obsessive translation of the music into
Visual language and just like the melody in Bolero
The symbols repeat
And repeat
Repeat
Obsessively getting bigger and bigger and bigger until at the very end of the second panel
Things unravel
Was unraveling
Bolero
And that unraveling
Turns out it happened before we come back we're going to mm
Explain what we mean by a rhyme
Don't have to explain it it'll just
Run
Hello this is Emily villani from Austin Texas
Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloan @www
Thoughts loan.org
Hi I'm Robert krulwich Radiolab is supported by Audible
As we explore the story of obsession creativity and strange symmetry between a biologist to the composer
Check out this is your brain on music
The science of a human Obsession available on Audible
Both the cutting-edge study and a tribute to the beauty of Music itself this is your brain on music
Unravels a host of mysteries that affect everything from pop culture to our understanding of human nature
Go to audible.com Radiolab or text Radiolab to 500 500 for a free
30-day trial and a free
Audiobook
I am Robert krulwich Radiolab is supported by cash
As we continue listening to this unraveling Bolero episode on creativity and symmetry check out the wave mattress
Will a premium support system that mirrors your body shape
The Casper with a breathable design and supported memory foam
Get your Casper mattress delivered to your door and a small how did they do that size box
You can be sure of your purchase with Casper's 109th risk-free sleep on a trial right now get $50 to
Select mattresses by visiting casper.com Radiolab
And using a code Radiolab at checkout terms and conditions apply
Jack Robert
Radiolab getting back to our story we heard and story about painting strawberries and painting
Painting a bat
Beat music until you're difference
Different time different place different person
But
Strangely
Run
Story number 2
Locate we jumping please
This is RV Ornstein
Professor music at the Aaron Copland School of Music
It's called
He's written about Ravel
Perform Ravel
Talk to anyone who ever knew Ravel
What should I say kind of a living presence inside my head
2ok Maurice Ravel
Composer obviously one of the greats
Born in 18
Papa was an engineer
Mother was
I'm an old boss
Family
I sent you in Spanish
Yes
Which is why I asked
This music like Bellaire does sound of it Spanish encourage them to study music
Andy's Meats
Claude Debussy and together they sort of invent this style of music which we now call impressionism
Kind of
Free-floating
Almost dreamlike sensuous
A lot of colors
Very flowery
Then like an
Revell makes a kind of s***
1928 West absolutely
Phenomenal
Just for the United States
Form for thousands is that the Zenith of his creativity and he's back in France at a beach house wearing a pink
Bathing suit
Story goes right before he steps out onto the beach this melody
Slips into his head
Runs over the piano Texas index finger when he goes
Duh duh Dunt Dunt Dunt Dunt
Are there it was
Just came to him fully formed
Well he I don't know if he played the whole Melody
But he's at least started
It Off
But here's the shift when he sat down to flush the whole thing out instead of developing a Melody making it super flowery likes other stuff
Decide now
I'm not going to that
I'm going to take this melody and repeat it
Again and again and again
And it's Amore never changes OneNote
The only thing that does change is the orchestration which grows around the melody
Very slowly
Bit by bit
Gets bigger
Big Bore company man
More instruments play the melody
Amelia self for 340 bars
Never
Berries to the point he says where the performers
Ready to see a psychiatrist by the time they're done playing this piece
And without the first performance in Paris I'm woman screamed out
He's crazy
Which turned out to be
Not exactly true but in the neighborhood
6 years after he wrote bolero
1930s
Ravel begins to forget words
She always been forgetful so no one really noticed it first
Then one day at dinner
Grab the knife by the wrong side he doesn't realize it
And continues to try to eat holding
The chop side of the knife and trying to cut with the handle
Then visit a friend leaves
Not 2 hours go by knock on the door it's Rahzel again
He didn't remember
That he'd been there before
Just two hours earlier eventually he could not write anymore
Speak
Is language at evaporator
Darby says there are documents Regency Ravel desperately trying to relearn the alphabet
A
A over and over
Well be
The
Kind of a shaking
And very small
Very very painful
Whatever it was that was wrong
Was getting worse
Use the word symmetry just like Ravel 6 years after finishing her Bolero by mm I would say
And
Also begin to forget
She would try to say things
And couldn't
She would try to find words and couldn't
So how are you today
Find
Eventually and ends up at the University of California San Francisco
And this was in 2002 and they gave her a bunch of tests can you tell me your your full name please
Anne Teresa Adams
This video one of these tests and innate you can see and sitting at a table
Black sweater
Gray hair glasses
Very composed you tell me your address
Like someone who's used to knowing the answers
Questions
B blaster
Which town
Which town Vancouver
By the time and had come to see us her communication abilities were
Markedly diminished
That's dr. Bruce Miller neurologist he runs the memory and aging Center at UCSF
Example we asked her to describe
A very complex rich
Picture with take your time
Children with a kite with a sailboat on the ocean and please tell me what you see
And if you can please try to speak in sentences
And would it be able to say single words with no grammar she'd go
Sailboat
Tree
Boy
Water people
Kitekite flag
And that
Four five words would come out over about a minute's time
She was very frustrated
Does an atom's in Maurice Ravel we're unraveling in the exact same way
Exact same speed
To the same soundtrack you might say
Just
Roughly 60 years apart we think he and Ann down to the very molecular process had the exact
Same disease
Anything cebollero the music and then the painting
In both their case
What's the first symptom of AIDS
6 couple of steps to explain bear with me
Start the disease called frontotemporal dementia and
It's begins when certain cells in your frontal cortex which is your forehead
Begin to wither away
In some cases literally leaving holes
In your frontal cortex and we know this about an
Some tests and brain scans we suspected about Ravel because Queen RV just before he died on December 28th
1937 French surgeon open up a skull
And saw that
One of the lobes of the
2 lobes of the brain
Had sunk
Disintegrate
Now in both of their cases the part of their brain part of their cortex got hit
What's on the left
Is it part of the brain does a lot of things I had lodged with memory but most importantly for our story this is the part of your brain that
Largely governs language
People who suffer from frontotemporal dementia
They lose
They can no longer string words together
And here's something about losing something like language
It has all kinds of other effects
In the brain because
Bruce you know our brain is a series of interconnected circuit
And when
In a normal brain a dominant circuit like language turns on
It is basically wired
To turn a bunch of other circuits off basically goes
Two other parts of the brain we have this constant Dancewear
1 circuit or many circuits turn on and then their obligatory really turning off other circuits
So language acts as a kind of brake on other things to bring Timmy doing
Like daydreaming
Taking a picture
But
When the language is no longer there to hold things back Austin
What happens if those other parts
Let's say the visual part scan
Rushford
Suddenly the mind is just
Flooded with images and you hear
Reports of people having these intensely visual experiences Express is very common
We see a number of patients would become visually obsessed he says he sees you no investment bankers who never shown any in
Interest in are never
Even walked into an art museum
All of a sudden they decide in their 50s well I'm going to move into a loft take up painting that's right
How many of these cases have you seen
Steal some of them has sculpted some of them
Painted he said he's seen people take up gardening graphic design
And what's so many of the cases have in common is that the sort of visual creativity that burst forth
It's not the free-flowing kind it's very mechanical
The repetition Obsession they get stuck in a kind of loop taking one visual ID and doing it again and again and it
Again
Like an Anne Adams Painting
Bolero
This said drive to repeat
Happens very early in the course of this illness
Teresa
What can seem like a simple creative
Choice to repeat a melody
May actually be driven by a condition
But you won't even know you have for six years we think that this had something to do with a very unusual
Rhythmic repetitive sorts of music that
Revell produce
I asked Bruce so why the repetition where does
Where does that come from
And I think this is a release of of
You said we don't really know
The effort of a theory which I find fascinating
Which make it to the root of creative Obsession of any kind
He says there might be
Several parts of the brain that are held back by the language
With circuit and one of them
Is this very ancient part of the brain
The basal ganglia the part of the brain we move with
You can call a reptile brain is the part of us that governs basic Behavior
Eating running
Motor programs that we do repetitively everyday
Eat run run birds and snakes
Get by with
Basically just this part of the brain
Keep them alive
Normally he thinks the language part of us
Inhibits these habits these repetitive motor
Programs
When the language part of the brain is not there to do the shushing these motor commands filter up to
So imagine you're one of these people your mind is
Flooded with all of the
These images may be sound
Also flooded with all of these
Kinetic repetitive instructions move
Move move do it again in the early stages of the illness
You still have enough brain to make sense of it all
There's still a lot of Cortex that is still available to
Act upon this desire to repeat
So you get art that is obsessive and repetitive but also beautiful
An abstract
Like
And painting unraveling bolero
But then resets as the disease progresses in more of that sort of Cortex a human apart
Hate the way the repetition becomes much simpler
In the latter stages of a disease he says you'll often see patients pouring water into a cup hundred times
Open today
Squishing apps over and over again
The complexity of the behaviors are diminishing as we're losing these are parts of the brain that make us so humid
This is sort of what you see in Anne's work her painting start off simple exploded abstraction and then get simple again
What's unusual compared to the other patients is that she kept painting almost all the way to the
Literally it was not possible for her to to hold and direct a pressure of pain
It's her husband Robert again and became progressively paralyzed on the right side of her body she lost
What's the ability to paint
And that. Is that what she said
Towards the end he said he would go into her studio and I would see her there in front of a blank canvas
She wouldn't be doing anything
She would just be looking at it
And I come back
Couple of hours later
And she still wouldn't have done anything
She had lost the ability to do the yard
Anatomy is one of the
I daresay beautiful parts of an story that the drive to create is as Primal as anything
Else in the body that even after she couldn't eat after she could barely swallow she still sat there in
In her studio trying to paint she had gone downhill so far by that time
That time
That she was hardly recognizable us as herself
At some point in the disease and you can see that in this early tape painting was really all she had
I don't have them memories of this
It's basically all she was
I do art
She died in 2007 in January of 2007
Almost exactly 60 years
After Maurice Ravel
Text to Robert Adams Bruce Miller at the University of California San Francisco
NRV Ornstein
Queens College
Well that's a song that's not that's that's
That's a pizza that's not good
Stay the same
It's funny I used to think of Bolero is like a happy jaunty tune
Now I'm like who it's
What kind of haunted it's an interesting sort of
Paradox
Assisting hands on
She sits in front of her canvas
Ferociously stalls
We both know it's the ferocious beast
That that that creativity
Consumer kind of restlessness
And the restlessness maybe one of the things I love
Leaves last
Nice picnic leaving we should go
Thanks for listening
Hi this is Mitchell Otto from Kalamazoo Michigan
Radiolab was created by Jad album Rod and is produced by Soren wheeler
Dylan Keith
Is our director of sound design Maria Montessori Padilla is our managing director
Our staff includes xiamen Adler Maggie bartolomeo Becca Bressler
Rachel Cusick
David Gable Bethel hockey Tracy hunt
Matt kielty Robert krulwich Annie McEwen lots of Nasser
Melissa O'Donnell
Arianne wack
Pat Walters
And Molly Webster with help from Amanda ronchak
Shima
Olay
Jake Harlow Andre Cannon
Are back Checker is Michelle Harris
Hi I'm Robert krulwich Radiolab is supported by Audible
Check out this is your brain on music
Both a cutting-edge study and a tribute to the beauty of music go to audible.com Radiolab or text
Radiolab to 500 500 for a free 30-day trial and a free audiobook
Hi I'm Robert krulwich Radiolab is supported by Casper check out the Casper or the wave
Mattress with the support system
That mirrors your body shape
Get $50 towards select mattresses by visiting casper.com Radiolab have using Code Radiolab
Checkout terms and conditions apply