Are you weightless
Radio WNYC
And NPR
I think I think there's a lot of moments in your life that you find yourself doing something
Anybody in here my name is Brittany would love to be able to talk with you
And you take that moment and step back from it
And you realize what the f*** am I doing
What just happened was this real I think that was one of those moments
Hey I'm Jared I'm rod iron rubber Co which is Radiolab in today on the podcast
A ghost story
Really we're going to do a ghost story at Halloween dude well you don't even know where to just listen
This one comes to my producer Matt kielty yet so I first heard the story from a buddy of mine
His name is Dennis Conroe dentist
Eddie what's up dude Mills total beds
Will Dennis yes about a lot of things but in particular
House
So let's let's start with the house when did you move back in with Steve I was probably I don't know
2010 college
Yep by the way what did you what did you study
Creative writing
Yeah I just got I just kind of got bored there
Going to stop going to class
I think what's my parents realize that they weren't very happy and
I would assume so and so
Set yeah I was kind of asked to come back home
Back to town just outside Kansas City towns called Grandview I did I did
And the house was fairly old at about a hundred and five
Years old at the time a White House nice little porch awning over a farmhouse style
You were at your parents home equity in your in your old bedroom and my old childhood bedroom
Yasso
There was always a sense of like I need to get out of this house it's holding you back somehow
So I got a job
Bruker job and got
Laid off
And when you're turned into two and then 3 then 4 then 5 it was not that great
Time to be there in what way just that I felt like I was
Still
He says he's over here is mom telling people on the phone why don't you know you never got to move out Izzy
She started circling classifieds jobs for typists printing press sales rep typesetter
I think everything in my life however I
Mean for it not to sort of moves at my own snail's pace
Eventually really old like 27 maybe actually he was 28 after eight years in this house
Dennis gets the job finds his apartment this ratty 6 Plex apartment
But
Right when he said to move out
Finally home my mom got really sick
Dance mom is in remission from breast cancer for like 9 years but that summer
Her doctors
Told her that didn't return and that's bread
Quite a bit
So
I said to hurt like a
Do you do you want me to
Be here or do you want me to
Go
And she was like well you know if this is my time
She wants to go knowing that her kids can take care of themselves
Spend this moved out about 5 months later
She went pretty fast
Vons or so after my mom died my dad found out he had stage 4 prostate cancer
And he was really too sick to take care of the house and just be the guy by himself at that point
Now that's pretty much had to come home I take care of him
3-4 times a week
Ed
Has he got worse
Kid said to me like hey let's try to find you a house to buy so that I can teach you how to like
Do all of the kind of stuff that one has to do men know how to do things like change out Plumbing
All this kind of stuff and so we put an offer on a house that fell through and before they can find
Something else for cancer from his prostate
Spread to his brain and you're the last week of his life he was really
Not there
I can remember
One day like maybe maybe a week or so after he died walking through the empty
Kitchen and
There was so much stuff there was so much stuff
Papers all over the place junk mail all over the kitchen floor
Down in the basement tools all over the place
Yeah I had this moment of
Yeah
Here are his tools and I
And now I
Have them in my hands and you know I just remembered taking up this
Clawhammer and just crying
Cuz this is my hammer
This is now my house is now
My
Problem
But few days pass
And clean it out
Soap
At age 32 junk in the basement but that stuff on the curb sale after c
Sale after sale horrible
Headed meant to replace it before he died but you know
Finish my thought was like oldest to this one bathroom so it looks pretty good to sell
Daddy never showed him how to
Doing it at stuff that point that I was like hell YouTube
And begin with your ceramic tile Nippers Michigan online or not I'll just Plumbing any redid the bathroom
And turned out pretty good it was kind of fun and then the next thing I knew I was taking wallpaper off of the kitchen
Flats got to go hardwood floors insulation to attic glass block windows in the basement
I turned into the whole house
How long does that take
5 years
Actually it was 6
Well he says the whole time he was doing this renovation
At night
I would have these dreams where
My parents just kind of came through the back door and it was just like a what are you doing here
Oh that's right your your dad and then I would turn my
My back and then
They would have
Somehow
Undone all of the things that I did
All they had brought the house back to where it what
State it was in when they were alive
And I probably had this dream I'm not kidding like at least a hundred times wow
Night after night after night just kept going on and on and
Ultimately kind of
Drove me crazy until one day after yet another one of these dreams Dennis is finally like
All right
I'm selling it
Put it up in the markets waiting for a buyer
And then
Something
Strange happens
Well something kind of strange I made this
Friend and she came over for the first time
Lady friend on a date you taking her back to your house and so
Improvements until she was in
The kitchen right by the basement door in the kitchen
When she was like there's some kind of weird presents here
And I was just like okay well that was kind of sign that was not going to last.
Fast forward a few years didn't really think too much about it until one day Dennis's realtor is having an open house
No one shows so she was in the house by yourself and then it starts getting these
Text messages from her dude your house is haunted
Like I can hear people
Walking around and
She texted that there was
Definitely something weird going on right by the basement door that's the same spot
That's that's kind of weird
But then here's the crazy thing called friend is in Eastlake
Hey funny thing to different people two separate occasions
They come over to the house
And they said they felt this weird
Presents and she was like wait right by the basement door get out
So I got Heather I got Stacey on that Carla all three
To say they feel this weird presents consider yourself a bit of a skeptic about such things
I would say so rashly I'm just going to say no
So you don't believe in ghosts no all right what happened next
This also having to be right at the time that I
Sold the house Dennis to finally put the pen to paper signed the contract packed up all stuff
And so Carla the girl that first felt this thing because he went on a date with think they stay friends
Sad to me like
You know I'm
Really curious about this
Would you mind if I call like these ghosts people to comment late check-out
This
Place
It was like well
Sure
I don't care you know why not so very shortly
2 minutes actually
Are bringing paranormal investigators
Define up
What's in the basement
Yeah I'm just kind of walking through the house I think I got this on tape of just media walking through the house
Like we'll probably a waste of time but I'm
Still kind of curious about it it's Friday night right it's a Friday night midnight
November 6th I can see some cars parking on the street so I go downstairs people start filing in
Maybe 10 people Larry's are Tech Guy
Love Clairvoyant psychic name
My name is Brittany Elaine well they're part of the Kansas City paranormal investigators club or something
Right off the bat
The only first got here
We both saw
A woman looking out the window
So what did she look like
I didn't really see what you look like
Headlighting lawn repair it was like gray and
She was wearing one of those weird old timey dresses
Dennis was like whatever
They set up cameras the basement in the kitchen in the clairvoyants had they wanted to try to talk
To this woman
Any other scared in the house
Tell Brittany she's like the ringleader of the night she sort of explained how she does things
Things you know she was like the best way
That she could get them to talk to to to them was through flashlights
What to do if they take a few flashlights turn him on
Enemy unscrew the tops of them
Juice
So that they turn off
Let me just kind of set the flashlights that better now off
In the room by themselves
The idea is that if
Ghost of the spirit wants to communicate
Distorted
Touch the top of one of the flashlights with their dosti finger
And I'll turn it back on
It's not that you are
And I was like okay
So she took three flashlights
And we all sat in this dark room in a circle
Okay and precept flashlights in the middle of circle by themselves
And she says Brittany
I love to be able to talk with you
Can you turn on the lights on
And reset their me sit there
Are you here
Then all the sudden this light
Kind of been sleeping song
And then she said okay
Thank you
Please turn it off
I'm going to goes off
What we can do with these lights here is if I can ask her then she says we have three
Lights you're the one you just turned on will call you us
Please turn on one more and that will be no
And then a
Second light comes on
No way any the room like looking for somebody who has like a little switch or something
These people so they have no reason to fake this I suppose but now I just keep thinking well
Houses close to the
Train tracks that maybe maybe the train vibrations of the train
But all the sudden they were like
Can you hear that
Footsteps
And they're going towards the kitchen
And I can hear
Dishes rattling on the countertop in the kitchen
No one's in the kitchen no one's in the kitchen
If you're in the kitchen right now can you turn one of these lights on
Teresa didn't stare at these three flashlights
Then
I'm leaving the room what happened
Well I actually
Everyone
Everyone in that room
Died
Except for Dennis
I have no idea why I even invited you into this building
Not. Actually they're fine
It turns out that I there was a guy downstairs in the basement one of the techies walking around
Pitch black down there and he just like bangs his head until I can air duct in the Sounders reverberated throughout the whole house
Jennifer Lopez it was very Blair Witch
Anyhow the techies is that they want to
Get the three psychics down in the basement by themselves and so you know
These three women go down in the basement by themselves kind of cure them downstairs talking but we don't really know what's going on
They come back upstairs and they said
She was definitely down there he'll woman the Fate first saw when I got to the house
And they said that she was standing down in the basement next to where the old furnace used to be
Middle Tennessee she said that she lived here for a long time and then it's like in a second
You knew that back in the thirties or something a woman has lived in this house
Who
Was kind of not all there
And one day she turned down into the basement and thought she was picking
Lice
Off of chickens in throwing them in this big furnace that was downstairs in the basement at the time she got a little teeth
Close the furnace Story Goes caught herself on fire and then died there
I guess in the basement
But then there was another man downstairs to show himself to me but he won't
Pop music completely disappeared
What did he look like
He was bald
News about Rick site but it wasn't right
Do you ever feel like me
A lot like love
Not a lot but
Similar
Definitely
If I were to show you a picture of
My father
Would you have any sense of this with him
If I saw a picture of them yeah baby
I found this
Tennis coaching get this photo of his dad that he had that was left over from his memorial service
Yep that's man I saw
If she's very hesitant at the beginning just like I should jump in here really quick and tell you that this was actually
The first time that Dennis has ever listened to this tape
Really yeah in the reason is cuz for long time
Didn't want to listen to it
Why
Part of it had to do with this moment because this is the point where my
Skepticism kind of ticked off
Part of it had to do with
What happens next
It's coming up when we return
This is Chad koenecke calling you from my living room and Cincinnati Ohio
Radiolab is supported in part by the National Science Foundation and by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world more information about Sloan
Www. Sloan
. org
Thanks
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help this summer I'm hosting a show and I've request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
About what we're calling Brilliance basically I want to hear about this
Yo did something that just means you lean back and say whoa how did they do that maybe
Who is the moment that our kids you've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you or maybe the kid was at
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the musical score or maybe the
Music in the margin of their geometry homework we're interested in the
Kid does something super smart but doesn't have anything to do with the test if you have a story
T-shirt with us and go to radiolab.org Brilliance and record a short audio message for
Again that's where you live. Org / Brilliance thank you so much
This is Radiolab let's get back to Matt killed his ghost story on where pick up
With our main guy Dennis Conroe
Having just heard from the Ghost Hunters that they encountered a spirit in the basement of his home
Who looks remarkably like his
Dead father
It must mean I saw you
Yep pretty here
If he's here
Can we can we try to talk to him
Her here or
He went upstairs not in the basement floor
Talk to him
So
Your head really told them a whole lot about what the different rooms in the house were
But they led me upstairs to what was his room and to the corner of the room
Don't worry this bad was
And they had no idea that I used to be had no idea
And
I said to them okay well if he's going to talk he'll just talk to me
My dad
Are you here
Need to turn on the lights if you are
Thank you
We're going to call that yes
Can you turn that one off now
Then turn on the no light in the other light please
I need to know that
.
Oh
Thanks.
Are you allowed to leave
Would you like
These people to leave
Talk to me
Yeah I know something
Damnit I want to know are you
In a good spot
Are you okay
Are you okay with that
Everything off
Lights off
Almost
Hip going to ask you is
Monster 2
My hair still
And
The other of the three flashlights
White Sox
Yes
I love you Grandma
Mississauga
So many questions for you I can't ask
The mall in this yes or no questions
But
I said what have you been able to see the things I've done to the house
And
Both of the lights lit up very brightly yes
And then so looking for 6 years
Redone the house I've done a lot of things he only said
Precinct are you
Happy with this are you happy with the things I've done at the house they both look very brightly yes
And
I said are you
Proud of me
Be proud of
Black dog
Clam
So in a few days guys
I'll probably never set foot in this house again.
I don't want you to stay here and feel
When you belong here I want you to Clearwater Beach
Free
Can you
Coco's house
I am going to
Recognize
The Haunting my dreams a lot
That's very important to you
That's where it ends
That's how I Call of Duty
Exactly like that
And
Yeah kind of teared up
Keep in mind that this was the first time that didn't heard this tape and so
He played it back to him
Cuz we just wanted to see you like
How we remember that experience I guess part of part of part of my fear
I'll listen to it was that it would change it
And that it would be a different
Experience it would be a little more hokey and it would be a little more
Unclear what was happening but
Listen to it again
Yeah it was
As I recall it being
Sonia does he believe he was
Actually talking to his
Dead parents
No
No I ended up actually
Calling this guy who explained to me
How this whole flashlight thing
Works and that there is
A perfectly non paranormal explanation
As to what's going on with the flashlight almost Goes Bad Manners at this point to have a pact with me but I'm very curious to hear it
What's going on is you turn the flashlight on
When you turn the flashlight on the bulb gets really hot
When you take the top of the flashlight and you unscrew it
Just like enough that the flashlight flickers off
Flashlight off
And the bulb it got really hot to the inside of the flashlight also got really hot and there's this little piece of plastic inside the Flash
Flashlight it when it got hot it expanded
And now is the flooding since the flashlight off that piece of plastic it starts to cool down and starts the contraction we can track
He pushes these two
Tiny bits of metal together
The two little bits of metal come into contact and that's your circuit
Did the circuit open the light bulb it goes back on or that it warms again
Dysplastic it starts in the hottest Spanish people chose this flashlight because it had that
Particular property do you think it's like a condor something no I don't think so no I don't think so I mean
He's like I think they're just trying to make sense of Randomness I mean they don't I don't think you necessarily know that this flashlight
Does this thing and therefore they can manipulate people here's my don't think it's a car
Because in this case it's such a it's such a
Strange
Coincidence
The whenever he wants his mom and dad his ghostly mother and father
To approve of him
And congratulate him
And honor him
With a yes
Miss Random you could get a nobody gets a yes
It's just chance
And util Dancehall
Yeah I told that it's cuz you told me to tell that it's true
Okay so when you told him what did he say
Well
I want level like it didn't phase him
Denim Paisley said like look I know I know
That
The way that the world works is the way the world Works people don't come back from the tab
People don't talk to you through
Flashlights
He also said that like he's not
Going to let go of
That experience
He wants to have it both ways I guess so I guess I guess I would have both yes this didn't happen and yes this apps
Truly happened
I understand that
Even if you are the world's biggest skeptic if you don't believe in ghosts like
There
Really aren't that many ways
Talk about these sorts of things these are the things that we all feel
You know guilt for free
Things are becoming our past the loss of those who
Will Be Loved
That like ghost stories kind of seem to stick around because
They aren't experienced
I'll be at like a metaphorical experience experience
But let's talk about these things that we
Can't adequately talk about
You know that feeling of being haunted
Anticipated he eventually sell the house move out of the house moved out no more dreams
Parents haunting him
In the time that I sold the house
Now
I thought the dreams would stop
And now
The dreams are the
I'm the one haunting The House of the new people
Or I will just walk in
Hear the
What are you like
Going around repairing things
Nope I'm just
Like being somewhat shocked at what they've done to it
It's like it never stops you
Not guilty
And if you want to know a little bit more little more detail about the flashlight trick
Snarly tracking flashlight phenomenon
Check it out on our website radiolab.org Mexican food
Asterid explained in Greater detail
And also you can see some pictures of Dennis's house
Yeah that's all we can say at this
Holiday moment at their names I guess I'm Jedi Cam'ron and Robert krulwich thanks for listening