Are you awake
Northern listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
And NPR
Hey I'm Jared I'm rubber
Makovich is Radiolab and today
We're going to tell you is
Is an old soul
You will notice
And it comes to us from
Reporter Karen.
Yeah okay
Start am I feel like I could fly can I blame this on my dad
And that's the house I grew up in just so you know
Oh
No that was my my bedroom I know who is Karen in her dad looking at pics
Pictures of his childhood home in this Tiny Town in Idaho called Aberdeen Aberdeen
I forgot how on a potato farm
Like he thinks we saw live on a farm Garden
Pretty cool
So we were talking one day
And he mentioned very casually as if it's like something we all know he says
Yeah back when we had Nazi prisoners-of-war working on our farm
Nose like timeout what is parenthetical
Can potatoes and then yeah the Nazi prisoners of War were helping us
Starting to remember how old I was just buy out all the guards were
They were very tall he was only 3 or 4 it's
Burgerrito
Do you know if there were like
The prisoners
Or just like a
Info
Hello there was a bun
Even know there were prisoners of War
Masters of war in America
Yeah me neither
Okay yeah so that was the
So after I talk to my dad I ended up calling this
Historian Kathy
Cuz I wanted to know was this
Just
An Aberdeen thing no
Like you were talking about Idaho
She told me in Idaho alone
This Branch camps in Aberdeen and Blackfoot and Emma Taylor and
False
There were 23 different camp
General you had prisoners that were in churches Kent City sand
Rodeo ground dormitories
High School gym
And this was the case all across the country
The only
State that did not have prisoners of War
At the max
We had over 370 1000 Germans
Italians in 5000 Japanese
Almost half a million people
God why don't nobody know this
I don't even know it doesn't even like strike a little cord that maybe I once learned about it and
Junior High
No this was not talked about
We just don't talk about it we just don't
I think we don't
I don't know
But today we are going to talk about it
And not just physical historical thing but because
Raises a question breaking news this Nunes stunning report looking into how the CIA interrogated detainees
Question that you know
With the torture reports
Abu ghraib Guantanamo Bay
Today which is when you capture Navy Soldier taken out of the battle out of the fight how should you treat
That person and it's both sides agreed to follow certain rules and one side doesn't
What do you do
An interesting thing was it 70 years ago this question was playing out in this
Really dramatic way in
In all of these towns across America
There were about 200 basecamps that were huge they were like
To 8000
And by the way that's like seventy times the size of Guantanamo Bay currently
Case
That she was researching Karen sword to zoom into one camp in particular
So this is really a Lester tivid what happened
There's this one camp in Aliceville Alabama
It's a Tiny Town of like 1500
But the camp has
Thousand
I was like four times the size of the town
Yeah
So I went and interviewed a bunch of people guards prisoners locals
From Aliceville and
It was quite a day
That's Thomas sweet he worked in Ellisville
Any told me that the day that the prisoners came to a thousand of them came at first and the police were like nobody is allowed on the
But of course one word got out that the first
Try and load was coming
Everybody rushed out on the street today the train come in there wasn't supposed to be any townspeople
But the course that was
Everybody was saying his from 3 years old people
70 years old
So these voices are from an oral history project that was recorded in 1994 about the
The prison camp analysis
So we all kinda Lumbertown
So that we could
Liam when they got off the train everybody super nervous
Debbie's images in their head
Just like a lot of people that was really didn't know what kind of devils was going to get off that train
Guys with horns on their head
So these prisoners that were sent to Aliceville were actually part of
Rommel's Afrika Corps in these guys were the most feared of Hitler
Fighters that were supposed to be the elite
Superman right so if the train pulled up
They stopped right on the main Highway doors open
Hundreds and hundreds of German soldiers get out
And they were marching
German March
And they're singing their military songs in German
Tell us about forty.
What you thought when I got off the
What did they look like when you listen to the oral histories
Really clear that this was a really complicated moment for the people in Aliceville Mayfield owls for Westgate
I didn't know what I was going to be mad at him when they first come in or what but when I seen it it was just a bunch of
Cryptkins fan with a ceiling off
A concern
In our hearts for them
Hey young lady
Haggard looking washed out and meet room.
And somehow
Mad.
Grissom you could tell they been to a rough
It was over
Food 4 Less
That sounds good. He was one of the prisoners stepping out of the train that day
I've been drafted into the Army against his will and captured in North Africa and then he was sent to America in the
The bottom of the sea
Big cargo ship runs in one room
Clouded 700
Pizza
You couldn't even sit there was no toilet of course we had found it
Tim boxes
We all love it
Soapwalla deodorant
Was it awful trip and you kind of
But on the other hand and you hear this too in the oral histories
The people in Aliceville are thinking these are Nazis
These are the men who are killing our son will you know I had three brothers
I will cease at the same time
So
We didn't like
That's just the way we felt
They said there's that question in people's mind in this is playing out all across the country
Here's the enemy at your mercy
What do you do how do you treat them
They're in your hands nobody's watching
You can do whatever you want with them at that point in theory
In practice
Will actually this was a significant moment
For the world I mean 14 years before a bunch of countries have gotten together and they'd made-up rules
For exactly this kind of moment
1929 at Geneva
Long before Hitler and his Partners began to lie the real estate of the world
That was an International Conference
Erin Nations solemnly promise to uphold the rules governing the treatment of prisoners of War
So it was a series of
Do's and don'ts
That's a story in Arnold Kramer he's a professor at 6
And then some of the rules he says they're pretty basic
Women and children should be protected
She had to give prisoners a certain amount of food
And then there's rules about medical attention labor
Can use people for labor Kathy Kirkpatrick again you also should be paying people for labor
Payment was $0.80 a day the Geneva conventions are this attempt to kind of
Civilize the most uncivilized thing which is war
The first world war was so horrific
Hundreds of thousands of prisoners died in p o w Camp there were no real regulation
With regard to prisoners
Besides did almost anything you want
So the Geneva conventions of 1929 was an attempt to kind of set things right
Because people just
Couldn't fathom
Another
War 2 end
We were well-trained and
The Geneva Convention
Best Thomas sweet again he was actually one of the guards at Camp Aliceville
And what she said is that
Even before the pows arrived at the Geneva conventions were drilled into their heads they had lectures the rules were
Posted in the Rec Hall and
Officers Club where you had to the prisoners had to be treated the same
As you would
Your own fellow soldiers
Which sounds kind of basic
But for somebody like Han to Stepping off this train and wondering how
Is he going to be treated
I should say it was
A sort of
Heaven
When I got into the
The badge is all been laid out.
Red
Playing
They had
Styles and shaving equipment for each one on each other each one's bunk
The prisoners washed up and then the guards opened up the cafeteria
Then we got to eat good things this is water filter he's another prisoner at Alice
Big heart
Piece of white bread W American white bread
We got peanut butter
I didn't know about the
Are peanuts nuts
And chased it
Wonderful wonderful what's the best thing I ever had
And I think on which times and I think on peanut butter
Here's the funny thing
Did you look into this
You start to realize that we're not just following the Geneva conventions
The letter of the law we're going up
Above and beyond
And according to Hans
What started out as a great thing getting all this food ended up to be kind of a
Problem The Voice came to me everyday
Please tell him we don't want to have so much ham
And the Saxon came to me who got that
Don't tell the captain that you're ugly
Just throw it away now no no no no
Tay Keith
End
Make a hole in the sand and put it in the sand
So
They buried the hatchet
And and a lot of it
That is a lot of the him
Because we didn't know what to do with it
They also didn't like corn but they kept getting corn and so they bury corn
And then they get caught because corn starts growing
Everyone's like wait a minute bad corn hiding
Within two months they have an orchestra within a year they have three orchestras
This is a p o w LED Orchestra
They're making instruments the locals are donating instruments the YMCA is giving them instruments
They open a schools
Youcanlearnanything from Pottery to like mathematics almost any language you want to learn
They set up correspondence programs with the local universities you can get credit
About everyday they drew big crowds
They had a newspaper their newspaper was called the fence to guess and it had like
Poetry
They also did a lot of theatrical production and sometimes through a regular art shows
This is where things get a little bit strange
On December 18th
There was another artist
Exhibition
This is a woman named Ellen vander's whose father was a p o w at the camp
And here she's reading from his diary
December 12th
DEF fuel that means
Hitler
Had sent
$2
To open the Arctic
Exhibition in Camp
. she saying that way
Hitler
Send money to the camp for an art thing
Wow
Why were fighting Hitler he sending money
Why we're fighting Hitler
While we're fighting Hitler
Really strange
Monday
Coming up the fence gester on fence be buried Amazon buried and the Nazis next door being an argument
If we're still having to this day
I'm Tammy Pate from Spencer Indiana
Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation enhancing public understanding
King of Science and Technology
In the modern world
More information about Sloan at www.delone.org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
About what we're calling tiny moments
Brilliance
Basically I want to hear about those times when I kid you know did something
It just means you lean back and say wow how did they do that
Maybe it was the moment that I
Kids started reading back
Do you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lesson
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of their musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed they're writing music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the small specific moments where a kid does something super smart
Anything to do with the test
If you have a story
T-shirt with us
Go to radiolab.org
Brilliance
Record a short audio message for us
And that's where you live. Org / brilliance
Thank you so much
Gay I'm Jad abumrad
Acrylic
Radiolab
Toy Story ears
So so okay with Hitler's Christmas gift to the art show
And a ham
In the bands and all that stuff did people in the in the outside the camp know what was going on inside
Once they start so
I think it was in 19
43 was the point at which we started realizing we're running out of American men to do
Labor and
We look around and we're like
Actually we have
Quite a few men who might be able to do some work here
Thanking God
Peanuts
So some of the farmers would bring them in the house for lunch they would drink with them there were drunk
There's some really funny stories of like probably moonshine the prisoners getting drunk with the fire
Farmers and then they get in trouble cuz they come home late
One of the biggest things at the war department says when they start sending the men out is like if you if you make friends with these pows hits
Against the rules
They do it
All the time anybody fall in love with anybody
Oh yeah
I mean not a lot but it definitely happen
Suit as these prisoners are out in the community and their forming friendships
A few of them are falling in love where it starts to get out about
How they're being treated and meanwhile Across America there's rationing
That's when they learned that the
Pows are getting food that they might not be getting
A lot of the American public
Bigot
Especially this radio guy Walter Winchell
They calling The Rush Limbaugh of World War II
Supporters in America
Spokane is funny nasal but that's exactly what it sounds like
Find out about the Nazi pure W program Walter Winchell just starts to rant about it
Radio
And he would do this week after week
Start writing articles in the New York Times
Tribune the Boston Globe citizen start flooding the war department of letters
I know that y'all YMCA War prisoners Aid
Does all the time in the meantime according to Thomas sweet
Inside the camp some of these
Prisoners are
Starting to get kind of Bolt
For couple night side cutouts wall stickers
Took the title
Flying the Kite had to swap stickers in the box underneath the kite
With a string that down to the ground
And they handed the string to one of the
One of the guards and said
Turles Dragon when they pull the string
The Trappe door open on
The gadget that made
And always
Swastika
Over the camping in Aliceville to in the townspeople
Started calling the base
Mad about that
How to that
We don't have enough men to guard a lot of these camps so so the prisoners are starting to get more and more control of the camp
Presidents heads around as a cat
And some cases the Nazi hardliners would would starts at torment and now I'm not
Threaten them they might be
Beat them up there were even
A couple of murders was not a Nazi inside of you
I'm if you would had been drafted but you didn't you weren't Idol
So the perception is coming out of these camps
Is that we created these hotels on American soil where Nazis
Could start radicalizing and people get so mad
That there's actually a congressional investigation into the coddling of prisoners of War
So I spend a lot of time at the National Archives trying to get to like all right what are the arguments and and here's kind of how it was
But you have this
Congressman on one side Richard Harless and he saying you're cuddling them
And on the other side you have
The guy who's now running the prisoner-of-war program Archer alert and he's basically saying no
Jesus we're just following the Geneva conventions and the reason that he gave was the same reason that Joe Biden would give almost
60 years later
There's a reason why we sign these treaties
To protect
My son in the military
We are torturing them they'll touch that's why we have these trees
So when Americans
Our capture
They are
Not
Torture
That's the reason
Case anybody forgets it
At 3
One problem though
Just one month
After that hearing in 1944
Sound of a machine gun
News breaks that 84 American soldiers prisoners of War now in Germany are gunned down
After they surrendered
Later that frozen body
And the mangoes found
Found what I felt then go on to liberate American soldiers from pewww camps in Germany and refine
Nothing like Allah
American prisoners of War report in human Hospital conditions
Walter Winchell github
Airwave
Our generosity
And olive oil when I treat it
By the one side of Geneva Convention rules and if you
2 months later
Things get even worse
It was impossible to fully realize the horror of a Nazi concentration camps
We start going into concentration camps
Germans have done what the Nazis have done
Call sense of dead bodies were piled everywhere. Never having received
The Living Dead
The Congress decides to hold a second investigation into the treatment of prisoners
But this time it's
Real
Soul searching I mean we just seen the full horrors of the Holocaust were thinking you know anything we do to these guys
Guys at this point they deserve
We've also realized we're not really getting rest
Prosody the we don't really have
Medical reason to treat them well anymore
So at this point the question has really become do we continue to be good
Even when we're not getting anything in return
The kind of amazing thing to me is that we decide yeah
We're going to stick to the Geneva conventions
Archer alert to Runza pow program at this point he gets up and he says
We are not going to lower ourselves to Nazi standards we are not going to let the enemy decide Who We Are
Another country
And that argument stock
Yeah
I think that most people associated with the prison camp
Experience in Arnold Kramer against treated them well not because
They treated her as well
But that we are decent people and we probably would have done this anyway
What makes an American
It's not any special pressure sort of blood
But the tradition we have inherited
It's tradition
Rokblok
The problem with the way we think
I'm acting
There's a great belief
That we have a special mission
I am we have a special
History
This is David Goldfield he's a historian at UNC Charlotte
Now that's the
Baidu
But
No
I mean don't you only have to look
At the treatment of Japanese-Americans during World War II
It says don't forget
Right as we're giving the Nazis massive amounts of ham were also rounding up
Tens of thousands of
Japanese American citizen
Citizen
And we're throwing them into these
Cramps camp
That are way worse in Aliceville
And if you ask David why are we treating the Germans so much better
They look like
These people look all right
A mailman
The farmer
All look pretty much like a back home
The major reason
Race
The Germans were white
They seemed familiar
But there was
A connection
Between the German pows
And the folks in the American South
Not only because of
The ethnicity of
The Germans
Not only because of their economic benefit
To the region
David told us that he's looking
To the historical
Thanks
The German laws
Eventually
Copy
From
The Mississippi
Black Codes
We couldn't confirm that they were
Literally copy
But there are
There are similarities
A bunch of a fish
In that time
Praise Southern Raceway
So
There was already
Connection
Between the American South
And that's a German
This is the most horrifying thing ever
Is it really true that like all the niceness was just a perverse form of racism
Well I would say racism plays an enormous role in why Japanese citizens were interned in the first place I don't think there's any question about
That's Paul Springer he's a military historian Maxwell Air Force Base Alabama
All of this
He doesn't know what you got to be careful because you're comparing
Treatment of citizens
The treatment of prisoners of War
And that's different that's not a fair comparison
For the case of of why you treat the German pows better
Well because the prisoners of War
Japanese pows were also exceedingly well treated
They were treated much better than the Japanese citizens of the United States and I think that's the comparison
That's probably more interesting is why did you treat
Enemy soldiers from Japan
Better than you treated
Citizens of the United States of Japan
Heritage
And he says very simply that with prisoners of War
It's because we had a rule governing international law
Like the Geneva Convention
There's no similar law
At that time that says what you can and can't do towards your civilian population
It's like maybe we're not racist or Noble
But both
And it's the rules that allow us to be our better selves
I think that in a time of War it's incredibly difficult to be good to your enemy it's not Justa
About aspiring to be good this American ideal it's about having
Really nitpicky tiny tedious rules to tell you exactly what you can do
And what you can't do
Because it would just be
So easy to not be the person that you
Want to be
In that moment
Just going to make you think back to February of 2002
Good afternoon
I have an announcement to make
President Bush today has decided that
At the Geneva Convention
Will apply to the
The Taliban detainees
But not
The Arcada International terrorist
The president has maintained the United States commitment to the
The principles of the
Geneva Convention
I'll recognize him
Vention Sibley does not cover
Every situation in which people may be captured
Detained by military forces
As we see in Afghanistan today
Prisoners
Will not get any more protection than they already
Are given under the Geneva Convention what you seem to be telling us is that the
Detainees will get fewer
Nope there's no change in the protections they will be
Provided
There
They've always been treated consistent with the principles
Geneva Convention
Which means I'll be treated well
If you're looking for anything that will not happen.
As a result of this announcement is that they will not receive stipend
American taxpayer
They will not receive musical instrument
Courtesy of the United States military
They would have received those had they been declared pows
They will continue to be treated well
Because they're in the custody of America
That's the concern the debate here was about if you don't do it here
The US soldiers
To be mistreated abroad is not correct and so is not a big
A big motivation here
Did the u.s. soldiers get the same kind of treatment is important for all nations
Route the world
Treat any prisoners
Well
And that is something nice as always expect
And United States always.
Lakota
David
David will get one more
And then look around
Wasn't this an important concern
It was important for this Administration
To be able to say look we want to protect our soldiers
Equations
Down the line
And if we if we don't Accord
If you don't work.
Phillies out of the Geneva Convention in Arkansas to be in peril
I was not in the NFC deliberations were various
Issues were raised inside really just no way I can actually answer that question
Horses they don't they often do not wear uniforms they often do not carry their weapons out really if they're captured
If they wouldn't be convention apply to all and those turn speaker themselves
Okay thank you
Thank you
Two reporter
Karen Duffin and also pretty sure Kelsey Pageant this is such a long and involved for voting process big props to them
Special thanks to Sam love the filmmaker who collected all those Aliceville oral histories to John Gilliam and Marybeth
Veloute current
Informer
Ellisville Museum directors Ruth Beaumont cook who wrote a great book about the
Campana
Mac Pro
Young Jedi boomerang
Ira Berkowitz
Tanks for Less
Message
11 this is Kathy Kirkpatrick
Credit Radiolab is produced by
I staff includes Brenna Farrell born
Dylan Keith
Not guilty and emails
Melissa O'Donnell Chelsea pageant
Molly Webster
Lauren Wheeler and baby York
With help from Danny Lewis
Kelly Prime
Damiano marchetti
Perfect Checkers or either gushers and Michelle Harris
Thank you
I like to hear the message again and this message