Are you awake
Northern listening to Radiolab
Radiolab
From WNYC
And NPR
381 hey I'm Jared I'm Robert krulwich Radiolab
This
Like this
This is Alex Bellos
Okay he's a writer he's written a lot about sports a particular Brazilian soccer but also mathur he likes
And
When I sweat my face my butt
Here's looking at Euclid
I went and got a loser
And the end of the tour
Always be someone to put their hands up
What's your favorite number
This used to
Irritate me because
My bicep that have a favorite number
You don't have a favorite number
No I think it's stupid
I did think it was stupid
I just didn't have
Where when why would the question annoying to me it's the most normal question you could ask
But this is my number this is this is he's talking about a math book to math enthusiasts what's your favorite number is
Like sort of a
It's like it's too silly or maybe it's like they making fun of them once
I think I was bit tired it was like
What's your favorite number
Turning it back at the post in the old days
And they said
Oh 12
You weren't asking me because you were kind of taking the piss out of the 👄
Actually really wanted to know
Play 4 number
I'd like for you
Antidepressant
I'm in my mind 7
This is interesting and I can remember about who he is going to favorite number
At least half the people put their hands up
In a wave
UK from being a smoker when you stop smoking to be I went from being
Agnostic
Obsessed with favorite website favorite number
I know just asking people to hit the question I put it out of that
And I helped them out on my blog and I had within the first few weeks I sleep over 30,000 people
How high
From all over the world
My name is sattar from Dubai Aaron skit
Sydney Australia my favorite number is definitely 8:30
29:11 of the reasons why reasons for is because my favorite card is there
Spades
It's commonly called the death card my birth date
59 Saum 5 from 9
For my favorite number is 100 because it has two zeros
Okay here's what's fascinating about this least of me first of all
The volume of
Response he got about
30000 submissions
All over the planet
We put out a call in our app
Which are the voices you listen to
Hiiraan
We got 30000
No
I clearly people want to talk about their favorite numbers and about the reasons which are
From the
The number 5
Was always a friend
Feels Like Home and Family
It's kind of hole and balance people talked about it any motion
Really warm is
Home Instead office just inviting
Is this a hole in
Emotional landscape
Sitting here under the number 2 nothing to do the number
They are it was there from the very
Where do numbers come who invented
Well it depends what you mean by number
If my numbers mean this idea that we can tell the difference between two things and three things
Well then we've had that ever since
The humans existed and
You can test on animals
But if you're talking about symbol
And worth
Abstractions to designate specific numbers
This is probably only about 5000 years old
And was an invention of the Sumerians
Iraq and Alex's from the moment they came up with
Lantana
Extra layers
Utterly unknown number e stock price
Like I just take the Sumerian word for one
Apologies for my accident in Sumerian
Mycenaeans been very rough
Guess
Which is GES
Japan
Or have you
Say that that's the word for one and that is also the word and the word for two
Mend meaning of the word for woman and one can anybody speculate but there
Why one is mad
It was women it could be
Could be they had some sort of Adam and Eve
Notion in mind like me first
You second
Could be
I'll distinguishing feature is
We have one of
What makes up a mine
And that woman has
Two breasts
Whatever they were thinking they were not the only ones to be thinking along
You go forward three thousand years
3000 years later you get to
Pythagorean
Yes it is repeated
The one is male to female
Thanks
By saying that
Old numbers
Masculine
Even numbers
What's feminine even tried to justify besides little to do that do the calculation
When you add even to odd
Say 3 + 2
You get all
Which means that when you add
Man swimming to get man said man
Is coming stronger
Shenzhen women
By that logic odd plus odd
Makes even
What is that two males make a female I mean it the whole thought is
A little far-fetched to me
So that is Steve Stroker
Professor of math at Cornell regular on our show friend of Radiolab
Thinking about
But here's what's weird is it you'll go 5000 years after the Sumerians it right up to the present time when Alex does
Is this worldwide survey
What's your favorite number
You something
Beauty familiar I will just read you for example
Some of the adjectives
In reasons why people
Preferred the number one
Strong strong
Independent
Honest Brave
Brave
Pioneering
Lonely lonely
Cowboys lose your tablet words
A picture of the number one
A man in a really nicely tailored Italian suit he's got dark hair
I don't know why
Marcello mastroianni
John Wayne
Kolaches
Wise
Pretty
Soft nurturing
Call Rodger
Very personal
Unintimidated
Friendly sympathetic
Complimentary
Easy-to-understand flexible
Makes more sense
Become feminine
Estereotipo
These are both men and women
Contributing these descriptors for these two not number
Yeah yeah that was really striking to me and it made me think
We could always offer Pythagoras in the Sumerians and all the candidates
People saying well one is male and Taurus female
It's some fragments of that remain
What does raises not like
A scientific study
Well actually
The movie look
There's kind of some science
Behind it
In fact there's a guy
Understudy
A place you know
James Wilkie assistant professor of the University of Notre Dame so James what they do
Take a baby that's just been born to be a few weeks old
Impossible to say
Just for the face whether it's a boy or girl
I'll see you together 50s
They show people pictures of you androgynous little babies and buried over in the side
We would hardly notice
The heartstrings of
4 5 digit numbers
Numbers having to either all even or all odd
Right and James guy say don't worry about it
They they're their there for the storage
These are tracking numbers
Go ahead and ignore these just focus on the babies in the
Pictures and tell a male or female
Just look at the face and tell us whether to Mahler if he had it turns out that if a baby is next to all digits
You're more likely
Say that it's a boy
That if the baby is next
Even digit
Really
Whip with a how much more likely by a lot or buy a teeny bit
Statistically significant amount not allowed
Do you yourself assign any gender to other one do you find odd
Other than one male
And some no not at all
No no
They were a bit different
Feel different
So he decided to invest
Just to see if there's anything behind it
Yeah why not
Which led him a note to a guy named Greg
Roland okay
Okay this is Robert producer working with Robert
Can you just tell if you have a peculiar job I guess
Ashley's peculiar to me like what what do you do well I found it
Put the semiotic Alliance
Which is a business
It is a consultant
See ya the Greg is
Hey very good money by some of the biggest brands in the world Coca-Cola for by BM to give them advice about how
How the Browns will go down we
Look at people's emotional response
Is to coccia symbols and ideas on the basis of this we can help
Companies with packaging habit
Appetizing and what that means is he's helping companies harness the symbolic power of numbers
I think one of the most exciting
Encounters with mathematics for me was with KFC
With the 11 herbs and spices
11 which is kabbalistic and it's in his secrecy
Such a strange number for I thought the Colonel Sanders was in his experimental kitchen
Understand you just happened
He said
Colonel Sanders was in his kitchen and he was just fiddling around he came up with 11
Herbs
Because it hurts here and spice well that's one version of the truth but
The symbolic tree
It's far more interesting and potent
11 has an enormous
Mystical potential simply because it's not
10 or 12:05 is not a sensible number what's wrong with 10
If I say
With my 10 herbs and spices with 10 you implying that you have a decimal.
It's going to hop it very hard to engage people emotionally
With with Tenten feels order
Feels
Heidi rational
Racism and something to do with the fact you have only
10 fingers are looking
And a 7-Eleven just is that extra water
That has
Made Colonel Sanders
Uncopyable and the same thing might be happening with 501 jeans like
The why is it 501j
And not
5 of 1
Again it's just the one Beyond
The place you would expect to get
But way to say what if you don't want
What if you want a product
Where you get plates safe
Well
Then you can stick with multiples of 10 which is really useful when you're trying to be
Practical or scientific absolute
Free sample
We're winning the war against it take the acne cream oxy 10
You and your face I know you're not entirely comfortable
The tender is obviously you know that's where we get to a solution that's where all fingers are has run out
So there is a sense of completion there
Censored we go through the process and we're going to come out okay
Equus sy11 that is interesting cuz you're you're a barking into the infinite
I'm at that point you're going to be on the human finger account
Herbs and spices
Triton
Now
Did you say that as if you want to taste the thing I do like I used to
Is it did the 11 is the 11 number 11 some tickle you in anyway yes
Definitely would not buy it with 10 herbs and spices that sounds very solid and
Stalinist
Really
No I'm yanking I'm yanking I'm yanking your Wishbone
I don't mean it no come on
I got to go to Steve like the idea that 11 is Mystical because it's one more than 10
Although with 10 if you get
It is boring
I agree you're just a fact
Big companies with large checkbooks
Call Greg up all the time
Stupid thing about numbers is it because they are so rational
ISO abstract
Adult very reason
Boston Subway Bazaar
I think human beings have it absolutely needs to invest
Emotion love hate fear who vested non-rational
Into things which seem almost obscenely rational
My magic number
Is number eight
I turned
Teen on October 18th 1988 number for because I've won
Swimming race in Maine for as a child
Because to me it recalls to mind
The Trinity know how are you feeling about all this
Steph one thing that you pretty interesting to Alex as you'd expect if you were asked
The world to give you a favor
The number that be a huge difference
From one culture
The next 13 is an unlucky number you don't have a 13th
Flooring America
In Korea they didn't have a fourth floor cuz it's unlucky for over there
But here's something
The entire planet all the continents and everyone in all the continents
Came to kind of consensus around 1
Yeah so tell me
Alex
What was
The worlds
Favorite number
I hope you got some good with a drum roll coming up movies
787 my favorite number is 7 number is number 7
Much the same thing
It's like a pixel 3
Acai places that nobody was a big win for 7:30 % ahead of 3
Feel is the favorite number
But why is it the peep
People's favorite number
And when did that begin and I have one
Oh great I love hearing reason holes in your head
Years
2 + 21
Narcissist
Looking for
Yai 607
Seven Hills
There's no way that can
Well then look up at the night sky and be a Mesopotamians you don't have a telescope what do you see the sun
On the moon at 5 Planet 7
Turn all night looking at 7
That's not what you hear
Number 7 just looks beautiful what you hear from people is about how big
Beautiful
I like the way it looks when I write it was good-looking number
Sounds beautiful sons perfect people came in
Sound
I get on that train I think 7 comes out of your mouth real nice
Set
I just don't feel like the number 7
Belongs to me
May I guess
It even sounds good in Arabic
Yeah
Hebrew Sheva
Really similar
Sit this makes me feel a little
Sad
Not to get silly on you but
There's a certain pleasure that people are getting that I'm not getting
Prime numbers
Ever cuz
I feel like
Like someone says 8 is curvy
Artemis
Feels
You're talking about the shape of the way that we draw them
The number 8 as a numeral
That has nothing to do with the number 8
It's the way I see you say 8 to me I see
I don't see eight apples I see that curd I see the two circles one on top of another resting Comfort makes me that makes me sad
That makes me feel like you're missing the reality of the number 8 which is
The date has intrinsic
Property that's really dry speak
At 8
8 is a
I mean
Like 10 okay 10 to me
Is much more like when you go to the bowling alley
And the Ten Pins are lined up in that triangle pattern
You know what I'm talking about there's the one and the two than the 304
That is a gorgeous way to think about 10
10 is about this magnificent symmetry that can make a triangle
But seven is a disaster as a mathematical
Object
I mean
It doesn't have nice symmetry
If I tried to put bowling pins down with 7 it's it's ugly however you arrange it
Tumi
So it makes me feel left out that I can't have the same fun
That other people are having
Okay but if you ask Alex why is 7 the world's favorite number
He says
Because seven is arithmetic
Glee unique
Is the only digit
The first 10 numbers
Can either be multiplied
O divided
Within the group
So 1 2 3 4 5 we can double them and they stay under temp in the group
What's left
I have 6 8 and 10
As you can
And the ones laugh
7 + 9
And then you can divide by 3
So
Is unique
Do you think that there's enough arithmetic in everybody
I without having worked it out as painfully as you just did
People will
Still fine there's something unusual about 7
Mathematica
Not about memories not about culture not about shave just about the method self
You can't separate the math world of those things the weight we
Understand numbers is to do with a rhythmic
And it's the arithmetic is being absorbed by culture
The greatest example of that
Is the predominant
Ab7
As the most
Special religious mystical number. There is
So you thinks it's not so much
That they culture has gotten in the math still around at the math actually was there first and then Dad got into the culture
Alright you making me feel better
Would you like to thank somebody I would I like to thank Steve Stroh gas once again for joining us whenever we call her
I like to thank Alex Bellos
The book is called The Grapes of math how life reflects numbers and numbers
Hey we should go again I'm Jedi
Thanks for listening
Christine Quintana from Vancouver BC
Radio
Is the port in part by the National Science Foundation
By the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Lansing public understanding
Science
Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloan
Www.