Are you weightless
Radio WNYC
And NPR
Okay sir Robert you know that like talking about music in a way that's compelling to be kind of hard.
Project build a bridge into a well
I feel like you Gotta Give him props
And I just ran into a really great podcasts that I think everyone should be listening to is called meet the composer
It's from Hue to music which is sort of the digital sister station and wqxr
And
Kind of what it sounds you know every episode they introduce you to one composer
But they do such a good job of seducing you
Into listening and maybe caring about music you wouldn't normally listen
Care about
I just thought you I really want to play some of their latest episode for you because
They just focus on one of my favorite composers a guy by the name of John Luther Adams
Show the Opera
Guy Jenna
John Luther Adams
Different genres
Any other guy I've heard of John Quincy Adams was he was a former president
This John Adams
Is a composer
Who makes music tutor Congress he's wide open spaces the kind of invite you in
It also seems to have been different to you and maybe
Mike Williams it has that kind of feeling to it
I'm intrigued okay so how does it begin
Nightmare begins
By the way it's hosted by Nadia Sirota it begins
With John Luther Adams as a boy playing in a rock.
Imagine fourteen-year-old John in a cover band in New Jersey opening for acts like Buffalo Springfield
And playing predominantly the 3 B's for the face The Beatles
The Beach Boys and the birds
Okay
So we started out as cover bands
And
I got bored with that
One side of my buddies and
Oh over time we started trying iron pan dad at songwriting and
I was a big fan of Frank Zappa
Frank Zappa the teetotaling 1960s
Musician and polymath with wildly eccentric tastes spanning from Rock to Jazz to European modernism
Play gets me off as good as some contemporary classical pieces and on the back of
Frank's early LP is there would always be this
Intriguing little quotes
The present day composer refuses to die
My Little Rock and Roll buddies and I wouldn't be dad and scratch I had someone Darrell
Who is this crazy guy
Ends of one day my friends think I'm horn was rummaging through the
Condensed shopping list College
And came across
This album with this mad scientist on the cover letter
Great shock of electrostatic gray hair bushy eyebrows
Stern countenance in the title was the music of Edgard Perez
Volume two
So he brought it home and we quickly
What are the groups
Just all sounds like a bunch of noise to me
We have this desert does ocean this
Is forbidding mountains of of sound
I remember thinking
I'll never be able to know where I am in this
Don't know what to hang on to
So your response to what is this music was just too
Immerse yourself anymore to any new experience
Courage
Young Musicians special young composers going to listen to everything you can get your ears on especially the stuff you think you did
Don't like I started to realize all okay there's that repeated
Notes on the oboe and okay that's a landmark I can grab onto that no one hears this place where
Tattoo figure with a snare drums in these units and stabs in the rest of percussion there
Gradually we begin to learn how to listen to
The forbidding deserts of rent
Did that affect the music you guys were making the process that was already underway was just accelerated we
We rapidly abandon the the 1-4-5 chords and the BackBeat
And the four bar phrases
And started discovering cage Feldman and then Carol and Pauline oliveros endurance crossword
On and on
So thank you Frank Zappa
Isle of the Dead
Who is his response to music bed
You know can be defined as very alienating
I mean it's not easy stuff
No
But instead of just writing off his ugly he was like
Ugly how to turn in case just to skip forward a little bit in the music composer hour from Q2
John Luther Adams goes off to school
He has a teacher named I believe it
James Tenney one of his first big influences body goes off to school at calarts
And right afterwards he meets one of his next
I had just left calarts
Haven't yet gone to Alaska
I would take long
Walks in the early morning and again at dusk
And I became captivated by
This
Singer that I kept hearing deep in the woods and I could never
Find the bird box
I couldn't get enough of the song
I started taking notes
The birds became
My teachers
After James Tenney
And the result was a series of
Pieces that I composed between 1974 and 79
Cold simply Songbird song
What
Was the translation process between
Hearing this Birds on that you just couldn't get enough of and constructing
A narrative
In working with the bird songs I just
Try to take dictation I try to listen
Carefully to the birds
Where they are as they're singing
And write down what I hear
I'm not interested in
Accuracy
Because if I were I just
Make a recording and play the recording
I'm interested in what gets Lost in Translation because after all this is music this is perhaps a language
That we will never
Understand
Also there weren't very many field recordings available in those
Those days but there were some and I decided no I'm not going to use them
I really wanted to hear them and to learn them
For myself
I was actually very different from the way I work
Much of the time
Rather than working with very specific
Details of the music and then building
He's up I usually sculpt away the whole field of sound and I work with one
Big
Jaipur
Image War
Color or atmosphere than that I have in mind that I can't quite hear but I want to hear
And
Try to hear that since that
Write that down as clearly as I can
And then all the moment-to-moment details
AllMusic follow
We're listening to excerpts from
An hour of computing music
From their fantastic series meet the composer
This one is on the composer one of my favorites John Luther Adams
Song burpees
John's living in LA
And it gets kind of fed up
I hated Los Angeles the whole time I was there I felt
Lost and not in a good way
It was such an interesting contrast because it was one of the most
Closest periods of my life in terms of of discovery
But at the same time other was asking to enter knowing I just felt lost in the freeways and
All that sprawling City that seem to just go on forever
It made me long for home
Which I never felt that I had because we moved all the time and I'd run up here and there and equally
Homogeneous Suburban surrounding inarticulate hunger to find a place to which I might
Belong the place where atoms belong
It turns out was off the grid in Wild open spaces
I went North in the summer of 1975
Psalms 20
Shoe that summer ends from the moment I tried to enjoy downtown
When you showed up in Alaska
What did you see what did you hear that made you feel like you knew you were home
Where to begin
It all really starts
MSR 1975 one
First canoed across Admiralty Island went into Glacier Bay and hiked on the tundra Denali
Eventually made my way to the port range to the Arctic
You know there was and still is
Hand
Those places
A sense of
Open this and space and
Possibility
As well as
Danger
These are Big places in which we feel very very small
Only realized that
We're in significance and the place doesn't care if we are there or not
And
The weather
Or the bear
Orla River
Can rise up at any moment in snuff me out
And you know I find a certain
Reassurances certain profound comfort in that
I was trying to reconnect
With
The larger
Older
World
That that we still inhabit but that we
That we forget
Unalaska
Allow me to feel
Like I was the only person in that place
Turn the summer of 1977 I visited the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge and we Flew Over the crest of the
Strange and out onto the coastal plain the Arctic coastal plain in there the distance was the ice and
And of course the song even
Even a midsummer the Sun
Doesn't get very high in Horizon so this is
Incredible deep warm saturated light the colors in the shower
Shadows and everything
Stands out and then you get out on the tundra and
You lose all sense of scale
I remember one evening with a buddy we are so excited to be alive and out and that Arctic
Ceiling light
And we saw this White Rock
I'll cross the tundra analysis odd looking things that well
When we walk over there only hook to that rock
Show me high
Bill kristol
Country is not easy to walk on
But we kept walking we kept walking and you know that the rock didn't get any closer
So we kept walking
Suddenly stop
Because
The Rock flew away
Iraq was a snowy owl
Sitting on the tundra
And apparently could have been a 12-foot outcropping of Whitestone you dispute
You lose yourself in that place in that wide into that endless space and that's what I'm
Morning music that's a beautiful ordering bits from
Q2 music
Meet the composer Series this one on John Luther Adams
Continue the moment
This is Darlene calling from Kampala Uganda
Rachel app is supported in part by the National Science Foundation and by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloane @www.
Sloan. Org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help this summer I'm hosting
And I request for those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
We're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments of childhood Brilliance basically
Kids you know did something
It just means you lean back and say wow how did they do that maybe it was the moment that a kid
And you'd been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons and you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin
Maybe the kids in math class you noticed they're ready music in the margin of their geometry homework we're interested in
Epic moments where a kid does something super smart but it doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story please share it with us
Go to radiolab.org brilliance
Record a short audio message for us
Again that's radiolab.org / Brilliance thank you so much
Where is Radiolab and we're taking a
This podcast to represent some music
I'm a
Tanya Roberts
And I'm not I'm not good I take that as a sign of success
End of the exercise you've been hearing come from Q2
Is a wonderful series meet the composer
Particular hour that they've just produced on the composer John Luther at
2 after I move to Alaska begin to make these amazingly huge
Sometimes the rain sometimes violent pieces
And you know what I think about one of yours work
Give me when I first encountered Looney Tunes
And the way that the lexham
Has assertive and inherent
Meaning to it
Feels like falling
Put some music of action pumping pumping tiptoeing
Bonking all these things have been kind of musical expression that feels almost like a physical language that we came into the world
With never had to learn
And when I went to music school
It was so
Difficult indents
Because suddenly I was thrust into this world of contemporary classical composition
It was all about
Understanding
The rigorous
Serial twelve-tone composition which is like you created in the mathematical systems that guide your choices
I was like I don't know what the
I don't understand this
And then you hear it you like I might your can't pick up on it I feel lost
You feel like you're literally in the forest
Then I
I didn't count composers like John Luther Adams where it wasn't about that at all
Selling a primal it's about like the movement of body see no masses of sound that serve crescendo-decrescendo.
Waves I do think of the sounds of musical forms and events as
Forces
As natural elements in some way
And
They may sounds ridiculously grandiose
Or laughably naive
But I've always imagined that I might be able to work in a space that's
Just outside of culture
Course is patently absurd
There's no way that we work outside of a culture
Police tase so many cultures
And yet is my friend Barry Lopez the writer says landscape is the culture that contains all human call
Vultures
And I believe that everything
We do everything we think everything we think we create
Who sing We Are The Rives
From the world we inhabit
R language
Our music are our minds
Everything is is shaped by
Incredibly
Complex and wondrous world that we inhabit
So ultimately this nature culture dichotomy
In a way doesn't exist
But it's been a useful conceit
For me to see all that I'm after something that that is
It's not
Part of the musical tradition
It's not specifically cultural it's somehow more
Elemental
Where does music come from
How does a composer take an assignment like write an 11-minute piece for string quartet
Translate those instructions into a concept into notes
Into a score
Free composer John Luther Adams it seems almost like the transformation happens in his sleep
I try to resist
Composing for as long as I can I really want to get it something
Essential
Before I start
Manipulating notes
Pushing things around
I try to hold things in my mind ear as long as I can it's at its
Maybe an inefficient way to work but it has worked for me
I find that if I'm trying to remember
Trying to hear something that I can't
Quite
Name it focuses my attention
In a certain way and then I finally
Start composing when I can't not impose
When I have to write it down
Thinking about like the way that we are discovering how memory and the brain works and every time you remember something you're actually recall
Creating a story
So I really like that you have an idea and you are continually remembering it so basically you're making a lot of mental Xerox is a
Yeah over and over again until it becomes something which is so steeped in your brain stuff
But it is
It is a piece
Exactly
So night after night
When I lie down to go to sleep I'm
Imagining
This
Group of
Instruments
In this particular space in
What they might
Sound like end
How they might move through the space
Physically and through the musical space of
The peace
And it's repetitive I'm doing it every night
Certain point I lose it and I drift off
To sleep
That nocturnal composition process
Is apparently what happened with John Luther Adams
Most
Recent most famous piece
The B-side I literally tried to copy
During a recent apocalyptical tour in the Pulitzer Prize
Apparently John was spending some time near the Pacific Ocean and you would fall asleep to the sound of ocean waves
Steeped in his dream
And what emerged
We finally start to
Compose was
This
Orchestral piece for three orchestras actually it's called commotion
What happens in the pieces that over the course of about 40 minutes
All three orchestras
Form these massive swells of sound like these three huge crescendos like massive tsunamis
Crashing over you
I'm talking about the title of a beast become ocean John Legend
Adam said life on this Earth First emerged from the sea
The polar ice melts and sea levels rise we humans find ourselves facing the prospect
It once again
We make quite literally
Become ocean
Well. In a conversation with wqxr is Helga Davis this is a global warming piece
And I would say everything that I do these days is in some way
Addressing the state of the world and the Delicate Sound of precarious position of we human Anna
Animals in the world
And yet I will also out of the other side of my mouth insist that it has absolutely nothing to do with
With current events or politics or activism and that music
Must stand on its own as
Music
And
I like to believe that we can have it both ways
She's very very Outdoors
It's without
Like it doesn't have people in it at all
That's just
Openness yeah yeah
You're floating on the surface
If you're there at all
One of the many reasons you should go to iTunes and download queue to meet the composer
Hour with John Luther Adams if they play this
Unreleased track of his string quartet
I called the wind in High places
Go to radiolab.org we will link you
Two more information about
Meet the composers
Highly recommend this podcast
Thank you so much to Nadia Sirota Alex Overton and Thea chaloner and Alex Ambrose
For allowing us to place mixer
I'm Jedi Cam'ron
I remember krolick
Thanks for listening