Are you awake
Northern listening to Radiolab
Radiolab
From WNYC
And NPR
Hey I'm Jared I'm Roberto but you should Radiolab podcast
Okay so Robert here's a question that I've been puzzling over
For a long time
What is the fruitiest fruit
I'd let you know
My food is fruit is a plum
Well now I mean that's well that's yours
You know you shouldn't
When you ask most people that question they say
Apple
Orange
No I mean it's true
Side of the figured out that when you make a category in your mind you're not doing it based on
Setlist
Traits
You're like
You quit you do you call to mind
D prototypical example
Of that category and then you measure this new thing against it
And for fruits
Prototype is the gala apple
If you asked me to
Red shiny waxy Apple you say there's somebody has decided that an apple is the fruity fruit experiment
Experiment bananas
Call Apple
Consumption Maybe
I bet. That's not what makes a fruitiest fruit
Fruity fruit
It's more about like how well it represents
The category
That's what it's about who we talkin about this though
Well because I've been wanting to explore this in story form
Forever
Could you never have a story so that's like a you never find a store but I got one now
You did what it's not about Frito what is about
About this
What is the weather
Let me explain
So I met this guy Andrew Marantz I work at the New Yorker as an editor and I
Right Stuff
Occasionally 100 in here one day by mistake I think Super interesting guy Gregory Porter and he end up talking with us
About this story was reporting for the New Yorker
But they're all
Kinds of rappers
And how hip-hop might be changing
As we all know this was a genre of music that began
Really specific time and place
Bronx
70s black and Latino kids
But it's since expanded
So much
It is inevitable questions pop
You know what to really simplify it
The more white people come to the party
The
More you kind of start going okay at what point is it
It's clearly a it can clearly it's really okay if everyone in the room is black
And it's okay if everyone is black except for one guy you know if ya if Rick rubin's at the party
But it's still
You know black people at the tunnel
In 1989 or whatever it's still okay
But
At what point okay with its 50% white if it's 75% wife
If all the people who own the record labels are white if
A majority of the popular rappers are white like at what point
Yeah then there's also that sonically the way it sounds there's the way the production is going to merge with other forms of music
So then all the sudden you're at a point where
You get the sense that there's somehow inherently
That there's something being replaced
We're taking over you start to have this
Dilemma
Which is
You know who owns the music now and
The Dilemma is obviously heightened by the fact that
Everyone knew this was coming
Like if there's never been a form of American popular music
As far as I know that wasn't invented by black people and co-opted by white people
And Andrew in his peace
I need the story of focuses on a guy who sits right
Part of that
One of the most influential DJs in hip-hop today
Peter Rosenberg
So tell me tell me how you came to him I mean the first
Thing was
Torn hip hop radio station
Listening to
That part 97
Because I
Like crap and I want to know
What is popular
And I was
Listening and I heard this guy who they kept calling Rosenberg
And I was like is that Rosenberg is that like Whoopi Goldberg
Rosenberg like what does that mean
And then I looked
Him up and I was like nah
The guy
Named Peter Rosenberg one two one two one two one two I mean listen to NPR is already pretty soft and I'm saying
Exe works just on the black
This going to hurt your credit
So he's a
Guy born in 1979 he grew up and I grew up in Chevy Chase Maryland
It is heavy with a c h
Peter says
News about 9
Your brother my brother's name is Nick Rosenberg Brother start staying up late making tapes
DJ Red Alert Marley Marl
He would start taping those
Guys on the radio
At that point 1987-88 here in New York they were the only two people playing hip hop
Late at night I didn't consider myself a music person
I just obsessed with sports
And then at some point
I was like oh no
I love
This
It was pocket was rebellious it was interesting it was just a little
You're now to be honest
It's almost
Cliched when people say that like
Who would ever guess you'd be into hip-hop I'm like I don't know
I would cuz I know a million white kids weren't Hip Hop
At that time though
It was not,
It is very much something that was a badge of honor for
For both of us that we really
Really loved it I was extra cool cuz I was
Superyacht
I remember one day here's a great thing
I traded
Jovan
My poison taste
I had
Poisons album
Every Rose Has Its Thorn album
I traded that
Poison tape for his
Biz Markie face
I was like
This is the best trade ever
It was business going off like it's a class
Album
And then it ended at some point my dad went out he was coming home from work one day and he said he stopped
Didn't nobody beats
The Wiz
He asked the guy behind the counter what like the good rap album
And I the kid actually gave him a pretty good recommendation and he bought me a
Called girls I got them locked by super lover Cee & Casanova rud
Are you have I know
So my knowledge base was always very
Very high very early
Item friend in elementary school we would talk about rap a little bit but quickly I exceeded them
And then I got to high school and I really took C
Seriously being the rap guy
What I heard the passion in Public Enemy like
That resonated with
I got the NWA
Scared me
What made me interested
I just thought this is
I was like yo these guys are killing people
Like this is really happy
I was really happy we going to the movies and song for I was going to the movies but to me I didn't know the line
Okay so Peter goes off to college mid-90s to College radio hip hop show
Then as he gets out decides he wants to do this for real
He secretly Mina wanted to be a hip-hop DJ but
People would not take him seriously you know why kid from the suburbs
Didn't compute couldn't get on what was then called Urban radio
Signs of doing a year on the Howard Stern station Eastern like talk radio you know
Whatever kind of radio
So he
Kept calling Hot 97 and the program director then was a white guy from Utah
I was like I'm super passionate about Hip Hop
I'm super honest
I don't think there's ever been someone
Who looks like me and is from my background
Who has is honest and louder voices me I really think I'll be something
Any business that I don't doubt you
But
We talked about
I mean they had
Token white people on various shows
But it was either your super white like Lisa G she was on the morning show for a little while after that she was super white
And that was kind of a joke
Or you were Bobby konders
Who does the Sunday Night Radio reggae show who you would never know he's wife
Joppa Flats
Because he just talks like he's Jamaican and the only place to make music The only things out Jamaican people
So you had to be one of those
Two things where you denied your whiteness or are you just
Extra like I'm going to I'm going to be the butt of the joke
White bosses have often been like you're really talented
But I don't know what people really like you like we don't
They talk to me the way you were talking right now
NSYNC if I'm able to relate
Why would our audience relate to you
If I say yes then why would my audience say yes with me because because they assume Their audience is so different than
Send them
For a while and then 2007 Ebro Darden took over Ebro Darden in the building
How you doing sir
On air
Ebro
Black half Jewish guy from Oakland
And he got it
The hip-hop it changed it's no longer so small and simple and provincial
So we can go on pretending this is only a black and white
Thanks so when Peter came to the station and gave me
Vetch AMPM deep which was my old name back then cuz I'm p
P4 Peter MD for Maryland you can call me EPMD
Andy Burrows like know you're Rosenberg
Ebro gave me my parents
More less
He's like the hook is that that's your name
Hot 97 Peter Rosenberg Summer Jam 2007 there's a video on on YouTube
Call Denny Peter Rosenberg does Summer Jam 2007
And it was my first day on the job
Summer Jam is the biggest
Events
Of the year at Hot 97 is this big
Show at Giants stadium all the topics
I showed up there until my first day was just walking into Giants
Parking my car by myself
Getting a backstage pass
And being given a mic flag that says Hot 97 the place I've always wanted to work
And being told
Go up to all the famous artists or here and just getting here
And if you go back and watch that video and see how much of an ass I make of myself
I say
Itsy I think I go is this your first Summer Jam and he looks at whoever
Fries with
And they both start laughing
Happy first day on the job
And I cannot believe in that respect I survived
This day
Now we survived you became the host of two shows on Hot 97 a late-night underground show
And also the big weekday Morning Show and
Rosenberg's brand is all about real name
The real
Is second in the morning is called the realness
Is late night show Sunday night to Monday morning is called real late with Peter
It's all real real real it's going to be real
Is it real cuz that's the best
Essential question
Can I be a real hip-hop guy
Even though I'm Peter Rosenberg
Suburban Maryland
I think you're I think you're raising interest
Sandpoint
Most Outsiders rarely beak
Come inside her
Peter says the key to understanding him is that he's kind of
One handy is the Suburban white kid from Maryland because it's going to be anything but
But on the other hand meme a big part of rosenberg's job is to go to shows and blogs and get tips from people in find
The new thing
So he has a stable of like
20 or 30 underground artists
For making tapes and you know trying to pass around beat
What's more inside of me than that
Plus
He is like a purist
I I've always liked
Are there certain pure form of hip-hop
And because you know in the kind of rap nerd community
They talk about certain things that are like
We are actively listening for the metaphors in this the intricacies of the music
They talk about boom-bap Beats
Big Sean
Trump lies
Boom bap
Spell check the hi hat
It's just a feeling of sound of energy
This is a lie
Ali Shaheed Muhammad
A Tribe Called Quest We called him up because he is the DJ and producer for a drive
Called Quest for Peter
Tribe
There's a prototype I was obsessed with them
They were they are like that shiny red apple day to find the category in fact
I guess up until my wedding weekend best weekend of his life
I guess now would be second-best
Was when he was I was 14 you went to a tribe show it was
Everything I ever dreamed a hip-hop concert experience would be
He says he spent the whole time at the front of the stage waving his hat around that said dogs
D a w g s is one of lead rappers is named Fife
And I held up my dogs
So much
At the concert that eventually fight
V v v v dog acknowledge me
The same way I would do now if I was hosting and someone kept doing it he just gave me the hand like
I got it
You can put the hat that in that
This was a weird moment for him
I just repeated it for hip hop in general like the early 90s
This is the moment when you had
Stations like Hot 97 converting to AllHipHop formats
Playing
You know NWA Public Enemy Tribe Called Quest
Group C know that were suddenly attracting loads of white Suburban fan
Yet if you listen to their lyrics
Everybody
They were about stuff those fans could have never experienced
Struggle depression
Lack of opportunities in the ghetto
The fact that
You have young black teenagers
Who
Or living in
A society where
They're told that they will never amount
And that their lives
Have no value
No worth
That to me
Becomes the
The Angst in the frustration in a rage
Which
Is that the embodiment of the
The music
I wanted to be a part of this
A black culture
I I felt
I've always been very interested in loving things that require defense
And Hip-Hop is definitely that
From the beginning
It was initially
Shunned by black radio
Being decent
Then you had the whole team
Tipper Gore thing I love things like that I don't know why but I think I do always see Hip-Hop
In that sort of lie
In the way that needs defense I can we talk about
Your your fracas
Weather
Of course
That's my paragraph to God forbid I drop dead tomorrow
Is Peter Rosenberg on Hot 97 evolve
In 2012
Nicki Minaj
Is this
Rapper from Queens
Hugely talented rap
American Idol
Now the face for the name and she kind of blew everyone away on this Kanye song called Monster
You know she was with
Aldi's
Big rappers and Jay-Z was on the song and she blew everyone out of the water
I thought you was really good
I thought you was
Unnatural and
Beautiful
Lake Havasu the total package
Common factor
The year before it all happened
2011 I pulled her aside at Summer Jam
I said hey I think you could be
The greatest female
Artist of all time greatest female rap artist
And I just want you to know that
In thinking that
I'm going to hold you to a high standard so I probably will say things
You said all of that in a really quick moment to it was really Brave she probably wouldn't remember
What happened to remember that if someone said that I and I said I think you could be the greatest
She had all this
Underground credit right
And then how did you spend that credit well she started making
Popular and popular record
Culminating in the following song
If you are me
You've not been able to get out of your head
For a week
She made this song called Starship
Let's go to the beach each let's go
Starships is a blatant pop
Lowest common denominators I didn't I didn't like
The song you listen to that song and you cannot tell that it's not
A song by
Katy Perry or pink or it could be anyone
So all of a sudden who is the underground crab
Cop
But Peter Rosenberg
Sometimes I got several mornings for his segment called the realness
He would get on there and play I play a clip of Starship
Hardcore hip-hop
Stop it
There is a real question being asked at the center of this which is
What is this music
Where the boundaries are
And also is this where hip hop is going
Is it just let me cash in and just
Follow the trends of what white music is doing it like you felt betrayed as it as a music
Yeah I felt like, and we just sent in the moment it felt like
You're at your hip hop star why would you why would you do this this is and this is not for us
Encore hip hop artists
Make pop song
It upsets me because
It's a bacon be a moment that blurs and messes up
Hip Hop
This song right here Stars
Is literally
One of the most sellout song
In the Papas
Just put that comment in a tiny bit more context vs
No mention of course the history right
That's so many forms of popular music have been invented by black people co-opted by white people jazz blues rock
We all know the story
According to Franny Kelly
One of the hosts of a podcast called microphone check
Podcast from NPR music 2013 was the first year that no black artist had a number one song
Since 1958
Since they started the Hot 100 charts this the first year where no black artist makes a number 1 at this may be a blip
May not be
What's clear is that there is a new force in town
A style of music called EDM.
Is a meaningless
Acronym that stands for electronic dance music
And it's like you know then
It's sort of amalgam of Cindy Dancy techno a Euro poppy stuff and
It is taking over
What happened with EDM was just so glaring and
Fast
And then to see that sort of start to creep into hip-hop with Gary for people
The idiom is
The style of music that's meant to work on any dance floor with any crap
So that way it's like a music without history
On purpose a lot of the criticism of like EDM is that
It is all about my it is the corporatization of
Play genre with along
History so in some ways I think the root of the protest
Is
Don't
Dell
Our stuff
To the highest bidder
Silicon texting app
After sell out song
In hip hop history
After Peter trash talks Nicki Minaj Starships
We arrived at that Year's Summer Jam 2012
And that your Nicki Minaj was going to be one of the big headliner
Plan was part of
Perform on the main stage
Inside giant snake
But outside the stadium in the parking lot
Earlier in the day there's the festival stage which is where the underground backpack kids Hangout
And that's Rosenberg
Zone
So he's introducing the axe on that stage
Before I get to the real hip hop of the day
Cuz I see the real hip-hop had sprinkled in here I see him I said
In trying to Hype up the
This Crowd
Who sings Starships later I'm not talking to you all right now
Crab Pina Gose
A little bit like there's a cheer
Nothing crazy though just a regular chair sound like
I didn't realize a bomb was
I forgot
That Not only was the festival stage lives
Streaming
What is live-streaming on her web
And her
Poor fan barbs as they're known are 13 year old girls
And when they see Peter say that Big O
Wild
And they
Go out on the internet
Who is this Rosenberg guy what is his deal he says with a got back to Nikki and her
Before she went on stage before she went on stage
So then there's this tax date conversation
Roseburg basically as soon as he gets off stage his boss my boss comes out pokes his head around the curtain and goes
Did you say something about Nicki Minaj
I was like remember
I'm like oh yeah I did
And he's like
Yeah what you just cancel the show
So she's not coming
And I was like
I was like oh
And I looked at my phone and I go to Twitter
Sitting on the stage
Is the crowds all out
Giants stadium
And I look on Twitter
And I go to Trenton
And on the main Trend page
It just says Peter has
And I was like
Oh wow
This is
Is this Sunday afternoon at like 5 and
I would like
Third most trending thing in the world
I was just
Watching
My name
Get bigger in a moment
What is a big drama that happened in New York I was reading just my name over and over and over again
Peter Rosenberg all these people saying I don't know who this guy is but he's dissing my favorite artist
Disappointed and I don't understand how she
I was reading who is this guy
Real hip hop one man say one thing
And everybody stop he must have got some serious cred from this
Not only was his name getting out there but it was getting out there as I'm the GateKeeper
I'm the defender and the defender of the real
The real
I couldn't appreciate it
At first because I didn't know if I was maybe going to get fired for messing up Summer Jam because Nikki's and beefing with the station
Come on your state or even say something
She's calling in you no matter the station
Papa John's
Busta Rhymes get some balls trying to broker a deal on Master Flex gets involved they're trying to reach a daytime
It becomes a months-long process
Nut
If they say unanimous
Sleep know you were wrong about that song this is
Is our song We included in our
Map of what's going on
Stop trying to draw the map
What do you say that in your inside you
I think my gut reaction
You know nothing you don't draw the map
You need people like us
To draw the map
Or there's nothing
What is that
If if we don't get to determine certain things
Who does we should leave that to the crazed thirteen-year-old who may not even like this artist in 2 years
Other Woman
Hearing that
Sprained ankle again this idea that
Young girls with your Starships
And say oh
That's Hip Hop
That's what I want to hear that's what I'm to judge everything against you wildly unfair
To the intelligence of young girls
Freddy says they can figure out the difference between hip hop and pop they don't need help
And furthermore when he chose Starships to single out
It felt
Revealing of another
Layer to this debate that
People want
Out loud
Which is it when people refer to things as quote real hip hop
Usually code for aggressive
Street
Masculine
Where is when they say pop
That's usually code for
Feminine
Which is a perversion of
What's the music
And so there is this idea that
You know people make
Songs for the ladies
Which implies that all the rest of them are songs that we can't hear or God forbid understand
Okay so all of this
Swirling around months go by and then fast forward to the week before the next Summer Jam this is 2014
2013 - 2013
Feud is still going to year later
But Grenadier Nikki decide
It's time to settle
Maybe because she wanted to perform at that you
Your summer Jan are so
Nicki Minaj
Radio station
She come to the station
Before
Summer Jam to make herpes
And they do this whole interview with Rosenberg and Nicki Minaj and Ebro the boss is moderating
On the air on the rosenbergs
Where would you like this interview to go
I don't know I'm excited I'm excited to see Nikki because
It's very odd to have some of that you don't know very well who's become like such a fixture in your life like
I've always wondered I was always like I wonder if Nikki knows that she's come up
Everyday of my life
For 350 days like
Point that where Starship got played on my wedding and it was like the biggest deal at my wedding
Starship playing at my way
After some opening remarks
Peter basic
I am sorry that things went as left as they did
I never had ill feelings about you as a human being ever
Mac says I have nothing against you as a person be on my
Sort of distaste for that song
That's cool
As water under the bridge
Do you mean that
Yeah
She then goes out of her way to apologize to
To her fans for
Skipping out on the gig
Danny Glover
You know what like I get it like
That's what you do
I guess
Tumi
I just don't know your resume
You know I'm saying so
I never found you funny I never found you entertaining another
You smart
I just found you annoying
Because
You know
I grew up in New York
I've gone out on Hot 97 like
I know Angie and I know Flags
Mr Stephen Wallace
People
Whether they like me or whether or not
We get along I just know their resume
But like with you I was just like
Who are you
I don't recognize you as an authority on WhatsApp sent
Tammy
You don't have enough
Of a resume
To make those comments
Who are you to tell me what to do
What people on Tinder
Is Dan is that when I
Can't when I was doing this
I took a lot
Men
She was like my whole career there just been random men
Who have liked being in no position to stop me
And tell me why I'm not good enough
I just did I just don't want a lot of
From guys and here you are
I don't know you
You just some random man
Manny bro jumps any kind of jokingly trying to lighten the mood goes and you
I didn't even say that
And then she jumped into goes
No no no
That to
Being white also struck a chord with me if I'm being honest
Because
I was like young he's on a
Black
Station
Justin Black
People like I don't
I don't I just didn't like
Did you get back to that idea
Category ideas
Like
When you don't have that like set list of criteria to help you figure out who's in and who's out
It's all about a gut feeling and Nicki Minaj that moment
Have a white guy from the suburbs tell her a black woman from Queens that she's not hip-hop enough
Spell wrong then Ali Shaheed Muhammad from Tribe Called Quest put it this way
Maybe feels wrong but maybe this is actually Evolution 40 years into it that's what it supposed to be at some point we're all going
To be so far removed from
The origin that no one would think
Qualify
Really but if you're going to be the person to
Querida
The torch I guess
To be the gatekeeper fan at some point what qualifies you
It's your heart
Miss that feeling
You could be Bill Gates kid
Still understand the struggle enough to be like y'all
I'm riding with that
And I want to fight for that
I was like yo
Black
Station
Justin Black
People like I don't
I don't I just didn't like the
The feel of it
Who am I going to diss if not black people I want a hip hop station I have to just black people sometimes
Watch your mouth shut and McLemore
Roseburg to this day takes
Reddit for her
Saying my next project is going to be at
Hardcore hip-hop albums albums awesome you will see me take lots of credit for it. Absolutely
She called me the other day
And I was
Half a sleeve
And she like
Hello
I know you're thinking
Why is this b**** called and I was like not at all what's going on
You better do something and the amazing thing was she wanted to ask me an opinion.
Something and it makes me feel ultimately super special
So we asked Peter like so what does that mean like if you are now a gay
Are you white guy from
Suburban Maryland
Very commercial radio
What does that mean for hip hop
Let me know hip-hop has by default been co-opted cuz like
I hear you are I don't know I mean I feel like hip hop is in a better place now
Then before I
Started
Doing this
I would break it down on paper
Let me tell you where we were when I started my underground show in 2000's
And let me tell you what I think we are in 2014
Let me show you how many those artists I broke and supported and worked hard with and talk to the label about
Push
How many I had involved with I think you see a really high percent
So that was part of his answer
We asked Andrew the same questions,
I mean
I look I
I don't think that hip-hop
Is Dad there was some
Quote on
Frank Zappa
Thanks Ed
Jazz isn't dead it just smells funny
Like
I don't think hip hop group what group
I think Hip Hop isn't dead
It always smells a little
Huge snakes to Andrew Marantz and The New Yorker magazine for letting us borrow Andrew for a Beat
Definitely check out his story in the New Yorker magazine is called old school it's
Great story goes into way more detail the week get into here
Also a big thanks to Franny Kelly and Ali Shaheed Muhammad
Together they co-hosts the NPR Podcast microphone check and Jedi bomber
Thank you for listening
So lest you think that like hip-hop is arrived at this new
Quote post
Racial
Situation when we were like maybe Bears thinking out loud
With Peter and he was like
No way no
God is one thing I could demand
That are drained is peace it would be this statement right here
Nothing has driven me more crazy over the
The course of my time in hip hop
Then why people come up to me and go
You know and it used to be really bad when he first came out
You know
Eminem is just so talented
I don't even listen to Hip Hop
But
Eminem
I mean now he's good
If you don't listen to Hip Hop
Why the hell should I care what your thoughts on Eminem are and how do you know that he's good you know that he's white
You know that he's white
Is Eminem good
Yes it just so happens that he's as good as you
As your guessing he is
Random you don't even know that
Eminem could be any could have been one of the dude from Milli Vanilli and you would have thought it was great
Drive me nuts in so anytime I think about
Over post-racial just look at what Eminem concerts look like and what
The sales look like
And you can be instantly reminded
The even though Eminem
Has
No experience that
Average Suburban White America could ever identified
I mean culturally the experience you went through
Is much more common
With someone went with
Went through a black struggle than any sort of
Regular white Suburban life
I'm just the guy who came up in a rough situation
In A Million Ways
Was the odd man out all the time
Never had anything
And then makes it
And all of a sudden the fact that people like home
I so identify with
What is it why do I identify with a guy who's from a trailer park
From a history of drug abuse who raps about things that
I'd be terrified of if a black man was saying
Identify with him so much and then Eminem cuz he's amazing
Raps about the same thing
He doesn't song called Dear White America retails them
You're an idiot
You let your kids listen to me
But you would like to listen anyone else just cuz I'm white you're an idiot and they love it
Unbelievable
My name is ayush srivastava and I'm calling from the University of Chicago
Radiolab is supported in part by the National Science Foundation
And by the Alfred P Sloan found
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern
More information about Sloane @www.