Are you awake
Listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
Everybody this is Jad
Radiolab
Okay so as promised in the last
Episode
The short end of the year gift for
Which
I'll be honest
It's a gift I hope will motivate you to make
Gift back
So let's call it
Plea for a gift
Exchange in a we are as no raising money to fund Radiolab
Through 2019
Dell pay for all the stories we have such big plans but we need your help
So if Radiolab on your device
Is the thing that you cherish please consider helping us out go to radiolab.org
Click that donate button
Or radiolab.org donate
We'll just text the word Radiolab to the number 70101
Have to wear Radiolab to the number 70101
Alright so
Let me set this episode up for you
At Radiolab part of the whole ethos here is there
We've got this incredibly talented
Team
Of producers reporters and researchers
In fact checkers
And everybody's got slightly different
Super powers
It's what we'll do on occasion is get together and and
Cher
My tips and tricks
It's a bottle on the way we ended up asking our reporter producer lots of Nasser
How do you go about finding
Stories
One of the things about latte
Find the weirdest
Best most interest
Stories
Stores like the one
Praying monk bot
Or the Forgotten history of our Southern border with Mexico or a
The game theory of badminton
And you know a pitch meetings are always like how the hell did you find that
So we have time to talk about
Peace process
And end up giving a talk about it.
The whole staff
And then he has of writing an article about it
Fort Ransom. Org
An article
What store went viral
And we figured we should just pass along some of the his
Advice
To everybody
Until one of our newer producers Rachel
Cusick
Got on the phone with lots of and he went through some of his tips and tricks
I think there's stuff in here that we can all Steel
That'll just make 2019 more interesting and fun
So yeah here's a bit of that conversation I hope is your listening you'll be motivated to
Help us out for tweens
But you're just
Whatever you there
I am
Austin
Guinness is an excerpt of a conversation between Rachel Cusick and lots of knots
Story finder
The game is
You want
Stories that people haven't heard before like you have to look in places where people aren't looking
Incas people
Like the the low-hanging fruit is all take him you just adjust
Assume that
And it's like okay I'm going to do some
Bizarre aerial acrobatic move and that's going to land me on this weird random tree branch
There's all this fruit over here that nobody's even touched you know
Lots of a listing for Rachel a few of his moves a few of the things he has engineered to get him onto those
Out-of-the-way tree branch
These are some of my favorite fun things to do to find new story slam on me so okay so one of them
Is Google Alerts so you may or may not be familiar with Google Earth
Use that one for yourself cuz that's what most people do but the most fun way to use Google art I find
Is that a
So what I do sometimes I just
Come up with
Phrases that I think are
Fun or funny and I just set Google alerts on them
Like what you have
So one of the ones that has been
Very interesting for me is I use the phrase
The human equivalent of
So I just set a Google alert for the phrase the human aquilo I know anytime anyone on the internet uses app
Phrase the human equivalent of
Like I find out about it
Here's another one of you
Bizarre but brilliant
Or like thing people say I'll spend no it's not it's not but that's the thing that's why that is a few
Times in India
Is get used like you're like oh exactly
Or like another one I have
A self-fulfilling prophecy
I love that phrase
The light
When whenever anyone on the Internet is talking about self fulfilling prophecies I got to know about it
Not to say that it's important that I read any of that stuff inside most of the time I just
Delete it I just like we glanced at it and delete it
But every
I think of them as like little scratch off ticket
Gets or something or like story lottery tickets like one day they're going to
Yelp me something but who knows
So that's that's one Google alerts on weird phrases
What what else
Who's on the list is there more
Oh okay this is one way I think we should just do it right now although maybe I don't know if your you have to run out the door
I'm good what do you want to do
So it's just Wikipedia surfing like this is my go-to way of procrastinating
Love
Wikipedia and in particular the thing I liked about Wikipedia more than anything else
Cuz if you go on to the homepage so go into the Wikipedia.org Do you have a
Okay so you go to wikipedia.org and then you go to English although if you want to go to another language
Okay so now if you look on the left hand side right
Okay that was like the main page contents featured content that random article
This is like my
This I have spent so many hours with this fares
Pacific but I've never noticed that type of
The random article around until you have one that's it like a fairly media article okay
Yeah yeah yeah yeah what do you want to go first
But there's not much here about to potato salad Hugo okay
Gisela Wyman is a German multimedia artist who lives and works in Berlin
So this one is sort of long but but
Not all the lynx look like not that exciting
I can't even say this Noah
Sokolka County which is a village in the administrative District of
What it what is it
Place in northeastern Poland to click that click that
Place in Poland
Tak province
Okay so this is an urban rural damina
In which it was going to click that what is that
Amina is
Is it the principal unit of
The administrative division
Poland all right okay
Your turn
Okay alright
Okay
I got
Amal Amin is an
Actor an English actor who is in among other things to show the Netflix show sense8
Okay
Hello
Would you find after Hardy was put under cover and was shot he was transferred to operation trident
What's operation trident
What is oxycodone operation tridents are simply Trident is a Metropolitan Police Service units if it looks like
The real thing
Originally set up in 1998 to tackle gun crime and homicide in London's afro-caribbean communities
Following a series of shootings in the London boroughs of Lambeth and Brent
So okay so this is
All the sudden something I've never heard of that sounds like it has some
Awesome teeth to it okay
He's going to jump in here and move things along to the two of them ended up falling on this
20 minute Rabbit Hole having to do with
Firearms dealers
In cases involving seizure weapons Shepherd is acquitted of all 13 Firearms offences with which he was charged
So why was he acquitted so there is a footnote here so then I can look that other one
Eventually they land on a story
Buy firearms dealers
The does ask a question
When is it gonna rain again
See
K a gun dealer specializing in ants
Peak Firearms has been acquitted of selling weapons
Which the prosecution is claimed could have been ended up in the hands of gangsters
Cohesive this is a story about antique firearms and like maybe the line between where are antique fire
Arms
Where are when are they antique and not
Scary and when are they
Not antique
Scary
Illegally finding the difference
Between those two things
That's kind of in
Never heard of that before how many how many times do this like 10 a day it's like
Like you're like X
Exercises
No I just do this every night I probably end up doing that but I definitely not like regimented
It's just a way of like getting lost
It's like one of those old like
People who would like go to a
New city and just like wander around until they got lost and then try have to find their way home
It's like that you're doing that but it's like you're doing that on the Internet or you're doing that in a library
What's particulars you want to find stuff that nobody else is fine then
Okay so weird Google Alerts Wiki
Pedia surfing those are a lot of tips 1 and 2 we have any more Hot Tips
Let me see some other
Fine Wines
The one of them that nausea.
Is that
I love
Oral histories
I love oral history
And
There's a thing called worldcat which is amazing worldcat.org okay that is it's basically the library catalog
Log of all libraries
You can search something so let's say you want to find just not even anything special
Like just a normal butt
What you do is you put it in there
And you also put in your ZIP code
And then it'll be like oh hey
The
There's this
Library 2 mi away from you that has
A copy of that book or the nearest copy that book is in Nashville or whatever it is
My alarm but it's pretty cool but
World cat is great and is super helpful
What you're trying to find superb
Also it has a kind of sister site called archives grid which is like kind of
That that thing for special collect
Cancel our special collections in libraries have
Do you have oral history
Jason mask
The stuff that I get excited about what it like
They're just so many I think like
To me if I'm looking at these websites it's just all names
What
How do you pick a name to even listen to
Oh sometimes I like read descriptions of someone's will just be named okay let's just try it
Like and I'll just go to the next one I'm bored similar thing to that the IRL version of that
Is talk to strangers
Like I talk to strangers all the time I talk to Uber drivers
All the time
She said the story so we did earlier this year we did the Border trilogy
That came from a conversation I had with a woman a stranger on a bus
So I was taking a bus from
New York
And I sat next to a woman very pleasant woman her name is Lynn
She's an anthropologist
And then I ask a question like like one of the questions I asked her was oh you know why
Like who are the really cool
New Anthropologist working in the field where they help young people
And then she told me she's like you got to read this book The Land of Open Graves
And then I was like okay and then
Describe it to me a little bit and I was super interested then I went home that night
And I read the book cuz it was so good
It was so good and then that
Like that started
You know that was the first Domino and then what ended up being not just
A full year for me but also for a whole bunch of other reporters and producers
Like making that
Into a full not just one episode
Three apus
It's like where we
Yeah and and that all started just cuz I sat next to a lady on a bus like
Know that everybody around you has stories like they all have stories
The great amazing
Stories that they they are
Fully willing to tell it's just like nobody's ass
You know and it's just like that's the thing like the whole world is like that like some other tricks that lot if shared
Some of these have to be honest like
I'm not sure anyone
Pam would have the
Patients are emotional fortitude
To do
But he says he reads a bunch of
Really
Secure
Trade magazines
The roller coaster Association of America
Like the ice cream manufacturer
Something something trade magazines that you will never ever care about him millionaires like if you were in solitary confinement and
You got a stack of Detroit magazine
You would still not read them like that kind of boring and then to find a
Dorian there
Define something that is not just
Interesting but also is like moving and also makes you
You think and also makes you like
Like if that's a that's a superpower
Superpower I like out of all the superpowers
To make boring things interesting
To make people
Like
Like awaken to the world around them and see that it's actually way more exciting than they give it credit for like that
I don't know that's like
That's literally the reason I get up in the war
Now one thing a lot of stress
I know this is really important is that even though he is constantly finding tons of ideas
He is here
Like the percentage of of the ideas he pitches
Versus the number we accepting end up going with
That number is still pretty low the one I should one funny story about
Story of pets like I remember when the first
Sorry that gets every alive I was like
Look like they're all there
Like
In the world of math
There are all these like people who do all this Advanced geometry and then the way they do it
Is knitting they like knit all these like complex shapes
Anime
Like the netease like
Absurd things and they learn
It'll be so cool like knitting a knitting all the time
I know I was like she still interested in it
I remember pitching in the room and it being like
The biggest dud and one of the reasons why
I think it was
Jazz
We'd like
You realize that
Like you can't hear
Skier knitting right like knitting is like the worst radio story idea like it's the most boring thing
You could possibly hear on the radio like
That's not going to work
Mother said that in part it was all that rejection
I'm sorry for the
It look what it led to
All that rejection led him to develop
All of these
Otter and Otter
Techniques for finding tails
Which formerly he kept to himself at first when I was doing this I was like so super secretive about it I was like you
He was all my secret sauce
She knows like no way like why would I tell you that
It's like a recipe that you don't want anyone to have like the best
Cookie in the house
But then at some point you're like
Yeah the world would just be a
Better place if there were more cookies and it's like like like theirs.
Yeah I know you do yes before Radiolab
Yep
Here's what I tell my
I tell myself that there are
7 and a half billion people on planet
Arthur 7 and 1/2 billion
And if you presume
That's a
That 1% or even Point 1/4
Have life
Fascinating stories
I'm like a dynamic newsworthy
Exciting dramatic
Movie where these stories happening
On any given day or any given week
Week rights
If you presume that 1% of those having a half billion people have those stories like
There is no way all the stories are getting told there's just no way but there's just not enough journalist in the world to tell all the
Those stories and those are just the alive people
There are a lot of dead people who have great stories there are a lot of
Animals who have great stories and businesses and
Consumer goods and
Planets
And inanimate objects and microbes and like there's like
Finity of stories
All around us
More dramatic than any movie
For True Story Finders
The world is a scavenger
And I just love it so much fun
So amazing I think that's like an amazing spot to end and I think you should go off
On your little scavenger hunt
And I will let you go okay
Thank you bye bye
Thank you to lots of Nasser
For sharing those tips
Lots of has a really cool thing he's working on for
2018 that I cannot wait
Thanks also Rachel Cusick for making that conversation happened
She and Pat Walters also
Have a
A series they're working on that
That is going to be amazing
All that is going to come at you next year
Before we closed a couple of things
Those of you who
Search out interesting stuff
For a living or judge
Out of habit
A hits on Facebook
And tell us your scavenger hunting tips
I'm thinking if we get a bunch maybe we'll put
Put together a crowd-sourced list
And we'll all be better for
And as we hurdle towards
Is the closest 2018 please take a moment
To throw some love our way to help us
What's fun Radiolab
Through 2019 you know the whole deal here is that we make the show available
Free
But we rely on listener donations to
To actually pay for it
That's kind of the honor System that makes the whole thing goes
We need to hear from you
Anyone that we do hear from by December 31st
Will get
Beautiful setup
A cars that commemorates some of the series
Arid 2018 including
Lattice border
Go to radiolab.org donate
Or
Text the word Radiolab to the number 70101
That's the word Radiolab
The number 70101
Thank you
Keeping a strong in 2018
We look forward to
Scouring
The corners of reality 2
Bring you more
Stories for 2019
But we need your help
Happy New Year everybody
Broadside