Are you weightless
Radio WNYC
And NPR
Davis Jad abumrad this is Radiolab the podcast Robert
Is out of town today he's actually
His son is getting married so it's just me
I thought in this podcast
I want a little bit
Generally and that should be in front of your mouth start with a conversation
That the Brooke Gladstone and I said Brooke from on the media
She and I had with my brother-in-law
Ugim Eugene Thacker I'm an author and professor at the new school in New York City
Very weird thing that happened to Eugene
Felt like a kind of story I've been wearing black since I was 13
Two-tone black right now set it up
Eugene is a hard
Quartz color of philosophy
And he writes his books
Let them be little use words like
Exegesis
And ratiocination
Until the family joke
Is that
He writes books
For now on I think the a joke started out I write books that nobody reads and then
After a slow long. Of acceptance I started to think well maybe I should write books
I'm for no one to read to just started embrace.
Meeting at a certain point if you do this kind of work you're going to have to ask yourself if you knew that this would not be published would you still write it
How committed are you
And he decided he was committed he would write it no matter what
So the Story begins couple years ago 2011 Eugene writes this book called in the dust of this planet
In the dust of this planet
It's kind of a hard book to describe but if you had to sum it up in a sentence it's about the end of the world
But not in the Hollywood
Sense darker than that your hypothesis is the greatest horror
Is that
Nothing exists and nothing matters and the world that we live in that weed
Define in terms of humanity doesn't care about us is often referred to
To his nihilism or pessimism that there might not be a purpose to things or to your life or to our
Distance or to the cosmos there might not be in order
The things we might not be here for a reason this all might be purely arbitrary in an accident that there's no inherent meaning
Anything but it just doesn't matter is what Nietzsche called most difficult thought
And in the book Eugene traces this idea through all of these different horror movies
He's from slasher films to sort of more supernatural horror music
One point he goes into the sea construction of how different types of black metal deal with a thought I don't know it's
It's something it's other way of thinking I've always found really intriguing and ironically kind of
Inspiring are you a pessimist
All my better days
Are you a nihilist
Not as much as I should be
Okay so Eugene writes this book in 2011 it is dark
It is dense he writes it at his house for no one and as expected
Beyond a few philosophy types
No one really pays attention
So keep your head down teaching writing but then
Something's Happened 2014
It's all one ghetto man giant gutter in outer space
The show True Detective comes along comes a big head and at the center of the show is this character Russ
Nicole is Louisiana detective who is one dark dude human consciousness
Tragic misstep in evolution these rant about how there's no order in the world how humans are just as accident
You was at a god consider myself very last time but in philosophical terms I'm what's called a pessimist
And I just remember watching it and being like wow
Sugs wife Priya Murthy my sister-in-law has so many conversations that we've had
Add in the car she's like where they listening in on us Dairy soprema goes online fix around
Then I see this article
About the True Detective
The director was an article where I actually the writer of the show Nic pizzolatto was asked how did you create that character
Wireless police detector
And he lists a bunch of things he was reading at the time in that list was
Eugene
Which I was like
Cool
At least one person but I really just try to
Keep my head to the ground and just keep riding just doing what I'm doing
But then
Things got weird okay so now he has pull up the
The Lucky Magazine the secret behind it
Short time later Prima is flipping through this fashion magazine Lucky Magazine and there was
A spread with this actress Lily Collins 25 year old actress I never heard of pretty big right now she's standing on a
Any street corner
Dressed up in all of this sort of God
Makeup and clothing and in the photo she is
Where is Eugene's Buck on her chest
She had on and one of the shots
Sweatshirt
That have the cover of the book
In the dust of this planet big letters
Right on her chest and I was just like no way it was definitely
What The Hell she's just casually wearing my husband's
Book cover I don't know I can't I didn't
React to but it was just strange to that a Norwegian artist had made a painting of the book
That eventually gotten picked up by a fashion label and turned into some very expensive clothes
Yep
I write books for now under himself obviously I'm not pulling in a lot of royalties
Honest but you know Eugene says he's not going to sue I'm not
Going to see or take any legal action
I really do anything about it
Cuz he says that's not why you right
Okay so that happened
Banana gets weirder still
My wife Karla Murthy is online this is the day that Jay-Z and Beyonce announce they're going to do the
Big International
Carlos watching the video that they released
Fake movie trailers guns fire
Hookers
Bonnie and Clyde thing
Ranking the running from someone you not quite sure who fiance is in a wedding dress and that Avail on
But she's shooting semi-automatic weapons in wedding dress cut the car chases cut the money flying everywhere but at
Exactly 37 seconds in
You see Jay Z turn stick a giant gun out to his right
And he is wearing Eugene's book
Right there on his back in the dust of this planet
What is the point of which I was like
Okay what do we make
Could it be that Eugene is no longer writing books for knowing that somehow he is become a conduit
With this idea that we all
In that Subterranean way that pop music operates that we all are channeling right now
That was my
Yeah and I think that's
That's the question
Is whether this is something particular
To the moment we're living in and Eugene
His knee-jerk reaction is
I think it could have been this cover or a million other covers
No
This is just meaningless appropriation I don't think there's anything more than that
To me then it's just the looks like a cool phrase to go on a t-shirt to put on a goth girl and Son photoshoot
And why is it
The cool
Right
Cuz my heart
Is you might be right but you also might be wrong because of the answer that you're about to give to Brooks Quest
It's cool because some publicist this was her the conversation one to have and swipe
Brooke like what is behind all of this nihilistic entertainment this everywhere
No Brooke for her part agree that Eugene probably is tapping into
Yes
But is this unique to this moment
And to that I would say no really
You don't think this says anything about now I think there are Cycles
In which
The sense of meaninglessness
Comes out in sharper relief
Then other time
But you can identify them over and over again
Nihilism
All the way back
Brooke actually turned it down to this guy
Simon critchley in the Hans Jonas professor of the new school for social research
Simon wrote an article that basically made the argument that nihilism is the basic Credo of cool is it
It's sexy it's interesting been that way forever
Echo echo echo the best thing for your love this
It's a Russian witch right he said the word really got its pop in 1862 this is 150 years ago
Does a novel by
Turgenev Fathers and Sons
And in the novel The Sun whose nihilist turns to his conservative dad
He says we pay Stockholm. Recognizes useful
In these days the most useful thing we can do is to repudiate
And so we repudiate
Everything
The fall this is everything
Everything with indescribable
Composure
Everything
Jokes
Simon Says roughly from that point on you see young people
Glom onto this idea again and again as a way to
You say no to the older generation or two just what's happening in the world for example after World War 1
Tens of millions of people dead this Lost Generation it was confused and disgusted what just happened
None of that says Brook you get Dada I want to
Pull up here on the computer
The manifesto of
Tristan tzara
He was one of the founders of the Dada movement he says Dada means nothing everything one
One look that is false
Dada abolition of memory Dada abolition of archaeology dada
Abolition of prophets Dada abolition of the future and after World War II
Can Simon say you had similar movements
In the seventies and eighties with the threat of nuclear Annihilation you get punk rock
Just keeps going pop culture at least since
I was a kid has always been deep in Odyssey
Alright it's nothing new
But when I ran Simon through the Eugene jacket situation then I asked him like
Is there something different about today's nihilism vs. nihilism of the past
Play something more potent about it
Without hesitation
He said
I say I say yes
Based on what
That's pretty sure any Mills who was with me during the interview
I know you can do you can get
Simon says it was more of a gut feeling
Based on this class that he taught last year
With Eugene I didn't actually know they knew each other but they have taught this class together so the seminar the wages in the
You foolish it was one of those
Resume. Switching mysticism nobody teaches mysticism
Pretty obscure stuff within desert fathers medieval female Mystics
This is early Christianity a religious
He says they started the seminar
Not really expecting much
By talking about how in the 4th Century ad
Where was the city Alexandria
Egypt Alexandria was a low-light Manhattan
It was an offshore Islands
Biblical name of a
Former Pala Roman Empire cultural learning in the ancient world
A certain point in the full century
People start to leave
They tell to leave and go into the desert
People wander off
And they seem to want something else
The sissy doesn't just doesn't do anymore
It's corrupt
It's broken it's it's sinful
He said crime is rampant pollution and so people just started to wander off into the desert
Live in these caves and vision tense forms of assessment practice became like he had these women who were
No education cuz when they couldn't be educated
Who is so
Enraptured with Christ they began hosting themselves throwing themselves into icy Rivers jumping into ovens
The body is something which is
You're trying to strip away
In order that you can free the capacity for love
I got a classic Mystic idea right the body is just getting in the way of
I want to go soul2soul exactly with God exactly for the premise of the again is the the world is a country
Field of ruin
He says what really struck him is it
As he was talking about all this he would
Glanced out at the student
And he would notice this
Look in there
I just felt in the room there was this
This deep need was being fulfilled by these
Strange Mystics
He said the students
In any way that almost never happens when your
We want no saving Souls but it was it was hitting something really really deep
What exactly I mean do you think they were starting
Deform the thought of
Wandering into the desert so to speak
Secede walk away you know that's where a lot of people right
As for what's behind it all
He says just turn on the news video showing the beheading of a second American journalist has now been verified
Davis is turning into one of those longest deadliest outbreaks ever girls were gotten raped and strangled
Photography nearby
Since it was
Completely
Crazy mutually assured destruction but it makes sense and you can understand and principal terms that was United States was
Soviet Union food going to be a Vista races that was clear but it in a you knew what the balance of powers
You're near a nostalgic for mutually assured destruction is that what's happening now seems a much simpler
You at least knew who to blame for it right
Atlanta again look at the Cold War
And you could see like pacifically like you Soviets the Americans the nukes
That's right that's right now
Carbon emission
Speaking of which today the world's leading climate scientists warn it will get worse no doubt one of the reasons for the current
Gloom is that we are in the middle of an uncomfortable shift
And how we talk about climate change in the ipcc
The intergovernmental panel on climate change released a report
We're for the first time they stopped
Using the language of prevention
And shifted to the language of adaptation in other words
Hundreds of scientists and policymakers
What's the world's top Organization for assessing climate change
We're now saying
We Can't Stop
It's inevitable
So now we need to talk about dealing with the mask that is now on our doorstep that's David Victor professor of international relations
University of California at San Diego
And he is one of the authors of
When the ipcc first began back in the late 1980s you could imagine
The people would take the climate change problem seriously
They would start to control emissions and then over a. Of decades climate
Would stop changing and it said what's happened is people have talked a lot about climate change but they haven't actually done much to catch
Emissions now he says we're all in this strange Middle Ground where we're trying to find the language
To say why it's important to keep working at this while at the same time
Admitting some degree of failure and that's the kind of inevitability that I think you see in the new
The new reports in any reports are bending over backwards to try and find ways
To be optimistic the report says
If you put into place all these Technologies and international agreements we could we could still stop warming at 2 degrees
My own assessment is that
The kinds of actions you need to do that are so heroic that
We're not going to see them
All of which reminded me of that True Detective moment I consider myself for real
Some what's called a pessimist okay what's that mean well pessimists like nihilist agreed
There's no meaning they're just a little more mopey about it less likely to do something means I'm bad at parties
Means that we're all headed you know in a recent Wall Street Journal
Poll 76% of people 18 and over
Weren't confident that the future is going to be brighter than the past
Which brings me back to Brooks question why is it cool
Collet nihilism pessimism whatever shouldn't be depressing
Why would you want to put a phrase like in the dust of this planet afraid deliberately negates the person wearing it why would you want to
I put it on your
Chester on your back
Encourage it
I have been here
Who is Jay Z
Jacket which was
Anyway the Catalyst for this whole podcast we decided to talk to him
That's coming up
This is Darlene calling from Kampala Uganda Rachel app is supported in part by
Foundation and by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology
In the modern world more information about Sloane at www.
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help this summer I'm hosting a show
And I request for those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
We're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments of childhood Brilliance basically I want to hear about
Kid you know did something
It just means you bring back and say whoa how did they do that maybe it was the moment that I can
Kids you've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons and you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed are ready music in the margin of their geometry homework were interested in the
Epic moments where a kid does something super smart but doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story please share it with us
Go to radiolab.org Brilliance and record a short audio message for us
Again that's radiolab.org / Brilliance thank you so much
Get that sounds great
Isis Jazz Radiolab so
We ended up in the flow of things you know as we're trying to figure out like in the dust of this planet
Why is that cool why is that just scary
Depressing
I want to talk to me why
Talking to this way
Who turns out was the person who made the decision to put it on Jay-Z's back
I should say my name I guess
My name is June Ambrose
I've been a costume designer for 22 years
23 this year in network with everyone from
Luther Vandross too puffy to xian
Mariah Carey Busta Rhymes Mary J Blige Alicia Keys
Dave Matthews Band The Backstreet Boys Kelly Ripa cancel trial R Kelly
Jamie Foxx Missy Elliott
Did you do the Missy with a balloon
That was you know my God
Of course
Jay-Z and Beyonce that's like culture basically
Nazi stuff it occurred to Andy and I during the interview that June has
Probably influence the fashion sense of a significant portion of the human beings on this
Planet and she was very clear that a costume
It's more than just a cost
It's like a conversation
Without words
What she's doing what she sows someone is
Bring me to all the people that are going to watch the videos come in contact with the Billboards go to the concerts
I don't have to talk to you
But I can create this conversation
With a pair of pants and how they fall and how they fit in the texture in the color in the feeling
He says with Jay-Z for that video
She knew she needed something Epic
But like Australis I knew I wanted to biker jacket it was a motorcycle scene but I knew that I just couldn't give up The Lacs
I need it I need it to say something feel like something
We're on the hunt
Her nurse assistant went to doesn't the place of cilia Studio the showroom looking at all these leather jackets it's like finding a needle in the hay
Nothing was right then the soundtrack to This one place black denim this place it does for high-end grunge.
They're flipping through the racks when she sees the jacket those were
Words and that was it I knew it
I said I need this is what I need
It just felt it was just
Perfect
Questions why
This one I hadn't really told her the whole back story so I pulled out a screen capture from the video is one where you see Jay Z
Standing in the desert shot from behind in the dust of this planet on his back
Really long Dirty Harry gun off to his right sode up
About to shoot the sun you think he's about to shoot
I printed it out cuz it's just got this like
Billboard quality to it right have a really cool one of my phone to this nevermind okay so we'll just look at it
And why did you choose that jacket
You know something very menacing about it
It's almost like
The aftermath that there was something going on it was paralleling
The end of an era the beginning of something new she says the back of her head she was thinking about
How the music industry might be dying it's definitely in a place where it's like what now you can hear it in the music
And you know this the biggest war in history really what now these are the Whispers that you here
But she says one of the loudest Whispers was super simple just here's a guy
About to go down the end of the world is literally on his back
It was almost as if he didn't even know that was on his back
You know what I mean it's like
That was the afterthought
Like oh yeah the world ending
I don't care it's going out of style
In other words he wasn't afraid
He wasn't afraid
You know what that's what that's what this we talked about Whispers
That's what I get from it and I know you said that it's not so much I don't give it I'm not afraid I mean we all have to
To leave the planet you know everybody has their day
But you work on his not being afraid when you have to leave
Thank you
This was actually refreshing AccuWeather
Walking out of that interview after we had told her that the phrase on Jay-Z's back was lifted from a book written by
Find my brother-in-law Eugene oh wow now I need to get the book in which she was very interested to know
Yeah let's do that and we did send in the book haven't heard back walking out of there
Keep thinking is that what this is all about
It always pop nihilism around us is not about
Turn down power structures or embracing nothingness it's just
Look at me
Look how Brave I am
If I can wear it on it
And this is why as you pointed out you know from Dada to punk
This is a recurring
Motif of how
How badass you are in facing mortality
King Kyle badass
That's what I was
I think
But that is nothing more than a posture
I mean it's all fine when you're 18 to wear that t-shirt but when you're like in your 50s dealing with k
Cancer like okay you know maybe maybe then is when you really have to confront this thing
So I just it's it's simply
The posture and that's why it's in pop culture
So you know why we love not listening pop culture is they saves us having to be done with it
Simon critchley again saves us from feeling it
We can we can enjoy in our rooms
We can get off on it and then we let it go
And we got we got to work
Simon says you don't have to be cynical about this if you don't want to be
I mean
Nietzsche
It's a dark pessimist himself
Had this idea about nihilism that it was just
The beginning
But if you really
Dealt with it took it in accelerated it to its logical end
You could get to the other side
What she called a revaluation of values
Some you
We're thinking about who we are with small creatures
County where I am
Unloved
Love is that
Capacity which can
See through that
And that he suspects is why his students were so interested in those Mystics cuz they had found a way through these people lose
Mystics
The uncompromising
Commitment to Samuel I love
The fact that they were ready to go all the way
Can you gate even their own bodies
For that love
Brighten the world web
Where love has been reduced to Tinder exchanges
If that's the hell that you're living in his 25-year old then yeah you going to read this Mystic something
I want what she's having turn my flash
And you could argue
I mean why not that Jay Z and Beyonce a little bit of that going on
When part of what's made this two are so big biggest store ever actually
Is it it's like this Grand love story
I'm with the love of my life
So it's not it's like a work but you're a fantasy
As fantasy that
Beyonce and Jay-Z will do this
Tour de will
Go off into the desert
And the live
Can a little Hut like his monastic existence
Together in love in a new a new sort of Age of Aquarius will begin
Starting with the two of them that's beautiful
Any chance that you can really hear me slipper
That was your answer
Pina colada on the beach
Olivia perfect response to judge
Search a Nike I can hear that
You're going to take
A lot of the stuff in your going to look at
The current moment can I see how
This ideas expressing itself in this made me want to watch
Go back
And see when and where and how it was
It's been expressed all along
So what
I'm delighted to be on this
And I'm going to be delighted to have you
On our showing a couple of weeks really yeah we want you to come on after
Oh my God I put it together love that we're pulling you in
Okay thank you for it for being game for this
Look for on the media's take on nihilism in a couple of weeks
Big thanks to produce Randy Mills who
Process of helping me put together this podcast began to say things like
My friends and I we were watching this lady bug crawl around my shoe
And then it started to crawl up my leg
Got caught in my leg hair
Go back down to the shoe we were all like huh
That's life
That's that they were all just bugs crawling around
On a goddamn shoe
And he was totally serious it special thanks to the Murphy Drive and 2-0 books and of course to Eugene Thacker
Even though he Harbors no Redemptive fantasies about human beings whatsoever
Is an awesome dude in this piece is an omage to him one of the most committed writers I
No
Also happens to be my brother-in-law
If you would like to read in the dust of this planet and actually do I highly recommend it super fascinating
Go to my website radiolab.org
And I will link you to it
I'm Jedi boom Rod thanks for listening
Are you still listening
Here's a little something
Extra so why we were putting together this
Podcast
We bumped into the band liturgy
And this pic
Particular
Tune
I want to play for you now
This tune
Gold generation
I'm obsessed
It's from liturgy off their album
After album
Betika
Thrill jockey throws
P.com this tune
But first attached to it is a Manifesto
Scored a bit
Transmittal black metal is in fact nihilism however it has a double miles and that's final miles in a once and for all negation of the entire series
Negations
With this final know we arrived it
A sort of
Vertiginous affirmation affirmation that is White Knuckle terrified unsentimental
Encourage
Here it is
Generation by letter