Are you weightless
Radio WNYC
Hi this is Jeff High hates me Jeff Roberts started when we bumped into
An article in the Philadelphia Inquirer
We're a little bit weird as to why we are calling you
Yeah I just don't understand the whole thing
Story really gets going with a phone call to this woman Elizabeth Mason
I'm receptionist last switchboard operator to the research lab in Boston and one day she's sitting at her desk
And she gets a call
From a woman who says that she has donated
Surmise to them and she wants to know what happen
Call you get everyday I just remembered
If it's just very unusual right I didn't know what to do with it I just felt like I got to find somebody to help this woman
Today the story of the of the woman on the other end of that phone call this is her story
Might save their story so far my title transfer
I'm Sarah gray I'm the mom
Lower
Really he has on vacation with a girlfriend was it it was it was it what the weather
What happened
That consumers
Then we've got different ideas
Different recollection what happened
We started dating across the
Ocean for a year-and-a-half and then
He moved to America
5 days after we arrived they were married a few years after that
They are pregnant with twins
When did you first know that something was up
It was at the 12-week
Screening
They called the first trimester screening and they're checking for birth defects
I think the most common one is Down syndrome
But it was September 30th 2009 ultrasound tech
Fetuses and shortly after
The. Came into the room and
Said that
Only one of the twins
Would make it
And one of the twins at anencephaly it would die
Within a few minutes or hours of being born
He said he could see that because one of the twins had a round skull
And the other one had a bumpy skull
The bumpy skull show them that the skull wasn't
Correct
Round enough
The brain in skull weren't forming properly
Which is what anencephaly is
Bookshelf
I can believe that
It's difficult the process of think
Copyright I just told this is identical twins but one of them
Completely different from the other
Making matters worse the doctor said that
The unhealthy twin was posing a threat to the healthy twin
And we were
To be safe
We would do a selective termination to save the life of the healthy twin
Surterra says they were suddenly faced with this Choice actually talk to two priests on the phone about it
Really yeah
Her family is Catholic
Jews raised Catholic
I don't know I guess I wanted
See what their take was on this
This is fine. The direction want to go to for this radio story but
Tell man suddenly interested basically what I was saying is would you come and do a blessing over the selection termination and what they say
1 Priest
Said
No
Jesus said he wouldn't do a blessing over a selective termination and then the other priest
Said that because of
Thomas Aquinas rule of
Leichtag is called double account or something basically like the rule that if you
If a train is coming
And you like
You want to save the life
Someone on the train tracks and you shoot the driver
The right thing to do
After looking it up it's actually called the doctrine of double effect and she's
Basically right maybe not the part about shooting the driver but the overall idea is that if you're trying to
To do good
And on the way to doing good you must inadvertently do some harm
It's okay in certain circumstances
As long as your intention
Anyway the priesthood because you're doing this with the intent of saving
Healthy twin
He would be there and he would do it
That's what a few weeks
We booked the hotel we packed our bags in the night before
Was really terrible for both of us cuz I don't know we had seen them on the screen and we're bored cat
This little
Kid next day they go in for the procedure
Going to the
Room in the doctor
What's the sonogram on me and
Start getting ready and he said
Your placenta has moved since the last time you were here
The location where it is right now
I don't think we should do this
Does he set up if I Nick it if I if I even just make it a little bit
Like you're going to bleed uncontrollably and kisses
He said they wouldn't do on his wife
Hela
What was that like to be on the on the
Table
Was it really wasn't really an elevator we just hugged her like a
Any decisions taken at UNC
It's not our fault
But then your healthy twin is more at risk Maybe
Yes
Is like a nail-biter for the rest of the six months
According to Rostow's six months were
Deeply strange just buying one of everything when you know those two babies coming
When you were going to be having a funeral as well so
You know I called the
What you called if you know that right though
And told them you know we're going to be having a funeral
Play Lil Wayne
Was that
Megan Barnett
Alright so they get to the day of
March
Weather 23rd okay 2010
Thomas came out first
Is the sick one that had an affair
And then a minute later Calum came out
I know it wasn't sure if Thomas was going to be born alive I sort of expected him to
Die within a few minutes
He was he was struggling that thoughts
Didn't think is going to last too long but then he Cana
Urology
Pretty good
Ali it was in Calum the healthy twin who started to have some trouble at the beginning and so
He and Sarah went off to the infant ICU and cirrhosis in the delivery room
That's just me and honest though
Quite well I C words
Come together
What was that like
It was
EIC was cute
Play Brandy Baby
Macride
He's like grabbing onto my finger
I don't think the kind of things that babies do you know
There's nothing you can do but
Toscana
You know I'm trying to
How do you spell from crying and cheering
In I remember coming to the
Recovery really Rasta this little bundle in his arms and I said
Who's that
And he said Thomas Edison
That he's alive
And I'm like oh let me hold him until I held him in
Yeah it was
Cute like he breastfed and we can
Feeding with a bottle
Dan of taking him out I didn't really planned on that like we didn't have another car seat
We just didn't
Think about it and I remember thinking like what if he's going to beat the odds like
Do we need to arrange daycare and like
You know we hadn't thought of that
Then soon after Thomas started having seizures
Start having trouble breathing
Stopped eating and at the time I remember thinking
You know it come on little guilin
Eat some more like
Eat some more than you'll be stronger
I was I just eat
What's up
How how
How long did Thomas live
6 days
Texas
He died in his arms newest Runaway
All of the people that loved him
And then right then
We called
Washington Regional transplant Community they sent a van over to our house
He picked up his body and took him to
DC Children's National Medical Center
Okay so this is where the story really gets going I guess so how did that idea of donating is working
Hey, do your head in the paper newspaper article or something there's
About a baby who would anencephaly who donated liver cells
And
Most major religions support organ donation
What happened next
I think some letters
Is there a form letter it basically said thank you for your generous donation Thomas's Cornelius it with incentives
This place in Boston where they study
Potential cure for blindness
Had his liver 7/10 this place in Durham North Carolina where they study ways to treat
Liver disease
Cuz I thought I want to know
Who ordered it which researcher got it and what study are they working on
Because I had this new baby Calum to raise
I put it behind the both of us
But then
Sarah says they got to the one-year anniversary
The one-year anniversary felt like a big moment to me like that's when
I can
That's when it stopped being in the present and it can start being in the past
You know just explaining it to people least I can say it was a year ago so they don't have to feel
Stressed out when they talk
Talk to me and it felt like a big deal like I think we were going to go to the cemetery and put some flowers on his
Craven
I wanted to
Tell my family
What were the results
What is donation
So she called the donor Family Services person at the place
I picked up Thomas's body and she basically asked them any more information you can give us
About the specific study or the researcher
It was published and they didn't have any
So I just thought okay well I tried you know
But you couldn't quite let it
Go mean what you mean she couldn't quite Let It Go
Curiosity
But I also think she was having
On some level like a big conversation with universe
I like this terrible thing happened
How do you explain it to yourself
In God
And how the universe works I thought that
Karma work or if I was basically a good person and I've obeyed the rules good things with
And whatever the reason these thoughts about Thomas and where he ended up
You just there
She had no real Opportunity Act on it so they're just going to come in and out of her mind
Then around the two year anniversary
Just now a year later I had a business trip to Boston
Nose exhibiting at a conference
Hynes Convention Center
And I Googled it and I saw that Skype inside Research Institute was just a few miles away that's where Thomas is Cornelius at
Lunch break
That's exactly what I did I called Sky pins
And I said you know I donated my son's eyes to this lab
A couple years ago and I'm here in town
Is there any chance I can come by for a tour for like 10 minutes
Then with the weird been a weird phone call
Yes I mean yes
Yeah that would like a wake her up that's Elizabeth Mason again it was just very unusual surprise
I didn't know what to do with it before never have gotten there for 25 years
She said hold on let me
Connect you to the right person don't hang up a lot of times they say something they hang up on me so I said please help line
I started searching for someone to speak with her to figure out who that is but don't hang up
And they connected me with someone in donor relations but it was
Financial donor relations
I would like
Like the different not known organ donor
But because they don't have any other donor relation that what you know like that was the person that gives the tours and deals with the public
So
That she got to talk to me and she was serious as the one was
A little bit flustered but super nice and said
We know it never done this before but yeah come on down will
Give you a tour
So excited I took pictures of the outside of the building
And I felt I stood in the lobby and I
Put one of the brochures in my purse
And I just felt like I
I can't believe I'm here this is like being in Santa's Workshop or something like
I didn't think this was a place you could ask
She's taking around
Eventually she got taken to the lab where Thomas is corneas when
And there were refrigerators with signs that said no food
And then she introduced me to this guy called dr. James ziskie
Who's the professor of Ophthalmology at Harvard Med School
He was eating his lunch at his desk
Can she explain who I was
And you said
You thank you for the donation and do you have any questions for me
Of course she did
I wanted to know how valuable the eyes were like if they get thousands and thousands or take it one or two or like when the
Delivery came with everyone excited or was it
No big deal
What was the sitting on a shelf collecting dust over people doing stuff with it
He put down his lunch and he said most of the eyes that we got her from people who are older just cuz
Most people are older when they die
An infant's eyes are worth their weight in gold
I was like that could barely speak
Could you tell me why
He said because they regenerate that
Regenerative properties
And he said if you don't mind me asking how long ago did your son die and I said about 2 years ago
And he said well we're likely still using your son's
Sales right now
Is that the one you love
I know
To that point there was like okay
Since that worked out so well why not just go keep going with it and visit
All of the
Places where bits and pieces of Thomas ended up
So you know
Chase down his liver his retina is Cord Blood how many doctors might that be
Well there's the Boston won their two in North Carolina she would ultimately discover one in Richmond Virginia
Affiliate
She turns out that these people
Didn't
Find anything
You know research is research you don't always
Have a hit
It's true she's not heading for validation necessarily here she might find it
Make it further lost
Yeah but she's going to go
She's going to go
She's not going to stop
Hi this is Shireen from Sunrise Florida
Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloan at www.slha.org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
About what we're calling tiny moments childhood Brilliance basically I want to hear about those times when a kid
So did something
It just means you read back and say whoa how did they do that maybe it was the moment that a kid
Did you been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons and you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed they're writing music in the margin of their geometry homework we're interested in
Epic moments where a kid does something super smart but doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story please share it with us
Go to radiolab.org brilliance
Record short audio message for us
And that's radiolab.org / brilliance
Thank you so much
Hey I'm Jared I'm rod iron Robert krulwich this is Radio are we okay yes oh Sarah gray when we left Earth
Two standing in a research office in Boston and feeling good
She got this Rose of a success until after that her and Rasika in the car and head down south to Durham North Carolina
Thomas's liver and a bit of his Blood for Blood because it turns out that in the delivery room
Right after birth Twins were born nurses had withdrawn a little bit of cord blood from both twins sent it off to Duke
Where researchers were studying the disease that killed Thomas anencephaly
She said they walked in
Study coordinator this guy who worked on the Human Genome Project
A grad student
They made all these different researchers who all seemed really excited about her twins blood sample
I think it was just weird that one of them had anencephaly one of them didn't and they were genetically identical
Play for them to compare
Kappa Delta one of the researchers even told them that they had compared
Thomas's blood to Callum
And
They found there were a thousand differences in epigenetics between both twins
They're called epigenetic Differences I think their genes are the same but the things that control the genes word
They began identical but then somehow in utero
Little changes
Set up between them
Yes
Fossil in a few this changes might one day explain the disease
In fact I even asked the grad student who work on it most closely
Deirdre crop as a were you surprised by what you saw and she said
For me to be surprised
That implies that I knew what to expect
So we're just at the beginning of this trying to learn about
So that's two roses like this is that is amazing yep is it to sort of
He's on a roll here
So after visit to they got in the car drove down the street to this place called Saito net
Is there a town with liver ended up
Basic recital net will take a solid liver
And they liquefy it
And then they inject the liquid liver into a baby
It's waiting on a liver transplant
Plant as a bridge therapy
Liquid liver
Yeah they went in again refrigerators Petri dishes
Issue with Thomas
His liver was bruised
When they got it
So they couldn't injected into a baby then they told her that they were able to use it in an experiment
To determine what was the best temperature to freeze infant liver cells
Which is -150 degrees C
As you already know
Okay have a rose and she says it one point as they were being walked around the place
We watch to the break room
And someone had taken a picture
Of Thomas that we had handed out
And they took the photograph and they taped it up in the break room
With a little sign that they wrote on it saying Thomas Gray was a donor here March 29th 2010
And it was so excited to see that cuz I thought they're just as curious about us
As we are about them
Like I was wondering who what kind of person goes to work and opens up a box with liver in it
You're probably wondering what kind of person takes their loved ones liver and put them in a box and mail it over here
So my name is Rupa Ganguli
I'm a professor in the department of genetics
At University of Pennsylvania School of Medicine
Nella Rupa Ganguly just switched her for a second she said he's a kind of cancer of the eye called retinal blast
Stoma which happens almost exclusively in children at this point
She doesn't know Sarah she has no concept of
What's happening
She is just studying eyes
Philly Philly Philadelphia
Nature studies tumors but she also needs healthy retinas in order to do her work now you can imagine that getting an arm
Retina
Is
Not a very
Easy task
Because why would you get it on
From a baby
I must have knew that if
And when an eyeball comes
It is not
A pleasant experience
Right because
For a moment you have to think
The origin of the sources
Stop this
Eyeball
It's
Sad
And every possible
Setting
It's sad
Sad and frustrating
Only when a normal child dies
That's what I can get this
Set a horrible setup
In my mind
She says often when the retina is arrived which is
After me once a year and you pull them out of their packaging you right away at you feel like
Maybe you're trading on other people's misery
And I mean it's so bad
When a child dies
But I am
Asking for his
Are her
Retina
Either way I had the sense of guilt
In my head
Never but never spoken to
Apparent
Any of her stamp
So when she got that email
Did you sitting your computer and she read the email from the company that provided of the sample saying the mother of this sample
Wants to get in contact with
I paused I stopped
And
Doing what I was doing and I thought
Why does the mother want
Talk to me
That was my first
Question
So
I did not reply right away
But after my conversation with the lab I
Took I think one day
To compose a letter
And I sent it back
Do Saturday
And they ended up eventually talking on the phone I told her I think
At the very onset that sorry you have to understand
And that
I feel awful
You said she felt kind of guilty because she wished for the stamp
Like almost by wishing for it
She made it happen
She said Aruba you should not feel bad about it
If you didn't use my son's retina I would have buried in the ground
You're the
Only one that wanted
Bad things happen to children
And so by being able
To help you
With your work
We added a layer
To Thomas's life
That was
I was amazed
Eventually Sarah and Ross visita de roupas lab
She gave them a tour
She sold them thomases right now
He still has
Samples of it in her
Freezer
Tiny little
I don't know tiny little vials maybe a third the size of your pinky filled with frozen liquid liquefied
Right now it didn't look like much but it was amazing to think of how many
People were involved
Getting the samples they're like
Like we had to
Approval we had to fill out this paperwork done the doctor had to come and remove the eyes and eyes had to be pressed
If not I have to be
Shipped up there that they have to
Do whatever DNA process they do and just
Valuable
Maybe even priceless
The simplest
Services that throughout the whole process
Nails losing
A child
And then seeing him reclaimed bit by bit by all of these differ
People
Something chic
Shifted in me
Like the universe
Treated people the way it should
And now I don't really believe that
But I'm
I do believe that
There are
Really amazing
Kind people
In the world
And
Science and medicine has something to do in life
I started feeling that
He's worked on his colleagues and his co-workers and that he was a valuable partner
In the important research that was being done
Can I feel 10 even more fundamental shift
Almost like I had felt like I was a boat on an ocean that was like
Rocky and choppy with waves
And I've had this feeling that I am not the boat on the ocean
Like
The decisions I make are changing other people
I'm supposed to just I'm about getting slapped with Waze all the time
It just made me feel powerful
Like to thank the Philadelphia Inquirer for getting us going on this
Michael Vick says for his reporting it's Damiano marchetti Productions portal
Pro that help with research
I'm Jedi Cam'ron
Message to the Radiolab credits
A job
Our staff include
Brenna Farrell
I want one
Either cable
David
Gambino
The test master
Target
Arianne wack
Raven Rock
Mario's Webster
Damiano marchetti
Bonnie Brae Jacobson Alexandra Williams
Are fact-checkers are Eva Dasher and Michelle Harris
And this message