Are you awake
Listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
Anyhow
So what have you been up to any microphone
I think we're going to share cuz what else are we going to do
I think
Strike like a Viper Radiolab
Go like this and today that's like that story about when things for
Far far away
Combiner head
Hit very close
Just put your hand on his forehead
Or over my bowel satisfying comes to us from producers Simon Adler
And anemic
Okay okay
So you're going to tell something about something
Who should I start
Okay so
We've been exploring what happened on May 18th
In the great city of Brussels
Specifically
Skarbek
Starbucks
When is mr. Gatti's in Brussels story starts with this
So
It was it was around
11:30 p.m. and I was
With one of my colleagues
Add a restaurant to have one of the good meal of the day
This
Is Emmanuel Emmanuel Williams
I am the the one everybody calls when should hit the fan now let's put it that way
And that evening Emmanuel along with much of the rest of the country
Was waiting around for that day is national election
The results
For all the
Difference parliamentary assembly
Manuel's mind was on something else
Because across the country that day millions of people had just voted on computers
Belgium was in the early days of experimenting with electronic voting
And so instead of filling
Paper ballot in the voting booth with a touch screen computer and and folders with walk-in
Insertive
White credit card size
Car tinting machine and then vote by selecting names on that
And I it was a manual job to make sure that all these hundreds of computers
Work proper
I'm an IT guy
Something like that at that point
At 11:30 at night after the polls are closed besides the usual
Computer glitches
It seems like everything has gone well and so we were there were two of us
He and one of his fellow ID
If you guys waiting for the others I guess
To talk about the other on the back for a job well done and that's when the
That's when his
Phone ring
It wasn't
And it was one of the officials of the ministry
They said that they had a problem that they had detected a problem in sky
And so some okay we're coming over
And so you pay the the check you hop in the car and I hope we paid the check.
15 minutes later they arrived together Black Escalade cuz I like to imagine and they they enter the polling
Station townhouse of Sky building with big tall ceiling
It's a very old building filled with this crowd of confused looking people
Well they explained to us that going through the numbers they noticed one of the contestants
Relatively unknown Communist Party candidate Maria vendaval gold had a very high number of votes
From this one
Polling station
And taking a closer look
They noticed that the number of votes for this contestant was
Impossible
Yeah if mathematical impossibility essentially she received more votes than there were voters who could possibly vote for
And so as a manual hearing this some serious is this just a fluke is there an explanation fraud
Thinking fraud
I'm smelling
It could have been tampering
I could have been a bug it could have been a hardware glitch could have been you could be anything
Yeah absolutely
First thing first they got all of the ballads
Does white
Plastic magnetic cards that the voters had loaded their votes on
Recount it
Reinserting every single
Magnetic card one by one
Several hours so now it's like 1:30 in the morning and they print out
The new recounted
Hold it up against the old one and they
How are the exact same results
For every single contestant
To the vote
Except the contestants which had had this
Abnormal number of folks
This time around Maria had far fewer
And at that point one of my college did the math
And set the difference between the number of votes she had in the first count and the number of votes she had in the
It's exactly 4090
Fewer votes
Does that mean anything to you
4096 know it means nothing to me
Well 4096 is not a random number
Is a
It's something about the number at this like I don't know. I don't know the answer but I have
This a deep sense
I'm feeling tingly
So if you guys are it people and you heard the number 4096 you feeling
Woodruff
To every it guy in the room
Number 4096 West was very meaningful
In fact
It was a clue a clue to a cosmic culprit capable
Is there a Bigfoot
Computers of swinging our elections
I can't float crashing our cars
And
Reminding us just how small and at the mercy of the universe
We really are
So it so it so why why is 4096 so important
Okay well to explain
I'd like to backup
Potato salad
Do the morning of the alarm
Okay so cold open and at some point
Live there white card through that card reader in
Maria vendaval received her first book
The registers booth number one for Maria
Yeah now when that happened inside the computer in its memory
Is 0 switch to A1
And I mean that both in terms of her vote total and also in in how a computer
The way computer works
Is that everything is stored in memory
I memory is binary
It's either a 0 or a 1
Either on or off
Tear It Off
In one
I think we all know this right there
Setmore we've heard it at least that deep down
Computers is everything one
Enter in this specific case what what that means is
All these individual votes that Maria would get throughout the day
They were all stored as as just once
As these individual ones
Not when you're limited to Counting with just one way to do it is to tally
Like you doing groups of 5 on a truck
Diagonal line
But when that Telly starts to get high
It becomes incredibly inefficient
Hope that way
So instead to save time energy and computing power
Computers do a little bit of math
8 Day Count using powers
Powers of 2
Remember powers of 2
Made something squared
Exactly two squared or two to the second power 2 x 2
Is 4
3rd power 2 X 2 X
2 is 8 to the 4th
Set a Rosetta Rosetta Rosetta so how is it a computer is doing that right
LP visualizes imagine inside a computer's memory there's this
Dreaming of 13 Light
Light bulbs that it people called
Each one representing a different Power of Two
Stick with me here first
First light bulb represent anything to the zero power equals 1
Second light bulb
Which is 2
The third bulb
Etcetera etcetera etcetera
When Maria received her first book
A little bit of electricity
Was sent to that first light bulb
2 to the 0 is 1
Now what you got her second vote this time some electricity was sent to that second ball
Turning it on representing two
Because two votes are stored in that second light bulb what what the computer does simultaneously
Is turn off that first
So to be clear when she got her second vote the first bald was turned off
Which represents ^ 1 with turn.
So it's now using only one bulb
To represent tube
Oh okay
Now in order to represent numbers that aren't powers of to all the computer does is turn on mulch
Will bulbs at 1
A sequence
Of power to for example when Maria got her third returned on the Earth and
Second light bulb because one plus two equals three when she got her fourth
It turned off the first and second light bulb and turn on the 3rd
V boat turns on the 1st and 3rd
What you got to say her 17th vote it is turned on V bald
16 + the first ball
Equaling 70
And so on and so on adding up these powers of 2 and with that respect
Is a power of two
C2 that number is one that they're like
Is that what that is
Yeah it's the 13th
Bit of memory
Which meant
That at some point during that day something somehow turned that bit off
Flipped what should have been a 02 A1
Yeah it was It was a
A binary flip
Your mind just went there and he shouldn't
Yeah I love that you call the IT people are like
Oh and all the non it people are like what
Well do he just trade
Okay so you know that it was just one bits
Flipped
What will what does that mean
So we knew that
The results
Could be
Trace back to the 13th bit
Flipping what we didn't know was what caused the bit to flip okay so what would that's your next question what what
What could cause if it
The flip
No idea
What did you spend it could have been a could have been in any number of things
And so we each in the following days we got access to absolutely everything
First thing they checked could have been
Software
So we carried out random tests on
Source code for any bugs that could have caused this bit to flip
But there was nothing
So we were fairly confident that it wasn't a software error
Okay so if it's not software
It Hardware right well
We got the machine that was actually used in that polling station on the day of the election
And Counting and they ran a bunch of memory tests on it to see if something came up
To see if some defect in the physical memory could have caused
Respectively what came back on that
Nothing
Not a single error
So the memory on that computer was working fine
What's up what the heck are you left
Not much
As far as we were concerned this one computer had a glitch which called
Give wrong answer
Unsatisfying answer that's the way things go we just simply had no proof
What caused the bit to flip
We just don't know
That's the way it it turned out
I'm so over the next couple of days Emmanuel and his
Team sat down to write up defined
Half expecting that once finished
Report would be filed away
Never mention
However hello hello Brussels can you hear us
Hyzaar
Simon in Smash
That was not
I have a
Your guest here
I arms
He was plenty of tea
Thank you
Yeah thank you Natalie
Hello
Hello is this Zoe
Yeah yeah it's me hello
All thanks
Tibet flight
Zoe's you know I'm a member of the volume and and back in 2003
Young and freshly elected to Parliament Iowa's 28
What's the age of most of the MPC
Yeah it's that
She was generally aware of what went down in scar back that there was a
This computer problem someone got some extra votes
It was read
Trench
And for me
It was really
Concern
Because our most concern is the people can trust the electronic system and wisdom
DeSoto
We are not sure the people can trust the system
Tok we waited for the report of the specialist
And finally
But three weeks after the election
Yeah we only what we ended up writing that at some point during the day
The 13th bit
Netflix
That's how we roll
Basically
Means nothing
Means nothing then that's what you think it no no no no there there must be more
Nobody can understand this sort of vocabulary
I was confused with explanation
Because way down at the bottom of the report in the final paragraph
The only thing they said about a possible cause was
And I quote
This phenomenon is extensively described in these specialized illiterate
Yes we did right
And what were you referring to their
Nothing in particular
What's this
Why
Did not
Explain what
Really happening
So Zoe went to her fellow parliamentarians and was like there was a
Problem
We don't know what really happens like we got to look into this
What can we check
Who can check
WeChat
But the people do older member of the parliament to say oh yeah she know she's
Daryl
Fringe
Style and she's speaking about problems basically
Forget about
It's done we are elected election our girl there was no problem
But I said no no
We must find out what
Where is really
The problems
Unspeakable
So
Zoe contacted me and she did send me the paperwork
Scary stories about to the guy named David
Cologne
He is a member of a group called
And we are fighting for ethics into electronic voting
Against voting machine yes but interesting way he's also like a Hotshot ikigai works for the European Parliament
Yeah and that's an IT people I tell you don't trust her
Don't put everything in or on for a long time you reached out and asked
Can you help me understand what are these random bitten versions like what is it called
I did computer science and bits are not flipping what are they talking about
So I needed to find out so I guess I started to
Google to ask what could explain the Articles or blog post
These are the things could always be traced back to some software bug
I'm eating something else totally satisfied comprised of new Search terms blah blah
Articles that made this strange claim
Good shape
A bit of memory
Wait what
They said yes
If the cosmic ray touch your computer the right way at the right spot
It could change
A bit
From zero to one
Gamma rays
Ain't that Belgium
In favor
I'm a particular Waterloo
We're not going to be able to use any of this statement
So you're saying that
Created this effect
In Belgium on that day
Was a Zing from deep space
That was the theory
The David kmak
My
First reaction West
But then it became a bit
Pizza because I found out about
Is IBM IBM research
Freeman's mind
IBM paper from the 70s
In in it
Electronic data processing center give me the latest news about random bit flipping and
Problem with computer memory
The report explain how in the 60s
NASA had noticed these random bit flips in their satellite
And then more recently how IBM itself Problems by the computer can be displayed and had studied their computers
At higher altitude so closer to
A space that's it
Closer to the sky
Closer to God
And I found out that they were more bit flipping
Hope they're all down at the sea level
In the only explanation they could come up with for for what
Be causing this
Weather
With cosmic rays
Yes when they investigated they found out that it could have been cosmic rays causing problems
Okay
Ghost cosmic rays essentially
Charged particle
Enso electronic systems
Can get affected by the way is Professor Bharat electrical
Jaringan computer science department Endwell brat wasn't involved in that specific IBM paper
He has essentially dedicated his life
To studying the effects
The cosmic rays
So we started noticing on the surface of the Earth this problem started around 2001
1 mm to time frame
Recent
Right and they helped me get me
Is this a thing that people know about me is just like a first time I hear of it
I don't know if she should continue on this road go to the cosmic ray land
Narrative or do you want cosmic ray land
Oh I like I loved it that that's a choice
Place where we get to decide
I am torn
Well I don't know it maybe
I think we dive in that we get we give some
Okay okay okay
I said so according to bharath to understand what happened that day in Belgium
We have to go back to a long time ago
Wait for it
In a galaxy far far away
I'm going to General Life way too much
Is in the distant galaxies there was a very very old star
That exploded and went to star explode it sent out the huge amount of
Material all sorts of little tiny charged particle
Discharge
Thrown into space
And this particles are going to travel through space
For millions of light years
Xiamen
These particles are passing through other galaxies they get disconnected they get prepped going or
Around songs by gravitational pull
Until finally on May 18th
One of these particles with lots and lots of energy
Entries are solar
And not long after that comes into the atmosphere
Ashes into an Earthly atmospheric Park
And in that moment
Energy transferred to most free particle potentially in hands off a little bit of energy
Causing that newly energized atmospheric Mart
Just started heading towards Earth on its way down its Max into a couple other part
Passing some of that energy on again causing those particles to fall
And crashing other particle
And this happens again and again as the particles and the cosmic energy catapult towards the surface of the Earth
And stop you get this Kaskade it's a shower of all these particles
From the doorway to look like a Christmas tree
Down at sea level
Down on the surface
Define discount
Belgium
Bose Electronics
System that was counting the world
In Belgium coming along humming along annoying its own way of telling the votes by
Turning on those lights
The switch that turns on those light bulbs is called a transistor but then start turns on or off
And that creates
-31 + 0
When it's on it sends out a little bit of electricity switching on a bulb
But the thing is
Different sisters can be tricked
Into turning on
So imagine
Suddenly this particle from outer space
Come zooming down and enters that voting machine getting precisely the transistor that
Troll that 13th bit
That instant the transistor is tricked and sends out a burst of electricity to that 13th
212 powder
And the bits
Flipped
Is 0 with change to A-1
And from the heavens
Does 4096 vote
Appeared
What the hell
Again David glow
I don't know I mean
Like if I took both cosmic ray
O on one side
I'm afraid that people will
Take me for somebody crazy
But
You can read it too if you Google those words you will find a lot of
Scientific stuff talking about that
Inside out not long after David and Zoe met up
Anne and David told her what he'd found
That that is pause
Who knows
That the vote was changed by the cops
Isis
Cosmic ray
Put down in the computer
And it's making me
It's not possible you are really sure
I've got no clue if that's the true explanation or not and there is no way to prove
That is a cosmic ray
But I mean it
The only thing which match their explanation
I will never can
Explain that in the party or going to laugh
Aware of all of this
At the next
Session of Parliament
I just decided
To ask a question to the new minister
Who was responsible for the election
Session gets underway
And eventually
The agenda turns design
Nope there's no audio recording of this
Possession but based on transcript
It went something like
She walked up to the podium at the front of the chamber
NBA
We should proceed alone but should be nice
She summarized but it happened in skarbek
And then explained what David had told
Better
Distr
Which inversion
Cayo Costa
Cosmic ray
Coolest program in the computer
The the room was that joking hahaha
So you should know come here with
The little green man
Dumb dumb
And the minister
You say yeah yeah poop worried was
Morrow are off somewhere but we see he has no problem with the results of the election
Without the minister
Serta motion to move on
But before her time could expire
Avant
Don't jump back in basically said
Wait a second
Think about what this could mean
If this is true like
Can we trust these machines
So I asked
Are you sure
There was no other
Cosmic rays somewhere
Change some of the results of the election
And the minister
After pausing for a moment
Admit
You was not sure
And when the minister said yeah press the other problem we don't know
There was a strength silence
And nobody can't laugh anymore
Democracy and stars do not get along
Apparently Debbie dips efecto dingo dingo I think
Someone here needs to hold the skepticism
I'll be scampi the skeptic what is what are the odds questions
And that this does happen
That that a cosmic ray can hit a computer and goofed
I mean
The only thing I can say is
I mean even a manual will concede that
Cosmic radiation can have an effect on electronic computers
And brats and his team have actually sympathized is happening this respect the mid flip
We will actually put the computer engineer accelerator
It's usually say cyclotrons which is basically this mini controlled supernova
I told magic to me but what they do within cyclotron bacon get you the.
Is concrete bunker
Point the particle beam added
Electronic systems working read drag all the wires out of the room blender few buttons to post
B21 the light comes on alarm sounds
Meantime
It's called Beantown
They blast a computer with these tiny particles a million particles
Or II just like those cosmic rays flying through space
And as is happening Bharat says you can sit there and watch the big flips
And given this fact would so he was really asking was
If the
Extrovert where I'm at
Photos of 96
Small bit sleeping
Then would you notice
Like what if a candidate just got 32 extra votes that invisibly changed and out
That that's the pot
It's only when the computer produce an impossible result
That you can tell
That day was something wrong
The tip of the iceberg
You want us to just throw the breaker do you guys want to come in and
Cintas is here what you do and then we'll come in and ruin it
Classic
Music Flower music
Buckle up
Can we come back we are driving full-steam ahead into that iceberg
Figure out just how deep it goes
What an interesting metaphor that the mixture going to drive a car
You have to ask mrs. Vanderbilt your third grade teacher to go back to the
Weather for section of the lesson rate correct in the next hour
This is Angela babiarz from San Jose California
Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world more information about Sloane at
Www.slha.org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help this summer I'm hosting
And I request for those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
We're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments
Brilliance
Basically I want to hear about this
I kid you know did something
It just means you lean back and say whoa
How do they do that
Maybe it was the moment that our kids you've been reading to 4 month started reading
Back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons and you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed are ready music in the margin of their geometry
We're interested in the
Specific moments where
Kid does something super smart but it doesn't have anything to do with the test
If you have a story please share it with us
Go to radiolab.org
Flash brilliance
Record short audio message
And that's where you're at. Org / brilliance
Thank you so much
Hey Betty
Jad and Robert Radiolab
So I so we just heard that 8 is that a single
Cosmic ray from deep space
Flipped a particular election result
I guess the next question is like you know why is this happening
All the time some of the I'm well if you mean like how often do those charged particles hit Earth
We are bombarded by this particle
Quite often
Is cosmic rays
Back having the coming
Yep they're coming for you right now
Somebody you are getting thousands of these particles going through
What an animal inside a building you're still going to get all those particles cuz most of these particles
Cannot be stopped Pages go through anything and everything
So Pratt seems pretty sure of
Yes yes
Simon Iver like weight
We got to see this
Parcels
Apparently Elder these particles are just too small to be seen with the naked eye
We are currently in the studio lacking the place out brought did tell us there's something we can build
Something called a cloud chamber with which is basically just an upside-down cup you filled with vapor
Yeah that might let us see the trails these particles leave behind
If you can make one that would be really really good
Here's what you're going to need
Make your very own at home
Cloud chamber now it turns out there's a lot of YouTube videos showing you how to do this
Chamber 1 starting a kid who looks about 4 years old
Outer space
So we had a pretty good chance of making it work
We got dry ice cast iron pan on my kitchen flipped it over
The chunks of dry ice
The metal cooling down
Most beautiful
Hazing
A metal pan was singing
Listen to
Puretone
Shut up next
Take a see-through plastic cup 24 oz
Friends
Had a little bit more red and purple
Thick adults in the bottom of the cup hold it in place with magnets on either side of the south magnets Chad
So that felt and rubbing alcohol pretty thoroughly soaked
Turn the cup upside down under the Nile very cold
Cast iron pan replace with modeling clay
Overhead lights off flashlight on Amite at the base of a cup
And then
Wait let's watch for it
How is this thing going to work or what are we trying to see here
So what we're looking for what should happen
Is that that cold metal is going to make
The alcohol vapor
Inside the cup condensed
And I turn into a cloud
Michigan to make a cloud
Sissy
Tiny little particles shooting through and we won't be able to see the particle itself but we will be able to see the trail they leave behind
And it's supposed to be very similar to
The trail that an airplane leaves behind in this country
Contrail exactly so what so what we're going to see is he's like tiny little airplanes are tiny little contrails inside this
Asbury Park
Exactly
All three of us are on our knees in the studio
It's black at the moment the only light is emanating from a headlamp on the inside
But maybe it's one of those like
Watched pot never boils
Nothing happened I don't think there's enough fog in there
Tomorrow
After about an hour of this
Halo around
Pulling up YouTube on our phones
Checkered scientific method to work via things to do
Okay
I see behind
Just in case
Alone in the dark
The little beam of light
I thought one
Very very tiny white thin thin thread
Materialize
They're there I'm seeing a bunch of offended in the cloud
Holding a shape for just a moment
How do you spell disappearing
Oh well
We couldn't not see them
Film
Three there
Doan's coming right through me
Okay I can now tell you not just because someone told me
Because I saw it for myself
Things are definitely real
And there are definitely a lot of
So I guess the next obvious question is
You know they're here
Besides that voting booth in Belgium
Like what else are they messing with
Has my phone ever
Is the probability such that my phone has likely been
Goof by a bit flip caused by a cosmic ray
Afternoon systems are getting big flakes on a daily basis
Okay
For example the routers
Let me hear when the internet hit parts of the internet get shut off by these things
Yeah I routinely even today
Whoa whoa whoa whoa down for five minutes
Cisco Systems
They already keenly aware of this problem
Apparently in the early 2000s
Google indexing system was down for 5 months
Okay what what what else
It has been approved by the
Lord of manufacturing plants have been goof Bible
Really expensive custom manufacturing plant which made custom machine
And one of the bit
So they were making things
Wrong
What's a real example of that
Not sure I can discuss what kind of
Machine
Not sure
Sorry something that the route was able to tell
Is that the higher up you are in our atmosphere
The number of particles with higher energy is higher
And that means the chances of a bit flip
Are also Electronics in airplane is always bombarded
By this particle in one thing the plane is flying it's on autopilot
And suddenly one of the bit flips that takes it out of the autopilot
Yeah
What airplane
Where
Transport site
Air flight
In about 2018 passenger
Send one crewman but was seriously injured when the Qantas Airbus noise.
Plummeting more than a thousand space
She's essentially dropped like a rock and it was all because of a one bit flipping weights
Caused by a cosmic
Wait it's just
Beaches nosedive 4015 people like Hitler had just turned off and have nobody
Oh my God
Because of a bit
Holy s*** now we should say that like even though bit flips are happening frequently
The vast majority of those flips
Behr midnight we don't even notice them flipping only Eve
It's right there in the right position
So for example in the Parliament that beat
Deadbeat flip method only if they were taking a wart at the time
And actually telling the world so the likelihood of a backflip having any consequence at all
Rare
Okay
Hello this message is for either Grover or Barbara
The strange call to receive I'm sure even crazier
Want to reduce my credit card interest or
Get me something for my pain this is Barbara Walton we reached her in Boiling Springs North
South Carolina one stop light town where she lives with her husband growth we've been here since
We got married 53 years ago
In one of those cars my gosh
Do you mind is just like telling me what you were doing the morning of the accident we live in North Carolina
We have a son that lives on the coast and South Carolina so we were going to visit to put a 4 and 1/2 hour drive
See through some pretty good-sized towns area we were in was more or less a rural area
2008 Prius Grover is behind the wheel in the back seat because I was on my computer and I didn't like to do that in
In the front seat because of the possibility of the airbag coming out and throwing the computer my face
I can ask what were you doing on your computer in the backseat
Probably solitaire
Something to occupy my time I usually
Snooze Orpheum
We've made that trip many times so I've seen the
Scenery
For the first three and a half hours at the drive
Everything is totally normal
Grover calmly at the wheel driver on a laptop
And then
Barbara looks up from a computer if my husband is speeding
And I I said are you doing
He said I can't slow down
And
I said will you have to play that he said I'm applying the brake it is not slowing down
When how did you guys remember exactly how fast you were going better judge of that than I would
When are when are car
Ran away with us
How fast would you say the car was going
I'm sure it was more than that
He's saying 65 I'm saying 6570
I can imagine feeling like
Really panics
Mr. Walton does
Panic mrs. Walton
I am freaking out
At this point in the Drive-Thru on a two-lane highway coming through a huge Wetland area so I'm both sides it's just swamp
In water
And
I didn't want to go down into the swamp husband the driver
Break
It's quick as I took my foot off the brake it was start
Accelerate being again I finally just basically stood on the
Break
The way they describe that it was almost like one of those Hollywood movies where you're like
Creating them Highway we are not slowing down dipping by car seat belts on in and out of traffic
Computers
Praying that this was going to turn out alright
4 somewhere between 10 and 15 minutes
Grover fought
With the car. I can't remember if
How how did you stop
I know we cross that swampy Bridge
Award
Brake pads and the rotor
Okay so that's what stopped
By just applying the brakes so long and
It's so hard
It wore the brakes on the road around that's how
The car finally came to a
They called her son who did some quick research online and apparently there were already
Complaint
Find in a toilet
Turned out all over the country
Silver a 100-foot cliff
Toyota cars Toyota trucks there Toyota
I remember this is abuse with a new story
From the driver point of view what was happening
Was that the car would take off
Sometimes at low speeds but sometimes at high speed
And the drivers would say
My foot was on the brake pedal but my car kept going faster
This is still coatman he's a professor at Carnegie Mellon University and co-founder of edge case research
Am I special to you for all these years
Fault tolerant Computing and Phil told us that around the same time he's accidents started happening in the early 2000s
Was the same time that Toyota cars
All cars really
We're starting to become computerized
That's right before this moment cars are mostly mechanical and you feel like you don't pop the hood
Basically figure out what was going on but after this moment it's
Mostly computers
And not just me engine your car has
Dozens or in some cases more than a hundred little boxes
DELL Electronics inside it has small small books
Like a paperback book in the wall and floor and ceiling of the
The car wherever they can find
They do all sorts of little things you take out your keys in your press the button and your doors unlock
There's a computer inside that key
Sending a message
To a computer inside the
The car telling the computer at the Lock to open the lock 3 computers are conversing about that unlocking moment
At least
In the responsible for some
Pretty important thing
Things like now when you press the gas pedal
I instead of it being this direct physical link
To the throttle
Make the car go that pedal is now basically just an input
Computer why do they want to do that
What you can get better fuel economy you know it's a it's a more pleasant Drive
So that part is great it's a better driver experience but
You just trusted your life
2 software
And that's a new thing
Was that talked about or known or was this sort of a silent transition that you as the driver would never really know unless
You looked it up in Popular Mechanics
I don't think that you would probably have known as regular driver
And so when this whole thing broke because most people didn't know that their cars were now
Computers and because most
The victims were on the older side
People
Barbara says when they took the car to the Toyota dealership I'll never
Forget
This
Market
Grin he had on his
Face
Telling us he didn't find anything wrong
With the car
If you're on the car company side you say so you press
The pedal and it kept going faster which pedal does that
Damn I've been driving since I was 15
What is a difference in the accelerator and Brake
Weather radar
Until August 20th 2009
911 call came from a passenger of a Lexus Toyota
Okay
You don't have the ability to like rental vehicle
Not one of the four people in that
Car survived
The 45 year old
Male California highway patrol officer Mark Saylor who Specialties vehicle inspector
A10 dead this guy can't stop
Best car
Just broke that driver error narrative
Toyota has a problem pieces and so that's what launched all the inquiries in the recall
Tarzan finds Toyota settled huge 1.6 billion dollar lawsuit
Bass car without admitting any blame but after that
2000 reported cases are federal criminal investigation into Rising 289
People accuse you of 500 death and injury cases
Started to form
And when the experts
Still being one of them giving full access
Do Toyota's software and Hardware they found a number of things wrong
But the key in all of this
Was
You guessed it if you had a bit flip the test that controls the throttle position could die
Causing it to stick
In some open position that would happen
They reproduce that on a car willing in in the first of those
Death and injury cases what
What happened
The tree said that they
But I have to make sure I only say things I'm allowed to say
Actually big deal after
I wanted the experts
African time
So you have to be careful
Wow okay
Start
The jury found
That
Toyota was liable
For the Deaf
And the only Theory presented in the case was that the computer
Kill people
A temperature agreed
Toyota settle that case immediately and begin to settle all 500 other cases in the queue
Hey everybody let's not drag this thing out and put it through
The public I can't speculate as to the motive spend right I think the facts speak for themselves
God humming this is
Yeah and I'm like one quick crazy side.
Is ruling actually led to the freedom of a Minnesota man named cool if only
We already spent
Two and a half years in prison
Charged with vehicular homicide for killing three people in an in the Toyota he was driving when it suddenly
Control ruling like
I got the sky to prison but he was in prison for 2 and 1/2 years
Do you know
Is acceleration
That's not enough
Winfred like in your opinion and your experience
Do you think this specific case and other cases were in fact caused by Justice
Frazee
Cosmic chain of events that led to
A tiny little bit of electricity
Grazing
A circuit board
As amazing as it sounds
These type of events are almost certainly caused by that now was that the primary
Contribution to the toilet
I don't know and
Probably no one will ever know
I think the way you're painting the world almost as looks like it they're just smoking wrecks everywhere they crashed
Planes and
Tarzan 2 light poles and the internet's not working it how are we
How are you functioning
We went back and we started fixing the prompts
Once we know that autopilot is the one that's causing the problem been respect
How do you fix it so you get three copies of everything the same electronic system that three of them
And at least two of them have to agree to do anything
Smart
So today like tripling and doubling redundancy is a norm and planes and cars with any other life
Trending technology
And actually the same thing was done in skarbek at after that incident in 2003
So now when they haven't
Election vote is actually counted twice by the
One of the tallies doesn't match the other that they know something's gone wrong and media
So that's cool
But here's the thing
Is doubling and tripling is just too expensive to do with mosto
Thanks
And as our Electronics gets smaller and smaller and smaller and smaller and smaller
Just going to happen more and more
Why would that be
The smaller the transistor the less energy you need to flip that bit
I need the housing electrons
30% of 1 or 0 how many electrons did you need back in the 70s
I'll probably million
Oh and now you just
And transistors made today
I like
Tiny Thai
Your hair is 50 Micron in diameter so take your hair
Inflated thousand times
So that gets you down to 15 m
And we are looking at 7
So you want some pretty much slices down 7 more times
And what you are left with
Easter size of transistors that are coming
In the market
In the neck
2 years
Baby in cell phones and laptops and things like that
They would be everywhere
Show as we get better and better and better than miniaturizing our technology
You're more and more and more
At risk to these tiny flying
Through our technological advancement
We have invited this problem upon herself
That is one way to look at it did you go back to those big cell phone
Being 5 kg each
Footlong
Then you won't hear this
Thanks Annie Simon
Yeah actually have one more thing
Sure
Well we've been doing some research into this and we talked to a bunch of electrical engineers
And this is going to sound very very strange
But what these researchers are saying
A likely cause
Was
A cosmic ray hitting one of the computers could cause
At the driver to lose the ability to control the gas
Oh my Lord
Well I am not a scientist
Sick person
Anything's possible
Now you're saying we're bombarded by cosmic rays all the time
If that's so perhaps
Maybe we just
Maybe we just got baptized
Do you think Grover would be if I'm just curious to hear his reaction to the possibility
Your car accelerated because of cosmic ray hit
What is he think about that
There is one
Siri said an engineer came up with that there
Engineer's hat
Come up with us
Siri
You know we're bombarded with
Cosmic rays all the time
What's Cosmo
Raise all the
What time
And it's possible
That a cosmic ray
If it hit
Just at the right time in the right place
On board
Shooters and
Possibly that
Accelerator
He wants to know how you
I feel about that
I'm so bored open-minded but
At this point in time
You know I question that but
It's not that big a deal
Okay
Alyssa
It's home and
White one time
Well we couldn't agree more and so what we've decided to do
Is provide you with a small entertainment for you to sip your white wine with
Simon has made a video
To accompany this app
Episode
Speaks.
It isn't radiolab.org
Watch it's very short
Weird
This piece was produced and avoided by Simon Adler and
McEwen
Special thanks to Lucas director and two veg week 2 Booker
Andrew Francesca constanzo and Kelly Gallagher Natalie Higgins in the Hailstone Ice Company
In Crown Heights book
Okay you don't go now
Yeah I think so
I feel real
I can I saw that in your voice
I'm Jared I'm rod and I'm just going to stay here
While you're here yet he's Robert
And I'll see you in the next one
Is so much fun so much fun
My name is Tim and I'm calling from Cleveland Ohio and is produced
Spy Store on Wheeler Dylan Keith is our director of sound design
Suzie lechtenberg is our executive producer Becca Bressler
Rachel Cusick David gamble Bethel Hampton Tracy hunt Nora Keller Matt kielty
Robert krulwich Annie McEwen Latif Nasser Melissa O'Donnell sarakari Ariana whack
Pat Walters Molly Webster with help from Shima Ali andreea Quinn
Are fact-checkers Michelle Harris