Northern listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
Hi I'm Robert krulwich I Molly Webster Radiolab and today
We've got breaking news Robert krulwich
Drake this is something we've never done before never done before what does anybody know about this yet
Well it is a new bit of research is being published today
We've known about it for the last few months
But we haven't been able to talk about it
What's this thing about
So is this is a discovery about Alzheimer's
Disease
Which I think at this point is something that affects
Basically every family
Affected my family
And this is
A discovery that is not a cure but it's
Basically about looking at the brain
Which is one of the most complicated things in the universe I thing
And poking at it in this super simple way
And getting
Desposar results
How is your car
Pretty bizarre
Hello
Hello hello
Hi Molly hi how are you alright so last night I was talking to some folks over at the brain Institute at M
A mighty and while I was on the phone with them they started telling me about some research that had been published
It was all very
Oshkosh
Be cool though we ended up
Defining to sign a non-disclosure agreement
And it was based on the work of this woman Lee Wei Tile
The weight I sigh
Ty I'm a professor and the director of The picower Institute for learning am I
Memory at MIT
Holy crap you're a director
How do you have time to do all that that's a good question she is like a badass is what she is
Buy this is the piece of work and I'm very proud of
I'm very excited about
Okay cool so Amy's eliminate let me begin okay so historically people work on Alzheimer's
Really
I would say generally when you talk to researchers about Alzheimer's disease
They either focus on individual genetic factors
The genetics of the disease so that
Jeans that
Predispose you maybe to alzheimer's the brain chemistry and how Alzheimer's affects
Chemicals in the brain molecular
Pathological features do my conversation with leeway
She was talking about something totally different sort of look at it from a different angle
Ignore work all centers around something called
The gamma frequency
The gamma gamma and what is Battlestar
I don't think it's that
You could think of it as a particular
Beat
In your brain
A beat in the brain
Yeah which means what exactly
Well just to oversimplify one of the most complicated things in the known universe
Got your brain
Full of neurons which are a certain type of brain cells we have
Billions of neurons in the brain they have you
Long tentacles that are reaching out
Towards other neurons
And for the brain to function neurons have to communicate with each other to process information and the way
Way they do that is
They fire
Yes
An electrical signal will go through them in a like that
Another neuron it'll turn it on and then it'll like an electrical signal will go through it and then
Turn it on but the cool thing is is that when your brain is doing things like making you move
Write a poem or think great thoughts
Groups of neurons fire in sync all together on the same
Beat
And there's a bunch of different Pizza happen in the brain
Some of them are slow like one beat per second and that's
When you're sleeping
If you're beating around 10 beats per second like maybe you're sitting next to a campfire in an Adirondack chair
Chair
Or unless I totally other end of the spectrum
Like some neurons fire at 600 Beats
Per second or do they do or die that I have no idea. All this is going on in your head simultaneously yeah
The cool thing is that when
All of these beats in your brain come together that's when you're able to
Process the world
And understand it as it exists
Is human being
But getting back to our story
When your brain is doing something really tricky that requires super focused attention working
Memory and and so on trying to find your way
Home from the subway station or if you're in a new city you don't navigate around it there's a certain beat
It sort of rises above them all and that is but so cold gamma frequency
This range between 30 beats per second all the way up to a hundred feet per second and is gamma frequency has been
Consider to be very important for the higher-order
Cognitive function and the interesting thing is that when you look at an Alzheimer's brain what you see
There's actually less gamma happening or people say like the power of gamma is reduced
Has can be recruited to oscillate at the gamma frequency it's still there
Quieter
Thank you turn the volume down right
Isos just a briefly some up here what we've got is a rhythm which we call gamma
Which is used when we have
Complicated are higher thoughts in the brain
Which one you got Alzheimer's
Kind of gets
Saggy
So tired of course
Obviously in an Alzheimer's brain there's a lot going on in this is just one of the things
Right you got the plaque buildup around the neurons the stuff that
Except your brain and makes it hard to think
The cobwebs in the brain
And then the connections between neurons gets all muddy heated immune cells get messed up but I was like
Forget all that
What would happen if I just bring the gamma back yeah
We decided
To just manipulate
Gamma oscillations
How do you how do you do that
Well
Hello hello hello hello hello
Technology hi this is Molly hi hi hi
Technology you can find at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology
And actually I went took a train up to Boston at MIT not too long ago
It's a
Big Shiny glass building
Eventually lose weight I came striding into her office to meet me
What you want to see
And Toby way let me down the hall to this tiny room
Brought in these
Adorable little myself my gosh they're like little black
Can soft and furry
Ears are
Tags little metal tag
So here's what they did
I get some ice we started all please a mouse model not the mice I actually got all excited over but my city
Early stage of Alzheimer's disease
Swissmar Depot notable defects
Do they have the Donkey
Black stuff in them yet or is that later but they do have elevated levels of
Peptide switches this protein that forms the plaque
So it's like basically black gunk
But the important thing to lose weight on your team is that they have less gamma going on in their brain
If you remember the whole plan here is
To bring the gamma back yes
So
To do that
They get what might be the worlds
Can I use drill and a drill a small hole
Into the skull of the mouse
And then they take a really thin fiber optic cable they slide it through the hole into the brain
And then they get the Blazer of blue light to flicker
40 beats per second yeah my frequency and they turn that on in the light travels down the fiber optic cable deep down into the brain
This group of cells that they modify
In the hippocampus
To be sensitive to light
So when the pulsing light hippie sells they actually began to fire at 40 beats per second
A gamma frequency
When our
Hiring and firing and firing and hiring and firing then
After 1 hour they turn off the light and then eventually they started looking at the the brains of these mice
Trying to figure out if anything was different
After the light flash
And they see
2 armat surprise
We're not expecting this at all we found
After they shop is pulsing light into the brain there was
Suddenly nearly
Half as much
That soon-to-be nasty black Gunk stuff
That was filling up
Half of the stuff was just Swept Away yes
40 to 50% reduction of beta-amyloid that just seems
This is crazy I mean
We were just so surprised
Do they know why
Why the flu turn out
The pulsing light somehow triggered the brain's clean up crew
Microglia the cells in the brain that are called microglia you can say they're the janitors of the brain
Normal brain these janitor cells usually gobble up a gum
Spot
In Alzheimer disease
It's known that Michael gliadin.
They don't serve the function normally anymore
I'd like these janitors just sort of
Stop
Cuttin Up
And go on strike
Fairy
Okay so we're looking at a screen that's now
Flat it's not not the one I was at a mighty one of leeway is grad students my name is Anthony Moore
Martorell
Boys showing me side-by-side comparisons of the mice brains on the screen
Which
The green things microglia
And you see after 1 hour
Of gamma wow
The microglia the cell
Themes
A lot bigger clearly see these round
Bodies
And also the belly
Sims will have more amyloid
Oh like you're doing more eating
Yes they go back to eat more amyloid again it's like somehow making the neurons fire turned on the
Sanitation system in the brain
The most
Wild
Results with there's more wild oh my God you got to hear this because what I'm about to tell you
You may say no I don't believe it it's science fiction
Okay
So one of the things leeway in her team were starting to think was that
Drilling in fiber optic cable
Very invasive right you never be able to do that on
Human exact
So we started to say well
What if we can get the light
Into the brain
In a different way like maybe
We could go through
The eyes
Tony the hole in your head would be your eyes instead of a hole in your head
So we way and her team created what I like to think of as
The flicker room
What is the real
This is a room and I visited is just a storage closet you know you have a
What is this
Just like
The table fairy DIY it's a plastic table you can buy at Target there was some plastic shoe
Box size containers lined up on the table for the mice
And then go see the strip
Around the edge of the table basically surrounding all the
Are duct tape
Strips of LED lights
And other reason or use LED this because a regular light bulb
Can't flash fast
Intellij idea is what if we just
Put the mice in this room and just let the light flicker
At 40 Beats
4 seconds to show Molly like attorney
Yeah
And so we turn off the overhead light in the room
So it's very black and then
Oh wow
The room was now glowing with this white LED light
Peso the light is
Turning on North
20 * 2
It is so there's not you not you don't see anything going like on or off
I just looks like something on but it kind of feels like my
My eye is twitching
And so is blurring the the Blurred the Lytle
Just on the edges
On the edges when do they put mice in this room for an hour and just let them kind of Bays
Bathe in this in this glow and guess what
What we look at
The amyloid-beta levels
In the visual cortex
And we found
There is a 50
50% 50%.
Weasley didn't they didn't
Do any Drilling in their stalls or anything so they didn't have to be sensitive to light
I filled the room with occasional LEDs flashing at a particular frequency for an hour
Are you going to tell me I don't believe it is
Science fiction
And they followed the study up with another study which was done in the same way so are the same flicker room light through the eye
Highballs and only this time they put the mice in there for one hour day for 7 days
And they took my SAT had full-blown Alzheimer
So this is like
Cognitive decline they're forgetting things and they've got hardened plaques in their brain
They say the same thing nearly
Half of the stuff
Was cleared away
Half
Flickering light
In front of them
That's the shot I mean that's the shocking thing
The thing I didn't understand after talking to you about your study was I was like
Why hasn't everyone done this before like why didn't everyone go we should just shine light through eyes
Will you know that's
It's really the most unexpected and exciting as back
Or study
Peaches
Something this simple
Yet
You know it has never been done before
One of the things at one of the caveat here
Is that if you don't do the flicker Lite room every 24 hours a level of gunk in the brain starts going back
Back up again and so now they're trying to figure out how they
Keep those levels
Down maybe the fur good
If
V
Mouse no longer has quite as much
Junking is he
Does that mean that it can
Remember things that
Happened to it
Yeah that is
There
They don't know that's what they're too that is now.
Next Step but nobody really understands how
Plaques and the gunk buildup in the brain relates to memory and key
Cognition
The Dogma in the field is that when you have Alzheimer's
You can't form
New memories and once you lose the memory it's gone for good
But there is another group at MIT that is actually
Thrift challenging that assumption that
You can never get a memory back cuz the person could never tell us
We all assume that the information have to be gone
All really
And we'll get to them
The first day of school
This is Kevin Murray from Fort Collins Colorado
Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation enhancing public understanding of Science and
Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloane @www.
Sloan. Org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
And I request for those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents
Aunts and uncles teachers
We're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments
Basically I want to hear about this
Did you know did something
It just means you lean back and say
Well
Maybe it was the moment that our kids you've been reading to 4 month
Started reading
Back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin
Or maybe the kids in math
Taking the margin of their geometry
We're interested in the
Specific moments where
Kid does something super smart
It doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story
Go to radiolab.org
Splash brilliant
Record a short audio message
And that's radiolab.org
Flash Brewing
Thank you so much
I'm rubber clovece Molly Webster
Is Radiolab more back and just before the break you said that
There may be a way
To bring a memory back
Holding me back
Team to be in the play
Yeah
Wide why are we so quick to jump to the conclusion that the information was somehow completely gone
And the person who said that to me is this guy
Something else
Over at the town of Growlithe they were thinking
What if we could figure out eggs
Exactly where the memory should be in the brain
I just give that spot a little bit of juice
So they took some ways that were just starting to lose their ability to remember things and they thought okay let's try to give them a memory
Meet them in a box that has a particular smell some sort of lighting and some texture on their feet a little mouse
Carpenter
The point is the Box looks and feels and smells different than any other box they would hang out in
And then give them a light electrical shock
And the mice
They just freeze
They don't move at all which is a sign that they're afraid
The Heat
And for the rest of the afternoon which is very long time and mouse time they go on hating the Box
Which means
With the carpet in the light in the smell if you put it back in there it'll
Breeze
Because it remembers
Yes
But
Day or week later when the same lights are put back into the same box
Still just continue investigating as if nothing happened
The cannot remember
So did Raj and his team did with leeway did they got some modified mice and then it put a little hole in their head
Slit in a fight Rock
Optic cable they shine some light
Trick of the neurons if they think
Hold this memory
And they were
Near the fear section so leading on the path to the fear section
So we do this
And then
Put them back into box the box with a particular lighting and smell in carpet
Is there any change in their behavior
Will they act afraid again
Do they show any more memory
And they did
Shut up if they actually were scared of the boxing
They showed recovered memory
Best memories in there
Exactly
Behaviors back
You can dig up the memory by
Shining Light in the right place
Yeah
I was always under the impression that their memories were totally lost
Just do it
Essentially the entire field
That's good because the patient could never tell us
We all assumed the information have to be gone
So one of the things to say is that deraj did tell me that you know all of this
The experiments they did are in
Mice that have early Alzheimer's
Are the Saudis so is that once you get to the late stage of the disease there's enough damage in the brain that you really wouldn't be able
How to get those memories
Is back
That might
Be right
Other memory loss
Distrust
Lost but you know when you
When you have someone in your house
And you are
Can you live with this disease day in and day out
The disease
Just
Goes its own way and
Puzzleyou or
Writing you or
I believe the clear something new that you didn't expect
So for example my dad had it for about
19 years
Slow
Active disappearing Heat
Wearing the last
Time my father
Team
Was so far into the disease
He hasn't spoken
For year-and-a-half
He was sitting at the table for the Passover Seder
And there's a song that you saying
Panagos die die die die
Dino Dino Dino Dino
Decorous
End
From out of nowhere
This
Being
At the end of the table who I knew was my father who hadn't spoken in a year and a half or two and have not spoken
Coherently
Suddenly
Blue into the song
And sang the song
Full-throated lie at the table
Like
The reappearance of some just last
Figment of himself
It was both horrifying
Extraordinary
The fact that maybe some information still persists hopefully someday we could maybe that's something we could do
Solo
My mind at the moment
As long as we can figure out
How to reboot
The pathway to retrieve the memory then I think there is
This is the way tie again but
You know I I personally think the most important question is
Whether humans were
Respond
Similarly
I mean keep in mind that both
Daraja study and leeway ties are in mice not humans
Right so I do have a spot that like why I like
Is there a reason that a human neuron might react differently than a mouse
The thing is I sing especially you know in all timers field I mean people got burned a lot
You know there's like I-99
.6% failure rate in moving something that seemed to work in mice to humans
6 yeah that was a study that came out in 2012
That's a horrible number
So
I just got to be
Julie
Conservative while we have in my stitches
So exciting and so unexpected so much fun
But
You know I'm going to keep my mind open
When it comes to Human
The plan is that we're going to find out because they're going straight to Human
Oh look a new human trial
Will they want to so yeah I guess we'll see
This is a glorious part of
This
Oregon
The main is so crazy complicated with whatever
100 trillion connections whatever it is
There's so much
Chance
There's going to be a lot of surprise
Yeah it's like I almost even if it doesn't lead to any that treatment in humans or
Something
Super concrete it's like we know this little secret about the brain now
And if something
That feels
But beautiful
Yeah I'm actually sitting the stuff for my Christmas
Are you really
That way I just bought the new LED lights and they can they can fix her a different color
I was different colors each individual
Travel through colors but while they're doing that they're going to be flickering at 40
We going to have a very
Therapeutics
Christmas household
This is the tree in your home
Yes
I want to have an eggnog next to that tree
We thank you Molly for free what a remarkable
You're welcome
It was also produced by Annie McEwen Matt kielty
Molly Webster again I would help
The Simon Adler and special thanks to
Susumu
Balaclava
NYC
And thank you all
Bye
This is Tiana Brinton calling from LA
Radiolab
Is produced by Jad appenrod
Dylan Keith is our director of sound design
Soren wheeler is senior editor Jamie York is our senior producer our staff includes Simon Adler Brenna Farrell David
Gible not guilty Robert krulwich
Annie McEwen
Latif Nasser Melissa O'Donnell area
Emily Webster
With help from Tracy hunt
Cigar Vitaly
Phoebe Wang Kitty Ferguson
Alexander Lee Young W Harry Fortuna and Percy of Berlin
Are fact-checkers are Eva Dasher and Michelle Harris