Are you awake
Northern listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
Hey I'm Jared I'm Robert krulwich
This is Radiolab
That's weird if you would tell those people who might have missed what you were doing what you been doing
We just finished our first
Mini season of our first spin-off
Call Moorpark
When you going to have part 2 part 2 is
Kunming
Soon I don't know not tomorrow okay but but not but not long because we
Yeah there's third they're definitely stories to tell for sure if you if you haven't checked it out.
Check it out at Radiolab.
It took me rescue you from this awkward situation by being back to Radiolab
Where I would like to begin by building a
A tall dark dense
Green Forest
Flowering trees
You're laughing
Right now
Anita
Bird
Gmail
Birds please
Birds why did like
Who started the street why are you do you give me
I want win Birds
How do I
Alright nevermind
This story you'll get your sound of sun
Begins with a woman or a man actually she was a very little girl
The outdoors
I mean
Really love
The outdoors
When I was a little kid I would be in the fourth and I just eat
The forest
And I know lots of kids
Do that but I was going to say what do you mean you got down on all fours and just eat the dirt
This is Suzanne Simard
And so my mom always talks about how she had to constantly be giving me worm medicine because I was
I always had worms she's a forestry professor at the University of British Columbia and might as well start the store
So you back when she was a little girl when I was a kid I grew up in the rainforests of British Columbia and my fan
Family
Spent every summer
I'm in this world
And her family included a dog named
Cheeks and so in this particular summer when the event with jigs happened what kind of dog is jigs by the way
He was a
Not a weiner. He was a what was he
You don't know what your dog what
Basset Hound
He was a beagle beagle he was a curious dog
And on this particular day she's with the whole family they're all out in the forest
It was summertime
And cheeks at some point just runs off
Into the Woods
Rabbit whatever
Couple minutes go by and all of a sudden
We could hear this
Barking and yelping and
We were all like oh my goodness
Texas in trouble
When school
The hope
Family in the uncles and
Aunts and cousins we all Rush up there
Do they follow the sound of the barking and it leads them to an outhouse
And when they go in there is jigs at the bottom of the old host
Probably six feet down at the bottom of the Outhouse pit
Oh dear we've all been you know
Doing our daily business
Falling in he's looking up at us
Quite scared and very unhappy that he was covered in
Oh and toilet paper and
Of course we had to get jigs out I mean jigs was part of the family
He was so deep down in there we had to dig from the five
To sort of like white in the hole
Basically expanding it from a kind of a column of a pit to something that
We can actually grab onto his
Front legs and swollen.
And so
Digging away
And jigs with you
Looking up with his paws you know looking at us waiting and they're digging and digging and digging and all of the sudden
She said she looks down into the ground and she notices
A tall round with a sore that has been cleared away
There are roots
Enroute Sepang rootinest
Greasy Tangled we're sitting on the exposed root system which is like
It is like a mat it's it's like
It's just a mess of matter intertwining exposed roots that you could walk across the Never
Fall through
She said it was like this moment
Wish you realize only
Is this
Who are the world
Right beneath my feet jigsaw provided this incredible
Window for me
No ends digging EX
How many different
Colors they were how many different shapes
Afterwards that they were so intertwined
As abundant as what was going on above ground
It was magic for me
What's the what's the end of the story did jig
Did you emerge as we pulled Tigs out
And
We threw them in the lake with a great deal of yelping and
Cursing and swearing and jigs
Cleaned off
But that day with the roots is the day that she began thinking about
Forest
Texas
Underneath
And now if you fast-forward roughly 30 years
Even makes a discovery
Lifeline
IND
Amazing
She's working in the timber industry of the time this is by the way what her entire family had done
Her dad and her grandparents
And when I came on the scene and 19 the need 1980 does a Forester
We were into Industrial
Large-scale clear-cutting in western Canada
Huge machines
Loaders and cats
She says a Timber Company would move in and clear-cut
An entire
Petrified Forest
MN plants and nutrients
And my job was to track how these new plantations would grow
And she said she began to notice things
One wouldn't be lyrics
Like
Trees of difference be
Are supposed to fight each other for Sunshine right
Yeah
Other way so they can get to the sky
But you was noticing that in a little patch of fur that she was studying if she had say
Tree next to us
Fir tree
And she took out the birch
The Douglas fir became disease and and died
There was some kind of benefit from the Birch to the fur
There was a healthier Community when they were mixed and I wanted to figure out why
Of course I could be at home any number of reasons why
No one trees affected by another
But she had a kind of
Maybe call it
Xen recollect
Flashback yes cuz she knew that scientists have proposed two years before
The underground
Economy
It exists among trees that we can't see
And she wondered whether that was true
And so
Design of experiments
Figure that out
It was a simple little experiment theater
Recover them in
Plastic bags
Videos of plant the tree in a plastic bag and then I would inject
Gaso tag with a with a knife
Which is radioactive so these trees were basically covered with bad
Exit within filled with radioactive gas
Suck up to photo center
So now they have the radioactive particles inside their trunk
Are branches we had a geiger counter out there
As soon as we labeled them we use the geiger counter to 10 rounded up and down the trees and we could tell that they were hot they were
I mean I do what she wanted to know like
What's the radioactive particles
Entry what happens next will they stay in the tree or where they go
Down to the roots and then what have
And what you discovered is
All these trees only cheese at work
Totally different species
We're sharing their food underground like if you put a food into one tree over here
It would end up in another tree maybe 30 feet away over there
Tree over here
I'm going to 4th Street over there and V street over there 6th 7th 8th 9th
10th 11th Olin all turns out one tree was connected
47 other trees all around it was like
It was like a huge Network
And
We were able to map
The network
And what we found was that the trees that were the biggest in the oldest
Were the most highly connected
SOB you know we
Identify these are kind of like hubs in the network
And when you look at the map what you see or Circle sprouting lines and connecting to other circles also sprouting line at a
Used to look a lot like an airline flight
But even more dense
Just incredible Communications Network that
You know people have no idea about in the past because we couldn't didn't know how to look
It's definitely
Crazy I mean
You're out there in the forest and you see all these trees and you think they're individuals just like
Animals right
But no
They're all linked to each other called The Artful amoeba
It Scientific American
Lincoln title
I spoke to her with our producer lettuce Nassar
And she told us that this
This network
He has developed a kind of a nice
Funny sword name
The wood Wide Web
The world wide web web it sounds like Elmer Fudd it would wait with
So this would wine
Is this just like the roots like what she saw in the Outhouse no no no no no
Armoire
Exciting than that
And sophisticated interesting in the
Astonishing
A completely separate organism I haven't mentioned yet I mean this is
Going
What creature where we going I'm not going to tell you I'm going to
Go there we might look for a song I don't know where you were that day
Any chewing Stephanie danler intern
Things are producer we decided all to go to check it out for myself
Think I'm not telling you about
We went to the Bronx
To the botanical gardens cuz we have to travel here in New York to get to actual Greenery Jackson was a beautiful green
Sweat New York Hat
And when we went up there we there was this
Whole man waiting for us
An expert
Is that really
His name is Roy howling
Unruly by the way comes out with the
Strange
It's like a rake
Hezekiah expandable
It's a truffle rake
Oh that sounds dangerous
I told her up there in this
Old Forest with this guy
He starts digging with his rake
At the base of the
Cubs away the leaves he shoves away the topsoil
And so now we're down there without a tablet
We carefully examining the roots of his Oak Tree on our knees with our noses in the ground that we can't see anything
But then
Finally
You have the length
Gives us a magnifying
Little Jewelers glasses handheld
Any answer to an
UCF
Oh my gosh I do see them
What do you say
Threads attached to the roots smaller than an eyelash
Maybe just a tenth the width of your eyelash
But why
Translucent
Harry
And while it took us a while to see it apparently these little threads in the soil
And when you measure them
In a pinch of dirt
What are pinch
What is it like as a plant
What is a what kind of creature is this thing that's what is it
This
Is the fungus
Which by the way is definitely not
Appoint
There's some other kind of category in for a long time
They were thought of as plants
But now we know after having looked at their DNA
The funds are actually
Very closely related to animals
They're one of our closest relatives Act
Now back in the day
Olga has a history of
When people first begin thinking about these things we're talking in the 1600s they had no idea what they were
What they did but ultimately they figured out that these things
We're very ancient
Because
If you look at
400 million year old fossils
Some of the very first plants
You can see
Even in the roots
Earliest land plants see those threads
This is a really ancient Association
I'm in later scientists finally look at these things under much more powerful Michael
I realize the threads weren't threads
They were actually
Tubes
How is little tubes
Two tubes
And the tubes branch and sometimes they reconnect
So there seemed to be under the ground
This fungal freeway system connecting one tree
The next to the next to the next
People speculated about this would know what it actually proved it in nature in the woods
Until
And there was a lot of skepticism at the time
Over the next
Two decades we did
Experiment after experiment after experiment
That verified that story
Suicide
What is this
Why is this network even there like why would the trees need a freeway system underneath the ground to connect
Why would the
Why would the funds I want to make this
Why are they going to this trouble
Creating this big Network
Yeah well
They do it
Because
Tree has something the fungus need
The fungus
I something
Trinis
Let me just back up for a second so that you
You came to set the scene for you
When you go into a forest you see a tree or a tall tree so what is the tree do what
This job sucks in sunshine takes the CO2 out of the air carbon dioxide which has carbon C
He in it
And it keeps the sea carbon which is
Science beaker
For food that turns into sugar
What uses to make
Its trunk
And its branches
The QC on a tree is just basically
Are made into stuff
Carbon and sugar the same thing
You can think of carbon is basically the sugar that builds the tree
However
If that's all they had was carbon
Isn't it only be this tall
That's Roy again he's holding his hand
Maybe a foot off the ground would be a teeny tree it would be smaller
So if you could do is get carbon from the air
You never treat this
Size of a tulip
A floppy tulip
A tree needs
Something else
And what a tree needs
I'm minerals minerals from the soil very similar to the sorts of vitamins and minerals that humans need
Does a tree need nitrogen and phosphorus magnesium potassium and calcium in
Why what did he do for the tree
Like a tree stand up straight without minerals
Twerking
Is important for making a tree stand up straight
And lignin is
Full of nitrogen but also
Well, like nitrogen is important in DNA right it's an integral part of DNA
I want to be a healthy tree and reach for the sky then I need
I need rocks in May
Somehow liquid rock to you need the nutrients that are in the soil
And that's
Where the fungus comes in
The fungus
Has this incredible network of tubes that's able to send out through the soil
End
Drop water
And mineral nutrients
That the tree needs where I thought I thought tree roots just sort of did like I thought I always imagined tree roots what kind of like straws
Pause like the tree was like already doing that stuff
By itself but it's the fungus it's
Yes in a lot of cases it is the
Just because
Tree roots in a lot of plant roots are not actually very good at
Doing what you think they're do she says the tree can only suck up what it needs through these
Almost to the Teeny tips of its roots
That's not enough bandwidth
Which okay to the fungus is giving the tree the mineral
What is the tree giving back to the fungus
Remember I told you how trees make sugar
So that's
Switch the tree gift
The founder of sugar
The funds I need sugar to build their bodies
The same way that we use our food
To build our bodies they can't photosynthesize
They can't take up CO2
And so they have the
The trading system with trees
She says what will happen under the ground is that the fungal tubes was
Stretch up toward the tree roots
I meant they'll tell the tree with their chemical language I'm in the neighborhood
Can you
Will you
Soften your route so that I can invade your roots
And the tree gets the message
And it sends a message back and says
Yeah I can do that
Like I can start softening up my
The walls and make room for you
Animals little tubes will wrap themselves
In the place
The little bits
White dress you can see the white stuff is the fungus
And we saw this in the Bronx that the little threads just
Wrapping themselves around the tree roots
The last kind of part of the route
Entangled stirring the edge
And it's getting that little space between them that they make the exchange
What is century
That would be
Sugar sugar
Benadryl sugar
Mineral sugar
I forgot to ask you something
82 if the tube system is giving the trees the minerals how is it getting it
The minerals
How's it getting ready to pull in from the soil
Well that's a mirror
That's why
That is
I got a doing the story this is the part
Knocked me
We'll be right back
Hello this is Ricardo from beautiful Monroe New York Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred
P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of
Scientific knowledge in the modern world
More information about Sloan @www
Scott Sloan
. org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents
Aunts and uncles teachers were looking for stories about what we're calling
Tiny moments of brilliance
Basically I want to hear about those times when I did something
It just means you bring back and say whoa
Maybe it was the moment that I
I kid you've been reading to 4 month started reading back
Do you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lesson
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of their musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed are ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the
Epic moments where
Kid does something super smart but doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story
T-shirt with us
Go to radiolab.org
Flash brilliance
And record a short audio message
And that's radiolab.org
Brilliance
Thank you so much
Run this is Radiolab and what was it what was the answer
Question about how did how did the fungus get the minerals
It is a three-pronged answer
What a fungus does is it
It hunts
Get mines it fishes
And it strangles what I'm not making this up in 1997 a couple of scientists wrote a paper
Which describes how fungi have developed a system
Remaining Jennifer says that what the tubes do
Is the
Worm their way back and forth through this
Well until
They bump into some Pebbles be little soil particles
Packets of minerals and then say
Acid amino acids come out and start to dissolve the Rocks like you're Drilling and the fungus actually build a tunnel
Inside the rock can reach these little
Packets of minerals
And
Minam
What if you look at these particles
Under the microscope you can see the little tunnels that curve sometimes they Branch they look just like mining tunnels
This is very like if you had little helmet with a light on it like I'm a human maybe not with a helmet but yeah
Snow White and the Seven tubes or something and that's just the beginning Jennifer.
About another role that these funcheap
Nethunter
Hunter what do you mean like the
The plant is hunting for water
Is hunting how do you make how do you mean
So there's a little insects that live in the soil just adorable little creatures called springtails
Flea size and they spend lots of time munching leaves on the forest floor called springtails cuz a lot of them have a little Oregon
The back that they actually can kind of
Deploy instantly spring way up high in the air David Attenborough
Want to look on YouTube
Gypsy takes in nail
Hooksett
Episode Springtime and you don't see it
Then of course because the BBC they take a picture of it it's doing like a triple double axle back flip or something into the sky
Equivalent of a human being
Jumping over the eye
Eiffel Tower
Annie
One of the things they eat
Fungus
But then
Scientist did an experiment where they gave some springtails some fungus
Put them all together in a dish
And they walked away
And then they came back
And they found that
Mosto springtails are dead
Instead of eating the fungus
It turns out the fungus
Eat them
In the little Springhill bodies that were little
Tubes growing inside them
And this is what makes it even more gruesome they
Somehow have a Dye don't ask me how they know this
How to figure it out but they have a little stain that they can put on the springtails to tell if they're alive or dead
When they did this
They saw that a lot of the springtails
That had their tubes inside them
We're still alive
Rule
The fungus would literally sucking the nitrogen out of the Springdale
Taylor was too late to get away nope
Anymore
And then they did experiments with the same fungus that I'm telling you about that was capturing the springtails
And they hooked it up to a
Tree to try to calculate how much Spring Hill nitrogen is traveling back to the treatwell
25% of it ended up in the trees
So they figured out who paid for the murder
Is there anyone whose job it is
How to draw a little chalk outlines around the
Springfield
Inspector tail is his name
Is the only spring-trap with a trench coat and other
Fedora
I have even I can go better than even that
Javier's
They have found
Entryway
Like as in the fish
In the tree in the tree well
In a way how in the hell is apparently Bears Park themselves in places
And grab fish out of the water and then you know to take a bite and throw the carcass down on the ground
The fungi
It's rained and snowed in the carcass
Seeps down into the soil a bit the fungi then go and they drink the salmon carcass down and it send it off
To the tree
That's insane salmon rings in trees
Saying there are forests
That we are trees that decided to found
Rough to 75% of the nitrogen in the tree
Turns out to be
Food from just
Bears throwing fish on the ground you if you would take away the fish
The trees would be like
Blitz Harbour
And in it and is it as dramatic in the opposite direction like the fungus to be given the
Trees a lot of minerals
I like the trees are so I can how much of their sugar
Are they giving you the fungus will I ask who's Annabelle
Like 2% or 2.00%
No I'm well people have been measuring this in different for us and ecosystems around the world and
The estimate is anywhere from 20 to 80
Percent will go into the Cabrillo Brown
20 to 80%
I'll go into the fallopian tubes into the into the roots and then into the
Microbial Community which includes the mushroom team
The point here is that the
The scale of this is
So
That we didn't know this until very recently
You have a forest
You have mushrooms now it turns out that their Network and together they're capable of doing that
A behaviors for Restoril Behavior
Did a deep cleaning
We just learning about them.
Under sew in
Let's say it's times are good the tree has a lot of sugar I don't really need it all right now
I'll put it down in my fun July
And then when times are hard
The funds I will give you my sugar back
And I can start growing again
Give me the fun Joe give me my sugar back
It is like a bag
She says we now know the trees give each other load
Oh yeah back and forth seasonally
They can also send warning signals
Through the fungus we've done experiments and other people in different
Labs around the world
They've been able to figure out the different trees injured
People cry out to the kind of chemical weigh
And those
Chemicals will then move through the network in Warren
Neighboring
Trees are seedlings that something bad is happening and I'm under a tack
There's an enemy in the midst
So if a beetle where to invade the forest
The trees tell the next tree over
Here come the Paul Revere
Sort of yes that seems to be what would happen
Chicken you can see this is like a game of telephone one tree hill
Start producing chemicals that taste really bad
So the Beatles don't want him
I don't want that
What are the spookiest examples of
Suzanne mention
Is an experiment that she and her team did where they discovered
But if a ferret is warming up
What is happening all over the world
Temperatures are rising
You have trees in this Forest that are hurting I don't do well in warm temperatures and their needles turn off 6
Yellow they will send out a good signal
But also
Important thing we figured out is that as those trees are injured and dying
Dumpster carbon into their neighbors so so carbon will move from that dying tree so it's real
Resources at Legacy will move
Into the microphone Network into neighboring trees
Oh so it says to the new or the healthier trees
Here's my food
Take it it's yours
Or it could be like okay
I'm not doing too well so I'm going to hide this down here in my mycelium a bank or if you're a
So it's not necessarily saying give it to the new guy
We don't know it again it's a tree
I'm just trying to explain make sure I understand I realize that none of these conversations you actually
Spoken give it to the new guy give it to the news
Yes
Suzanne said she's not sure if the tree is running the show and say like
I'll give it to the new guy
It's the fungus under the ground is kind of like a broker and decides who gets
You know I don't completely understand
She has one of the weirdest
Parts of this dog
Is wincek trees give up their food The food doesn't usually go to there
Kids
Or even the trees are the same
Species what the team Fair
Is the food ends up very often with
Trees that are new in the forest and better at surviving global warming
It's as if the individual trees
Somehow
Thinking
Ahead
To the needs of the whole forests
So we know that Douglas fir will take a dying to go through will send carbon to neighboring
Ponderosa pine
Answer why is that so and I think that you know the whole
Forest then
There's an intelligence there that's beyond just
Wait a second wait a second you just used
A very
Twisting words
Robert
You know what it's
All right
Unfortunately right at that point Suzanne
Basically ran off to another meeting
But
Lou's Gun speaking
We could catch up with her a few weeks later
When we last left off I'm just saying you just said in
Intelligent
Elison
Doesn't
Don't professors begin to start falling out of chairs
When Network gets used regarding
Plants
Yes
We don't normally ascribe intelligence to plant
I'm in plants are not thought to have
Brains
But when we look at the below ground
Structure it looks
So much like a brain
Physically
And now that we're starting to understand how it works
Speaking bothers so many
I do find it magic
I think there is something like a nervous system in the forest
Because
It's the same sort of
Large Network
Of nodes
Sending signals to one another
It's almost as if
The force is acting
As an organism
Itself
You know they talk about how
Honey bee colonies
AR
Sort of superorganism
Because
Each individual be a sort of acting like it's a cell in a larger body
Once you understand that the trees are all connected to each other all signaling each other
Sending food and resources to each other
Filled flavor of something very similar
Special thanks to dr. Teresa Ryan of the University of British Columbia
2ar engine Stephanie Pomeroy howling at the New York Botanical Garden
Stevenson Swanson there into Eddie McEwen and benna ferrell both produces
Okay it's time for time for us to go and yeah
Lie down on the soft fart
Floor
Admit hopefully not be liquefied by the fungus and beneatha
Baby brother
Emma Berkowitz
Start of message researchers specializing in New York
Botanical Garden this is Jennifer Fraser and I'm a freelance science writer at Scientific American
Radiolab is produced by dad
Urban Rock designs
Senior producer includes Simon Adler Brenna Pharrell
David Berkowitz Annie McEwen and emails
Richard masur
Alyssa Webster
Suckers are either doctor
And remember
If your springtails
Don't talk to strange mushrooms
Actually that's good advice for anyone
Thank you
And this message