Listening to Radiolab from WNYC
End NPR
Religious Radiolab and our show today is about being witness to something especially not something you really
Choose to witness and you feel like it should I be saying this is a story that for me speaks to like what it's like to live
The city when you look out the window we're somewhere Elso Jam together that suddenly you're seeing into the live to somebody else
Through their window and the
You just kind of fall into it without even want to in this particular tale it what is observed is so sad
Surprising and so forth tenderness and forth quiet love that we it's a rare thing to see so we wanted to send it
Your way from our friends over radiotopia Nick Van Der kolk and Brendan Baker to here we go this is how their Story begins
Started Living in
In my apartment about 15 years and one evening
I walked in the living room which has three bay windows which Facebook Gardens in the back
And over half a block of Gardens and across a small Street there was this bright window
That I've never noticed before it but it's at the exact eye level of my third floor
Apartment and after a while I realized that I never seen it because there had always been curtains
And so I think dimly-lit the curtains were often closed and all of a sudden there's this bright light and milk
Curtains and it was like a movie screen
15 years and that window is meant nothing I haven't even know
Noticed it and now it's all I think about
There were new tenants and it had always been a live
Living room and now it was suddenly a bedroom and there are these two people in there and they
We're naked this young couple in their twenties they were really lovey-dovey and they were
Always naked csdn wiper who tells the story and she told it to
Radio voter Brianna Breen who produces peace with Megan Brennan the thing is they pushed their
Bed so that the head was up against the windows so their heads you could see the both of their heads
Lying there so you'd see things that you just like there were just shocking I just had been there all of this time and
And suddenly you could see people having sex really clearly like this like amazing we clearly I-84
I had no idea that you could see so well across such a distance and it was
Was really uncomfortable my husband and I were still adjusting to Parenthood
And it wasn't the most romantic time in our in our lives and my son was probably 3
And when your new parents to a toddler especially because he sleeps in bed with us
That's too so he's like literally right between us the last thing you need is a couple of hotties getting it on
Across the window reminding your husband of everything
I have this really beautiful young woman that was really thin and and and naked
Really you know it was very frustrating and end in if she had this beautiful
Tall lanky well-built boyfriends
Anti first I die just because I felt like my husband was going to be staring at the naked woman all the
What time I started closing the living room curtains which is really kind of silly and it made our room really dark and we know
Never close those curtains and so that didn't work
So I thought about like making a really big sign that says like close your curtains
Buy curtains they didn't even have curtains by curtains we can see you and I thought about going by their building
I have no idea what their unit was and leaving a note and then I started
That was really silly and prudish and started realizing that they were just young
And I had to just get over it and live with it and move on and so
So that's what I did
We got really used to them and then they became sort of the symbol of what we used to be
In our twenties and they were living the really care free time and that's another thing that was kind of hard
Hard not to sometimes when you're in early Parenthood you get a little bitter I think that some of those freedom
Then we'd watch them sleeping till 11 while we've been up since 5 with our toddler in and we saw them
Eating breakfast on the roof together so we got used to it only we know we would notice like a new
Can I plant in there and they became sort of part of our Lives you know because they were just always there and never
Ever bought curtains do you think all the Neighbors in your building and the surrounding building
Also saw this it's funny I think that the way that we are positions
Because all of the buildings around us are different sizes and our building is the tallest one on
Tarblock but it's exactly at the right level to see their their windows
I have a friend next door and then a friend across the way and and all of them have Windows facing the gardens but not
All of them are blocked and I look at the other windows of the buildings around us and I don't think anyone has
This perfect level view the irony is that I'm such a private person
And I don't know if my supposed to have maybe respected their privacy and just looked away but it's
It's impossible because that's the way the chairs face to face the window I couldn't I couldn't not see
If I wanted to but I guess I could have not gotten the binoculars
Set a timer
By and this is maybe a year-and-a-half later two years later and I remember seeing the room
And the light was on but it was empty and I thought that was strange because it was 5 in the morning and
They never went anywhere early and it was like that for like a whole week was just as empty room with a lighter
And I thought that was strange they they didn't seem to be there as often
Or maybe just she would be there and he was gone for long periods of time and we just kind of forgot about them you know
There were they weather wasn't as much action going on and they were in his presents and so we just kind of
Lived our lives and forgot about them for maybe 7 or 8 months
The end of last year in December
There was this night when my husband and I separately had both seen this woman naked sitting
The window kind of chubby slump shouldered woman who was just looking down at
The street and we both thought it was so strange just couldn't figure out who she
He was and what she was doing and why she was naked and a few nights later there was
Was this young man standing right at the window by the bed and he was
Skeletal he was so thin and he was bald completely
And we realized it was the same couple they had completely changed
You sick there's something serious
Wrong with him
After that I just watched the window all the time
We're going to pause it right here
Here let's just be right back
This is Charlie from Brooklyn Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world more information about Sloan at
Www.slha.org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here I'm a producer at Radiolab and I'm here because I need your help
This summer and I have request for those of you who spend a lot of time
Parents and uncles teachers were looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments
Brilliance basically I want to hear about those times when a kid you know did something that just means
How did they do that maybe it was the moment that I kids you've been reading
Started reading back to you or maybe the kid was a piano lessons and you suddenly noticed they were due
Advanced math class
Origin of the geometry homework kid does something
Super smart but it doesn't have anything to do with the test if you have a story please share it with us and go to Radio
Stop. Org / Brilliance and record a short audio message for us again that's radiolab.org
Splash Brilliance thank you so much
I am Jedi Broad River coach this is Radiolab let's get back to our story from Brianna Breen and the folks eleven radio
Nick Van Der kolk and Brendan Baker so we're just going to go back to the room C
See what's what we can see through the window you're staying wiper I just watched the window
All the time and
He would sit all day he was there because I work from home and I would see him
I'm all day in the bedroom either lying down or sitting at the computer and then after
A couple of weeks he was just lying down and he was just there and his bald head would be
Up against the the pane of glass all the time and she would be there
There and she come in and she would bring him things but mostly it was just him there by himself and
Sometimes he would have liked his knees bent and you could just see how skeletal they were they were just bone
And sometimes you kick off the blankets and he was just lying there naked in it
Emaciated
And then after awhile he should always burrowed under the blankets like I found myself
Thinking like what maybe she's been through chemo and he's recovering and you guys going through this
The six phase before he gets well because you so young he didn't you know he's just such a young guy
And
So we had to go to Colorado to see my family for Christmas and worry
Read all the time I was there I would have thought about them and I worried that he wasn't going to be there when we got back
Back I worried all the time about it when we got back about 10 days later
He was still there but his head looked so much smaller and
And there were a lot of people there and and then I got out
My binoculars
I got my birding binoculars I'm not proud of it but at that point
I felt so invested
They look like people coming to say goodbye
And there was this sort of short blond Midwestern look
Looking woman who I guess was his mother and then there was this young guy who just kept pace
Chasing the Halls you know you could just see their two doorways leading out of this room and you could just see him go down one side and 3
Other than back and forth and back and forth and I figured he was the brother and
It look like the girlfriend's sister was also there was just I was just a guess looked like her
I remember there was just this little gathering going on in the living room
Right below the neighbors were standing around and having drinks and they have no idea at all
What was going on right upstairs I would watch people come and go then after a while
Everyone left except for the girlfriend and the mother and and I spent
And I spent all that evening like sitting vigil in
On the back of the couch and and watch it and and
I remember the girlfriend lying beside him for a long time on our own and she was just stroking its face
So tenderly it was so much affection that really transcend
The kind of young love that you expect all I could see was the top of his head all that time
And I remember later seeing her standing by the
The bed when the mother on the other side and they were just all talking and she put a hand on his forehead to the back
Back of her hand on his forehead and then she was wiping at her eyes and you could tell that there was
This that there was the sense that something that it was getting closer
Then I could see this Reckoning or she she was wiping her
Her eyes and touching his forehead and wiping at her eyes and
There were candles lit and in this
Young woman was on one side and his mother was on the other side
And they just were lying there for a really long time and I had
Their hands just resting on his chest and so I watched it
Prolong time
The mother in the girlfriend relying on either side of him and you could tell it was his this was the end
I thought now all that's left is the girlfriend in the mother and inexplicably
Me me
Three people at the Deathbed
And I lay there for a long time and then they just got up and they hate went into the other room
And I realized that must have been the moment
Aunt
All this time you know what I always have the sense that you know that they're going to break up
They're going to move out nobody that age stays together very long and
I had no idea it was just like this beautiful love story
So the next day the next day I got up and went
The window first thing and they were folding up blankets and stay
Stacking them on the bed and I figured that he had been taken away and so
I was in the kitchen and my husband called because he had maybe knew how obsessed I'd gotten with the sea
Situation and he said there's activity over there and I came running and I got my binoculars and I
I looked him and realize that he was still there he was still in the bed his body was still there
And it was the coroner so the coroner and his assistant came and they had these white plastic glue
Gloves on and they pulled his body to the edge
Shut the bed and onto this white sheet and I just remember the lifelessness of it it look
So shrunken it almost looks like a shrunken rubber proxy
Everybody
So incredibly dead they wrapped him in a sheet and they zipped mm
Into a vinyl bag and they put him on this kind of Gurney they took the gurney out
I just had this very strange impulse and I ran and threw on my coat
Kind of over my pajamas and ran out to the street ran to the corner
And I got there just as they were calling him out they were carrying him out
And the girlfriend was there she was talking to one of them in the doorway
And they loaded him into this van and I realized that
They know me at all like I had you know I have no place to be there and
They looked at me I remember the coroner's assistant looking at me like I was sort of a like a rubbernecker
Girl in the street you know looking at this grisly scene and I realized that's that's what I was
I had no place to be there and suddenly it all felt so perverse and so I went home
Home and I felt very strange about the whole thing
And I tried to tell myself that I never wanted to be part of their lives I want it I was the one that wanted them to
How to put up curtains I wanted them to just shut the intimate stuff out I was uncomfortable with it I was the one
It wanted out
Can I started remembering all of a sudden when I moved to that apartment so many years ago
And I was in my mid-twenties that had to share the apartment with a roommate cuz it was too
Expensive my bedroom was in the living room and I remember how when I first moved in
And I pushed the head of my bed up against the three bay windows so so that in the morning I could see
See the sky and
I remember that I had no clue it never occurred to me that anyone could see me that
I remember that I felt like whenever I looked out the window I never saw anyone and
I never close my curtains either
Did you ever find out either of their names I I never
Have found out their names and I looked through the local obituaries obsessively
4 weeks and there was never anyone that fit his description there was never anyone young enough for
That looks like him so no idea I walked by their place ever
What times and there's only their only numbers on the mailboxes in the buzzards and there's
There are no names so I can't look up anything I don't know I've no idea who she is
I have no idea who he was
No idea what he was sick with
I don't know
If I've gotten anything right maybe they were married but I didn't get the fact that he died
Because
I was there I was there for that
Because I saw it all
I think about that a lot how he chose
But he chose to die in that in that bed in that bedroom
And he didn't choose to Goodwill hospice or
Anywhere he wanted to be in his bedroom
All of those long days from the morning when I looked out in the evening he was just exactly the same position
That was where he wanted to be
And I
It's where all of the happy times where I guess in the end times you know
Just a couple days after it happened she was up on the roof with a friend doing
Doing yoga and I watched her lying around a lot she
When out-of-town I think for a bit and she still there
I have been watching her recovery and instead of being this
Young woman
She looks totally different she looks so changed she just
Looks like this very experienced world-weary person
She has a job now that gets hurt very early cuz I get up at 6 and she's already dressed
Kids out at like 6:15 and the other night I saw her
And she was in her bedroom and she was wearing this bag
A T-shirt and all the lights were on and and she was dancing
Just dancing around her room so yeah
On her I want her to move on this this young woman that I was so
Cranky and bitter about you know now she's now she's that way.
Protective and kind of maternal you know
If you ran into her at the corner market or something do you think you could ever say anything to
Yeah if I ran into her I wouldn't say it
What would I say I've been watching you through your window how creepy would that be
Yeah no way
She doesn't know she doesn't know that
She doesn't know that there's this person that
I don't know if it's a complete stranger
But that they're really rooting for her and I
Diane Webber told her story to radio reporter Brianna Breen
Who produced this with the folks eleven radio Nick Van Der kolk and Brenda Baker
Special thanks to Karen Duffin to Brendan Brianna antonik and there are some wonderful stories on their podcast
You should listen to all of them is called love and radio you'll find it at love and radio. Org on chat album run time
Thanks for listening