Listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
Nice.
You might want to hear me
21 of your own
Ono poke
You know what it is it's like
It's like
80 Hertz
Was that an idiot is this meteor difference as 80 grit sweater what cuz when you move Ed her it's better just think about that
Off Mike I lose like 9250 hurts
Robert krulwich
You do when you
When you
When you get off
Talking to the dump
When you get off Minecraft
You robbed me
You take away
My appreciation of your 80 hurts and it hurts
It hurts me it literally hurts me
Hertz me Savannah's Bakery
TSS
Old is Sublime whatever you call word that sounds like another word that isn't the same word that sounds the same when you say it
Pamela
Hummina hummina hummina
Yeah if I'm an umbrella homonym covers
I think it's a different word
Homophone
Strawberry ready for this
What are you about to get me ready. So this
Just to put a
Iframe adjust off top my head frame
So
Last year
We decided
To do a thing where I
We went to the inbox
What's the Radiolab inbox
4 years
People had been sending us
Questions they want dance
Stupid questions if we are calling them collect
Wait we say that love
Sometimes they would say
Question I don't know it may seem too simple.
Why
Do and then some
Sure thing, is the sky blue
I think so do a lot of these kind of question to accumulate in the inbox
Last year we took a bunch of those Quest
And we try to answer them
And it was very fun everyone got to do one and one pic
Question and ran after it
And there were some questions left over there was also
Questions that we ourselves
They were here.
It's like filed away in
And so
We decided we were going to do this
Except this time
Broadneck constraints so there's not just
Questions that are sent to us but we questions we ourselves had questions that were given to us by
Friends of the show
Came into our heads and never gone away
Here's the deal
If you were wondering for your life reading a book talking to a friend browsing a magazine
And some question came up
But you thought
I don't know and it never left your head take that question the one you
Still think about never answered
An answer it
Exactly
Yes right we have four questions in this episode and then I'll be another episode with a few more questions in a couple of days
Starting us off and we have the levels all right
Yeah
You sound pretty sure Simon Adler
Okay I'm looking at my checkbook while we're doing this
What what's going on in the checkbook at the moment
August
Checking
And close relative
You sound great
Very good
Soap for my question a little while back I give my dad
Jim Adler and Simon's father
And your first time being on the show
That's correct
Been on before with
Ponderable questions I wanted to bring back on because
Since his last
It's an honored
I'll be back a little over a year ago
You could kind of say he's become a new man
All thanks
To a phone call
Okay
It was June 25
Okay and it was a gorgeous day
Sunny day
Good temperatures
And
I had decided about 1
In the afternoon
To take a walk
And as he was strolling along cross the River from our house
I felt my phone
Vibrate in my pocket
And
I looked at it and saw that he had a voice
And it said
Hi this message is for Kim
Are Timothy on this is Carrie calling from UW hospital in the transplant Department
Summer calling because we have an organ offer to discuss with you it said something to the effect of
We have a long
Available a couple of numbers that you can call reserved for you
Call back
Now that the transplant coordinator
On-call pay something like that
Wow
This this is hard to believe thank you
If I can back up here
Go back 25 years back my dad was diagnosed with sarcoidosis
It's a relatively rare disease with no cure
Better Century triggers the immune system
To attack the body
Typically it it targets and wreaks havoc on the lungs
Usually sarcoidosis goes away on its own after a few years
Hoping would happen if I dad
But in his case the disease became chronic
It's a beer after your breathing became harder and harder
Can't stop running a marathon runner at the time and suddenly just walking a mile became difficult
10 years back he
Started using oxygen at album get around and then five years ago things finally got so bad
That he was
Place on waitlist for a lunch
Inside that call was the transplant team
Calling him to say that
After five years of waiting they had
Awarded this long to me
If I was still on board
Assembly was almost like you're a sweepstakes winner
What did you feel like a sweepstakes winner or you would like
Well
Ice I had to ask
That
I always said that if one was made available I would take
And it's going to make a great story
When it's all said and
I unlock back I called and I said we're in
And Damn the Torpedoes Full Speed Ahead
And from there this years-long glacial Pace process
Started moving
Very fast
It was pretty much honey pack your bag
My folks hop in the car drove the three and a half hours south of the hospital in Madison Wisconsin
About 5:30
You know within 45 minutes I was basically immobilized
Because I had things coming out of every orifice
And then just a couple hours after that very early that next morning the surgeon came in and said
It's time
They just told me to relax
What's the next thing you remember
Well
I woke up
And my arms were strapped to the gurney
And I had a breathing tube down my throat
And
Yeah you just got hit by a bus
Operation
That was the beginning
Now sitting in my dad's hospital room
Is he was coming to
I really realized for the
The first time
Then
That this was
Like this wasn't over
The phrase
Is
You're just a
Exchanging one major set of problems
For another's
Majors that a problem
The biggest being the threat of rejection
In fact about 50% of folks
To get a lung transplant
Only live about 5 years
And you can always be on the wrong side of that
I'm sure that that had sort of been
Explain to us
But I am
I didn't really
Imagine what that meant
Until
We saw him lying there
Sister said they weren't they were all these sort of terrifying question
Surrounding
All of us
In
My
I think we wanted to find a way to talk about all the
Terrifying
Oceans without
Having to ask
Disgusting
And so
The way we
Decided to talk about this was
We inserted this
Intellectual or legal
The question was
Who had
Ownership of
This long
Throughout the
This entire process
Because like I don't know if they're transporting a
Suitcase full of
Hundred dollar bills like somebody has to be responsible for that suitcase every step of the
Oregon is essentially
Valued at
Much is a suit
K400
Dollar bills
So who the heck was responsible for and who owned it who is liable for a teacher
Wager
When
Did I
They have complete
Ownership
I was alone
That was that was the Ulta
Wait so you and your
Are you just you and your
Your mom and
Brother talking about the sources like are you talked about this with your dad
Started between Barbara and
Barber you're my partner from there that the circle of conversation group
As
Search as the week went on
And eventually my dad was roped into it in my dad
Lawyers that he had some thoughts on all this
Yeah it's awake but isn't it kind of a simple matter I mean I would imagine that when the longest in the donor
But you know anything about the donor
We we don't know it's all
Kept quite confidential
Essentially there's a process through which my dad is
Send a thank you note
Start of into a black box that is the
Nonprofit
Organ donation
Machinery
And that will be delivered to them and then if they would like to reach back out to him they can do
But up until this
Okay so getting back to it so
I would think that when the longest in the donor's body
It is in that person's possession then it taken out and then if that's
Intermediate stages in the hospital
Possession is a trend
And then when it goes into your Dad's Body he then immediately assumes owners
Simple as that
What you think so
Right okay
Nothing that really looks simple ever is very simple at least when lawyers get involved
This is Fred now I'm afraid Kate I'm a professor of law at Indiana University Maurer School of Law keep the guy
I ultimately called to try to tease out an answer here
Because he's written a lot on the laws surrounding
He said the first thing you got it
First of all property is a really special thing in the law
Code of laws
Hammurabi in by Daddy means many of the oldest written laws we have as humans
We're about
Acting property historically protecting property was in a very much at the heart of it
Set up to settle disputes over ownership
An enemy take away from him
Assess damages the broker shall be free of obligation
And overtime the number of things the law protects has only grown you know intangible things like
Intellectual property you know I can own a copy right now and so we have a respect for property that's
Reflected in the law
That is really quite distinctive
Okay but having said all of that we don't really allow property rights in most body parts
And moreover the law doesn't let us call the human body
Property
Obviously in this country there was a time when it did
But then you have the 13th Amendment which ended slavery and since then have a squeamishness it could
To be a reaction to the
Prohibition on slavery that we don't want to ever give the notion that one person can own a another person's body
Austin princess
US law has gone very silent
On questions of ownership and by
And so as a consequence
When someone donates you in Oregon
Legally you have no ownership claim over
Back working we're just not willing to
SEPTA call it proper
Okay
I think I get that strange then however
Is that
Apparently
That same provision applies to your own by
Yeah you don't have property interested in your body and so although you can donate them and you can leave them
When your will we don't really treat them like
Property
Wait so you're born with along in your body
You don't own that thing that's been with you since birth
Correct it is yours but you don't own it
What are we quibbling over the word property here or ownership cuz rental lawyers do we
We we don't come equivalent this is what we
Making money doing is arguing over property
If
It's not property what what is it what's the what's the term at that point
I don't think we really have a term for that
Now
Near me
When I relayed this to my dad don't own your own
Oregon
Yeah
She was as
Confused design
At the risk of a pond made
Certainly carved out
Interesting
Concept
And it turns out the consequences of this legal carve-out are
Spectacularly spray
Let's say you drew a little bit of blood out of your arm one evening
I don't know why and you
You put it in a vial in your refrigerator and that night
A burglar breaks into your
Your home your apartment goes into the refrigerator
And steals app
That that
Thief would not be charged
With that
For for stealing that but there might be criminal claims like breaking and entering
But I just don't think it's going to be a property claim there because they didn't actually
Steel
Something that was your possession
Equally strange
This is come up a couple times where
His wife John Elway husband in this case a guy by the name of Richard Batista
Donated kidney to his
My priority was to save her life operation
Well
To save
True love
But then says his wife began having an affair about 2 years after the trans
The marriage falls apart
Enter divorce proceedings uibe so stunning demand husband Bautista
Bat once the kidney
Shut up
True story and of course
Was thrown out by the judge
In part because of
But also because
In the judge never said this but he could have it like sorry bub you never owned your your kidney to begin with
Let alone after you donated it
To your wife
So I don't think you would ever find a situation where that would be treated as marital property
But ironically and this is just going to make it even more complicated
Blood skin and corny is tend to be an exception in the way we think about this in the law meaning
That you can sell your blood or or your skin the law allows that don't ask why that's just the way it is
Even still in these cases
This cannot call it
Property
I don't
Own it but I could sell it exactly
What did they eat when they took that blood
I would assume that they don't own it either well the purchaser
The folks who do buy it from you the blood bank the hospital that is that have collected it
They own
Here's the kicker
So if you then broke into the blood bank
Steal back your own blood
You could be charged with
Right we have cases on this
Okay that's definite
Marriott
All right
Well
What I think is interesting here is
Like I think we we first
Started wondering this Quest
As a as a tangible way
Think about this
Barb
More abstract
Impossible to answer question which was like
When would we feel like
This long was really yours like when would we
Feel like we didn't have to be worrying
Right
I don't know I guess that I'm not
I'm not fully there yet
Oh
Are you
Well
Three months ago I received it
Call from
Nearest it's been handling
All of our
Transplant
Fairs
And and
She just almost there
As an aside sets
I think you're going to
Stick around a long time with the
It's long because it's going so well
And I I didn't know what
She was talking to
It first and then she went on to explain that
Autism mortality rate after 5 years yeah
50%
The nun
It's me
But I don't
I think you have to worry about that
I think you're going to be one of our 30 year candidate
Well I never I never seen
Consider a 30-year planning anything I've always lived on it
Five year plan
Because
When I was
Given that
Decline of
Pulmonary function
I said
To myself I am going to be lucky
I'm going to be the luckiest man in the world if I could
In order to get 260 I had to get 250 and then 255
And then at age 60 when I got listed or thereabouts
You know then
On A Five-Year Plan where no longer came along
So they've always lived
In these five your gaps
And have been happy to reach
Those
So anyway it was I was dumbfounded and it was pretty
Awe-inspiring
Here's always turn
Right then and there I said that
This is it this is what this is all about
It's working
This long
And
It's mine
I'm really happy
And for us I am happy for us
Aqi
Pretty please myself
Good
Producer Simon Adler
Is that
I'm listening to that I sent to Simon
Don't want
What does
This story
Doesn't have
Cowboy
Merchant of Venice
I think
Is it really
My birthday
Guys might live bunny estamos Shylock as money today
Antonio
Pound of Flesh
Sure
And then he doesn't pay back
Social activist
The court and says
I want
Pound
Flesh pound
Pound a pound
I wanted to run away but I will kill this guy
Lisa that's the deal he signed
Iona pound of Flesh from this man
I mean Tire play then turns
On a court case
No way
What will happen
He wins
He gets his pound of Flesh
Well it's a
Trick ending
He wins
And then the judge says of course
You can have the pound of Flesh
The contract did not include any blood
So
No blood
See if you can get the pound of flesh but if any blood of Antonio comes
Your way you have
Violated the criminal laws event
You can have a pound of bloodless flesh there is no sex
Think so he's
Hot
Some twisted
I just hit this
Looks like you've been productive this is
Has been fought about face
Really smart people before this
What is what's going to number the second big little question this one
So to you by our producer Becca breast
Hello
Did I tell you anything about what I want
I am talking to you about my question comes from the sky Jason Pfeiffer
Okay I'm recording now
Is that always how you test your mic
This is Jason
The hosts podcast I really like called pessimist archive
Is little too hard to explain right now but it's really great you should go check it out
Anyways I reached out to him I just sent him an email and I
And you know I'm a fan of your podcast you seem like a really interesting guy I imagine you have some
Fairly interesting question so
What keeps you up at night what burning questions do you have that maybe I can help you answer
All right
So you won't get a shot your question
Okay so here we go
So
Okay so here's my question
How far by myself out cuz it's such a complicated question
Are we going to start
I do have a question
Okay
So here's my question why question is
How far back in time
Could I go
And say a word that
You are like an English word a word that means whatever it means to me in English
That
No I didn't do it yet
Hard Rihanna so hard I know I can't even write this in an email so that it was communicated to you
I don't know
Okay so here's my here's my question
If I could walk
Into Bill and Ted's time machine and go back as far as possible
Step out and say a word in English
What word could I say
That the person whose hearing they would understand exactly what it means because the same
Sounded meaning
Have been retained across time
What is the oldest word that I can say in English that the
Possible person from
Totally different Ivan culture like they would think I'd say the word and they be like
Yes I understand you don't know how they would respond cuz I don't know their language but they would they would know what I'm saying
Know what I'm saying
How what is that word
Does that make sense
Yeah I think that's it I think it's great
What an odd question what is the oldest English word
It hasn't changed
Yeah and I asked Jason do you have a guess
Oh
He was like maybe something basic tree
Like something just Elemento
Grass
Dirt
Water
That's
Probably where it would go
So
I
Just started calling around hello
Sara Sara hello
1st percentile
Westerra
Thomas and professor of linguistics at the University of Michigan and she told me I can get you six thousand years back
4000 BC
Which is when you have this language known as
Proto-indo-european
Pro 200 European
FB
Ultimate ancestor of English and all its relatives are known as Indo-European languages
So proto-indo-european is like the great great great grandparent of Greek German
Dutch most languages in India all over the world
Colonization by the way
The Proto Indo Europeans
So we talking about like
Tribal Forest people from in the people in Eastern Europe near the Black
Sort of fisherman little bit of hunting
And
So how long was this against 6000 years
And I think my best guess
Forward that would have been understood way back then
Is
The word is
And why did she think that was the oldest one
So the way that you thinking about it was
Certain
Consonants like T&K or 6000 years changed a lot
But ass
Didn't change very much
Underground
But they're told me that the way you would have pronounced is
Is
St
At the end that's not to say it's not the same I know I know it's not the same so I kept calling
Around
Describe on another linguists and I work on language change and language documentation
My question and she was like okay
How about the word for me
Me
Yep
Simple it's Elemental and turned off that 6000 years ago me
I know I know
Next up was Robert Robert can you hear me Robert
Toronto
Yes I can hear you now
Sack you know completely hold things in
Stock
Call them another guy you might just introducing yourself
Chicago
Love you
Words that really have not changed that much
So the English word
6 eat an apple into what would those like
Proto-indo-european pronunciation speed
Estrellas
+ 6
Is swac
Apple is horrible
Eat is Ed
No none of that
Yeah well maybe the answer is there is no word to survive so they're just going to get as close as they can
Answer your question exactly but I can get under the
Under the cloud that covers the subject switches
Super satisfying right I mean like why what I want isn't it as a very precise
You know
Literally the exact same word
And so I thought like well maybe I can't go back to 6
Thousand years I can go back
Something and so how's it going
I got in touch with this guy Andrew rate
Professor of English at the University of Louisville
Period in England
Pretty much between 500
In 1066
Very modern now okay what's what's the word
Word must be an Old English word
So much of our language obviously comes from Old English words
Percent or so
Come to us directly from molding
It has to be holding
Thinking
What if
Not what if it were something all the way back with
Proto-indo-european
Cuz Andrew went about this a different way
Keith Wade Andrew was thinking about this
Is he was looking for an English word
Sounds
The same or really similar in a
Bunch of other Indo-European languages
Cuz if you could find that word that was shared among these languages
That it would it would mean that they were all holding on to
Something
From Proto Indo European European languages together
More words for father
Dough Latin
Has popped air
Old English has father North Bossier
German boxer
And then you also realize that mother in German
Masters polish the same way
So he went to his dictionary of proto-indo-european and he's looked up father and mother and they're not quite the same
Mother is
Something like mother and father is
Something like
But we did find is at in the dictionary right under the words mother and father
Ready to other words
Mama
And Papa
Mama and Papa Mama and Papa
Mama and Papa
So yeah if we almost almost certainly if we went back to Eastern
Millennium BCE and we said
Mama
Or Papa
They would have understood
That's just a little
Who
God are you raining on my mind
Of course
Why do I think about myself of course it would be sure it's like babies
First words
The thing that did surprise me that I thought was really cool and talking to Andrew is that the words Mama and Papa
In virtually
Every
Language
So obviously all the languages that come from Proto into your
Mama in Norwegian
Mama in Italian
Papa's
Or apus grandfather
But also the more sound patterns in Chinese
Amma and APPA like it's not just Indo-European language
The sound show up in
Swahili in Eskimo and Hebrew Arabic
The linguistic Universal
They just go right across the board
She just came up with an answer that's I get for everybody
Yeah you find me sounds in a vast majority of languages
And why is that because you said that no one's really quite sure but maybe the
The
M sound because it only involves the lips
The vocal cords
Papa's
The sound
I was just to take away easy for babies
It's been gif
Perhaps
The whip movie
Involved in Fang
Mama
Similar to lip movement
Involved in
Latching onto a woman's breast
Ultimately we don't really know
Why release the babies know what they're not telling
But you know what
The very fact
First words we learn to say as babies
The oldest word
Potential really lovely thought
Oh
Call json to tell him what I learned
That
Is that where they come from
Are we saying mama and papa because desert sounds babies can make yes the easiest sounds I can make ya exactly that's awesome
That's really awesome
You know what
What's a cool is that I
Was thinking at first about basics
Trees and stuff but this is this but actually that wasn't
Basically
The most basic thing is the
First relationship that you can understand
And the first sound that you can make about it
That's the most basic cats
Becca Bressler
What's funny is that
Most the time I feel like dad comes first
For some reason
Shouldn't
Why no man it's always a great it's always like this classic moment
The fence with moms like
What
First
We said she was like okay you're going to go to him first
Not the person who birthed you and who is feeding you
I look to you for the cheapest price like he doesn't know what he's saying
Let's go to break
Joey
Yes let's shall
Let's
But shall
This is Carrie Coon from LaGrange Illinois
Radiolab is supported in part by the hour
Keystone Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world
More information about phone at www.slha.org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
This summer
And I request
For those of you who
You spend a lot of time with kids parents
Aunts and uncles teachers were looking for stories about what we're calling
Tiny moments of brilliance
Basically I want to hear about those times when I kids you know did something
It just means you bring back and say
Maybe it was the moment that I
A kid you've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of the musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed are ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the
Epic moments where
Kid does something super smart
But it doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story
T-shirt with us
Go to radiolab.org
Flash brilliance
Record short audio message
And that's radiolab.org
Flash brilliance
Thank you so much
Hey ready 3-2-1 hey I'm Jared Polis Radiolab is what we're doing yes and we are in
The midst of big little question part three friends and family Edition and
Yeah we said at the beginning that we're going to give we're going to we're going to nod to the questions we can't get out of our heads
And it may be a little bit and
Right
And if you said that last part
The beginning
And
Did this next one satisfies both
Of those criteria it comes from producer Annie
We came and she delivered it
2 producer Matt kielty
Are you recording yourself right now
No yeah I don't know I guess
Maybe we could start by
How would you feel if I
Called you a neanderthal
I would feel
Like a
Dummy
Dum dum yeah
Feels like something you said to me
Big dumb men
And then so if I see the word Neanderthal what do you visualize
Like a bigger
Had like a big block head
A really big barrel
Chest
And what is that
What is the per
Person doing
Punching stuff
What country
Anything around I think the image that comes to mind is something Harrier
Club
Hunched over
Prudish
This is Evelyn Jugo de IMAP
Blind in Harvard
Human evolutionary biology Department
Unlike most people you know researching a topic she's got a Google alert
Set up for the word neanderthal
About half
The time it's an actual size story about neanderthals and the other half of the time
Absolutely Andrew Saul on trefoil using the word Neanderthal to me in
Finance referred to her
Eyes and I quote
A neanderthal make me angry
Evelyn says his image of Neanderthals is just
Just not quite
It needs an update
Yes I remember you saying last we spoke on the phone kind of the way that we think about Android
Did you say Saul or tall
I honestly can never decide what I say
I think so but I feel like a bit of a weiner when I say meander
I feel like such a
OK Google when do the wrong image
Stuck in a brain
Yeah so it got that her brains about
100 years ago in France with this guy named Marshall on bull use a payload paleoanthropologist
And when he was in his lab in Paris
And he was brought
This
This at the time with most complete
NFL skeleton ever found
Which is very exciting and so we took a look at the skeleton and what he sees is
Something small something
Curled over
Hunched
Decrepit
Any interpreter set insert a famous drawing based off his interpretation turns out to look like this
Hunched-over 8-man
That is where we get our ideas about one skeleton then
Became
What we now think of today
Colloquially as what Indian Palace
But
It turned out that this particular skeleton actually had regular arthritis
Skeleton
Oh but you just thought that's the way it was
Exactly yeah it's like an alien species coming and finding the
The skeleton they find that represents Humanities
85 year old woman in a wheelchair something like everybody looks like this
And it's so tell me a little bit about what do we know about neanderthals now what are the things that are
We are learning
How are they evolving in our mine
I would say that going from that brutish woolly mammoth
Primitive Neanderthal picture
Okay a lot of Sciences
Today
Have more of a sense of esl as a different flavor of you
Bring me to my question
Hey so so a few months back and I we were making this
Story about using help his leader
Speed hybrid polar bear grizzly bears
You were there
And while we were hanging out in studio
I thought that two different I was trying to explain to you just how far apart evolutionarily
These grizzly bears and polar bears are evolutionarily like hundreds of thousands of years ago
Pretty much the same time that we broke off from the Neanderthals and so be like us meeting a neanderthal
Odin the you know is the Crown Heights bar or something
Going home a person and creating
It's really specific it sounds like you had
Franklin Ave April 10th
Show me the kind of dumb joke it is very silly
The question kind of stuck around my mind at the Lutheran like wheat what would that be like as a funny image meeting NFL in a bar
Relate to each other what would we do we have anything, are we at all
Tools that you question like if you met of the installer bar what would it be like
Yeah like could we communicate
What would it sound like
Ha
This is why I originally called Evelyn chicken
Okay
Help me imagine
And we can be suspected of here so you're free to step out of here I like
Scientist hiding from your artists hat or whatever you want to do
I was even today I was even put that part and I will see I will
Okay
You want to tell me you would have said the same okay
So where are you
Okay let's just say I'm at
A
Jazz
Club
Cool the lights really dim
The music is kind of like that likes
Amy Rush on the symbols type of bags
Maybe it's raining outside or just finished raining and I'm shaking my umbrella
And I look around and I see you at service scattering of homo sapiens
Summer summer playing pool
Tell me why are we living in reality
Sometimes it's homo sapiens and sometimes your standard fellows or is this just how you be a special night
I'm looking around at all the people and interests
On this one guy
Fairly robust
He's got red hair red hair red hair brown hair and most of it was on their head
So they didn't really have much more body hair than
The implication of that is that you must have had fire
Are you playing it cool or you or you just like gawking what are you doing how close are you
I don't like Sidle up to him and and then slip into the the stool next to him
You notice
His Highness
The back is
Treating out
Got a pretty big nose
Smallest chin
Brown eyes
Katie is working on
Riding up
Medicinal plant
It's been a long day
Evelyn says that there's no evidence that neanderthals use plants
To make medicine
For more incredibly they also like
After their sick in their elderly
The good people I know you got to get home to care for his grandma
You're captivated you like this is something different but
Familiar
You don't realize it's nobody guess that's just how short he is completely by
I'm like oh my gosh
We are aware in my question
We're just looking at each other
And I just wonder what's the next step
Any talk could neanderthals talk
This is one of the great debates about whether it is Alzheimer's
We don't technically know if they could
Talk but it's really hard to tell just by looking at their DNA and their skeletal remains
But
There's the check out all this stuff
Evelyn says that they had a variety of
They're able to hunt mammoths Robin ball game art yes like
Geometric
Keep getting
And furthermore the other things that there's
Evidence of dance on Saturday
And you think like with all those things
How could they have done it without communication they just make me think they had language
Yeah
Yeah it makes me think that too
Okay so if they could talk
What would that sound like
What would this guy at the bar what would his voice
Oh goodness that some
Hesperian
This is a human
This is a human throat
This is a neanderthal
BBC documentary
Made back in 2005 where they tried to answer the
The question so I imagine that they wouldn't have Shuffle sound it would be loud very loud
Very very loud vocal coach and she is
Third of interpreting all the things that they then knew about neanderthals bigger head bigger nasal cavity
Chest and then getting dressed
Into an actor
So this voice is it create
Bring it back
Into my barsi
And imagine my Asus neanderthal
I have your number
According to BBC his response would have sounded something like this
No
Speak
Now let's make
Make a sound
Huge
Again is it that that was the voice that came up with base in the science
But you know I got like 14 years of past in a probably decides his updated
What is
What is the better answer that question today what is a more up-to-date version of this voice
Dr. Barney are you there
So I called up dr. Anna Barney
Institute of sound and vibration research in University of Southampton
Does question partly by focusing on this
Tiny little u-shaped
The tongue
And anybody who reads
Murder mysteries will know that because it's the one that
Tax when you strangle so sweet baby.
Sodus bone is a very important little bone for me
Sounds
A neanderthal skeleton
Habitue
But it hasn't really been clearly
Exactly how they used it
Did they use it in the same way we do
So doctor Bernie's team using computer modeling they sort of did a bunch of things to figure out where the hyoid bone probably sad
In the neck of a neanderthal
Escape is a slightly different shape of vocal tract
Turn human
Digitally push something like
Rest through it
Puffs of wind
What sounds were you going for
We were interested in water
Kodachrome sold out
And then those are the ones if you can produce those then you've got the range of sounds that the mobile human can make income
The primary colors of
The basis of
Speeches that right that's right yes you could think of some assessment and Atticus to this primary
So the idea is if they could say these three vowels
It would have been physically tape
Full of some kind of language
Which structure is okay and what
Did you find a note we found a very good match
It sounds a bit
Stole compared
The most inhuman
What does it sound like
A bit more like
Their ass be
Become Oz
Yeah so they still screaming yelling like the thing in the BBC
What would a saint about that she said based on what we know now there's no real evidence
That account see why they wouldn't have the whole range of being able to whisper and being able to shout
I feel like Neanderthal women
Just like excluded from the depiction of true
There were Neanderthals live in
Wow okay maybe I should have maybe I should meet an ESL women across the bar
That's my kind of story
Okay so let's return to our nyanners
It's over this time
Inside of a man
All right
It's 100 Fun character switch
And like the BBC 14 years ago I bought a new voice actor
Sandra Clark
To be my Neanderthal how tall are you
Perfect
Beforehand that actually Workshop it's a couple
Of
In a bar appropriate phrases
I guess you could say with Anna Barney the sounds
Like what could we have this man
I was thinking like
Hello you are beautiful or
Did it hurt when you fell from heaven that kind of thing
Buttchin kind of a different idea and you gave me this one
So weird but it really does highlight that special vowels
Patience
Nugget so I'm standing next to this
Women
They just imagine the sister of the other
She's got brown hair
The same piercing brown eyes
And I just say
Hey
And she pauses for ammo
And then she says
The cart
Thought
On the mall
The cat sat on the map
Pink sheep
There's back there's vowels in it you got your vowels
Kind of lean in you know it's mysterious
So
Come here often
Yes
I'm Annie
That's right my name that's my name
Can I have your number
Can I have yours
Yeah
It's one two three
Revere Aires
I'm picking you up at school
No face looks
So it's not too dramatic this
Which I think is itself dramatic
No I just think it's so totally amazing how similar their
The more and more we learn about them the closer and closer they become to being
Very close cousins
The caught
Thought
On the mall not only a close cousin or actually a part of us
For a lot of things
For a lot of us we have a 2% Neanderthal DNA
Init
When I spoke to another scientist
Asking all these scientist what would it be like to meet and yes I want a bar
She actually had this.
All around today because if we each carry about 2%
I'm leaving.
Especially when you consider
So actually a monkey
She was living today
We have that I'm guessing it's very right now but
70%
Beijing, Japan
Living today
What is she saying if you take all the 2%
Very very
Individual humans and Adam monkey get to 70
What does 70% of a neanderthal walking Among Us
The ghost of Neanderthal
That is cool
So when you say you know what would happen if you met in the answer my boss today is kind of Misfits of an ant
Bowling balls
Alright Andy call me
The caught thought
On the mall
Pre-screening McEwen
Oh boy so Indiana calls reading dr. Seuss
Strangle
I sentence you to reading the Cat in the Hat
They will be like in the NFL present
Truly good
Shelby round things out
One more
One more big little questions yes we should
Go to the Final Cut
This
Final question
Yes it comes from our gang like the other ones but this one just is so
Wonderful
Weird Siri quality this one so if this time it won't be I want to dedicate
What's about to happen
2 people who are living in New York when I was growing up named mr. and mrs. purple
Are these people who just drove on a purple bicycle dress
Can only purple and lavender tie dye clothing
Had purple colored hair
Purple Panda
Panda makeup
And they were just
Very purple and they were always
Here there New York and they became a kind of legendary
Free prints free prints
And I'm sorry
Sicknesses purple
Right now
Heaven
But there
Heaven might very well be perfectly described
Bible Church
Interesting
Pinterest
Okay so me let me set it up so this is this comes from producer Rachel Cusick
Rachel in addition to making radio with us
Formerly was a professional maker of food
Xi'an
She worked in a she worked in a restaurant for 2 years
I would call her a professional cook
Although Apparently that is
Maybe putting a
Strongly
Queen Rachel but she's a food wizard
Regularly every couple of weeks
We'll bring in these like
Food inventions that she makes
In the wee hours of the night
Like a hallucinogenic lees colored rainbow
Shortbread cookie things
Incredibly delicious
But also incredibly weird
That will set you up for what's about to happen
For sure
Yes so she ran into this question that
I guess you could say
Combines all of that
And throws in a bit of science as well as science meets food meets journalism like intersection that I'll
Yeah this is my wheelhouse
Customer begins with this guy
How are you doing
Hi how's it going with excellent but can I ask you to introduce yourself so I'm under Sandberg
I'm a senior research fellow at the Oxford Martin school at
University of Oxford
So I guess to start I was wondering if you could tell me how you first
Stumbled across this
Set the scene for me where were you what were you doing well
That was going back to my office in Oxford
Use on a bus
Coming back from a meeting
It's summer it's warmer than the I'm tinkering with my laptop because the counter side is pretty boring
So deserving around do they like Wi-Fi on buses
So dedicated that
He brings his own form of
Anyhow
Who's on the bus
And she starts answering questions from this website called stack
Exchange
It's it's I think of it like Yahoo answers
But for like science nerds where people post questions summer science related
And then anyone can come in answer
Who are these people are these all smart like atomizer and no I think it's kind of like teenagers who want help with homework and then there's
They're just random Joe schmoes who like are taking a break
Reddit and they're like let me
Show you how I can
China right now
And then there's Anders
Scrolling
Baby looking out the window every now and then and then he like that a certain point on the ride
Cease
Bizquest
What if Earth turn into blueberries
It was probably just like that like what if the Earth turned into blueberries
More or less
Golf courses
Blueberries Robert I'm already compressed blueberries
In other words
Take this Earth We're living on replace that dirt and water and rock within Earth's
Size ball pit of blueberries
What would that look like
What
Why would someone
That quiz
I want to I want to take a moment right now because I think I would not ask that question
Also the kind of person who just needs to be convinced why is this an amazing Quest
Hardcore science is on this website next to sirius science
Questions
But it's also like the most Fantastical form of that it's like let me work within this
Structured world
Like a lot of physics
Planetary science and see where we can
I love what this question I'm a big fan of
Taking some assumptions it where does it live
So Ender says the moment he saw that question pop up
I can totally see how one can answer is
But as soon as enters got started
That the people over at stack exchange the moderators close the question because
Apparently they thought it was too stupid
When the moderators on Stock Exchange that took down the question Michael's really angry
Why
Wait tell me why you was doing this is a good question because it allows us to exercise
He's not even a physical ability
I'm an amateur
He's just like look I'm not even in this world but like these formulas are out there for everyone to use this is like why we have laws
The physics is so that we can imagine
These new world
Tom Waits
Angelby
Anna
That's actually why I wrote the paper
Array technical paper about the physics of it how
Behave what it would look like what it was
You like
Can you walk me through just so I have an image in my mind I'm on this blueberry Earth
What's the first thing that I would notice
What you would feel like
All right this morning
Why is that
Well results show that the density of afterlife in the temperature range between 303 and 353
Ender says if you calculate the density of uncompressed blueberries are about 700 kilos
A cubic meter
They got plugged into another formula to calculate how much less Mass with blueberry or have
I'm from / r
R squared formula to calculate the surface gravity and it turns out that you get about the same crime
16% of the gravity that you would have on regular
So we can bounce
Accepted so you would be able to bounce around surface of blueberries
Blueberries
Welliver squishable
So Ender says will happen is that as you're bouncing on the surface of blueberries will radiate
Pressure downwards into the center of the planet score
Hooters at the center of the planet will start bursztynowa squishing
1st and 1st and Bruce
Until it more liquid than it was blueberries at the center
And is that happened
Planet starts to compress
And normally when you pack a blueberry they're like little corners of are tucked in between each one but once that's being replaced with
Liquid that is being squeezed and squeezed
That air has to go somewhere and it gets pushed up
About like a volcano
Through the core up
To the surface of blueberry
Who haven't been
Then
Another gaesser start the total gravitational energy of the constant
Density sphere remembers Luna gravity so you going to get the cases
Dairy farm small letter
We tell me tell me how high up I never seen a geyser this is not a funeral at the Geyser in Yellowstone
Kilometer of the rookie on the water boiling
Meters of moving air a blueberry powder
Just go to be tremendously dramatic
These guys are they hot they must be hot
One of those things where you might have noticed if you were pumping up your bike
Prussic acid gets warmer Heat
You're going to get boiling blueberry jam all over the place
The geishas I think some of them are likely to notice it some of the blueberries into orbit
Well, they're streaking across the sky shooting stars
Imagine
And meanwhile geysers are exploding everywhere
Because all this Jam is a shooting out from the center it has to go somewhere and when it drops back down to earth
It just covers the earth in warm blueberry jam
And so it's no longer like a surface of
Full blueberries it's just like
An exoplanet like an ocean planet of blueberry jam
Yeah
Noland
That's pretty cool to imagine
Is it like an ocean like we would think the notion of kind of similar but
It's going to be like a little bit more nothing like there's going to be massive waves
But here on Earth at some point the wave Galaxy squishies down cuz I be like nah
Gravity Falls Gravity so they can be actually much taller can you
East Coast surfing on blueberry jam ocean waves
I think you come
This might be easy for us with not to use the surfing is that they going to be moving more slowly
That kind of sounds like my ideal to learn how to surf is just to let go slowly in a jam wave
Yep and if you fall and you just get to Lake Lane Jam
Okay so
Address Artemis Jam wave which by the way is now your amazing life
University things
First you noticed that the air is pretty
About 10 times bigger than it is on regular Earth which means you go to have enormous clouds
The scale height of the atmosphere
Disgruntled hazy
Disguises
Blue purple white milky color
Swirls
I think you would probably find that it's going to be relativity
Another thing I noticed is that the days will be a little bit shorter because blueberry or the compressor
We end up with a planet with .89 time angular momentum conservation gives
So you're there you're surfing and then you look up
The problem for the Moon is it's bound to Earth right now but only because the Earth
Western States blueberries if the mass goes down a lot
Keep hold of it I got a lot of other things that has to worry about
Orbit around the Salton Sea
Recede into the sky
But now we have an interesting problem
You better or if he's going into an orbit around the Sun and the Moon is also orbit
Roughly in the same orbit
But they're very close
So from time to time you might just see the moon
Swirl by at night time and then eventually according to the mass there will come a time
Bangkok Get Closer Closer Closer
No pairs of time it's pretty like living
Sooner or later
They will collide
The blueberry Earth and the moon will collide
Oh yes
It's going to be a big splash
Who's going to win my guess is that the Moondance office of Court on there
Then and now Friday
It says if we just like
Absorbed the moon and put it into blueberry Earth in this mood and gets to live
With in blueberries
Forever
More or less yes
Even imagine the moon splashing into it is probably go to sell blueberry jam at Roseville solar system
Deleting too also two very hilarious to call of the craters on other planets
Innovative
So the calculations have been describing
You do them at when you do planetary science
Is no
Lifeline
Will come
Pure Imagination
Our brains
Developed it to handle the normal world around us
But in some sense there was a overshoot we can imagine things but they're not here
We can think about stuff at
What to be here or could be here
Door must not be here
Supplemental imagination with science
So we got ways of reasoning about strange situation
This is an expression of being Uomo imagining other worlds I think it's worth
Really makes us human
Thank you so much for coming in on a
Saturday to Talk About Blueberries this is awesome
Producer Rachel Cusick
Also special thanks in this episode to Sandra Clark and Alexander glacier
Weather, I'm Diamond I'm on team blueberry now and second. I'm just not like I'm antagonist anymore
Maybe I'm just lost my
Joie de vivre
You think you did if you did
Succumb
Some people get Chihuahua early
Some people getting y middle
Some people get Schwab
Thrust upon them
Shakespeare yeah of course
Yeah but maybe maybe
The distance one has to travel I can pick you pick you pick a person out like at 3:33
On Any Given Tuesday
And you say
How far emotionally spirits
Do you have to travel to get to Joy
How far is that that that Journey
My journey used to be like I'll just take one step to the left I'm there
Now it's like I got to board a plane I got to take off I got to fly all the way across the world I got to land the plane in Tahiti
And then then I'm enjoy
Yes you have you have
Slid
Further from the
From the ideals and you wish
B
You should just troubling me but that's what she that's the advantage of a story like this
This is a story that
Can
Gently tug you
The way
Gravity.
And then land you
Totally Magic
Chamois
Soup of Glory jammies
Glory
Anchorage
Yeah
But you know what I will say just be just as a closing thought
Your 80 Hertz is really good right now
Is it
Yeah. You got a little bit of a little bit of a gravel
Happening
Under the gravel I hear some really good ATR
Well thank you gif
You're welcome
Welcome back to me which makes it listen more questions in a few days
Play the message press to start of message
This is Evelyn.
Produced by Soren wheeler executive producer
Our staff include Simon Adler wrestler Rachel to Zach David that the Hopi
Cityhunt not guilty Robert krulwich Julia Longoria Annie McEwen
Melissa O'Donnell Kelly Prime sarakari
With help from FEMA oldies
Emma and Neal
A fact Checker is Michelle hack
End this mess