Are you awake
Listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
So it may be just want to start at the beginning so how did you bump into the
We've had you been following Financial stories and not I did some Financial storage but I think my beat was more
People in the headlines at the worst moments of their lives
And then I would go in and
Become their friends and we would talk intimately about
What downfall means when you've been at the mountain
Top
Hey I'm Jared I'm Rod Radiolab
A behind-the-scenes look at the greatest financial fraud
In history
What's going on here
Play come on baby I know you got
It's a series called Ponzi Supernova from audible.com and she said of how we got to
Ellenhorn the great Eleanor and who was one of the founding members of Radiolab
Couple years ago she left us
It was raining that for us but you went off to Audible
Teamed up with a guy named Steve Fishman who just heard
And together they produce
This series which has tape in it that has never before been hurt
And it's pretty extraordinary and kind of
Given what's happened recently with
Financial reforms
App for reconsideration
What you're about to hear you will find
A little bit troubling an extremely Timely
Until what we did a couple days ago we got Steve and Ellen into the studio
Play us some stuff
And to think about it
Sure you spend the first episode
Really
You spend the first episode really chasing
The guy trying to get access to Bernie Madoff in prison
Yeah you know I did all kinds of things that mean this was like years long
Pursuit I would send Bernie
Novels in the mail I would try and up
Insult him I copied out Sartre play No Exit
And I sent that to him
You know just to try and get a rise out
I put money in his commissary account and then
You know send him a you're welcome note
Never receiving a response do you know why at this point
What was driving this
I mean listen Bernie has done this
I mean everybody does and we keep reading about the details and we keep
Triangulating Bernie from friends who very obviously didn't know him investors who buy these they obviously didn't know him
I want to hear this guy
Tell me I want to say where are you why did you do this you were already rich
Come on
What's going on here
I mean
Bernie
Had the greatest seat in the house
To what was going on
Behind the scene
Steve is explained to us for years he just kept pestering the guy in prison
Do I like a whole series of other prisoners asking them to get the word to Bernie and
Eventually just cut to the chase one day my home phone ring
So I pick it up it's a Sunday evening the Jets
Game is on and I
Got my two young kids running around at it
You have a collect call from an inmate at the federal prison and then and then you can Bernese voicing Bernard Madoff in the sky
Kind of
I need a kind of disgusted
That tone of voice and a nice like Captain Ahab but now you have kids running around the room at Jets game on here
The phone call oh my God are you ready or not
And I'm not ready I don't have a pen and paper I don't have a tape recorder
And my kids are
Hey kids
So then it called come out only in 15 minutes
Sads
For whatever reason there exactly 15 minutes exactly 15 minutes
Wait 15 minutes
Call you back while he hangs up I know at 15 minutes I'm running around
Well I must have a tape recorder
I'm on in a closet
Tested
At this point we're just going to drop into the series
Yeah I was just saying it was great to talk to you because
You know talking to you in person is so different than reading about you all day
Caricature out there in the
I will send to you as being a
You know just as one-dimensional person
So what
Bernie Madoff is the greatest Financial
Trucking history
But his voice is familiar to
Middle could be the uncle I run into at bar mitzvahs
We have common roots
Middle-class New York Jews
And also and
Interesting the Jets
I got it recorded
Yeah I like that
Increase
I try to imagine the former chairman of the NASDAQ
At a payphone in a Cell Block
Inmates lined up behind him
With prison made tattoos
Prison Hound muscles
Oh and you can eat and you can call at night to
Prison
Is not with Bernie expect
Pretty big picture window
Open it from being separated from everybody in love
Time's up
It's frustrating
Nicole starts we build momentum
Journey Begins to open up
And then
The guillotine Falls
Trust is tough to build on a timer
And I need to be the person he will trust
The whole story
At least
As he sees it
Bernie lets me know he has a story to tell
He's been misunderstood
I'm a good person he tells me
He starts with this
His family didn't have a clue
Bernie and Sissy shielded
Ace family
Nobly
Kept them in the dark
Until the on seasonably warm afternoon of December 10th
2008 he was at his office
Bernard L Madoff securities
A family business
What happened
They went into Bernie study
I don't know what else to tell you I said but
And nobody gets angry at that point
Everything is fine
Andrew Birnie youngest son have been diagnosed with lymphoma 5 years earlier
Afforded and recovered fully
He consider changing jobs
But Bernie talked him into returning
To work beside his dad his
His brother
His uncle
His first cousin
Really
As for what happened next
Daily left
They went to a lawyer that you got to turn your father and I never saw him again
And didn't hear from them again
Until two years into Bernie's 150 year sentence
His oldest son Mark sent a message
In the most horrible way
End
Roots on the phone and she tells you
Mark Madoff killed himself at age 46
Hung himself with a dog leash in his Soho Loft
While his toddler slept in the room next door
The date
December 11th 2010
2 years to the day
After his father's arrest
The Bernie marks message to him was
What's clear
You
Ruin my life
Bernie told me he still hoped he could reach Andrew
And explain
But Andrews cancer returned
He blame the relapse on his father's crimes
The stress and shame of it all
Andrew Madoff died in 2014
Bernie's always a survivor
Once he confessed to the largest Ponzi scheme in history
For him
The worst was over
Be able to get this off your
Show
Earlier
It was
Absolute
It was a nightmare
When you were looking down the barrel of this
You kind of knew it would end up here
You know where you are now by sooner or later
Destroyed the family
Need to do this and I said
I don't know
Yeah
They have wonderful psychologist
Well that's great
That's right
That's great
A New Yorker and his shrink
Seeking reassurance
Searching for answers
Where does a monster come from
Am I a sociopath
Not a sociopath
You have fun
I came to think of my conversations with Bernie as a
So III status what are you thinking at this point is you're talking to
I mean we're running through his story and beef develop the kind of Rapport I mean
Udo
But there's a different generation but Jewish roots New York area this is a guy
Who's familiar to me and I
And we developed a report and Bernie kind of tells me the story
Of his father and of how he got into this
Sporting Goods
Metal rod
And it during the Korean War
You watch that happen
Everything
Bernie West
Determined to attain success last
The kind that had eluded his father
Whatever it
22 years old
He convinces a handful of investors to
Trust him
Prince parents former customers of his high school lawn sprinkler business
Clients of his father-in-law's
Accounting firm
New issues were hot in the 1960s
Go without the Mad scramble and hype of today's IPOs
Back then there was no CNBC no computers
With new issues he thought he'd hit on a money-making strategy
Practice 62 with a Cuban Missile Crisis
Bernie lost almost all of
Is clients money
Is he tell that he was embarrassed
He was in tears
We took them to her father
Bernie bags
His father-in-law saved
Bernie needed a better
Strategy
The odds were against him is he saw
Bernie wasn't one of the Wall Street Elite
Steve says
That idea like a Bernie is that
As a lower class kid from Queens who want to prove himself to the big boys be accepted
Citas that's one of the keys to really understand how
A guy like Bernie Madoff could have gotten into this gigantic
Check fraud because
When Bernie's business started to really take off
Possibly
Increasingly through fraud
All of a sudden he had all these guys from the big Banks
Calling them up and wanted to take him out to lunch by the mid-90s word
Spread people clamor to put their money in Madoff
Hedge funds Bank funds and feeder
Funds created to funnel money to Madoff
To Pumped out
Those in
Credibly consist
Sip returns
Everyone wanted to be with Bernie
Country Club golfers
Hedge funds prestigious Bank
No but we need you to commit to the money
According to Bernie
This was the turning point
The market went against him
The boy Genius failed
And they lose your money
That was his undoing
He couldn't move billions of dollars in and out
Of the market
Irresistible for the young man wants shut out of the
Club
You know where you had a history of
You know breaking up in the country club at the New York Stock Exchange with the market makers
Now in some sense I guess your
You're finally getting the record
Recognition
Kind of same people that
They need you
The Mummy 2
Can I get something out of the way till Ponzi scheme which we sort of need to know Ponzi scheme is
I give you money to invest
You pretend you invest that money but you don't
Right said what you do is you go out and you get new investors take their money give it to me and then you can go out and get even
Newer investors take their money given to the ones before them and on and on and on
Cilic all you're doing is just repositioning money like taking it from the new guys giving it to the slightly the last new guys
Making it look like you're trading when you're not and it only works
As long as you have new people coming in young need a constant stream of new people coming in with new money
But that'll
Stella Parton 2008
2008 Riviera
Huge
Stock market
Bernie woke up after decade
Getting a lot of money in one day
People. I want my money back I chew me too me too and he had not done anything
Except
Expect more money to come to the front door on that day there was no money
And so
Bernie's version
The fraud started because impressive people threw money at him
A good person
Who made a mistake
We spent hours talking about this
And it seems to me at some point that there's always going to be that next phone call
But there's that Gap you know 15 minutes I have to wait until the phone rings then
And 1 time the phone doesn't ring
Bernie doesn't call back
And I get from the
Prison a letter
Basically explaining that I have been
Declared a security risk
What is a security risk
I have no idea and
You know it is some kind of casual I mean I try to appeal that to the Bureau of Prisons is an appealable so base
The warden says
You know
We don't want this disaster
It always is
Security risk you can't talk
An injustice in upside just so
At this point
But having spent a hunk of time
You you went into this thinking okay I'm going to sit in his shoes
I'm going to
Feeling
And where are you right now
At this point
So now I've spoken to him for three or more hours
And
You don't like taking this journey with him
Hershey Story
You know I have felt some empathy for
Bernie from his point of view
I'm so now I start to listen to the tapes and I
I start to really kind of digging in it
And it occurs to me
The bird is telling me to story
Bernie Madoff
On one hand is this
Wizard
Conducting this game
Rideable Financial
Criminal Wizardry
A mastermind
And on the other hand he's just kind of poem
P***
Not aware you normally associate with Bernie Madoff
More on that after the break has what ends up happening with the cool Revelations of the series is
The way in which Bernie actually sees himself
As a victim
And it's here where the story sort of starts to expand Beyond
Can you start the sort of C
How much bigger field of play
Yeah that's coming up after the break
Details Alicia Bridges calling from Saskatoon in Saskatchewan Radiolab is supported in part by the
Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world
More information about Floyd @www.
Flooring.org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
About what we're calling tiny moments of brilliance
Basically I want to hear about those times when I kids you know did something
It just means you lean back and say wow how did they do that maybe it was the moment that I can
Kids you've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of their musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed are ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the
Epic moments where
A kid does something super smart but it doesn't have anything to do with the test
If you have a story with us
Go to radiolab.org brilliance
Record short audio message
And that's where you're at. Org / Brillion
Thank you so much
Hey I'm Jared I'm Robert krulwich Radiolab today we're playing a series of excerpts from brand new
Sisters from audible called
Ponzi Supernova comes from reporter Steve Fishman
And Ellen Horner
Former executive producer
And a
Series about Bernie Madoff and the largest financial fraud in history
Triple behind-the-scenes look it in the series
There's lots of really
Kind of crazy frankly descriptions of
How Bernie Madoff and his team pull it off
And how on many occasions
They almost got caught
Former US attorney Matthew Schwartz
Tell me about one of the closest
Of the clothes
Calls
One starring Frank dipascali
Madoff stop lieutenant
He pascali testifies
That he's going to sing in a conference room with the Auditors they ask for
This is report called s sayak siac report
A conference room
Full of auditors
One asks for this routine report
Something illegitimate trading firm
Would have on the Shelf
Of course Madoff isn't illegitimate trading firm
So they don't have it
And quick Frank
And be cool
In front of the auditors
Frank phones the computer programmers
Incest
Hey can you bring up the sciac reports
And the guy that says basically
Kayak report
You told us we didn't need the Sonic report where the hell am I going to get a sciatic
Report
This is great I'll see you in 10 minutes
You know that he does
This is he
Describe that a little soft-shoe to stall for time
Meanwhile the team has minutes
It's to prepare a false report
And then make it appear
As if it's been idling on a Shelf
They're frantically putting together and printing out
This
Report which is you know it's
Half a foot thick
I'm just being paper dot matrix paper
And then it supposed to be
A report
It's been lying around for a month and it said it's hot off
Depresses
So
First
They stick it in
Refrigerator
Down in the investment advisory
Cool it off
And then they literally
Play football with it
Horsing around the room to one another to make it
Weather
And then they run it up to a
Pascal
Cooley
Hands it to the auditors
The clothes called
Over and over again
Fabulous theater
Steve actually described Bernie madoff's operation
You're the created like this
Massive 65 billion dollar fraud
As looks
Super recognizer
Busy held together by
Taping
Safety pins and old
Dot matrix printers in the series goes into a lot of details about
To the mechanics and how it worked what caught our attention
What's the thing that we sort of mentioned for the break this idea that Bernie saw himself not as this like all-powerful
Criminal mastermind
But it's kind of a pain yeah there was an original group of investors that Bernie made up
And this group is called the Big Four
And that's exactly right the Big Four
They came to be known even made off calls in the Big 4
For Prime big clients
Jeffry picower
Norman Levy
Call Shapiro
Stanley Chase
Commonly referred to as the Big Four
It was very clear
That those accounts in particular Shapiro Levy
Picower
And Chase former assistant us attorney Matt Schwartz again or handled very differently
From other accounts
And we're Handles in a way
That you no matter less if there was a mistake
For these accounts the workmanship was quite different
More demanding
Less
Exacting
Some
Employees were
More meticulous than others and some clients you could afford to be less meticulous with
Annette Bongiorno have been there a long time
She was employee number one in the Ponzi business
Garfinkel tell me she handle the accounts of the Big Four
Steve garfinkel was one of the FBI agents who investigated Bernie madoff's Operation Pets
Clients
The way she
Fugazi there
Account statements
There were some instances when the customers got their account statements from a net
I complained that
Am I you know you promised me
You know 18% and I only got 16%
The
Statement back to Annette
Statement
With miraculously you got the
Yeah your new statement with the new hire return
Madoff himself says the accounts of the big four were
Fugazi
They were doing all sorts of major a praise
The Jewish term that we use
Taking more sprays and stuff that they did was unbelievable
And I was doing it to me
They demanded Bernie do
Kinkier
Maneuvers
Example there was explicit testimony that he would not tolerate
A single losing trade in his account to he had a particular trading strategy where sometimes
You can have a losing leg of a trade but the trade is a whole is a winner who's a three-legged trade he wouldn't even tolerate
For some reason
Every single trade every single leg of every single trade had to be a winner that doesn't happen in real life
And no one can demand that of their money badge room each of the Big 4 pay back Millions
U-Pick hours case
Billions of dollars
Every one of them
Claim Madoff Hadoop them
They weren't process
Security
And it's impossible for Schwartz to say for certain
Who knew what
What he can say is there was activity in the accounts of the Big Four
Backwood raise
Questions in the eyes of
Anyone now you might believe
That your Genius money manager
Can get you 700% return and a good year
But
No one has the ability to rewrite history
Entering stocks into bonds
And so these men mostly older powerful mentors to Madoff
Open for me a new door into the Madoff Ponzi operation
They gave Bernie his break
And then demanded that he provide them things he couldn't honestly achieve
These people are these people who are
Everett is
They are asking for things that are not
Possible
Bernie is accomplishing those things
So now ask yourself who has the power in that relationship
Is it barely because he knows he's doing illegal things for these parties
Or is it the
The party who said who's now making Bernie do illegal things
It's both of them but when burning since you gosh like
I I discovered that people are really greedy
Member that was in the beginning
Is this what he means that these people were using him
This is what their name means end and Bernie has actually
Particular enmity for those big 4
One of them jeffry picower
Cook-Out 7 billion dollars
It's getting billion dollars from this eating right beyond what he invested
That's a longhorn who produced the series now the story of jeffry picower
Is one of the more dramatic moments in the series
What's going on
10 months after Bernie Madoff arrest
Barbara picower
Wife of Madoff largest investor jeffry picower
Dial 911
This call is hard to listen to It's upsetting
Okay Samurai
Actor Jeremy pick out had a heart attack and drown you can congratulate me on that
According to Madoff
The fort picower went for his final swim
Bernie phone him
I called up
Jeffry picower and
You know I said
EB got to give the money back I said you guys
Only money
And I want the money back
Picower that you know that the well you know I don't have it all I thought I said Jeffrey
I know that you have the money there
If you work 9 billion dollars that I want
7 billion back
Consider what made of
Regarding the death of someone
What this says about Bernie Madoff
Who he is
Whenever someone hears that I interviewed Madoff
They always want to know this Bernie feel remorse
I'd interviewed serial killers child rapists
People considered monsters
I suspended judgment
I want to hear their stories
To understand them
This doesn't mean I wasn't horrified by what I heard
But I try to see the world through their eyes
An exercise in empathy
At times
I feel empathy for Bernie
But here's what struck me about Bernie
He
Didn't feel empathy
Declaimed feel remorse
Now the words but
There was always a but
On the phone with me
Every single time Bernie mentions victims
He can barely get
Through the apology
Before interrupting himself
They were warned they were greedy
Always this strange
Sorry not sorry
I could go crazy and do something stupid
It's Joey if you want it
So put your money in
It's impossible to tell the story of The Fall of the House of Madoff
Without understanding that there were real
Real suffering
Back in early 2009
Victims were telling stories of their ruined lives
On TV on the radio
On every local talk show it was the worst thing that ever happened to us
This can't be real we have lost everything I've lost everything and you've lost everything everything
That we work for you down the green
X at the end of the month I
I made a lot of money for a lot of people
Did you catch
What's the remorse
Or was it too fleeting to register in your brain
My producers and I were in touch with dozens of victims
To the victims
Bernie's indifference was enraging
All over again
But it wasn't the slightest bit surprising
What is surprising
Is what happened to victims
Since Madoff drag their 65 billion dollars
Down a dark
Call
I mean there is now this is a 9 years later
There is any
Industry that is created around the Madoff collapse
There
Hundreds of lawyers working on
Recovering money
And that's a very complicated story and and
When we trying tell because you know what
A lot of people who lost money
Didn't have any inclination couldn't have had any inkling that this was going on
The Justice group comes in
Private lawyers
Courts judges the justice department
And they try to make amends
Holiday
Justice is a very complicated issue in
The universe created by Bernie Madoff
You have a trustee appointed to recover
Funds for victims
Well some of those funds
Little people
Who took those funds
In good faith
They given Bernie
Millions of dollars they took out
1000000 + 1
And so they thought they were doing the right thing they thought it was
Their money
But we got to get money back to the people
Who lost more money than they put in you're going to have to
Give some of your money to them so it's a very complicated Marvel Universe
Well there's the individuals and then in the last category
There are the banks
And the investment institutions
That
Bernie
Two ordinary people all over the world
Yeah there are these financial institution
Hedge funds raised
Billions of dollars to come to Latin America
Europe
All across the United States
Marketing
Bernie Madoff
As a safe bet you know he was weaponized
By the financial system
And so we wondered why worth
Those hedge funds accountable
For not doing their job
And this is the still
Still happening still
Unraveling still needs to be reported part of the
Storytime solutely
That question
About why the people who
Quote weaponized Bernie Madoff haven't been punished yet probably will never be punished
That is something that Eleanor Nancy fish and tackle in the final episode in their series
And we definitely recommend you check it out audible.com
Slash Ponzi Supernova will take you there as well from radiolab.org
And thank you to Steven Fishman and two ellenhorn for sharing this work of beers with us
Also a shout out to producer Kelly Prime who
El Pelon Steve work on series
Thank you audible thank you for listening
I will see you next time
Hi this is Logan from Hamilton Montana
Radiolab is produced by Jad appenrod
Dylan Keith is a director of soundesign Soren wheeler is senior editor Jamie York is our senior producer
Staff includes
Simon Adler Jennifer L David Cavell
Matt kielty Robert Truitt
Annie McEwen Latif Nasser
Melissa O'Donnell Arianne wack
And Molly Webster with help from Tracy hunt
Valentina benini Vitaly
MKT Ferguson our fact-checker is Michelle Harris