Before we get going just a quick warning this podcast contains some descriptions of graphic violence and also some strong language
So be warned
Are you weightless
Northern listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
Nice to see you again Chad
Why did you say that was convinced that all about
Sister you been away for awhile
The only way I can see you is when I come visit you
But the other family
Okay so this is Radiolab producer Matt
Guilty
Talking about
Supreme Court case from 1989
Today man has a story that he's been reporting for about 2 years
That we are going to play both here on more perfect
And also here on radio
So buckle up
Where's where should we start I think we might as well just
Start
Should I try to sound Southern
With a guy named Woody connect from a lawyer with Essex Richards
A law firm in Charlotte North Carolina
Pick it up in 1985 by 295 I was a very young lawyer I was 32 years
So I just started Mountain Law Firm
And I was talking about anything that came through the door
And 1 days
This guy walked in late 30s
Fairly thin
5.95 foot 10 bone crushers
Annie's he's a black man
PS
Or was he passed away
Mr Graham
The man's name is Katherine Graham and what he says
Well
Like white what happened your leg what's with the crutches
And the thorn lays everything out for him.
So he was pulled over on West Boulevard in Charlotte which is
Four lane road
Buddy he work for the city of Charlotte in the department of
Station on road crews doing Road repairs
It was Monday afternoon and on that day when adjusting one's friends or co-workers stop by
After talking for a bit Mr Graham asked to be taken to a nearby convenience store
It was only two or three blocks from his house
He needed some orange juice
Because he was
Suffering the onset of a diabetic insulin reaction
Soda Thorn Hopkins from car
They drove over to the convenience store to Thorn got out got a bottle of orange juice
Got to the checkout counter but
There's a line there
So I put the bottle down and hurries out get back in Sprint car they take off
Now
This is where the problems
Started
10. At the same time all that's happening there's actually an officer who was African-American
Sitting in his squad car and what that officer observed was a man hurrying out of the store jumping
Sing into a waiting car and
Quickly driving off
So you started to hail the thorn in his friend but after a couple of blocks
Pull them over just to determine what was going on there
So he goes up to the driver side presumably gets to Thorns buddies drivers
Goes back to his squad car
Start radioing
Get ahold of the store to see if anything that happened
And it's right around that moment.
The passenger
Seed of
The car suddenly opened
His door got out of the car
Circle the car once or twice
Lake Sardis stumbled around it. Down on the car
He started going
In shock
Almost like a seizure he would have a really yeah and it was terrifying
This is the thorn Graham jr. he was a type 1 diabetic what is type 1 diabetes been with one and two or more.
Understand the type 1 diabetes
Is when your body just doesn't produce enough
Insulin
It won't be that seizure look like
Like well
One incident in particular
Art remembers being in church and he got like this Blank Stare on his face and
You see the beads of sweat come on his forehead his body was seized up and he was shaking
He would bite his tongue up and
I'm so I can remember my mother trying to let you know for sure spoon into his mouth for keeping from
Biting his tongue up and
The main thing was try to get some orange juice and that way it would raise his
Blood sugar in
And what you got the orange juice and heat sleep for a couple hours and then he'd wake up and
DB exhaust
But he be alive
Alright so
Charlotte City street at this point
Four other officers arrived
Thorn has actually passed
Out on the curb one of the officers
Rome Instagram over on the sidewalk
And cuffed his hands behind his
Is back
At what point
Have one of your officers
Rab's Thorn by the handcuffs in
Picks him up
Off the curb from from behind
The Thorn was sort of in and out at this point I guess he tries to tell the officers but it was a diabetic but he had a medical card
Cardinals wallet ask the officer to pull the wallet out of his back pocket
And one of the officers
Said ain't nothing wrong with the motherfuker Buddies truck
At some point around here the details are a little unclear
Pretty nasty scuffle ensued
According to what is known as kasodus of the storm was resisting the officers and apparently officers slam Des Moines head into his friends
Car is over head and shoulder injuries he also ended up with a broken foot cut around the wrist
And eventually
The officers pick him up
One on each arm one on each leg and just
Throw him in the back
Back of a squad
While this was going on a few people gathered around and how long after that
The officers
Learned that nothing at all had happened at the convenience store there was no crime there was no robbery there was no show
Shoplifting
Set a dragon back to his house still in handcuffs
The car
Infinity Stones has gotten some OJ
And the officers
Lay them out in
Front yard took the handcuffs off and then just drive away
Was there an apology
Oh no
Now what came out of that day in Charlotte
Would end up becoming one of the most important
Supreme Court cases
History when it comes to pleasing
And
What you mean about this case is how something like you needed some orange juice
Something so seemingly small
Would eventually become tied to this and all the
Shootings we've seen in the past years mostly of young black men every time we hear one of these shootings every time there
Alki everytime the copy atop this incident is looming in the shadows
Shaping the outcome
In many ways it is quietly Define the air that we're living in
And I wanted to know how
How did it happen
Rihanna
Supreme Court of the United
God save United States and this honorable Court
At 21.2 clock little bit I will say this about my dad now he wasn't someone that would
Would just lay down and roll over
Talkington storing Junior I asked him a little bit about his dad and he told me that the thorn senior group in the Southeastern North Carolina
Owner tobacco
Farm use a hard worker get student is sisters
Told me that
He was the first
Blackish
Pixar African-American accepted to Duke University
But
My grandmother
She wouldn't let him go because of you know doing this are right there that she didn't want him to have to experience
All that
All that mess
This is a CBS News special report in spillover the kind of day I mean like the Civil Rights
Movement was a lot of things but there was this big part of it that was about
Police brutality
Angeles
Also known as the long hot summer of 1967
50 race riots across the country
A lot of which was sparked by accusations of police brutality
50 Cent
I will not
Accept charges against policeman I will not
Except
Charges against policeman this is a statement
Might be any difference might not be any different
You understand that
If we cannot bring charges against the policeman who have murdered us
I just throw it out homes and businesses where will we go
Where will we go
She didn't want him to have to experience
All that all that mess
So ended up I think he ended up on the Fayetteville State
Inspected by college in North Carolina
And when you graduated actually one of the first jobs that he had he work for an employer called Precision spray
Spring Steel company that specialize in making Springs but at a certain point you assuming the company
Discrimination based on how they were treating you
You know people of color
So after that day with the officers and Charlotte one thing I do remember
Dad saying was that it wasn't right
Difference in a fight
Right
And that is how he ends up walking into Woody's office on crutches in 1985
He tells what he
I want to sue the Charlotte Police Department
So we went ahead and just filed a lawsuit in federal court Woody takes it to trial and basically is arguing
Squeezed I had used excessive force
That was totally unnecessary under the circumstances like they roughed up a diabetic who is telling them
He was a diabetic
Eventually the judge presiding over the
Ruled that
These officers did not use excessive force and if you were going to
Claim that they did
We had to
Show that the police officers had acted
Maliciously for the purpose
Causing harm
Hot today they had to prove that the officers at cement
To hurt him
Yeah that Woody and the thorn had to prove that the officers
Had it out for the thorn and we simply couldn't do that
If it seems like a really hard thing to
Prove it's an almost impossible standard to me
I think it's important to zoom in on this for a second because it's really kind of like the
Crux of the story
If the question is what should the standard be for holding
Cop cannibal
Portuguese
The forest ending
In the mid-eighties
Malicious intent was sort of the prevailing stand
If you're going to claim
That a police officer use excessive force
It's you and the standard was that you had to prove
That the officer did so
With malice in their heart
Why was that the standard
This is kind of hard to explain. I don't have the 14th amendment in front of me but it
Essentially
All you really need to know is that it was connected the Fourteenth Amendment to a particular clause
In the Fourteenth Amendment
And this is why would he in the thorn lost that
It's okay alright so loses a federal court loses Federal makes its way up to the fourth Circuit Court of Appeals
That went nowhere
The Court of Appeals
World against us
Same thing same thing
Then nothing after that ruling what are you get the phone call and you hear me from this
Jerry Beaver unknown civil rights lawyer in the area in Fayetteville North Carolina Gerald was older and wiser
So then maybe that's your wording not mine
Gary had caught wind of the circumcision images Lake
You should not have to require that
Police officer had it in for you
I just wanted to beat the crap out of you just cuz it made him feel better
So I called Woody and said are you guys planning on taking this case to the Supreme Court and we was like no
McClain can't really afford that I said tell him he doesn't have to worry about that we will be glad to take it on pro bono
When see if we can get this ruling overturned
Make sure that what you said
Sure
Let's go
So Jane we get together and they start looking around like like without their what cases can we draw and argue that there should
Be a different standards and there was this well of Glee season 4 cases
Bubbling up in the court and you had lawyers trying out all these different ideas now most of the courts were using the four
14th Amendment malicious intent standard that during would even like then there was also in the number of cases
What's the eighth unusual punishment
From there what is cruel what is unusual
Imply that you're trying to hurt somebody right
But
The winters are there men in at some of the courts were you seen that
Woody and Jerry look
Tuazar sort of like
Redeemer
The Fourth Amendment 4th amendment
The 4th amendment which is
Swim which is the government cannot subject citizens to unreasonable search and seizure
I have it on my legal pad
The fourth amendment is
The right of the people to be
Secure in their persons houses papers and effects
Against unreasonable searches and seizures
Shall not be
Violated
It is seizure just another word
Perforce
Like I have the right not to eat
Beating your shot by my government yeah it's it's not just that but yes it it also includes that
And it's like so much about the fourth amendment is that in there
Is this one
Important
Worried
Unreasonable reasonable reasonable
Concept of reasonable
What is reasonable and what is not raised
In law reasonable is it supposed to be object
You look at the case from the facts of the case
You look at the who what where when
Not the correct then you asked was this person's Behavior reasonable
Or not they have to act with objective reasonableness
Wait a second reasonableness is a slippery thing
What you find reasonable would I find reasonable could very well be different be completely different yes or no
It can feel slippery but legally the whole concept of reasonableness have
Hundreds of years
Use of
Precedent
I mean I I find this very fascinating and I don't know if you want me to give you like a little bit of
Backstory
Do you want
To give me a little bit of ice. It's interesting how it came to be and how popular it is
Take me to take me on the ride
Okay alright so we go back to the 1830s Andrew Jackson
Elgyem this is going to be like a little windy but I think it kind of makes sense so
In 1832 sky at all catala
I don't get away is a mathematician he's an astronomer if you want to picture something he had Hollow cheeks
He's big sideburns
A little bit like
David
Straight turn
The guy from
The Edward Murrow movie
Jason Bourne movies
Music that helps you at all
Set up an observatory but astronomers
Have this issue
They had trouble pinpointing the location of stars because their telescopes work
So bad
But Kelly was one of those farmers who knew you could use
Asset statistics difficulty
How you could
Take an average of all the different measurements and average of the meteorological data and I can help you pinpoint
We're stars were actually going to be in the sky
Lego that they can make predictions
It's whoever seems like revolutionising
Astronomy
Italy became
Fascinated by this idea of averages and what he did is he
He kind of took that idea
I took it down from the heavens from the sky and started applying it to
Cute
So you can call me through data in medical journals trying to determine the average height of a person the average weight
Temperature
Was he trying to come up with these or proto-man Tennessee
Totally ever had a huge impact on public health
But
Ginza actually going Beyond this and Beyond just like physical traits and starts to like push into
Man's morality and he's looking at crime rates
Suicide rates
Marriage rates
And in the 1830s he starts
Laying out this concept what is
I in French
Loam when which
Translates into the average
Man
The average man so so this is like big data 1830 Style
Yeah and in this idea of the average man
And they became
They're useful in law
English law
Really
How exactly
Money
In Victorian England there was Much Ado About people who wanted to sue for damages or left advantages there were
Need for Thompson averages
Way to take measure in stock to see if a person block
This really seemed like the best way to determine if the accused had to pay that you've wet
English judges they decreed here's how we will
Guilds meaning
What a man
Honest and have him raise his right hand let's say he's back some hay in a terribly negligent way much more
More like a funeral pyre caught his neighbor's home totally on fire
But he says that he did
Nothing wrong so Jerry I ask of you what is it that we shall do how about think of ordinary Folk
Avenger
Take a look
Attic use that hand
And ask yourself
This one question
Did he behave
Like you're ordinary
Average
Reasonable man
Wow
I didn't even know you had that in you
If it's okay
So you're saying
Judges and juries begin to use these averages as a way to
Disorder like
Figure out like if you're suing somebody else
If it's somebody else did they act out of the ordinary where they unreasonable
Yeah it was this.
You can lay in this whole average man thing that English law
Started developing this idea this
Standard don't initially
As the reasonable man
Standard
Eventually switches a person to be a little bit more
Gender inclusive
This reasonable person
It's one of the longest established
Fictional characters that exist in what is known as like the legal Village we have these other little characters like it starts with the reasonable person
And then you start you get like a slew of these other
These other characters that come out of that which is I have a little list there's
The ordinary prudent man of business
The officious bystander there is De fair-minded and informed
Observer
There's the reason Bulger there's the reasonable parent there's a reasonable landlord there's a reasonable neurosurgeon reasonable civil engineer their cellular
Hairdresser
Really sort of like it's like in any sort of
Trade or craft
Where there is business being done or you have the ability within your craft
Harm somebody
Legally it became very useful to have an
Average archetypal person
Doing that crap
So that the jury or the judge
Would have something to use as a measurement when rendering judgment
It's interesting so like in the hairdresser example
Whatever it was that led to that phrase
Probably was a kettle alien survey in an imagine one of hairdresser Behavior
Yeah like like maybe you went in to get a haircut and you walked out and 1/2 years gone right and you're just like weird half
And then it's just you go to Courtney like any reasonable hairdresser would not have made that cut
Right
What starts with this astronomer and ends up with this
Village of reasonableness the funny thing about the village
Please
So like in English law
Like Matt said there's like this Village of people but in England at the
The time they had this idea that
It wasn't like
A village it was people on a bus
Call the man on the Clapham Omnibus which is roughly I looked at the London bus route 88
People are they going
I don't know they just ride the all day those people just waiting for the case to come up and be a hairdresser
In the next. Concept moved in like Australia was like okay we should do that until one part called that the man in the Bondi
Another Park called at the man on the Bourke Street tram
Hong Kong got it
And they said it's a man on the
Shank shank E1 tram to the bus is just a convenient vessel to hold all these reasonable people
England said all these people are on a bus
Because
You didn't want someone who's like
So slowly
That they are like they're not riding the bus they like hold up in a cave somewhere or someone that is like
Play upon their Castle it's like the common man it was described as reasonably educated intelligent button
Nondescript
And I think like what what Woody
And Jerry
To bring it all the way back we're centrally
Trying to do is to say we need to use the 4th amendment in this idea of unreasonable search and seizure
To create a reasonable offer
So we need to add a reasonable officer to the Village or the bus
So
Bradley the cases submitted
In 1989 almost five years after everything happened to the store in Graham that one day in Charlotte
It will hear argument next number 87 6571 his case went before The Supreme Court
Graham vs Connor
Now it's almost there for the arguments we was there
The Spectator
Watch in the case of butterflies
Of course
You may proceed whenever you're ready
If the Chief Justice
Combat place to court pretty quickly these arguments you don't know what
Turn into like this word soup
Standard free. Jerry
The lawyer for the officers
The justices
Subjective
Getting super meta about what constitutes
Activity objectively unreason
Black subjectivity
Subjective factor analysis test
Standards of object
Anthony objective analysis
Bad Intent no intent
Woodward
Until
One Justice
Thurgood Marshall the lone African-American the Quarry
Clumsy Ninja task
What reason was there for a diabetic
At the time the officers didn't know that he was
Diabetic
So violent you had to be there
Do you have to go back once that's even before the officer Connor
So application
In a very suspicious menu
Oriental convenience store
What did he do that was violent
Mr Perry's
Testimony is petitioners on Whitten
Petition was throwing his hands around
The berry had asked for officer
What procedure
What was he doing before they tried to put
Was acting in a very bizarre manner
Ran out of the car
Circle around it twice
And then sat down
District Court
The officer didn't have to wait until he is
Any strike anybody
He was acting Indiana drug predictable and potentially dangerous
Can you answer to
He did not overly sweat
Tri-County
Did he have a weapon of any kind
The record of
The residential rehab
The record shows that he was properly stop
Has a suspect
Criminal investigation
He was acting suspiciously that he was acting in a bizarre
Manor
Did even after he was handcuffed in the officers wanted to put them in the car the Undisputed record shows that he was vigorously fighting and Kicking
Subject to being arrested
Rather than
Giving Tree
You would never
He was handcuffed
Because the officers were concerned that he was a criminal
He was acting a very unusual and erratic way
He was
Throwing his hands around indeed a district court stated from the record that he was handcuffed in part to protect him
As well as the officer
That's the VA District Court summarize the record
As indicated
They are different
Different illusions
When Justice Marshall
Said that
Suddenly
Hard adjudge
Who understood our point of view
Somebody gets it
And
All of a sudden
I felt like I was not an idiot after all
Then she put that their opinion it's written by the Chief Justice William rehnquist
And in opinion requests
Skipping a little bit
Claims that law enforcement officials have used excessive force
In the course of an arrest investigatory stop or other quote-unquote seizure
Other free citizen are most properly characterized
Is invoking the protections of the Fourth Amendment
Which guarantees citizens the right to be secure in their persons against unreasonable teachers
And must be judged
By reference to the Fourth Amendment reasonableness standard
So they get their reasonable officer standard they get it
Any get it unanimous
The nine nothing opinion
Whoa
It was a breakthrough
I don't think it'd be a stretch to say that at the time to a lot of people were concerned about
Howdy
PCS Forest
It felt like this was speaking
The new era that favored plaintiffs and claim us
Now if you were a victim of police violence
You want Justice you have this new Universal standard objective standard we no longer have
The show The Office
Is active
Maliciously or sadistically
Facts of the case
And you say what a reasonable officer do the same thing
Or not
Established like what a reason Lobster is what they would do by calling experts looking at dad about age and rank
Stranger things
What's up with that this would be
Objective
For the first time in hundreds of years maybe they would have
An objective
Standard that was a break
After winning
Did the case get kick back down to the Circuit like what happens to the thorn
Everyone in the Supreme Court
The case went back
To the trial court level for another trial
Effect of it
I'm sorry Mr Graham had another day in court another trial we picked another jewelry
That represented the better insulin reaction bottle of orange juice pulled him over unconscious and coughed
Physical education broken foot lacerations risk
Bruised forehead squad car front yard
The guy who did nothing wrong
Amazon
The case was given to the jury
Injury was told
Okay
Knowing what you now know
Take the standards reasonable standard and ask yourself
Is what happened to the store in Graham
Reasonable
The jury deliberated came back out
And I decided in favor of
The police office
Pussers Mr Graham lost
Now what do you think is real or not at the jury really focused in on the police officers
Perspective
And from the office
Protective all they saw was a black man running in and out of convenience store
They thought you might be stealing something they had no idea he was a diabetic
I'm up he was a little bit out of control car creating trouble
Aesthetic but he's drunk
Mike dangerous
Reasonable officer would subdue that person
Excuse me I'm so sorry
There goes the dog in yard
So when I got it turned green junior he was actually moving from his home in St Louis
Did Ryan I'm still open the garage up
Back to Brazil had a lot of family in Charlotte
Okay I'm on back
Hopefully I ain't cocaina
I was just wondering did your dad talked about the
About what happened that day or do you talk about the court case at all
He didn't
It wasn't something that he talked about
Different Junior says that established
I'm trying to get on with his life he started making Furniture in his spare time
Going to church a lot but
He had his he had his troubles
He had a p ends up having
A substance abuse issue
So
And what
Fortunately you you was able to overcome that and
That was after the Supreme Court case after this correct that's correct
So I mean I don't know if
His this way of trying to deal with that was
Do substance abuse
I don't know
When you are dehumanized
Like that
When when another individual
Weather today
It's you know it's kind of hard to explain math but when when someone
Who has Authority
Just eat
This is like
They is like they take something away from you
When someone does something like that to you
It strikes at your core
It strikes at your very being
And I think you lose a part of yourself
That you can't get back
Franklin senior died in the year 2000 he was 54 years old
But after his death
Is named lived on in this case
Naseberry
Weird
Way
So 2014 is tonight after an unarmed African-American teenager was shot and killed
Police in St Louis suburb of Ferguson Missouri
Not far from where does Warren G live
A white officer Darren Wilson
Shot and killed a black teenager Michael Brown a reporter from CNN contacted me
And you talk about how
They want to use my dad's
Case doing that trial
As a defense
Pretty officer
The CNN report in pharmacy
That's not what I had no idea
The grand jury deliberated over two days
Making their final decision
What equation shows the jury was
Did Officer Darren Wilson act recently
We shot Michael Brown
They determined that no probable cause exists to file any charges against officer Wilson
And returned a no true bill on each of the five and dime
That was reasonable
They killed her baby man
Object Java
Same here shot and killed by two officers while holding a pellet gun
Jimmy ryce we are instructed to ask what
Original police officer
Would do in this particular situation
Detroit found that the officer who shot and killed the 12 year old boy Tamir rice
Did recently
Ben
Eric Garner
Get another white police officer
Set an unarmed black man reasonable John Crawford on 18 year old black man killed last month
Reasonable
Samuel Dubose
Reasonable Alton Sterling
Reasonable reasonable
Oklahoma Charlotte
Philando Castile
Reasonable
Are you kidding me right now
We're not evolving as a civilization
Where did Bobby
We're going back down tonight
And in almost every one of those cases
Graham vs Connor Supreme Court decision
How many people felt was supposed to establish a new Universal standard that would deliver Justice
For victims of police violence
In almost every one of those cases it ended up doing
The exact opposite
Victims from getting relief
And instead
Protected the cops
One person my colleague who covers cops describes it as like cops cops ehat is like their first amendment
Texas break glass
How did that
And we'll watch it app
More perfect will continue in a moment
Radiolab
This is Christopher calling from South Florida Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloan
Www.slha.org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help this summer I'm hosting the show
And I request for those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
We're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments
Brilliance
Basically I want to hear about those times when I
I kid you know did something
It just means you lean back and say whoa
Maybe it was the moment that our kids you've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of their musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed are ready music in the margin of their geometry
We're interested in the
Specific moments where
A kid does something super smart but it doesn't have anything to do with the test
If you have a story please share it with us
Go to radiolab.org Brilliance and record a short audio message
And that's radiolab.org / brilliance
Thank you so much
This is more perfect I'm Jad abumrad we're featuring more perfect on Radiolab today
Me to say a few words for contact police officers have dangerous
I think we can all agree and on occasion they do have to use Force
And we should say that the majority of the people who are killed by police every year are white
But if you look at the number of black people were killed and you balance that against
Fact that black people only make up about 12
70 overall
Population
What you end up with
Is that an unarmed black man is
Roughly about seven times more likely
To be
Killed by police in an unarmed white man.
Escorting once
Add these numbers
Are very disputed and argued about but what is clear
Is most police officers who use deadly force or never charged in the even smaller percentage serve jail time
So mad
Yeah actually let me just ask
All the cases we heard about before the break that Litany of case
For the past few years in every single one of those
The jury was asked did this officer behave like a reasonable officer should
And every single one the jury said yes
Yeah yeah
Why
Well that's is because
The reasonable officer standard like from from the moment that it was created
I was actually kind of a word constrained
In a few very important ways
I have here the
The jury instructions from the 9th circuit
And this is what dreams members are
I told to think about when they have to assess this kind of use of force
Geraci told this is your job
Go to the bank at 8 Primetime Kelly Prime
Yeah it says
Under the Fourth Amendment a police officer may use only such Force as objectively reasonable you must judge the
The reasonableness of a particular use of force from
The perspective of a reasonable officer on the scene
And not with 20/20 vision of hindsight
Those those are a couple really crucial
Phrases with
Perspective
Of
An officer on the scene so you have to look at it through the eyes of the officer on the scene and then
You can't look at it through the 20/20 vision of hindsight
Put yourself in the shoes an officer in the moment and look at the world through their eyes and and that's how you have to understand these things
Where did that where does where did that idea come from to that
Comes from Graham the guy comes from the Chief Justice
William rehnquist
Pinyin
Which
Tiebreaker
The reason why this particular use of force must be judged
From the perspective of a reasonable officer
On the scene rather than with the
The 20/20 vision of hindsight
AP Calculus must embody in allowance for the fact in This Is Us
Swimming party
The police officers are often forced to make split-second decisions
About the amount of force necessary in a particular situation
It so as you can see this this idea of reasonableness is
Circumscribed
Fairy-type Eevee
By time
It's not asking like what a regional officer would do
Herein in general
During a moment where
Where they have to use Force
Instead
What is asking is what would a reasonable officer do in this split
Second
In his little tiny sliver of time where the force
Actually occurred
In fact that moment legally has come to be known
As a superseding event
Meaning what what does it mean meaning
Meaning that that that moment
That superseding event it is essentially it breaks
The
Chain of causation
So if you think of times just this like Continuous Flow this is like no
You break that
You stop that and you take this one little moment you pluck it out
And you like this moment this is the one moment that you look at
That's all they can think
Read it and it turns out if you ask
A jury
The question
About you Sephora
That way
About this one little moment
The Graham standard many people saw it
I'm in Hope wood would help victims of police violence
Does the exact opposite
One person might my colleague who covers cops describes it as like cops
Kopsia dislike their first amendment they just think of it like as a shield
Yeah
Okay so this is NPR reporter Kelly mcevers host
Embedded
Podcast
And
All Things Considered
He's actually as she's cover police shooting to the Past
Year for NPR and we started comparing notes with her as we been producing our story
LOL back
As she sent us an email
That most people don't get to see
Assertive
See how cops
Are actually trained
To understand grammar
Do you want in
Timberlake
Okay
So I went to
For this
Today
Training course
Called
Street survival is in a hotel Ballroom one of those hotel conference and how many people do you
Remember
Is somewhere just under 200
Cops
Lots of really jacked dudes with cats
Mostly there was some sergeants and lieutenants rookies right out of the academy submit to your guys from all over Ohio
Ohio Pennsylvania labor. Super happy about
Angry stares in the beginning there's just like a lot of side eye
Good morning Cleveland
How's everybody doing
How many of you have been to a caliber press
Place your hands
That's why you never been here before
ProPress class
Oh wow
Json whole thing is put on by this company called Calibre press
It's actually been around for a really long time and they teach classes
Questions are in the police departments are they out from all across the country in this particular one
I want to talk a lot about stress
Survival in
The general idea is
How to survive and Blake make it to retirement
Emotional health
Suicide
You know how to basically do this job and
7 survival
And live
Living
And lastly
25/30
They talk a lot about self-care
About sleep and exercise
Crab your
Making sure that your spouse in your family like understand the stress of your job and they talked about going to therapy I mean it's like
Wow there's times when it's this really
Touchy-feely kind of thing
Overwhelmed
Happening
There's demonology says when a lobster got up
Let's talk about contemplating suicide
Starting secluding myself
I started alienating myself
F****** hating everybody
Everyone
Play crying so I mean it's a really intense
Couple of days
But for our purposes the reason we were there the reason we're excited for Kelly be there
Is it a big chunk of the class
Let's talk about the
Is devoted to gram
Ugly uses Force
But if you stop
How to understand Grand and and how it impacts their life
By the way this is the instructor that like Granite structure his name is Jim Glennon he himself was a cop for years and years and years
Charging ports for 18-year outside of Chicago
I tell you what we talked about a bramber Connor and rru
On a regular basis
4 *
Red
What I would do is show a video and then let's talk about brandriff
Video so
Find a projector
It is really interesting to see these videos from their perspective
Video of a
September 2015 guy named Freddy centeno
Freddy centeno has gone to a woman's house
Like a woman's front door
And threatened her and said he has a gun in the cops pull up the other car there's like 20 feet away from centeno who's walking
On the sidewalk
10 shots
7 mm head
I translate the white one
Jim's claims it happens in 1.5 6 6
2nd Swing
Clips that Jim shows the lawyer for Freddy Santana's family
Is BAC just like
Atrocity
Like this was an atrocity nothing about this use of force should be considered reasonable
Because the cops in the situation they rolled right up on Freddy centeno they didn't create any space didn't give Freddy centeno anytime
Get on the ground
Do you have a chance to get on the phone
One second before the fire
And the video shows the officers did not get a chance to respond to their commands
Search employees all these reactions
And then
Play the original body cam video again
See Freddy centeno they tell him to get on the ground he doesn't
An engine slows the video down
As you can see Santa's right hand
Reaches into his pocket
Composite
Things like take a look at this right
Here
Annapolis green gym has it
Frozen moment where you can see that Freddy symptom of hand and started to move
The movie
Just starting to come up out of his pocket that's moment from the pocket to the out of the pocket this to Jim was the
Moment
Seems like this is the only moment that matters like forget what happened before forget that the officers rolled right up on centeno forget that they weren't giving too much time
Space
This moment
Right here
Start pulling his hand out of his pocket this is the moment where you ask the question what would a reasonable offer
Street view
Right now
This man appears to be pulling out
Bach I can't tell what it is you probably can't even without outside in
Turns out he had a a nozzle from a garden hose
What was the
Malaga
However you see this
Start moving up or down
He doesn't go to the ground
Pull something out
They think it's a gun any reasonable person
And so
Is this work under gram
It's sad that but
Yes
I believe
For him he's just like over and over and over stress is
What would a reasonable police officer do
In that moment
What was the
Text about rehnquist in the decision is like what rank was said is
Split Second
Circumstance
Certain rapidly-evolving about the amount of forces necessary
This is fast
Dynamic it's nothing like television there's no five cameras on it there's no change in the music there's no upswell in the music
It's fast and the court recognizes
Albuquerque
Chase plays another example this one of the guy
Like I've police officer shot because they thought he had a gun and a knife but the cops got in Call of Duty had a gun and
In the split second he raised his arm like he was raising a gun
Another one
Chanel video of a police officer shooting an unarmed white man in head and again walkthrough beat by beat
City-Data look at just a moment forget everything else
And what you realize if you do that
Did you force someone to agree to look at
Just that one moment forgetting everything else just look at this one
Slice Through The Eyes of an officer
Pinhole contact
What is reasonable
Ships
The only real question you can ask when the moment is so confined is
Did the officer feels
Lake was the fear that that officer had a reasonable fear in that moment
That is a very different standard than what
Woody and Jerry in the thorn Graham that intended
Yeah
So
Tele exitos
Story that you reported for podcast embedded
Alexi gets at some of the stuff
In this particular case who was Jennifer Lynn what happened
Jonathan Ferrell
The football player
From Florida
Yes he looks like a football player
So this was September of 2013 John Farrell is living in Charlotte North Carolina's black man 24 years old
And one night it was a Friday night
He goes out with some friends goes out to a bar
Has a couple drinks makes his way home exactly know what happened
But well John the bear was making his way back home at some point his
Car with lost control of his car crash in the woods office Road in Suburban Charlotte he didn't have his phone
Buddy's in like this little Suburban neighborhood so he gets out of his car to the house of this woman is knocking on her door
Woman psychiatrist a white woman new mom she comes to the door thinking it's her husband who works nights
So she's come to the door and she's like about to let him in and then she's like well wait a second who's the person who opens the doors he chosen Ferrell
Delinquent
She calls 911
Car Alarm Systems going off and you can hear
John girl screaming turn off the alarm turn off the alarm in the background and you can hear him in the 911 tape you can like hear it
Banging on the door
I don't know what to do okay I'm right here
Pressure on our way okay
Now we don't know why John Farrell was banging on the door but
Very possible
They likely it was just because he wrecked his car and need some help
So they called
Thinking that they are going to the scene of a breaking and entering
Music asking video from the squad car 20 officers they've gotten a description it's an African American man with green shirt and light pay
Since officers driving down this road driving driving driving until finally you see
Connect man's green shirt and white pants walking on the side of the road
Walking towards the squad cars you see the red light of a taser on his chest
And then
Take off one of your officers is yelling at me get on the ground. Keeps running runs off camera
If you have sex with them
Running upstairs fire 12 shots
Heavenstrike John Farrell
Foster ground
Bumbu
Any dyes
Or that here's a guy who was unarmed who did nothing wrong
And he was killed
Like plain and simple if you
You asked was that reasonable on some basic level
No
It was not reasonable this man
Should not have died
What in the trial this case did go to a trial jury trial
The jury was instructed forget everything but that moment of force
Looks like no 20-20 hindsight look at just a superseding moment
And then ask the question again
Was it reasonable for the officer to pull the trigger
Ie
Was it reasonable for that officer to be afraid
And the officer who shot and killed Jonathan Ferrell
Who's facing charges his name is Randall Kerrick
You've been tried for voluntary manslaughter
Begin aggressively coming towards me
Entering courses triops
The character cast and could you tell the jury about
What pace he was coming at you
At first it was a pretty rapid pace
More and more of a fast walk
I gave loud verbal commands
Stream stop and get on the ground
How loud are your verbal commands
Very loud
Tell me how loud you were yelling to the suspect and what you were yelling to the suspect
So
He says he was running at him
Misses a huge question
Was he running Adam
Really running away from
I tried to run past them by him yeah
Like if you sort of diagram the whole thing out the way the cop cars were
Parks and Rec characters
Standing
It is possible
The Jonathan fair was trying to start a run between the mall at the prosecution masane defense was like no no no he was running at the
The cops didn't suspect
Say anything
Nasir
Why did you interpret his
Body language to me
He's going to attack me
He's going to assault me he's going to take my gun from me
Did you have time to holster your weapon
No sir
And here I was
Suspect match the description
He just ran through a taser
Which at the time I thought was
Had that work
I thought the taser had struck
Make contact
I had absolutely no idea if he had a weapon on him or not
And
What's the average dick was the suspect ever still
No sir
Did he continue to advance on you
Yes sir
No matter what I did he wouldn't stop
I wasn't sure how many rounds I had fired none of them affected him and anyway anyway I didn't think my gun was working
I thought I was going to die
There's nothing I would do to stop it
What was the reason that you continue to fire your weapon
Because he wouldn't stop
People trying to get to my gun
Toilet down the question was
Was it reasonable for officer character
Feel afraid
And after 11 days of testimony the question was put to the jury
There were six opinions one way there were six another
Text to sex
On one side a white guy named Bruce Raffi
And we were sitting in that dreary
Deliberation room has no bigger than this living room
Okay
And
It's hot
We're arguing where it's
It's it's going nowhere
And so the more it went on this went on for days
And he started the leading the charge on that we have to acquit carrack
Felted officer care can it be right to be afraid
And he told Kelly that Jonathan Ferrell the guy that shot so what Bruce Rafi sang to me like you know he was a young man
Disheveled confused
Angry
If you will be made a very aggressive move towards police officer
After disobeying commands
How many choices in this video
And it was clear from the very first time I viewed it
Stop sit down
Put your hands up
Do any of those things
Other than what you chose to do which was Ted charged
Lobster care
And told that there's no other way around what I saw
And then I kept coming back to that
And this is exactly how the defense painted it right this case is not about race
Viskase
Is about choices
And that's stuck in grease trap he's mine so that when he was asked was it reasonable for character shoot him
Johnsonville made all these bad choice
This is an old trick
From from
From my defense attorneys
Kelly spoke to Moses Wilson and African-American man he wasn't supposed to be
He might have had a few drinks where he was
The police responded to what he calls
This was early in the morning
This was far from where he lived
This was this
This was that
Which caused me
At the end
To write on the board
Just what did he do
To deserve to be shot so many times
Mystery Room
In the Jury Room
I wrote this on the board
What did he
Do
What's the what happens with the jury
Split
Bunch of Italians eat to quit Ford convicted
8 jurors most of them Wayside with
Quitting Cara
And for jurors most of them people of color
Side with Conviction characters
Breaking news
In the trial of Officer Randall Kerrick the judge
Has just declared a mistrial
2015 St Charlotte settle the lawsuit which on the Pharaohs family
2.25 million dollars
Roulette same here optic Eric resign from the Charlotte
Police Department
The city paid out $179,989.59
The money was
Backpage hair accessories
Security and retirement
An attorney representing them in a separate civil suit
There's something interesting about
Listening to Moses talk just what did he do
To deserve to be shot so many times it feels like
This time
Fourth Amendment reasonableness
Standard this reasonable officer
Standard like what
Understand is that it was an attempt to really
Look at these situations these shootings
Uses of force cases
Through this sort of objective lens where you're just looking at all the fat guy on the ground
And yet
Kisses don't seem to be tied it like any sort of objectivity or you're like oh that's actually like
That feels like a pier sort of objectivity
Like what what what has this guy done yet
Actually done any
He ran it a buddy
Maybe
But that was
It
And
Like if you're white
Are you more likely to say yes that was reasonable because he's white and he was afraid of a black man
Like that is the question
Given the history of our country I'd say many cases that's not even a
Thanks question I'm actually left with is
If this is where the reasonableness standard is
Is lettuce
Is there another standard
I think that's right
This is what he can at again he represented the thorn Graham in that original case
When You See It applied you wonder
Whether or not this is the best and her there might be something better
I just don't have an answer to that
I would I would suggest the whole more radical
Is Elie mystal more perfect legal editor we ended up talking with him about this
Shortly after
The philando Castile verdict came out so he was
Well that was a tough pill for him and many people swallow I would suggest that they have to be
The cops have to be right in fact
Which is something we usually do not apply for what does that mean like it from in the scenario of a police person woo-hoos
Is that mean like I need to be right that you don't have a toy gun that that's to me
So if you shoot me because you think I have a gun I had best have a
And if I don't have a gun your ass is going to jail
Cuz you were wrong
I don't care if you only thought so
If I was telling you had a gun
If I if you are not
Write in
Back then you
Have to go to jail
I think that is that would be a standard
Sterile hours to process
Cute Beast Boy
Cinepolis person's going to just going to argue that like you don't understand the pressures that are under it's a Split Second
Decision
Monday morning quarterbacking if you
You do what you just said we're not going to be able to do our jobs
I'm sick of you
I would say screw you if you have had your chance
You had your chance
To police my community
Without murdering us
And you have failed for 300 years
That's what I was saying
More people might get hurt if I wasn't
I'm willing to risk that
I'm willing to try it that way then
I'd rather I'd rather
Illegal shoplifting people
Go free
Then one
Illegal shoplifting person gets shot in the street like an animal
Kesha
If you want to talk about changing the standards that is a standard change
Now that is a zelle said
Radical
Probably not real
Given that most Americans according to polls
Respectively
I have confidence in the please proceed please to be the enforcers
HIPAA law
But
There are other ideas
Out there they're starting
Bubble up
And it was constraining us if what's keeping us
Stuck where we are are the words of Graham
Then what offers does a way out
Could actually
Also be hiding in there
What do you mean
Okay so you know how
Chief justice rehnquist when he wrote the decision in 89
He put in all these phrases that took the idea of a regional officer and unconstrained it right
These were like
Constraint only two
This little moment in time it's been trained to the perspective of the officers or constrained that there's no 20-20 hindsight
All that stuff
What in the decision he also he's slipped in this other phrase
He's actually calling back to an earlier decision
And what he wrote was
The question is whether the totality of circumstances justifies a particular sort of seizure
Totality of circumstance
Totality of circumstances which seems to be at odds with all of the other stuff
Right which is all about like little slivers and moment
Suggesting that this is like this is the whole thing
Both both ideas and their wants yet which is why right now you see the lower courts are arguing
About what this phrase actually means until half of the circuits are saying kind of like everything that we've already talked about witches
Is that all the totality circumstances means is that
You look at everything to answer the question was the officer's scared you look at everything that the officer would have known
Known everything the officer would have seen received and then you ask okay knowing all that was a reason for the awesome music
In the moment
The other half of the circuit a
Natalia circumstances
Isn't just about what the officer knew what the officer
I saw and how it answers the moment
Fatality means like totality
Like what did the officer
Do
Leading up to the mall
Did the officer
Try to get a search warrant to the officer try to deescalate the situation before
Are using voice to be officer try to subdue the person before using deadly force it's only all those things that usual
Out of the frame
Maybe
Can be let back in
Supreme Court so far has shown no interest in ruling on this in trying to sort this out
But they might
Because the argument is happening in the lower courts
So in a way we're kind of living at a time very much like 1984 when does Lauren Graham.
Pulled over outside of convenience store in Charlotte
Waiting to see whether it matters that the thorn Graham
Wasn't trying to steal anything
Maybe just a diabetic
Chinese Mauritius
Did what happened your dad affect how you
Thought of
Police how you spell police
Bean bean black man
Well
You don't believe it or not
It didn't
What's up
I like the base my
Opinions based on my own
Experiences
My dad
I can say this Kelly
Matt
I can remember my dad telling me
Stories of
Where he grew up in eastern North Carolina
On a tobacco farm
In that small town
I can remember him telling me a story of
A black man
Who have been accused
Being inappropriate with a white woman
And how the white
Got him in broad daylight
Castrated him in broad daylight
And I say that
In saying that
Although he experienced all that stuff growing up
And the racism that he experienced growing up
He didn't teach that to us
He didn't teach that has he told us
To love people
People
So
Even now my
Cell
I base my experience of a person
I base my experience of the
The police
Based on my dealings with
In and not that I want
But I have yet
To encounter
A police officer who's been mean to me who's been rude to me
Who's mistreated me
And that's the God's honest truth
Without a button in being completely honest
When I see you on the news
Like a kid in the 12 year old in
It had to be begun
Raci
Examples like this
That
That that does affect mean that does
Make me does that make you think of your own children if you talk to your own tears
Course I've got a twelve-year-old home
He's got BB guns that look just like real guns
And you know what he he knows that
Hey
They don't leave the house
What's it what's your twelve-year-old name
My son's name is Tanner
Tanner
And when you when you talk to Tanner about
The fact that like the BB gun doesn't leave the house I mean what is that conversation
Tamir rice when he was shot
Concealed when the new story came on by pause it and cuz you need to do with live TV now
Say come here
Why don't you watch this
Right now tan is 12 years old he's
Cuties this is that
But the fact of the matter is
In a few
Few short years
He would be considered a black man
Unfortunately
He's going to have
Target online
Himself
So
St. Louis BB guns you got see this is why you can't take these
Out of the house I don't want you
You take these on the house
Even if you're outside in the yard playing
In a police should happen to come down the road at 8
Drop it
Drop it immediately
This story was produced
Reported by Matt kielty
The Pegasus from
Go get yours Kelly Prime
Weather objecting to analyze my behavior
Definitely check out
The other more perfect episodes that are many more at radiolab.org more perfect or search
Search for more perfect wherever you get your podcast
Deathly check it out spread the word
More perfect is produced by me Jad appenrod Susie lechtenberg Jenny Lawton Julia Longoria and Kelly Prime
Alex overington and sarkari
Battalion install Cristian farias
Linda hirshman David Gable
Michelle Harris
Production support this week from Derek Don and Dylan key
Thanks to Kelly mcevers and Tom Dreisbach from NPR's embedded
Eddie montgomery at the Tampa Bay Times
Frank Aycock Leonard Feldman
Cynthia Lee and Joshua rosenkranz
Supreme Court audio is from Olla
A free law project in collaboration with the Legal Information Institute
At Cornell leadership support from our perfect is provided by the Joyce Foundation
Additional funding is provided by the Charles Evans Hughes Memorial Foundation
Do you think that would be reached