Are you weightless
Radio WNYC
And NPR
The word hit us
Like your hit with a
With a bullet
I would like that cannot be argued that cannot be our sun
On Chatham Road by Robert krulwich Radiolab in our story today begins
With a boy
That boy
It's going to vanish not Into Thin Air but to a place that we know very little about
And if you're the parent of that boy
What do you do if your child is
Falling away from everything you know how do you find him
How to get him back
So part of this time we got from Ron Susskind new wonderful book life animated some of you may have heard it some not
Let's start where we run start
Began
Around 1993
And it was an exciting time
Well we're going into Cohen's room
For what is his last
Night
In the crib
ISO Canon
You still can't watch it
Can you tell us about your crib own
Do you like your crib
Yeah
Do you know where you're sleeping tomorrow
What kind of feather you and Walter going to sleep
In 1993 the Susskind family decides to make a big move Ron and his wife Cornelia
Kinder Tucson's Walton Owen wolter is about 5 and Owen is about 2 and 1/2
If we decide to relocate from Boston to Washington DC
You know I had to senior National Affairs job at the journal
Good night
Say nighty-night
The dream job
I love you
Lots of excitement have a nice last night
So they make the move and as soon as they arrive in washing
We start sort of noticing something
I miss
Their youngest son Owen who
That point in a totally normal chatty almost three year-old hitting always
Markers suddenly goes sideways
Maybe the
Very first thing that happened was he stopped sleeping
He stopped sleeping stopped eating
It was very fussy and it's got to be the move
And then we start losing eye contact
Then he starts losing motor skills
He can't hold his cup
Slipping out of his hand his gate became very odd
And he was sort of
Look like a drunken sailor walking around the house
And then he stopped speaking bit
Pipette
I bet this is all compressed into a few months
Could have banged his head
Ingested something toxic
UniFirst you hit the regular pediatrician and he's gone
Descendants 2 Center
It was a woman there
Who sits them down and she says the word autism
The word of the word mean to you at that moment
It meant rain man just I mean I'm a very good driver
We saw
Thyroid that cannot be art
That cannot
Our son
Yeah it was just terrifying
Now in reporting the story we ended up going off in a variety of different directions but we did visit one place
We got a glimpse
Just a hint
What parents like rotten Cornelia must have felt
We visited the school here in Manhattan called the Rebecca school it's a
Really unique
School for children with autism other
Developmental delay there's little kids in their age for all the way up to 21 every kid
Did you meet in the school is differ
Autism is a mini mini flavored
But the overwhelming sense you get Walking The Halls there is
But each of these
Kids is
China
Locked away live
Just that they don't know how to be with
Like Kelsey pageant I we got there during lunch
Hey one of the rooms I don't know who you should describe that we went to this one classroom
This one boy who really stood out he's about six years old and he had this big mop of black hair
Care and he was just standing there at the table holding
Snapple
Apple
Do you want to eat
And just
Hobby
And the director of the school team court she was there and she just stayed with the boy and really like try to be there
Are with him but
There was nothing she could do
San Jose Apple
It was
Hard to watch
Because
You don't know how to
Help him
So that's the challenge
There's a kid who'd actually can't tell you what's upsetting to write that's Gil Tippy the school
Is clinical
Could be that he physically he actually doesn't know where he is in space maybe it's as if we were being
Thrown out of an airplane but you just tumbling you don't know where your body is it's a thunderstorm
So you only see things in flashes right so now the world is totally frightening totally out
I mean I do remember the drive home
From that on that terrible day
We'll just I mean I just remember
You know you and I driving home in Silence with Owen in the back
And
I just felt like
Do you know
There was no
There's no hope
Like they had no idea if the Owen they knew was in there
Or if he was just
Kind of lost it
Gone
But keep in mind this is 1994 we knew even less about autism than we know now we still have no idea what causes.
But then
The prevailing wisdom seemed to be the kids with autism they couldn't feel emotion
And no capacity to empathize with other people this is way before the neurodiversity movie
Actually right around the moment when autism was becoming a spectre
For the first time
That's happening and they
Forward to starting
Barely started the point Owen was
Before
Was he active or was he is very he was hyperactive
A lot of self stimulatory Behavior you know hand-flapping running around and Cornelia
When they would call him
It was as if he didn't even hear the
We're hoping he's hearing
You know it but he's not really responding to you needed them to come to the table or basically have to go
Oh and leading by the hand or pick him up and bring him over
And
He was down to one word which was juice
So the only thing he was doing was drinking juice for about a year and also you know there was the Disney movies
But he would sit for he would sit for in for television entertainment
He wouldn't sit for the whole movie for sure but he would
That would be the one thing that he would sit
For quietly
Her.
You don't know
Because he didn't sleep so at night
I was usually up with him
All night thrashing around
Azan watch one Disney movie after another after another not sleeping at all that word
Juice it seems
Span just a little bit he began to repeat the words you survive
LG service
Weight loss
Juicervose
To serve house but you don't know what first what that it all now we think it's juice Cornelius like I said does he seem to want more juice
He's like no I gave him more juicy this evening
Aaron says he would say that word over and over for weeks and I had no idea what it meant
Until
It's about a year and a month after the symptoms have started
One night all four of them are together in living room
And we're watching The Little Mermaid
And a certain point Owen who's got the remote
Starts
Remaining the movie back
To rewatch a scene typical so I wouldn't know how to work the remote
Kind of showed him how to do it
He took to that
And
He's rewinding the part where Ariel or protagonist
Father's Day
Wants to become human to get her man Eric Ursula
Says it will it will cost you on The Price is Right
Your voice
My voice
You got it sweet cakes
NFL sudden Ariel and Ursula are having it out
And this parquetry lamp again
Again
Call David Owen stoprewind you just play them
But after the third rewind
Cradily set
It's not juice
Massachusetts just
I said what just your voice at which point I'm like
Gravel my God
Add Walters like jumping in the bed
Crying and laughing and jumping as a Bailey Chair that phrase for a reason
That's a weed
That's of course immediately what we thought he's trying to tell us something like he has things to say
But he
You just can't say it's his voice
Another words he's in there he's in there because he's trying to talk to us so we run to the doctor
The very trusted guy and he's like
Sit down with stalking
His son called echolalia
Tackling sound
That their auditory processing
Their ability to process sound speech goes Haywire
And so
They just repeat
The sound
And wishing so he doesn't know what it means
And he's like probably not
Echolalia
It's what it sounds like Echo what it sounds like Echo
I said like a
Parrot
Do you like you
So we go from Helen Keller to the pet store parrot
Life Goes On
End
Years go by Breeze murmuring a lot of
Gibberish
We might be able to decipher from some movie
Maybe
By 6 he's got you know
3 word sentences I want juice
Just seen a one-and-a-half-year-old speech
Coins are full-time 24/7 Ron's working around the clock in a kind of
Frenzy paper all the therapist and we're fighting it out
Basically
Desi tiny tiny bits
The progress
But no more breaks
Until on that six and a half
Anawalt
Is 9
And
Want to get a little emotional on his 9th birthday
I'm not sure maybe the anxiety of the
Moment
Attention of it this is Walter Scott
And how old are you now I'm 25 your voice is so much deeper than I imagined it would be
People usually after like 10 minutes
Cuz their first time meeting me a sandwich
Taking my voice and I have to share them
Does not affect
Erika Schwartz has his 9th birthday
His friends come over then
After the party he's out in the hammock in the yard and he's
Kind of crying a little bit
Birthday is it was
Are they were just kind of strange days for me
Like sensory overload in a way well Owen walks in after Walter
This emotional
And we're in the kitchen and he
Seems to kind of look back and forth between the two of us
In like you there's something he wants to say
To this point on it only said three words set
But in this moment
According to Rogers
He looks at us and says
Walter doesn't
Want to grow up like Mowgli or a Peter Pan
Simple sentence
Colton Colton
Wow
I'm literally was like a thunderbolt a lightning bolt went through the kitchen
And I want goes runs off in some you know where every whatever and we look at each other and
Like what that was that
This is his first complex sentence or thought that's been expressed and it's a subtle one actually
Could you taking three different character two from the movie one from real life and he
Putting them together
Ron Isley
I got to follow this so he goes up to Owen's room
And I see Owen on the bed
Looking at a Disney book
And I see on the carpet
Are some of his puppets
And
In one of them is Yago
From
From Aladdin
The plush toy you know which is the $98 one that goes up to your elbow
And I grabbed it and I put it on
On my arm right up to the Elbow
And I crawl along in the rug
And I throw the bedspread kind of over my head
Edge up to the edge of the bed and I push the puppet up through the crease in the bedspread
And so now they're face-to-face
Bowen and yoga
And I'm looking up to the crease
My arm
And I
Talk to him as Yahoo
Now this is an easy voice is Gilbert Godfrey voice I mean anyone can do this I say don't always always
How does it feel
Beat you
And he turns
To the puppet
Like he's a bumping into an old friend
And he says Nah Nah.
Good I'm lonely
And it was his voice
Wow
And so white
Sato when did when did you and I become such good friends
And he says when I watched Aladdin and you made me laugh
And we go back and forth like this 445 Morris
Exchanges
And then you're always clears throat
Play card
Like that and then all the sudden I hear him say back
I Love The Way You Lie
Foul little mind works
Is it what
I love the way your foul little mind works
That's too far the villain
Yaga's the villainous sidekicks
Jafar the villain of Aladdin
That's if that's the next line from Jafar you please anywhere in the movie you ain't asking for me to respond
As y'all go
Did you know the next time I didn't know the next line at that point I just jumped out from under the bed
Nelly Hot Like A
He he is pissed in there and despite everything that they have been told about autism Owen was in there
And somehow these Disney characters were in there
With him it doesn't take as long that
You know we start we called the basement sessions where we
Say let's see how far this can go couple times a week we go down in the basement and start playing at scenes
And we do it the first time we do it with the Jungle Book which is a movie he was in two at that point then
101 Dalmatians Beauty and the Beast Peter Pan
Turn to Stone
We we kind of ran the gamut I mean pretty much weed watching
I mean every Disney
What describe these guys what was it like
When Mom and I started doing voice of Little Walter
Spell amazed
Zelda maze
Who who was amazed you were amazed with a ride was amazed
This is Owens
He's 23 now why were you amazed I was so surprised
By my family
I could hear them respond better
You're saying that when when everybody was acting out the Disney movies
Only you could
Hear them better
Right
So when people when talk to you not in the Disney
Do what do you remember about how they sounded
A little weird
Yeah
Gibberish and rubbish
Do you remember how you felt
A little worried
You told Mom wants that you were scared I was scared
Why did it feel good to watch them over and over again that you kept wanting to
Watch them over and over again how did that feel
Silk comforter
Comforting
Spell comforting
Why
Cuz it would help me with
Reducing my autism
How does a movie
Help a boy
Knowing
Stay tuned and we'll will attempt some explanations
This is Candice currently calling from her bicycle
Baby Alive is supported in part by the National Science Foundation and by Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of science
And technology in the modern world
More information about Sloan at www.slha.org thank you
I hate everybody Pat Walters here I'm a producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help this summer I'm hosting
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
About what we're calling tiny moments of Brilliance basically I want to hear about those times when
So did something
It just means you lean back and say whoa how did they do that maybe it was the moment that I can
Kids you've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons and you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed they're ready music in the margin of their geometry homework we're interested in the
Epic moments where a kid does something super smart but doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story please share it with us
Go to radiolab.org brilliance
Record a short audio message for us
And that's radiolab.org slash Brilliance thank you so much
Hey I'm Jared album run Robert krulwich Radiolab in today's story about a kid named Owen and a condition that no
No one can quite pin down
Now we just heard
That Owen
When he watches
Disney movies he feels comforted and that somehow
The movie seems to dial down his Auto
Really why would that be
How can a Disney movie
Make that much difference
I'm can you hear me okay I can read pretty well we ended up taking the question to this guy
He's a leading researcher in autism
And yes he is the cousin of this guy is my wife
And I'm the director of the autism research Centre at Cambridge University
A couple of different thing first of all
He says that in the last few decades are whole notion of what is happening in the mind of a child with autism has totally
We sort of tossed out the Rainman idea the idea that people with Autism lack
Some in our life
I think that's completely false
It's not necessarily the can't feel emotion or empathy and says not at all it's often a decoding prop
Like they have trouble decoding all of the information is coming in I mean some Studies have found it
A lot of kids with autism
Literally have too many synapses
And their brain so it might be
The world is just coming into loud
I think often people with Autism you feel I have very lost and confused
Desaster little predictability in the social world
And if people come and go they got no two days are the same people say things unexpected
Levi do things unexpectedly I'm people with oil system seem to need
Weather predictability
We spoke to Temple Grandin the well-known author and
Autism advocate
Here's how she play
Got a little kid I want to feel the nice feeling being held but there was just too much overwhelming stimulation
No loud sounds hurt my ears
Like the volume control on touch and hearing
Was Wei Wei Wei
Return. And one of the reasons why I withdrew into things like dribbling sand to my hands
Is a cushion shot out
The hurtful sound
As a Temple Grandin explain it to us a kid with autism gravitating to something like bus schedules or
Knowing every single a fact about every dinosaur that ever lived that is just a way
Slow things down
And make the world predictable
Happens the same way every time it is
Simon baron-cohen puts it in Owens case
He had these Disney movie that you can play over and over and over and over the fact that it
Are insides not just repetition but it's repetition about human action
Where are you out in the Menagerie
And that creates a kind of structure to be able to look at human behavior and in the real way
World has no opportunity to rewind the movie
Where is in the world of movies you can watch the same Disney cartoon a hundred times Arthur
Thousand times when you could pull my sky frame by frame like a literary critic
Horror film critic you can really analyze the action to understand okay that's what happened.
What caused him to do what he did
Add to that
The element of Music we spoke with a
Geraldine Dawson Neuroscience Professor Duke guess that maybe it's not just the repetition that made the difference but the repetition
With music one of the things that we've learned from Neuroscience is that music
Nick activate
Emotional centers in our brain and in fact
It's pretty reliable that certain kinds of music make us feel
Frightens make us feel
Happy make us feel worried and so forth
It's a done brain scans of kids with autism
They found
That during kind of normal interactions people with Autism don't necessarily activate those emotional
Centers of the brain areas like the amygdala but during the experience of music
The those areas of the brain did become activated in a way that was
Very much like a typical person
So it might be that while Owen was sorta forensically examining these moments of Disney movies
Who's the Disney music
That was binding those moments
Feelings
So you know like when a person looks like that that's when they're happy when a person looks like that
That's when they're sad
However works Simon baron-cohen thinks it's at least plausible
That is using the movie The scaffold to make sense of the month graczyk
Complexity of natural life
And that's what got the runs
Play this is a whole new planet hearing that maybe this
Disney ish therapy that they use without on
Might be a whole new approach to treating kids with autism instead of the one-size-fits-all model of sit in the class
I hear the things you're supposed to know
To be a working member of society and said it's like go with their passion
Follow them in there
It's it's a pathway the brain finding away
To get to what people need which is
Interaction and emotional wholeness
I want to sing the song for them
Seaweed is always greener
It's a buddy assist Lake
Eugene Public School wake up their product has a big Miss steak
Does Ducati
Who are the ears sometimes down in the basement with the family or sometimes even in doctor's office is Owen started
Improvise
Keep go off script
And use the characters you knew so well to explain
How he was feeling under the sea
Dollies with the dog bed is way to take you from me
And I were thinking about all this
And asking ourselves if this works with Disney movies
Put your very emotional in
Fear
What are you how you do this with paper clips
Bus schedule
Questions kept coming
We ran into inevitably
Counter-reaction
Gerunds
This we didn't expect
Story
It's great it it's a wonderful story
But the fact is most I mean wanted
The danger with a with a book
With any book including life animated is that is going to
Give the impression to a lot of people that this is the answer
That psychologists and journalist David Rico he warned us that like with autism we still don't really know
And we don't have yet and a body of establish science and Aliana cook your hearing
They're just attic.
If you known
One person with autism you've known one person with autism
Daddy says it's really all you can say and to take one person's experience and generalized on it
It's a mistake
Vacation point is sunburned when is turning 21 years old today oh my God happy birthday to him
Sendai
Ben is never going to be able to live independently he's never going to have what anyone considered would consider a
Grateful in normal life
Ben has severe autism and is now living in an assisted living
He was diagnosed around the same age is Owen
Same basic symptoms of lack of eye contact suddenly
Speech fascination with spinning wheels with ceiling fans the whole the whole package
Dave says he and his wife tried every therapy they can afford
What they couldn't
But then never had any of those big breakthroughs
He said he was a teenager
Cherrywood hit any wood scratch new wood bite me with
Continue with Kik honestly I was always afraid one Karen and I would end up having to go to the emergency room for some reason that
If they saw her arms that they would arrest me because I would think I was
Some horribly abusive person because her arms were nothing
They were covered with
With scabs and scars and scars on scars and on top of that
You know there be the crap
Play like he was not
Well
I hate to say it but here we are in his 21st birthday and he's still not 100% reliable when it comes to
Honestly the reason we ended up calling David's because he wrote a review of Ron's book where he said basically the Great Book
But it's just one more story of a triumphant
Happy ending in that is not the norm for many many people who experience autism
You don't have happy endings
I mean that's that's a sad fact for many of these families
And we're not expecting in our life
A happy ending for Ben
Sheeple
Seem to believe
That
That it's dangerous for parents to have too much hope
Because what if
They really think it's possible for their child
Progressive huge amount will recover and then their child doesn't
We have the other concerned that's Ron Kaufman of the autism Treatment Center
Great America we find that we're not afraid of so-called false hope
We're more concerned about fall specimen
And here's what he says.
In 1981 Randstad
Barry
And on over with tips down on a local TV show with a very young Oprah Winfrey
How do you describe suzhou
Okay we had a child who is diagnosed as unsure of the ill or hopelessly L something
Gold watches
He tells how it a really young age a year-and-a-half older son
Began to regress
Dentist
Clap hands
Lose I contact Rock back and forth and then one day
His wife decided you know what we're going to just sit down on the bathroom floor right next to him and we're going to rock back in
Imports just like
He explains that they did this
Over
Over and over hour after hour to one day
His son turned his head
And he actually looked
At us
It took 900 hours before
He ever gave us
Eye contact on its own
When he looked at us
We cheered
Cried
Just that was really think for us
So somebody else might look at us
You crazy
But we're not
We just got this little boy just fine hundred
Freaking hours but he just looked at us for 3 seconds my
God
And he went from that to a little boy now who functions on a near genius-level who talks as communicative is
Loving is embracing little boy
Is Ron
For me it just felt like my mother was
Loving me and enjoying me and playing with me nowadays interviews run
Seems to say that maybe his parents cured him a lot too so I actually have never used the word to write
I don't use that in my lectures YouTube is not no one's ever actually heard me
You say that what I do say
Is full recovery which is essentially the same thing
Whatever you call it armed with his heroic story Ron and his dad Barry now running autism treatment program they call
Sunrise
Som
People come here from all around the world
What's a my child is severely autistic and I will smile and I'll put out my hand
Don't shake their hand and I'll say
I am so excited for you
Wow you are so blessed
You know what the store to do
Decry
And I say why you crying
No one ever said that to me you really say that two parents with a severely like severely autistic
Severely I say it all over the world
You know last year
There was a woman and Kelli Stapleton
Who was a
Fairly prominent autism blogger
And I gotta know Kelly a bit kiss a daughter with autism in one day when her daughter was 14 she locked herself
Funny van with a couple charcoal burners in in tried to commit suicide with their autistic daughter
In the world of autism more than I can't think of any other place you see it
Believes that one of the reasons you see so many suicides in this community and by the way there's a huge debate about this on the web
But he believes it one of the reasons you see it so much
Is it all the success story seemed to say to parents like him
Did as hard as it can be in it.
Really hard
You're not trying hard enough it's depressing
You're a new bumper sticker other than showing up
The autism is awesome and awesome spell like a you some like can't like
Saint Laurent
I know you want to
It destroys lives
Is is what it does in our definition of it
And that's one of the things that makes it
Very very confusing for people outside the community to do
Describe what's going on
You know how this
Situation were obviously autism suspect
Do you have all of these different kids
Describe
By the same word
Making things even more confusing to take a child when they're too or
Free butts Temple Grandin again to kids that look real severe
And I look real severe when I was
When I was three
Real real severe
And then you work on these kids lots of one-on-one therapy
And one kid two kind of pull him out of it
And the other one you're not able to pull them out of it
And they both look the same at Age 3
So if a lot of these kids
Start out with the same set of symptoms they end up in vastly different place
No one knows why
Vanessa Paradis
You really
Have no idea what is going to happen
How much
You can dare
Notions of
What could be up the road or what should be now if they pop into my head which is rare eye
I dismiss them
I have absolutely no idea
Because we have been down so many roads
That were disappointing
Panda
That's next
Hey guys
This is Nathan Sanchez calling from Santa Clara California
Radiolab is supported in part by the National Science Foundation
And by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloan @www
Sloan. Org
Thanks guys
Robert krulwich Radiolab in the story after Owens
Disney basement sessions has really taken off in the Disney therapy as it were
Seem to be working and was getting better and better and better
Things
Took a turn at end and not for the good
Remind me how old is this point
14-14-14 9th grade
I was 10th grade 10th grade
And what what happened
We didn't know what was happening you know we just saw over the months at Owen was
Really out of sorts
You got quiet and withdrawn basically stop doing Disney
Over this. He's losing a lot of weight is not sleeping the three of us were scratching our head saying what is going on with
Oh and he is really moving into a bad place I mean I was
Actually worried that it was becoming schizophrenic
Do something is wrong with them and we couldn't get it out of him
This is Owens older brother Walt again and he says when he pick up Owen
School you're shoving self you talk to him so I pick him up
You talked himself in the car and it be no floater
You know it's not true or something under his breath and then at one point I overhear him
In a kind of conversation
With still the sidekick of Hercules in that movie Hercules Danny DeVito does The Voice
And Phyllis can always listen kid
You can take them you're not you're not to stand up for yourself that kind of
Thing that Ellen was saying and I didn't
I didn't know where to fit it in wrong. It seems like only was trying to psych himself up for something
Switch on the couch and a grilled them for an hour
Until eventually I won told him about his music class
It's cool there two kids in this class who red kids emotionally disturbed kids so they're not
They're not on the autistic spectrum and socially there very
On Target
And they
Basically
Torment and terrorize him for
6 months
Of that school year unbeknownst to us
And unbeknownst to the school
What did they do
They sat on either side of him and basically said you know
We're going to kill you we're going to kill your parents
Two bullies
Leiden
Bullying me badly
I mean right then you were in a very bad spot and couldn't tell me your mom or anyone
All right because what happened the police said what
Burn your house down if what
If you tell
And Owen was so literal as are so many autistic kids
She believed that they literally meant they were going to come and burn his house down but there's an extraordinary MoMA
Pain in the middle of this where Walter picks him up
And Owen starts to think go through a calculus the bully said if you tell your parents
About what we said will bring your house down but they said nothing about your brother
And so is he seems like an opening
So did you tell him
No I didn't
No I didn't I
Why not
Does I'm afraid he would beat the mop
I didn't want that
Walt at this point you know is a football player and
You know what he looks like Hercules to Owen and
Oh and later describes to us this thinking
That if he tells Walter
That Walter will
Hurt the kid
And maybe kill the kid
And in Disney none of the heroes actually kill any of the villains
No
Walter was the hero you were afraid he was going to do what
Kill but it's wrong
Did you ever talk to Walt about it a little bit later after it happened
I just never finding out
Like a combination of like
Rage and helplessness
That
I literally just thought
Of what
I would have gone to that kid
If I wanted told me
I really wanted to kill that kid
I mean
Ditto
I'm his protector
In a way you're you are kind of Walter was worried about protecting you in that time
In a way it was
Me
That was doing what
Protecting myself
And who else and my brother Ryan and Walt and Walt
You're protecting Walter
So here you have this moment we're at look like Owen was sliding backwards but according to Ron
It might have actually been his greatest Leap Forward
His most profound moment of empathy these days when is 23 just turned 23
A few months ago and are you in love right now yes I am with the girl made dreams Emily
She and I graduated
From review last month this has been a three-year
Program called getting ready for the outside world and so he'll be graduating from the
From the entire program
And off on his own and now me her and our other two friends John and Julie also go to school
Are all going to move
And live a life and Hyannis
What is wife
Living independently forever or what is it what kind of adult Independent Living Program
As we were talking it was hard not to wonder how independent will Owen be because
That's the question that's in front of the SS
Especially with
I think what scares me
Sometimes it is
Kind of
Just having to go it alone in a lot of ways
And
At the same time just
Being there for
Sorry
There's some
Thought think things ahead of you know
Goals have to be ready to
Take these things on
Kind of
No wonder you don't like birthdays
Well it's a tough one
Amy Walters like
And I said to me what pain is like is it always going to be Disney
Lemmy forever
Oh my God on that wall
But we talked we talked to him about you know
About everything about you know our will and who will be Owens
You know how he figures into everything all the efforts of her we're trying to do and have been doing for all this
What time is 2
One of my favorite movies is the Jungle Book
Cuz mowgli's
It's his quest
With his animal Sidekicks to get him to the man Village
What we've been doing all this time and what we're still doing and we do everyday
Is to bring on closer and closer to that man Village the
We all inhabit
There's so much hoping that in as he progresses you feel so good about it
But at the same time
That's not to say hello
Ever totally get there
It's hard as we might try we
We may not get him there
But that doesn't mean you you leave him on the path you
Stay with them on the past even if
The Never Ending path
Thanks to
Ron suskind Cornelius, Walt Susskind Owen suskind the whole second family and mystery
Book is called life animated Steve silver
Pamela deal for
And
Kelsey
Also tagil tippy and the Tina McCord at the Rebecca school and the whole staff at that school
Are all heroes in my mind to so
PayPal
Do you have time Chatham Rod I'm Robert krulwich thanks for listening