Are you awake
Radio WNYC
Is Radiolab on Jad abumrad couple days ago Joe Frank passed away
One of the greats
Your business
Huge inspiration for me
But a guy his work you may not know
He was one of the originals
Nobody told stories like Joe Frank
Nobody tell stories like Joe Frank no one day he is still
You know what Imma do I want to take this podcast
To play for you a little bit of his work
It's so good
So good
Elsa play for you a few conversations I've had recently about
Joe Frank the impact of that work
Starting with a
Conversation I had with Brooke Gladstone from on the media she recently interviewed me
About the impact that your hat on Radiolab which is significant so let's start there this is an excerpt
A conversation that I have Brooke Gladstone that they use for on the media and I believe
Starts with clip
Let me play a clip
Or maybe a couple of them and get your reaction
You hug people goodbye after a social event
Apsa dinner party
Or gallery opening
There is always that moment
When they squeeze you more forcefully than before
A polite way of letting you know
They are about to withdraw
Usually
The one who disengages first
Is the one who cares less
This used to happen to me
Dog rejected
I come home with a lonely sick feeling
That's why
Naughty to assume the power position
Game the psychological advantage
Are people very briefly
22 seconds
Before freeing myself
Sometimes
Detect any resistance
I'll push the person away
I caused a woman to fall backwards over a chair and during their back
Sledge or hospitalization
But I had no choice
What's the matter
A self preservation
That is classic Joe Frank
It's really good writing you know he writes
Scenarios
They're like demented Talk of the Town
Anyway later
Little fragments of dark
Experience which are beautifully realized very Vivid
Kind of funny but kind of also struggling
How do you think
He
Influenced you
You are always
A great producer always
Technically adept
You had
Tons of musical composition training you understood the rhythmic possibilities of radio
What did he do that you
Don't think you could have done without him
A lot of different things
This was way too beginning for me
Radiolab was just a 3-hour thing
On the AM station
We're going back home
We're going back to the Stone Age so January February 2002 somewhere around there
Willie the beginning
Everybody here who knows the beginning of Radiolab knows that I didn't deserve that show it was too soon I didn't know what I was do
Doing it didn't have a style I had this
I had the unfortunate
Thing that we all had back at you.
I said I would she wanted to be Ira Glass everybody
I want to be hourglass right
And I was still trying to figure out like a case of who am I what do I want my stuff to
The sound like
And so I would
Every Sunday night
How to put a 3 hours and it was an anthology show at
And it was literally
Take
The best documentaries from the BBC the CBC
In Canada the ABC in Australia radio Netherlands all the stuff
And
Package them into
3 continuous hours
And I would certain aerate in and out of different segments
And so from 8 to 11.
Playing my show House boar. Big
At the time which means I wasn't just making the thing but I had to sit at the board
Hit play on the CD and then it between our one and hour to an hour to an hour
R3 I got to say the weather
I was doing the whole thing
And after me Joe Frank would come on
And he was part of my shift
And everytime I J
Just be like
F is this that I would just be sitting there listening to him and just
Like amazing like mentally taking notes be like oh
This guy has a
Feel
There's a surreality and a disorienting Ness
To his stuff that I just really fascinated by and I was like oh I want to
Going to do that
Can we play that one that we
Said that we can play
It was a time when I danced on a street corner
Dressed as a chicken
My job was to draw attention to a furniture store down the block
One evening
When my shift was over
Still wearing my chicken outfit
I walked into a bar across the street
I go to the Bombay martini
Straight up
IMAX on the side
Prostitutes sat down next to me
She was young
Willow Way
A Faraway look in her eyes
We talked about our careers
The importance of networking
Focus
Then I excused myself
Walk into the men's room
Sat down on the toilet
Had a bowel movement too broken to
And half of it was still hanging out of me
So I had to wipe myself 50 times
Repeatedly checking to see
Who's more left toilet paper
Written on the wall for the words
Know that someone is suffering anonymously
And unknown
By the time you read this
Oh that's good
That's really good
Wow there's nothing wrong
Who's playing that
Clip
Actually he's not using any bad words true and you just have to see violations there
Simply
Growth and yet
You tell me that there is a
Person on the planet
That has
Joe Frank always had the quality of like he's coming from inside your head out and then back in again he has that kind of quality
It sounds like he's somehow like the voice in your head but broadcast back into your head are there something about that quality
That's what I want from the radio is what I want from
Guess I want someone to be speaking
Inside me
Anyway
Have you ever talked about
Joe Frank
I give this talk
3040 times a year
Where I have like
An extended Joe Frank excerpt
I have an image of Joe Frank that I show
Yeah I talked about you all the time
The vast majority of our listeners
Other people listening to this
I'm going to have to assume they never heard of Joe Frank and
He was always available on
Podcast
He was like this
Mystery
People who weren't willing to sort of follow the breadcrumbs to him I'll tell you I mean when I give
Talk that I
That I have to give
I go through the series of
People live in FLA
Let's meat
Always ask any Joe Frank fans in the house
Diesel be like audience
2500 people
One time
What happened
Like there's a clap in the far right now
Joe Frank fan
It always broke my heart a little bit
Cuz no one ever knew
His stuff
Like amongst us our little turtle Posse radio people
She's a legend
Nobody on the outside of her do him
You know
This is going to be there Chan
Yeah
Last night I dreamt I was lost on an elevator all the floors were the same
And I realize the elevator was moving horizontally so I tried another elevator
The express but it just got be more lost faster
People kept getting on and getting off the roll wearing green gauze over their heads who were smoking ice cream cones
I said please let me on 39th Street and the conductor said this is 35th Street.
3 blocks and take the escalator but when I got to the escalator it was just a phone booth
So I need to call I called my father I said hello
Post on 39th Street looking for an escalator and I can't find it anywhere and he said
I'll be right there and there we was in the phone booth started moving for
Very slowly with my father and I in it and I didn't know where it was going or why and he said
Don't be afraid this phone booth will take us home and I said but we have
And he said we live on the 8th floor apartment why
I said why and he said
Yes
That was a condensed version of a conversation I had with Brooke Gladstone for on the media
Can find a full conversation upon the media. Org
Pool return with one more Joe Frank recollection in just a moment
Is Michael Burrows from Portland Oregon
Radiolab
Supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Lansing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world more information about Sloane at
UW. Slone. Org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help this summer I'm hosting
And I request for those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
We're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments of childhood Brilliance basically I want to hear about
Kids you know did something
It just means you lean back and say wow how did they do that maybe it was the moment that I kids
You've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons and you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin
Maybe the kids in math class you noticed they're ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the specific moments where a kid does something super smart
Doesn't have anything to do with the test if you have a story please share it with us
Go to radiolab.org Brilliance and record a short audio message for us
And that's radiolab.org / brilliance
Thank you so much
I'm jad abumrad this Radiolab we're paying tribute to Joe Frank
In this podcast
Joe unfortunately lost the battle of colon cancer just a few days ago
After my conversation with Brooke Gladstone from on the media
End up having
Later that same day another conversation about you
This time with Ira Glass from This American Life
Hello
Hey how's it going
It's going okay
There are two entirely different okay's just
For the purposes of this conversation I'm doing I'm doing just fine
All right did you know Joe Frank
No I had one interaction with your Frank
Which was
It was almost
Perfectly Joe Frank
And that
I met him once at Third Coast and he
I asked him something and he looked at me for a long time and then just
Walked away
That was my window Frank interactions
Do you remember what you asked I think I might have
Said something
Utterly like not my place cuz I just started the show doesn't hey if you have any work
Do you want to like you know
Get on get on the show
Let me know and he just looked at me like
You have the gall just walked away
It said that was it
So what do you remember about who I'm just like what what you saw cuz you will you work for them
Right
Basically when I was when I was 20
I had my first paid job at NPR
And I was there a production assistant to this guy whose job it was to invent new ways to
Tudo radio for NPR
And get a Regular Show when he would do different things in
Weeks and then he brought Joe Frank down from New York
And that was the thing we're doing for a while and I was Jose production assist
As my very first paid job at NPR
And I ain't never heard it on the radio I mean he wasn't
National media
So I'm never like
A few very specific memories for
Trish suhr
The best way I can explain it is like
I've had the experience a number of times over the years where people try to tell me
Liko the first time I heard your show
Was this
And generally the singer trying to say to me is like I didn't know that the radio could
Did I mean like I didn't realize it like old radio could you like
Australian
Feel like this
And I myself had that exact
Experience the person who I had it
Was Joe Frank
And dumb
And I remember there was a day
Early on
And I was standing in the old control room at NPR's original Studios like the original two
Studios they have
Studio 1 Studio 2 on the 1st
420 20 amps
We're in studio 2
Standing by the reel to reel tape
Get the bank of them
And I remember Joe was
Telling one of the stories I remember feeling like
Oh I've never
I've never heard this before I just remember feeling like
Like this like this thing like I didn't end end end it was just elected feel like
Totally caught up in a story
And you don't exactly know why you're so caught up with it and you don't know where it's going
And
And you just want to stay with us
In the sound of
Voice is such an incredible
Radio performer
Like much better than you were made
I don't remember which specific story it was I do remember have gone back because there was one story of particular called the
In fact I've gone and dug up that I remember at the
Hi
I thought like this is at this sums up the whole thing
Literally what it is I'm riding up the elevator of my building is he gets on an elevator
I'm standing there sharing with small space with a
Terrific looking girl he totally gets a crush on this woman but I feel shy
Edible
Scratch my head
Vici
I gaze up at the numbers of the floors lighting up one after another imagine their life together and everything that they will be
She seems like
Kind of person I'd
Really like
Eddie cannot bring himself
To stand there silently
Not looking at each other
Say a word to her
Edsel
Pulls out something from his
How can I reach into my pocket and draw out
Paper which I unfold
It turns out to be a cash register tape from the A&P
But I scrutinize it is if it's very important before putting it back in my pocket
It has a guy come very magnetic
Forward motion and it's like 4 5 minutes long
And the entire thing happens in the elevator
Are you going to races describing the floors going up and all the feelings he has
You go through your life looking and looking
Sometimes you see her.
The woman you might have loved
Might have loved you at a bus stop
Museum across a smoky room at a party
In the lobby of a theater
Online at the supermarket
In an elevator
When she leaves in a panic you want to run out to her calling out to stop
Stop
It's me the person you were meant for
Don't you recognize me
I may seem like a stranger but I'm the person you've been waiting for
The one in your dreams
But you just stand there and watch her leave
This happens to me with a different woman about once each day
And I remember
What has 20
Curing that and being like this is at
This guy is doing
Like I want to know
I want to know how you do that
Yes for me the equivalent thing with Debbie hurt his rent a family
Trilogy
No, I'd be hard-pressed at 2
To summarize a story but it's essentially it's a
This whole world in which families can be rented
For occasion
When I saw this ad
And it said
Rent a family
We have certain
Package programs
Where an individual can experience over the course of
The twelve-month period A pretty considerable rain
The family
Hi
And it's all like in this very documentary
Format and it's done really well so you can
Okay sometimes like
Aren't totally sure that what you're hearing is a drama that sounds super real
Society
Seems to be
Speeding up
Before I buried
The whole idea of renting thing
Have to do with the people's desire
Do not have a permanent commitment to them
I think it's important to recognize
Depth of loneliness
That
That must be addressed
The end like doesn't resolve at all you'll just left would like 12 different feelings that you don't even know what to do with
I think that's that's what he represents
You're like thrown in the middle of the action and it's greeting you don't understand it's kind of dark
And it's not all going to get resolved all the answers aren't going to be given to you
And enjoy going to have like weird feelings you don't know what to do with and often it's good over reach
And it's not even going to work
But it was still kind of cool
You don't like all of that is completely his completely 70s film turned into radio
So what is it
Is it you think you took with you from Joe Frank and putting to This American Life
I mean honestly the first thing is just what he gave me the most important thing which was desire
To do it
Hearing him made me want to make stories
And then I spent a decade
Trying to figure out how to do it
With ax
And with reporting
The thing that started me
With that ambition was him so that's one thing
The second thing is I'm just the way he would use music in the way that the music would pull the story forward and
Create a mood but also kind of like
She went to the dream of it the notion that you'd use music as a kind of cinematic
Scoring
Which is not the way you know music would be used in old time radio dramas and certainly not the Wave Music
NPR
And the way you use music is so built into me that a couple of years
After this American life was on the air
Joe is already letting out in California have been for
And I like mutual friends I mean Ohio is so angry with
And I was like why is Joe so angry with me
You like why is he so angry
And it turned out that Joe thought that I was listening to his show
And stealing the music oh yeah
And I got in touch with him
And he's just like it's so petty said this is so petty
Choosing any music and you listening to my show is like it take me so long to find decent music and I
Edited so carefully
You know it's such a part of the identity of the show
Are you just listen to my show it rip me off like do a little work brother
Isaac Joe it's so
Much worse than that like the fact is like I haven't heard you're showing years I haven't heard him so sorry and would have
I just learned how to use music from you
Pat Metheny comes out with a new record
I hear the same track you do and you're the same possibility in it and I just do the same thing because like it's so built into who I am
So in a way like I am totally stealing from you but I'd swear I guess I didn't know it
Did you ever
Did you ever like Linda in a good place and he was fine at the end of it I think
It seems so small what's the matter with you
Yeah so there's that and
What else carries forward
I mean I mean it's it's
Honestly there's a thing or two that he does
That I have never figured out how to imitate that in the back of my mind
I still feel like I'm going to stay
And one of them is a thing I came up last week I was talking to Parker one of those like the younger producers
I just say what I think she went to do in kind of a moment that she really loves and she's to be a film professor
And is like a super cinematic think she was shooting for us like you know what you should really listen to disguise Your Friends cheat
Heard of him
I downloaded last week I bought a downloaded
The eighty yard run
Have you heard that one now no never heard
God
It's a super early one in fact I think it's just an aircheck of one of his WBAI broadcast
Play with natural actual
Live radio show
I've done late at night
It's just him in a microphone with music
And he's telling the story of what he keeps referring to as
I like to call it my Infamous 80-yard run
Twisted
Convoluted tale now before I get to the
The full story of my life
I hope
You will bear with me
There's a few things you need to know
The first and the first thing you need to know is
Despite between
Luis Rodriguez
And Rubin Hurricane Carter
Professional fight
That happened over the years and tell them
Oh wow
Terrible beating
Standing crop top
Unconscious
And then there comes a point when he's like
Did you like 6 or 8 but it's another thing and he says
Stop before I can tell you that part of the store you need some this next thing and I would tell you that
After a brief interlude
During which I will
Drink some tea
The music
Comes up
And then he just leaves
God
30 years trying to figure out how to steal that I don't even know how to do it
I honestly honestly
I don't know man
I mean I mean like like
I'm going to figure it out
The first
That's Ira Glass from This American Life thanks to him thanks also to Brooke lasting from on the media
Anti sarkari and Kelly Prime
Nothing more perfect crew who produces tribute
Also a very special thanks to Michael story
If you want to hear excerpts of Joe Frank's work which I would highly recommend
Go to joefrank.com his entire archive is there will also link you to a from radiolab.org
Here I think
If you listen
Iran I talked about
This is it
Even though he's a guy who's inspired so many of us to get into the business of telling stories
Nobody sounds like him
Still because it's completely impossible to imitate
Into the hundreds of thousands of podcasts that are happening now
Is nobody doing anything as
Daring and competent at the same time
Yeah I could so singular you can't really imitate it very well
And I'm personally not one who believes it matters like if your work clothes on past you
The people of the future
I meant to be enjoyed like
I'm doing right now and then like if no one ever listens to them again after we're gone like
Wolf pack them anyway like walking around in
Being alive while we're dead first bumfuk office people
Being alive and having sandwiches and beating for lunch while we're dead
And not existing like I hate them already they can f*** themselves
But it seems that it seems sad that
That that other
People
Lake won't know this
Weird thing that I know it's a special
You know like he's so outpacing everybody even now even out there like this Army of
Of people making podcasts
I tried to invent something that's like nobody else is doing
He still is he still has outpaced every single one of them
From the grave
That's perfect life and
Goodbye
This is Sonny from South Africa radio
Jad abumrad and is produced by Soren wheeler
Is our director of sound design Maria matus Tapatia
What is a managing director
Our staff includes sign
Backpacking you Tracy hunt Matt kielty
Arianne wack have Walters and Molly Webster
Help from Amanda aronchick Shima
Jake