Are you awake
Northern listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
Okay you're here should I just test you
What is the supreme law of the land
The Constitution
Yep you got it
What is
Freedom of religion
What what is it mean what is freedom of religion like you can be out with any religion you want without being
Persecuted
Great Gun device to make me nervous cuz it feels like they're too easy and then I'm going to be gone
Who is in charge of the executive branch
The president
If the president can no longer serve who becomes president
Vice president
Yeah
Robert krulwich Radiolab
They were going to start off by Serta
Sitting in on a conversation
It's telling me to study for the
The English test
Between our producer and reporter of Kelly Prime and
Producer reporter
Master who is right now in the process of becoming a US citizen
Estimated case completion time is August
2019 when did you start applying
2014 maybe wow getting married is
The fastest way of getting citizen
Hey what are your feelings as you approach this date
It's a weird
Time is it
Citing it's exciting because like my kid was born here so my kid is an American citizen but I'm not an American citizen that's kind of
Like a weird thing like I feel like I want to be that for my kid I feel like
As a
Muslim guy
There are protections that I get as a citizen that I buy me not otherwise yet
But I mean like for my family my family is
We've immigrated a lot my
Like two maybe three generations ago my family moved
From India
2 East Africa
Tanzania
And then my parents generation they emigrated from Tanzania
Canada
But what's funny is like my family my dad
My mom like when they came to Canada
They were so grateful that Canada
Accepted them
My parents so badly wanted to be Canadians
But because they were sort of these Outsiders date
They kept coming really close would like not quite getting it like my dad
She knew like as a comedian dad the thing you're supposed to do is like go down to the ice rink in sign up your boyfriend
Hockey lessons
But instead she signed me up for figure skating lessons until like 3 years I took figure skate
Reading glasses that was like the only Brown kid in the class only brown boy
Did you guys watch hockey
Yeah I know what's the thing with hockey like in Canada hockey
Such a thing but for me when I was in high school I would go home I would like to do my homework really quickly
And then I would watch Hockey Night in Canada and I hated hockey but I would watch it
Because I knew the next day at school like that's all anybody would be talking about is the Maple Leafs game it was
Was like a like a simulation homework there's something you know he's like okay like let's memorize the names of these players OK Google who scored
Vertigo always a good girl with an interesting call like where's Tupac Back
I don't even can't even
You know it's like there's this club and this is the homework for the club and in order to be part of the club
I have to do the homework
And for everybody else the homework is fun and for me the homework is homework
So here at the show for the last
I don't know 6 months a year
Whatever since a lot of theater show about voting and elections
You know we've been thinking about
Democracy and citizenship is Big sort of amorphous concept
I'm trying to figure out how
How do we
Make something about them it's hard though because Big Ideas
I'm mushy and hard to pee
Down
Yes we would have kind of lie for a bit but then
2 of a reporter
Walked in with
Stories that really brought those big fuzzy ideas down to earth
So for the next
New episodes in the world
About what it means and what it takes
To belong to a boy
Starting with Kelly Prime with a story that takes place
Probably know this by now
In Switzerland
Right so I had
Found
This
Kind of viral article to hit all over the world
That was
Dutch woman too annoying to get Swiss citizenship
And it's a good title
So there's this woman Nancy Holten
And from what I could read just on the very like click baby stuff was that
She is a vocal vegan
Cheap anti cowbell anti church bell in the town turned against her
Refuse to naturalize her to Auntie cowbell cowbells like why would why would you do things in the world
World's like you go to Switzerland and on every postcard is this like
Adorable cow with big eyes and brown spots
And houses
Giant decorative Bell on its chest and that is like
Switzerland
In this lady Nancy who's like a militant animal rights person she says that the loudness
For the cows that it is
Disturbing for them and it is cruel and that it is a Swiss tradition but it's got to go
IC
And her social media presence is always smiling and always happy that she post things like
I don't eat babies do you kind of like over-the-top a self-righteous right
But
The idea that a town could deny her citizenship
Like being annoying for her personality is Anjali
I just decided I've got to go
Find out what that's about in like meet this woman
So as soon as Iraq and I rented a car
And I picked up my fixer and translator and a Kerber what would I think
Okay
Come around
And we headed out of town
Into the Swiss Countryside
We just drove in a cornfield deposit actor
I think we're here
After about an hour we got to the town where Nancy lives
I called gift
Burfict
Get over freaking out afterwards
Whatwears
It's in the very north of
Of Switzerland
And it's like this
Quaint little town beautiful
Flowers
Surrounded by Fields but once you get in it's like
Houses going to pack together in these little
Attorney Rhodes
Nancy lives in the pink 4-story apartment
And I was like ready to meet with a militant vegan
Eventually
That guy
Grand provocateur
Kelly hello hey
Kybella information was just
Super warm
Like incredibly warm piss
Cat is very very shiny blue
Eyeshadow on
Long brown flowy hair and should never ever not smiling
And the
Here, beautiful
Home to walk into her apartment
It's at the Sun comes very good
Here in the house and I like it when it's
How do you say that
Right I don't know how to say that the walls are pink for the blue couch
Twins
Stop PS3 daughters
His name is Krista
So we settle in and we've actually taken off our shoes at this point
What would you taking a picture of my feet
Just because
I'm a chicken survive a few bar food
She had Life Send Me
Status
She's just very strong advocate for barefoot walking
It's a feeling of freedom and it healthy and
So she takes pictures of her
Her feet and post them to YouTube and Instagram social media
As part of one of her many campaigns to get people
To walk around Barefoot more often
Which she herself does
Anytime it's warm bicycle and coffee to go shopping
How did how is she making ends meet what what do you do for work
Dubai to Oz
Hollister
It starts of with model T the hair model
Writer I just want to listen freelance journalist
And all the coach and Angel coach
Any like like like Spirits outside her house
And communicates with angels there
And helps
Coach people through their lives using the help of angels
And you have what kinds of do you know what kind of Crystal seas are you
There are my friends
The help me cuz she has a crystal in the window sill
Rose quartz
What plant is good for the opening for
Crystal for the hamster
Teddy his name is Teddy Bear long-haired hamster
I'm starting to harm has an eye infection in a tumor
So she put the crystals inside the hamster cage to help with his tumor
List animals
Wendy's
The Dutch
If
I'm Dutch
Nancy was born in Holland and when she was 8 years old
Opposition
Old is Manny Mota is her mom got divorced
And just kind of up and took her to Switzerland
Put her in a van with a bunch of stuff and she took a nap in the car and when she woke up her mom said do you like
Like it here
Ocean deep action down the mountains are nice and then her mom was like right because we live here now
Wow
Nancy says it was a
It was a rough
Transition
Yesterday nobody else to shoot sake
Pekin duck on West Dodge
On the first day of school she couldn't speak any German all and apparently his teacher asked her to open up a window so defensive
And she was just like
What I was asking for disability fashion start remote
Alshon
I'll tolondra Nostradamus
As a whole arm
Alarm 4
Well first of all for being ducks
But I called her duck
Cheese
She dressed differently if I need to
Had a had a rather tough time
Beginning of school
So is hard to fit in
Aspire cleito saves.
Though she said she started to turn inward and
Keep to herself
And even at home with her family
Alignment
Quinoa
In the family settings who was not he was not allowed to speak her mind Any Man of Mine on The Voice her opinion
Your feelings and Woody Harrelson the whole weekend
She says even as an adult she just never really felt
Self-confident Ehrlich learn how to stand up for herself
But then she says in 2003 she was 29 years old the sexual sin is spending the Komen
Calta uninsulated Century Theater Salinas
She had what she called a spiritual experience
So she was living outside of Zurich
And she already had a 3 year old daughter she was
Pregnant with the
Quincy fire stronger than feeling in
And she said she felt under a lot of pressure
Pressure to have an abortion
In fact mm film Amazon
They're already sitting at the doctors
She just had to sign a form but all of a sudden she said I had enough stuff and that's with no stuff
One night
Just let me sleep one night
And she says she's
Stood up
And in that moment. Is Tamia
Click the mouse and a click went off and I had these penis estimate
Moose's
A mannequin that came from now.
Coming out of Goodfellas
And she said no I'm not going to do it that's where she said
She got the
The strength from the senate for your kids and set up for yourself
That's when Nancy says all these things
That she felt all her life
About barefoot walking
And not eating meat and
Pressing a spiritual connection to the natural world
She had kept all those things inside of her
And now she was going to let them out she was going to fight for them
And years later
She moved to gift over 4
On the assistant house fire
Fantasy Association
She fell in love with a
She said she
Never loved anyone like this
And it's the most idyllic beautiful place in the world that's why I'm too many kids in the house
About for me
Liberia
This is my home
I'm staying here
Because living here she was just able to be so much closer to Nature
She took us
To the stream by her house
Milwaukee this cold
What grass is lightly raining and
So
And as we were walking
Down
This little embankment to put our feet in the water
Cccomm
Popeyes
Whenever you feel like how this whole thing is
Starting to work
If you were getting a little warm but you have the goalie sensation throughout your buddy
Tia Vine
Act like
Sweety professional
Shattuck Naga Trinity
If it's raining
And she was like when the sunshine
This place is
It's my heaven on Earth
This is Timmy Chang Minecraft plus
Display
Her place of strength of flowing water carries away all the
Worries and Sorrows end
Concerta strengths
And at this point Nancy feels like she's found her voice and she's found her home and she wants to make it official if she wants to be
Bswift
Because
She just hadn't gotten her citizenship
Before and like
Her kids are Swiss she wants to be politically active she wants to be able to vote
And the process for citizenship in Switzerland is pretty intense
Yes you are
Tesla paperwork Language exam
But the final step for Nancy is
That the town gets to vote
We're literally
The town is mailed little pamphlets
And those templates have
Someone like Nancy Holten
And a little seedy about her
Forever into town can read her basic biographical information
Come to the town meeting on the set day at the school gymnasium
And
Raise their hand or whether or not she gets to be sweat
No kidding and so at the end of the day it's a
It's very public kind of like
Consensus
And that's
Where are the trouble started
Because Nancy had some ideas about
How the town might be
Improved
Starting with
The church bells
B&D Savannah
On top and talk to Max
Zexal Morgan
She said when she moved into apartment she just noticed that
The church bells in her town because she began to side
Woodring really early in the morning instead klimas me cows in bed
And they wake her up what do you think
Good morning
At 6 in the morning get heavy
Because then I'm waking up
And I'm also I can't sleep with eyes open
Window image
Keeping room
So Nancy filed a formal complaint
The nine angles
Boosie wrote a letter to the to the municipality
Asking for it
Can O2 stop
Basically just looking moms Einstein
The reason the bells ring in the morning it's not really just about announcing time and there's actually a pretty long Christian
Tradition in the community
Alpha wolf
Sexual Morgan
It's like it to call for prayer
Which she considers outdated in Spanish
And it's right at fire religion on this Metheny
It's going bad
This is like look
I got free religion and I do not want to be woken up in the morning to pray
Lamb
Aziz article the national
The local paper found out about Nancy's complain
You basically told him about it
And when article came out that's when the town started talking
From the beginning it was like so much of gossip
End up going around the town and
Kind of talk to people about Nancy it's like a pretty small town like
I think 3,000 people are so and
One of the people who agreed
Talk to me
Was Andy
My name is Andy Andreas
Disturbing
I grew up in this
Send us a village here his family's actually been in dip over fix for
Three generation
I'm just right from here and he told me that after the church bell article
People with
At the pub
Soccer practice or
Choir around you have a beer
And you start talking to you
A little while later
Take another beer
And a penis get a Little Bit Stronger you know what I mean
So I think they are
People would start talking about her
They have you have you heard or have you read or have you seen
She doesn't like Bells
DuckTales
In the morning why does she rent an apartment besides the church
This is Ursula
I'm Swiss
I talked to her and her husband Max
My name is Max
I have
Steve four-and-a-half-year
And some of their complaints I honestly felt were very reasonable if you decide
To go to an apartment
And you choose your apartment beside the street
Don't wonder if their cars
And if you decide to
Take your apartment beside the church
Don't want to talk to her belly
Soba town
Was starting to like notice her and get mad at her and people would yell things are Haram to his biking
Oh wow so it became like okay
Partly because it wasn't just the church bells
Nancy Ajram making noise about a lot of things here and get over sleeps at a time
Jaundice and India most expensive
It is a tradition in Uber
Big frog samples she had complained about this one tradition where townspeople can bring mice tails to the town hall
Once a year
People can bring like the Tails of mice
To the town hall and you will get like one Frank and
$0.10 m
It's like population control I think originally yes
Legos back like
A hundred years hundred fifty years ago
Now it's a tradition
So Nancy went after that
Oh what a
So she started the procedure was like writing letters to the municipality and to all sorts of like
Animal rights groups
She got an article in the
Paper at one point she showed me
And there was a
Horrific bundle of tales
Nancy's real thing more than the church bells is like animal active
In fact just a little while after that church bells article came out on TV
Come down and turn a list.
Hawkmoon of the reporters asked her team does indigenous Canada
We don't like church bells are there any other bills you don't like
And she's badass t-shirts women
Googlem
Well yeah how about this is literally this is
Any other don't you don't like them it's happy K9 best in this Crystal
Constant can be made in Villa d'Este
I kicked the Hornet's Nest and that's when it all
So it sounds like she's
They never ever ever graduated escalation of
Attacks on Swiss culture
Suddenly trips the big one
The commander-in-chief
Easton
Now I have to say I didn't totally get why cowbells would be the Tipping Point
And I mentioned this to Andy
The cowbells are an image of
Romantic feelings in in Swiss culture
Drive up into the hills around get so perfect with Andy and his daughter Olivia
Pikachu
With end of the day we parked the car
You pulled into the
Long driveway leading to a farm
And we thought
Six seven eight nine ten
Cows in what very quickly became clear to me in that moment is that cowbells in Switzerland
Aren't just about postcards or with a selling a gift shop or whatever
31 cows
And
Good morning baby
I really like it here and get the sunset like there's two stunts
Touching a
Touching all those fields
Such as beautiful
They really represent this particular way of life in Switzer
Agrarian way of life
A real simpler farming way of life
It's like the cowbell is attached
To the Swiss version of the American Heartland like
Nebraska farmer
I don't know
And in Switzerland for a lot of people
That feeling is connected to
Cowbell I think you know also ID for example
It's a story about a Swiss girl growing up with their grandfather in the alley
Everything gets like
Like the beautiful lies in the Alps and Ukraine
Milk and Peoria cafe
Cheeks
Cowbells are there
It's some kind of a stereo type of
A society where there are no problems
Everything Is Beautiful or the sun is shining
Please make every little boy and girl in the world is happy as I am
Heidi
Hi
Dynavision
So when Nancy
Lake launch an attack
That was like
Do you think it felt like it was like attacking
People sense of well-being and
Absolutely Santa Clara ocean of War
I'm coming coming to a 4-inch
Country
I first have to look how
And then I have to pay
The choice
Is that okay for me
Or maybe it's not okay for me I'm coming in until you you have to lifelike
I think
Yes
This is Ursula Knox again
It's not okay
Nancy comes in and tells
That's how we have to
To do it
She's suffering person
She will tell us how to live concerts
Okay
Do you remember how you felt before your meeting
It made me feel so people in the town are not happy about Nancy's cowbell stance
And in the midst of all this the night of Nancy's citizenship meeting arrives
. device is really
She's glad that she didn't know what she
She didn't know then what you know today as far
Hardcore like the whole thing with
Hardcore
Describe
It takes an effort to go back
Particular night
The teeth
Tonight is Nancy citizenship meeting she shows up at the school gymnasium it's in the evening
There are rows and rows of folding chair setup and there's one round the back where the prospective citizens can sit
So Nancy walks and she sits in that back row
And I'll say these meetings are usually like
Calm and pretty sparsely attended there's like maybe eighty to a hundred people
But this time there was
Twice that
The place was packed
And
The first thing to happen is they go through some administrative stuff like
How much budget are we going to use to fix the rotor like should we put a roof on the roller hockey rink
But then came the citizenship part of the meeting
I think they couldn't really control himself
The townspeople just like
China lost their cool people like like
Peasant Farmers they would stand up and able
Get angry and say Well that's
It's not right if you're against it and then
The things that were said
Really surprisingly violence
They would get so emotional
I'm in the disgusting
I'd almost there was a very hateful
That's very loud and no we don't want and then
Alex heeringa fabric
I was astonished about them
Power off
Saying no
We don't want
Getting off yelling saying she doesn't belong here for me
It was a shame
And he got up at one point
To speak on her behalf then I spoke and the
How about them
It was
We did not have any chance
Inconsolate out loud
Stock
I was skipping
And apparently the whole room just started booing him
Inconstant hambu and Nancy is there for Olive
Best listening to everything people are saying just sitting quietly in the back
Swindon oxidative Fila argumentative
Steve Montenegro Clinic
At this point in the assembly people start speaking out against Nancy accuser of the muscle
Cynthia Howell to bring veganism into Switzerland peking Cottage
2 ninjas against tradition Spanish list the motor
Terrible mother lament in the poor kids
Below the belt
And this whole time her daughters are sitting right there next
At this point Nancy's asked to leave the room
She goes out with her daughters
Stands behind his big double doors
She waits
And then she hears
How to eat an apple house
Boniva singlecare
Pause because she had been rejected
So
Having it so obviously
Having a room full of
People
Dority's really not on your side is
This is really hard
Does it says tree like
Euro
Add the in addition to what went on in the room that night there was
Facebook page that went up called Nancy go home
And
It's the cover photo is a field of cows with Nancy's face photoshop on it and it's got
A big circle and
Some of the comments on there like
She should eat me for once
Come to her senses
In the old days
Which would have been chased away with a dung for
Such women were burnt at the stake as witches
Coming up
Nancy fights
Radiolab will continue in
Hey there this is Greg in Huntington Beach Calif
Relapse
Supported in part by
Alfred p
Sloan Foundation
Public understanding of
Websites technology
Confirmation about
Sloan
Www
I hate everybody Pat Walters here I'm a producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
This summer
And I request for those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents
Aunts and uncles teachers
We're looking for stories about what we're calling
Basically I want to hear about this
I kid you know did something
It just means you lean back and say
Wow
Maybe it was the moment that our kids you've been reading to 4 month started reading
Back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons and you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin
Or maybe the kids in math
Music in the margin of their geometry
We're interested in the
Specific moments where
Kid does something super smart but it doesn't have anything to do with the test
If you have a story
Go to radiolab.org
Flash brilliance
Record a short audio message
And that's radiolab.org.
Thank you so much
Jack Robert Radiolab flatly rejected for citizen
Chip by her neighbors
Yeah assume that this is not the end of Nancy
Nancy's tailor
No nothing
I mean the meeting was like pretty awful for Nancy
You know her daughters are Super C
Supportive socks mama
The best chewing tobacco
They're like
You can't give up Mom you need to do this
That because I feel okay to myself
Ons
And what she did was
She wrote to the Canton official the Canton is like the region
And
She wrote to them asking for another try
And she sprayed the stationary with perfume
Let me hear Coco
It was Vanilla cocoa
Cruelty free vanilla perfume
From the body shop that doesn't
Do animal testing
Give it a little bit of her Flair and the response was good they said okay you can try again did you think about
Stopping your campaigns against the specifically Swiss
You know cowbells
Church bells
I just feel like if it were me
I would probably
Things like other so many ways to help animals
Maybe I would try to choose one that
Doesn't cost much friction in my community without ever thought like maybe
Something not
About the cows in the churches
Never
As-salaam Aditya
She's like as long as the animals need a voice
I'm going to continue
Is water-methanol bigly
Exact
Nancy
Google and her family during this week's a Nancy
Keep it down
If you're Nancy
She said that would be honest it wouldn't be me and I don't want to
Ganache Collision
Cross someone's ass
How do you say that how do I put this
Yeah
And by this point
Slow-cook Rita Morgan
The media has gotten hold of Nancy story and things just
Harga
Writing and posting about the cowbells and telling people that
Shouldn't eat meat
Is a Buick Enclave
Pacific rear I use this Fame in order to reach even more people on TV protesting
The Graces and
Is the use of animals in circuses
Since the price was involved everything change
Anywhere in Switzerland Where You Are
And you excited
Infographics
The Ultimate Salon
So along the way all these articles about Nancy they end up putting a spotlight on the town too
A village bus machine from the outside as being
Oh because I make you feel
Fairy
2 years.
I think this will see the anger that was formulated
At this point Nancy goes in for her second vote
And this time she actually bakes vegan gingerbread to give out around town
And the town rejects her
Again
Which again
Picks up the media
Telophase
Unforgettable lyrics
What's the time
A left-wing Dutch woman has been tinnitus with passport
Because she's annoying
It goes International
And she even end up
In a joke on the bluff The Listener test
On wait wait don't tell me
It's tough
How to get the Swiss
To take aside
Even the Nazis couldn't do it
But when it came to 42 year old man
Beholden they couldn't help but
Take a stand
She's that annoying
She's a pain in the ass as a person
I'm sorry
Yes you can
Pain in the ass
So I was in the area I stopped by a local newspaper
And I met with this reporter and nausea and an editor Roth
And of course they knew all about Nancy Holten people enter that you know the hatred that they have
Who's kaivac breeders in the valley of
Breakers coming from they say
If I have to read one more story about that her I will cancel my subscription button
Critical story
So the reason Ross said
It's a critical story is because
It's not so much a story about weather
Nancy's well-liked or not whether she's annoying or not it's more about
Who gets to decide
Who can be Swiss
And who cannot
Anna from us perspective
May be hard to
Kind of wrap your head around the fact that there's so much
Kind of local autonomy to make these kinds of decisions but
I think that there's just a very strong tradition in Switzerland
Yunnan local matters and they should be
Delta waves in the local community
So this is professor of political science at Stanford University
One of towns voting on someone's citizenship
Was it that time a huge issue in Switzerland
Still is
No because like back in the early 2000s there were more and more and more people immigrating from countries like
Kosovo turkey former Yugoslavia
And when that happened people started noticing something at the Times the media reports about some seemingly disc
Mandatory rejections
It look like
Some towns were
Purposely rejecting immigrants from those countries
And in fact in 2003 there was actually a court case
In Swiss federal court because there was a town in central Switzerland and
8 Italian applicants got in while 38 applicants from former Yugoslavia where reject
And the court looked at that case and what they basically said is that
I'm a Swiss law immigrants should have a right to appeal
If that rejected
No
In order for you to make an appeal you need to know right like why you were rejected
So the decision making body
Like needs to provide some justification
Why you being rejected
Basically they said the problem with these town.
Is that people can vote Yes or No for any reason they want there's no way to tell why that person was rejected
And because it seems like
People who were getting rejected were mostly from muslim-majority countries
Certain immigrants might be rejected just based on their membership in a certain ethnic cultural group which Friday
The anti-discrimination clause in the Swiss Constitution
The courts way of solving this is to say that the towns have to justify
Their rejection
And if they person gets rejected that person has to be able to appeal the decision
It's all in the wake of that ruling much more common
To have politicians
Decide on those
Naturalization application
And the Naturalization rates actually went up quite dramatically
A lot more people started getting citizenship
Increase particularly
For those applicants the busy face the strongest discrimination under the direct Democratic vote
Now is that the question of towns voting on citizenship
Has gotten all tangled up in the issue of immigration
And there's actually this political party the
Farmers party
Bowring Park.
SVP it's a very
Old
Very rule party
Arguing basically that town should go back
Voting on citizenship
Yes
This by the way is Lilia my name is Lydia Home Security
When we spoke she was an elected representative in the region and head of the immigration support group
Integration Auto and she basically told me that the SVP which is actually grown pretty dramatically the
The past couple decades
The big thing is immigration voting rights Party Station to change
Just stay
Dade
Diamond a sphere area
I mean when you see this campaigne zits
So clear and so easy to understand what they mean just an example of a while back
The party was campaigning for the slaw they wanted to pass where you could deport an immigrant who commits to crimes and
10 years
They put out these poster than on the poster
R3 white sheep
Kicking a black sheep off
This was flat but literally taking it off
And the party says that it's just meant to represent the black sheep of the family you know what the trouble maker but
I think it's it's it's
This black sheep it's a black sheep and it's not the black sheep of the family it's the black sheep because it's black
Color and I think it's
Iteration
Campaign
We got like that
Hardy from the right
Side of the political Spectrum
I get kind of strong are your berries
Andy from over Frank again in every move against
Direct democracy
Is perceived as
A lot
Control
Skip over Frank is actually one of the last towns in Switzerland still holding on to this town vote
Feeling good like that fear of being invaded
Everywhere
I think it's a fear of loss of culture
Knowing all that
I wasn't sure how to see Nancy story like
Is Nancy's attempt to get citizenship and then
Town shooting her down
Is that
Part of that larger story
I just wasn't sure how to think about Nancy in that contact
Until
I met this one last person in gift over fret
I was talking to some people
About
Nancy and they said oh you want to hear about Nancy
Farmer down the hill
So I went down there you drive down this hill steep steep hill
To get to his farm
There's a really old house and right next to it a barn with cowbells hanging from it
And I came across him
His wife
Boston Fish Market
Just sitting around this round plastic
Patio table and they're both wearing blue season warranty
T-shirt on his. This like white bristly mustache
Rose drink
About drinking a beer and then yeah come on down
So and I sit down at the table introduce yourself
Road Joliet on the door
Sleepover
Cancion he's retired with small pension he's lived there for his whole life
Multiple generation farmer
Nutella nativities
Father bought two toes
They moved here in 1937 he remembers Nick had in the bombers flying over he's like
Swiss forever
Does HIV
Ice for the healthiest Ahuja it's one of the oldest houses here
If I sneak nobody really knows how old
Appraisal
Already at the point Lake about 200 years ago when this became
I can fix retinal Astro anymore
Already done people didn't know how old the host
And right next to the house
Could we go to the horses
Is a barn
We're looking at two horses one of them is blond
Both of them are blind
Paula
Where he keeps his horses
JK
What's new at the horses of his nephew in his nephew he is there is a butcher on the right side
2000 Bachelor
Interesante
Youngest with the remark that
Bachelors never get children
But never go extinct
Yeah
So anyway these horses are where Nancy comes in
Thank you
Because Nancy rides her bicycle down the little road by
House of barefoot by the way she would Cycles by and I peek into the stable and checking the horses
Industry
The way he's at imitating her is like in the way that you know it's visible for them
50 that she's peeking in from the street Nancy complained about
The table here
About that there wasn't enough
Flight
Slimer
She came in me like a fast like a little loud bird I'm done
Press charges against him
I got my. Came by
Found everything is okay
But
Nancy didn't give up she kept on completing this was years ago now and apparently
Still comes by here twice a week to get off her bike and make a little show of checking on his horses
On that he's just
Shaking his ass
And on some level it's this is not all that surprising like this what people say over and over again she's so annoying to just drive you crazy
But on the other hand I feel like
This is what I kind of
Realize the emotional impact of what Nancy was
Doing here like
I mean for one thing this guy has been working with horses on this land
Junkyard for decades and not only that
His is a
Yvette's is there something wrong with you
January 5th
And it was
Clear to me that Nancy was really poking at something that was painful for him
It doesn't with a bit of a heavy heart
That
This type of farming that's not sustainable
Hilton Hotel children like
Ticket in school get a proper job and do something else and there was
Used to have filled
Cherry trees and they would grow wheat book for them to eat and to sell to people who used to have Cows as well
Smallville
The cows with all grades on the hills around the farm
When you in the evening start looking for them and getting them back into the stable find them by following the ringing of their Bell
And in the morning everyday of his life is walking up to the sound of the church
Church bells
Pastiche
Hearing those church bells in the distance
If they cannot get the feeling of home
That I'm that sounds really does to you
And now times are changing
People employed by tech companies in the city
And I'm moving out to this country to live there and just commute in
And everything's getting really really expensive
Can't afford to fire many more
They leased out their land
This way of life
It over
Yeah
And so
There's this massive sense of palpable culture lost people are coming in it is changing
The way he has lived
His entire life
And that is sad
Just cleared it Nancy coming around
Check on his horses it was like
I was just one last
Insults Tumblr see only problem
Couldn't keep quiet act like a you know like an angry wasp
Seahawks realistic Provence Target Aveeno like all the other things that hurt
And so he didn't want it to become a Swiss citizen if you would have
Definitely voted against her but it felt like too angry to even go to this empty
IPhone
He was just like Beauty disgruntled with the entire
Town
So get over Frac is one of the last ounce
To do these Town boats
But they don't have the final say anymore
Because of those court rulings I mentioned earlier
Everyone has the right to
Appeal to government officials in the region
Which
After being rejected by her neighbors
Twice is exactly what Nancy did
And she won from door
Against the town's will
She was naturalized
Buy everything from the Kenton
What did it feel like
To get your citizenship
I like to
Corsola
Zach Wilson
Big feeling of relief
And I didn't really realize how much of that
Actually meant to her as well
And that sometimes you just really really
Have to stick to your guns
I did this
Experience change the way you think about democracy
It's been a busy
Shannon Torres
The whole procedure
Slightly disappointed in democracy
But also taught her a lesson that she says
So today she would say
Democracy is a
Power
And this power should be given to people
Who deals responsibly with it
Is it used to
Power on an emotional level
Insulting monkeys in math
Invita unseen
Is power should be taken away
And honestly
Sitting there with Rudy
Jessie
The system of karate
He said well this is not what democracy
I felt conflicted
Because
I
Understand why he wouldn't want Nancy to be a part of his town and I also kind of I get why it would be painful to give
That kind of a choice
But then the conversation took
A turn now used to meet Islam
We're having philia and keep you
Islam
A lot of people laughing that realized Singapore Pacifica
Austin from the Constable Bosnia Serbia WW2
Computer Guy turkey
When one person
If naturalized
They would bring
Apart from their home country
And
When the partner then comes and stays here 5 or 10 years
And we will get that fit like they will get a switch
Or two that's how I thought you ain't like this development
Celebration game.
Asthma little bit of a headache
Why headache
Mentally dead
Steinhoff
Intelligent
In that moment
I realize that
Behind Nancy story behind the
Just kind of clickbait tale of the woman too annoying to get citizenship
There are all kinds of things that are a lot harder to talk about
Harder to separate out
A real loss
There's fear of
A changing world and the promise of
Received
The promise that people could have a voice in a power
But
Also
Xenophobia
Hostility
And
All that made me think about the conversation I had with lots of
About his family
Moving to Canada and
Do you know him watching hockey but all the things that his family tried to do to make a home in their new country
I'm wondering if you think that
If your family had faced more outright hostility do you think they would have
You know body in on the club as much
Yeah like I think we certainly like like I think there were certainly dark times for my parents were people call them Packy's all the time
Yeah I'm sure they didn't they didn't anyway
Yeah they did like I think it was in part because it was like okay this is the only place that took
Gas like we got a really
Make good here it's not like we have any other options
But I do think like I do think
Like I think my parents felt a lot of probably felt a lot of pressure
Conform in some way like like being the first
You know immigrant generation who
Maybe you still have a trace of an accident Maybe
Because of the food you eat you still smell a little different
I'm sure that generation usually that first generation is like super sensitive about those things in like basically comes out at like
Oh I'm going to be
The most Canadian like more Canadian than any
Yeah
Degree of like erasing you know you're like okay like it like
Forget that I came from another place like let's just erase all of that
Yeah and I think about that and how assimilation to me is always seem like a
Sad word like
The giving up of something
Somewhere you know
Yeah
But at the same time as that sits in my mind
I think about
Okay what if
Lots of lettuce immigrate to Canada
Yeah and they all think like wow thank you so much
Hockey is not for us
And now suddenly hockey is no longer the thing that holds social capital and in some way Canadian identity lose
Does that thing I know it. Now I feel sad or some Indian sport or something yeah
Where to put that
Yeah we can I get that I get that
Feeling like where you're like all like just the thing that I love and all the sudden now there are people here who don't love the things
And I love and
My love is being diluted or like my
Or like or or or even potentially
Supplanted
And that like I think that's a fair thing to feel
There's also a way to like
To sell it you know like it's like okay like let's get some Indian kids in the NHL I remember
Are there was a guy Minnie Mouse
I was like obsessive Manny Malhotra he was like an Indian Canadian guy who is
He's like a hockey player and I was like oh yeah cool like if he is in there like I can start to
Feel my way into it and I think it's just a matter of like
Stella at like share with me why you think this is so great and and let me have some purchase in it you know and then I'll
Call Suddenlink
Like I'm going to love that
Leica III will
Yeah so we did a lot of work on trying to figure out about what happens to people if they get citizen
In some way lettuce
Speak to something that yantai Mueller told me
Really kind of flipped the way that I
Was thinking about citizen
Forecastle
You know. Swiss citizenship
Compared to those who didn't get much more likely to know important facts
Switzerland
They're much more likely to read
Swiss that supposed to Home Country newspaper it's showing that the orientation as we move towards kind of Switzerland and being informed about what's going
Going on the even report let's termination
Suggested
The citizenship
It's not
As some people argue with the endpoint of
Integration
It's not like the crowning achievement of integration process and people work very hard
To become citizens and then
Haven't there
It's more that the citizenship itself can be an important catalyst
That kind of
Facilitates the social political and economic integration
Okay
So I visited Nancy on the day she was going to vote for the first time as a Swiss citizen
I'm nervous you was feeling like my heart's going to visit
I wish I had this on tape but I was not allowed to record in the meeting
I just parked the car
And just I parked the car and was getting out
At the meeting Nancy rode up on her bike
And she been talking all day about how she didn't wear shoes
And
I saw that she was wearing shoes and they were a sparkly
Sequined silver shoes
Why are you wearing shoes here and she said
It's my first meeting as a citizen I just really want to make a good impression and it was just so interesting that the
The Moors was rejected
The more she was like no shoes
No cowbells at I am Nancy in the second she is
Accepted
Do you wear shoes
She starts to compromise
There is a
Like I said that maybe one of the quintessential Canadian Foods really a cup
Backlot food but a Canadian food is out 14 right
It's like a chain
I think I like Greg
Patina
Hot in Toronto Canadian
I know it's a Greg's poutine on the menu if I'm remembering last time I went
It has like a chicken tikka masala
Poutine or something like you're like oh awesome like that's cool like yeah like let's do it both ways
Is butts like match this up and now we're
Now we're all living in the same place
You know my heart is getting physically warm
Hopeful 15 letter forever
That story was reported by Kelly Prime produced by Kelly and also Annie McEwen
Big thanks to lots of Nasser of course and a huge thank you to report harana mayumi Kerber
Primadonna maybe Kerber
That's what I mean
She went around and arranged everything and translated for the story
Also to dominik hangartner
Who is some
Do it works in the garden usually using his hands
Airport Toyota Ali Dineen
End
Gregory corbino
Well I guess we should yodel out of here let's do it
The coolest thing
Honored
Who played the message press to start of message
Baby Alive with crazy bike
Gas oven light
Third wheeler
Director Van design
Producer
Baby Gap
Tracy hunt match kildee
Glorious
Lattice macular Melissa O'Donnell have a crime
Rbny and Wally West
And this message