Ouat
Northern listening to Radiolab
Radiolab WNYC
Hate this is
Pat Walters
Coming at you today with the final episode of R-rated mini-series on intelligence
G
Answer for this last
Episode we wanted to check the mood
Because everybody in the series together
We did
Lots of Stories on human
Intelligence
But we also found ourselves thinking about intelligence in other end
Enter to get into that we decided to host an event
All about animals
And today we're going to share that event with you
Just a quick warning at there are
Some curse words
I and Joe
So say that mine
And the reason that we're doing this is because a couple of months ago
I ended up on the phone with the science writer I really love named an amber
And then went on a rant
About how messed up is that
We only seem able to talk about animal intelligence in terms of our own until
He said
So much of animal intelligence research
I is built on making animals do stuff
That we feel like
Humans would be good at
Instead of considering their Intelligence on their own
And tonight we decided we're doing episode about animal intelligence
That shifts the focus from
From us
To them
That considers their unique abilities
On their own terms
I enjoy doing so
I hopefully might help us redefine a little bit what we think about
Intelligence
A general for Olive
And because we're humans and
We like
Contest we decide to make a competition
Here's how to work
We have four contestants
Who engages series of head-to-head bounce
To convince a panel of judges
That their animal is the
I'm going to bring up our first pair of contestants in a moment
But I
First
Let's meet our judges
Oh well music
Okay
How's your first please welcome
Did you guys have done
Hundreds of stories about all kinds of smart animals
I please welcome the colors to Radiolab Jad abumrad and Rubber products
I kind of had to use the guys
The obvious choices
But we also invited one more
Surprised
The real star of our judging panel
From humble beginnings in a shelter in Oklahoma City
She's risen to the highest levels of success in Show Business in New York
Her television credits include high maintenance
In the leftovers
And she is appeared in more Productions
Of the Broadway play Annie
In the role of Sandy
Been any other actor like any great Stars she goes by only one name please welcome
Macy
Messi is a dog
Got 30
I pound
Scruffy brown fur
Cheap try to drag on the stage and I happen to a chair next gen
Okay
So before we start I just want to ask the judges here one question
Kind of set the terms
And make sure we all know what we're looking for
I want you guys to just Define intelligence
In three sentences
How did you find what you're looking for in the contestants
Asteroids
Robert Wayne
Animal Inn
And I would say that a very smart animals
Should be
Asked
How well do you understand
Expand your world
Knowing that
Summer sniffers and summer tasters in
Summer Good Flyers with someone but really
When you see a fox
On a snowy day
Jump into a
Pound of snow
And somehow land right on the little mouse that's two feet down
I think that's a smart
Smart animal
Jen
I think what I'm going to pay attention to
IR arguments on behalf of creatures where you see the creatures
Encounter some kind of Ops
Sickle
And then
Problem solved their way around
Show pictures that are flexible can adapt very quickly
And I'm going to give a special nod I think two creatures that show Collective
Intelligencer like moral intelligence if that's even a thing
Hokkaido that's what I'm going to be paid
Okay good
Macy
What do you think about how would you define intelligence Macy
She just repeating Chad really
Phuket
We brought our contestants onto the stage
And Whitworth is they each had four minutes
Make a case for why they thought their animal ortho
The smartest
At the end of each round the judge
Boat
And we bring out the next to Kin.
You already meet our contestants
Okay
Okay so first up we have
Tracy Clayton
Android nougat
Tracy Clayton host the hit podcast another round
And more recently the podcast
Strong black Legends
Sir
Man
Andrew Mendoza is that comedian
Central and a host
Alive science and comedy show in Brooklyn called drunks
Okay so Tracy what
What animal did you bring for the
The smartest animal in the world hands down is the crow
I was just kidding
I know he meant that This Is War now this is a fight
What's your entry for this rent
Slime mold
The first round
Crow versus
Slime mold where to start with Tracy
Ready
If you don't know how amazing crows are as not your fault
It's because the media is racist and they told you how to feel about crows for example
Most famous crimes in the world are these
Here you got the dumb the crows from Dumbo
Address like Street pimp
5 crows were brightly colored
Women smoking a cigar
Shiftless lazy
Black
Coincidence I'm sure
And then here
This is a this is Jim Crow If you don't know that Google you got to do a Google
We don't have enough time
Go
Here is why crows are the best
Number one
They are
Extremely resource
Have you all heard of this dude named ASAP
Heroes in Fable
One of them was about a crow who had to get like a
Treat or something out of like a picture or something
And so what he did was he dropped
Stones into the picture
Does the water level with raise
Got what you want to guess what
Crows really do that for real in real life Ben Tracy showed a video of a
Crow and a half empty glass
Water
Any Chromecast adding stones into the glass until the water was at the rim and the crow could get it
Most of my ex's cannot
Do this
Pro to solve problems
Puzzles with as many as 8 depth
Definitely none of my
What number does
Crows can be taught
The Talk
Write the surprise guest
Crow or a human
English words or human word
Human
I'm Crow the songbirds y'all still the Ravens but you don't know that because you're not parrots and not brightly colored
They're black again racist
Be no it's not it's the doesn't count
But their vocalization skills are really really really good when you get a chance Google
Talking Crow
And you'll find some videos I think we have one
Oh my God
Yep yep exactly
Yeah that's an actual Crow crow look inside a scan Raven
Point number
3B
C pointer BC
Crows have funerals right
But they have funerals for
Good reasons that the humans don't have funerals for good reason
But humans have funerals and make ourselves feel better like oh my God I miss big mama's so much I just need to
One more time before she goes on to the whatever in the sky
I thought we still have wait where we literally sit around and look at a dead body and wait for it to wake up even though we know it's not going
Evolve out of that please it's not as mad sin
Black rose
Have funeral
Right though Rashad.
Bless
Just that he's
Rashad is the crow
So the crowds alike but cannot what it what is the cuss word
Things you can say whatever Hitman Rashad what the f***
What happened
Install
All the crows like congregate around Rashad
To see what killed him so they can be like we need to stay away from whatever wish I was doing because
Little Richard now you know
Point number 4
Is that they can recognize faces for up to five years and hold grudges so if you walk past two-and-a-half years
They just like 9 don't fuk with this number here they thought all their friends
The next time you come around the crows are going to be
This motherfuker
Don't trust him
It's amazing the explosion
Crocheted not be called a murder
They should be called something smarter like a symposium of
All right
Winter is here
Next up with Jordan Mendoza with the slime mold
Repurpose slide of a petri dish with this
Yellow lightning bolt T streak going across it
What is this
But guys don't worry I freaking looked it up
A slime mold is a brainless single-celled
Pulsating wad of yellow goo
I learned if you put a slime mold in an environment where there is a complex decision to make
Princeton switch directory directions
Choose to find a good food source
The superorganism can solve that problem relatively easily by spreading its cytoplasm out
Advancing and retreating in response to what
What is fine
So this is a superorganism
Composed of thousands of nuclei
And they will collectively decide to make a decision for the group
Humans on the other hand are not at all good at collectively finding a good food source
Have you ever tried to order seamless with another person not easy
What are we going to do
Pizza Korean Chinese sushi
My roommate and I always end up choosing diarrhea
There are three General types of slime molds
Plasmodial slime molds
Cellular slime molds
And Gary Busey
Jordan put up a picture of Gary Busey if AB
If you don't know you looks like
Google
The joke here is that Gary Busey looks
And is like a slime mold
Plasmodial slime molds are masses of thousands of nuclei that move around by spreading out in a fractal pattern
Learning the lay of the land and even solving mazes and mapping Network
Incredible efficiency
How efficient
It took human engineers
Years to map out a Tokyo rail
It took a slime molds
Hours
I read that in an article titled watch this lyme-old dunk on Japanese engineers
I'm just kidding I made that article title up with that
The second type is a cellular slime mold and this spends most of his life as a single freewheeling amoeba
Which sounds like a sitcom that just got greenlit on Fox
This quirky freewheeling amoeba just got the consulting job of her dreams
Mackenzie balance love work and New York City
Check out all the single-celled ladies starring Zooey Deschanel as the slime mold
Then turn around explain how slime mold look out for each other in this amazing way when one amoeba runs out of food
Did something incredible happens it starts emitting chemical pulse
Assembling clusters of other amoeba into a larger
Superorganism
This is a process called chemotaxis
Or if it's trying to save money
Uberpool to find more food and then
When dies
Chemotaxis shows that slime molds are altruistic
Being still sacrifice themselves for the benefit of the
Species
I on the other hand
Will never die for the benefit of others
I won't even give my subway seat up to an elderly pregnant women who
Repairing a piece of furniture
Finally the last category is slime mold
Is Gary Busey
An oscar-nominated American actor who has appeared in over a hundred and fifty films including Lethal Weapon the firm and
Piranha 3DD
In conclusion slime molds are very smart please vote for me because I'm Asian and if you don't vote for me that's right
Did not know we could do that for the record
Do diaper Dreamin designs
Okay judges
Deliberating asking questions with what are your reactions to these two
Bros vs Glenmoor multiplied so many times
Could come too complicated and sophisticated conclusions is a pretty impressive accomplishment
Each individual
But also I
I was leaning in that direction but there's a sort of give
The crow a fair Shake
Alyssa Crow
Can see if a person and then remember it and disseminate
The reputation
For two and a half years
So that that's some kind of crow
Language
You have a crow feeling one way or the other
She does
She's saying that she's not sure that she knows that many
Molds
Oklahoma City is a sort of dry town and they don't have a forests there
So she feels a little bit
I'm equal to the challenge here
What would
Oh well
She did study the ones
Do you speak dog rubber I understand that I can't
Okay well she is partial to Gary Busey which okay
I just confused her
Well let's let's let's vote when we go down the line Chad what do you choose
I think just
On I think I'm going to have to go to the
Slime mold
Wow after giving up for Crows okay so Jed slime old Robert
I under eye in a with great respect for cross that hate well I I agree they can but I'm I'm going to go
With the slime mold as well
Amazing
Macy
What are we what do we have for Macy
Crowd surprising
Alright alright surprising For Your Love of Gary Busey from
Took the judges voted in favor of the
Slime mold
An app that we brought up our next
Set of contestants
Depend a whole new pair
Okay
Let's get our next contestant up here
Laurel braitman and Dan Egbert give it up everybody
An ember is a writer for slate and the New York Times magazine
And all right man is the author of the best-selling book animal Madness and a teacher at Stanford
Laurel
What I animal are you entering into the mix
Sperm whales
Hermleigh I'm way okay good
And then what will you be bringing to the table to chicken
David chicken
Okay
Okay I will start
With Laurel
Take it away
Sperm whales
Are huge
The biggest toothed whales
But in a lot of ways
They're like us
They have big brands
And really complex socialized
But unlike us
They live in a matriarchal culture
They probably even have stronger social and emotional bonds than we do
Young males go off on their own to find a new pod and then everyone else stays together for life
Sperm whales communicate a lot like us to physically and with
But they also have a third way and I think we should consider it like
Sense
Maybe you think about echolocation like boat sonar
Like a ping goes out
And then it bounces of the sound bounces off
Nothing in their environment in the
Comes back
And giving give that boat like a grainy shape of whatever
A dolphin and whale sonar does this too and so do bats
But animal sonar also comes back as a physical feeling
In a case of sperm whales is really loud
They make the loudest sound
Any animal on Earth
Up to 230 decibels
I know
Is actually it's louder than standing next to a jet engine at
Are eardrums can rupture at 150.
Which is basically like a gun going off next to your head
Sperm whales make these click
Creaking and buzzing sound in their knees
And then they amplify and direct them with this big fatty wack
Taxi organ in their forehead
Called the melon and it's like
I know it's
Terrible where they probably have another word for it
But it's like a huge built-in megaphone in their head
Just like that but way louder like
Read aloud so loud that it would have hurt us to be listening to
And this echolocation is so powerful that if they can track a squid up to a mile away
And their social messages
Probably travel just as far
So knowing what we know is are really complex social lives
Expense likely comes with its own emotional
Experiences to
But we can't name those because we don't know what those feelings are
So
I want you to try to imagine it
What would it be like to be like
Reading a book
What's suddenly finding out
Just by feeling it
But your ex girlfriend is coming around the corner of an underwater Shelf
A half a mile away
Now
She broke up with you
Matriarchal culture
You been so lonely but now you know the signal is meant for you just because of how it feels
When you pick it up
And not only that but you have an immediate accurate picture of exactly what she looks like not just the shape of her
But the perfect curve of her jaw her sexy 12 inch layer of blubber
That you've missed
But also you can also immediately tell how much
She cares about you too and that's why she's coming
Also you've been hunting a giant squid
Might have a particular emotion that goes along with experiences
Any maybe even have a different sense of
In the mid-1980s a neuropsychologist named Harry Garrison
Proposed that are collocated Communications that are emotional and nature
For joy
Might be
Experience by whales and dolphins as more than shared information they at
Actually might come in as shared feelings
Shared emotional
Experiences
Jerrison thought that this might give rise to something called the communal self
Meaning whales and dolphins might not say
I they might always be a we
We are sad
We are
And there's some evidence for this
So like in whale strandings for example
When a bunch of whales
We'll come up to the shore and strand themselves and die
But when we actually
Do studies on the way we find out that maybe only one or two and 100 was actually sick
Something is going on here and I think it may be
We sick
Stop
I don't want to end on that super sad no guys
It also might be why whales in
I'm going to tell you one really nice singing
Turn it over to the mystery mystery animal
It also might be why dolphins and whales are
So many reports of them coming to the aid of swimmers who are struggling
Or fending off sharks from somebody who really needs
Action or help
Or even doing things like this which I love
This is a case of
Sperm whales who adopted a deformed dolphin
So if I'm golfing with us
Spinal abnormality who they welcomed into their pod
So
Sperm whales man
What looks like extreme empathy to us
Might just Demby being themselves
Or maybe it's a new kind of intelligence
One that requires
A kind of communal feeling as opposed to thoughts about other people's
Thank you
Okay well done
Very good
All right
Next up
Denenberg
Breakfast chicken
Let me start with s
A chicken
Can beat a human in tic tac toe
A chicken almost always
Pizza human in tic-tac-toe
I learn this back
In high school when my friend Rob
Obsessed with one particular
Chateau plain chicken named Willie
Who lived at the video arcade at Mott Street
Add Willie beat RAB
Over and over and over again it's
Tic-tac-toe
Willie wasn't unique birds like him we're one
A pretty common Carnival attraction their popularity
Peaked in the early 80s when train chickens were shipped around the country
Rent it out for $200 a day
Or sold for several thousand dollars each
Annies chickens were so good at Tic-tac-toe
That humans were getting demoralized
At least one distributor started having the birds lose on purpose
Every fifth game
To make it seem more fair
How it turned out this whole thing it started years earlier in the south at a place called the IQ zoo in Hot Springs Ark
There
A pair of scientists Marion
And Keller Breland head build a business out of training up strange animal behavior
There's it was like a product showroom a place to demo
The Ducks they talked
How to play piano
Rabbits the drove around and little fire truck search
Hamsters on trapeze
Butterfree
You don't have to be that smart to go on trapeze
The prelims mosto
Popular in during Act
What's the bird brand
A chicken in a box which disappeared behind a screen to Packo's onto a game board
Chinatown Willie with one of those or maybe
Someone else's knockoff in any case I watch that chicken play a lot of tic tac toe
Peering over my shoulder I tried to figure out
Chicken secret strategy
But then
Last week
Really last week
I discovered that all those observations were
Preferred not as I got ready for tonight's talk I stumbled across a copy of an old instruction manual
What's the breland's
Would send out with her bird rain units
According to that manual
Chicken in the Box
Wasn't really playing Tic-Tac-Toe at all in fact
Behind the screen there's nothing but a single light bulb and a switch
When the light went on the chickenpox
Headed out to appeared somewhere on the board in the spot chosen by computer
I found this
Kind of devastating
Partly because I promised had a talk on the intelligence
The chicken
But here's the reality
Chickens are kind of dumb
As we seen their even dumb compared to other birds they don't
Have funerals
You know they're not
I or make tools like crows
They don't learn to speak like parrots in fact if a chicken has any special talents at all
Is that when you chop off its head it can go on acting
Like a chicken
4 days or weeks or even months
But still I think there's something amazing about Willie and the other bird brain
It's not that these chickens were smart enough to beat us at Tic Tac
Because they weren't
Is that we humans
We're dumb enough to lose
I mean
Tic-tac-toe is not a complicated game actually
If you can think of had just a bit you ought to be able to play any round of tic tac toe to withdraw even against the computer and yeah
It seems we humans can't or won't succeed even at this
Very modest test of our intelligence
I think that's useful to remember especially tonight
Because this whole
Project
2-ranked species according to their smarts takes it as a given
The ugliest exists between the very dumbest in the very smartest animals that the chicken and the chimpanzee or the spur
Sperm whale or the crow live on separate continents of cognition
But I call that vanity
That's what Willie taught us that
There we were standing the same arcade
Befuddled by the same computer
Each unable to succeed at the same simple game
We were joined together across
Several hundred million years of evolution by what we couldn't do
Judges
A boat for chicken
Is a vote for finding that common ground
If the vote for Unity
Absentia
I vote for chicken
It's about for all of us
Okay wow
So
This is reading our heartfelt together continuum
What I would I
I don't even know what what are you which way are you leaning
I did not know that stuff about the sperm whale actually played
I'm at speed with the China Township in the 1980s so I probably should not have lost
So I don't know whether the other judge
Is awake
Butner
At this point Macy had that curled up in
You all can take a backseat of judging this is like the Merrell
Cheapest vacation I mean
If we were better humans
We would have the kind of antenna and radar that a great actress would have what you can just somehow
Project
Return
You go to a movie night with her and you go
Your every move she makes like
Touches you
Why can't I quit
I am enthralled by this
With what you saying
Doesn't like Streep
With jacuzzis she's a blood waves
Starter solenoid
She's feeling Street right now
Can I ask if I see question about the best formula is
Isn't all emotion somehow it is fits a physical physical rap
So is it a question degrees is it somehow they are experiencing that
Or is it an entirely different kind of intelligence
I think that they have another way of
Accessing their emotional
Then we do so they have everything we have
Write like their friend can go up and clap them on the back or
Giving up
Sperm whale hug or whatever they still have that and they also have language but then they have his other thing
Which item just because
I avoid my inbox or whatever
It feels like some form of email right like you send it at a great distance
What is emotional and you pick it up with your face
I I think I got it ice my heart go sperm well I thought the political platform I vote chicken
But my heart says
It's a good service to you both I guess perfume
I go sperm
Sperm whale 2
But this point the first round was finished at the judges
Waitin on some pretty compelling cases for
The crow the spine mold
Sperm whale and the chicken
Next up we have another round of competition same basic idea we asked each of our four contestants to frame
A smart animal
Table to make a case for
But this time we threw a couple curveballs at them
Matt and the final crowning of the world's smartest animal
After a quick break
This is me and Arisa from amps
Radiolab
Enhancing public understanding of Science and
Knology
Modern world
More information
Monat
Www
Scott Sloan.
So in part one of our competition we heard Arguments for the intelligent
Of The Crow
Define mold
Sperm whale and the chicken
And in part 2 we decided to raise the stakes a little
I give our competitors a couple more chine
The first challenge is that they are now going to have to compete with their nemesis from the first round
Turn around at 2 on to round
The other challenge we gave them is we noticed that
We weren't really paying that much attention to the furry mammals I think a lot of us imagined that we may be amongst
Smartest animals in in the in the animal kingdom and some of us want yeah
Let's do some furry mammals but the challenge was not to do any of The Usual Suspects
Texto no humans of course
No chimpanzees no elephants
I know dogs are messy
Come up with an unexpectedly smart
Furry mammal
I with your with your new former enemy team a
So
Brush up where Dan and Laurel who had
Absolutely
No trouble at all agreeing on a smart for a man
Obviously raccoon
OG is Animal Kingdom been showing us how to live
Cities for really long time
There is no other choice
Why are we talking about this
Loretta no-brainer
All right
In the fall of 1906
22 wyndance
In the fall of 1906 this headline smart raccoons was picked up by several major newspapers
The column underneath
Describe the mister and misses goal apart
Who been traveling from town to town in a double-decker covered wagon
Bonita family of trained raccoons that work for them
Is Chimney Sweep
Who's not the only story of its kind
In those years
Raccoons were often touted by reporters for their high intelligence
What are sagacity order Skillet making mischief
This is the odd and tragic story of how we came to understand briefly a century ago
That raccoons were among the very shrewdest animals of all
And then
We forgot
The link between animals
Slipperiness and it's smarts was once well established among scientist
At Columbia University Edward Thorndike have been testing the intelligence of cats and dogs
By locking them in box
Heat seal the box with latches Bolt
String police
Leave a snack
Motivation
This was
Houdini
In the lab
An escape room
But for animal
Then in 1907
Psychologist in Oklahoma named Lawrence Wooster call thought to put raccoon through the same puzzle boxes to learn
If you put it there proper place in the scale of mammalian and television
And he found some amazing things
His raccoons Tom Jim Jack
And Dolly
What did X Break Free of the puzzle box and then ignore the food reward it was as if they'd gone through the exercise
Turn service of their hunger is other animals by 2 but
To satisfy an inner curiosity
Cole also found that his raccoons unlike cat
Could learn to escape a given box just by watching humans
Based on this and other work
A soft consensus came together and psychology that raccoons were in fact quite high on the scales mammalian intelligence
Much higher than a cat
Weird dog
At any rate and maybe even on a par with primates
But alas
This whole idea was soon to be challenged
Had erased
In the same year Cole publisher
Research
The president Teddy Roosevelt lashed out against the tendency of nature writers to ascribe
Human-like abilities to raccoons and other animals
The president was an avid Outdoorsman called this fake news
Within a few years some of Cole's most impressive findings with raccoons were challenged by his peers
Even scientists
Who believed in Kohl's research would find it hard to follow up for one thing the raccoon say meant to study
Escaping
Add a new paradigm was spreading through psychology one that had little time from using sauna raccoons imagination or
Real City
What's loneliness
In place of Tom and Jim and Jack and Dolly
There were rats
Nameless rat
Do raccoons banished from the lab and then As Cities grew they vanished from our lives
Out of sight
And for a while
How to find
But
Turns out as people moved out of the country and into the cities are raccoons followed us
Urban spaces aren't just the perfect place for raccoons to demonstrate their intelligence
Butts
I argue that they are also
Making them even smarter
Today though the people that know the most about Urban raccoons are the people whose job it is to get them out of our Urban spaces
Like Mr Raccoon
AKA
Junio Costa
The number-one no-kill Humane raccoon Trapper of the California Bay Area
He told me that the animals are bold and curious and he pretty much everything
Raccoons move into your attic
Enter crawl spaces they study us
The user tiny sensitive hands to manipulate lock
And laugh
Or pray out Loose nails
Thenar things open and then they take
Running leaps also to knock things over
A raccoon will work on a problem like lifting up a garage door or prying open a window or praying event
Vent cover off of a basement
4 hours until they figure it out
Sometimes it'll come back like night after night to work on the problem until they see
And once they do they keep coming back
Mr. raccoon told me that once he got a call every night
From the same neighborhood for like 2 weeks
Because one ambitious raccoon figured out they were all tract homes and so
What would work to get into one of these tracks houses with work in the entire neighborhood so she just went house-to-house
The house the house
Stop
Recruiter really the old one of the only animal species to fare better
As humans spread all over the planet
Not only that
But we re
Problems for
Each other
They try to outsmart us
We try to outsmart
It's unclear to me which of us is getting more intelligent faster
Picked up where Tracy Clayton and Jordan Mendoza
Endive animal was
A little harder than that
Type of mammal or type of mammal marsupial
Yeah okay have our own individual
Traci kicked off 14 marsupial with this adorable little creature called the quokka
Which looks more like a chubby squirrel with teddy bear eyes and little black
I think we're having literally if you're if you haven't had hold on to it
If you're sitting in the chair
Hold on to the
Hold on to your boy
Sam Jackson I thought that the response would be okay
This ladies and gentlemen not to oversell it is
Is the most
Amazing animal facts
Do whatever here
In your life
Are you ready
Judges are you ready
Maybe
She's into it
Kids on the pocket is a smartest anime
Serious business
When
Try today
We're going to get through this as a family I swear
Okay when approached by a predator
Apparent quokka
I don't know if it's the dad the mom do you know pronouns I don't know their lives
Approached by a predator
If a parent
With a child
They will throw the child at
The Predator to distract it
While it runs away I need to describe this image
For the people who cannot do at this point Tracy had an illustration up in the screen of
Passing a baby into a bad car
Batman Arkham you know this is really smart
Cuz you make another one
You can make
You know
If the both of y'all die
Because
Did your dad attached to your child then what happens to your genetic line it doesn't get passed on
This way
Crab legs
Oh s***
I like Emily but
I can make another I can make Emily II
Emily
Parham and that's that the crocodiles on the Live Another Day
The crocodile don't survive longer than anyone else well
Thank you
It's your turn if you
Is very funny I am scared and Jordans decided to fight for
Kind of a weird
So boy supposed to be a presentation
The smartest animal is
And a long time ago I was like
Yeah I'm going to do koalas
But then I looked it up and apparently koalas are famously stupid
Here's how dumb koalas are their brains only take 2% of their body mass
Which is Apparently one of the smallest brain to body mass ratios
Any mammal
Clothes brands are also super smooth which is bad because
The more folds your brain has the
The smarter you are
The human brain is like Marie kondo lots of folding
Shout out to my condo heads out there sparking Joy
You Know Who You Are
Honestly I love her so much
Ozark
So dumb they even sound dumb listen to this
Perhaps koalas aren't conventionally intelligent
Just like how choosing koalas for this presentation wasn't conventionally intelligent
But I propose that we rethink intelligence
Partly because I'm stuck with this animal but mostly because I believe that this animal is in many ways smarter than us
Perhaps koalas are like how my mom describes me
Smart in their own special way
Let's compare koalas and humans
Sissy who look smart bike
Comparison
This is a koalas daily schedule
A koala sleeps 20 hours a day
While the remaining four hours they spend eating and mating
Incredible
Imagine only being awake for the amount of hours you need to
To eat and have sex
I mean I'm not a huge fan of sex because I'm quote-unquote awful at it but boy do I love eating
The human schedule on the other hand is horrendous
Weekly Pond average 6.8 hours a night
We wait for my nightmares then spend 10 hours reading emails and worrying
5 hours on a conference call
In 2 hours eating dinner out of a big bowl while watching billions and hoping to God that Paul Giamatti voice can Lola
What's to sleep again
In conclusion koalas have optimized themselves for Life's greatest gift
Eating
Having sex
Those who enjoy that kind of thing and sleeping without the need to listen to Paul giamatti's voice
And that
Smart
Now who sounds
Stupid
Still calling
I realize I clapped with everyone else
You know what I am proud of myself
Feeding a koala would have done that
Wow okay so
We've heard from both the hairs
Raccoons
Marsupials
Quokka and
Dum /
Smart qua
So after that but proceed with you guys it was time for the final judging there's a lot.
Taking their a lot of different arguments were put forward I
Think I got to give this to the marsupial
Duet alright alright alright
I missed your call which
Well I was I was I was impressed by the boldness of the chicken of the
But before I got a chance to always win
Raymond has walked a giant bone across the stage and giving it to Macy the dog judge
A pretty curious incident of bribery went down
Don't you do it to keep things Fair we decided to just throw the whole thing over to the audio
The boat with their Applause
After their take
On this murder
Animal abuse
So just to recap the contenders were the crow the slime mold
Sperm whale the chicken
The raccoon and Marcy
And the winter going to be audience
What does
I think
If I think it's pretty clear who the winner is
Elasta QP
A drum roll
Yeah right
Drum roll please
That we could do it here
I think the winner of the contest the smartest animal in the world is
This firm will the crown goes to lower brightness
You had a good price somewhere I don't know who out here from our team has it
Enterprise
I
We had we had planned to give a give a gold
The winner
And instead we have a red fish
A betta fish
Forever our winner Laurel braitman one more time
She flew here from California with the
The leg of an animal
She's flying back with a
Tennessee attendance of rams
The judge
Okay
That's that's our show everyone thank you thank you that everyone please give it up
Thank you thank you to our contributors Dan ingber Laurel braitman Tracy Clayton Jordan Mendoza
Take a Bow
Robert Crowe H Macy & bill berloni
I thank you to the Radiolab staff and put this night together Rachel Cusick
Talking bird in the whole team here at the Greene space
Add Tonight Show and all our reporting on the intelligence series that starting to come out next Thursday
Has been supported by science and boxer by Simon Foundation initiative
Dedicated to engaging everyone with the process of science assignments and additional support for Radiolab
/ the Alfred P Sloan Foundation enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world
Thank you all for coming out
We can't do this without you coming in the rain
And have a great night
Hi this is Skype calling from New York New York
Minilab is created by dad and Rod is produced by Soren wheeler billing capias are directors.
And if I do the Lautenberg is our executive producer our staff includes Simon Adler back of breast
Play Rachel Cusick David Gable Bethel happy Tracy hunt Nora Keller Matt killed
Robert Froehlich
Any McEwen lots of gnostic
Barre Quarry Ariane Wax Hot Walters and Molly Webster with help from FEMA only
Where Fortuna Ruth Samuel Imani Leonard
Neil Danita Harrison Bach and Melissa O'Donnell
Are fact-checker is Michelle Harris