Are you awake
Northern listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
200k
Ready
Hey I'm Jared
I'm Robert krulwich this is Radiolab
And we're getting ready
For what this whole podcaster about
Here is an invitation
If you join us in the next life
We will be going
Not a second year I hate
Facebook I hate that everybody knows this
Are there so many of them
You ladies and gentlemen are witnessing the death of privacy
Yes it happened we thought we
Anyhow back to the flow
And this particular episode is more or less
Invitation for you to get ready for the next episode episode we are working on Fury
Seriously right now
About
The periodic table of elements we're going to tell
Individual stories about the different elements
The stories are going to take it
Space
Deep man-made holes in the middle of America into our cells
All kinds of place
So this week we decided to make a small
Telescope
Preview
In which we go to one
Apartment
In one building in the sea
Occupied by the rather singular
Dr. Oliver Sacks
We should say this was a visit we paid him about
7 years ago I think
This is the story that in a very real way in
Inspired us to do this
Upcoming at the
About the Alamo
I will also know by the way that I love you
Is intensive
Right now
Which makes
Perfectly wonderful
Enjoy
Alpha-gal
I think that's always been a desire to somehow
Plastic rice and classify
The world around us
And when you were in
I don't know when I can 8th grade when they
When the teacher comes in and general science and he pulls down the periodic
Table of elements
Yeah I want to be a scientist but not for me but for kids who love this kind of thing
Oliver Sacks
ESO a couple years ago we'd went to talk to Oliver Sacks about something
Was that supposed to use was going to talk to him and I was
Tagging along for the hell of it
For some reason
We ended up in his
Bathroom
Maybe to look at a book or something
He seems have facts and figures in this is wrong
. a lot of us in there
That's when we noticed
Elements on the wall in the bathroom
Wow funny
Periodic table the bathroom but then he said well you know if you go out to the couch you'll see.
Embroidered with the periodic table and then he took a Swiss bedroom
Where you should assist periodic table comforter
On the tungsten
But the cool part
Was when he took us to the living room
We had this describe what it's before us here
Alter a little dictionary Stan on top of which was a beautiful
Mahogany boxes
Find wooden box at the size of a Backgammon set
Periodic table of the elements is a very fine wooden and if you can't open it
It's a
Play The Sims where to find wood comes from Russia
Is there a trick to opening it
Okay we've all seen the periodic table pinyin chart
But I was response there there were the usual elements
We have like 90 some odd little
Little tubes
Hydrogen + nitrogen
2 time for drama having my 72nd birthday tomorrow and element 72 is half an hour
Iraq
Do what they sound like
I have coming to me I hope it arrives today and English of hafnium which would be very about tomorrow
Satisfied
I'll be able to hold it in my hand my first love of chemistry have to do with the essential
Yeah one of the liquid album I love the colors around me Brown
Lobster very very beautiful day the physical properties
Best trapped in a little vial yes
Cuz I I I really need to know things really crazy about that box
And this you don't get from from looking at it.
Chart on the wall is it all those elements
Ashley
My everything we can see and perceive this
Table right here the thief in my mouth
Sky ocean mountains it all
Need of some combination of elements from that box
And the Box itself
Gives it all in deep
Deep
Order
I have noticed myself
I can't help noticing
Elements
Organized
In a very special
Sort of way
I have managed to not notice
I find it a little odd
Then you could organize them at all I don't even know how to begin the process of figuring out there to relate
Well then you are sort of recapitulating Watch
I know what what everyone felt in the
In the early days question a really early days people thought there were just four of them
The ancient notion of elements that took the form of
Basically the thoughts of the whole world
Could be composed of these four ingredients
Different way
Then in the 18th century was skipping ahead of it
Small pieces like wind became castles
Like oxygen and hydrogen and nitrogen Earth
God divided up into things like salsa
Phosphorus
I am and eventually chemist got all the way down to the root which was the atom
That's really what an element is it's a particular kind of atom the problem was though
When chemists begin to start measuring the atoms they found that they were all different sizes and types like one would be heavy
Another would be light third one be really friendly likes to link up with other items worth the 4th would be a loner
Anyway, combinations like heavy friendly
Heavy shy light friendly light shine what was the pattern that was the question could they fit all of these differences
Similarities
Let me hear show you a picture of the
Here's where we get to Oliver's here outside.
I see this cold that will be Dmitri Mendeleev
Over has a black and white picture of him
His
Habits man is not going to win any
Any beauty looks like a mix
Strip between the Rasputin
Anthem
Who do I mean I mean he is a big nose a Shaggy slightly unkempt white beard and mustache the puzzle
All over the place
Piercing eyes
Thick eyebrows
And looks like he's in a hunchback position
Generally if you met him on the sidewalk you probably want to walk around it
Yucky didn't believe in wasting time going to a barber
The degree of your passion when you look at this man
You think he's a beautiful looking guy or do you see what I see
Isaac Mendeleev had a beautiful mind
And when that mine
Can get Sonic
Train and it was
Is a long life York what's the Moscow
Strange things
As you're about to hear
I'll be right back
My name is Annalise and I'm calling right before going to bed
In Des Moines Iowa
Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the
The modern world
More information about Saloon at www.starone.org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
About what we're calling tiny moments
Brilliance
Basically I want to hear about this
Times when a kid you know did something
It just means you lean back and say
Well
How do they do that
Maybe it was the moment that I
Kids you've been reading to 4 month started reading back
To you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lesson
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed they're ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the
Epic moments where a kid does something super smart
It doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story
T-shirt
Go to radiolab.org
Brilliance
And record a short Audiomack
Again that's radiolab.org / brilliance
Thank you so much
Hey I'm Jonathan rod
Radiolab Oliver Sacks talking about his hero
Dmitri Mendeleev now
Okay
In 1860
Around 1860
What trains going order Russia Mendeleev
Could afford to pay claims he was often on in Norman
Journeys the time since you couldn't do chemical experiments whatever he would take
Take playing cards with the name
A various elements that chemical and physical properties
And he would play what he called chemical solitaire
Sorting them for lightness or sorting
Wanted II don't know the details but you know we can imagine right
On the trainees looking out the window
Hydrogen and oxygen made of silica
A shuffling
What's the pattern
Until one night
This week in February
Of 1869 he is said to have had a dream and stream all the atoms of all the elements of all the way
That was a small one dance was everyone's the friendly ones to shine once they all begin to dance in his mind and then
Into a grid
Be woke
With a vision of the periodic table
Dreams wrote on the back of an amp
The thing about what he wrote on the back that envelope
It starts out so simply left to right the atoms just get heavier and heavier and heavier
But every so often while they're getting heavier their other trades
Diamagnetic or whatever those traits repeat
Simple repeating structure you get a table that you can read in a million ways
There's so many ways to read this table
Use your imagination
You can see yourself in there
Shy kid
Weather
Difficulty forming relationships
And I sometimes compared myself to the
Inert gases
Inert gas
Their very eyes
The baby I could nothing
Because I I felt
They too had difficulties
Human relations
Button
I
Just now left the chair in his move to the library
Give me thick
Actually a Dangerously
This is a handbook
Physics and chemistry
Did you see it
Is 5000
I had a smaller version
As a boy
I'm done
Brooding
In this book
It seems to me just pasta
Did one of the inert gases
Might be seduced
Did the combination
By the most Act
Element of oil
Which was flowing
This lonely lonely gas might find a partner somehow do they ever get together
It came to me with great joy when I found out her
In the 1960s
Did ASU Canadian cannabis
I had in fact made
A floor light up set on
Elemental
Love
And speaking of Love event tickets come here
He showed us
Small painting
In the paint
Then there was this dramatic
YouTube
Fowling
On the side of a mountain
Holding two stone tablets over his head in the sky was filled with lightning
Wasn't it was Dmitri Mendeleev when I heard of how
Mendeleev
Haddam
Discover
The periodic table
I imagined Amendola
SSO
Going up to a chemical Sinai
I'm coming down with a tablet
Of the periodic law
And when I mentioned this fantasy
To Pisa
Silicon
My friend a narcissist
How do you keep the picture
As a Young Man
The peak
Are the chemical cyanide behind him
Holding a lot
The tap
Are the periodic table
Which raises maybe the deepest question of all
Did Mendeleev think this up and impose it upon the world or was this pattern always
Is there
In which case mendeleyev just
Remove the veil and set out there you are is the periodic table a discovery or invention
Is it a human construct
Who is it a revelation of the cosmical Define water is it so to speak God's abacus
Okay so that was our visit with wow did I just get gas
Carried away with
The sound
But yes it is a little bit
The closet cluttered but it's a long time ago was long time ago
That was a visit to Oliver Sacks
Add also preview to an upcoming episode that we're making right now.
Which I'm really excited
Hope to be back to that
In the meantime I'm a witch
This is Radio app
Hi this is joumana calling
Aamco bedside Arabia
Radiolab
Is produced by Jared Evan
Our staff includes Brenna Farrell ellenhorn
David Gable Dylan Keith
Matt kielty
Andy Mills
Latif Nasser
Kelsey Padgett
Ariana wax
Molly Webster
Serenity wheeler
NJ New York
With help from them yet oh my kitty Molly McBride Jake
Jacobsen Alexandra Lee Young
Kathy two and
Simon Adler
I fact-checkers are Eva Dasher and Michelle Harris