Okay before we start
New York
New York City
If you're listening any live in New York you know somebody who lives in New York or New Jersey you know
Long Island yeah wherever New York
Ish
I know that we have a live show on Wednesday May 16th
We are taping a new episode
Of a series that is
Shortly to be here
From amazing producer Molly Webster it's all about sex this particular event
Daily sex ed
Come join Molly and Company for a night of stories debate end
Nervous laughter
You can get tickets at radiolab.org sex ed
Can be good
Also what you're about to hear is going to be good but we should warn some of you that there will be descriptions in
In this coming up coming package right now.
Kind of Grandma and about people dying in the desert so
Hope there's some kids in your house or you don't wanna listen to that maybe
Take a break
Otherwise
Here we go
Weight units
Listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
So we come back here
Will you see you got another case
What is
What are those
Hairs
What's a strained muscle
SmartStyle closest I can
The closest thing I can
Can say is that
The muscle dries out
So we could string and shredded
Let's go actually let's just start from the beginning okay so so we are and what what room is this
We're in the special procedures room
Pima County Office of the medical examiner
And what we're looking at here is a case
Mostly skeletal remains do we have that we have a
Skull
A few we have some
Parts of the
Define it looks like and then just
And all three all three major bones of the lower limb saw the two thigh bones and femurs
To tibia
Tua fibula
We didn't we know it's the mail he's in adults
22:30
40 year old
Migrant
It came in and lay
January
And
Animals found in
Maybe 50% of the
The skeleton is missing
Is upper Limbs and his pelvis and most
Spider missing
In his hands and feet
We have evidence here that a vulture
Speeding was feeding on the person
But I don't know if this is it
The hive beetle there globally and these hide beetle specialising in
Eating dried hard tissue still eating
Yeah yes he in his Colony would have been on the body
Wow in the body bag and although we try to get most of them off during our exam
You can see there's lots of little crevices were a single bug could
Could be
Wow
Oh wow that's
So
Yeah wow
I'm Chad album run time Robert krulwich Radiolab and today represent the final episode of our border trilogy
Eatwith Reserve lots of Nasser and Tracy hunt and this is episode 3 which were going
What remains
Yeah okay so just to catch everyone up your lot.
The person I was just talking to his name is Bruce
Anderson
He's a forensic anthropologist at the Pima County Office of the medical examiner in Arizona which is where
When they find a body of a unidentified migrant in the Sonoran Desert
That's where they bring them
And
Bruce
Had been working there you know on and off since the 1980s but he told me that it was only nearly 2,000 that he started
Seeing you know
Just more and more and more of these migrant bodies being brought in and we're just crushed by the
Weights of all the dead
All the missing person
Such reports
It's like working at Mass disaster when
People are still dying and plansource
Crashing around you
And you
You throw your hands up in the air so
Sometimes when you just think when's it going to stop
And it hasn't stopped
The number of bodies found last year was in the same range as the year before
The number of people crossing did go down after Donald Trump's inauguration but traffic is basically rebounded so
People are still coming through the deserts are not being tutored
Which meat is Wonder is deterrence that fundamental idea behind our current border policy
Is it even pause
In some ways that's a policy
Which we talked about in our last episode
But it's also a human
Is Jason still there I'm still here and that's what let us back to the person who we started this whole journey with
The Anthropologist Jason De Leon
All right can you hear lots of to pressure can good morning
Well I feel like maybe we should just start off where we left off
Which is that you were going to tell us this
The story of
Of Maricela
Sure when was this by the way
This has been
Joel June of 2012
Okay so we had been
About two weeks into the pig experiment is the series of experiments were json
Team most students
Looked at how
Pigs decompose in the desert
In order to understand how people.
I was in the desert and it wasn't until about two weeks into this experiment where we
We're out hiking one day with the group of about 9
People
Down in Southern Arizona
It's on this particular day
On this trail that I had hiked
Many many times
Student
And run ahead to
To check the fountain was taking pictures of us
As we're walking up a hill
Ethan Roberts yelling at his he says hey you got to come up here
Something has happened
So I threw my backpack down
Anatrace up this hill
And by the time I get up there right I see that that he's kind of staring at this
Body that's just laying face-down in the
It's on the trail
Like a fully intact body
Yeah
A woman's body
If you could tell it was a woman because she had long hair
You know she's wearing camouflage clothes
Stretch pants
Women's running shoes on
She's got a scrunchie around her wrist
But
The rest of it I mean her body was incredibly bloated them to the point where a little bit was about to
Them to pop them all the gases that had built up
Beside of her
Her body cavity
I didn't know what to do at this point I mean student start walking up I mean these are we young
Students we had someone in the group who was
For some of the students this is the first time they've seen a dead body
One of them was crying I tell everyone I said Hey look
You got to go sit down and give me a second here to figure out what
What is we're going to do here
The first he called the police we do that and then we kind of
Had a conversation of God weekend
Photograph this person are we going to record any information is it so we still doing research right now
And Jason decided
Yeah we should
We should document
Uno's downgraded green discoloration
About what she was wearing brown to Black discoloration of arms and legs pictures of the body or fingers have started to curl
Ankles are swollen to the point
Leather sneakers
Seemed ready to pop off
Is a steady hissing of intestinal gases
And then it just got to the point where I was like okay
This is enough I don't want to
Do this anymore
And so they covered her with a blanket
Because
Jason noticed the birds
Circling overhead for turkey vulture
And so at that point they just sort of sat down and waited
For the police to come the sheriff
An hour went by
For just waiting with the body
Is about 5 hours in
That a sheriff and three border patrol agents show up
And they had hiked 3 miles to get to Json with a stretcher
Until they bring the stretcher
The sheriff
Puts on gloves
He ask them a few questions like did you guys put
Put the blanket on there
And then they roll her into this white body bag
And as the authorities do that
Jason cashews Face Down json gets to see your face for the first time
And so he writes a paragraph in his book and it's
It's pretty gruesome but I'm going to read to you the paragraph that
He he writes about in his butt
As her body turns I see what is left of her face
It is frightening and unrecognizable as human
The mouth is an aural purple and black
Cool that
I can't see her eyes because of mouth is too hard to look away from
The skin around the lips is stretched out of shape
Has already been melted
Her nose is smashed in and pushed up
She died face-down
And the Flesh on the front side of her skull
Asafa
I can't order to fit around the dirt and rocks beneath her
The scene is a Pastiche of metallic gray A&P grain
Whatever Beauty and Humanity that once existed in her face
Has been replaced
Buy Stone colored cool
Stuck in the Middle screen
It's a look you can never get away from
After this thing that happened and it really
Just shook me in a lot of different ways he just couldn't shake the question
Who was this woman
How did she end up face down in the desert
So that night I remember Jason calling me just called a friend of his
A woman named Robin Reineke
And being really clearly shaken and you know asking for advice
Robin Ashley runs this nonprofit in Tucson called the Colibri Center for human rights
And they do a lot of work with the missing and with bodies that have been recovered
So Jason tells her look we've today we had this this thing we found this person out here and could you help us ID her
Now the thing is Robin's office is actually in the medical examiner's office so that means
Just down the hall from Robin is
The guy we met at the beginning Bruce Anderson
A couple hundred people are least bones of a person are in here
Bruce is working on the medical examiner sign
Anytime and unidentified migrant body comes in Bruce tries to piece together who this person is looking at
Dimensions in the shape of the skull markers
Robustness of the bones I like looking at the length of the bones or the density of the bones by the fusion of these
Separate bones
Weather some bones in the body are fused together which is something that happens right after puberty
What age the person is there sex their weight their height and in the case of the woman that
Jason found
Her body was surprisingly in relatively good condition Tok
Pretty quickly
They were able to determine you know
Probably in her 30s she's five
But for
They were able to get
Fingerprints from her as well
Meanwhile on the other side on Robin side so each of these tabs as a person
Is that right
She's dealing with
Hundreds of missing persons report
All day everyday she spends her days
Kitchen calls going through voicemail which is full of relatives searching I'm looking for my uncle he disappeared into
2010 or I'm looking for my daughter she crossed two weeks ago we haven't heard from her and she's also getting tips
From different people at different organizations
Any sexy one of those calls
That leads to a break
In the case
Of the body the json
Okay
This is an email from me from 20
Hi Jason just a quick update regarding the woman that your group found
The case number is 1250
1867 and as of yet she's not been identified
Robin tells Jason that she got a call from an eight organization that had spoken to a guy would cross the desert
Start with a big group of people
Around the same time and around the same area where Jason found
The body
He said that he recently left behind two fellow Travelers who were in serious Medical
Distress
He said one of them
Was an elderly man
70 years old
And the other was a woman maybe from Guatemala or Ecuador late thirties early forties
It isn't certain that this group is related
2 ml 12:50
It's highly likely
I will contact
Guatemalan and Ecuadorian consulate
Regarding new Miss
And eventually using all the information they got gathered Robin was able to determine that the body to Jason
Found its the body
Of a 31 year old Ecuadorian woman
Name Maricela
Alcapurria Marcela
Zagreb Croatia
Robin gets in touch with Jason and tell him Jason and ask
Her I would just
Would appreciate if you could
You don't help me at all connect
With this family
That request would oddly enough
Read Json to New York City that story in just a moment
Hey it's made from Cincinnati Ohio Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world formation about Sloan at WWE
UW. Sloan. Org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers were looking for stories
About what we're calling
Brilliance
Basically I want to hear about those times when I
Did you know did something
It just means you lean back and say wow
How do they do that
Maybe it was the moment that our kids you've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of their musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed they're writing music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the
Specific moments where
Kid does something super smart but doesn't have anything to do with the test
If you have a story please share it with us
Go to radiolab.org
Flash brilliance
Record short audio message
Again that's radiolab.org / Brillion
Thank you so much
Jad Robert Radiolab we are back with the third installment of our border Trilogy what remains
When we left Jason along with Robin from the clery center
Add manage to ID the body of the woman he found in the desert and so now he was trying to get in touch with her family
I don't know when people disappear when I die in a desert I think that the family makeup
People had been so I was hoping that if I could find this person
Family
I could at least say
This is what it was like when we found her
This is what we think had happened
The Robin was eventually able to get Json the contact information for maricela's
Brother-in-law who will call Fernando and
I make the awkward phone call that says hey
I'm the person that found Maricela on the desert
And I would like to come and see you if that's possible
Turns out Fernando actually lives in New York City
But he had spoken to Maricela just before she left
And when we heard his story we decided okay we would have send a report at Ray C hunt
To talk with him
Yes I went to visit Fernando at his apartment in Queens
Jubileeblais
She was there with his three dogs
Friendly guy little shorter than me neatly dressed
You got in a dark hair longer on top shorter on the sides and
When I got there
He pulled out a bunch of photos Maddy Salo
This is their marriage their wedding photos
Shoes design brother's wife
So in this picture that Fernando showing me it's his brother and Marcella they're in the church and they're posing at the all
Alter cheese in a white satin gown her hair is
Long and dark and shiny and she got kind of like an oval shaped face
You know she she looks beautiful but even though it's her wedding day that the thing that struck me is
Is that she's not smiling
Not even a little bit
Is he with you like what she serious like that it is it'll actually that's part of the reason why
My mother said she didn't like Christmas in the beginning
She said you know she always has an angry face on
She looks like somebody who doesn't have a lot of friends
And on top of that
Tornado said she also had a habit of getting his brother in trouble
You know she'll tell my brother to sneak out of the house to go see her
Dancing parties La permission you know those kinds of things
But
Banana says she even sleep on the family / she help out at home
She treated my mom really well especially his mother
Actually I think my mother loves her more than she loved.
So my cell and Fernando's brother they got married they ended up having three kids
Two boys and a girl
Mary said I had a job in a factory that made counterfeit jeans
I think Levi's
And Fernando's brother he would go around to different Villages selling sodas
They just couldn't really managed to make ends meet they were living real rough
At the time I mean going when I went to the house and saw with
So Jason after he connected with Fernando D actually ended up going down to Ecuador to meet
Marsalis family
Before she had left him and they were living in a one-room
Plywood
Shaq with a dirt floor
And animals running running to the house and you know what she had told her
Relatives recycled my kids are literally starving here yo comprendo La Casa Para
Prodigy
Tamia
At the time I wasn't able to help out as much financially because I was also helping build a house for my parents where they were also going to go
And so I wasn't able to support them as much or help out with things
Set School Minneapolis unit place on Del Escuela in so you know what she really wanted to do
You know in order to like Central
Schooling all that she really wanted them to have what she never had never had anything
So that was really
The pressure that you was under
So Fernandez in 2012 he called home
Are you dumb
One time when I come home my mom said that she wanted to talk to me
So I said okay on the phone and she told me that she wanted to come here
She told him that she and his brother they wanted to follow in his footsteps
That if they could come to New York like he had
They can make money send it back home and how about their kids
But that was the only way
Immediately
Fernando was like
Absolutely not
No
So
Fernando told her no because
He didn't want her to go through the same thing he went through
10 years before
When he going to Sunnyvale
He was 17 years old I'm about to turn 18
And his aunt was about to go to New York
And she convinced him and his parents
That if he went to New York he be able to get a job make more money and support his family from there
To have a better life to help
Things we need it
So my father thought about it and gave his permission
But he told me not to stay here too long and so he use his grandfather's
Land as collateral and took out a loan for $12,000
$12
Yeah I do know what the interest rate was on the loan 10%
10%
Yeah
So one thing that a lot of people have talked about is the fact that prevention to deterrence
It professionalized the human smuggling business because not only do these migrants need be no guidance
From all these South and Central American countries
They also need guidance
Do the desert
So now you have the smuggling business that's
More expensive
And also more dangerous
Yessir the coyote
Cold as fat 15 days maximum
Fernando says he and his aunt took a bus from Ecuador to Peru
And then from Peru they flew to Panama
Got another bus
Somewhere in Costa Rica
In really mountainous
There was Ripper all that
This bus pulled over and the coyote he was with them at that point just said okay you have to get up here
And
Cookie donut
And they threw them on the ground towards the river
And they said you have to cross the river and someone will find you there and signal to that person
Becoming a single media
At the very most we were left there like that
With my aunt saying
Hold on that wasn't the deal
The deal was to take us all the way to Mexico in cars but from that point
We started Crossing mountains on foot horrible thing started
From that point on they were packed into the trunks of taxis hidden in basements
Chicken coops and Hutch
Totally filled with rats in 3 months into this journey
A journey That was supposed to take just 15 days
Somewhere in Mexico
Fernando says that he has undertaken to this run down Hacienda
This just
Sprawling Ranch House
Inside the red house
Javier Madero ciento cincuenta personas
I
There were more than 250 people there
From all over the world Chinese and American from every country
From all over South America
There's all these rooms filled with people and Fernando actually says that they were all these armed guards
All over the place
Nobody was allowed to leave
And so we were
How to make enchiladas
And in there for about a month
And while he was there deported until Jason what happened to me there
Abuse sexually
Fernando says that he was sitting outside the Hacienda when they with his aunt
When a group of men approached him and told him that he has to go inside with them
And he said no that he was fine sitting there you know outside
Let's be quiet
Begged him not to hurt me.
Please not to be with me or do anything to me and they said no don't worry is that the only one
Tascam questioned inside but that wasn't what they wanted to look you can come
With this now or you can come with us later after we beat up your aunt so finally Fernando relented
And went with them
And when they got inside Hacienda they went into a room and once we were inside
They raped me
3 *
Mercedes
That's okay I'll make it
UPS Memorial maker
After that I went to
I just wanted to die
After couple of weeks
Fernando is on finally got out of this Hacienda and they start their Trek into the desert
Fernando's thinks that he went through the same desert that Monticello would try to
Cross 10 years later
He's actually caught by the border patrol and held for about a month
Before he manages to bail himself
Out of detention
And make his way to New York
And Fernando says he shared all of this with Maricela except his own rate
But he
Did tell her that migrants to get raped
That he seen it happen that he knows it happens
When I told her all of that she said
None of that what happened to her
She knew how to defend yourself and you know what you have to
She would hit people and then he told her you might have to go without food or sleep outside
Came up as an import tariff
If I said that didn't matter that all that mattered was
Getting here because the kids are the ones that matter X
Any sacrifice made is worth it for your kids
And then he
Doesn't talk to me anymore that's that's actually the last phone call they ever have
Because he thinks that if he cuts her off maybe she'll just give up
But she goes to one of her brothers
And her brother says that he would only pay for her to go but he's not going to pay for her husband's ago
She was going to come back herself did you try to tell your brother looks eec you shouldn't let her come here by yourself, it always
CC ligament
Yeah
Yeah I called but my brother said that there wasn't another option
And that he wanted to go first
But her brother has put the condition that she goes
And
Because they didn't have another option she said she would go
Mid-2012 Maricela left Ecuador
About three weeks later right before she walked into the desert
Medicine center family a message on Facebook
She told them I don't know how I'm going to get there
But I'm going for my family
God willing I will get there
Wenatchee
Mi Corazon
Only they were from the consulate
And I said okay finally she can found
And then they told me
Unicorn kisses and they didn't know
What day exactly she died but that's
She's been dead for about a month
Exact time in the movie open Amazon okay Anthony album Mezmur
Pictures of really
Difficult
Wondering
If I'm going to do more damage than then goodbye by
Going to meet these folks
8 months after marcela's death Jason came to New York to meet Fernando and he brought with him
The pictures of Marcella's body that he took when he
When you found her in the desert
Yeah he was like this right now show me the photos and I was
Just dancing around that for
Over an hour
Decongestant katana
Fotos de Maria Fuentes
Jason Warren that the photos were
Really upsetting
They were so many like that
But I said that it's okay to show them to me and I'll give him the book of photos that I printed
Innocent pictures of the shrine that we built for her
I'm in the desert it's got pictures of my students who were there and then eventually
It's just pictures of like the back of her head so it's her hair
It's some of the clothing
It's her it's her hand
It's all the photos in the truth is that
22 pieces to see your
Imagine everything she had to endure in the desert
She tried to keep going
Dragging herself
Jason brought me photos of
How she was found in
Body
Abstract
Trying to keep going
Before maricelis body was sent back to Ecuador
Fernanda decided they should have it sent to New York first
Don't sass
When I talk to my family I said you know
Her dream was really to arrive here
And so I thought
At least we can fulfill that dream with her body
To be able to have
To have a wake for her here
They held a wake at a Funeral Home in Queens
Almost a hundred family members and friends came to celebrate maricela's life
They were told to keep the coffin shut
The next day her body went back to Ecuador
Fernando tatis stay in New York because he knows
If he were to go back to Ecuador
It would just be way too hard to try to come back to the United States
He says that you know right now he's just
Trying to
Philip Ramos
Promise that I made to maricela's body when it arrived here
I was going to look after the children
I was going to try to give them
What she had wanted for them
When you think about that conversation do you think that there's anything you could have said that would have made her
Hold her what could happen along the way.
Camino
I thought that would be a way of
Trigger
Gay
And it's worth
Cleaning out
You know I mean more generally
Prevention through deterrence as a as a strategy
Hasn't deterred people from coming to the US either
The annual budget for the border patrol is roughly 3.5 billion dollars bigger than it was
In 1990
We have
About five times as many border patrol agents
And get the number of
Pupil immigrants living here undocumented
Has more than tripled during
From 3 and 1/2 million to
About 11 million
And more people are coming
Every year every day
And more people are dying along the way
Yeah what's it doing here
About a year after Marcella died Jason got a call from her family
Do you want some
Maverick Iceman
The name of drones
Tucker
Another family member had
Appeared in
Pretty much
The same place Marisela.
Which is this
Text Maverick Maverick I'm going back to the to the Arizona desert basically because
Marisela has a
The cousin
Who 13 year old cousin named Jose Tech hoodie
Who disappeared
Almost one year to the day that she died
I was able to kind of triangulate based on interviews with people who he was with and with information from
Cranberries folks
Where we think he went missing
And I told his mom that I would not stop looking in
It took me a couple years to figure out a weighted to
To do that
But right now
It will go back and will you see Toronto
And see what we can come up with
And you know
Better than anyone what happens to bodies in the desert now I think
I mean
Why are you still looking for him
White piano
Yeah but that's calluses that question sounds I guess
Give me part of it I just don't know what else
To do if you feel so
Hopeless
I told his mom
Like I won't I won't stop looking for him I'll do whatever I can whatever little thing that I can do
And if I can't find him
Well maybe I'll find somebody else
Me now so we will
I guess getting mad at me cuz it's run out of batteries
Weather
Do you want to do one more
Moron
The immigration issue
Problems and challenges and is always provides great opportunities for the American people
Babies born on Medicaid
Constitutional rights
Adele music
They can't just arbitrarily stop YouTube because of the
This episode was reported by Latif Nasser and Tracy hunt produced by Matt kielty and
Tracy hunt
Jason De Leon book inspired the series is called the land of open Graves special thanks to our interpreter Allison
Corbett and for giving voice to Fernando in English. Album and Carlos manager
Ted Brunson
Thanks also to Hayden Stewart real Russ Pastrana Paulina Alonso Chavez and Ambassador Jacob Prado from the governor
Mexico
And to the staff at the Pima County medical examiner's office and the Colibri Center for human rights
I'm Jenn I'm Ron I remembered Robux
Listening
This is Lori from Katonah New York Radiolab was created by Javon rod and is produced by Soren wheeler Village
Sr director of sound design srpd at their managing director our stuff together
Bartolomeo Becky Bressler Rachel Cusick David devil methylheptane Matt kielty
Robert krulwich
Annie McEwen lot of nazarick Melissa O'Donnell Aryan whack Pat Walters and Molly Webster with help from a
Amanda rajic J Carlo and read Cannon are fact-checker is Michelle Harris