Before we get started this episode has a lot of strong language including
Repetitive f-bombs
Strung together to a beach
Start listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
I Molly Webster this is gonads episode 5 this week we're bringing you a pair of episodes This Is Us
Second one in the pear
They grew out of our reporting on
X's and y's and all the different biological realities that live inside of us
In this episode
Dana Zim hello hello
I can hear you buy this is Molly Webster I can hear you or one of your working the other ones Purdue
Why would you want to just
Turn the headphones around
Lena is doing something
China historic
I guess you could say and just to start us off Dana uses the pronoun they
Not him or her but they
And a few years ago cuz I was 15 or 14 I can't remember which
I have memory issues
It's around 2014
Dana is filling out passport application and there are two boxes
Male or female
And Dana's like well I'm not either one of those
And so they wrote in a third option
Intersex
Bye-bye basically apply for my passport
Got talked to by the manager of the office
You should be no side inside you. You cannot get this password
And they turn me down and I
Appealing you can appeal a passport app
Yeah
To who
Do you go back to the passport office
Yeah but I feel
The passport office rejected the appeal basically saying male or female
That's all we got from there I found legal counsel
So
Dana and
Suing the state department for a third non female non male option
Seabright Dana into the studio to talk about the State Department case
And
While we were having our conversation what began to unfold like in their personal life story
Was it tale of words
How words have the power to shape the world
I was an Air Force brat
So we moved all over the
Replace
I was born in 1958
Michigan was in the military your dad or your mom
It was a clear Air Force pilot
So is in Alabama for awhile Texas for a while Mark Montana for a while
England for a while as a kid
Grew up with a bunch of Brothers who older brothers and one younger like a whole pack of boys
Only 18 months apart
But they never really felt like one of them
Yeah I got Tuesday
When I start showering with
Other boys in probably like the 5th grade
Sorry
Cheese about
Life-size
And looking physically different down there
My testicles didn't
Book like the other boys would it look like a stuffed sausage it was little
Didn't look right never felt right either
From when you were little
Smaller ball like a girl
The brothers tried to help or
Trying to teach me how to do things better to use my hero 4 try to stick up for me but we will
The world was a scary place
My dad was always gone flying and he was kind of a scary figure
Mother she had
A backhand that wouldn't quit and she never play tennis
And Dana says for some reason
Their parents always kept a close watch on them
Remember once in childhood
We are living on Arkansas the girl.
Store had
Lowe's cut out Barbie Walt doll clothes and when you know where is cardboard
Barbies
She has those and we're playing with those
She and I
Yeah
My dad caught
I got my my butt
Sprite and boys don't play with dolls
My brothers were able to do
Somewhere that but I was allowed to
I'll see you think like if your brother was playing the paper dolls with the neighbor it would have been a different response
Did you have any idea like why
Nope
I knew something was different I just
I have no words
My world
Was very small
I think you could say was partially because of that smallness
An effort to make the world
Like a little bit bigger
In 1978 at 20
You did
That's so interesting because I would think that you would run away from the military after your dad
Frozen air force of one of the stations
What 260 Americans
And I'll be getting there
Day of captivity
The Persian Gulf
Android
Praetorian
Beirut
How did it feel to be to be part of the military or at least away from home
And away from your siblings in your parents
It felt really good I felt a little free
Free free of the confines
But
Couple things happened when I was in the Navy
About 5 years ago
People started thinking I was
I thought I did anyting
To encourage that I didn't date anybody to do anything
Or do you remember how that started or why I was so
Small I didn't go out
Drinking and trying to pick up women with a guy
Yeah
There was somebody on board my first job
Who I guess it was
Putting books and magazines
Are my rock
Greg a contact
Gay-p*** or something horn
Are some books
You could think that leaving gay p***
On someone's bed or bookshelf
It's not that big of a deal or something
Initiation thing or something
But this was at a time before don't ask don't tell where if you are gay
You were kicked out so
I got caught up in
Witch Hunt
You're a one-point
Which is a precursor to the NCIS
The National Institute of security
Navy intelligence service okay
Give me another acronym on May 11th
Anyway so they interrogated me about
Yeah I know who I was dating who I have sex with friends
Yeah you know those kind of things
And then while all that was happening on my second tour late
All
1982 was working below deck is doing some paperwork in a noisy fan room and
An announcement went out on the ship that said that they're going to do a test launch of one of the gigantic missiles on board
But Dana didn't hear the announcement because they were in the super loud room
Anna
I get done with paperwork
I opened
Hatch to go back into the ship
I step out
The gun goes off
Firing a 70lb projectile
20-30 feet away from my head
Holy crap
Now on the Carmen basically white blood out of my ears get me some aspirin and said get your balance back
I can go back to work
Raceway back in those days I didn't know about where you weren't too concerned about
Brain injuries are there that didn't say just go back where you find you know they didn't really realize how much
Screwed up you can be from
Dana said that ever since that time so I can't I have a hard time
Looking backwards
Telling time
Needless to say
After the Witch Hunt
And brain injury
But I'm like
When I got out you know for years after I got out I think it was or a little bit longer I
Started going to Colorado State University
I was about
30 years old
During their first semester Dana was in
A poetry class
And Dana says something in the words of those
Poets and in the class discussion
Christian to go see the college therapy
I walked in and someone you know
I think I'm depressed and I'm think I'm gay
Tell me more about the why you thought you were gay
Two things
All that confusion going on in my mind
Am I a boy or girl kind of thing is I don't really know what the hell is going on with me anyway
Dennis's didn't really feel like a boy like the way other boys do
It kind of felt like an off-kilter kind of boy
What do you call that
And then
All these
Which France
In the Navy got me really excited thinking about
Whether I was or not
Like maybe those guys were seeing
Something The Dana couldn't see it that that was true
I thought well I must be a gay man
Cuz I didn't know anything else
I didn't know how any other term
We had gay lesbian bisexual and we had crossdressers
Oh yeah sorry that you're like okay out of those options which one feels the most like me
What I thought was
So
I want the game a land
You know I didn't date anybody but the therapist that Dana saw ended up recommending that they go join
This group on campus
It was the gay and lesbian Alliance
Which later became the gay lesbian bisexual Alliance
That's how long ago was
This would have been 1989 ish
Yeah like walking into that
Group what is that here I am
What does it feel like to hear you are
You know I don't know what to wake
And they just said I'm welcome have a seat
Are you dating her your father anything like that doesn't me some hard first questions I think I drive
If someone started the conversation went bad
Sign off on certain things
Yeah but they were very welcoming and I thought well at least there is a
Place that I can hang out with people
Accept me for being different
Within a short while
Dana is not just going to meetings but is protesting at the group because
Cuz around that time something called amendment 2 was proposed in Colorado
Local law that protect homosexuals from discrimination
Amendment to close up in Colorado
So
We got ourselves pretty organized
I want to learn Moore County
Republican convention thing oh my god really so you became something of an active
A spokesman for the
TriStar waking up or being woke
What are the term is is
I'm a lot more woke now than I was then
I was like I got my first sip of coffee and the caffeine started okay start to work on your brain
Different colors
There was one problem though
Living as a
Gay man as I was at that time
Dana was not gay
They filled it home as a gay man but they were mostly attracted to women
And towards end of college in their late 30s
Working in the fibers Department doing my studio class
This woman
When he kept coming in and watching me work
She got the wrong me I got to know her
We started dating
We got married
Really
Wow you went all the way to marriage
And this isn't this is
Early aughts or like late night okay
2007 we got divorced
5 years
Yeah didn't work out we both had issues we weren't dealing with
Dana says this. Of their life up through the marriage through the end of it it was very confusing
They're just trying to figure out where they
Stood and they were trying out of these terms like
Bisexual
Also Prince
Transformer into the room
Because I mean I was hearing more more about
Trans
People in Lawton okay
Starting to read a little bit about a so
White well maybe maybe and why did that feel more true than gay male
Or straight male
Where are you because I knew this there was a feminine qualities about myself. I had to record
Okay so
I thought well
Another man I must be a woman in the only kind of woman like I thought I could be was going to be a Transformer
Meaning to Dana a person who was born male but identified as a woman
So you're like
Holy crap so you were like
That's so interesting that like
Well that's where I went to I can't halfway house
HSN it's it's like in
In a world where there's limited words
You're just you're just trying to figure out the word that fits you
Right what's it's like a small steps towards
The truth
So yeah
After the divorce I'm I'm looking at
Myself
Insane okay
What's going on here with me
This isn't working
What Dana discovers
After the break
So cool
Hi this is a net calling from Newcastle California
Radiolab presents gonads is supported in part by science sandbox simons foundation initiative data
Vacated to engaging everyone in the process of science
Additional support for Radiolab is provided by the Alfred p
Sloan Foundation
I hate everybody Pat Walters here I'm a producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
And I request for those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents
Aunts and uncles teachers
We're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments
Basically I want to hear about this
I kid you know did something
It just means you lean back and say
Well
Maybe it was the moment that our kids you've been reading to 4 month started reading
Back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons and you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin
Or maybe the kids in math
Music in the margin of their geometry
We're interested in the
Specific moments where
Kid does something super smart
It doesn't have anything to do with the test
If you have a story
Go to radiolab.org
Flash brilliance
Record a short audio message
And that's radiolab.org
Flash Brewing
Thank you so much
We're back
Episode 5
The story of Dana's in
At this point Dana is divorced and feeling really unsure about who they are
They tried girl trans
Bye
None of it seemed right
I was really just shoveled I was really
I was praying I was like
I wasn't taking care of myself
Dana says at this point
I started to really wonder where is all this confusion
Coming from
So I started digging deeper
Okay
A lot of stuff is going on what happened to me
As a child
I had always have these like Memories
Some of them
Of having surgery as a kid being like 3 4 5 6 Indian Hospital
So I was pretty much there alone most of the time
My grandparents visited me once my dad was her once
How many surgeries do you think there were
I don't know
I'm more than one definitely more than one
Between 3 and 6 years old I have multiple
I just don't know how many
Only had like
Tiny fragments of these memories
It's hard to remember anything when you're 3 anyways
But now in their 50s
Dana started to look back in wonder
What were those surgeries
Also does that explain why I feel so different down there and like why I'm in pain I was in such a
Pain that I was walking bow-legged
Try to keep anything from touching it
If I started working out
Penis surgeries
Trying to figure out what happened there
Okay I don't know what happened to me as a kid but I know I had this pain and I know I had the surgery so maybe they're connect
Right so I started looking up that look a lot of different diagrams of penis surgeries
All these different types of thousands of different penis surgeries in mi
Should I didn't know there was that many
Erectile dysfunction surgeries
Penis pumps
Looking and then I'm like
I was trying to match up scar tissue
02 that was your approach
Am I approached you must have seen some gnarly photos
While searching all these photos on the internet Dana did start to see
Images where the scar tissue like the patterns of the scars
Looked familiar
That's when I found this term
Better sex in the Maya just popped up
On the screen that pops up on
You want to do surgery things
Intersex
What the hell is that
So I typed in Anderson
The internet was full of information
Bills are really starting to go off
Rain in my head drawing
Baby
And I was just starting therapy at the VA Hospital up in Cheyenne Wyoming
Wyoming
She convinced me to go see a urologist at the VA
And he confirmed yesterday that I was intersex
What what does intersex actually even mean in your case cuz it can mean a lot of things like what
Did one of the doctors say she was born with ambiguous genitalia and they constructed
Basic Ray my genitalia look male
Other words like Dana wasn't born with what the doctors would consider male or female genitalia it was like they
Add something that seemed to be there in a large clitoris or maybe a small penis it was unclear
And maybe there's a little bit of a vaginal opening
And Dana's case and as is often the case
Babies that are born this way
Parents don't really know what to do in the doctor will basically say well you got to pick one
And they picked mail
I don't know exactly who made that decision I think it was my father
Shut that off looks like a penis to me
That sounds like my father
But anyway
The doctors
They constructed
Apenas
Should have been
Large clitoris probably
How old are you at this point
When you figured all this out
You are 50
I'm 60 now 10 years ago
Wow
You are 5-0 when you finally found out that you were interested
Next Step
Dana says
When they figured all this out they had
Two simultaneous
Feelings one I was living
Why didn't my parents tell
I
Basically lion true my whole life
Did you call them
Yes
What did your mom say
Not much
She basically was angry back at
She said your boy
You're always be a boy
Would your father still alive when you found out about the inter
Oh yeah I called him to and what did he say
Feeling hot a lot and kind of said he was sorry
Which is where we start reconciling
Did he
Blaine
Where he was coming from it all when you were alone you're a little
No not really but you know
How to learn how to forgive myself for all my anger with my parents
And forgive them as well
Medina says that like a mitts processing that rage
For almost a year
Tell me about the Euphoria why
Because I finally had an answer I mean it was a question I had asked and wondered about my entire life
Open at Point
The question being
Am I a boy or a girl
The answer is yes
Both
Yeah
That was you fart
What does Euphoria feel like to you walking on air
I know what I am and what I had to break the binary
That was
Break the binary
Yeah
Are you okay if I'm not a man I'm not a woman I must be
Intersex or hermaphrodite
That works
But it's not the question I should have been asking it was like who am I and those kind of things but
You're saying the question you should have been asking is who am I not am I a boy or a girl
Be kind of questions most people ask
What Dana means is that those are the kind of questions most people get to ask
But they were so forced
Inter
Like wondering if they were a boy or a girl that they never got
To get to like the big existential life questions that most of us
You know wrestle with they were just
Way back at Ground Zero
But I got unstuck
What is it like me until I find a word that explains you
It was so cool
Ja
I think it was probably the happiest times in my life
YouNow identifier
Herm intersex
Non-binary
Queer
Is there anything in
That that do feel like
Free end
Found and
Start of euphoric and you now or is there anything that
Still feels confining
Yeah pretty much I'm I just had a t-shirt made up so is that but I says you know AF at the bottom of it
Intersex non-binary Queer as Folk I don't know
You look as pretty much yet I got to put on a t-shirt hope nothing else changes
Hello how are you going to put that
Since discovering intersex 10 years ago Dane has become involved in the community rapping and traveling to conferences
I've actually would kick this whole password thing off
And in May of 2018 Dana and the state department were back in front of a judge arguing the case on its constitutional Mary
In September a judge ruled in favor of Dana saying that the federal government cannot refuse a passport based on face
Sick identity
But two months later the state department appealed
Another round of oral arguments is expected this coming spring
Cynthia case began 7 States and three cities including Washington DC have non-gendered identification.
Special thanks for this episode go to Paula Stone Williams Kathy to Matt Collette land illegal and Gerry Callahan
This episode was reported by me Molly Webster and co-produced by Jad abumrad
Reproduction help from Rachel Cusick and editing by Kat Walters
Our word play music was written performed and produced by Majel Connery and Alex overington
And before you go we'd love you to sign up for our newsletter you can do that by going to radiolab.org
Flash newsletter
Ortega
Gonads to
701 - 01
That's gonads
2701 -
Sia
Hi this is James Murr from Denver Colorado
Radiolab was created by Java from Rod
Is produced by Soren wheeler
Dylan Keith is Out director sound design
Burying myself idea
Is a managing director
Simon Adler
Mikey Bustos
Becca Bressler
Rachel Cusick
David Cavell
Bethel hep C
Kasie hunt
Pat Kelsey Robert krulwich
How do you make Yuan
Latif Nasser Melissa O'Donnell
Arianne wack
Pebbles
With help from Shima Ali-A
Tasha hotch
NECA
A fact Checker is Michelle Harris