Northern listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
Okay so how we going to start this I think we should start with a
The first of all time
Is Radiolab and today we're going to start with our producer letter faster
Now you'll let me take you to
Biggest democracy on the planet
Yeah they did that you know in fact
Do you have mobile data
India
Over 800 million voters
And from 2010 to 2012 this guy is why she was in charge
The whole thing from 2010 to 12
And before that election commissioner for 40 years
She told me something that just astonished
They have this crazy rule to be within walking distance
Maximum to kilometers
So not a single of the 800 million + voter test
The travel more than a mile in a bit to get to a polling station
No matter where you are in that country that is India
This is true yes I have pulling sensation in the DeForest
The mountain Reddit
We danced to walk 13 or the way you can read that so you can try
Helicopter party
On camels and elephants
Unamused
Bicycle motorcycle
Which brings us
To the Gir Forest
We have a police station in DeForest
2 in Gujarati
There is a forest
And there is a temple priest
Who lives inside a temple
Deep deep in this Forest
By himself
And so
What career
Is every election
Keep send him into that Forest which by the way
Is the home to the Asiatic lion and there are regular reports of lions actually attack
Basically these guys
12 1/2 miles into the forest
Dragging along with em diss voting
Until they get to this
Like it's like a little Forest Outpost
They get there they sleep overnight
And then early the next morning to set up the polling station
And then they wait they just wait for this guy for him to come and work
And
There's actually a video on YouTube of this emerging
From the forest
Te bote
His name is Muhammad
Burrata
Darsh under is wearing traditional clothes that you know this long sarong type skirt
So he walks into this
Little station
Fills out his ballot
Gets his finger painted with a little red. Right that's to make sure he doesn't vote twice
Which would be a little hard to pull off in the situation but anyway he filled out his ballot
And then
His boat
Get counted
This could be the most effort ever put into making us
Single
Personable
And this is done again
Because no
Voting Indian should be denied a
Place to vote at a convenient location. It's a it's a kind of
Beautifully Noble idea why do you waste money
Because I believe that every single workout
But
It's not like that guys vote actually
You made it
Of course it may every
This is a beautiful
Have a vote vote make beautiful thing in
In principle but it's not vote actually is ever
Decisive like one but never really makes
All the different you want one vote changes the world kind of thing
If not for that one vote
Things would be dead
So I decided
Dig around
End
This is the first thing I came
November 1996
The day before
Clinton Dole presidential alert
Okay and Landers
Chicago columnist
Writes in her column
Dear readers
Tomorrow is election day if you don't bother to vote
You have no right to complain about who gets elected
The essay that follows was sent in by a reader in Missouri
So here we got they were going to read and Landers as mail
Basically
The whole thing cuz it's too long but it is most important
Is one vote
In six
One vote
Dave Oliver Cromwell
Troll of England
In 1649
One vote caused Charles the first of England
2 BX
Oh my God
In 1770
Sixth one vote gave America the English language instead of German in German
The two of us one vote brought Texas into the Union
One vote saved president Andrew Johnson from impeachment
France
From a monarchy
To Republic one vote gave Rutherford B Hayes the
Residence
Sunshine
In 1923 one vote gave Hitler leadership
Now this is a pretty incredible in each case had the vote been missing the result would be different
Write history would be
It's a wonderful place to
Begin anyone who's thinking of not voting
Consider this list
With kare-kare and once they go out and they research and they read their history
They will find it this lists
Totally bogus
Bogus exaggerated mischaracterized
1 volt David Cromwell control of England are you multiple this morning into one of them wrote to me that this was
This quote absurd there was a voting
1645 Cromwell was made
Lieutenant
General of the Cavalry but
No one knows
The margin of that Vogue are you the next with Charles the first to be executed
According to another historian
Complete nonsense over to us this next one one vote gave America the English language instead of German
I never heard of that there was a vote to translate
The laws
And then they decided
Yeah I know maybe it's better.
How to do that
One vote brought Texas into the Union in the Senate
The vote was
Too much
Not 1.
And that wasn't even the decisive vote
The next one vote saved President Andrew Johnson from impeached
A jacket that was true
The guy who made that vote was bribed
Devote when he was bought that it was bought by moving on bed right one vote changed
Plants from a monarchy to a
Republic pressive but
You conveniently omit the fact that there were three Revolutions in the prior 80 years
One vote gave rutherford Hayes the presidency
So this is true ish disputed election so it went to the special committee
And he did win their by ones open it was more like
Politicking that actually like voting
And last
One vote gave Adolf Hitler leadership
Hardy in that case
The vote was actually
2 1
So he got this week
Exactly right exactly wrong
So that concludes our lessons in journalism today when receiving letters from total strangers to Nada
Always assume that they know what they're writing
But it's like a bit
It's more than just a journalistic correction it's like this
Instantiation of everything you believe about the society that you live in it somehow your voice however little
It's important and its value
And for this all to be wrong
Devastating
You know and then you you going to
Distance not make me feel
For even a second that your vote is not valid
That's right
I don't know. It makes me want to put my money where my mouth is
And it's like spine you think one vote matters
Prove it
Make your own
Fact check
List where you can prove that this is not an idealistic
Pipe dream
This is a real thing so are you about
Represent us with absolutely solid thyroid
Softwareone votes matter
Finlanders did her homework
These are the stories that she would bring you any pain and they are going to Dear going to inspire you
If I have any
Say about it
Okay so are you are you ready I am ready let's go
Are they got a lot planned here for the next few minutes
Okay we are going to go to shiney hiney Ranch to shiney hiney Ranch
I'm also going to take you back in time
Time to up drunken scandalous hotel lobby
But before we do any of that I'm going to take you back
To India
Yeah good I'm be back
They're ready to take the onslaught
You're an amazing story I heard from our
Friendly election commissioner Sy quraishi
You just tell it as it unfolded from your perspective
Stocking 2008
Rajasthan the state that I was going for the election
Welcome to Rajasthan is this enormous desert
State in Northwest India with almost
75 million
Nearly
2 caliber
Forneus
And in 2008 they were going into their election
And still dr. CP Joshi
Josie was
In his fifties
A member of the Rajasthan in Congress
Representing the Congress
Party which is a little
Confusing I know but anyway over the past eight years he had been climbing the political ladder
And in 2008
Public party
Gender perceptions
He will be the next chief minister
Which college did Governor so if he wins it's like
He'll be the governor of
75 million
What was your role
With respect to that particular election
I was one of the three-year election Commissioners and so
The day of the election arrives
CP Joshi Congress president
Cpj's Redmond
TB Joshua
Which may not be as big a surprise given the title of the episode
The final tally for the top two finishers
With 60 2216
260 2200m
I mean next sister
Can that be but that's what he that's what he
TS right dude like a Joshi the incumbent it's like no no
Show me the questions on the postal ballot
Like the mail-in ballot
What about 500% ballot
Unit 15 minutes recording with.
Still lost by one vote
Why is weird
Then he called up a second time
Requesting for the recirculating the totals from the machine
Meaning recounting all the electronic
Thousands of ballot adding them all by hand again
And then after that he lost his chief minister
Nobody Love by one more
Now that is
Brutal that is brutal to lose by 1 but it actually get to even more brutal and
Personal because
People started talking about his wife
Biblia
Rumors went
On the day of the election
His wife had gone to a temple
To pray for
And because she was praying at the
Temple she didn't make it to the polling station
She didn't vote
That's
What's the difference
That's a difference
He looks at his wife he can look as I say you didn't
Vote I didn't win
One causes the other
That
Certainly you can take given your family for granted
I said the other day of the pool
The most important Temple is the police station
The most important Temple
Is the polling
But this is CP Joshi I am the person who lost by one vote
Columns
To check this one. Because of
Absence of anybody from my permit
My mother my wife my son
You mind if I talked to your wife a little bit and I was you sleeping with me tonight please give the telephone
Hello hello dr. Joshi you mind introducing yourself for me
Dr namita Joshi you definitely voted for and supported your husband
Definitely
Saigon Village
Totally wrong
A morning prayer Joe she's all this gossip
Started because on the morning of the elec
Dr. Joshi and his son went to
To vote there was a photo op at 1 take pictures when did photo
Was Felicity TV
In-depth photo my wife my wife came from Jaipur and later in the day did go to the polls
I with my in-laws my mother-in-law and sister-in-law
So because
The picture of him and his son was on the news everyone thought so it's because his wife didn't though
Hi CNN Landers was probably covering a simply announced while the wife didn't vote right but this is where
Where things get even
Stranger
There was actually another wife involved
You know that part of the story
Easter
Mustard emetic
So I normally I don't even just that part of the Jody
Am I supposed to go
Shortly after the election
Some of Joshi supporters started coming to him and saying
Yeah and pretty quick and videography
They had proof that one particular woman had voted
Twice how do you vote twice voted at two different polling stations once under her married name and ones under her maiden
Is the very very rare
What happened
And here's the
What advice
It was the wife of the man who won the election
And so glad I went for the election petition in high court and then Supreme Court and they ruled it was true she did fragile
Italy vote but then what because after all this week on DVD
Did the word commode
Equal
Citizen Times
So what are they going to do that but to do what
What happened was it this investigation
Actually took
4 years for them to figure all of this
The stuff out
And the term
That they were being liked is a five-year term
So then what happened did they did they let him serve out his term or did they
Let it be like this that said because you destroyed me that's expiring
If it was me I think I would be so bitter
But you don't
Sound very bitter
First time it's your birthday is a blessing this guy first Reese's being defeated by his opponent who by the way we
Reached out to but he was
Sexy was not able to talk to us
Being beaten by that
Guy Joshi
She's it as a sort of blessing in disguise
Sky Zone
Because
6 months after his loss
There was a special election
Not the
Street-level in Rodger time but the federal Universal like Indian level
So he ran for this election
And not only did he win
But eventually he got tapped
Tubete minister of railways
Which in India that's a big deal.
Destiny I decided
Did I should do a lose by one vote Elijah Cummings government of India
Steve have not lost me one more time.
What does it mean how do you make sense of
I can only say that
Everybody is important
That message goes above my erection English
So after we hung up
The phone our reporter and fixer no engine of almach who is
Stop over on the other side with the Joshi
She just kept asking them questions
In this case
Do women wear matching Focus
I did my best positively but she did
Digital
Destiny
Bt1 destiny
To that extent
You can understand stupid
Honestly I
Like I'm a little bit on her side I mean like this was Eva
Matter story but it was a fraudulent boat
I wasn't expecting for you to Champion the cause of
Of one Blood by giving me
A stolen I'll be honest I took me a little bit by surprise too but the next one vote story
I promise you it isn't
Hayirli legal better be
Totally legal Place each side deep in the heart
Leaving
I'm on Bam Bam Bam Bam Bam before you break into song
We have to go to
Oh
Hey this is Marta calling from Toronto Ontario
Radiolab
Supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloane @www.
Sloan. Org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here I'm a producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
And I request for those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents
Aunts and uncles teachers
We're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments
Basically I want to hear about this
I kid you know did something
It just means you read back and say
Well
Maybe it was the moment that our kids you've been reading to 4 month
Started reading
Back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of their music
Or maybe the kids in math
Music in the margin of their geometry
We're interested in the
Specific moments where
A kid does something super smart
It doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story
Go to radiolab.org
Flash brilliance
Record a short audio message
And that's radiolab.org
Flash Brewing
Thank you so much
Alright we are back I'm Robert krulwich this is Radiolab and today our producer lettuce Nassar is taking us
On his tour de force
Of Great Moments
When one vote
Maddie
And as promised
What's the next story
Certified to be fraud free
Takes place
In Texas
So these are the property up on the right at a cattle ranch
Tiny cold shiney hiney
And the guy you just heard is
Alan Russell
And I'm the Emperor of shiney hiney
Shane
Okay
Explain I should back up a little bit
In 2009 Alan had just finished up grad school he was living in Dallas
With his parents
Yep
Yep then one day I was actually on my way back from a ski trip
And I get a call from the man I know
You know he said he was looking for
Somebody that needed
Change in their housing situation and had an opportunity to discuss
And so
I called him back
And he said I've got this Thousand Acre Ranch up north of Dallas
What's the time trying to develop
Nothing up there right now.
Cows in field but
I need someone to live up there for awhile in a mobile home
And if you do it
I'll make it worth your while
So for $150 a month I got a three-bedroom trailer with the kitchen in the living room
Room and bedroom and office and all that
You got his utilities paid for free internet and put in that satellite dish so I can get high speed in a
And he's like
Yeah I'll do it handshake deal
And
The next thing I know you know he's ordering a trailer and I'm changing my residence
Can you describe what it looks like it here
We got fields
As far as the eye can see
Ripley at Allen give reporter Stephanie kwolek with tour of the ranch
And for those cowpatty honestly it was refreshing
To do
Campfire
Man gets hot I would go for a dip in the
The watering hole
If I didn't want to see another human being I could go
Days or weeks
Without seeing another human beings probably in the biggest piece of shape and got
So if he's getting all these
Goody's
What's his buddy to developer getting in return well well it is basically required me living
Up here as the only legal resident
In other words the only eligible voters
Voting
What you going to vote for
So
Allen's buddy and his crew they want to put houses on this
The first they have to put in a bunch of utilities you know
Streets and sewers all things that normally taxpayers
Of course these guys are private businessman not a government that can Levy taxes
But according to
It's law property owners and residents can get together hold an election
And decide to create a
Special district
It's like a tiny little government that can love you
Which would be ideal for these Developers
Is then they could just get a loan to build the streets and stuff
I didn't pay the loan back through that tack
Problem is
There aren't any residents on this land there's no one to vote this whole deal into existence
In the first place
And that
Is where Allen
Once he's living on this land
And pay the tax
So they told him
You can live up your cheap with all utilities and internet paid for
You just have to vote in this
Election didn't push me in any One Direction but it was
Clear one if there's one issue on the ballot there's a reason that one issues on the ballot and
Woman named Angela comes in she brings me my voting booth which is basically a little table it says like a
Folding table along with an electronic voting machine and a whole list
You have to open pause and 7 a.m. you have to close you have to be the election judge have to sign this things like that
Does that mean that this guy is going to be the motor in the election was going to run the election
Can you go vote
Manage his own vote
Exactly had to be aware of the perimeter and cuz if if somebody could come up with a
Political poster or something and tried to put that up within a hundred feet of the polling location I would have had to ask them
Stop
Oh yeah
Of course
I wouldn't want my kitty cats to know how I voted on that election
Get Arena and Lucius then Valley question because they were I was the election judge but they were my
Pulling a cyst
Even got name tags
So
Day of the election
Sun rising over
For the plains of Texas
Set up my music outside
What kind of music are you playing
Play House music
The crank the beats
Setup is voting booth standall legs plug it in Boots up
Hello you know whatever and I think it was like pre-programmed with the ballot
There is no worries
Got a trailer dance music
Cat's name tags
Voting machine
Is this part I literally sat here from 7 a.m. to 7 p.m. but then at some point he
Cert makes a decision
What is the ballot look like
It was not as simple as yes or no
I want to say there were there like three or four parts to it
Here in front of me
Actually
Have the
Ballot
Okay weather Missouri proposition on several Proposition 1
Literally just says District
For there's a box
Against there's a box
Shall we do this
Exact
And then after that there's a section where he vote
What's in the board of
So there are so yes vote for 5 it's like a choose 5 of the below
And you have
1 2 3 4
There are only five candidates issues five people and there's a list
Volume up five people
And then this little government that I've just created one proposition ago will be able to
To borrow money and the people who live here afterwards
Will a severe back
So Allen
Voted yes
For everything
Yep or did it say what it was for or was it just like all know I know there was a dollar
Paramount and if I remember correctly I want to say it was
340 million dollars
240 it was something like that
371270000
Which means that the future resident
It's of this
Property
Are on the hook for nearly four hundred million dollars
Is this
Practice at this point there are
Right now at the moment I just got this email from the
The government there are
1237 of these types of Utility District
To cross Texas right now they cover
2.9
Million Acres
So that's basically
To Delaware's and according to the Houston Chronicle you've got two million Texans right now
Living
It is kind of utility
How much money has been raised
Jamaica's government
Ballpark figure again from Houston Chronicle okay outstanding debt
Of these types of utilities disk
Billion dollar
60 billion billion dollars
60 B billion
This feels
Wrong to me
Like these
Taxes
What created by individuals
Who squatted on property
For a while and mostly laugh
Didn't have to pay the
It just feels a little unfair to
To me anyway for the people who will live there when they will pay the
The taxes and never go
Got to vote
If somebody you know lives in their $300,000 house
And every year that they have to pay $3,000 in tax
That they wouldn't have if I had not
Voted the way that I did
Would they resent that
Maybe
But
People complain about about paying their taxes
And yet they get in the car and they drive on the road that's supported by federal tax
Dollars
Dysuria
This is Republican state senator Jane Nelson
And she argued that these
Fish and chips but way too much power in the hands of a single voter
When she brought the committee a bill
That would fix
The problem
Is required minimum
40 Motors
Basically she said these election should require no fewer
10:45
Which would help ensure the actual residence
Community wild horses
But at least for now the state legislators in Texas have decided
They're all you need to pass
The tax of this kind is one vote
That's the story
Wework coming to celebrate
One vote matters in a glorious wave the flag sort of like
Not enough
Fraud in India and
And taxation without representation what I wanted
You wanted some yay or something okay I have one I have one more I have one final score
Real good
And why don't you
Come with
Why don't you do this
That you make me happy
Yes
Come with me let's figure it out
Now y'all in New York
I'm going to put on my most southern accent now
Alright so this is Carol Busey
And I'm Robert so we let the frobert in Tracy
Okay
Hi. By the way is a reporter and producer Tracy hunt
It's a three-on-one
Well you know we southern girls we can handle anything
Carol is a professor of history at the volunteer state Community College in Tennessee near Nashville
Well do understand that Nashville is now the it
City
Seems to be
But for our story there was a moment in Nashville
History is not just the it
City it was the
Laugh
Stand in a long and vicious
Struggle
For women to get the right to vote
It was the summer of 1920
That's a real history recording of a 101 year old woman and Abby Crawford Milton
Who in that very hot summer 1920
Descended upon their
I spell with hundred and hundreds of other
Suffragists like herself anti-suffragists
Lawyers
Politicians
Business people they all came to Nashville for the
Legislative battle
Okay
Now let me stop here and take us one step back
And we're also going to bring an historian Jill Lepore history at Harvard
She told us that at the end of the Civil War 1865
Congress was considering this new amendment to give former slaves the right to vote
Yeah the small band of women who work
Wishing hoping
Fighting to be included in this new event
Women expect
The Fourteenth Amendment is going to lift
Any
It discrimination within the constitution on the basis of
Race
Color or sex
And why would they think that since nobody was
Saying let's do this for the women of Gettysburg or at Antietam or what they had been the stalwart
Ernest and women are really important of the founding of the Republican party and so when they say they know y'all can you guys going to do the cement off
Obviously you're not going to forget it's right like we're going to write this political Ramos do it like let's just do it let's get this
Done this proposed amendment is being talked about in Congress being
Perfected as being tweet and
It's about to come to a vote when almost at the last minute
The word mail is put in there
Amending Amendment so that only men can
And it's
The first introduction of the word male into the Constitution
So not only
Does Apple 18th Amendment
Spell
To guarantee women their citizenship
And the rights of come in
Privileges become a citizenship
It's specifically
It's real right we're starting back at
Square one so
At that point some women are like God damn it like all right we're just going to go vote and so for instance
Actually tries to vote they won't let her goes to the Supreme Court I guess you won't be surprised to hear you on the edge of your seat
What are we going to do I can't wait to do it.
Is it raining right now
Ladies it's so cute that you thought you were included in the Cubs
No no no no no
We love you but no
And then in 1878 Susan B Anthony proposed another amend
Address for the right to vote people laughed about it and then put it aside for the next 40 years
Has no movement
At all on this amendment
June 4th 1990
Just after World War 1
After centuries of
Suffering suffrage
Both houses of Congress finally passed the 19th Amendment
To give women the right to vote
Amendment came after months of women protesting
Outside the White House and years of working jobs that before the war it only ever belong to men
But
Force it also came with a constitutional
Catch it had to go to the state
To be ratified
Was just means that each state had to vote to approve it
Three-fourths of the state legislatures have to ratify the amendment
Well 36 in this particular instance had to vote for it
Now they got Wisconsin Illinois Michigan and then after that it's just like dominoes
Then we got to 35 States
And
Stopped
It just got
Stuck at 35
Knowing that the suffragists were only one vote shy
The anti-suffragist
Beefed up their camp
At which made it
Harder and harder to get that final
Allstate it was looking grim
Until
There was a Wednesday
Just one state that seemed
Like it might be.
Teetering
August 1920 Nashville Tennessee legislators from all over the state start arriving at Union Station
Dirt immediately
Roane
Anti
Suffrage
Kind of pain either a yellow or red rose on their lapel
Tell everybody
Across town would know which side they stood on that was Tom vikstrom he's The Unofficial historian of the very places
These legislators were headed
The most fashionable place in town
The Hermitage Hotel
Picture of the lobby there in the month of August
Swarming with people both Pro and anti suffrage
Women cooling themselves
Palm leaf
Fans and of course no air conditioning man smoking cigar smoking politicians
Turn on the second floor mezzanine you have the headquarters of the anti suffragists and it's actually worth noting that a lot of the end
Anti suffragists were women campaigning actively against the right to vote
Suite 309 you have Carrie Chapman Catt leader of the pro suffrage
She had no children and her husband had died she had devoted all of her Energies
Towards this
One goal
Getting women the right to vote
So she's up she's the big Washington to Bigfoot from Washington is really much like
A general
Who is both groups are there because this hotel is just a few blocks away from the State House
And they are trying to convince as many Tennessee legislators as they possibly can
To come over there so it was all kind of high Jinks and you name it eavesdropping
Holograms
Are fake phone call messages
Are running around trying to stop these legislators from leaving town
There's a room back at the hotel called the jack
Daniel's room where there was some Jack Daniels being dispensed
By the anti-suffrage people
And supposedly Pro suffrage legislators
Could be heard through the hotel walls singing anti-suffrage song
Tennessee is supposed to be dry
And yet the aunt has are flagrantly violating prohibition
By having these events
In which the liquor flows quite well
The closer and closer they got to the final day of voting it became apparent that paper
People who had come to town saying they were in favor of ratifying this amendment wearing yellow
LaRosa's started wearing red
Roses
On the morning of the final vote
So many
Red roses to yellow roses to yellow roses to red roses flip-flopping floppity flipping around
Bit by this point no one had any idea what was going to happen
That's exactly right way to stop you here for a second
Sure is it now clear to everybody that if the legislature of Tennessee
They will become part of the US Constitution
Absolutely absolutely you know you didn't have any cushion states that you could go to
You know
Nevada next there were no cushions
It's now or it's going to be a long time
And finally is going to happen one way or another
On August 18th
So the morning of the vote
The hotel starts emptying out
Everyone heads over to the state capitol
But misses cat because she was going to be looked at as an outside agitator
Headed to stay behind
In the state capitol in the house
Chamber
Hot and humid in the room is
HAC
The 96 legislators are settling at their desks and above them in the gallery around the top of the house
Lost chamber
Stand with suffrage
Why are there along with the anti suffragists
And you can be assured that both sides have their little pads
Enter counting the votes
And if they look at the Roses
There are 48
Yellow roses
In 48
Red roses
And all these roses reliable I mean
If you're wearing a red rose you're going to vote against it before the voting even begin
They can see that
We've lost
And yeah cuz you have to have a few have to have a majority
And the Speaker of the House
He had initially supported suffrage but he's really on the side of the ant Eyes by this time
And before they really start the vote he actually steps down on the floor
To give a speech against ratification of the amendment
So you know
There's another let-down you know
Is lost we've lost we've lost
And two blocks away
Suite 309 of the Hermitage Hotel
Tits Carrie Chapman Catt
She was very nervous about what was going to happen
So what you going to do
She said there is only one thing left to do
We can
Pray
So they start
The Roll Call
And as
These names are called
1byone these men stand up
Invoice Turbo
If they are wearing a yellow rose
You say I for women's suffrage
They're wearing a red rose
They say nay
And among these legislators
It's a young man Harry T burn a republican legislator
From Niota Tennessee a 24 years old he's the youngest
Legislator in the house
Small man
Little glasses with a serious face
The air is tense
I'm still
Until
Harrington
The young man
Stan's
From his dad
A red rose in his lapel
But in his pocket
He had a letter from his mother over there in Niota
Dear son
We've had nothing but rain since you left
Her name was Fab burn
Uncle Bill and mr. Bushnell came over this p.m. State about an hour
They were in the Ford
We haven't had that car out since you left
And if this rainy weather doesn't let up I fear we'll all have to
The stay-at-home the rest of them really it's just this ordinary letters Tower of what I'm writing
From a mom to her son
He was real sick yesterday but was better this morning
She's been complaining all summer tucked into all of those mundane details about lice in Niota
There was this little motherly
Dig
Aprotic
I've been watching to see how you stood but haven't seen anything yet you know son I've been reading about the suffrage fight in the paper
Prison Everly unchain your name anywhere
And then she says don't forget to be a good boy and help Miss Thomas cap
Vote for suffrage
And don't keep them in doubt
With lots of love Mama
Harry T burn is wearing a red
Rose
And his vote
Cheap boats
Women to have the right to vote
So up there in the balcony
There's just a moment of silence what's going on here what's going on
You can imagine
She can imagine this
And then it Dawns on you
Hey Harry changed his vote
It's not going to be 48 248 it's going to be 49 247
The suffragist you can imagine our crying
The anti Tsar Furious
You can imagine the total
Chaos here in this situation but there must be an awful lot of attention paid to Harry Wright Lake
The legend is that the anti
Start chasing Harry
Through the house chamber
Harry is completely undone oh my gosh what have I just done
So he jumps out of window not nash not jumping out of five story running but he gets out of the building and
Jimmy's down the ledge to the
State Library which is in the same building
Where he gets in the window there and mrs.
More the librarian Mary Daniel Moore hides him in the stack
Until the storm blows over
Now that's the legend Harry really climb out of that window and he
Shimmying happen
We don't know
How exaggerated that part of the story
The sounds from the hill carried all the way back to the Hermitage Hotel
Mrs. cat could hear them from her window she knew they'd won
It was in fact pass
The certificate of ratification
Sent to Washington DC
And receive
By the Secretary of
The final tally was actually
After Harry changed his vote
When other lights
Just later switched sides but
It was clearly because Harriet Janet
First that's right to vote was the wreath at vote
Became the 19th Amendment to the United States Constitution
Yes in the in a manner of speaking yes
After the vote
This is cat
Fat burn
A telegram
You are blessed
With a brave and honest son
Whatever the enemies of justice and decency made do now to show their vengeance upon him
He's bound
To have a great
You will ever be proud of
Carrie Chapman Catt
Well is political career ended rather short
But you know he took his mother's advice
And
He did get his name of the paper did me
You think about it the difference between
Tween men and women as voters
Just gotten
Decisive
Yeah
You know what
This has made me
19th Amendment
Stories yes and checking them and thank you listener for voting which working already thank you for
Cuz we know that you're going to do
I can go out and vote whatever you
You just got mad because
This is a
Does it matter
Yes
My grandmother went to the Methodist Church
In November of 1920
With
Her four-year-old daughter at her side
And voted because of something that
Took place
Right here in Nashville Tennessee
I will never forget when I went to pick my mother up the last time she voted
She was sitting in the lobby of the
Retirement center where she live
Patiently waiting for me to come and pick her up
With your American flag
Pain in her lapel
She was proud to be going to vote
Thanks to Peggy heinkel-wolfe at the Denton record-chronicle
In Texas and thanks to Professor Rachel Goosen at Washburn University
Thanks also to Lynda Randle and Adrian Heath then Professor Mildred Warner Cornell
Thanks to Wayne shulmister and to Debbie Daughtry
Who lend us their southern accent
Thanks to Andrea Morrow and the Texas commission for Environmental Quality as well as
The Tennessee State library and archives The Hermitage Hotel
The Calvin McClain historical collection of the Knox County Public Library on
Last but not least
Thanks for the Plymouth Fife and Drum Corps including and especially
Director
Jim freedom
Whose last name rhymes
With freedom
Start of message
Hey this is Jill Lepore Carol BC in Nashville Tennessee
I service the Davidson County historian Emma professor of history at Volunteer State Community
City College
Because our director soundesign Sharna will wheeler is our senior editor
Assassin Creed
Simon Adler Brenna Farrell
Robert krulwich
Logic nacho Melissa O'Donnell
Katie Ferguson
And our fact Checkers are Eva Dasher and Michelle Harris
And this message