Are you awake
Northern listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
And NPR
Hello this is Lynn
Someone on the other side of us
Hey
So a couple months ago a producer Lynn Levy did an interview with
Yeah her name is Margaret Lovett
This was Margaret's first time doing a radio interview magic voice
But this is definitely not her first time
Talking into a microphone
Profound
Two three four
R34 this is the orange Ma
Almost exactly 50 years ago recording was made on November 19 1964
At 2300 hours
Margaret was at the center of this amazing weird experiment
Yeah yeah
Who were you at that time like what were you like well I I've always had a bit of if everybody's going left all going right
Cheap tri-college for awhile University for a year but she dropped out and I was
19 Somethin
And move to st. Thomas in the Caribbean
Got a job at this hotel did menus check people in and out and one day she hears about this strange research
Facility on the other side of the island
I wonder what that is about and I asked a few people nice I don't know
They don't like people they are kept
And I was told not to go there so I went there
And that's
Sourdough starter
That's how I can start the show I'm chatting Ron I'm Robert krulwich Radiolab producer Lynn Levy brings us a couple
Full of Close Encounters
Cut alien like not out there
Hello
What happened what she ended up becoming roommates with a dolphin one bedroom apartments
Sort of yeah she did end up living with a dolphin for for many months
In this
Buy me a
Kitchen area with
It was a little two burner stove or something
And a pot and a tea kettle but the thing that's a little bit weird about the apartment is that whole apartment was
Filled with water
It completely film well I wasn't submerged but I was in water up
Miss size
Is just flooded with water
Just about there she could share it with this dolphin die young male Peter
Peter was a 10ft long bottlenose dolphin young adolescent male and he lives there with
With Margaret and like he would you know he could swim under the desk and there's balcony
The balcony
The balcony was also flooded yeah it's really cool what was the idea of me to try and study the dolphin
To study the dolphin
And take a lot of
Extensive notes
Did you have waterproof paper
No I had a
Typewriter
Board hanging from the ceiling they also had microphones
And specifically the tasks she was given
Pacific Peter
To speak English
She was supposed to keep the dolphin English
Really well
I mean this was John Daly's
Project
Just for some context people get all like a little bit crazy these days about dolphins shirts with dolphins
Poses with dolphins in blacklight posters right so this all kind of
Sort of comes from the sky John Lilly
Who was a scientist or researcher starting in the forties total Right Stuff
Physics major kind of guy out of Caltech
Man's man according to Graham Burnett
Epiphany
During the second world war at the time people just weren't thinking that much about dolphins
In general like it was not this idea that they were sort of
Extraordinary beings
They were just like
Big dumb fish
No they were shot for sports
Regionally is doing this
Research about
Brain map
And he ends up working with dolphins
And
Bonded
The story that that he's told goes that he was
Experimenting on these dolphins and
As he's working with them you know kind of like
Shoving
Things into their brains they make
Noises
As with anyone
And when he listens back to the noises
She's recorded
It sounds to him like the Dolphins are trying
To say something to him in not in a not a dolphin e-way
But in a human
Way like trying to speak
Really
What did you say the dolphin was trying to say 2
I don't think that we know that
But it sounded to him enough like human
That he he thought like
Something's going on here this is
According to Graham he said later that
It made him realize like we are not the only intelligent organisms
Like we have company
That maybe humans are what happens when
High Intelligence involves in an animal that also has
Has hands
And dolphins
Or what happens when
Comparably
If not
Still more extravagant
Intelligence
Evolves
And I want without him
What do hands get you hands basically got you an appetite for punching people in the head
It makes us to users but the distance between us
You're the hammer
That you use
2 watt knock open your coconut and the hammer that used to knock open the head
That other Cro-Magnon you were never that Keen on
Is in fact
Zilch there's no difference at all
By the time get to the sixties if you know like peace and love exciting to think
The dolphins and whales
Ibiza huge Brands but they don't like they're not after
Anything I'm not doing anything with enough Turner anybody that not building cities
They're just
Like being
And keep in mind this is on the verge of the Vietnam War where you have all this anxiety about
Do the overpopulation Environmental
Construction
What are they doing
So very quickly the Dolphins become like this
Vision how we made ourselves
So Def
Then we come to feel
We were tragically
Stomach signs
So tell me was one of the first people to get swept up in all this
He quit his government job moves to the Caribbean and sets up this
Lab John Lilly's communication BC
Search Institute
To try to talk to dolphin
Which is where Margaret ended up and my feeling was this is everybody was talking about how bright they were and how smart they were and it was
Awesome stuff
Dolphins and then it was it was the Hot Topic
And yet every
Hey everybody at that building would get in their car and go home
Yeah
What is that
So
She volunteered to stay
Her bed was on this kind of wooden plat
Farm in the middle of the apartment
I was maybe
Two-and-a-half 3 inch
Bob's
The water
And Peter was right there and Peter could
Flip me a little water and wake me up in any
And that was the whole point of it I mean if this wasn't just sleep all night and then
Excuse me working today and then
Sleep again all night and then do some work in the day I might as well go home so
I eventually I didn't really shave my head but I buzzed it
Whatever it's called now really close
Because any you know the hair getting wet thing in the middle of the night was very annoying
Yeah of course I just got rid of hair
And and that was helpful and then when Peter with comments word some water or want to play or throw something at me
Then I could just roll off this elevator into the water and be with him
Do whatever
She says he was fascinated by the things she
She brought with her
Piece of
Sloth
A tea bag
Tea bag was a fascinating thing and I
PrankDial
And the tea bag would fall into the water
And he would come and get it
And
Sonar it
What is creaking noise they make on there
Sonar
And
Take the string oversby cancer
Women around
They probably will
Tea bag and then you throw it up
Against the wall and it was stick
And then he squirt water on it and it would come back down into the water and
Cuban playlist
Eventually coursehero
Would fight it is very short teeth
And that was a very exciting thing when the teabags finally broke open
It had babies
Billions of
Tea leaves floating around and he was so nice of them all in one
Count every single one of them
What did you think you would find out
Now
You know I was not coming out at
Cos formula science
Point of view that that's not what I was bringing to the table
Yeah I just I just I did I had no idea I
I was
Programmed by by John to work on the speech
Aeio she had sort of declared that they could probably speech
Look when your
Trying to have a conversation with someone
One person speaks
And then you speak and and I listen and end people sort of normally do that back and forth
When you start with a dolphin making Airborne sounds once they get the idea that's a lot of raining at those are
Every so often they want to overwrite you
I am not
So you have to
Spend a lot of time getting it down to I'm talking now
Speak now
And now it's your turn
I can see it now
Upset about something Hill over my face
Pater
Come on Peter
Start again
3 yes but he learned very quickly to listen to me
1 2 3 4
Babies
And not to pick up my instruction
I would say no no no Peter I don't want you to do that I want you to do
This
He would give me back this
Cartwheel off and saying no no no Polly want a cracker
They will beat the whole thing of whatever you say
Peter Woods
Would pick up what I wanted when he was
Being a good
And he was a good student there seem to be
Which is one dolphin anyway can't speak for all of them and interest
In in what we were doing
She wanted to practice
Does he wanted to get it right
Yeah there was a mirror and he would spend long periods of time by himself didn't want me
To be part of it
And he would practice whatever it was we have been doing
In the lesson that
Over and over and over and over
He wanted to get it right
Wouldn't work at that
For no reason he's not getting fish I'm not interacting with one another
Just once
I like doing homework like homework
And after a few months of this
Peter did start to sound
Really different 1/2
1 2 3
Better
Getting better
Really difficult for them
They just have a blowhole like they do not have the apparatus to relieve asses are almost impossible
I would feed him my name
And M is very hard he would eventually roll over almost into the water with the
Blowhole to Muscle Up
Hi the same really you're saying he would he would use the water as a way to help him make the sound
With that word
And
And I knew that was your name
I don't know
But nevertheless we were up
Pretty good match
I know his mood his temperament
And he and he knew mine he knew when I was sick
And I would get sick
Pioneer in the water all the time you're bound to get a cold or something
He just loved my anatomy he wanted to know what my knees were doing
He would go behind my knee and sonar and look at it and feel it and push it
And find out which way it wouldn't wouldn't go he just
And I gave him the time
Cuz I wasn't going home
To look at my knee
To look at my feet
He was enormously interested
Oddly enough in the space
Between
My fingers
Not the fingers so much
What's he would
I mean it
You don't speak to just barely sit there but he wanted
Put in between each finger.
NC
What that was all
The same with the toes
You didn't have any spaces anywhere
You know he had solid flippers
But no space in between them do you think he was so interested in your fingers and toes because
He didn't have any
Yes I do
Margaret and Peter ended up spending
About 9 months living together
But towards the end
Things kind of started
To unravel
First of all
Don't really results from this
Experiment they never were able to publish any
Scientific
Papers
And
There were other problems Lily got
Very involved in
Drugs
Especially LSD he did bring it down
He did
Give LSD
He says he did I believe him too
Two two of the dogs I would not let him give LSU to Peter I wouldn't
Why would he give them LSD well
It's not a hundred percent clear but it seems like he was trying to find
A way to get the Dolphins to open up
Connect
Maybe to talk
In any case by 19
His funding it started
To dry up
When people heard about
Markets work
They tended to focus on like one particular
The story
You don't have to answer but a lot has been made of your
Sort of sexually engaging with Peter and I just want to ask if you don't seem like a shrinking violet I just want to ask is there anything you want to
Say about that
What would I like to say about that I think
It is The Sensational side of it is
Cheers what Margaret told me
Peter was a young dolphin
He was horny and
He would hump her leg
What kind of
A dog might do
Just getting in the way of their work
So eventually I just said the heck with it
And she use her hand to
You know and and it would quickly satisfy him and then we could go back to doing what we would do
And I I never really gave it another thought I never thought
Don't let anybody know I never thought
That shouldn't be because of details like this
Drugs
This experiment became a
Extremely controversial
Almost untouchable
People didn't want to be associated with Lily nobody wanted to fund anything that sounded like Lily
It just got this like
Aura of
Don't go there don't go there even people who wanted to do really rigorous
Work with human dolphin communication
Had a tough time
Getting a fun day and that lasted for a long time
The thing is
Even though there are
So many reasons to disa
Approve of this experiment
When you talk to Margaret
Champs
How much
Want to be in that apartment
What's up
He would come over and when he was in what I call his sweet mode and Peter had a lot of very very sweet moods
He would sink to the bottom
And take my
Foot
In his mouth
And he wasn't so narang and he wasn't looking at anything he was almost like a little kid, she just wants to hold your hand and
He would just sink to the bottom and closes eyes and just hang onto my foot
And then you have to come up and
Breathe and then you go back down
NHS
Grab my foot
And he would do this for a good while
I'll be back in a moment with another encounter
You have two new messages
Graham Burnett
Arrigo
The Alfred P Sloan Foundation enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology
In the modern world
Www.
Borg Radiolab
Produced by WNYC
And distributed by NPR
I think that's it
Hang up now thanks again
And this message
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
This summer
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents
Aunts and uncles
Teachers were looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments of childhood brilliance
Basically I want to hear about this
When a kid you know did something
It just means you lean back and say whoa
How do they do that
Maybe it was the moment that
A kid you've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of their musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed are ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the
Epic moments where
A kid does something super smart
It doesn't have anything to do with the test
If you have a story with us
Go to radiolab.org
Flash brilliance
Record a short audio message
And that's radiolab.org
Brian
Thank you so much
Hey I'm Jared I'm Robert krulwich
This is Radiolab and today hello
Or the dolphin might say
Howard Johnson
I don't know I'm glad that you know what that is exactly kind of the question of this next segment mean to dream that a human being and
Talk to a dolphin or any animal really getting their heads
Cross that Gap this is a dream that you must have had four since like forever Saint Francis of Assisi goes away by
No it's so far as dolphins are concerned
After the John Lilly situation
Researchers did get a little tepid
No
Along Came this one doctor Denise Herzing director of the wild dolphin project
Best decided to take John Lilly's experiment and flip it
Rather than have the Dolphins speak
English let's have the humans speak dolphin
Are the very least let's create a shared language were humans and dolphins can speak
Or at least whistle
Finding
Finding a place you
Meet back to producer Lynn Levy
Okay so for Denise
This dream of finding that meeting spot
It goes back to when she was a little girl when I was 12 years old I used to
Page
Through the inside
Wikipedia Britannica in the days when we had books and I would always stop at the whale and dolphin
Look at the Dolphins and go now I wonder
What their brains are like cuz they've evolved in the water we were 12 I was I was I was a total nerd in fact
I entered this
Contest in Minnesota like what would you do for the world
Do something and I actually wrote I would
Build a human animal translator so weak
I can't figure out what's going on
Am I the animal so yeah I don't know I got the bug early and here I am a fantasy about what you might learn
No I was just curious
I don't know you look in their eyes there's definitely something behind there
Don't know what it is
Fast forward many years
Denise got a bow and I went out to the Bahamas she was like if I'm going to study these dolphin I'm going to do it in the
That's where they lived so she track down a pot of wild dolphins
Yep she just
Try to blend it I actually
Anchor the boat in one spot most of the time the spot in the Bermuda Triangle in the middle of cycle of the Dalton Highway
Where Dolphins come and go they could come by if they wanted to and if they didn't
They didn't
When they would come by
She and her team would just
Flip into the water and behave ourselves to start a watch
Pay attention to who which dolphin had a
Cricket sandwich
And when they believe we'd get out and
That's really how we operated for the first 5 years and it worked 5 years
Spent five years
Just watching
Not doing anything else yes
Dentist take an enormous amount of patients sure I mean
Grabacin Pocus entradas
So they started just going about their own business
Like feeding mating nursing and tok
Or at least making a lot of noises
Which team her team would record
Wow that's all dolphins looking kind of
Squeaking sound that they make
Sounds like a whistle that are more kind of Distinction and they make sounds are like longer
Weirder and
If you have any sense that each of these sounds means something different
Well
That's exactly what we don't know I could tell you what kind of sounds are correlated
Fighting in with meeting or discipline
Find a calf what we don't know is
Are there detailed
Words and there's are more kind of encoding
Information but what they do know is that each Dolphins seems to have its own kind of signature with
Just basically a name
Every individual has
Peter had a name nobody has ever asked me that
Here's Margaret again
His name was
Really it is almost saying Peter here
So I can call you Lynn by your whistle and you Robert by your whistle I could be a dolphin.
Slim
Baidu
Not only that apparently Dolphins will use
The names of other Dolphins who aren't even around
Nickel talk about each other behind their backs
Yes maybe
Well that means that
There
Using representations
Things which aren't in front of them which is certainly the beginning of language
If that's what they're doing what they're doing then yeah that's kind of like
The edge of language
So you know
It gives us hope that there's
Probably more information going on there than
Arduino
Now
Finally
She has
That
Device
Which device can the magical you know human animal translator device
Place that she was dreaming of writing about when she was 12
She has this box that can generate dolphin noises
And it can recognize dolphin noises
And if it works the way that you know that she's dreaming it'll work
It could be the first like
Real
Two-way back and forth conversation between a human
And a wild animal
So we're looking forward to
Summer and getting out and getting more data and really exercising the Box
Getting ready so I beg my way
Everybody good seasick pills left
On July 8th from Florida
And headed for the Bahamas
To see the spot that she's been following with kind of forever most 30 years now
Photos called the RVs Donella Donella is the scientific name for the
Particular type of dolphin the spotted dolphin have you seen
Boat like a tiny boat but it's not a big boat and it was just absolute
Full human
And you got a captain first mate research assistant
Meijer's Les Mason Bethany aulier volunteers
Images of men for a long time I couldn't even figure out where everybody sleeping cuz they both seem so small is like there is not room for all these people on this phone
Stop hot soldering iron next to fridge
His name is bad starter you don't have
Like any dolphin experience before this right
Oh hell no to invented Google Glass
And I'm out here and was hungry weather to do what
He's in charge of these
These boxes with the boxes fry cost 100K at this point
Wiz when he came down to visit my lab I was telling about the two-way work in the difficulty with underwater stuff and he said
Wearable computers shouldn't be hard
Four years later what is this machine look like if you'd like one of those fancy Chrome
Toasters except you wear it on your chest
Are they silver they are silvery they have a bunch of sort of knobs and buttons and speakers on them got pre-program
Whistles in it
I can punch
Chucky and a project
Whistle Aid
It was the be
She's programmed in signature whistles of some of the Dolphins rat pellet Bijou
We made signature whistle
Ourselves
Oh
She can call their names and then go hard
That's what you think that is the idea yeah and and if they do call her name
This name that she's made for herself then the Box should be able to recognize it
And can tell her
That she's been called by name it'll actually
Say into her ear in English
Denise this is real time I call it real time sound
Ignition but it's real time
Whistle
Definition underwater
How does
If she's made up this name for herself how is it that they're going to know that that's her name
She gets into the water over and over and she says you know if equivalent of hi I'm Denise hi I'm Denise
Over and over and over and they learn it you know they developed this
Start music
Call her
Hope they call you
How do you release a decision
Vegas the very least
You could call their names and see how they react
Right with you that would be a Eureka moment I thought
Think if you hit
The Lolita button and Lolita suddenly
Turned and look right at you
You with a shotgun
What the heck
Wow that's
Even called me by my side
Solo hasn't happened yet it hasn't happened
Yet
And this is something I just did not appreciate for a while I was on the phone with
Why is this so hard like seems like it should be these people are so smart like this should be easy but they're just like constantly
Being defeated by the ocean basically which I the ocean is like a worthy foe but
It's like the first year to work
Everything broke the boxes just kept shutting down as soon as we get in the water
That's not good. What you want and last year that the box is working but then we couldn't find the Dolphins
The Dolphins just disappeared where did they go
They went a hundred miles away to another location they don't know why I kept up with my side of the other days
Your Dolphins stood you up
One of the reasons I was on the boat is it felt like everybody was thinking like
This is it this is the year we're going to go out there where
Find some dolphins and we're going to make some history
You ready
Now
Any minute now
Okay turns out it's not that easy to find these Dolphins they're not tagged you know they're wild dolphins so
So you just like you go to where you think they might be he stare at the water
And you wait
For the first three days pretty much I would we were just
Driving around
Game of Thrones
In circles like literally in circles
Yeah I feel like I had like a like a
5 our conversation about Game of Thrones I've never even seen an episode of Game of Thrones
Dolphins anywhere
No nothing else to do
Again
Looks like a dolphin that looks like a dolphin
I just say that I would like
Everything looks like a dolphin to me right now
There are days like that
Often they are right there
All the sudden out on the water with one fin to Sims 3 4 5 6 7 8 9
There's so many of them in there so cool standing there watching them Denis turns to me
I don't know what do you recommend it
And I was not prepared her to say that and also holding recording equipment everything
And so I just I ended up to tell me to go in like in my clothes
I like my shorts and like a bra and I'd like ice all modesty aside like a throw
Decide they're like you can go in and
Cheesecake
Ergo
Bully Ryback
Aloha
This is Michelle from Honolulu Radiolab is supported in part
By the National Science Foundation
P sloan Foundation
Contempt
Public understanding of
Science and technology in
Modern world
More information about Sloane @www.
Sloan. Org
Mahalo
Hey I'm Jenna Cam'ron I'm Robert Kovac does Radiolab and today their shows called hello back to Lynn
I mean it
Poodle sensory shift the temperature change
Everything goes quiet it almost feels like this like classic through the looking
Last moment where are you like you go through the Looking Glass in like everybody
He's walking on the ceiling and I jumped in and they were too pretty big dolphins coming
Wright Patman maybe two feet from my head
And staring at me and I was like
What did you do
And how far were they from you oh my God
Like what we see you and also there they make these sort of clicking
Zonare sounds are like talking to you or just talking about you
It is so darn me looking at me with their with sounds
It was vibrating they can see not just body shape they can see your bones they can see
Cn2 you like you really feel
What that
It was heart-stopping
Whois
Oh
Put in now and I am happy
You know and everybody was like calm down
Those weren't even the right dolphins
Well those are bottlenose dolphins Denise studies
Spotted
The next day we set out again
Go for a few hours Bethany does this Dolphin Dance
And got some
You sound right yeah right there yeah there we go
So then everybody's like you I was like all hands on deck situation it is like strapping
Headphones
It's like a fire drill now I'm putting on my box
Here's the problem I'm just testing
Unlike
A captive dolphin wild dolphins
They have other things
They have
Betta fish to catch you kind of have to entice it into having a conversation
Otherwise it'll just swim away
How do you do that when you don't know what's language
Well turns out dolphins are just crazy for scarves
Scarf scarf they sweep it up with their tail fin and then they let it go and it wasp
Through the water and another dolphin comes up and sweep sit up with their Rostrum to the ideas use the scarf as kind of like a
Bridge
Denise
Another diver will get in the water with a scarf passing it back and forth
Human the human like hey look at this funny thing we're doing the game sometimes we'll take
Press the word for scarf
They just made up a whistle for scar
Ideally and this is the key the Dolphins will pick up the word and use it to ask
For the scarf
If and when they do that
Tiny bit of common ground that you can build on
Okay so you got
Yes we're waiting for them right we have just before they jump into nice walks another diver to the game plan
You're going to hold it and you're not going to give it to him
Stop it in like way better and just really get them with you moments later
Good already
Any something followed by three other drivers
Corn water were you in the water the sun no actually to watch the whole thing from the deck and like you can see from the store
Surface 3 or 4
Adolescent dolphins
Hey Denise is right up next one of them to the back of her head and her little snorkel
Sure
They're kind of like twisting around each other I will say this
She is
Tremendously grateful in the water if she gets in the water and she's like totally at home
She might secretly be a dolphin sound like around and around
She goes on there
And what is happening under there
This is what it sounds like underwater
This is the actual sound from the scarf and stay record everything that
Go down together
I'm in a lot of that is the Dolphins
Just doing whatever they're doing
But some of it it's me with the boss making this
Scarf whistle over and over like
Scarf
Got the scarf
Yeah
Garf cuz she's like trying to get a dolphin to say the word
Right yeah
Eventually she and the Dolphins surface and
One of the Dolphins is holding the star of red
Then they all go back under
Anthony's comes back up with it
That's real good
Wednesday
After about a minute she surfaces
Lincoln East has it now
She dies one more time
A minute later dolphin has the scar
I just went on and on and we're passing it back and forth so fluidly that I thought maybe
The dolphin has begun to ask for the scarf by name
Eventually nice cap
And we all just heard gather around like
Well pick up the scarf right away
Play something that you whistle
Five piece of seaweed
Nothing that trigger the system but it looks like
Exhausting
Didn't get anything
Well I mean nothing the Box recognized as a match
You know nothing that indicated the dolphin like learned a word
So what's the right there
But
There was this one thing that have
She said that when she
Address
One of the dolphins
Bias
The dolphin turned around and looked at her
Intitle caca
Pitbull dog
Really
Wow
Also there was this moment where that and Celeste were looking at the data later and they saw that
Right after Denise meters
Signature whistle another dolphin made its signature Whistle Sweet
You mean like she said hi and it said hi back
Yeah that's amazing
Well maybe I mean
The thing is dolphins make their signature whistles
All the time
Or it could be this
Moemon
I mean she's a very rigorous scientist
Like she wants
That to happen
Another 30 times
4eva
I'm starting to take it
Seriously
But still
It does make you think about the possibilities
Do you want to ask
I don't know I want to ask everything so
Like what
I'd like to know what their lives are like when we're not around how do you spend your day and do they think about
Do they sing about
Think about the past I mean we know they have long-term memories you know
How did they remember their calves from 10 years ago
Do they think about death
Anything you'd ask your friends right
Everyone disliked
They even get there
Miami will sit goals to have a Converse
And you can't do it this way we are
The wild
Can touch them you got very favorite whistle 35 * 1
Are they ever actually going to have a conversation
Margot witz
All the problems of that
Experiments
Which she was actually getting somewhere with Peter
Like they're actually having a real Exchange in the moment perhaps but
Thinking forward
I believe that
What you can accomplish by talking
They having a two-way conversation
Just infinitely greater
And I totally agree but if it's taking her thirty-something years
To get
A maybe hello
Yeah I don't even know what you got to Hallelujah and
If all she has is a
What's the limit amount of time with
Dolphins every summer
And 50 more times
51 years old
God's plans
17 degrees warmer by that point
Dolphins are in a ball migrated to some other spot it just feels like
Just get in the pool and hold little left but the dolphin hold your foot
She's already got the hello going for her maybe so that's like a start
And then gets in 50 years should we have move past hello to
The three words
How's your mackerel today
3 word sentence yes
I would put money on a three-word sentence in 50 years
Question is do we ever get to the point of
Exploring.
Yeah yeah yeah I don't know
I have faith
That
If
Please continue with what she's doing
That will be able to talk about
Concrete things
Will be able to talk about seaweed and we'll be able to talk about
Coral and we'll be able to have a
Scintillating conversation about scarves I do believe that is not nothing
I mean that is pretty impressive in its own way
Big Texas our to our producer than Maybe
I'm Jared I'm Robert know which thank you guys for listening
Start of message
Hey guys
I like your smile
Dolphin project
But you have is produced by Chad album
Tim Howard
Lenny York Lynnwood
Animals Kelsey products and with help from Ariane Blackberry single and really solid
Special things
David Rothenberg
Philip Hansen Bailey
Kelly Hall and the crew of the vanilla thanks again
And this message