Are you awake
Listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
Hey I'm Jared I'm Ron I'm Robert krulwich Radiolab today
We have a mystery that is vanishingly Tiny
Shockingly hot and managers to combine submarines Keanu Reeves Red Lobster in Game of Thrones
Producer Molly Webster
Many members of his family
Hello hello hello hello
Where are the children you want to begin in the beautiful state of
South Carolina South Carolina
On a pier is my radio Gear waterproof
Onondaga case we're going to walk down to the docking which is just looked
The place where they all put boats in the water and that's where we always
I like a bomba
My parents recently moved to this
Marshy swampy area near the Intracoastal Waterway which is like a connecting series of
Salty Channel
And we grew up in Ohio and he was like
Totally different landscape than what we were up a little people would be my nieces and nephews
The Weeknd ride it back America was or my children
Getting along and compromise Webster one of my sisters
Every time the weather like
Okay so this is the story of the story is
So my parents first move there and remember going out on the docks with my dad and we are sort of looking at the beautiful
Marsh rides
And it was really weird sound like
Coming off the water
I recently took my nieces and nephew out to see if they could
Allen vs
They're not going to move
Are not going to squeak
Macintosh
Not going to talk
Okay so we leaned down off the dock and see if we can hear it
Oh my gosh I hear some Crackle
That crackling sound
Yeah what is that
That was a question
It sounds
Sounds like rice
Most of the scientist you talked to say it sounds like bacon frying or Twigs crackling in a fire
Maybe have a large.
I would say that except there's no bubbles popping like on the water
Oh so it's not a gaseous emission it's a
Clickety clack
Let me just pay you a better record
Yeah but up
What do I have to put it through the producer PC
I went.
This is actually under water report
Oh my God
Cashing a teeny world that would be like the 4th of July
Kevin Bacon Bacon you're frying what is the sound what is it
This sound is a very tiny
Welded the story started in the forties
That's Michelle over spouse of physical Acoustics and medical Acoustics at the University of Toronto in the
Basically what he said is
World War II is the first war were like really using submarines and sonar
And so you've got all of these u.s. Navy submarines down deep in the ocean and they're like listening out for the
The enemy but what happened is all they hear is this
Like crazy crackling sound levels that were measured so very very until
He says in some instances is actually interfering with the sonar
I found a classified document that was Declassified right after the war
Wear the Navy they actually
Tired
Actually hired this scientist is guy named Martin Johnson this is in California San Diego
Go at the scripture hired this guy to figure out
What is the sound like what is the sound we're hearing like all over the ocean what is it already
Tell me what the damn sound
Yes well
It turns out I don't want to go too fast year notice in those years that that sound originated
Tickets from
Bishop B's Tampa
It was
Shrimp oh yeah shrimp is called a snapping shrimp
Or a pistol
Pistol like that
An interesting lead I found these like Old Navy recording
Did they win
Give to the Navy guys were they had to learn the sounds they were hearing coming in through the ship and through the sonar
Work with the Expendables radio tunnel Bowie you will probably hear many sound other than submarine
It was like this is the sound of a snapping turtle
It produces a harsh clicking noise
Okay shrimp sonar cool I get it in there
And then I found with altamese be a crazy article which is newspaper clipping from 19
Basically says
Shrimps Help win the war
And it's about how the American Navy admitted that one of their tactical sings during
Like World War II was that they would hide their submarines in the beds of these trim
So I like the Japanese submarines couldn't detect our shift
Visibility clothes
Yes
And according to Michelle the US would also speakers on the hull of the ship
22 simulator
Snapping shrimp it was sound camo
Yeah so we may we are these are they like normal normal shrimp cocktail shrimp
Welder about the 5 cm
2in feel like smaller than a shrimp
Depends what sort of shrimp you eat
Why do whatever
River Red Lobster
If they're that small how are they making that sound
That
Is Xanax
Silly question we where do you think the sound comes from
I'm thinking
It's
Fish and bees are eating
There
Illinois's is there little
Woosh Beauty teeth
TV I think it comes from
They're like
Clotting easy and that's what you would think right like especially if you look at these things up close they have
Two front claws
And
The clothes aren't the same on each side that's Nancy Knowlton a marine biologist
Snapping shrimp
Expert
Claudette specialized for pinching and a class tiny and a Claddagh specialized for snap
And that clot is like
Exponentially bigger it's like 10 times
Maybe three times bigger is quite a bit bigger
And so they use it to defend themselves against
Potential predators are competitors
They're very territorial
She doesn't want shrimp runs into another shrimp can get into these prolonged snapping matches where they snap at each other to show
Me this means bigger and stronger
Okay Vine
Anakin
Mike Judge how big they are by the
Power of the snap
All of which is to say
My niece Sophie's guess
Their likes
Clotting issue of course it's like the two sides of the claw just like snapping
Just like you snap your fingers like this just a snap
Snap without and turns out not to be
So not true
Who sings
Were wrong basically with a picture so I don't know if you ever try to clap your hands
In swimming pool
Underwater but never difficult you don't feel very smart
That's not a lot of that is because there's a lubrication layer water in between that prevents direct mechanical
Contact yes there's this lubricating layer between the two claw halves and it makes snapping hard
And the second problem was that sound the same way too loud
When they measure the
The decibel level of a single snap
220 decibels of sound that that can be produced by by single snap
To put that in context that is basically equivalent to
From Just One Snap
But it's very
Impulsive
Sinsaenum very very short
Jewish
Still sick one of the loudest sounds in the ocean
So Michelle was like
Probably more than snapping
I'm going on here
Yes I said so
So it was 1999 a new high-speed camera in our lab
Camera at
The shrimp and see what happens when they say shrimp
Snapchat
Claw they takes a little shrimps and they glue screws on their butts
Igloo screws on them
Screw them into tiny platforms
It's like a little aquarium so that they were fixed in space and that was important
Because I happened in like a microsecond and they need to keep it
Still see the camera can focus right on the clock
And to do the experiment what we needed to do was to tickle them a little bit
With the paintbrush
You tickle them with a paintbrush
They're closed
Nmda
And then
Fires
And the camera captures
The entire thing was like thousands of frames
Did they say anything they did see something
What it what happened what is it when they look at the footage of the moment
Just after its snaps
In super slow-mo very blurry
Object
In front of the shrimp
What will blurry had it was just like bloppy Blurry something
It was blurry blurry especially
I mean it turned out that we were
Certified auto focus
So they refocus the camera they do the same thing they take all the shrimp the cloth snaps
And they see that win the claw snap
They see
Dislike
In front of the shrimp
Claw and it turns out that it's that bubble that's
Causing
The noise and
This is so much undersea turmoil
In with the high-speed camera they were sort of able to see how it all breaks down
Netsertive unfold like
What actually happens when this Club closes is that
The water that is in between these claws to squeeze out at high speed
The typical speed
Can be up to 60 miles per hour
60 miles per hour in what happens is
China jet
Empty spaces created like a little voice
All the water molecules in that space cuz they start to expand outwards
And essentially they just become like a little gas bubble change from liquid to gas
They actually go from like liquid is like tightly packed molecules and then as they spread out they become like gaseous
And they create this like little bubble pocket in the middle of the huge ocean and as they have all the space they like
I can figure and bigger and bigger until the oceans like nope microseconds later the ocean star
Cushing
Back in on this bubble and the all the little the little love
Are molecules in the Indus bubble have nowhere to go in there
Force closer and closer together and so they really want to get away from
All those are molecules but you're pushing them together really hard and since they can't get away from each other like that
Energy build-up super super
Acute pressure Rises and the temperature rises
Really Rises
5000 degrees the surface of the Sun is also 5000 degrees
Sit inside the bubble turns to plasma
And that plasma image very short intense flash of light
Edesur bubble inflows and then
Like a microsecond later degenerates to Shockwave
And that Shockwave
Will basically
Kill or stun
Any I pray that this nearby somebody from the College of exaggeration graduated this
Explanation
Because you
Teeny little animals
Okay
That's amazing
How Eeveelution Master created this kind of Sonic weapon
So basically
Quality
Generate huge bubbles Heat
It's like
The Black Veil
Spitting out light
End
Hot hot hot temperature
Yeah
Does that mean
That's crazy I feel like it should be like a Marvel
Character
Totaling
Yeah cuz if you scaled this up
The bubble bee the size of a basque
Humanscale
What can I do with a basket
Fall of sun Heat
Light
Rule the world
Song about with my sister's hanging off the dock she asks like can we use this to power like
Make the world or something
Know the answer was no
But the same physical process
Disease that are involved in the shrimp Bubba
Pulse right sole
The temperature in
Heat that bubbles
Create
Researchers became really excited about is there a way to
Harness this bubble power
Yeah that's also a Hollywood movie I think I did it
Is it stable on powerful couples with Tatiana Reeves Rd
There is enough energy in this glass of water to power the city of Chicago
Went too far
Taken with the web
With the weapon possibility
Yeah my nephew got excited about
Bastille
But
I hate to tell you I don't think there are any you can like make a bear claw tub
Sorry guys
There is one thing
Where
Researchers are thinking about using bubbles in this goes beyond the shrimp bubble
In a way that
Save-A-Lot
My name is Josie Packard I'm calling from Columbia South Carolina where do you live is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan
Foundation for enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloan at www.slha.org
This is Radiolab now going to go back to the story from Molly Webster
You were saying people here are trying to use bubble power
Save lives
Yeah so when I was talking to Michelle versluis
Applications
We're talking on the phone and he explains all the crazy bubbly stuff and somehow like in the middle of a conversation
And he just said
If you think the shrimp bubbles are cool
Everything we know about the shrimp bubbles like
Can also be like
Adapted to use bubbles in the body
Oh and I
Like what in the body is
Totally I had the same thought like when divers get the bends or when they like
Tap bubbles out of IV lines and stuff but these are very very small bubbles smaller than red blood cells
According to her
Are sloths there like 1 20th the size of human hair
And he told me about how in Toronto and they actually just did this for the first time in November
On a patient
They're using bubbles to get across the blood-brain barrier
What is what exactly is the brain
Blood-brain barrier
It sells or is it
Yeah in tissue super super tightly packed
Cells
Is there a sits between the bloodstream and the Brain
It's like this protective wall
And it keeps out all is like the nasty stuff so it keeps out any like
Bacteria or viruses that would be
In your bloodstream can't get past the wall to get into your brain I kind of keep thinking of it as like
I've never actually watched Game of Thrones except for like one episode and if there was this
Giant wall
Yeah
To protect
Civilization from third of all of the the bad thing
The Wild Thing
It was made of ice and it went up
Forever I kind of feel like that wall in Game of Thrones is like the barrier
Are between
The rest of the body in the brain
But you said it's there to protect the brain so why would you want to punch a hole
Well you can imagine that if somebody has a brain tumor and we want to deliver chemicals in there that we think can
Help fight the tumor
Those chemicals the brain does not want in there
So the blood-brain barrier can create problems
According to Todd
Give me a price on a neurosurgeon at Sunnybrook
He's part of the team in Toronto that using this new bubble technique and here's how it works
Okay so say you got a tumor on the right side of your brain right above your ears
You're so mean price in the team will stick you in a chair and then I'll put a helmet on
Special helmet
This helmet has 1024
Ultrasound transducers
And we aim
2024 Altima same spot
Right on the spot at the wall where the tumor sets
Just on the other side
Just Out Of Reach
Okay so they all the ultrasound waves kind of
Focus at that one area
And then we we inject the bubbles
How many bubbles are in adults
Like hundreds of thousands
Play just put an IV in your arm
And the bubbles go in
A no-go like into your arm like over your shoulder into your heart to your lungs back to your heart eventually some of them will get
Up to the brain approximately 28 seconds from the time we inject the bubble into arm vein to buy time
I start going into a brain and eventually some of those bubbles get up
To the blood-brain barrier that wall
To the spot without laser beam is focused at specific spot is tumor sitting on the other side of and when they cross
Have with that beat
Ultrasound waves causes
The microbubbles to oscillate in size
Google big and small big and small big mouth
Bubble dance party so at this really specific part in the brain and it can be small
Smaller than like 1 millimeter by 1 mm Square all these bubbles are dancing and what that does is it
Causes the wall specific spot to almost loose it and so like a little
Like a window of space or a little hole is created in that wall and if you happen to have chemo
Therapy in your blood which you will because ahead of time the minute that hole is open
Good ideas to chemotherapy in your bloodstream would be able to just order
Flow through that opening and get straight to that brain tumor
Instead of using sound to turn the
Bubbles and Tall dancing robot
Yeah drill through the wall
Wow now that the bodies of living organism
So
Over the next
6 to 12 hours they will close those
Gaps
Transient
Meaning
It heals itself
In about 6 to 12 hours and you say they try this on someone
Yeah last November
And I think it went well
One of the things these researchers said was
Once
You're able to open these passageways
To the brain
It's not just chemo that can get in there but like suddenly any type of drug you might want to send through can can get through
Through and we just never had access to the Brain before in that way and there's a question of
How will drugs interact with the brain
Kind of don't know they've they've never been there before
It's like a whole new frontier
Using shrimp in time is done
So
I mean basically all boils down to the same
Physics of bubbles that we have
Learn from the shrimp that we can apply to many other
Applications
Wicked put it on the radio so you'll hear it.
People that like
Why do people don't like shrimp
Then they'll just keep it
I make no promises this is gone on the radio
Molly Webster this piece was produced by Molly and
Annie McEwen with help from our guest sound designer
Jeremy Bloom special thanks to clear the James Byrd Lawrence from Aunt Sophia
Albert in graffiti letters
Next up a story from our producer Simon Adler who who got interested in bubbles
Sasha Molly founder shrimpy's
Got instant Bubbles and you manage to find a guy named Dave Stein
Who is taking bubbling
To a whole new level why is a bigger bubble better
Really trying to make things bigger is a function of growing up
I don't know I always thought this was kind of inherent in the
Human psyche is
He's bigger and better and so
Well we might even make this
Stein's law
Okay
Spain's law
A bubble of bubbling
Stein's law of size
Turn off the top of my head
Air Bud
For any given
Object
There is
Hey
Larger size
Such that the nature
What's the object
Is transformed
In simple English what would that be in the
As something gets bigger it gets
What
Okay
Take
Jupiter
Okay gaseous
Planets
All right
Gates fuel tank
Jupiter bigger and bigger
Bigger and bigger at there is a size
At which
It becomes
Star
Hagen it ignites
The Sun
It transcends what it was
Then
Can a bubble get so big
That it's no longer even a bubble
Well
Before the invention
Of the bubble
Bubbles
We always thought of as
Being relatively small
And relatively round
But
As soon as you get
Up to a certain size
Say
5 foot diameter
Kind of in that rain
I know suddenly they're not round any
And
They don't pop in the same way
People who would think of bubbles popping instantaneously because they're thinking it was a little round bubbles
The dime store
And what really happened
In
Very large bubbles like the ones
My friends make
The Bible doesn't pop
Instantaneously
It gets
Punctured at a certain point and then it
Ripped open like a zipper
And there's a sound to it
It kind of goes
Pie tap
So it's not
It's
A from 100 this long bubble
To the other
Can we back up to
Tell me the story of how you like why
Who were you in 1984 when you're like
I'm going to make
This bubbles
What what what what motivated Olive
Well what motivated all of this was I was in architecture
The time I was working
For Heidi Holtzman Pfeiffer very fashionable
Affirm downtown and he says he spent his days designing these
Really intricate building
Swear like
Glass staircases
Meet the stonework of the building at a
45° angle
And the roof is going
Another I don't have to work down to the
16th of an inch
Wasn't very happy
In fact
I used to worry about
Structural collapse
He said he'd be walking down the streets of Manhattan
Imagining some building he was building in his mind
Say the addition to
Did the Virginia Museum of Fine Arts at he's imagining this building and then all of a sudden his mind with shipt
Worry
About that building collapse
And he says this just kept happening with every project
All these buildings
Crashing to the ground and just keep you up at night did you wake up yeah I felt I had to
I felt it as read
Architecture it's my responsibility
Imagine all the possible
Disaster does it became this not-so-healthy
Occupational obsession
Y
That's good for us
Let me tell you something
I'm probably getting some of these details are on but
My grandfather
Clarence
Balky
Wasn't metallurgy
Is true
Had something to do with
Building the atomic bomb and so does my uncle
And
My mother was
Quite traumatized by being a
Daughter of
The bomb source
Distance
Became part of the family Legacy
Maybe
When did way into his psyche
Poisoned his work
Oh that's just the way
I registered it
I underworld trying to basically trying to say was that I was not really happy
He is an architect
Anyway that summer 1984 my little daughter Kayla
Who was 1 and 1/2
Saw a man blowing bubbles with one of those little Dime Store watch and
She was just
Transfixed
Transported to another Realm
And so says from that point on
We were always blowing bubbles
All kinds of small bubbles medium ones large when he says pretty quick he started to wonder
How can we make you fall asleep
Kiwi Hues so you know we cut out the ends of
The coffee can help dip when it in the soap
Glue to the other
Maybe a bubble that might be
Foot foot in diameter tried getting a coat hanger and bench
Do a circle dipping that into
Do a frying pan full of soap
It was that you can make a bubble Maybe
Truth or Dare or something your daughter getting more and more excited as the bubbles get bigger is this about you
She was getting kind of bored with it
Actually Dave started to get a little upset
Yes that's
True
And I was thinking
Yeah this is an interesting design problem maximizing the size of a bubble
How you go about initially thought was
This is kind of everyone's thought when they
Start thinking about the
You just need a bigger Circle
A bigger hoop through wish to blow the bubble
Like a hula hoop with a handle on it and you would need a little one for solar Plastics
Swimming pools
Full of bubble soap with starts
Seemed kind of like
Soprema design perspective
How do you scale that up
You can't just keep making the hoop and bucket bigger
That seems crazy
So at that point I was sort of
Stuck at whatever he was going on with his life designing buildings
But then he says one day in the summer of 1984
I was
Lying in bed
One morning I can still remember the
Pattern of
Fractions
See the idea hit him like a ton of bubble-shaped
Why not have a collapsible
I
Sort of instantly saw his
Sing in my mind it
It was what we now know as
The bubble bubble
And so
I hate leaps out of bed heads to the hardware store buys his stuff
And I bought
The doll and the chain in the vast
Freetone start assembling the device
And what were you and your kitchen where were you when you were doing we don't do this
You stepped outside and what he had in his hands
Was really nothing more than like
Stick with a loop of chain
And one of the loop
Slide up and down on this
So that you could expand
In collapse the loop
That's the beauty of this design to have that control and be able to close
Back in the backyard
Close to Luther it was just like a
Record like
Straight cord
I dumped it in the bucket of soap I raise it up I open the loop
Right away this huge
Bubble
Starts
Coming out tube stretches for 7 8 ft
He's not sure
But at a certain point he closes the loop
Pinch It Off
And now it's a free-floating bubble
And it's sailing way over there
Over the Housetop and through the fog
Tell me there's a
Gigantic bubbles floating away
Biggest bubble ever
Loan
I believe since it was somewhere between the size of a
Refrigerator in a car
Iridescent is wobbly
And then suddenly
What did you feel in that moment
Bring your doctor Frankenstein who would just let this monster out in the world
Hi I got this
Cold thrill going down my spine I'll never forget
Desi sent more and more of these
Into the air
Pretty soon people started arriving in their cars and trucks
Everybody was
Totally astonished
I thought this might be my ticket
How to draw architecture
So day was able to patent the bubble thing made enough money to get out of Arkham
And in the process he transformed bubble-blowing for the thing that just like
Kids do
Kind of sport where you have like bubble athlete
My name is Gary Pearlman all over the world in Mexico they call me
I currently am the champion the heavyweight the big boy people are playing like really big
You can picture to 18 wheelers stacked on top of one another that's about how big
The bubble was
That's a slight exaggeration but anyways
There are debates going on about what kind of soap to use
Which is the best
Polymer to add to that so
And what kind of
Fabric to use for the loop
But despite all this experimentation
Pretty much everyone uses a variation of Dave's original idea
Read these people are sort of my followers you see I find it very interesting
That you had this fear of your buildings collapse
I'm sure you go into this world where
All of the things you're making are meant to
Collapse
Well that here's the thing
It's true that every bubble will
Collapse
But there's no blame
Nobody got hurt
I think we might be able to get
I'm here
So that night Dave took me out Bubba
Baking powder we have thermometer we have test
Strips for measuring pH humidity
Settings okay but the wind is so amount of wind is usually very difficult. So good
So we'll go down and try to find some
Shelter gets around the corner
Of what West End
106 to EUR
Midnight in Manhattan
Pretty much empty
Couple cars
Almost no one walking
So now I'm going to
Junket in the show
And now I'm going to raise it up
And I'm going to open the loop and I'm going to see if I can make
Pretty good
It is
Sailing along
Into the intersection and
The bubble is not chasing the taxi
That's about
The size of a
Killer whale
Maybe 20 feet long
When you get these giant bubbles
Sailing around
Buildings
It activates the
Space he says it seems to transform the architect
It definitely did
Like I made this city
Look Suddenly Beautiful and
A lava lamp
Alien and we got some people I can buy that are now taking videos of them
Look at that one
Oh that's a great one
That's that's the size of a smallish baby elephant Maybe
Okay and the taxi is now just done a U-turn to watch sncf
We got we got a bike messenger
Who's rubbernecking is even at midnight an audience with material
It just incredible like everybody okay New Yorkers are assholes
And people are stopping
Richmond
Stopping with smiles
We could detect he had just stopped in the middle of the road to watch you do this
Zoe
Do you often stop your taxi to look at a to look at things
Before
This is our life like this
It's so silly write it very silly
Very wonderful
Is vacated
Yeah that's
The size of a killer whale for sure
Do you ever feel silly out here
I
Sometimes too but
I also sometimes
Compare myself to my grandfather
Much happier to have invented
The giant bubble thing than having
Invented the bong
I also think you know
I in a way I
Feel like I have started an art form and that is
Going to go on and
Evolve
Thanks producer Simon Adler
We also want to thank all the Radiolab listeners who came out recently in blue bubbles with us in Prospect Park Brooklyn
Message
Oliver
Is produced by
Aaron wheeler is
Robert krulwich
Melissa Padgett area wac
With help from
Minecraft
Michelle hair
About science
And this message