Are you weightless
Radio WNYC
Hey I'm Jared I'm Robert krulwich it's his Radiolab so Robert one of my favorite sounds
Of all time in the sound of hearing people think
You know of a
Hearing a mind kind of formulate a thought
It wasn't there
Until it clicks in yeah that's just going to be a beautiful sound especially when the mines are you listening to
Is a person who has shaped you as shaped the show sure
So today a little bit of departure a couple of months ago I got connected to a guy named
Bill Hayes mutual friends or put us in touch. A really good book actually about Anatomy music
If I give it to my son really
Yeah
He is a writer and a photographer and I was the partner of the Late Oliver Sacks
And together we made
Tapes or recordings of conversations in the last year of his life
Now Oliver Sacks one of the great great writers of Science and masterful
Masterful writer Radiolab of grown up with him
That ended his style of combining sort of clinical scientific observation with
Deep Humanity in poetry
I feel like we're always trying to walk in his footsteps in some way
Many many times that his voice will be familiar to a lot of you but what you hear
On these tapes
Is an altogether different portrait
And why why did you start these recordings
Oliver got his diagnosis of terminal
Cancer in mid January 2015
He had had cancer about nine years earlier dealt with it
But it was back
It's spreading to his body the prognosis was 6 to 18 months
And thought it was shattering
Shortly after bill says they were sitting at the kitchen table talking
Things on his mind that he wanted to write I said well what do you what do you thinking about writing this is about
4 days after he got his diagnosis and he paused
And then he looked at me and he said
Something like
A month ago I felt that I was in good health
Even robots Dallas
881 I still swim a mile a day
But my luck has run out
And
I said stop right there
And I grab the pad and a pen
And I said start over
And I began writing as fast as I could
Has he dictated
Virtually the entire essay
Desserts spelled out like that
So we had the idea of getting a little audio recorder digital recorder
So they could be on hand at any time whether to record what he want to write
Or reminisce or
To collect stories after his death I put the recorder in a drawer
And didn't pull it out again until
Over a year-and-a-half after his death I didn't even listen to it
Any event to write my own memoir
I have been kind of very nervous about listening to them cuz I thought I'd be very sad just that we're just
Make me depressed and sad
But I took it I took the recorder out of the drawer where you had sat for 18 months and
Cypress playing of course it didn't work because the batteries were dead so I had to scramble to find batteries and when
When I did and then
Push play
Okay this is a recorded conversation
Between ows
Play
Chinese I mean
The hairs on my arms
Went off
It was as if he was alive this is the first recording you made it was eating at the
Time and he began telling me about his dreams
Dream
Springsteen
Archetypal dreams
I have to make
No
Getting lost from
I guess you found
Full of surprises to maybe
Landscape
I'm tired of fighting with being so
Very religious
But then finally coming to some
Greaser
Heavenly
Mountain Meadow
And then waking
Dreams about Journey's
Hootenanny
The journey from where to where
This was February 6th 2015 show about 3 weeks after Oliver got his diagnosis
Terminal cancer
And his immediate impulse was to write
Nevis Island
Beautifulest
My mind
Oliver was quite deaf
Even louder than he realized he would whisper words to himself trees
As he wrote them down on the pad and you wrote with a fountain pen
For Oliver writing was a form of thinking and the primary activity
For human being
My new mom
Renewable
Imaging
Activities one-year-olds
Give me pages
These are out
From there
Out
What I'm going to do is just leave that all there so you can look at it again
I'm a creature multiple draw
I dunno
Was Jim feeling
Skin peeling disorder
Trabion
Change recipient
Movies Savannah
Costa Vida
Truth or dare
Priceless Palos Verde
You known for that
Where to find John Oliver was the kind of guy who would take dictionaries to bed
To read with a magnifying glass
You mean
Need a magnifying glass
And I have one here haha I also feel the missing Mac defines off
Veritiv
Can you see if there's a word visitation
Taliesin
Yes there is
Change to a better frame of mind
Bwise
To be wise
Can you pull up the big dick strength if you come
Find the nearest Home pulse in particular I want to know whether a return to help
I sure was a man with a huge vocabulary and love of writing but still
Everyday you would be struck by a word that he want to look up
For misconduct
What did you say repentance for misconduct
Recognition of errors committed
Return to a better mind or opinion
I'm all but what's the origin of the world
To recover one's senses come to oneself again
Counseling services
I think Brooks on car do what I want
Imitation game
PCH Lotto
Return energy
Restasis
Coming back
Trust
PlayStation 3
Country max
Unexpected happened
We can pick you some harm
OK Google a slime read something to you
A general feeling of disorder
It is especially when things are going wrong internally
When homeostasis is not being maintained when the autonomic balance starts listing heavily to one side or the other
It is core Consciousness the feeling of how one is takes on an intrusive unpleasant quality
And now one will say I feel something is amiss at such times one India
Everything comes and goes and if one could take a scam or in a photograph of the body at such times when was he
Vascular beds opening and closing peristalsis accelerating or stopping is there a squirming or tightening
Spasms secretion suddenly increasing or decreasing is if the nervous system itself or the state
Weight of indecision instability fluctuation and oscillation are of the essence in the unsettled state
This feeling of disorder we lose the normal feeling of the procedure the relatively benign would lead to the death of
The huge mass of melanoma cells bees and dying would give off a variety of unpleasant and pain producing so
Substances
Soon after waking from the embolization
I was to be assailed by feelings of excruciating tiredness
In frocks isms of sleep so abrupt
Pick-n-Pull asked me in the middle of a sentence
Or a mouthful
Delirium with sees me within seconds
Even in the middle of handwriting
I felt extremely weak
And inert
Monday 10
I turned a corner I felt awful as usual in the morning but a completely different person in the afternoon
This was delightful and wholly unexpected I suddenly found myself full of physical and creative
Energy and Euphoria almost akin to hypomania exuberant thoughts rushed through my mind
How much of this with re-establishment of balance in the body how much an autonomic rebound after a profound
Autonomic depression how much other physiological factors and how much the sheer Joy of writing
I do not know
But my transform State and feeling were I suspect very close to Whitney she experienced after a. Of
Illness espresso lyrically in the gay science gratitude course for
Earth continually as if the unexpected had just happened the Gratitude of a convalescent for convalescent
This was unexpected the rejoicing of strength that is returning every waking faith in Ottumwa
Tomorrow and the day after tomorrow of a sudden sense and anticipation of a future of impaired
Pending Adventures of seas that are open again
I'm wasted Wednesday microphone on this bloody thing
Well okay you are recording this
Did the time is 9:20 in New York would be 5 hours difference between
Meantime
And it is Monday tonight
And that's to say the 20th day
After my embolization
And. 48 hours
Till the next one
End of recording
Force
On March 11th Oliver had the second embolization surgery which would cut off blood supply to the tumor
Growing in his liver
With the idea that it would give all of her
More time
We energy
We've been together six years I knew him well
And yet
I've never seen him
Massage Focus
Custom writing
I don't know what to call this piece they can't I sit on the Glorious Forest
Future I shall never know
I think I need to put in
Indicate
Pepsiman
Who is a good deal younger
Was younger
I wish I could choose to test my age
Okay
The New Yorker yes
I like the idea of staying exactly two thirds my age
Affection
Three courses yes but not 2/3 I like the idea of putting a tiny Iris Medical
Conundrum
9th Avenue reverie
Published March 20th 2015
Driving down 9th Avenue
Choking on diesel fumes from a truck just ahead of us
I say to my friend Billy he's exactly two thirds my age
I wonder whether you will see the end of internal combustion engines
The end of oil
A Cleaner World
The thought zooms me away from 9th Avenue to a forest world
A particular to the one described in that glorious Forest
To Gillian Francis book about his 39 visits to the Amazon
The past 50 years
He sees what we are doing to the Amazon and its many peoples
Speak for conservation
Sanity
Reason before we destroy it all
I went to that glorious forest in 1996 11 days of Botany study and hiking
Sing hundreds of different species of trees in a single acre
I planned before I became ill
Go to Madagascar to see its 4
Annie's Unique fun and other wildlife
Especially the lyrics
I love lemurs
Would have to see them
Study them
Graph the origin of our primate nature
But most of the forest on Madagascar have already been obliterated
And not a naturally
Lemurs are dying
Honking horns bring me back to 9th Avenue
I seem to spend hours lost in reverie
Thinking about the Amazonian a madagascan forest
Lemurs
The Time Machine
We have scarcely moved
Are still behind the stinking long destroying truck
Not in my life
Billy answers
Yes
I'm eating a lot
Isis recording where Oliver is talking on the phone to Lawrence weschler RN wechsler but anyhow he
Irish dude have a
Abscond
Follow up
On Thursday
I was terrified to this
In fact was it did show was that 80% of the metastasis in the liver
I'm have been destroyed by the embolization
With luck I should have two or three
Good maps
After this
I'm well I just hope that I'd come
See friends advice and maybe traveler little
Yeah and I think next month timeout cuz I'm going to go to London
To say hello to be farewell
Who albums
Friends and family
I'm done
Accountant to head beyond that
Tell them it's still one short
I will also
Ovulation
Who I want to hear I want to hear
Over the years
Eiffel Dupree 2000 notebook
The Contemporary area
The three of them a type of special function
To record abnormalities perception
During times of sensory impairments for deprivation
The calendar book
Is there a modest affair
Does quite small chips easily into a pocket
Crucial
If I need to have it with me at all times
Increasing decimals
A normal phone to mishear what people say
But missed hearing the Devon entirely
You kept what you hear you except what you see every mishearing is a novel surprising concoction
I never get used to them
Refresh
Harry
Cannabis hearing
Take the car for a spin
I can't take the conference room I've noted that
This is beautiful
Terracon sick time publishing has heard of the big-time cuttlefish
Price of a Gucci bag
I need $5 to put the mall in I think they should
Format will make the point
The sound
Humps everything
When surroundings one's wishes and expectations conscious and unconscious can certainly Biko determine
Shenzhen miss hearing
But the real mr. flies at lower levels
In those parts of the brain involved in phonological analysis and decoding doing what they can with distorted or deficiency
Signals from our ears these parts of the brain manage to construct real words or phrases even if they are absurd
And yet there is often the sort of style or Witt
A dash annies instantaneous inventions they reflect to some extent
One's own interests and experiences
I rather enjoy them
Only in the realm of mishearing at least my Miss hearings
Can a biography of cancer become a biography of Cantor one of my favorite mathematicians
Tarot cards can turn into pteropods a grocery bag into a poetry bag all-or-none s
Into oral numbness
And a mere mention of Christmas Eve
A command to kiss my feet
Brooks no wonder I couldn't write anymore
I'm I'm asking more cartridges and going through these to quit today
I want to reassure you
Are already in the drawer okay
So I think it's time to let your
Weary mind rest
Receipt Hog in the morning
Supra just kiss me whenever I have a dry mouth dry I can have them
CSI Pacific Raceway
Hello this is David from Berlin Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan foundation in hunting public
Understanding of Science and Technology in the world
More information about Sloan at www.
Sloan. Org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here I'm a producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help this summer I'm hosting a show and I've requested
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers were looking for stories about
That what we're calling tiny moments childhood Brilliance basically I want to hear about those times
Did something
It just means you lean back and say wow how did they do that maybe it was the moment that I kids
You've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you or maybe the kid was at piano lessons and you said
Only noticed they were doing math class
Play music in the margin of their geometry homework
Something super smart but doesn't have anything to do with the test if you have a story with us
Go to radiolab.org Brilliance and record a short audio message for us again that's
Radiolab.org / Brilliance thank you so much
You like to impart some wine for your elderly law
You look very happy
Which one of these jackets appeals to you if you're going to pick one to go to the Stars
Not one of course I have to take my own unfortunately
I know I want you to respond
Owned
DeSoto
Routine
I don't know where I got my package
Hohhot
Hot
Know that word
You're very handsome
You should have something to me I might go out
Enjoy that
In Littlestown do I go out into the neighborhood
Remind
Good Karma
Rejoice
I wasn't counting how many did you do with your friend
Overhead enjoyed a couple of really good month of feeling well and fit
Getting lots of writing done you had completed not only a general feeling of disorder short piece miss hearing
She's Autobiography on the move was published he worked on a piece on the evolution of the eye and he comes
Completed a major case history on the performer Spalding Gray weed made
This wonderful trip to London for 10 days
After we returned from the trip he knew that he would have to get another CAT scan to see how things were going
And I I would say that we kind of had a feeling an optimistic feeling he seem to be doing well so he went into that
Hoping for the best
But it was exactly the opposite the cancer had spread
Beyond the liver to other organs vetted
Was looking very bad indeed
Oliver
More than anyone I think knew that
Timeless
Running out
I'm believing
Am I wonder if I could ask you to look up something
I'm about
Cheap
Is that what I hear
Remember the Sabbath day to keep it holy
Sexual camera
Identity
She was having a lot of discomfort and had to have a catheter implanted in his abdomen
To drain off fluid that was accumulating from the tumors
Which is around August 4th or 5th
It was really the only solution
And I
It was quite uncomfortable
And it had to be drained
Daily
And it also
Unfortunately ended his swimming he was a great swimmer and you love to swim
But he didn't complain
Swimming to come to an end so he
Put his head down basically and begin working on this essay Sabbath
What you doing
What do you think of Siri
Dramatic reading
Just started a little while ago how are you
His longtime assistant editor Kate
Pittsburgh street parking lot uses her healthcare living top her
My mother
What is the temperature right now
Okay fine stand them
My mother has 17 brothers and sisters
Have an orthodox priest
Also structure that Harbor show him where
And I was told if you woke up
Turn off the lights
I love that my father to trade for the Orthodox backgrounds
Hopefully Ravinia concert tomorrow
Remember the Sabbath day to keep it holy
I'm trying to get some from the rest of the week
My mother would like to share those things with her having some moving
Phone systems on different
Two Jewish life until they're gone.
Sugar collagen
Harvard spaceships refusing to tell me to admit
She won't be able to take it you did tell her
Exported she came down for the look of horror on her face and sheets
Joanna fulmination
Kind of cordiality even Loft
Sweetfields hateful eight
Judaism
4 inch human figure 3 and 4 us to determine
Social Security
Oversexual
PS4
My mother's would still Echoes In My Mind
YouTube us what we received
60s era
Video for you to share the pride of Friday evening Virginia
What's the translation for peace
What time is high tide at comfortable
If she was difficult and Billy Isaac photos from September
That's how you feel able to trust hard to find life
Full of transfiguration of bisexuality
Chasing the world who could be a dream about GCC.
And now weak short of breath I want
Melted away by cancer
Peace River North
Horses that fight different from Food Network for a life
I find
Mindful statistical. Of the day of rest
When was the show Friends workers.
I want to beg. Seuss dress
On August 14th Sabbath was published in the New York Times
That same day he began to
Dictate the table of contents for the river of consciousness
The collection of essays which he knew would be published posthumously
It was getting his house in order
I don't know that I'm capable of much rice and you know that I wanted
But I hope I come to you and
Cage quarter
Home hospice
Star secret I will require an amount of cash
Shooting intravenous nursing
Things beyond what you want Kate and provide or should I
Andersen 200 release you and I
Just my friends and comforters
A1 nosker tinting my appetite
Can you bring me an address with attention ready
Yes
I probably should have some dick.
2 weeks later
On August 30th 2015 Oliver Sacks died at home
In the last seven months of his life
He wrote and published
9 pieces and there were many many more that he
Started wasn't able to finish and some of the exes who wrote a note and a new collection puppet after he died
Cult of the river of Consciousness and that's just out
The readers that you heard in the story of were radio lovers and a mccuen Simon. Learn Bethel hop.
Thanks also to Mike Pash cash for engineering out and the piece was produced by Carla Moretti
This is Emily calling from Houston radio I was created by Jad abumrad and is produced by Soren wheeler
Keith is our director of sound design Maria Matisse are Padilla is our managing director our staff includes Simon.
Rachel Cusick David Gable Bethel hobdy Tracy hunt Matt kielty Robert krulwich
McEwen lots of Nasir Melissa O'Donnell Aryan whack and Molly Webster with help from Amanda or rhonchi
Shima Ali Ali David Fox Niger Vitaly Phoebe Wang and Katie Ferguson are fact check
Where is Michelle Harris