Are you awake
Northern listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
Hey this is Radiolab on Jedi Cam'ron I'm Robert krulwich topic today is goodness
Goodness
Selflessness
Show me the map
Okay so you ready for this it's a while back we we did the story that
Brussels is really stuck in our heads
It was a story that was
Ask and it's really deep question and the answer that we got to answer didn't quite
Click
Yeah it's so just assertive
Set the table the question was why do people
Do good in the world
World so we ask that question look at it from the perspective of genetics computer science all kinds of things we ended up profile
Jordan Air
Heroically good
People that were Heroes
Slate that remarkable things
We told her stories with that question in mind why do certain people do good in the world and others don't
Yeah so we can revisit that question today in the story that we told
Because I think we have something better and smarter to say about it finally something
Very peculiar to say about us it turns out.
First and then going to come back and hopefully sheds new light on
So
Here we go
Again this story just began with a simple question
That question lettuce
Two guy named Walter Rutkowski executive director and Secretary of the Carnegie hero fund Commission
Cool thanks for doing this
Can you just give us a little background on
The hero fund what is the Carnegie hero fund
The Carnegie hero fund is
Is a private operating Foundation
It was established by Andrew Carnegie in 1904
And what we do is recognize civilian heroism throughout the United States
Canada
By giving an award called The Carnegie medal
And accompanying the Carnegie medal is a financial Grant
How much
Currently the amount is $5,000
And how do you guys choose Your Heroes
We judge the
Heroic acts against a list of
Performance
So then you have to have some kind of definition of hero which includes some and excludes other yes
Perfect basic definition
Which is
Civilian
Meaning no military
Who voluntarily to
Leave the point of safety degree
Risk his own life
Apply for
To an extraordinary degree
To save or to attempt
To save
The life of another human
How about 7
Just came from memory so don't like it happens in a person's mind at that pivotal moment when they decide to voluntarily
Voluntarily leave a safety and risk their life to extraordinary degree
To save a life
Another human that's what I wanted to know
Treatise jumping
Okay so the first one we have on our list is
Is a loris
Shrek okay
Phone number 73546
And the award number is 8
8000 +
I am Laura shrake
I am from
Mattoon Illinois and I
Currently live in
Dubai United Arab
Laura spoke with our producer timeout okay so we're going back a little bit
Yeah 15 years
Back in the mid-90s
21 year old College to
And I was driving through the country
And
I saw a woman getting mauled by a bull
And attack
Faster
She stopped to see what was going on and started yelling at her
To see what I could do
The woman was on the ground in the pool was
Turn the air back on the ground while he was clearly struggling
Side of the fence but
Defense
Was Electric
So here's the moment that we find fascinating
At this point Laura can either go forward through thousands of volts of electricity toward an angry bull that will lie
Likely Mall her to or
She can stay safe
I went ahead and
Just climb through the fence
And I don't remember ever feeling the electricity
She says by the time she got through
A neighbor has shown up in through or piece of pipe
The whole time she's yelling at me
Hit the ball in the face as hard as
As you can and don't stop
Shrek went up to the bull
And
Beat It repeatedly
Which is 2 foot lengths of tubing
I think
It distracted the bull enough
Where she was able to get out from under him
And as soon as we are outside the fence
Looking back into the past
The bull was literally right there
Apus
Get the ground few times and snorted
He was not happy
To a question
When you were there at that fence
And
You had
The choice either stay put or to go through it
What was going through your mind when it was there calculation there
No
Can't really say that
I mean you know your options or anything like that I did not know
It was just
Here's the problem
Here's what I need to do
Something needed to
So there's no choice moment
Not that I recall
No
If nobody came to This Woman's rescue she would die
Unfortunately
This is the usual explanation
I couldn't stand there and not
Do any
I would like
Repeal 2A
I didn't really take the time
Think about
What else could
I can't say I ever really thought about loan
Okay we just jumped ahead cuz we thought we try again that's the voice of the next Carnegie hero that
Walter told us
Yeah William David Pennell
60 second
Person to receive the credit union
I producer Lynn Levy tracking down there can you hear me
William David Pennell
37 years old at the time of his heroic act 1999
I was
Early in the morning it was like 3:19 a.m. in a small town near pits
Pittsburgh Pittsburgh Pennsylvania Monongahela Pennsylvania
We was in bed sleeping in
My wife a lot crash I actually didn't hear it for the dog
On my one dog was carrying on so right away I buy run down there
Panel went outside his house there was a very bad automobile accident
A car crashed head-on into a utility pole was like Rippling up the windshield out from under the hood
Did the same wearing only sweatpants no shoes or barefoot
So here we are standing in front of this ball of fire there are three teenagers inside that
Louis doesn't know it neither A or B
Go into the driver's door
And it's big fella out the door so I reached out to hold of him around the chest
Pulling from the driver seat out to the ground meat on their car was just like Blazer
My neighbor was there to holler and there's more of them in there so I run back to the vehicle you found that the front seat passenger
It was trapped in the wreckage
Arthur young man entered the car third time by then it was tired
Ft above the car's roof
Screaming
But nobody nobody would help
In.
I reached in and grabbed the older the kid was in the back by the Scruff of the neck
Alright so when you're coming out of your house
Spend any looking at that car what was going through your head
I'll just
China's try to help
I mean
I did what any normal person would do I mean
You know I just kept saying this is somebody's kid you know what I mean
It's a tie my daughter was like 16
I'm saying to myself you know
There's something golf
Forbid whatever happened to her
But I would hope someone would be there at the hell
Do you ever talk to your neighbors and ask them
Why didn't come in there
I know you know what that
Those funny you brought that up because now I've never never brought it up
Never brought a
How come
I don't know
Maybe I probably wouldn't like their answer
I don't know why I've never asked
What do you think is the difference between you and those other people who just started
Twisted by
Are acronyms
Aquaman trailer
So Arbol girl she didn't know
This guy didn't really know either
Somebody must be able to tell us
Something
About what they were thinking at that moment that
Allow them the gave them the courage to do what they did I can't give you a definite answer as to what propels people to do this no
But we took one more shot with Walter and if we take a quick break we're going to here
One more hero story from him
Come back
This is Sam calling from Denver Colorado
Radioactive
Supported in part by the alpha
Alfred P Sloan fan
Enhancing public understanding of science
And Technology
In the modern world
More information about Sloan
At www
Sloan. Org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
And I request
For those of you who
Who spend a lot of time with kids parents
Aunts and uncles
Teachers looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments
Brilliant
Basically I want to hear about this
When a kid you know did something
It just means you lean back and say
How do they do that
Maybe it was the moment that I
A kid you've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of their musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class
Are ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the
Epic moments where
A kid does something super smart
It doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story
Go to radiolab.org
Flash brilliance
Mrecorder short
Audio message
And that's radiolab.org
Flash Brewing
Thank you so much
Robert Radiolab
We're back now with Walter Bukowski who's going to tell us the third and final of his Hero Stories We Tell
Rid of all the cases he's heard
This is the one
The puzzles in the most
The case of Wesley James Autry
I-88 construction worker from
New York 50 year old man
Who did jump into the track that in a subway station
To remove
Hey fellow young man who had fallen onto
The track
The gentleman was
6 foot 280 lb
He was he was in Earth
And yet mister
Ultra persisted despite
Back to the train was coming
Their appointment was at least in my estimation where you would have to say
I have to get out of here
Because I'm going to be killed
I'm not suicidal
But Mr Audrey didn't think that way
He and I parked in this
This manner
What he did was he lay at optiv
Between the rails
While the train passed over them
In the farthest reaches of my imagination
I can see myself jumping onto a Subway track to attempt the rescue
What I can't see myself doing is lying atop the victim all the train passes over
Making the story even more nuts
When we finally met up with Wesley autrey on the platform where this incident happened
35th and Broadway
Explain to us
Des daughters
And
How old are you
Not at that time my daughter was
4 + 6
And
Dismiss them there
Should have picture
Oh my God
Super cute Robin one behind me a shoe key
Envista baby sauce
So entertaining there in the sky starts convulsing and then eventually
Falls off the platform onto the tracks right of the train is
His choice of pretty Stark
Northern state is complete stranger
He's got to leave his daughters behind
Actually without a dad
I'm looking at him shaking and going into another seizure or some strange reason to voice out of nowhere they don't worry about
I don't worry about the daughters you can do that so he jumps
Runs the guy
Is he conscious
Play slip I look up the train again clothes I grabbed his hand again will slip apart this rain is closer
50 feet 20 ft 10 ft and it's right there at all
The guy get him in a bear hug and flattened his body against the guy as much as he can
The first train called just graze my cat
Train car went right over them
When the train came to a stop 45 carlls path over I look them in the eyes excuse me you seen that
I have a seizure or something I don't know you you don't know me so I just kept talking to him until he came through
And he was like well we have like we are looking for train he said what who are you I said I can't not to save your life so he kept asking
We are we dead I wouldn't have him I gave him a slight pinch on his arm he's at all just a see you you're very much alive
Have you did you ever ask yourself at this point like what am I doing
What am I doing here what about you
Between-the-legs I can hear my daughter screaming so when that train come to a stop
Viola from underneath the train
Excuse me I'm the father
We are okay
I just want to let my daughters know that that I'm going to tell you because I know that they are worried about me
Everybody start clap
Can I ask you a question
So it's
The point which
You said You Heard a Voice
That
Said I can do that
I can do this
What's what is amazing to me
Is it you left your daughter's right here and dive after a guy you don't know
He was a stranger total stranger but you know what
The mission wasn't come completed
I was chosen for that
You felt shows like you were charged
I feel like I'm the chosen one
Luther religious person though
I would plunder
Why me
Maybe 20 years ago
I was supposed to be
At a certain point
And then explain to us exactly why he jumped he was the one guy who could
He said right before his feet left the platform this one specific moment
From his life flash to mine
This thing to happen
I had a gun full to my temple but you know that it was a misfire so
A gun was put to your head and miss it so you are almost dead for almost dead
So you think you might have been spared for
After that moment he says when the gun went click
He didn't die
He always wondered
Why had God spared him
That moment
Until he was on the platform
Guy fall off
He says when he knew
This is why I can do this you just I could do this I can do this
That boys when a boy said that you going to be okay I knew everything was going to work out
You know what I think
The end of the day
I don't think that there's an answer to the question we asked
I don't think you're a question
Why were you a hero I don't think that any three of these here I mean the last one had the longest explanation
He had been selected for some purpose but does he know why you lying I'm not a clue.
9/3 gives me some
What is he give you
Okay so the first to write they have no idea
This is just something in them that made them at
Pick a number 3
Talking about circumstances
The world prepared him for that mower
Serendipity
Makes me think
What what if
Circumstances are just right
Tamela Mann
He used to say to me all the time usage
How did you make
I don't know if I could have done that
As well you know what
Don't say you wouldn't do this or you wouldn't do that
Do your put in that situation
Back when we asked Walter
How many nominations
Do you get a year
Are they hard to find
No they are not hard at all
Defined
We are fortunate to be living in a society
Regardless of what you hear elsewhere
We are fortunate
Society where people do Lookout
Others even strangers
He told us
They've even have to up their guidelines
Make it harder to win
Simply because of the vast number for wrote Deeds
Happening day-to-day life
I got to save it
We went with this feel good thought about
About all the people who are doing good because I honestly don't think we knew what to say
Say to end that story was nice to know there was a lot more good people than we thought
We went to we were trying to figure out why people
Why do people who do that do that and why we're different are there different than us at the end we didn't really get there
But then yeah
This guy walked
You should say
I just for a business purposes who you are once again Robert sapolsky I'm a professor of neuroscience at
Stanford University Robert has been on our program many many times talking about any number of things that you just come out
Out with a book called behave trying to explain why we do everything we do
Rain in the history of the culture everything
Maybe he would have something to say about it
Puzzle
Yep I will it let me just let just ask you you've heard all three of these things
What does this what do these details make you think
Think what we see
With all three
Is how highfalutin moral reasoning plays like zero role in what went on their moral reasoning
Doesn't do anything
Can You Stand The First
Think about it supposed to be told us which
Is it
When we were asking people what were they thinking
Serve the wrong question
And everybody else always gets the same answer we just
I wasn't thinking I was
Feeling about what if this were my sixteen-year-old daughter I hearing a voice or
With the bull woman sang I wasn't thinking
Like before I knew it I had jumped in
The evidence suggests
Sapolsky says that in situations like this
People just don't reason their way to a decision that's not how it works correct people don't think their way
Turn moral decision in fact you give people enough time to release
Think their way in a circumstance like that
Most people think their way to concluding this isn't my problem or
Somebody else will take care of it work
Here's why it's their fault
So that means I'm okay if it's not thinking or moral reason
Then maybe what these heroes are doing is they're their feeling
There there
They're empathizing more than the rest
That's why they do what they do
Ironically probably not
Probably not yeah
Okay Sue empathy your ear feeling somebody else's pain
Weather
Paying your toes on fire or pain
Feeling the pain of somebody else
Pain is painful
And if it's painful enough and acute and burning enough what that translates into
Is
I can't take it this
Too upsetting and you need to run away
Some point
If you were mostly focused
On my God what were this to be with this feel like if this were happening to me
That's the predictor of people who don't necessarily don't very readily make that leap
From feeling empathy
To actually acting compassionately
No that's not what I asked you to say I thought you were going to take it the other way
Hot when it's memememememe at your pain is my pain
Those people are less likely to step forward
Yeah
They're less likely to actually go into the compassionate thing
Suppose he told us that there have actually been studies that have found this
That win
Someone
Actually empathizes
Physically feels another person
Pain
They're more likely to turn away from it
Rather than
Step forward and try and alleviate that person suffering you put somebody in a circumstance and for example how many shocks
Really willing to get to intervene
To help somebody in some simulation
Game for example
And you look at is this the person whose heart rate soars
When they see somebody else in this tough situation
Or is this the kind word remains fairly steady
The latter is more likely to act compassionately
So interest okay so what we're barreling towards here is
It's not so much about moral reasoning
It's not so much about new Fast empathy but it's about a type of empathy
That allows you to remain detached enough
I actually Act
So emotional distance will create the Humane or Charlack
Exactly
You need a certain amount of detached
That's surprisingly where comes in
And that runs counter to so many of our instincts about what empathy should be about and what I think we see
See here is probably the most reliable Realm
People going into English heroic thing
Which is when it's implicit
When it's automatic
When it's not you sitting there reasoning through well how many coffees my jeans am I going to pass on if I do this for my
My close relatives
And where's not empathy
The hour
Feeling for this person or as this person or with this person or above the
And instead
Before I knew it
I jumped in the river to save this child
And I think that's where you see some of the most
Interesting reliably
24 Robux stuff
When it's implicit when it's
And you know how a person can
Get that
Kind of
Compassion made implicit is it
It is something you're born with or something cultural at your parents
Can you have any idea
The thing is
We don't know what
Hunt about the neurobiology of how
A moral good goes from being a frontal task
To an implicit task
But we know what time about how that works in a much more mundane area
Which is like
You'll learn how to do something
Like you're a Pianist and you're learning some new top piece of music
This is really tough
Trill
And every time you're playing it
As you approach the trill your thinking here it comes remember tuck your elbow and weed with your thumb
Come and do this
It is what would be called a declarative task
Claire's
Explicit knowledge
And that's completely about this part of brain the hippocampus talkin the frontal cortex
And it's sitting there saying here it comes and remember how you do it and remember how you do it wrong what happened last time and
How great it felt when you talked to your elbow into remember to that and then
Suddenly there's the day
We are playing the peace
And you realized your four measures passed the trill and you played it just fine
That's the first day you played it without having to think about it
And jargon in the learning field is it is stopped
Being
An explicit
Declarative task
And it's become an implicit
Procedural tasks
That's the first
Time
Your hands know what better than your heads
Take somebody who's like beating the pants off of you at tennis
And they've just unlike some amazing backhand and crushed you
And what you need to do strategically now is
Force them to take that procedural knowledge and make it to Claret again
Stop at that point you give him this
Sequias
Smile
Cuz you're amazing
Tennis player that was amazing
How did you do that
Do you put your hand over on that side of the West Side what what about your butt
Scrunching your butt on the left side of the right
Any for some it's like you make somebody like
Think very
Explicitly and procedurally how you go down flights of stairs and you're going to fall down the stairs because none of us have done stairs procedurally
Since we are about 2 and 1/2 years old
Swarmed over our threesome release the first two of our threesome they might have been ruined for the next experience
But if you let them do their natural thing
Then they would rescue again maybe
If I could just keep it in place at
Do you think that the simplicity
Do you think that that there's a clean dramatically analogy I mean do you think that
Is that it
The people
For whom it is automatic
It's automatic.
Because they practice
In the way that like the primes Subway
Yeah freak zample Lots
Studies were done this to which people in
Either Germany or nazi-occupied
Europe
Shielded Jews
Give them shelter but their own lives at risk
And it wasn't predicted by level of
Vacation there goes all that moral reasoning stuff
And it wasn't even protect
Predicted by things like religiosity was
People who had simply been raised
You do the right thing
It was automatic
It was implicit for them
They didn't have to sit there
And
Think about or feel about it was automatic
Is that thank you mommy and daddy is that what that is
Thank you mommy daddy Rabbi priest
What is that
I think it's mostly that
But of course it's messier than playing a Trill on a piano we're doing a 10 that I can
Meet people first learned about it and
You literally can see the transition from which part of the brain's handling the task
To the initial view was okay that's how you do trill's on the piano
But then you see something even more amazed
Which has more complex stuff happens my my father
In his last years had
Pretty severe dementia
He was as a professor or even an architectural historian and he reached a point where
He could not identify the names of all of this kids consistently didn't know where he was what decade excetera
But
Crompton
And he could give you the
Totally Lucid opinionated
Frankie entertaining
10 minute lecture on the history of flying buttress
And
Then come back two minutes later and prompt them again and you give you the exact same one again
For him that was as implicit
As
The tennis player doing the backhand
Or playing the trolls on the piano when
I fully expect when I'm demented someday I'll give this exact
What sure that I just gave and I can do it over and over and over and students complain
So all sorts of stuff more complex than a tennis backhand becomes implicit
I think what we're seeing with the woman with the boulder in the elect
Expense is
Something
Ratably
High-level abstract stuff
Becomes implicit as well
You don't like fling your elbow way out to the right when you do the trill
And you don't stand by and watch somebody being like done in
You just before you know it you don't reason you don't feel you just do it before I knew it I had to run in there
No is this one of your lectures do you talk about that this very thing love
Otherwise when we come and visit you in 13 years will you be treating us with this very
Precisely
Empathy empathy is an interesting topic sit down this will be on the final
Big big thanks to Robert sapolsky who's new book
I just called behave
The pieces produced by Amanda run check and
If you like the story and it's kind of got you thinking go and listen to a good show which is at radiolab.org
Good in the British application yes
Pancetta
This is Graham Elwood from Memphis
Radiolab created
It is produced by Soren wheeler
Dylan Keith Sr director of sound
Maria matus art Padilla is our managing director
Our staff includes Simon Adler
Becca Bressler
Rachel Cusick
David gebel
Bethel Hobbs
Tracy hunt
McAfee
Robert krulwich
Latif Nassar
Melissa O'Donnell
Arianne wack
Pat Walters
Aunt Molly Webster
With help from Amanda or on check
Shima Aji
David Fox
Vitaly
TD Bank
Aunt Katie Ferguson
Checker is Michelle Harris