Okay so we'll try to simplify something sure
Hey this is Chad before we launch into
This week's podcast I want
Make you aware of a lot of friends down the hall
Truck my friend are friends
On the media Brooke Gladstone is here with me
I have a new show coming out
Did I
I think I might be in
I'm excited to be in
Excited about so what is it
You are going to be in it it's an episode oh you don't want to say show because hun Radiolab that generally means you're launching a whole new
New Enterprise this is an episode on
Twitch
Which
Some people know as if
As if it was part of their family or like what yeah is that something you need medication for so it depends
Are your situated but we are going to do is examine
How it came to be
And how it points to the future of
Where our culture is going
Most people if they've ever heard of it
They know it's about
Watching and commenting in real time
On
People
Playing
Video games
No
Oh my God
And you guys are more like your profile one of these
The main character in that story is
Ninja who makes something like half a million dollars a month
What box
On Twitch
Yes
Through contributors who say
Davis out loud
Or
Point me mention my name
When is the same time he's playing the game
Even
Giving advice
Young boys
With girlfriend
Don't act like you know don't make doughmakers
Reassure that
I really feel like I'm putting in more effort into relationship
Then like
Then I feel like you are
And I want to know I had anything I just want to make sure that you're
You're just a bit
Invested in this is I am
I think it's something
New
I want to hear that
Well thank you ok dufur letting me in the top of your shell
Absolutely so
Twitch on on the media
Onthemedia.org check it out I'm in there it's
You can be amazing but not just cuz of me cuz you broke
And Bob and Bob
Are you awake
Northern listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
Hey I'm Jared I'm rodheim Robert krulwich Radiolab and today we have a story about what we can say
And by the way there's going to be a smattering of curse words here that we're not going to believe I think makes sense given the content of the story
And also there's some
Graphic scenes
Stat
Got kids with you may want to
Might want to anyway the story comes to us from producers Simon at
District start in 2008
Sure how about with a song
Yes please
Bmac Facebook
Rise up
I stopped and put back on
So I December 27th a sunny Saturday morning that this group of young to
Middle-aged women gathered in Downtown Palo
That's awesome
They're wearing these colorful hats
And are singing and swaying directly in front of the glass door at headquarters of
Facebook
Is there a song called
Yes
Was a humble Gathering of a few dozen women and babies
That right there is one of the organizers of the Gathering Stephanie Muir
What do you call an event Facebook nursing
Nursing as in like
Breastfeeding
The intent was really just to
Be visible
And be peaceful
And make a quiet point
Waterway point
Are they trying to make Stephanie in this group of mothers you know they were on Facebook as many people were
And they'd have
Photos taken of themselves occasionally breastfeeding their babies
They wanted to share with their friends what was going on so they would upload those photos to face
These pictures
Would get taken down
And they would receive a warning from Facebook for uploading pornographic content
And people work
Really getting their backs up over this
They wanted Facebook to stop taking their photos
To say that will nudity is not allowed
Breastfeeding is exempt
.
Android backup
Now
What
Stephanie couldn't have known at the time
Was that this
Small
Peaceful protest
Turn out to be sporting a Faceoff on Facebook
One of the opening shots
Facebook trigger The Hornet's Nest and what would become a loud Rock
View Facebook
You and Global battle
And now I'm not talking about
All the things you've recently heard about
Russian interference in election meddling oreda breeches
But but rather something that I think is is deeper than both of
Free Speech violence against what we can say
And what we can't save Facebook
Fondear
Thank you mr. chairman
Mr. Zuckerberg I got to ask you
Do you subjectively prioritize or censor speech
Congresswoman
We don't
In trouble for doing a sensory
But there are
What what what really grabbed me was
Who is discovering that
Underneath all of this
Is
An actual rule book
Apex
Document
That dictates what
I can say on Facebook
What you can say on Facebook
And what all 2.2 billion of us
Can't say on Facebook for everyone in the entire Globe one set of rules
That all 2.2 billion of us are expect
The following is an actual document it's a digital document
It's about 50 pages if you print it off
And I
In bullet points
And if then statements it spells out sort of a First Amendment
For the glow
Which
Made me wonder
Like
What are these
How were they written
And can you even have one rule book
Right exactly
I don't into this world book and dug up some stories that
Really
Put it to the test
Okay I'll I'm going to sleep now. We're going to hear 3 ish
Okay okay give me to send the issue but that's go ahead with let's start back
On that morning in mm
The morning that you could argue
Started it all
Cuz in the building right behind those protecting mothers
There was a group of Facebook employees
Sitting in a conference room
Trying to figure out what to do
Cool so if I
So I'm just going to
So I was able to get in touch with a couple of former Facebook employees
One of them was actually in that room at that moment
And now neither of these two were comfortable being identified but they did give us permission to quote them
Extensively house that will that take work for you
Just so we have it
So what you're going to hear here is is an actor we brought in to read quotes taken directly from interviews that we did
With these two different former Facebook employees
All right ready
So
At the time when I join them there was a
Small group 12 of us mostly recent College grads Integrity team again
Keep in mind this was in the early 2000s
Change this week in the internet hierarchy deep dark
Myspace.com
Is now the most visited web
Us
Facebook head somewhere in the neighborhood of 10 million users
We were smaller than Myspace
The vast majority of them College
And so in those early days those 12 people they would they would sit around in a
Conference like room with a big long table
Each of them in front of their own computer and things would come up onto their screen flagged to Facebook
And I like meaning like I a user saw something that I thought was wrong exactly like a reporting a piece of content that you
You think violates
The community standards this is Kate klonick she's a professor of law at St John's in in she's been a lot of time studying the
This very thing
And in she says in those early days what would happen is
A user would flag a piece of content and then
Fat content along with an alert would get sent to one of those people sitting in that room
It would just pop up on their screen
Most of what you were saying was either naked people
Blown off heads org
Things that there is no clear reason why someone had reported cuz it was like a
Photo of a golden retriever
People are just annoying
And every time something popped up on the screen the person sitting at that computer would have to make a decision
Whether to leave that thing up or take it down
And at the time if you didn't know what to do you would turn your pod leader who was you know
Somebody who'd been around nine months longer than you and asks
What do I do with this
And they would either have
Seen it before and explain it to you or you both with knowing you
Google something
It really was just kind of an ad hoc approach standard or any common standard
They had a set of community standards but the thing at the end of the day they were just kind of that was one page long
It was not very specific guidelines were really one page long there one page long
And basically all this page said was
Nudity is bad
So is Hitler and if it makes you feel bad take it down
And so when one of the people sitting in that room would have a breastfeeding picture
Pop up on the screen in front of them
They be like
I can see a female breast so I guess that's nudity and they would take it down
Until
Rise up fight for the rights to have breastfeeding
Anyway
Now a dozen or so people in front of their office
This is on a Saturday
It it probably wasn't causing Facebook too much heartache
But I thought
You know hey we have an opportunity here with you know over 10000 members in our group
According to Stephanie mirror those protesters were just a tiny fraction of a much larger online group
Who had organized
Clean up
So to coincide with the live protest I just typed up a little blurb encouraging hour
Members that were in the group
To do a virtual nursing
A virtual nurse
Right
What we did
They posted a message asking their members
Two for one day
Change their profile Avatar
To an image of breastfeeding and then change their status
To the title of our group pay Facebook breastfeeding is not obscene and it caught on
The social networking website is under Fire for its policy on photos of women breastfeeding their children
Thousand members participated and the media requests started pouring in
Hundreds of interviews for print
Chicago Tribune Miami Herald Time Magazine we are X Washington Post
What is an interesting phenomenon
It was a media storm
And
Eventually
Perhaps
As a result of our group in our efforts
Facebook
Was
Forced to get much more specific
About
Their rules
Soap for example by then nudity was already not allowed on
But they had no definition for nudity
They just said no nudity and so decide Integrity team that does 12 people at the time they realize they had to start
Spelling out exactly what they meant
Precisely
All of these people at Facebook were in charge of trying to
Define nudity so I mean yeah the first cut out it was
Visible male and female genitalia
And then visible female breasts
And then the question is
Well okay how much of it
It's me showing before it's nude
And the thing that we landed on was if you could see essentially the nipple and areola
The nap nudity
And it would have to be taken down
Which
Theoretically at least would appease these protests
Because you know now when a picture would pop up
Of a mother breastfeeding
As long as the child was blocking the view of the nipple in the area let they they could say cool no problem
Then you start getting pictures that are women with just their babies on their chest
With their breasts
Bear
Like for example maybe baby was sleeping on the chest of a bare-breasted woman and not actively breastfeeding
Like is this actually breastfeed
No it's actually not breasts
Spitting the woman is just holding the baby and she has her top off
No but she was clearly just breastfeeding the baby
Well like I would say
But I would say it's sort of like kicking a soccer ball
Like a photo of someone who has just kicked a soccer ball you can tell the ball is in the air but there is no contact between the foot
And the ball in that moment potentially so although it is a photo of someone kicking a soccer ball they are not in fact
Kicking the soccer ball in that phone became the procedure or the
Get the protocol of the approach for all these things
We have the basic
Shirley on what we can see in the image
And so
I didn't like that to stay up under the rules because it could be
To easily exploited for other types of content like nudity or pornography
We got to the only way you could have ejected Lee say that the baby in the mother were engaged in breastfeeding is if the baby's lips were touch
Touching a woman's nipple
So they included but you can call like an attachment
Closs
But as soon as they got that rule in place
Like you would see you know a 25 year old woman and a teenage looking boy right and like
What the hell is going on there oh yeah it's gets really weird if you like start entering into like
Child and I wasn't even going to bring that up cuz it's kind of gross
It's like breastfeeding p*** other sites like the currently
And so this time they realize they needed to have a nudity rule that allowed for breastfeeding
But also had some kind of an age
So then we were saying okay once you've progressed past infancy then we believe that it's inappropriate
But then pictures would start popping up on your screen and they'd be like wait
Is that an infant
Like where's the line between infant and toddler and so the thing that we landed on was if it look like the child could walk on his
Cizeron
Then to all
Big enough to walk
To bigger breast
Yeah and
Like the World Health Organization recommends breastfeeding until you know like 18 months or two years
Which
Mets
There were a lot of photos still being taken down
Within
You know days
Sweep it
Continuing to hear reports from
People that
Their photographs were still being targeted
But
Facebook did offer a state
You know that's where we're going to draw the line
And keep in mind through this whole episode
Is this perhaps the next big
Facebook.
Cam the company was growing really really fast
And they're just got to be a lot more content
500 people
100000 sub who knows where we're going more people are joining Facebook everyday
60 million user so far 200 million by the end of the year and now War people on Facebook
Not just within the United States but also it was growing rapidly
You were getting in Turkey
Facebook getting big throughout the EU
Content coming in from all these different places in all different languages
How are we going to keep everybody on the same page
And so
Once I saw that this was the operational method for dealing with this
Creating this like nesting
Set of exceptions and rules and he's clear things that had to be there or had to not be there in order to keep content up or take it down
Datsun became
Their procedure
And so dis
Small team at Facebook got a little bigger and bigger
60 people in 900
And they set out to create rules and definitions
Forbes
Everything
Can we go through some sort of the ridiculous examples with left over here okay
Sogor
Gore mean violence, Gore
The gold standard was
Headline we don't allow graphic violence and Gore
And then
The shorthand definition that used was no insides on the outside
No guts no blood
Going out of something what was a separate issue there was an excessive blood
Rule had to come up with rules about bodily fluids semen for example would be allowed in like a clinical setting but like
What Does the clinical setting mean and
You know does that mean if someone is in a lab coat
At one of my favorite examples is like
How do you define art because as these people are moderating they would see images of naked
People that were paintings or sculptures
,
And so what they decided to do is say art with nakedness can stay up like it stays up if it is made out of
Made out of metal
Made out of
Don't really yeah because how else
Do you define art you have to just be like
Is this what you can see with your eyeballs
And so from then on is they run into problems those rules just constantly get updated constantemente
Yeah constant Amendment
New problem
New rule
Another new problem
Updated rule
In fact at this point that there are mending these rules up to
20 times a month
Really I take for example those rules about breastfeeding
In 2013 they removed
The attachment
Claws
Said the baby no longer needed to have its mouth
Physically touching the nipple of the woman
And in fact
Nipple
And or areola could be visible in the photo
Only one
Then 2014 they make it so that
Both nipples or both areola may be present in the photo
This is what happens in American war all the time just everything
Yeah
I know it sounds a lot
Like common law
So common law is this system dating back to early England where individual judges would make rulings which would sort of be a
Law but then that law would be amended or evolved by other judge
Soak the body of law was sort of constantly flashed out in face of new facts
Literally every time this team is Facebook which would come up with a rule that they thought was airtight
Apply
Something that they that they weren't prepared for that is that the rule hadn't
As soon as you think yeah this is good like the next day something shows up to show you yeah you didn't think about
For example sometime around 2011
This content moderator is is going through a queue of things
Reject
Escalade
Accept and she comes up on this image
Oh my God
The photo itself was a teenage girl
African by dressing skin
Breastfeeding a goat's of baby goats
And the moderator throws her hands up and says what the f*** is this
And we googled breastfeeding goats and found
That this was a thing
It turns out it's a survival pract
According to what they found this is a tradition in Kenya that goes back centuries that
In a drought
Unknown way to help your herd get through the drought is too if you have if you have a woman who's like that
To have her nurse
The kid the baby goat along with her
Human kit
And so
There's nothing sexual about it
Good farming business couldn't and theoretically
If we go
Point-by-point through this list
It's an infant
It is sort of could walk so maybe there's an issue there but there is no physical contact between the mouth and the nipple
Obviously
Breastfeeding as we intended anyway meant human infants
Consuming that moment
What they decide to do is
Remove the photo
And there was an amendment and a strict under the rule stating animals are not babies
We had that so in any future cases people would know what to do
Foot but they removed they did they discover was culturally appropriate and a thing that people do when they decide to remove the
The photo yet
That are aged individuals are a determined wheeler why why didn't we make an exception because
Cuz because when a problem grows large enough you have to change the rules if not we don't
This was not one of those cases
Juice wasn't worth the squeeze
And like if they were to allow this picture then they'd have to make some rule about when it was
Is okay to breastfeed an animal and when it wasn't okay this is a utilitarian document
It's not about being right 100% of the time
It's about it
Being able to execute effect
In other words we're not trying to be perfect here and we're not even necessarily trying to be 100% just or Fair
We're just trying to make something that works
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8
And
When you step back and look at what Facebook has become
Like from 2008
To now is it 10 years
Xiamen I've just arrived at Accenture Tower
Kerri mennella idea of a single set of rules that work
That can be applied fairly that's just a crazy crazy concept
1516 because they gone from something like 70 million users to 2.2 billion
Cartoon pig Camp I would say it's about 30
They've gone from 12-volt sitting in a room deciding what to take down or leave up
2 somewhere around
16000 people
So there's a floor in this building where the Facebook supposedly outsources content moderators
It's out around 2010 they decided to start Outsourcing
Some of this work
Places like vanilla
Where you just heard reporter Aurora on the drawl
As well as
Dublin where we sent reporter Garrett
Stack
Scene where they get their stitches Facebook
Everybody's beavering away
And we sent them there to try to talk to some of these people
Tube for letting sit at a computer and collectively click-through around a million flag bits of content the pop up
Another screen everyday
Wow what was just curious like what's what's that like well
Citizen question
Found out pretty quickly
None of these folks are willing to talk to us about what they do
So there's a lot of running away from me happening
Facebook
I mean like
He just came out of there
I know you're lying in fact most people wouldn't even admit they work for the company like what's up is there something
Wrong about being inside like an NDA that they signed so when I finally did find someone willing
Willing to talk to me do you want to be named or do you know
Or do you not want to be named
That's totally fine
Explain that he and all the other moderators like and were forced to sign these non-disclosure
Stating they weren't allowed to
I admit
But they work for Facebook
They're not allowed to talk about the work they do
Ernie from talking about
Why
Several reasons one is that
Up until recently Facebook wanted to
Keep secret what these rules were so that it couldn't be gamed
At the same time at
Create
A sort of separation between these workers and the company which is your Facebook you might want
Monitor graphic images
Just given the nature of the job
That's going to have on you
I know you got to do this guy I talked to him he got his first contract doing this work several years back and for the day
Duration of it about a year
Get you up to theft every morning
Kind of headphones
Ignore delete
5006 everyday
Yeah I was like there's a lot of cases or some other piece of content
Three or four second
Wow all day long all day 8 hours a day
Well if I can ask what kind of things did you see
It's true I think it's too x-rated unspeakable
The magic button to
13 year old girl
Having sex with an 8 year old boy
And it's not just one
When did you did this like keep you up at night and you did this
Wake me up at 9 about these videos photos when he was trying to relax
He had to start avoiding things
SES
Exploding
I have to walk away
And I just I have to IX
I I saw that
A different moderator I spoke to described it as seen the worst side of humanity
You see all of the stuff
But you and I
Don't have
Because they are going around
Plane cleaner
Yeah good job
You're in it and it's worth noting that I'm more and more this work is being done
In an automated fashion
Particularly with content like Gore or terrorist propaganda
The game better than make that they
Through computer vision they're able to detect
Hallmark
Of of
Are the terrorist video or allegory image and with terrorist propaganda de now
Take down 99%
Of it before anyone Flags
But
Moving on to our Second Story here
That there is a type of content that they that they are having any
Credibly hard time
Not just automating
Even getting their rules
Straight on
And that's running cheats
Oh good
Snorlax coming up well there will be laughter
There will be comedians there will be joke. All right
No I think we're going to keep going okay
Testing 1 2 3 4 5 testing 1 2 3
Simon Adler
So a couple months back
I think it's a shame
We sent our pair of interns
Parker Haj
Standing Room
Wicked tickets for tonight
Cramped
Narrow little comedy
Club
The kind of place with light
El Super in Toronto
$15 smashed Rosemary cocktail
High top tables
AC is dripping on me
But still
Kind of.
We sent them there to check out
Someone else who found a fault line
In Facebook
What's real book
Where to keep it moving right along the next
Tina, stage
I guess so
Mad I feel like my person to the city I was such a
Care for you brat
You know I was young and I had these older friends which I thought was like very cool
And then you just realize that they're alcoholics
Got dark curly hair with razor
Oklahoma
And I think I was raised Jewish so
Winter is Jewish you read about Anne Frank a lot
You know a lot a lot
And
She
How did you decide to become a comedian
You know I was kind of the only thing that ever clicked with me and especially political comedy you know I used to watch the day
Daily Show every day back in 2016 she started this
Political running bit
But I think can be called sort of
Absurdist feminist,
I know a lot of people
I think that I'm like an angry
Feminist
Which is weird
Because I am training and
In the wood
At first I just had this running bit online
On Facebook and Twitter jokes
You know like we have all the Buffalo Wild Wings around it
You know things like that eventually took this bit on stage
Even wrote
Shadowsocks
No no not my dad
So about a year into this running bit
Marshall was bored at work one day
And logs on the face
But instead of seeing her normal Newsfeed there is this message
It's that pops up
It says you posted something.
Discriminated along the lines of race
Gender
Or ethnicity group and so we removed that
And so I'm like
What could I buy
Possibly a Post-It
I really I thought was like a glitch but
Then she clicked continue and their highlighted was the violating po
It was a photo of
What is the picture can you describe it to me as what can only be described as a
The chair of cute little seven-year-old with big curly hair and she's wearing this blue floral dress her teeth are all
Messed up into the photo Marcia had edited in a speech bubble that just says
Kill all men
As it's fine it's funny you know it's just me whatever
So
I thought was ridiculous because she searched through her Library photos and
Found that killallmen image
I post it again
Immediately after like yeah and it got removed
Again and this time they were consequence
I got banned for three days after that then after several other
Shoot forward this is months later a friend of hers had posted an article and underneath it in the comment section they were guys
Guys posting just really nasty
So I commented underneath those comments
Men are scum
Which was
Very
How long did you get banned for this time
30 days
Wow
Yeah I was
Dumbfounded
So there's a rule somewhere
If I type
Men are scum
You take it down
Yes
I'm like what could it be
Inside Marshall called on her quote militia of win
Exactly
To find out like is this just me
Female comedians who are sort of like mad on my behalf
Started experimenting posting men are scum to see how quickly it would get remove and if it would be
Remove every time and it was
So
They started trying other way
Fluff yeah
Did find out where the line was
My friend put Menard duska that got removed
Men are the worst
Remove the band this one girl put men are septic fluid
Band
But we're only at the middle of the Saga
It doesn't end there
Because now she's really like
Like what the hell is going on
Is it sexism so I just start doing the most
Bare minimum amount of investigating
Cheap Googling around trying to figure out what these policies are in pretty quick she comes across this leak
Facebook.com
So this is when I lose my mind
This is when Mark Zuckerberg becomes my
Sworn nemesis
For the rest of my life
Because what you found with a document Facebook used to train their modern
Inside of it in section detailing who Facebook protected from hate speech
There was a multiple choice question that said
Who do we protect
White men or black children
In the correct answer was
White men
Not black
Not even kidding
White man protecting black
Children are not
That's not it
Look it's racist
Something's going on here
There is absolutely some sort of unaddressed
Bias or systemic issue
@facebook
Hello
How are you
Not long after sitting down with Marsha
Facebook invited me to come out to their offices
Susan California
And sit down with that
I'm going to eat one cookie and then
Typing
Could I just get your your name and your title and
I'm Monika bickert and I lead the policies
Facebook Monika bickert is in charge of all of Facebook's rules
Including their policies on hate speech
So I asked
They're like why would there be a rule that protects white men
But not black children
We have
We have made our hate
Speech policies
Let me rephrase that
Are hate speech policies have become more detailed over time
But
Our main policy is you can attack a person or group of people based on
A protected characteristic
A characteristic like race religion or gender
Set this takes a couple beats to explain that the gist of it is that
The Facebook borrow this idea of protected classes
Straight from us anti.
Discrimination law
These are the laws that make it so that you can't not
Hire someone
Say based on like the religion their ethnicity there
Race
And so on on Facebook you can't attack someone
Based on one of these characteristics
Meaning you can't say menarche
Nor could you say women are trash
Because eventually you're attacking all men for being men
So is it the all
Can I say Bob is trash you can say Bob is
Because at my stores explain to me
The distinction is that in the first instance you're attacking
A category
In the second instance you're attacking a
Person but it's not clear that you're attacking that person be
Cuz
They are a member of a
Actor category
Oh so Bob might be trash for reasons that have nothing to do with him being a man he just might be
Right okay so that explains why you take down men are scum but why would you
Leave up
Black children
Hawaii weather
Not
So traditionally we allowed
Speech
Once there was some other word in it
That made it about something other than a protected characteristic
In Facebook jargon these are referred to as
AIA non-protected mod
Sapphire
Just beans and literally nothing to give us an example of this
So traditionally if you said I don't like
This religion
Cab drivers
Cab driver would be the non protect
Did modifier because
Employment
Is not a protector
Category
And so what the rules stated was
When you add this non-protected modifier to a protected category
In this case the cabdrivers religion we would allow it because
We can't assume that you're hating is person because of his religion you actually just may not like
Cab driver
So in the case of black children children is modifying the
Protected category
Black
Pizza children Trump's black
Age is a non-protected category
Okay so
Children
Becomes a non-protected modifier
And they're their there
Childness
Trump's their blackness
You can say whatever you want about black chilled
Whereas in the case of white men you've got you've got gender and race
Both protected
You can attack them
That's just a bizarre rule
I would think you would go the other direction
That you d protected class would outweigh the modify
Well they they made this decision
As they plan to meet because their default was to allow
They were really trying to incorporate or nod to the American free speech
There's a whole lot of stuff out there that none of us would defend is it
Valuable speech but didn't didn't rise to the level of stuff that we say this is
So bad we're going to take it down
And that in this case their concern was
We're all members of like you know at least half a dozen protect
The categories like we all have gender
We all have sexual orientation
If you made the rule is that
Anytime
Protected
Class is mentioned
It could be hate
What you are doing at that point is opening up just about every comment that's ever made about anyone
On Facebook to potentially be hates me
Then you're not left with anything
Turn right no matter where we draw this line they're going to be stopped some outcomes that we don't like
They're always going to be casualties
That's why we continue to change the policy
And in fact
Since March is debacle they've actually updated this rule
So now black children are protected from what they considered the worst
Forms
Now car reviewers
Take how severe the attack is
Into consideration
But despite this there are still plenty of people that is flawed because you are a social network
Marcia who think they're still just isn't good enough
There are not
Systematic efforts
To eliminate white men in the way that there are other groups that's why you have protected groups
She thinks
White men in heterosexual should not be protected
Protect the group
Who are actually victims of hate
Makes sense
Oh yeah because in sort of hate speech
We're thinking about hate speech
There's this idea of privilege door of historically disadvantaged groups
And that those historically disadvantaged
Groups should have more protection
Because of
Being historically disadvantaged
And the challenge with that that was presented to me was
Okay
In the 1940s
Cut off the Chinese
Caffe in change if you had
Japanese soldiers
Chinese
Showing millions of China
During World War II
At that same time you had Japanese-American Citizens
Would have to move
Being put into internment
And so we have to ask ourselves a question like
Are the Japanese and historically
Advantage or disadvantage group
Japanese Americans
Pretty easy to make a case that they were disadvantaged
But in China it is a totally different story
In this happened at the exact same moment
You got two different places to differ
Cultural
When you have a website like
My Facebook
Transnational community
They realize that they decided that ideas of privilege
Are so geographically bound
That there is no way
To evade actively weigh and consider who is privileged above who
And decided therefore
That we are not going to allow historical advantage or historical privilege
I into the equation
And I think it's very important to keep in mind here
The moderators only have like four five seconds to make a decision
In those four seconds is there enough time to
Did to figure out where in the world someone is particularly given IP addresses can easily be mask
Is it enough time to figure out a person's ethnicity
On top of that we often don't know an individual's race
Other categories are even less clear like sexual orientation
And they've they just realized it would be next to impossible to get anybody to be able to run these run these calculations effectively
When we were
Building.
Framework we did a lot of cats
And we saw some
Sometimes that it was just too hard for reviewers
To implement
A more detailed
A policy
Consistently
They just couldn't do it
Accurately
So
We want the policies to be sufficiently detailed to take into account all different types of scenarios
But simple enough
That we can apply them consistently
Can accurately around the world
And the reality is anytime that the policies become more complicated we see dips in our consistency
What Facebook's trying to do is take
The First Amendment this
High-minded lofty legal concept
In converted into an engineering manual
That can be executed every 4 seconds
It's for any piece of content from anywhere on the globe
And when you got to move that fast
Sometimes Justice
Lose it
That's the that's the tension here
And
I just want to
Make sure I emphasize that
These policies
They're not going to please everybody they often don't don't
Please everybody that's working on the policy team at Facebook
If we want to have one line
The reinforced
Consistently
Bennett means
We have to have some pretty objective
Black and white rule
Coca-Cola
Very funny
But
When we come back
Those rules
Bacon tapas
This is Danny from Denver Colorado
Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloan at www.slha.org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
We're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments
Brilliance
Basically I want to hear about this
Times when a kid you know did something
It just means you lean back and say
Well
How did they do that
Maybe it was the moment that our kids you've been reading to 4 month started reading back
To you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lesson
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of the musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class you notice their writing used
Taking the margin of their geometry
We're interested in the specific moments where a kid does something super smart
It doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story
T-shirt
Go to radiolab.org
Brilliance
Record a short audio mess
Again that's radiolab.org / brilliance
Thank you so much
Jad Robert Radiolab
Back to Simon Outlet
Facebook free speech
So as we just heard before the break
Facebook is trying to do two competing things at
They're trying to make rules that are just
But at the same time can be reliably X
Executed by thousands
People spread across the globe in ways that are fair
Consistent
I would argue that this balancing a
It was put to the test
April 15th
Bruce Wright
We have some breaking news
Otherwise I wouldn't cut you off
Monday the 15th 2013 just before 3 in the afternoon
Two pressure-cooker bombs
Through the crowd near the Finish Line Boston
And
The answer to the dust begin to settle
Oh my God
People are springing into action
Add this one man in a cowboy hat season spectator who's been injured
Pick some up
Rose in a wheelchair
Announce they're pushing him through they're the sort of ashy cloud
There's a photographer there any snaps this phone
In the photo show is the runner in the cowboy hat
And these two other people pushing this man
Who I
His face is Ashen from all of the debris
Is hair is there two standing on end and you can tell that actually the force of the blast and then the the particles that got
Tanner actually holding it in this sort of wedge shape
And
One of his legs is completely blown off
And the second one is blown off
Below the knee other than the femur bone sticking out and then sort of skin and muscle and tendons
It's it horrified
Meanwhile
CVS Bay Area Studio on the other side of the country
I remember Snippets of the day
Facebook employees for clustering around several days
Staring at the computer screen
Watching the news break
Kern just in the last half-hour or so I have memories of
Watching some of the coverage has just released
Of the Boston bombing remember seeing the photo published online and it wasn't long after that
I posted on Facebook
From the folks I spoke to the order of events here are a little fuzzy but
Pretty quickly
Photos going viral
And we realized
We're going to have to deal with it
This image is spreading like wildfire
It appears to be way out
Side the rules they'd written by its in this
Totally new country
So together team together
Sat down in the conference
I don't know there was probably eight or ten people thinking about like
Should we allow it or should they take it down
According to the rules
Yeah so if you recall the no insides on the outsides definition that we hadn't placed
Meeting
You can't see like
People's organs or that sort of thing
And if you can then we wouldn't allow it
And in this
In this photo you can see
You can definitely
And so by the rules the photo should obviously
Come down yep
However
Have to run says
No
The other people are saying
This is news
Essentially this phone is being posted everywhere else it's important
We need to suspend the rules
We need to make an exception
Which immediately receive push back while I was saying that
What we've prided ourselves on was not making those calls
And there are no exception
There's either
Are there mistakes
Orange Roofing
We made the guideline for moments like this
Twitch the other side shoot back oh my God are you kidding me like
The Boston Globe is publishing this all over the place and we're taking it down like are you
F****** kidding me damn the guidelines must have common sense your lips
The humans we know that this isn't
End
Yeah there
Kind of
The right
But
The reality is like
If you say
Well we allowed it because it's newsworthy
How
How do you answer
Any of the questions about any of the rest of the
In other words this is a Pandora's
And in fact for reasons that are totally clear team consistency team follow the rules
Eventually wins the day
They decide to take the photo down
But before they can pull the lever
Word starts making its way up to
And internally within Facebook
According to my sources in executive under Zuckerberg sent down in order
We were essentially
I told
Make the exception
I don't care what your guidelines say I don't care what your reason is
The photos
You're not taking this down
Yes
That's what happened
This decision means
If Facebook has just become a publisher
Whitley.
I think maybe they have
Bucket Maiden news judgment
And just really knowing they've become CBS ABC near time and Atlantic
A news organization yeah
I in this brings up a legal question that that's at the center
Of of this conversation about free speech
Like
Is Facebook a sort of collective
Scrapbook for a cell or is it a public
Square where you should be able to say whatever you want
Or
Yeah it is it now in uzor
Currency election
I'm sorry to interrupt but let me get to one final
How to release what year
You talk too much
What exactly
Facebook is
And this question has been popping up a lot reason
In fact it even came up
This past April
When Zuckerberg was testifying in front
Congress
I think about a hundred
40 million
Americans get their news from
Facebook
So
Which are you
Are you are you at
Company are you the world
World's largest
Thunder this is
The primary thing that
We do is build
Technology and products
Well
I agree that we were
Responsible for the count
Compatible with
Fundamentally yet
At our core
Bia technology
Company were the main thing that we do is having
Engineers and Bill product
Basically Zuckerberg and others at the company are arguing no
There not a new Darkness
Why what would be the downside of that
Will Facebook currently
Sits on this little idyllic illegal Island where
They can't be held liable for much of anything there
Subjected to few regulations
However were they to be seen in the eyes of the court and the media organization
That could change
But setting that aside what really strikes me about all of this
Is it here you have a company that really
Up until this point has has been crafting a set of rules
That are both
As objective as possible
And can be executed as consistently
And they've been willing to sacrifice
Rather large ideas in in the name of this thing
Forgettable privilege
Which we talk
What about that they decided was to geographically bound to allow for 1
But if
If you ask me that there's nothing more
Subjective or geographically bound
Then what people find interesting or important what what people
Find newsworthy
Don't get it and I'll give you I'll give you a great example of this
They haven't just six months after the Boston area
Embalming when this video starts
Out of northern Mexico
And it's a video of a
A woman being
Grab
And forced onto her knees in front of a camera
And then a man
With his face covered
Grabs her head pulled her head back in
Slices
Her head off right in front of the
And this video starts being spread
I can't count how many times I just reading my Twitter feed I've been like you know like
One person came across this video or at least
Dozens of others like it was Shannon Young
My name is Shannon Young I am a freelance radio reporter
Been living here in Mexico for for many years now and then is covering the drug war in doing so years back she know
Noticed this strange phenomena
It first caught my attention in early 2010 Dragon social media you know your scroll
Run through your feet and he know you'd see all this news people say there was a three-hour gunbattle and
Intense fighting all weekend long for posting about clashes between drug cartels
Government forces
But then when Shannon would watch the news that night
Sheep the reports on the economy and
Soccer results but the media wasn't covering it
There be no mention of these attacks
Nothing to do with the violence
And so she another journalist
Try to get the bottom of
Reporters in Mexico City with contact State authorities and they know public information officer and they be like shootings bombing
What are you talking about
Nothing's going on we have no reports of anything
These are just internet rumors
The government even coined a term for these sorts of posts
The famous phrase of the time was Collective psychosis
These people are crazy because you know they didn't want the situation to seem out of control
But then a video is
It opens
Looking out the windshield of a car on a sunny day
The landscape is dry Dusty
Videos of a shaky clearly shot on a phone
And then the woman taping star
Cards talk
This woman she just narrates
As they drive along this
Highway
Sheet pans the phone from the passenger window to the to the Wynn
Windshield
Focusing in on these two silver destroyed pickup trucks
And she said look at these cars over here are there if you know shut up and eat
Mercure unibus 18-wheeler as you know totally abandon it got shot up
1 Point sheet
Stick the phone out the window to show all of the bullet casings
Littering the ground
And she just turn the the official Denial on it
Ted
The government was saying there's no violence
Here were cars riddled with bullets
It was impossible to dismiss
And from then on
You had more and more citizens
Citizen journalists uploading anonymously
Video of the violence
He's Lo-Fi shaky shots of
Shootout dismemberment
Beheadings I mean
Bodies hanging
Dangling off of overpasses
Proved the world that this is really happening
We're not crazy
It's a cry for help
Yeah
Which brings us back to that beheading V
Yeah that video of the beheading
A lot of people are uploading it condemning the violence
The drug cartel
And when it started showing up on Facebook
Much like with the Boston Marathon bombing photo
This team of people they sat down in a room looked at the policy of weight the arguments
And my argument was
It was okay by the rules during the Boston bombing
Why isn't it okay now
Particularly
Given that it could help leaving this up means we warned hundreds of thousands of people at the brutality of these cartels
And so
We kept it up
However
It's f****** Raw
It's why I think it's
Oxalate responsible and impact quiet despicable of them
People found out
I have little neighbor kid
It like that
Backlash
Application for Lawrence
Videos to people as powerful as David
Cameron Wake
Today's appointment is done
Stony criticized the move thing we have to protect children from this
David Cameron tweeted
It's irresponsible of Facebook to post
Beheading videos
People were really upset because of what it was
And so according to my sources
Some of the folks involved in making this decision to leave it up or once again taken into an executive's office
And so we went up
And and there was a lot of
Internal pressure to remove it
And I go to my boss and say Hey look
This is the decision we made
I recognize this
This is controversial I want to let you know why we made these decisions
And they made their case
There are valid and important human rights reasons why you would want this to be out there to show the kind of
Savage
And she vehement Lee
They took another approach arguing that if we take this down you're deciding to punish people who are trying to raise awareness
Again
She wasn't budging and just didn't get
Didn't get passed
And
Ultimately
I was overruled
And we removed it
Just because there was pressure to do so the same people that six months prior told them to leave it up because of his music
Said take the video down
Reverse a decision in band a video post
Go to the site of a woman thing
The headed
Facebook
A quote when
If you want the one from Boston and you probably should have the one for Mexico and right
It was a mistake
Yeah
I think it was a mistake
Because I
I felt like
Like why do we have these rules in place in the first
And
And it's not the
The only reason
But decisions like that
Are the thing that precipitated melee
Leaving
Yep
Not too long after that incident a few members of the team decided to quit
And what would I think this story shows
Is that
Facebook has become
Too many different things at the same
The Facebook is now
Turtle playground
It's also an R-rated movie theater
And now it's the front page of a newspaper
My mother thinks the same time it's all distinct at the same time and in what we
The users are demanding of them
Is that they create a set of policies that are
Just
And the reality is just as means a very different thing in each one of these setting
Justice would mean that the person in Mexico gets told the truth
In Mexico by Facebook
A little boy in England doesn't have to look at something gory and horrible in England
But you can't put them together
Because they Clash
Exactly
So how do you solve that
The I don't know
I think it's important to keep in mind
That even if you have the perfect set of policies that
That somehow managed to be just in different settings and that
To be consistently enforced
The people at the end of the day making these
Decision
They're still there still
Still human beings
Is the office working or no
I can hear you
Yeah great okay
At long last we figured it out huh
Yeah clearly
I spoke to one woman who did this work for face
Buckeyes want to be
Anonymous I don't want
Dump even know that I'm doing it because
They might file charges against
Will call her Marie
She's from the Philippines where
She grew up on a coffee Farm
That's my father's
Stop grow
And I didn't know that coffee was only for adults
She said many afternoons while she was growing up
She and her mother would sit together
Side
Sipping their coffee and
Tuning into the shortwave
Washington DC
And they sit there
Listening to The Voice of America
Silent
I'm going to ask that we all
Bobbleheads
She said one of her favorite things to catch on Voice of America where Billy Graham's
Billy Graham one of the great evangelist
Our Father we thank thee for this
Love of God
That reaches around the world
Xiamen golf
But then
Fast forward 50 years to 2010 and Marie is consuming a very different sort of American Media
The videos were the ones that affected me
There were times when I felt
Really bad that I am a Christian and then I look into these things
She became a Content moderator back in 2010 and was actually one of the first people in the Philippines doing this work
Usually had the night shift
In the early morning or in the dawn from 2 a.m. to 4 a.m.
She work from home and despite it being dark she put blankets up over the windows so no one could see in at what she was look
Cheap lock the door to keep
Superkids out
Are you have to go drive them away
Alright without them. It's Otto
Making of Watch
And she and the other moderators on her team who lived throughout the Philippine
They were trained on the guideline
On this robot
There were policies if you have to adhere to
Some of us were
Redis
Gleeking passpasspass even if it's not really fast
Spanish
Just to get through the content fast
And in some cases she thinks
Number of the moderators
My doing it
As a form of retaliation for the low rate
People were pissed at the low pay
If I can ask how much what how much were you making an hour doing
As far as I remember it
We were babies
Like $2.50
Where our
Marie wouldn't say whether or not this low-wage led her to just
Let things through
But she did say
Based on my
Ghost background
That I can look objectively at
So I reject many of the things that I
Think are not
Acceptable
Really
Of course
She said whether something with outside the rules or not
If forgot told her to
She just took it down
Whenever it affects me a lot
I would click the button.
It's a violation
Because if it's going to disturb the young or
And he should not be there
So
If there's a nude person
Whether it was a breastfeeding photo or an anatomy video or a piece of art
I would consider it that's pornography
And then
Right away
It's a violation
You took the law into your own hands you went vigilante
Say something
So yeah I have to
Protect kids
From
Evil
Site of humankind
Where does that leave you feeling good leave you feeling at this is just at the end this is
System
Undoable
II
I think they will inevitably fail
But they have to try
And I think we should all be rooting for them
This episode was reported by Simon Adler with help from Tracy hunt and produced by Simon
With help from Bethel habte
Big thanks to Sarah Roberts whose Research into commercial content moderation got us going big-time and we thank her
You're very very much for that thanks also to Jeffrey Rosen who helped us in our thinking about what Facebook is Drew Michael cherniss
Whose voice we use
To mask the people's voices to Caroline Glanville
Who's Rodger and Dugan Ellen silver James Mitchell & Gyros encuesta to all the content moderator she took the time
Talk to us
And
Ready you want to go first
Thank you listening
Minecraft
Messi
Pequannock from Brooklyn New York Radiolab
Created by Daddy Vermont and is produced by Soren wheeler
Doing keep is a director sad design
Berea madisar Padilla is a managing director
Assassin
Xiamen Adler
Megabox
Manao
Becca bronzer
Ric Ocasek
David gobble
Bethel happy
Kasie hunt
Not guilty
Eddie McEwen
Melissa O'Donnell
Darien whack
Pat Walters and Molly Webster
With help from FEMA Ali-A
Omni Theater
The fact checker
Michelle Harris
And this message