Hi I'm Robert Goulet Radiolab is supported by Casper you spend 1/3 of your life sleeping
So you should be as comfortable as possible when you drift off get $50 towards select mattresses by visiting cast
Casper.com Radiolab
Have using Code Radiolab at checkout
Terms and conditions apply
Hi I'm Robert krulwich Radiolab is supported by audible as we learn more about the dark side of the Earth
Endurance a year in space a lifetime of Discovery by Scott Kelly
The astronaut who spent a record-breaking year
Aboard the International Space Station
Go to audible.com Radiolab or text Radiolab to 500 500
Free free 30-day trial and a free audiobook
New York City we've got a live show coming up May 16th
Taping
Four new show
About
Sex
Specifically sex ed
All those bad memories we determine a good memories
Join longtime producer
And host Molly Webster along with a bunch of writers and Comedians and thinkers for a night of
Debate
A night stories a night of nervous laughter
That's Wednesday May 16th
It's going to be good
Going to be there for tickets go to radiolab.org sex ed
Radiolab.org
Flash sex ed
Are you awake
Listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
All right
In space right now
I am really sick
Okay we believe you
Is Radiolab Jad Robert
That guy
We were just talking to just named Mark vanderhei
Was he to show us where he was
He he
Talk to you
Back down into his chest and spun
Laika space flight
We should explain Lexi this is one of the weirdest things that ever happened to us
Couple weeks ago we got to talk
Does astronaut Mark vandehei while he was in the International Space Station
Apparently each
Astronaut
Space Station
Can make one request
You talk to an Earthling of
Their choice
And
For some reason each other
I really enjoyed your program
Like we actually got initially contacted by NASA
Dial in the mission control at a certain time and we did then they then connected us to him 200 miles up
And we could see him
Honor iPad
Jesus in space
And so we spent
I know like an hour the enchanted hour
Talking to him asking him questions about what's it like
The mostly looking over his
Is shoulder
Back of the Earth
He invited us to the store place
So they have on the spaceship
If it's a room with giant Windows looking right down at the ER
Straight down
Are we just passed over the southern edge of
Australia
At that time it was night time in Australia
Pool of black
No Contours
No edges
I'll check to see how long it'll be before the sun shining earth below us
Open up for the shutters
Horizon
He pointed
Out the window at this band of light
Did it just appear in the
Cats with sun coming over horizon horizon the Earth
Turn the blasted out in the school like a few minutes later
Change really fast the Earth just lit up all the lights on.
Yeah cuz they're going 17,000 miles an hour when you're going that fast
Sunrises basically instantaneous
As we were talking we zoomed over Australia over the Pacific
North America facts
Within just
Couple minutes felt like
Scenery out his window went from Rocky Mountains to somewhere near New York
Then we are over the Atlantic
The interplay of the sun and the ocean is where I need to be
Shimmering patterns on the ocean and
Swirling Cloud masses
And as we were screaming across the face of the Earth
You know we're asking all these mundane questions like how do you eat rice in space and things like that
But at a certain point
We
We asked him
When you first got up there what was most
Surprising to you
And he started talking about the Earth's
Atmosphere
I think you saw my first impression when I sat up here is that
Neptune layer of atmosphere
He says that it's
Funny to him
Now that he's been up there for
To understand how close we all are
Two deep space
People who live on earth
Parole action
Under a very skinny protective wrapper
It's been described as
Less
Thick than the skin of an apple around
All of us
Just a few miles
From the dark
It makes for some
States that mean
Incredibly thin
Intensely
Very very isolated
He says when he looks down at the Earth and he sees that
Thin layer
It separates us from space and all the Blackness around it
He feels
Protective
Which going to share that because it was just this weird thing that happened to us randomly just a few weeks back
Well actually
As cool as that was
It's an order
To one another
Yes who wasn't delish
Definitely
Faintest idea who that was it more of a official formal
Wright's arteritis
Search for the Restless podcast going to play you another astronaut story that we ended up taking on stage as part of our in the dark tour
For which is
Figures of Altima 2012 I think
About 20 cities list
Particular recording happen in Seattle I believe
I don't know
So here it is
Silver final segment
We would think through this show we thought you know who would have a really in
Chrissy perspective
Maybe somebody who works
MMA
Rich
Dark environment astronauts
So we called up
Talk to master
We connected our little studio in New York
To theirs
Studio DC
To talk to an astronaut but he's a little late
And I use the funny thing
When you are on hold
With NASA
This is literally what you
Has a blast off filter
This is literally the case you. 1-800 Nassar whatever and they just
The go to the Moon music
Oh
Hello
I hear someone breathing.
It's probably I'm breathing
So this is our guy Dave wolf is his name me the NASA astronaut have been since 1990
Over 20 years he wasn't really sure why we had called him
What what's our topic here
So explain to him that you know what we're doing the show called in the dark
Are we going to get on stage
Very nice folks
Do you have any stories that relate
And right off the bat
You've triggered an interesting Darkness story I have
That's why we calling you up
Yeah okay you're at your taping and you're ready
Yep darkness is an interesting theme in space
Because there is nowhere
Where the
Contrast between light and dark is any more extreme
Davidson doesn't
The space waxy says there have been times
We sister out there floating in space next to
The Craft
And maybe the
Tilt a little bit
And wing
Blocks light
The Sun or the Moon
And it creates a shadow
He said the darkness
That shadow
Is blacker than any black you thought it could be
Now they're in Space the shadow has no light in it
There's not reflected light from dust in the air the Earth around you or clouds
Pure app
And
You can reach
Into a shadow so deep
So black
At your arm can appear to disappear
Wow right in front of your face
When your head is in the bright light
And your arm is in his
Gaps of Darkness
And she's gone like
And cut off
But I do want to tell you
An experience I had
You're my first
Spacewalk
Play 897 I have this
Experience not gay
It was from a Russian spacecraft
Your mic might remember the mirror
Yeah sure face craft
Today was up there he was
The two Russian cosmonauts
Kent and Anatoly soloviev
They were suited up
And getting ready to make their first
Walking to stay
For his first one
And we did all the preparations
How to get the suits ready
And more in the airlock
And
Door open and they floated out we
Flipkart others on outside he and entally gently float to the worksite
And it was dark out and dark up in space means you're on the nights
Side of the Earth in the shadow of the earth and there were no external lights on this phone
Spacecraft this was really really dark and we were over the ocean and at night that basically means
She'll see the Earth you don't see it at all
Not at all when it's up a moonless night you don't see the Earth in fact all it might look
Look like to you is the absence of stars
I want you to imagine Assuming he's up there in this darkness and the Earth with all of us
What's on it somewhere Far Far Below him you can't see it
All the while and this is really important what happens next he is
Shooting through space he's rocketing across the dark shadow of the Earth at 5 miles a second that is 6
15 *
Speed the world moving right now cuz we are on the Earth
He said that he didn't steal any of that it just felt like he was
Bended in this Cocoon of black floating gently you thought no problem
It was just me and the spacecraft and blackness
And suddenly
Blazing White
Grafton from Below
At the Sunrise which normally happens here on Earth very very slowly calmly at that speed up there the Sun
Screaming from the Eastern edge of the Earth straight across the Earth lights up everything is seconds
Below me suddenly I can look down 200 miles and see that we're
Removing at 5 miles per second
I clutched Andres handrails like there's no tomorrow white-knuckled in my space suit gloves
Because I suddenly had this enormous sense of height and speed
Like if you're standing comfortably on the ground and and then some someone just flips on the lights suddenly and you realize
Actually I'm not on the ground I am on a 400000 foot ladder
Crazier still in that Sunrise moment the temperature also increase
Reese's by upwards of 400° in the moment in the moment
Stream thing I've ever heard are conditioned or whatever are you you are we are totally depend
Combat space suit
But the colors
What you're seeing on that Earth
Is so spectacular
The greens and blues and the
Delicate pastel light colors
Contrast the brights
Are you just are present
Anything I've ever seen other than up in space
David is Russian buddy and totally
There after 4 hours
Doing repairs on the ship so they are
Is there speed they're going in and out and in and out of these days and nights
So it's
90 minutes of a light dark cycle
So you have 16 nights in 16 days
Forever Yours day
As they're working
This change is happening over at
Over and over every 45 minutes to go from blazing light to
Quiet.
Blazing light to dark
Lost
It will you get stories
Of people doing spacewalks that lose their orientation or feel like they're falling
So he says the only thing to do in that circumstance
It's just a focus on your job look straight ahead
Only at the screw
Only at the
Don't look down is kind of this
It's real in this business
So
We wouldn't perfectly happy to end the story right here cuz David Anatole finish that
Repairs job well done
Come back into the spacecraft
But we cannot not
Tell you what happened
Different kind of Darkness
We'll continue that story
Hi I'm Robert krulwich Radiolab is supported by Casper
Talking about dark side of the earth reminds me of another dark place
That would be your bedroom with the lights off while you're sleeping
Very little feels better than crawling into a Casper bed knowing you're going to get it
Deep restorative night sleep Casper offers 109th
Free trial and you'll get $50 towards select mattresses by visiting
Casper.com Radiolab and using coude Radiolab at checkout
Terms and conditions apply
Hi I'm Robert krulwich Radiolab is supported by Audible
As we continue listening to this episode The Dark Side of the Earth
Check out these stunning Memoir endurance a year in space a lifetime of
Discovery by astronauts
Scott Kelly he spent a year aboard the International Space Station in this candid account
Kelly shares the experience you had
He takes it on his journey navigating the extreme challenges of long-term space flight
Go to audible.com Radiolab or text Radiolab to 500 500
For a free 30-day trial and a free audiobook
Does Radiolab let's continue now with our story from Astronaut Dave wolf
That we performed live as part of Art in the dark tour in front of an audience about 2,500 people
Where we left off
Dave and his
Cosmonaut
Anatole
They had just been out in space
Doing a space walk
Repairing the
Space Station
And they're about to Come Back Inn
So the two of them pull themselves by their tethers
The comeback
Into the airlock to go back in
When it was time to Come Back Inn
They couldn't get back at you were locked out of your spaceship you could call it locked out we
We were trapped outside yes
Essentially their airlock was busted if they couldn't repressurise
If you can't get it at the right pressure
You can't win
And we worked on it for for 5 hours and
Ran out our resources and when second ran out of
Oh yeah we oxygen or what plenty of oxygen it turns out
Then what you run out of first
Is your carbon dioxide scrubbing
Yeah unit
Takes the CO2 out of your suit
Another problem with this one is
Usually
In space accident
You figure it'll only hurt for a moment
Back
When you die
CO2 intoxication
That drags out that's not a that's a that's a miserable way to go
What it what does it mean did you ever find love
What happens if first you get a headache
Then your muscle starts at which eventually your heartbeat starts with
Accelerate faster faster faster you go into convulsions and then you die
Luckily
The life-support system has an extra cartridge that gave us an extra 6 or so hours
We used all that
And trying to fix the hatch and we couldn't get it to hold air
And
We were done
Did you know you were done I mean you're pretty much
And and over
Yeah yeah no more ideas
Done like in debt
So they decide okay we got to do something last dish maneuver if we can't get our usual airlocks work
Maybe we can make a new one because he on the Mir space station is this big cylinder with these rectangular module
One of those modules is the airlock Jason once but you're normally just a living quarters
Stop well if we can't get our usual airlock to pressurize the right pressure maybe we can go to the next one over
And up next module in as a airlock
And
We open the hatch into that next modules and in order to go to go into it we had
Had to disconnect the umbilicals
Cuz you can't close a hatch over your umbilical right umbilical was providing our Cooling
You are suits so as soon as we disconnect it
Well that gives you maybe 5 8 minutes at Max before you before you what
I won't talk about it
It's so bad you did you did you look that up
What happens if you boil
Inside your spacesuit ugly way
So they can actually think okay we've got to get through this tiny hatch into this room and they've got to do a fat
They also know if you struggle hard
Go to fast you'll get much time at all in that suit before that heat builds up on you so thick
Okay hurry hurry but slowly
Hello
But I did not anticipate was as soon as we disconnected our umbilicals at the visor with fog up
Now be having to feel your way of blind
You can spit and kind of get a little area through the
Fog
So I'm in the airlock
Trying to make my way into the next section
And I was crawling along the wall moving into the next section
And I Spit on my visor Rio to make a little hole to look through and get a hint
And it was an area I had been sleeping in some weeks before and
I left a picture of my family taped with Scotch tape on the wall
And I Spit on visor and my helmet light went there and there was a picture of my family
Right here in this moment
As I was scooting across the wall and in what was likely
My last minutes
So this is how it's going to end
So this is here
And didn't look at so strange there they are
Did I look back at that
And I shudder
Of course
Dave and his partner
Made it back in
YouTube space station
Barely
But it didn't strike me really till months later
On the Earth
Pow wow
How close a tab in
And what a strange situation
This Russian guy must be your best friend like
Gmail
Well not many people been through anything like that together and and and are there to talk about it and
You just reminded me of something
So we're going to leave you with one last story from Dave
He's got a story she
This is from that same stay in space involves the same friend and a totally they were out there doing some work
On the ship and floating space again
And then a mission control radios and
Tell them to pause for a while we had
A period where we had to wait through the night
To go on with our work so he says up David uphill on Russian of course
I want to show you something
And we cooked our tethers on
Pushed ourselves about 6 feet away with
What about 60 to tether
So RI
Couldn't see anything but out in space
I turn my air conditioner down a little nipple is kind of warm
And I was floating in this space suit just looking out
Into the Blackness of space
And
I felt like I didn't have a
Space Unicorn
It was so comfortable
The air temperature was just right
I felt like I was just out in the universe in the star
I couldn't see anything that stars are all around me I couldn't feel anything
Outside of spacecraft going
5 miles per
Second
Universe
Was that what he wanted to show you
Yeah I think so
This is his rocking chair on the front porch thing
Duro hammock Olmos
He didn't want to talk he said let's just be
Why it turn your helmet light off
So you don't get any reflected light
Yes.
Relax Riesling relax
Relax
I had you been there in the sea
Either
This is the moment where we gave everybody
Little pinpoint of light
A little hand-carried star
They could put over their heads
And weave together
He was like this
Canopy of stars
Special thanks to the musicians that you here playing with us on stage
How win Jason soda
And
That's it for now
Pancetta
Thanks for listening
This is Valerie calling from Washington DC
Radio
Lab was created by Jad appenrod and is produced by Soren wheeler
Dylan Keith is our director of sound design
Maria baltazar Padilla is our managing director
Our staff includes
Simon Adler
Maggie bartolomeo Deca Bressler Rachel Cusick David gamble Bethel Hoppity
Tracy hunt Matt kielty
Robert Roldan
Annie McEwen
Lots of Nasser Melissa O'Donnell
Arianne wack
Pat Walters
And Molly Webster
With help from Amanda Orange
Shima Olie
Shay Carlo Andre Canaan
Are fact checker
Michelle Harris
Hi I'm Robert krulwich Radiolab is supported by Casper
Not only do they make outrageously comfortable mattress
They also offer pillows and sheets and duvets and more all to make your bed even more inviting and more come
Comfortable get $50 towards select mattresses by visiting casper.com Radiolab and using Radiolab
At checkout
Terms and conditions apply
Hi I'm Robert krulwich Radiolab
Supported by Audible
Check out these
Stunning Memoir endurance a year in space a lifetime of Discovery by astronaut Scott Kelly
He spent a year aboard the International Space Station and he miss candida count Kelly shares the experience you have
He takes it on his journey navigating the extreme challenges of long-term space flight
Go to audible.com Radiolab or text Radiolab to 500 500
For a free 30-day trial and a free audio