Are you awake
Listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
Play a podcast that we made back in 2012 this is a show that I believe has disappeared
The RSS feed
And I thought we bring it back because it
Captures
A Feeling
But I think maybe we all need a little bit more of these
Restart
Okay hello hello hello
We are super super excited to talk with you
Life is crazy
Yeah I know
But the
You were so enthusiastic so I left just I need to talk to this guy really mean it
This is Alex
Alexander Gomez
Gundam are you Norwegian all the way back
Typical noise
Yeah if typical includes things like in Sahara and
Climbing
Things like that he's going to be a professional
Adventurer
And we got the studio because he made a video last year on one of his trips
Get to this video then it's it's maybe the most
Amazing
Internet video I have ever seen
I think so too
So let me just set the scene for you okay
What you see in the video is this guy Alex
Moving along this
She's on skis
Snowy snowscape
He's filming himself
The camera is right hand where is he
Antarctica
Herpes on a 3-month track
The South Pole and back by himself
What he's been doing is every couple of days on his trip you know every 200 kilometers is so he would bury stuff in the snow
Some fuel and
And sometimes a little bit of gear that I did
Was that just to lighten your load
Yeah
Yeah cuz every outside
I need weight
Has to go
In this video
It's day 86
Almost 3 months since I left
3 months of working 10 hours a day and I lost
Almost win
25 kilos
Exhaust
Shut up
Come upon his last cast
So
On the Lost
Cash
Where this
Video is captured
What you see is Alex Neal in the snow start today
I'm telling that I'm quite hungry
Whatever is in this last cash in the snow it's been 3 months since he buried it so I didn't really recall what was there
Mobile home
You up to something good
So he digs up his bag of stuff starts rifling through it
Vaseline
Zinc ointment
Nothing new trash
But then
Double pack of cheese Doodles
And then this is this is my favorite part he's just
Reese's
And he's staring off into the distance almost like
Did that happen
Is it real
Seatac to Dixmoor
And then
Schutz chocolate bars milk chocolate
Just like you think cementos
I find more and more and more
Have you ever been that happy in your life
Well I've been thinking about that
How when did you shout last time you were
So happy
I think that's why we've been watching this video over and over again
Because none of us can remember what stands between you and that feeling is it really
Fremont's with hunger
Actually I think the reason I liked
This video so much is not just
Is it happy
City somehow
Stumbled into this moment
Perfection is just like a person
Situation
By being so tired and so hungry
I'm finding such a stash of candy that he had forgotten that he left
He created a moment of just
Absolute complete
Bliss
Is this hour on radio that we're going to be searching
Free moments like Alex Hanna in Antarctica we're going to be
Searching for Bliss
List of all different sorts
Perfect moments for the world's slips right through your fingers
And the kind of bliss
It just might last
At last
Just before we go to the first story in this episode
I want to mention that this
Flower was produced by guy named Tim Howard
Was a longtime producer Radiolab and then went on to become the editor of an amazing podcast
Reply all
And ask him
What occurs to use you as you listen to it again
There's this moment that jumps out at me where you here
This woman Shirley McNaughton
Who's like
You know key character in
In the story
She just radiates
So much generosity and love
And
I just find it so freaking moving
Like
She goes through a lot in the story like
Like she she really is just like
Challenging
Incredible in
Kind of impossible ways
Did I think would turn a lot of people really bitter
And
And I wonder how I would react in the end
With everything that she went through if I went through it myself
And it's really
It's really nice to actually think about that
Like how I would deal with such
Such an incredibly child
Situation
And
Could I myself
Keep such like
Love
And admiration
For this guy char
And I I just find it so
So inspiring that you
State open house
Yeah
As I listened back I was just like men I just feel so lucky that that that I
That I got a chance to talk to her
I don't know that's
Not a pledge drive you but it but honestly that that was like a
You can't hear is that original story it begins with a box
Send you got a rectangular
It is a very old looking
Inbox
Doesn't look like much
Just about like
15%
10 / 6
Singing and playing to friends in America
Studio of fine otherwise you might be okay so this is Charles
Charles cascio bliss
An amazing character and that's Richard but you do a he's a fellow gave me the
He was a friend of Charles
Garage
He look like I suppose a little know my little Leprechaun almost
Lowe's
Still alive
La Jolla Shores
Bulls
And laughter the whole time
You so lovable character simple set
Explain why we're talking about this
Because these types tell
An amazing story about a guy who really embodied his name
And he tried to save the world
But ultimately
Try too hard
The turning point in my life
We can start story here this is from a lecture that he
Gave
Decades later
So The Story Goes it's 1908
And he's a little kid living in what's now the Ukraine
And his name is
Carl
Blitz not terrible but not Charles with Carl Blitz bli
TZ
That's his original name
Endive
Little Carl was fascinated by Tales of Discovery in adventure my name is
Is Erica ocrant Erica wrote about Charles Place in this great book called
Getting back to the story one day she says when Carl was 11
A lecturer came through town about some
Expedition into explorers talking about their track across the North Pole and he was so inspired by
Like what he saw and heard it that lecture did even decades later he couldn't talk about it
Without getting choked up
My father took me to this election
I'm glad I show
Bullet Journal
And when the ice and snow
Checking this
For what
Bring idea as he tells it on those tapes
That was the beginning of his big idea
That was going to change the world
Fast forward a few years
They came together
After the first girl who did end up going to the Technical University of Vienna
Give me the best mandolin player in Austria at one time
I played the fool Opera Orchestra
So sweet
And then
Everything changed
In 1938
Nazis came to town he was sent to Dachau and then boom
Innovate concentration camps
Feeling groovy xi'an desire to end my life
All around him people were being worked to death or outright exterminated but his wife Claire
Was a German Catholic with connection
Play My Good Vibes in my guitar into the concentration
I became so famous among two notches
The princess is coming to our but I can say this
And you can say that it was
Here in buchenwald that Karl started to develop his ideas about language
By the ways that you can manipulate word
For instance there was this one song that all the prisoners say
The saddest lyrics in the world
At a certain point Carl started to play around with this song you know he'd swap out something sad lyrics for some jokes
Sing it for his fellow prisoners
And forgot for a few minutes
Study Island
And there was terrible on the flip side
Outside force him to stand there in the cold in front of these loud
Speak and listen to
Speechless speeches of Hitler and Goebbels screaming Nazi slogan
Like Germany above all
Which makes you mad
But after about a year his wife
Somehow wrangled of a British visa for him and he gets out
Thank heavens shows breakfast times
And now I can play
And improvisation as it comes into my mind
In 1939
He went to Britain
As a manager of a factory arrived in England just as
The blitz Begins the Germans start to bomb every major city in England
Did you hear at the moment is the sound of an air raid siren every time you'd introduce himself to somebody new
Shutter
That can't be your name because I like Blitzkrieg good attitude
Trainwreck blitz so I change from the wall light switch
To the peaceful
That was how he became
Charles
Bliss bliss has all the right Association so he went forward with the feeling of
That he was now Bliss and
Would bring happiness to the world
Or later he and his wife end up
China in Shanghai where there was a big population of
Excel choose
Shanghai was the only place that would take them at the time
Apply lifetime
Now we come to his big idea
I realized
Did the Chinese have
He became enraptured by the Chinese writing that he saw the Chinese symbols
In each symbol is a word
Any rights about having this Epiphany when he saw the Chinese symbol
Format he saw that the Chinese
Written form of
Man sort of looks like a man that looks like a stick figure man
Adam means man
He doesn't even know what the Chinese word for man is he doesn't know how to stay mad but that doesn't matter
He is
Skipping the word
Then going directly into the meaning so here was a way of getting Beyond language
You could think the word in any language if you see it in the symbol that was a revelation
Why
Well
I'm you think back to the concentration camps when they were outside in front of those loudspeakers listening to Hitler
Saying stuff like
Deutschland Uber Alles
You know Germany above all
That phrase
Charles new
Did it actually predated the Nazi
Earlier in 1848
And originally it was meant as a rallying cry to bring together all the separate principalities
That spoke German but these were not one country
So when they said Deutschland Uber Alles
Event unification
Venetian above the state's us it was an Australian aggressive
But
Hitler change the meaning
Instead of the nation above all states
He changed it to the nation
See see what happened this phrase that started meeting one thing unification
Can the Alps
Yeah
This is what the Nazis did
It would been words to obscure the truth of what they were doing
Extermination
The college solution
By doing that
As he saw it
They were able to convince
Good
Same people his neighbors
To go along with the genis
Then I realize that something must be done
To make language more to it to Nature words were the problem words made people do cruel things
To each other
Fort dangerous instruments
So when he saw the Chinese symbol for man
He thought
This might be the answer
Chinese symbols but even clear
Picture so simple if he could sit down and work it out
You would look at the symbol
And know what it meant instantly regardless of what language you spoke you wouldn't even need words which he felt could be eaten
Manipulated you could just have the symbol and get straight to the the truth of the matter and the way he saw it right off
About you have all of these Bennett
English women historian
Would you have the window everything from traffic accidents to health problems could be avoided he thought
Thought his symbol system would just be adopted he had this Vision that high-level political and Commercial Legos
Associations would be done in symbols did he say anything as Grand as like
War wouldn't happen constantly
And even of course
He reckon Hitler wouldn't happen basically that is the German people understood with symbols
They wouldn't have caught
Google's propaganda
That's a pretty tall order but it did seem to be what he thought everything could be cured by the system he's a biggest Dreamer
Ever
How did he go about doing this he started working out with the basic
Lines and shapes would be he also wanted to make sure you could produce it with a typewriter so it had to be a limb
Limited set
Of shapes out of which everything could be created
Okay so he works on it for 7 years 7 years and he comes up with
That wow that is a big way this massive book called
Listen bollocks
Samantha ology
Illogical writing for an illogical world
Explain the logic of his system for example here he was a symbol for sword which
Looks exactly like a sword
And then
Sword plus it Forward arrow means attack
I buy it
And then if you see a symbol for sword and another symbol for sword
In the cross that means war
Just the idea that you take these basic Elemental symbols and combine them exactly
Here's another one
This symbol here
Is like the top half of a circle
Like a little Rainbow
That means mine
Mind it looks like the top of a skull
Now if I were to take that
Symbol for mind
An hour to go like
This her to put
Inside it
?
That means
I don't know or I know
Doubt
And they're all so you know ways indicate adjectives
First person second person
Pass
The future but
How did the one thing that it did that no other
Language arts symbol system or anything is attempted
To do
At least as far as I know
Is that it would
Make clear when something was
What he called human evaluation you know basically an opinion
What you do is you put this little
Does Little V symbol and you put it above this symbol
And wife wifey well because you know how heavy is balance on a point and unstable at wobbles to him
That represents
Opinions human evaluations anything that comes out of mine
Take metaphors
If you say something which is the top four
If he says
You must put up
Timothy wheeler the reader
Do not
Take this literally
Without further ahead
Not exactly bulletproof but
I can I can see
See the thinking there I actually think it's pretty impressive
Ben
Okay so what happens next
Well after he finishes this and he and his wife are living in Australia.
They spent all their savings on producing this book
And sent it out
Two professors
Government officials heads of state like 6000 people
And
They waited for the orders to start rolling in
No response
From anybody
And then they had nothing
Can't say I didn't see that coming
Yeah and
With great
Disappointment Charles went to work
Cuz a welder in a factory
The General Motors Holden
He was working on the production line
Almost is a robot
And a year later
His wife died
You know he had fought in World War 1 had been in a concentration camp had lived in Exile
But he says this was the lowest point of his life
Until one day 1971
As he said this letter floated onto his desk
With this picture of this beautiful dimpled child
Proudly
Using his symbols
Yeah it
I it was a poster a poster
Upholster
This is Shirley Shirley McNaughton and at the time she was a nurse at a place called The OCCC
Ontario crippled
Children's
Center
A name that we
We're very happy to leave behind us
Matt Davidson
Changed my name I started there in 1960
8 truly was part of this group of teachers and nurses
Worked with these kids who suffered from cerebral palsy
If you have cervical palsy it's the motor control
From the brain that's been effect
Which meant that they had trouble moving their arms or legs
And even in some cases
They couldn't speak
They couldn't form word
And in a film that was made of this class
You see these young kids
Children from 5 to 7
I'll sitting in wheelchairs
They're watching the teacher
Talk to them and you hear them try to talk
Her
But they can
These kids had no way to communicate
Can they learn how to read
They could if you knew what they were understanding and they have no way to communicate that to you
The only thing all these kids had we're pictures that they could point at they had a picture of a
Toilet picture of food picture of a drink a picture of a bad
They were limited to that kind of communication
But I knew they were bright
But it's a good move and they couldn't speak how how would you know
Inside on that was the twinkle in their eyes
But she says a lot of doctors and nurses at the time I thought I was crazy. There really wasn't much going on inside
You know they thought I was projecting into the children what she needed she said was a way to get through to them
So one day she was at the library with a colleague and
They come across this
Dusty old volume that had never been checked out
Called
You guessed it
The symbolic
And what did you first think when you saw it oh boy I can I get back to the group how fast to the group with
Is exactly what we need
So do you remember what the first symbols were I think it was I
DUI looks kind of like a standing person upright line
Small horizontal line at the base
Next to it
The number one which means first person use the same symbol but with a number 2 for a second
And then they had to have a verb
And with love
Heart with an arrow through it so now they've got a sentence I love you
One of our mothers that's the happiest moment she's ever had with her child was wondering child came home and said I love
View you know self
Shirley and her staff started to add more symbols but they caught on
And pretty soon they'd created this giant laminated chart it had died
And you and he she we
And they then it had mother father grandma grandpa doctor nurse teachers therapist most men firemen
Library dentist eventually they added adjectives happy sad and frustrated all the verbs
You had loved and by
And he wants needs understand
Pretty soon the kids
Started to do amazing things with symbol combinations we started improvised
Charlie remembers asking one kid
Terry Martin what did you want to be for Halloween Harry pointed first that the symbol for creature
Creature
Not a person
Then he pointed at symbol for
Send
Blood that night
Creature who drinks blood
At night right he wanted to be a vampire
He spells a new word
It sounds like an explosion
With these kids
It was
For the first time she says
Actually
Talk to them like
Know who they were you got to know who the leaders were
In the classroom those who wanted to help others
Those who
Copy. Others
And it was around then that she and the other teachers decided to send Charles Bliss
That letter
We were sharing our excitement
For this gift is given to the children you know he was in Australia if he was an elderly man we had
No thought that he would come and visit us
But Charles bless he was delighted
Infinite baffle for cilantro recognition
And now he had it
Three mortgages house flies over
Dances around and kisses everybody effusively
Your long conversations with the kids in symbol
He was very happy about
The children
Joy
But somewhere along the way
Pinotage
Shirley Shirley in the teachers had begun to
Augment
They be going to add their own symbols
Such as the opposite meaning
Symbol
This allowed the kids to take one of us a standard symbols
Invert the meaning opposite of happy sad
Opposite of Uptown
Vivian out this would effectively double the number of adjectives
Switch would be great for the kids and
We developed rules for adding combined symbols for how to be more precise with the symbols
Pronouns that were missing the difference
Between he and him and his
In short I would make the adaptations I needed to me
From the very beginning we were using it
To meet the children's needs
Therapist
Specifically
And of course that is not what he had in his mind
He wanted a system that was
Universal
Every change that she made
Created like a
Separate dialogue
She would get very emotional about it. When he got back to Australia he started writing all these letters
Basically taking issue
With her changes and
Her failure to understand how his system work
Meanwhile
Thanks to Shirley worried about bliss's Temple's head Spread Way Beyond Canada
Too hungry
France
Sweden
Israel
Zimbabwe
Zimbabwe and then Argentina Brazil Finland Iceland Italy Bermuda Guam Japan Portugal Spain
Netherland Hungary Switzerland Venezuela Madagascar Yugoslavia
Fidelity places yeah
And in each place
The symbols would inevitably get tweets
To suit that country for example in Israel cuz the writing goes from right to left you the blissymbols 1/4 Mile
But what really pained him the most what really got him
Was it these teachers were using his symbols as a step toward
English or French or German or Hebrew or whatever it was just a way to get the kids
Two native language
The teachers always saw it the way they saw it you start the kids on Bliss and then you introduce
Reading and letters and eventually they're fully literate or with point
You don't need the Blessed symbol
This was the ultimate insult them
They're using his system
To bring these kid
Back
To the very thing
That he was trying to get
Everyone
Away from
Evil words
If I try to explain it today
I don't want to listen to me then looks roomie
That's right about this point in the story
That you start to hear
A different Charles
Shannon McNulty
Hess
Who sang perverted
Yeah
She smiles
Shibaguyz and she lies
He kept sending Shirley and the other teachers letters and the letters got angrier and angrier
This was not with the language was for this was a universal language that had nothing to do with spoken language you are
Are ruining my system you are abusing it
Eventually he decided to take matters into his own hands
And he travels back to Canada
And he started going to the various centers where the kids were using his symbols and saying horrible things about
About me
I'm getting them very upset that's when I got upset I got upset when he got them upset not long after
Shirley received a summons
He sued them
Misses jelly mcnorton on the tapes even suggest that he's going to have Shirley put away
Pro-life
4life
Why was he so upset with her in particular
Well because by this time she started the international organization
BCI with symbol Communications International
And you felt like
This was
The total unique and in powerful tool which could
Could and should transform lives around the world and more teachers needed to adopt it definitely
What was he asking for did he wanted us to use the symbols in his way
So 1975 the bci-1 a license agreement to use the symbols in the workbook
It's for the kids
But Charles Bliss
They should all be fine
Didn't give up
Authority parts
He published endless tirades and sent them out to anybody who would listen
Please show tonight
In paper
Or pacification
And
The administration of the program or Shirley was working was desperate to make him go away he had basically just
Destroyed the program and so
In 1982 he and the BCI
Finally come to an agreement
It was
AIA financial
Settlement that satisfied him what was the financial settlement
$160,000
You know we were a little program in the basement of the Ontario crippled Children's Center
We were
You know just the classroom
Wow that
To a guy who wanted to save the world ends up
Robbing a bunch of
Disabled kids
I'm at Calabria crudely with us house
Southfield
They're basically that's
Then
Did the symbols ever go anywhere
Well there was a lot of excitement about it in the beginning
But it never spread very far it's used
Now it a few schools in Canada and Sweden a couple other places
But it never went very far because he was constantly
Taking it down at every turn
But here's what I find most surprised
When I when I talk to Shirley
She didn't have
Any bitterness
Not even in the worst mom
When we were having the final
Legal
Action
Go through that in the morning and escalators are packing up their papers
Charles Place with Beach across the table and eats I surely will you help me
So should go to lunch with him
Sit with him and then he asked me if I would come to his hotel that night and put the ear drops in his ears
And I did that every night he would
Involved with the sink that's just the way it was
It wasn't just that she takes care of people for a living
She fell in
Still feels
That Charles Bliss had created
Something
Really new in the world
She even told me that
When she uses Bliss symbols
Actually thinks differently
Yes
Definitely
Stephen what what's different
Oh I just think so much more but what a word means
And it's it's it's like
Poetry in its purest form
I can playing with stained glass down here in my
Retirement and you can you know you can just
Take the symbols and put them into one
Composite
And
They say things that only I can say
It's beautiful
Transmit
A meaning that is beyond any word
Thanks producer Tim Howard
And Erica okra
Author of in the land of invented languages
We'll be right back
Bliss is having
Friends and family you can rely on
My name is Libby Graham and I am calling from the side of the road
In Dallas Texas
Awaiting rescue
This is ginger
Socially awkward introvert
From Cabot AR
Bliss's one day
Which I do not have to interact with another human being
Bliss
Is political ignorance
This Is My Boo from Mario
Hi this is Erica ocran
Radiolab
Recorded in part Radiolab is supported in cars are the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world more information about Sloan
Can be found at www.
Sloan. Org that work for you
Thanks in this message
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help this summer I'm hosting
And I request for those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
We're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments of childhood brilliance
Basically I want to hear about those times when I did something
It just means you lean back and say whoa how did they do that
Maybe it was the moment that our kids you've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of their musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed they're writing music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the
Specific moments where
Kid does something super smart but doesn't have anything to do with the test
If you have a story
Go to radiolab.org
Flash brilliance
Record short audio message
Again that's radiolab.org / brilliance
Thank you so much
Wait wait don't
Madison record
Okay now what were you saying spontaneously moment ago
Paytime Jad abumrad hi Robert, this is Radiolab in today
And in our last segment we met a guy who dreamt of a perfect world
Where words can never muck things up
Hello Kitty wig
Forget About Dre now we're going to look for protection right here
Physical
Okay so
Soda story
The perfect person
It begins with a with a birthday
Is February 9th 1880
6 miles outside the
Tiny Town of Jericho Vermont
And we're on a farm a family farm
Bentley
Family Farm And The scrawny 15 year old kid named Wilson
Get the microscope from his mother
So it's February and its Vermont and so naturally the first thing this kid does is he grabs a handful of
PicsArt
Single
Flake
And he puts it under the mic
And what he sees
This is is the most
Beautiful thing he
He's ever seen
Stereo land
And perfect
He calls them Master P
As 830
A great work
Safari cousin that
In his fifteen-year-old looking back he talked about that moment
And what he was thinking when he when he started for
Obviously
In a minute sir
Maven II
Master P
Disappeared
Without leaving any evidence
The date that they ever
They just started
Ines he remembers that he he should have decided then and there that he's going to dedicate his whole life
Ted 2 documenting bees
Master P
Otherwise no one will ever
Know that
Even exist
He's going to spend his whole life documented snowflakes
Yeah it's a good life Jen
And it pays well
It's just me with lazy and didn't want to do the farming chores
The beauty the beauty really good at digging potatoes but he just sort of was
So busy fussing around with his microscope that you know
I don't like this kid I don't like him
Depends your work ethic
That sucks so he takes his mic
Any moves it to this unheated Woodshed Baha'i
A man and he starts catching
Snowfall
And what Wally schedule you can't even breathe
Because he was worried that his breath would melt
His specimen
Holding his breath in in drawing these you know this extremely complex Crystal that they can take
Thinking maybe it'll maybe an hour to drop it
But depending on the temperature of the humidity the size of the crystal he had most yet 5 minutes
If you look at the mall and and he's not
Satisfied
He just felt like you wasn't doing it just
You know what he calls these
Miracles of
So Bentley
Persuade this mother who persuades his father
YouTube I am a camera
Where is a great white weight
1880 where in February 1880
We entered into the in the era of picture
Taking shots
Just barely
And for farming families
Just like a lot of money
Birthday by for him
And he gets it any sort of Jerry Riggs it to the microscope
And at age 19
Wilson Bentley
The first person ever in his
The photograph
A snowflake
Emily Cuvee
Snowflake celebration music here
From then on
Basically for the next
46 Winter's until he died
Every snowfall every blizzard
This a Bentley would stand in the doorway of his little Shack
Holding out a wooden tray
With
With thick mittens cuz you would wear these drumstick oven mitts
It took to make sure that his
None of his body heat would kind of leak out and then inadvertently melt any of the snow
Tweets artists and their
Give it a once-over with his eye if nothing was promising hehehe busy we had a
A turkey feather and he would sort of just wipe it clean with
What is turkey feather
Until I did find something you like
And then and then he would
Tiny little wooden rod
And he would just
Really delicately
Tap the center of the Earth
Crystal MN
Really really really gently lifted off
And then transfer it onto
Country Glass
Slide
So that you could put it under the
Mexico end
He could photograph
Basically
Photographs of a5000 snow crystals
Just a farmer
Doing this kind of is a hobby
But he sold copies of these photos for $0.05 a pop to places like Harvard in the British museum in the u.s. weather
Weather bureau
Research journals magazines like nature and National Geographic
I mean you've already seen the phone
It's like you've gotten them on a Christmas card they're on your
Like ugly Christmas
My sweater in your closet somewhere
Turn shirt with them on right now
They're everywhere they're beautiful symmetrical
Really clean and complex
A lot of the greatest scientist who ever lived like
Descartes and Kepler and hook they all tried to
Sketch and draw
And capture the essence of snowflakes but none of them could do it as well as this one
Obsessive loaner from Jericho Vermont whose photos were perceived to become more faithful to Nature than then
Than anybody else's
That was until
This other guy
German guy
Q the other guy dramatic theme music
Yes yes
He was a German meteorologist named Gustav hellmann
Gustav Hellman
Not of the man
Fame I don't believe
I hadn't even thought of that I could see a contemporary of
Yes and he's working on his own book about weather
Until he hires a
Micro photographer
Who is another German guy named Richard neuhaus and Mike
Microscopic himself and you just take normal size
Put it on and they take a bunch of photos using basically similar
Technology
Cameron
Essentially
But would they find
Is
Totally different
Date did you not find it
The elegants metric
Ideal snow crystals that Bentley found
Did the crystal they found work
Laud
Lopsided
Broken
In the Martian who would only ever seen like glossy fashion magazines
I just been given some like random family photo album
Oh wow this is
They're not so
Pretty ladies are kind of ugly
Call
Did Germans day
They basically called him out. Bentley was a fraud
There was a particular way that Bentley prepared his photographs what you would do if you would use
Pen knife
Scrape the negative around the snow crystal which is
What gave it.
Can I make black background because he thought it would
Can put it in me to soccer relief
The German guy said that's
It's it's misleading that it become mutilates the snowflakes
Wait so he's
Photographing these
Snowflakes
And then
Significantly messing with the photograph
Exactly right
Here's a quote from the
Photographer who sad quotes
In many images Bentley did not limit himself to improving the outline
He let his nice
Play deep inside the heart of the crystal
Fully arbitrary figures
Emerged
Well I don't know that doesn't seem so
Got no longer a candidate
Well that's
That's the question to them so they basically log this in
Just kind of going in there
Journals
Bentley basically launches a counter-attack and what she says is that
Doing that not correcting your photographs was anybody use this word like pervert
Why wouldn't you remove specks of dust or other imperfections what white photograph of a broken snowflake when you
You can photograph complete one so this is a quote from Bentley he said
A true scientist
Best wishes above all to have his photograph
As true to Nature as possible
Any free touching will help in this respect
Then it is
Bully Justice
So he thought his
Retouch snowflakes
For truer than
The
Normal ones
Yeah yeah exactly
Did the scientist supposed to
Various
Experience
Who is
Seen every different variation on a snowflake
But Ken
Bring it all together in one drawing One Scotch One photograph
The true snowflake
So if I brought him
A slightly
Gloppy
Snowflake
Look this is what fell on my nose
This is a true snowflake
Because it actually
We fell from the sky and it's you know it was a nun
Enhance
Yankee Woods
Say that you're an amateur like
Like this is this is not good work
You know this is an aberration this is an abnormality why would you choose to kind of highlight an abnormality as opposed to
What kind of disturbance
True ideal snowflake
It does that one exists
That's the key question for me like does the ideal snowflake exist in nature
You think there are such
I am scripture
Sadly beautiful I would like to think there are no I think it if my
Facts are right but the world snowflake expert is actually in in Pasadena Calif
All right
Check check check check check
Who can sunny Southern California
Yeah t-shirt I have sunscreen lathered and I'm going to talk to
World Authority on
Snow
How are you his name is Tenley bracket he's a professor of physics at Caltech
Wilson Bentley
Turn of a snowflake pictures under 10000 now
He actually
Mix
Artificially okay wow so this is a giant tank this is a nitrogen
Nevermind that
And get to your question about the ideal snowflake
A few things so number one
Thereof
Bajillion different kind
Dendritic Crystal Stellar dendrites needles and columns and Hollow columns and
And the sectored plates
There never was so every single moment as it falls to the Earth
It's either growing or shrinking
Get depending on the kind of trajectory through the different pockets of weather as it's moving down
There is no real
Platonic ideal form of a snow
Because it's
So
Influx
There's no such thing as a purple
Snowflake
But
That doesn't stop Kenly black from
I'm looking
You know I tried upping
Taho in Japan Ramon Michigan carnivals all over the world
Looking for Bentley perfect
Alaska
And Alaska
Just waiting for my favorite spot is Northern Ontario
Boomtown called Cochran
Population 5480
So where do you go in Cochran Georgia
Just anywhere they're just falling all over the place mostly it's the it's the parking lot of my month my hotel
Because there's a lot of waiting
You're only really snow as well that once a week
Even though things have to be Goldilocks perfect too high
Then they evaporate a little on the way down there look for a pretty or if the clouds are too light or too heavy
And a lot of times the temperature is wrong if you want those Christmas
Hard supermodel snowflakes
You need to have exactly - 15 that's
5 degrees Fahrenheit
Not so much wind
So that they'll put her down slowly and have more time to grow but every once in a while I mean when are the conditions are right
You go outside in a hopeful anticipating
I got crap
11 garbage out here
So you back go back inside and read some more email and you come back a half an hour later
Nope still lousy
Can you half hour later note
Still allows it and you know you do this for hours and then all of a sudden they'll get
Really good
The letter that I just out there
Frantically
Trying to collect as many as I can
What what a thinks I like to think about
This is it here I am
With my little piece of cardboard in a middle of a
Continent
It's snowing
I am catching some incredibly small number
Of these things for a brief.
And getting some really cool pictures and so you kind of wonder what that what else is out there you want you missing
I mean imagine just all the beautiful little works of art that are there just falling down
Totally unnoticed and then they just disappear
I mean stuff that is far prettier than any of the pictures I have cuz they're out there
You know they're out there statistically
They're out there and so you know there's such an awful lot of
Really gorgeous thing that you just starve like you say they're just totally ephemeral and you'll never see them
And they're falling constantly
You sort of want to just stop the world and go look at them
Thanks a lot of Nasser and toucan
Who wrote the book The Secret Life of a snowflake
This is Matt Neely Dawson from Asheville north
Carolina and Bliss is this sound
That's the sound of my 7 month year old daughter
Reacting to my puppy dog licking her
Hi my name is Igor and I'm calling from Northside Serbia Bliss is Indiana
All free Parts by Radiolab this is Steve Stroh gas
Is the taste
Of
Hot pastrami at Katz's Deli in the Lower East Side of New York City
We're 5 hours away from New York and don't get there very often
So I spent a lot of time in between visits thinking about that first taste
Pastrami
Call for me that's Bliss I get to think about some kind of almost unattainable perfection
It is attainable I just show up and there it is
And I have a list of bliss
Michael Flynn
Number one
Laughing uncontrollably number two
Zero-gravity liver for the first 10 seconds in a hot hot bag number nine
Aron twister
This is Anna calling from London
Radiolab was created by Jad abumrad has produced by Soren wila
MK4. Director of sound
Susie Larson bags are executive producer
Assassin Creed
Simon Adler Becka Bressler
David Gable
Bufflehead
Tracy hunt
Matt kielty Robert krulwich
Jalen goriya Annie McEwen
Melissa O'Donnell
Kelly Prime
Sarkari
REM wax
Pat Walters
With help from Shima ODI
Audrey Quinn
Anneal definition
Checker is Michelle