Everybody this is Jad
As you may or may not know we just started our first ever Radiolab spinoff
Call more perfect
Which is
Unity ideas
To tell
Stories
About the Supreme Court
Cases that are in front of the Supreme Court in
To hear those dramatic
Stories in Ventura
Think about them really
Hard
Taking the Radiolab Vive and putting it into this new space
It's done really well
So excited we want the entire Radiolab Posse to know about it
So if you haven't
Tried yet
Go to iTunes Riviera podcast check it out we help you
Scribe
Play X you one more episode for you guys this one is
And episode we've been working on in researching important for months and months and months
Really hope you enjoy
Hey I'm Jared I'm Rod this more perfect
Today to stories from reporter Catherine Wells
The first
SM adult content in it so be warned fills me with kids
Might want to skip
Yours Catherine
So maybe we can start with the
The night
Started yes or no start with a start the who what when where
The best way to describe Vienna
You have a front row seat
The Greatest Show on Earth
September 17th
On the outskirts of Houston
There's
Deputy sheriff named Joseph Quinn around and he hears this
Call go out on the radio
Somebody's called in and said there's a man going crazy with a gun in an apartment
She happens to be driving right by
Apartment complex
Pretty familiar with the complex
I knew where the building was so he's like hey I got this
I could listen and see if I can do any kind of sound to disturb
Walking to the breezeway
On high alert has tightened Reynolds pumping
In-N-Out in the middle Courtyard
It was a gentleman standing out there
Tootsie
Xiaomi start yelling over here over here I can tell him I was
Upset
He's up there he's up there I should up where any Place apartment on the second floor
Is that where you're saying that apartment right there he said yeah
So a couple other officers arrived and they get information
Control your breathing
You know their adrenaline watching a blood pressure down the way you don't get tunnel vision
Went up the stairs
Wireless
When I get up to the top of the stairs
Got to the apartment door and their door was
A jar was open
I listen for a second
I could detect anything in the apartment
So we got ready and I
Push the door open all the way open
Announced our presence Sheriff's Department
Anyone in apartment come out where we can see you keep your hands in plain sight
I did just two or three times very loudly
Still no response
There's a bedroom in the back of the apartment
What's a door
To a back bedroom
It was closed and
These
Two officers start walking towards it open the door
Is it open
As soon as he did
People arched back
Startled
So go to the bedroom
You've got to be kidding me
Really
What was it
It was
Two guys having
Something I'll never forget I mean it's like
Dodgers
Flabbergasted
Okay so here's the story the two guys that were in the apartment where John Laurens
And Tyron Garner
John was an older white guy he was in his fifties and Tyrone was a younger black guy in his 30s
Come to find out basically these gentleman downstairs
Former lover on again off again lover one and he was upset that the other today
They were engaged in some kind of
Okay so the guy in the parking lot was the boyfriend of Tyrone and we don't really know why
Call 911
But the thought is that maybe he was jealous of whatever was going on in the apartment and he decided he wanted to get the
It was a Lover's triangle kind of thing
So you know the cops come in and Johnny Tyrone have no idea what's going on they didn't know that
The boyfriend had gone and
Call nine-one-one so they're shocked
Quinn says they start yelling at him
Just I mean combative
Belligerent
I refuse to comply with anything
We hated gays we were homophobic we were jackbooted not
So the starting point
When does suicide
We're leaving here in the way you're acting and they're intoxicated we're going to have further calls here
Yeah it's not again
If we leave them here
Recite Surah restaurant
Really what what
On what charge I mean they're just in their house
So that's the
Question
Coleman for 15 years and
Blessed with the ability to have someone of what you would call a photographic memory
Meaning Hindu the penal code really well
He starts
Thinking he starts going through all the possible laws
Could apply to this
20 lines on this one
Statute 2106
It says that members of the same sex can engage
It's a law Banning sodomy
You get sexual intercourse
Or not
Even treated like civilized
This is John Laurens from an interview he did with Lambda legal in 2008
It's one of the few bits of tape that we have
This is all of a sudden we're taking you downtown
I wasn't allowed to put clothes on
I was handcuffed and dragged down stairs
Officer Joe Quinn has a different version of that story
They refuse so
We forced them to put
Some underwear on you know actually tell him down and put underwear on them and escorted them out apartment like that
It was a struggle just to get them to put underwear on
It's time for second whatever happened in that room which capital golang
Second
This moment
Two guys supposedly having sex and being charged with sod
It was like a strike of lightning
It would begin the process would profoundly
Reshape America
What's interesting
This is one of the first things that you bump into if you are an idiot
About the Wall of China
And then you try to make a podcast about the law
Is that
There's often disconnect like laws are these things that float above us all these beautiful abstractions
And yet if you want to challenge law you've got to find a person
Down here in the mud
Who's experienced perfectly SoMo captures what you feel is wrong with the law you got to find a perfect plaintiff
How do you find that person what happens if they're not so perfect
These two stories are going to hear about a particular tactic that sometimes called test case litigation
And I wasn't aware of the for catheter
The Second Story actually touches on a current case
Just decided a few days ago
Affirmative action will meet the guy
Who brought that case
The critics say it's basically destroying some of the most iconic civil rights law from the 60s
First
Get back to Katherine Wells with a story of a case called Lawrence V Texas
Okay
Come on Inn
I brought out my alarm
Vs Texas box of
Stop
So went to Houston and I visited a guy named Mitchell katine he's a lawyer there
And
He showed me the arrest papers he had the arrest paper
Words for these two guys
CJ Lawrence Criminal
Officers observed
The defendant engaged
In deviant sexual
Conduct
Charged with homosexual conduct
It's right there in writing
It really is strange to see those words on a piece of paper it seems like such an anachronism but it was not actually
Has dated
September 17th 1998
Now in 1998
Texas wasn't the only state that had this kind of law on the books
At least 13 other states also had an anti-sodomy law and it's important to note that you know this law wasn't used very
Very much people were not arrested for this law because when would police be present in your home to observe you having
Jill Carpenter
International law
SMU Law School
I mean sodomy laws weren't really about stopping any
Body from having sex
They were really about ensuring
That we could label
People Criminal
It was
A label that
People could point to
So the people who disapproved of homosexuality could say
Looks defining a
Of homosexuality
A crime
Crime
Can you commit the crime
Well you're a criminal it's a criminal statute people can say your criminal
Which then give the state
Illegal basis to justify all sorts of housing discrimination employment discrimination
Military and every context
Statin effect
How many people argue that these laws
They also sent
A strong cultural message
The most recent example here in Houston is better described as a vicious
Killing in this was at a time when hate crimes in Houston word
Surprisingly comments after being beat with a nail-studded two-by-four
2nd senseless killing in the Montrose area in less than three months is a lot of blood and was really apparent that he
Benshot
To make a long story short was very eager to repeal that sodomy law
Okay so John and Tyrone were arrested on a Thursday night
The next day it's so happen
That
Because of the location of John Lawrence's apartment
The case landed in a Justice of the
Peace Court meaning after Quinn made the arrest
The report was sent to that court for processing
Now this court is
Mostly deals with traffic
It's mostly a traffic court
But there happens to be this clerk in the court
Who was
Gay and it couldn't believe that there that somebody had actually been arrested for homosexual conduct in their home
Is Clerk and his partner go to a bar start talking to the bartender
I believe it was a Friday night
This is Lane Lewis he was the bartender what I was doing
Under nineteen
Who is two guys come in and they tell Lane
You're not going to believe what happened
It's a couple of guys were arrested
And charged with the sodomy
And when was like yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah
You just can't believe that such a thing happened it's such an unusual occurrence
And
Landsat send me the report Monday morning bright and early
I can hear my fax machine go off
But in their not pull it off
Officers observed
The defendant
Engage in deviance
Anda
And that's when it hit me
Oh
I mean it was so clear night and day to me
Immediately knew what I had in
White why does he care so much about
Well so when he wasn't
Being a bartender Lane was a community organizer
Tickly around LGBT issues I was present of the game has been political
Caucus that's one of the oldest LGBT civil rights groups in the south
He been waiting for this moment how long have you been looking for a case
7/8 years
7 light years
Cuz just too
Laid out explicitly what why did you need I need a test case
You can't change a law like that
If you don't have
A case
People in the Texas legislature have been trying to remove this law from the book
Books for years according to Jill Carpenter every time someone would introduce a proposal to repeal the law it would
Snickers and catcalls in the state legislature
It just wasn't really going anywhere
So activist who decided the only way to get this done is to bypass the legislature and go straight to the courts
So I need a case I had to have a someone guilty
Celine start trying to track them down at this point that you guys have been released from jail
Conversation basically went like this
Hi my name is Lane Lewis I'm a gay activist here in town you don't know me
Oh that's not important but I understand you've been arrested
I'm begging you not to plead out
Meeting don't just say you did it and pay the fine I knew I couldn't have them played out I will find you
Do lawyers
Raise the money I will pay for everything
Just
Don't do anything
Until you when I have a notch
Opportunity to me
Weeks later they all meet at Mitchell katine xoffice
And it immediately becomes clear that these guys are sort of an Odd Couple John Lawrence at that time was
About he was 55 years old
Lab technician for a hospital with a young skinny black guy 24 years younger than John
Study job and job to job no idea why
What their connection was they weren't lovers
Both heavy drinkers
Very heavy
Both have criminal records
Tyrone has been convicted of assault and drug possession and John have been convicted in the sixties of Murder By
Automobile yeah they were not the perfect plan that they were not the poster boy these or not
Pretty tween
And they weren't political no not at all
Not at all
Weanling told John Lawrence
I'm a gay activist here in town John Lawrence didn't even know what that was I don't know what a gay activist is
Basically neither of them had any interest like no interest
And being a public figure
You're so
I gave him the whole
What your country can do for you ask not what you can do for your country speech I mean literally
I reminded them of who Harry hay was
Arguably the founder of the original LGBT movement
Ulysses may not remember but at one time it was illegal for
Certain number of gay male
And the LGBT community
To get together in one location is illegal
Can do it the idea that they would be Networks
I'm sanctuaries in places where we can come an hour to which we would be able to move and organize and change things across the
The country
So I told him a little bit about that history in
How far we've come and how far we had to go
And that
Badinage
How to change that
So I told him
I said
I'll be able to protect you
For maybe the first year or two
But there's going to come a time when
It will no longer be about you
It'll be about some
Much much bigger
So
They agreed
Tyrone's attitude was okay
What do you need me to do
John was much more indignant
They took the wrong person
Golden song
It was a ridiculous law
But
Texas loves to keep Samantha
Quiet things around
He was mad
He was angry
Here's where the story gets
Complicated
Because
At one point according to Lane Lewis
They were having this conversation and John was ranting you know about how he been treated and
He said you know what the worst part is we won't even
He said
That they were not having sex
Wait what but they were not having sex they were
Sitting in their underwear on the couch
Watching the late-night news
They say they were sitting there doing nothing and the cops just burst in and started pushing them around and
But they were never even having sex
Wave it is in this whole case about them having sex
So you're saying the thing that this case is supposed to be about
Might not be true
Right so I interviewed
Three of the four police off
Carpenter says when he talked to the police officers
He did find that their stories were sort of all over the
The place one guy said it was anal sex seesaw
One day later said he thought it might have been oral
Officer said they never saw anything
Fidel says he believes John story there probably was actually no sex
You think what might have happened is that the cops walked in and saw some gaytard on the wall and some gay magazines lying around
Feeling that really set off the office
And they said well we know they're homosexuals they probably engaged in homosexual conduct at some point and that's illegal in Texas
No no I'm not there was no no no doubt about it I mean I have no
No reason to live Quinn to this day
Still insist that he walked in on them
Copulating he says he saw what he saw and he just did his job
That's fine I don't agree with your lifestyle but that's
My opinion that's what it is
So there's no way to know what actually happened obviously but
In a way it doesn't matter
Because when John said that Tulane that they weren't even having sex
Message on don't ever say that again
Don't ever say that to anybody
Again
Because we could have people know that
We couldn't have people find that out
Is it going to go forward to this yet we were scared that
Another case would get screwed up at that point
And potentially
The da dropping the charges if police report
You had to preserve the LIE
Correct correct
Dumb question
You can just do that you can just preserve a lie to keep a case going
Is that that's okay it wasn't our job
Prove or disprove the LIE
The thing that mattered was not what did or didn't happen that night the thing that mattered
Arrest report
Set but if what the arrest report said
Potentially didn't happen
Should that matter
Well
No no one
Our legal system is not designed to bring out the truth this is a misc
Conception does not bring out the
Hotel Carpenter against people who play their roles
And pursuing
Whatever they think their best interests are
That's exactly what happened
So
For the first few years my job was to keep the boys out of the out of the news
And why was that
Well they had a tendency to drink
And get Rowdy and fight
And they like to go to CD hotels and rent rooms and get really really
Hi drunk whatever
And inevitably they would start fighting with each other
And so
What I did what I would do without wood
I knew the difference
Places they've stayed since he would go to the city hotels and talk to the clerk's give him a business card tell him
If these boys come and check in they cause problems
Call me first
Fan on more than one occasion that happened I'd get a call at 2 in the morning
Your guys are here they're causing trouble I'm going to have to call the cops I would jump out of bed put on my clothes cuz we couldn't have them
You know what they're already on the front page of the Houston Chronicle we could not have our dependence
Doing a perp walk for drugs and alcohol
So I would drive down there and I would figure out
Which one was causing the most problems
Put them in my car
And I would drive them somewhere else I would separate them out
That happened more than once
More than once
Celine city of the spear that
John and Tyrone wood would start talking to the media and let something slip
About
Their version of the story
So we gave them these little cards kept small little sentence basically said
Thank you for contacting me
Please refer to line Lewis and had my phone number in my ear
And I said so anytime to Media contacts you
Don't think about what you say
Right that's what you get screwed up when you start thinking about what you want to say to the media pull this out of your wallet
Read it
Even though there were these close calls
As a case wound its way through the court system
Mitchell katine told me about this
One time there was this
Press conference
And we came outside to the normal media
Group that was out there wanting
Quotes and talk to us and they didn't want to hear from the lawyers that wanted to hear from the clients
He was like all right
Just this once
Tyrone get up to the mic and I think a reporter asked him
You know how do you feel about this
And he said
We didn't do anything wrong
He just kind of yelled at out and
Angry way we didn't do anything wrong
Metropolitan back and was like that's enough
That's enough next day
We didn't do anything wrong
That was the quote on the headlines of the mornings
Paper the next day and certainly I knew what you meant
But they weren't having sex what you know
Could also be interpreted as
Homosexual conduct
Nothing wrong
He says luckily
That's how people took it
Fracking
Couple years
You're kind of how it went down
They started at this
Justice of the Peace Court they were sentenced to a fine of 125 bucks so happy old
Send the case gets kicked up one level to the Harris County Criminal Court their find again they appeal it again
Level to the 14th court of appeals onemorelevel ultimately the Texas Criminal
Court of appeals which has the highest
Court of Texas
Criminal Appeals refused even to hear the case
So the only next step is
Will hear argument next door number 02102 John Geddes Lawrence and
Tyrone
March 26th
Almost five years after the arrest
The case lands of the Supreme Court
And by the time it gets up there
Mister chief justice inmates
The court the story is not dwelled upon at all
They didn't say
These guys weren't in a relationship
If these guys were having sex
One of them was cheating on his partner
Seems like they might have not been having sex anyway
Didn't say any of those things I said
Family relationships are established that there are hundreds of thousands of people that this is about families and relationships
Relationships how people in loving relationships
Have the right to express themselves in whatever they want it's none of the state's business opportunity
In the privacy of their own home
Perform the same function
You know basically people in relationships have the right to have sex with each other regardless of their gender
Protected forever
The distance from
Fundamental matter
Of American values
Wow
It's like watching something float up from the sort of monkey like Realm of of humor real life and then it just
It's kind of pretty rats
Netflix app
Yeah
It was such a pretty story that people words
Suspicious
My people were asking
How did this arrest even happen this was a setup you all set this up
That was their big Battle Cry
Show me Tokyo teen says he heard this over and over again
But I always want to say so so what if it was does that make it any less
Uppercase who care has further questions
Thank you very much
The Honorable court is now adjourned until Monday next
3 months later
Record number 02102 Lawrence against Texas
Justice Kennedy begins reading a summary of His
The question before the court
Have a Texas statute
For two persons of the same sex
Intimate sexual
Everybody's waiting for the out
Houston
Texas
Super context it wasn't totally clear how this case was going to come out because 17 years earlier there'd been a case called
Bowers vs Hardwick
And
Then they ruled that sodomy laws were fine
There is no constitutional
Conclusion
But there should be a fundamental right to engage
Homosexual sodomy
And Supreme Court almost never will sings order that recent
So Justice Kennedy starts talking about all the similarities between the cases
Dispatched
The tension starts building
And then finally he got
To the moment where he said
And it's not correct today
And at the point Justice Kennedy said that there were
People sobbing
Stars versus Hardwick should be
Rallies Across the Nation gay rights Advocates celebrated their legal Victory a ruling so brought it surprised even many of
Court rules in favor of two Texas man who challenged a state law that made homosexual
The ruling overturned a Texas law that allowed police to arrest gays for having sex
12 other states have similar laws
Including a good morning John Lawrence was at home in his apartment in Houston
Watching the tanks
And all of a sudden it says has rule the law in concert
I came out of bed quite happy
Obviously not everybody
What's happy about it clear that I have nothing against homosexuals
Promoting their agenda
Justice Scalia said
Basically
If you want this to happen that's fine but you're going about it the wrong way the court is not the place where this decision
Should be made you need to go talk to your fellow citizens
And convince them that this
Blonde needs stitches
Coming to us and asking us to bypass
What your fellow citizens seem to want that is
It's not how
Persuading one's fellow citizens
And imposing one's views in absence of democratic
Is something else
He sees this as a
Small minority imposing their views
On everybody else
Ebony
Said he was worried about something else
Today's opinion
Dismantle
The structure of constitutional law
That has permitted a distinction to be made
Between heterosexual
I'm homosexual
Set this decision would open the floodgates
And that it would only be a matter of time
Before the court was being asked
To decide on gay marriage
And he was right when Kennedy read the marriage decision in 2015
The courthouse
Private intimacy of same-sex couples
Yet it does not follow the freedom stop
Outlaw to outcast
Maybe a step forward but it does not
So what happened to
Garner and Laura
Well
John Lawrence and Tyrone Garner didn't live to see this
Tyrone died in 2006 from meningitis
No job
Had no money
He was 39 and his family was very poor
And they didn't have the money to bury him
They didn't even have the money to reclaim his body from
County morgue
As for John Lawrence he died in 2011 at 68
From heart problems we didn't even find out about it until a month after he
It was dead
This hero of the gay rights movement
Was unknown and under
Is passing
What is a fairy about
Sort of boat
Practice of bringing things to the Supreme Court
The two people who story this case revolves around
Concerta Fade Into the background afterwards
Well one is tempted I think to be very cynical in some ways because it means that
These people were useful as long as they were useful in after that they could be forgotten
Galaxy had that reaction a little bit I mean this is
Story of social progress but there's something a little funny at the center of it for me
NFL gear playing this for our legal editor Italian style
In a lot of ways are our legal system
Duval's in to an end
Justifies the means
Kind of Justice
We we care we we we care about the process so much
Manitowoc the processes
Extremely important Ellie isn't this just weird to you like this is a dumb law like a dumb dumb dumb dumb law
Why not to
Should there be an Avenue to say this is a dumb law was taken away why do you have to find some people
Didn't
Have
Sex they say
10 + 1/2
And March them up all the way through the court system and then forget about the time you just seems weird to me
Seems like a
Empty theater
Why do we have to do it that way
Because if you want to put a ballot initiative up in 2003 in Texas saying
Is gay sex okay
It would fail
It would fail in 2003 in
You probably fail in 2016 in test
To probably fail
In 2032
In Texas
That's why
The majority isn't always right
So you you you you
Take the USB take the Democratic at
And this isn't this is a this goes back right to the founding of our country
Like when are you going to let popular will
Run wild and when are you going to
Constraineth
Not just restrain a country
You know when you going to stop it
Amanda
Why do Texas is a is an example of a
We just going to stop
And it was the right call
So after this Supreme Court decision to Texas immediately go and repeal the law
No actually the laws still on the books in Texas
Know the Texas legislature
Like other legislatures around the country refuses to repeal the law it stays there assertive
Remnant of a
Kind of a dark
Almost forgotten past
Keep in mind they can't enforce the law now that is unconstitutional
But they refuse to take it off
Coming up a very deep dive into the guy behind one of the most
Universal cases this term in case that just got decided late last week
Score perfect
United States
Hi my name is Peter Fink
And I'm calling from ritsona refugee camp
In Evia Greece
Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloan
At www.slha.org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
About what we're calling tiny moments of brilliance
Basically I want to hear about those times when I did something
It just means you read back and say whoa how did they do that
Maybe it was the moment that I
I kid you been reading to 4 month started reading back
Do you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lesson
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of their musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed are ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the
Epic moments where
Kid does something super smart but doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story
T-shirt with us
Go to radiolab.org
Brilliance
Record short audio message
And that's radiolab.org / brilliant
Thank you so much
This is more perfect I'm chat album Rod if Supreme Court cases can sometimes feel like plays
Where the activist and lawyers are sort of like the directors pulling the strings in the people in the center of the case
The plaintiffs are just
Imperfect actors
Pooping cast
And the scripts are written for them will that dynamic
Definitely an effect this term
Texas last week we have had a decision just handed down
In what was billed as the landmark affirmative action case
Of this term
University of Texas centers round the following question
Use racial preferences in college admissions
Now the University of Texas has a policy where the
The top 10% of every High School class automatically get in but for everybody else
They will consider factors like race in the question was
Is that okay
Couple days ago the court decided
Barely
But yes it is okay the Supreme Court has upheld the affirmative action program at the University of Texas
Fraction and higher education is constitutional
Now the case was brought by a young white woman named Abigail Fisher
Race may have hurt her chances to attend the University of Texas
Activities I was in who were being accepted into UT and the only other difference between us
She was arguing that affirmative action discriminates against
Her his wife
Carson now
What you saw in the wake of that decision and even before
Eonline
Courant
Hate
Directed
Fairland okay
Get into a good college black people have it better
If you don't take your baby if your grace didn't suck your dumbass
Maybe you would have gotten into a good college
Becky with the bad grades
Really happy you and your racist lawyer got shot down
Because this case may have very little to do that beef
Picture I mean if you look at the press conference
Treated differently based on their race
Abby Fisher is the one of the podium but behind her
Are the back
You'll see the sky
He's there in every single press conference quarterback
At the edge of the frame not too many people know about him his name is Edward Blum
And he's the one who actually brought the case
When it comes to this case and so many others
He is
The architect
He's brought dozens of lawsuits notches
This one ad
He seems to be a maestro of getting cases
Is to the Supreme Court that challenged civil rights law
Critics or paint messes like one-man Wrecking Crew
For civil rights
He's almost single-handedly rolling back Decades of civil rights law
And when it comes to affirmative action he says he's not done just to make a long story short we wanted to meet him
Figure out how he does it
Went to Tallahassee
Border Katherine Wells takes from here
That's where you live or
He Winters in Tallahassee
You walking what initially struck you
Golden Retriever
Is what initially struck me
Literally physically like
Of course
And
I don't know what I was expecting but when you hear about these cases you know
Critics are really
People are mad about
Case it is deeply disturbing truly outrageous
So I go to meet him and your flight
From Austin
The Dallas
To Tallahassee uneventful and
On time and
Good he's like a totally nice guy
A regular guy
Was it look like
Like a dad there's something in me that just loves
Tradition Inn
Custom you love
Listen to The Great American Songbook
Beautiful thing
Frank Sinatra
And hum
Ella Fitzgerald
I love
Art and Museum
Independent films golf what's his what's the story with his backstory
Well he's 64
Small town
In Michigan
My dad owned a shoe store their my mom worked with him in the shoe store
Cleaning up to
I'm
The first Republican my mother ever met
How to use the word typical but it
It really was a typical liberal
Jewish household
My mother and father
Where Franklin Roosevelt
Harry Truman Democrats
Always
Democrat and he said he was
That way to all the way through college
The University of Texas
Grad school University of New York where I spent a year studying of all things
African literature
But he says somewhere along the way his political leanings
Started started to shift I spend
A summer in Israel
Living on a
Auntie says he came out of that experience a little less liberal than he was before
And you got married and then in the early 80s he's living in Houston working as a stockbroker
And
We met
Aren't our neighbors
This particular couple they were New Yorkers who would move to Houston both grew up as
Liberals and the guy she opened my eyes
To the world of the Neo cons
National Review commentary magazine conservative magazine
And this was around the time that the neocon movement was really hitting its stride
Garibaldi's New York liberals
Defecting
Is what he says
Bowser
Individuals who grew up
Question
The wisdom
Obvious liberal
And he says slowly
Overtime very
Graduate
He became one of those people
Fast forward a little bit he's living in Houston Garden variety
Existence and
Something happens that sends him on this entirely new
What path
Basically he and his wife moved to a new neighborhood
The move from the suburbs into the downtown area
Urban and in 1990
When
We went to vote for the first time in our new neighborhood
I realized that the Republican
Party had not fielded
Candidate
To oppose the
Democrat
Incumbent
Running for congress this is a
District that has
Almost 600 thousand people
You don't have a choice you only got one person running
Decided to run himself
I lost item
It was no great surprise to anyone
He actually lost by 32 point
But along the way
It's something really unusual happened
During my campaign he and his wife Lark piano they decided they were going to go meet voters in their District
I got a giant print out of all of the addresses in the 18th congressional district
Call daywalking list and they just started going door-to-door meeting people handing out literature
And I'd walk down say Oak Street
Take
The even side of Oak Street and my wife would take the odd
Numbered side of
Oak Street
And we would start to walk and
Very quickly they realized that
The district
Shape
Was funny
Some houses on one side of the street would be in the district in the house is on the other side wouldn't and sometimes the district would
McDonough Highway caption apartment,
Flex come back at it just
Didn't make sense
This is like Bloom wife of Edward Bloom was peculiar because we had Maps
We had to follow
And it was
Very odd the way some streets were
And the districts and some weren't
Took a while for it all to really sinking as to how this could happen
After I guess a better week of this
We realized that neighbors had been separated
Almost house my house because of their race
You come to believe that the reason this was done
Was for the explicit purpose to create a majority at
African American
This is an untrue
Clothes from a clear and simple wrong part of the reason this was done was the Voting Rights Act of 1960
Of Americans are denied
The right
McCall of their color
This act was
Giant
Step forward in civil rights
One of the primary things that day it is eliminate barriers to voting like poll taxes and literacy tests all these
Strategies that have been used to keep minorities
And then this other thing it did sort of in a roundabout way through a series of interpretations is
Encourage the creation of districts where the majority of Voters
Where minorities
And that's because
You know one of the strategies that have been used previously to
Dilute the minority was to take minority communities and
They called it cracking lately
Split them apart into many different
So that they were never
In the majority
Elect representatives
So the Voting Rights Act tried to correct
Bat
18th congressional district
Was one of these majority-minority districts
The district
Drawn by the text
But you have a slight
African American majority
I think about 51%
African Amer
But this was the problem according to bloom
The way they got to that
African American majority was bite creating this District that's zigzagged all over the city and cut through neighborhood
I could not understand
People live close together they
Eccentric kids to the neighborhood schools they shopped in the neighborhood
Shopping centers they were worried about
Neighborhood issues
Rick these neighborhoods apart
By race
Seemed
So wrong
In his mind this law was actually
Not limiting discrimination but actually perpetua
I don't know what a
The average person upon realizing this would have done
I decided
To file a lawsuit
Decided to sue the state of tech
Call the few
Friends
Who lived in the 18th District
And a few other districts in Texas American American Hispanic and Asian kept looking and looking and looking and
Until I found a lawyer that I could afford $7,000 a month filed a lawsuit challenging the
Constitutionality Texas's redistricting plan
Recent charged with yes the Voting Rights Act was good in its day
But now it was being used as this excuse to segregate people into racially polarized
Worked its way through the lower courts and
Tomorrow
And surprise
In 1995
Number 94805 George W bush vs Alvera of the Supreme Court
Look it up
Yeah we all did
Court so there we all are
Our opponents
Step to the lectern and
The constitutionality of three congressional districts they make
Their arguments
Texas basically said all we have to put people together by race
The Texas legislature has the obligation
To satisfy Federal requirements in the federal requirements
Like remember the Voting Rights Act we're trying to make sure that there are enough minorities in this District
So that they have a chance to elect a representative or advocate
His arguments
That was just being made I said
But look at the map
The map is
Bizarre
And the only reason
It could have gotten this way as
Because you're only thinking about race
Only race
Think about it that seems messed up isn't that messed up it doesn't matter what your ultimate goal is
You cannot use
Forbidden tools rate is forbidden by the 14th Amendment to be used as a tool
A very tense situation
Let me explain
So in the end
Supreme Court
Hair-splitting
But I think it's at this deeper question that
In our society
Discourse we just haven't figured out how to talk about anyway
You don't look if you're defining race just as the color of someone's skin
The government cannot use that in any way that's against the constitution on the other hand if you take the
Wider View and you look at race in the context of History social context then
How can the government address discrimination without taking race into account that they have to
So it's a difficult balance
You can't look at race
But you have to look
And
The Supreme Court says to Texas look
All you're doing in this case is sorting People based on how they're labeled on us
You're not looking at that wider context you're not looking at if he's communities with next to each other
You're just sorting them based on
Race alone and that's not good enough
You can't do that when the
Opinion came down
The Supreme Court ruled in our favor five
That was
Quite
A day
The day that we won that lawsuit
I was
Hooked forever
After that Edward Bloom decided that this would be expected became
Do you support to try to strike down every race-based policy he could legal team
I was taking on the road I recruited plaintiffs in New York Virginia South Carolina to check
Challenge congressional district
Plans and we won in each of those States
He helps to school districts in Florida and Texas and the use of racial quotas in case through 12
Magnet schools affirmative action in Houston city Contracting
Kill affirmative action
I've been the architect of a over two dozen lawsuits
Six of which
Made it to the Supreme Court
Including
In 2013 in a 5-2 for vote very divided court and supreme court today struck down
He parts
The Voting Rights Act of 1965 Supreme Court struck down a very important part of the Voting Rights Act
She 1965 Landmark lock is considered one of the most important pieces of civil rights legislation
They Shoulda never pass Shelby County vs holder this decision
Gutted the Voting Rights Act
Specifically there was as part of it that said
States and counties with a history of discrimination
How to check with the federal government first
Before they go about changing their voting laws basically the federal government was saying look
You've been up to all this stuff we're now we're watching
Supreme Court said
You know
Time for change
That list was made a long time ago and
It's update
This decision
Restores an important constitutional order to our system of government
This was Bloom's bigots
When Shelby County
I think a lot of people burst into tears when they came down
Disturbing
Deeply disappointed
With a court
Decision in this matter
Change during the Civil Rights Movement people died
For the precious right to vote
This is congresswoman Sheila Jackson Lee of Houston
I would like to have the Supreme Court Justices go back in time go back
Sometime and March with those who marched after Bloody Sunday
I from Selma to Montgomery
A balloon has a right to his opinion
It doesn't mean that it has to be the opinion of the
The United States
I understand that
People were in a
Gravely
Upset
I also know that they were
People who were Gravely relieved
And Gravely
Ratify
Yeah but I think what gets a lot of people
Is it
You look at the Civil Rights
Videos UC
Thousands 40,000 people in the streets marching and
You hold that if you make a split screen in your mind
Hold that thousand ten thousand people in one side
On the other side
You one guy
It does make you ask basic questions about tomorrow
That's a false
Paradigm
It's
That maybe your split screen but that's
Really not
Good luck in 19
America was held hostage
Bye
The legacies of slavery
And the
Choke hold
Jim Crow
Fast
Forward
To 2006
The reauthorization
Of
The Voting Rights
The
Choke hold
Had gone
Away
African Americans
In the Deep South
Registered to vote
In numbers
Often exceeded
Participated in elections
Trends in numbers that
Exceeded
In terms of
Elektra Opera
Opportunities
We have
Come
180 degrees
From
1960s degrees because of the law which you helped overturn
In an instant we don't know it's a boy degree that is the psychology of America changing or the fact that we had a lot
Cat people online
And now that love has gone
And now we see voter ID laws coming back in the play which I think any
Like sane person would admit is it is it is it is an attempt a blatant attempt
Disenfranchised
People who it feels a little bit strange that two I mean I completely agree with your things have gotten better
Same time I think
Well that was because of the law that's now gone
Look laws change
Laws
Evolve
+ and at some point
They need to come to an end
Okay
So just to jump back in
Play something we haven't
Actually talked about yet
Is
Original question how
How does this actually happened how does it work
How is one person
Able to be so effective
To do this work you need a car
Computer a printer a cell phone
Really about it
Play who pays for the lawyer fees
Who do you go to individuals that know of my work
There are
Foundations
Okay so he's a 501 c 3 like the n-double-acp and Lambda legal that funded
Lawrence versus Texas
And if you're a 501 c 3 public
Charity as he has you don't have to reveal your donors to the
We do know a couple of his donors though and they're
Wealthy very conservative
So in the end what he does is
Just sort of a
More
Maybe more strategic or sophisticated version of what Lane Lewis did in the first
Like
In this case that he just lost
Last week
We wanted to challenge affirmative action
So
The first thing you did was sort of do a cast
He said to find the perfect
White suit
Set up a website called UT not fair. Org
Race as a factor in the admissions policy pretty budget it's just him looking at the camera
In front of a poster that says UT not fair
To visit at
UT not fair. Org
Tell us your story
How many started talking to the people who respond
I think I ended up with
Responses
Of those about a hundred were
Viable
With the 75 you throughout just
Didn't think they would be sympathetic
Whittled a hundred down to seven that he thought would be sympathetic 7
Number 1 or 2
Did not
Really want to go forward
Like I don't want the attention or they were fearful
Aveeno
The backlash
To make a long story short he ended up finding Abby Fisher because a friend of his called and said
Hey my daughter just got rich
Rejected from UT
I heard you were looking
I think I'm a very
Like a very like introverted person so I feel
Like sometimes it is a lot of pressure
I think it's in the end it's totally worth it and and to be able to tab a voice
In this into know that my voice is making a difference is really reward
She seemed like the perfect planet
Strawberry blonde hair she's petite she's kind of shy in front of the camera in a good way
But last week
They lost
Sweet talk to him before all this happened so we weren't able to get a reaction from him but he did tell on Austin news
Paper that
The night after the decision came down
He had three glasses of wine
He took an Ambien
What about this particular lyrics
In a Billy Joel song
The song called Keeping the Faith
I'm a long distance
Runner
If there's something just emblematic about my personality
Run
Long distance
He says he's definitely not done
He's
Actually already has two more cases against
Affirmative action in the works
I have retained counsel to litigate
Harvard admissions portal
University of North Carolina's admission
I'm am Sergeant just doesn't strike anyone I mean forget the politics whether you're on on lucite or not.
The tactic doesn't strike anyone else
Fishing
I resist giving Ed Bloom that much credit
It's aliens Dollar General Eagle ad
I would say
The fundamentally he's just implementing
A strategy that was perfected
By the people he now ironically seeks to disenfranchise
On this is civil rights movement 101
He's got laws if he doesn't like
That he knows he can't
Overturn
Through an election
Clemson failed Congressional candidate
He had that Lust For for political power
Couldn't get it through the electoral system but he found this other way
I'm to do it this is exactly what this is
Okay so tell me this is one of the most
Fascinating
Things about the story
If we go back to remember this case there's a famous case called Plessy versus Ferguson
Starting to not really I think is a good example
This is Susan Carr law professor at American University Washington College of Law
Plessy versus Ferguson 1892 that was a case
Where are the state of Louisiana
Law which said that people of color
White people could not ride in the same train cars
If you heard the story
This is how it goes with somebody named Homer Plessy
Black man sits down in a white car he is arrested
He decides to Sue and his case goes all the way to the Sea
Supreme Court
The thing about that case
Is that it was a total setup
Leaving
So we go back when Louisiana passed that law requiring separate cars early civil rights groups were out
Obviously horrified by this but
The railroad companies were actually
Mad about this too because they thought it would be much more expensive to run the trains
If they had to have add additional training so they have
White cars in Cars of color
And so right activist
Companies
They recruited somebody named Homer Plessy
White 1/8 Safra
And they sent him to go sit in a white car
On a train
He got into a
First class
People's car
And they said somebody to go arrest him like they got a off-duty police officer
Ashley hired
You could do that at the time that you can hire a private detective to make
And today they hired that person to sew
Plus he gets onto the train
The conductor comes by and plessis Lake
Just thought I should let you know I'm actually in a black
And the conductor says well in that case you're going to need to be on the other
Car in the string Homer Plessy says
I'm good actually I I'm going to be staying right here and the conductor says
No really you have to move and Homer Plessy it says no really not going to
Things get heated and eventually this detective that they've hired comes in and arrest him
Brought a lawsuit
That's amazing the whole thing is cooked starting with
To challenge
Is the separate cars law and they were able to get it up to the US
Supreme Court
And they were hoping that they would be able to establish
That the idea of separating
The races with uncut
Institutional
But unfortunately they miss
Calculated in the Court ruled that the law
Was
Constitution
And what they got instead was
Separate but equal
Totally backfired
But
It was this early example of this other way
You know if you can
Find a plaintiff for create a plaintiff
You might be able to bypass the legislature and go to the Supreme Court instead
The n-double-acp later pickup on the
Today weather true
Geniuses
They perfected it and they perfected it under circumstances where victories were highly unlike
For example in the early 1900s they do things like send
A black guy in a white guy all over New York City to segregated theaters
And see if one of them was prevented from being seated
And if they were
They would sue those theaters
And when victories that way
Then there was this other law in Louisville Kentucky that said nobody could buy a house
Or live on a block in with white people lives if they were African American so they were
Create a white guy to sell a house to a black guy and then they had the black guy refused to take the house so the white guy could say you said you would
By the house but
I'm not buying the house because I can't live there white guys who's the black guy that was a manufacturer
2 case
It was one of the
First victory
And that's the case where Justice Homestead in
Dissent that he ended up. Publishing
Hey wait a minute this isn't even a real case
What's the time
Anything that involves manufacturing a case
Fomenting litigation
All of those things were
Illegal to not just unethical but actually illegal
Yes
Criminally illegal
Sienna's
Something like how we see ambulance-chasing today the lawyers for the n-double-acp were very aware of AC
And this came to a head in the 19th
ICP
Wanted to get the court to end segregated
Basically they wanted
To overturn Plessy versus
Ferguson
And the way they were doing this
You know they needed a plaintiff so the way they were looking for plaintiffs is going to
Meetings with parents and sort of
Quietly in a subtly trying to ask
Parents if they wanted
SOB's cases
Virginia knew that they were doing this
And they tightened up these regulation
It said you know you can't
Drum up litigation to try to stop them from doing this
So the n-double-acp
Sued
And they took this issue all the way to the surf
Tesla
It's essential
Because
No matter how illegal it is
Maggie's the Supreme Court said
Actually
Manufacturing litigation is
Is a form of political expression
Really
And it is totally okay
Like free speech basically
It's a way of
Expressing your
Teskey's litigation exploded
After this in the 60s and 70s a lot of other movement
The women's movement Poor People's movement
Saw the success of civil rights movement was having with these strategies that they adopted them is
And now I guess I'd include that blue
The founding principles
Of the Civil Rights Movement
Have been embraced
By the vast majority
Noah's founding principles
Those founding principles
Guide
These laws
That
Basic fundamental
Guiding principle
The Civil Rights Movement
And how it needs to be apply
Today I am.
I can't say what I think of that on Family Guy
Family Radio
That that is that is not that is on
Fmovies not
Carrying the standard forward for a civil rights in America
Bailey says he is actually doing something good
Deeply important to our political system
Cycling I see a lot of people who
Who agree with
Adblue
There they agreed with him in a way that can't be expressed in the polls
They're out there
I'm this is one way for that again that's another
Call back to the Civil Rights bill
When you have a minority pocket
The blazing sun
They just get trampled
In popular elections okay
But do they still have a voice should they still
Should people have a way
I'm to not change on their behalf
/ the will of the majority
Again
Textbook what quarter
Supposed to do
To look out the rights of minorities political
I'm more than a method of a racial or religious
And see that they are not being trampled by a majoritarian attorney
A bloom is helping a minority of people who believe what he believes
Yeah I'm so not prepared for you saying any of this
This is really surprising to me
Kitty Catherine Wells sincere thanks to her for 40 use two segments and Elie mystal are legal editor more perfect
Please find me Chatham rod with Tobin low Kelsey Padgett and Susie lechtenberg will take it from here
With Soren wheeler Elie mystal David Herman Alex overington Karen Duffin Sean rameswaram
Captain Wells Barry Finkel
Any Mills Dylan Keith and Michelle Harris special thanks to deal Carpenter his book flagrant conduct is all about law
Lawrence versus Texas thanks also to Lambda legal Lisa Hardaway JD Doyle Ari Berman Amy Howe and guitarra
Supreme Court audio is from Oye a free law project in collaboration with the Legal Information Institute at
At Cornell more perfect is funded in part by the William and Flora Hewlett Foundation The Charles Evans Hughes Memorial
Foundation
And the Joyce Foundation