Hi I'm Robert krulwich Radiolab is supported by Casper
Check out the cast
Or the wave mattress providing support of comfort for every body type
Visit casper.com Radiolab
Code Radiolab at checkout to get $50 towards select mattresses
Terms and conditions apply
I'm Robert krulwich Radiolab is supported by audible so as we begin this episode of the bad show check out the blank
Slate by Steven Pinker one of the world's leading experts on language and the mind go to audible.com
Radiolab or text Radiolab to 500 500 for a free 30-day trial and a free
The audiobook
Are you awake
Radiolab WNYC
Okay here we go ready Robert
Jad abumrad Robert krulwich I feel like we haven't you and I sat together and said her name's and quit them
Because you because Molly's been in the chair series
You haven't heard it yet this is a kind of a rush through to sex reproduction what makes boys boys
Girls girls and the Infinity of gray spaces in between
And now that we're sort of just on the other side of that
We thought that maybe the as is return to Corner ourselves we should refresh
But even that sort of way
I mean it's just one of those things we've been bringing back shows that we think are just vibrating
Still in the world so at a time when there are people all over our country and other people
All over country and thinking she's bad
He's bet your bad I'm good you're bad there's a there's a lot of black and white thinking happening right now yeah and so we've
Decided that it's time to go back to something we did once upon a time when we were wondering
About good and bad we did a show called The Bad show start asking me questions like what makes a person inherently
Good or bad is there a way to
Explain why some people act the way they do and others
The little bit of bad that is in all of us and he's really really bad that is in some of us
Yeah hello David
Yes hello
Who's that oh hi Pat
Let's begin with this story from our producer pack
That guy
Okay so I heard this one from this guy named David was David
Redbus2us
He's a psychology professor at the University of Texas at Austin
And this particular story comes from a book that David wrote
Can you just
Just tell me
The little
Story that you
Begin your book with
Okay yes
This is
One of the things that
This is one of the things that spark my interest
In the topic of murder
The whole thing happened several years ago
I had a very good friend another professor at the University and I used to socialize
With him and his wife and one evening they were throwing a party
And invited me over and so I went to the party party was already in full swing when I got there
I walked in and asked his wife
Where this friend of mine was
And she
Got a disgusted look on her face and said that he was
Up in the bedroom
And so I went up to the bedroom
To find him and he was
And in a rage
In a rage how like you walk into the room what would you find
Well he started he started fuming that his wife head
Had distemper
And what did she do she expressed
Disapproval about his
Clothing choices
She made fun of a shirt or something
But did it publicly in front of her friends
So it's kind of a he felt publicly humiliated
And while David sitting in the bedroom with this friend the guy looks up at him
And he says
I'm going to kill her how did he say it like quietly or like truth is
Keith and I'm going to kill her
David
Always known this guy to be
Pretty mild-mannered but he is a
A large
Very strong
Man with a black belt in karate I knew what he was capable of
So I suggested that we go out for a walk and I basically spent the next half hour away
Walking around with them trying to cool him off but eventually he did
He just
Calm down
And you go back to the party then in like
Continue
Dinner partying
For a while yeah I did good too
Yes and he did too
And then
He seemed
Fine
When I said goodbye to him he seemed calm and
I left and went home
And it was
Several hours later in the middle of the night that I got the call
And it was his friend and he says, I come over and sleep on your couch
I don't leave my house right now I'm going to kill her he was in this
State of Fury he said an in instead of
Hitting his wife he smashed his fist into the bathroom mirror and
Then realized that he had to leave the house or he was going to
Do damage to her an event so he says that in your like
Okay yes
Come over now like
Yeah
Exactly
Meanwhile leave it at night on the other side of town his wife
Went into hiding
Literally disappeared for 6 months and didn't tell anyone where she was because she was terrified that he
He was going to kill her
This story made us wonder it is David's friend
Easy unusual
Or
Does everybody at some point have something dark in the
Just tiptoes
Justin Time
Yeah
This is Radiolab today
We're going to get
This is a bad show
So you asked why do people do bad things
Relaxing me to be bad anyways like how do you tell the real Baddies
From the rest
Snap timer
Omron automatic Radiolab
The bad show
Back to back
Okay so
What happened to David that night with his friend
I'm really curious about murder and Badness and all these things were thinking about
But it wasn't until a few years later that
He weren't something that
Really put what happened that night into contacts
At this point David moved on to a new University and he's teaching an introductory psychology
And I devoted one
Class session 2
The topical
Homicide in white people
Kill and
I designed a little
Questionnaire
Where I simply asked the students
And I've have you ever thought about killing someone
And they would Circle
Yes or no
Then he wants some space at the bottom
For them to elaborate
If they said yeah
And you know the class ended and I went back to my office and I just
Sat at my desk and started reading these
And I was just
Astonished
Define page
After page
Of yes
And not just yes
But these very Vivid
Descriptions
About who they would kill
Where they do it
When
The precise method
How many of them went into that kind of detail
I would say
75 or 80%
Wow
A little bit like horrified like oh my God my students are murderers
Horrified as I was
I was pretty stunned
And so
I
Expanded the sample where we asked about five thousand people all of the world
Singapore jeru the UK that's in question have you ever thought about killing someone
91% of the men
Said yes in 84
Percent of the women
Said said yes I've thought about killing
Yes
If any
A sizable fraction actually acted on their homicidal
Can I see the streets would be running
Running red
Yeah but that's the
Actually seemed like
But here's one more than just fantasy
From
A woman
Sure okay this is a 20 year old female
We asked who do you think about killing
She said my ex-boyfriend
We live together for a couple months
He was very aggressive
He started calling me a w**** and told me he didn't love me anymore
I broke up with him
Then a few months later he started calling me trying to get back together but I didn't want to
He said that if I ever had a relationship with another man
He was going to send videos
Of us having sex
To all the people in my University
The thing is
But I do have a new boyfriend but my ex boyfriend doesn't know it
That yet
And I'm terrified
But he'll do what he says
Then suddenly the thought occurred to me
That would my life would be much happier
Without him in existence
And then she said I actually did this
I invited him for dinner
And as he was in the kitchen looking stupid peeling the carrots
Make salad
I came up to him laughingly gently so that he wouldn't suspect anything
I thought about grabbing a knife quickly and stabbing him in the chest
Repeatedly until he was dead
I actually did the first thing
But he saw my intentions and ran away
I went to ask how close she came to killing
She estimated
60%
I don't think I've ever had a fantasy that
That anatomically specific Ryewood
See the part of the other person that I was going to say
Forever
Planet like that well
Have you ever been blackmailed away this one
No no one is ever sent about a s******* that I've ever
So you don't know it is a fair question to ask
What are the conditions under which you
Premier any of us
Baidu
Thanks I think they have to be extremely extreme
Well know how my lighter.
You know what the sex brings us to our first stop of the Arizona
Just to set it up Robert I'm going to give you this piece of paper here
What is this
Edward Paris read these words that use these words
Nice day
Fat
Mac yes
Sad
Face what are the soft hair I don't know what this is
I want you to commit them to Memory
Give me some the memory you know and your finger and I'm going to
Little electro-jazz finger clear-air
Give me a paper bag
Already comes up
So I'm just going to go in
What what
I'm not ready for this
To the best of your memory
Which word is mashed with knife
Okay I'm choosing
Job
Wrong
Actriz de 285 volts
What did you just do
Obviously no need to be alarmed that was not a real shock we were just in acting an old
Great famous experiment that may have heard that was May 1962
Done by this guy an experiment is being conducted in the elegant interaction laboratory at Yale University
Stanley Milgram talking about the experiment film in case you've never heard of this
Probably happen Katie heaven
Create a bunch of subject or subjects of 40 males between the ages of 20 and 50 normal everyday dude
Subjects ranging occupation from Corporation presidents to Good Humor man in plumbers near am through something like
But you and I just would have each subject sit down at a table
Front of this really impressive looking machine
Machine had lots of switches on it
Any other room there was a guy who he called the learner who is supposed to have memorized some words
Everytime that guy got a word wrong that you just did
Volunteer was instructed to shock that guy with higher and higher voltage
The volunteers couldn't see the guy he was shocking
They definitely run
Yoakum staged the whole thing like it was some experiment about memory and punishment but of course it wasn't about that
Continue play is that how far these people go how many times would they shock that salve
Sap in the Next Room just because they were being told
Guy yelling of course was an actor in the shocks weren't real but
The questions in the air at the time were very real
This is the moment when human cruelty was on trial
Quite literally
When I stand before you judges of Israel to appear
And I knew I met you
I do not stand alone
So Stanley Milgram actually begins these experiments
The same year that I don't like man goes on trial
For Nazi war crimes
That's radio producer Ben Walker it'll be our guide for the segment and in the trial
When the prosecutor is essentially
Ask him how you came to
Commit genocide
He would say over and over again
My personal affair
I was just
Following order
I had to do what I was ordered
It's this defense
This is basically what Stanley Milgram
Set out to test
285 volts in a lab at Yale University with a bunch of regular American
Like is that something at Universal or just 10
Eichmann think he figured maybe 1% of these men would keep flicking the switches
Up to the highest voltage but
That's not what he found
65% were willing
Shock their fellow citizens over and over again even passed when they were screaming and
Even when they stop screaming when they were maybe dead
You won't answer me or nothing
Please continue go on
They continue talking there
Corpse
His experiment remains one of the most famous experiments of the 20th century
1962 Stanley Milgram shock the world with his study on obedience it is still trotted out to explain
Everything from hazing to war crimes what is there in human nature to gang Behavior
Allows an individual to act in you mainly genocide it's like a downloadable from the internet
Instant defense doing wrong but
If you look at milgram's work Coast
Like this guy did
Alex Haslam professor of psychology at the University of Exeter
A different picture
Well maybe that story is being told
A million and one times for the last 50 years we just got to get together now what you need to understand about
Haslam is that he hates it when interviewers
Only want to talk about the Baseline study
The one that everybody knows the circle Baseline to 65% 1
Want me to talk about
Yeah so there's more actually he studied between 20 and 40
Different variants of the same parody
Stanley Milgram took electric shocks is very seriously
He did this experiment a bunch of times and in a bunch of different ways
Change where the Shocker in the shock ESAT
Women participants she had an experimental he wasn't a scientist it was a member of the general public and everything
Scenario produced
A different
Results
Really yeah
Let me get me. I'm just in front of me I just got the
Did they see from the middle console images
I mean solganik the Baseline study is the one where 65% of the volunteers go all the way
Highest dose
Text but an experiment number 3
If they put the Shockey in the same room
What's the shocker to the Shocker can actually see the person that he's talking about 4
40% in an experiment number for when the teacher has to hold the Learners hand down on a plate and Order him to feel
It drops to about 30% wow
Experiment 14 if the experiment was not a scientist but is an ordinary man not
Wearing white coat constructs to
20%
How low can we go okay here's another one experiment 17
You and those two other participant both actor
If Lowe's to participants refused to go on like saying I don't want to kill a guy
Under those circumstances got one experiment 15 experiments who's giving you
Use instructions that he put two experimenters in the room and they start disagreeing with each other at least this one you got
0% going
0 in that condition you said zero
Not a soul
Exactly 0%
Well alright I'm starting to feel a little bit better about my fellow man
Hey hey hey
Okay
Where is he
Mom in the closet
Closet cuz this room is echoey
And you know there's nothing like
A closet full of clothes to like how
Bounce It Out
You see it's just in that one experiment that 65%
People are willing to go all the way but in all of these other scenarios they don't
And even when they do say yes even when they go along with the experiment
As you can see in the film
Woman
They struggle continue using the last witch on the board
No answer
Please continue the next Warriors White
They have
Debates with themselves
Please
Debates with the experimenter
Sometimes an experiment requires that we continue
Whether Lerner likes it or not we might what's interesting is that how all of these struggles all of them
Please continue play out the same way it's the experimenter
Frothing the Shockers along
For me it's all about the prods
This is what totally pulled me in
Story
Ron Stanley Milgram had
4 script
Prods that he wrote out for his
Experimenter
When the subject didn't want to continue
Yep the first one was
Please go on
Continue play
And if they
Didn't go on if they resisted
Experimented with breakout Prada number
The experiment requires that you continue
ASAP. 195 old Innes they still were resisting or struggling they'd get Prada number three
It's absolutely essential that you continue
Absolutely edible but you can't a little bit more direct
The critical. For the critical. Is an absolute order 4th product is
You got no other choice
You have no other choice teacher
You must continue
That is definitely in order exactly
But everytime the experimenter pulled out the fourth Broad
And this was confirmed when the experiment was redone in 2006
Total disobedience
Disobedience
Anytime the experimenter said you must continue
The Shocker would say
Hell no I don't
You got no other choice.
I have a choice I'm not going to go ahead with it
Well I have to discontinue the experiment that
I'm sorry
Here's another one
We have no other choice you must have a choice
That is if you don't continue what we're going to have to discontinue the
You'll have to eat this cut it out after all he knows what he can stand
That's my opinion that's where I'm staying on it
How so
The subject seemed willing to shock another human being but as soon as you say its in order they don't do it
Now that's important is very important because
If you ask University undergraduates what does the Milgram study show they will invariably say something like they showed the people
EBay orders
Well actually the one thing that the study really doesn't show is that people obey orders
And it's a pretty big thing to Mississippi
Do it if it doesn't show the people are
Just
Obeying orders
Yeah and what does it show
Okay I think it looks just like this
I was going to instructions
We will begin with
The participants of Avenue in the study
Which pair of words are very Poolesville very credible hycite is scientist a scientist Institution
Who is going to do this powerful piece of science
Say sit down in the chair thinking wow
It's really important
I'm about to help this quest for knowledge
I really want to do
No snow in life lots of things that we do that worthwhile doing and not always easy
And you find yourself in a situation where you've got to do something that's hot like shocking an innocent stranger over
If you think that's the right thing
If you think that song says worth pursuing you say okay I'll go along with this
Seriously near shocking these people because they thought it was
Worthwhile
Bryn Athyn
This won't just blowing the bead and sorrow you tell me so yes sir no sir three bags full set
Are engaged with a toss that trying to be good
Participate
Are you all right
But trying to
Do the right thing
They're not doing something
Because
They have to
But doing it because I think they ought to
All the difference in the world
I want 220 volts
Something I said I see a darker interpretation the original absolutely darker as they are doing it no question
They have the agency they think it's right on someone will they know it isn't
Chilling comparison with choose a speech that him like I visited SS some SS leaders
About to come it's arranged for choices he's me so this is what you're going to do is cause you don't want to do this okay
Cool nobody wants to be killing other people we realize this is hardware
What you doing is for the good of Germany in this is necessary in order to advance Noble
Cause
So then anyway I'm almost done
Give me two more minutes
2 more minutes so in the Milgram case
Haha
With the idea that people will do bad if they think
It's good
The good noble cause what's the noble cause in this case science
You can see this in the surveys that the men filled out
After the experiments were over exactly what was on my mind at the experiment
If the experiment had to be successful
Had to be carried on
The questionnaires they filled out are part of the Milgram archives at Yale
Willing to help and worthwhile experiment
And it's
Kind of surprising a lot of them are really positive even though they've just been told
But they were
Duke research in any field is a must
Herculean this
Do you think that more studies of the sword should be carried out definitely yes
We as as up on Lucas to the study we have this going to go to like
So vision is like what what course what they're doing is wrong
But if it looks I'm from another person
Active there's a sense in which you could celebrate what they doing I mean I'm not suggesting but I'm just saying
These people are prepared to do something that's very painful to them until someone else
Because they want to promote Sons
You know you can see that's a good thing
I mean cuz it's like we started with this experiment that we all
See as
Evidence of humans
Latent
Capacity for evil
Yeah tell us a casino under some circumstances we don't do the bad thing weird
Because
Your other flip we don't have to be told exactly hate being told but we will do it on our own if we think it's good
Yeah now you're saying actually these could read that
That very dark
Fact as being actually evidence of something quite
What if you dress to happen if you just had some on your parents the Paradigm you could presumably making as make this out these of these are people who own kind
Emmys the fact of course at the administering pain to a stranger that's what a horrifying about it but I met you
Already will I have to administer shocks themselves or something good
Then we say these are people already believe in something isn't this a good thing that we have people in our society
Who are willing to make sacrifices full of great the greater good
Tony and where do you come down do you leave this experiment in a light mood
Or in a dark mood
We're close to some really fundamental truths about human nature
Onion emojis by human nature as it affords infant potentials for loneliness in dog
Lots and lots of lessons and that one is I think you know when you're enjoying to do something for the greater good maybe I'll do some
Question
What is greater and what is good
Now that right there slap some quotations around that
I think stupid Walker whose podcast he has a podcast that's a good one it's cold
Too much information yes awesome thank you Ben and also thank you to Alex Haslam professor of psychology at
University of Exeter be right back
Benjamin Walker and here are some Radiolab credit
Alfred P Sloan Foundation enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern
Www.
Hi I'm Robert krulwich Radiolab is supported by all the
As we continue listening to the bad Show episode on human nature our neighbors and ourselves check out the blank
Slate by Steven Pinker
Available on Audible the blank slate follows one of the world's leading experts on language and the mind as he
What is the idea of human nature
And it's moral emotional and political coloring
So go to audible.com Radiolab or text Radiolab
To 500 500 for a free 30-day trial and a free audiobook
Hi I'm Robert krulwich Radiolab is supported by Caspar as we continue listening to the badge show on
Nature in our neighbors and ourselves
Check out the wave which mirrors the natural shape
Body or the Casper mattress with Zone support for your hips and shoulders for better alignment
You can be sure of your purchase with Casper's hundred Knight risk-free sleep on a trial
I can get $50 towards select mattresses by visiting casper.com Radiolab
And using Code Radiolab at checkout
Terms and conditions apply
Ig321 hey I'm Jared I'm run I'm Robert krulwich uses Radiolab and today
Evil
Although
I don't know if that's the right word
Cuz it said if
Can you call someone you will then you're kind of done with them but there's been a fellow
I've been thinking about him for better part of the year as you felt such a puzzle to me
I can't
Quite
Please him though it's very fun to try
And I heard about him
From science writer Sam Kean
Fritz Haber so so so could you just like
When did he live and what did he look like in math
He was
Doing his his great science work right around the
The twentieth century so right around 1900
Very distinctive-looking man
Bald on top
Trim nice mustache
Wore a little
Business is that how you say it
Pince-nez with one of those very tiny old-fashioned pair of glasses that would pinch on your nose
And he was someone who had very big ambitions
Just put that in context
I'll bring a few other of our storytellers in Breslau Germany that's Fred Kaufman which is
A fairly small you know the smallest sort of town and
So does Clara
That's right Albers wife-beater later right Clara comes in the same town and they're both secularized Jews this
The moment in German history says when Jews
Had a decent amount of Freedom then this is the difference between Kaiser Wilhelm and of course Hitler's Germany
Dan Charles historian his was the first generation when I Young
Jewish boy could truly imagine that he could just be a regular part of that Society
He could do anything
And believed it
Fast forward 10 years for toddlers professor
Small University
It's working with chemicals about 1881 of the central issues facing Germany today
Bedtime
Germany
Has a problem
A big problem
It has enough what they used to call them solar energy, energy from the Sun to grow crops to feed
About 30 million people
However that leaves behind 20 million Germans do you mean they're looking at 20 million people
Going hungry
That's what we're heading towards
I'm yet to remember it during the
During the Crimean War in the 1850s
York Stars
So around the turn of the century for German scientists like Hopper this was the d challenge he is he wants to feed he wants
The feed Germany
Next you this wasn't just a German thing
A lot of people are beginning to worry that with about a billion and a half
People on the planet
The maybe we were maxing out
The Earth couldn't support this many people
And everyone we know the solution yeah we need a whole lot more of one simple Ella
Nitrogen nitrogen nitrogen nitrogen they needed more nitrous nitrogen is an essential part of amino acids
And proteins
We stick a seed like weed seed in the ground what are the reasons it grows is because it's sucking up all the night
Nitrogen in the soil make it cell walls without nitrogen
You don't have life
Now of course you could find some nitrogen out in the world natural deposits would be like seaweed or
Cow manure or
Poop valuable and actually two nations in South America went to war literally over bat
You can say people work
Crazy by the way that's reporter lots of Nasser
Everybody was desperate for sources new sources of nitrogen to make the problems even more annoying
The most common source of nitrogen is in the air around us
It makes up
Out of every five or so molecules
That we breathe so it's very a lot
Yes 80% of the air
Yes nitrogen atoms
So all the nitrogen you'd ever need
What's right there you can't like throw that are onto a plant they couldn't.
Deploy it mean they couldn't capture that's right and I'm part of the problem here
And although once again we're getting a little ahead of ourselves we'll be right back The Hobbit way I look
Is that is that nitrogen is
Trivalent
Triphase prevalent in other words nitrogen
Is really strong attachments
To itself what he means is that when nitrogen atoms are
Is free floating in the air they will
Cling to each other
Distill nitrogen atoms will
Beardslee hold together and it's almost impossible pry them apart his calculations show that it couldn't be done at least not with her
Tremendous amount of energy
Like
Yeah yes but you know
Being ambitious
Harbor start stinking
In order to do this
We need to R
Pressure this we need to put it under a lot of
Pressure
So we start experimenting you figured out a way to take a lot of air
It's filled with these little nitrogen bonds cleaning to each other and pump it with big iron
Under extreme extreme pressure at high temperature
Get in there and number chemical reactions and
What happens is that your elbow in the months in nitrogen apartment cell
And then forcing it to bond with a Hydra
In a new way
When hydrogen and nitrogen bond together
Thing you get
Is ammonia
A liquid
Is captured the nitrogen
Right out of the air
You literally get
Adrift
Drip
Of ammonia
It is it is
Arguably the most significant
Scientific breakthrough
Of the ball
Bread from the air was the phrase
Does Hopper have figured out a way to take nitrogen
From the air
Put it into the barren ground
Grew wheat
This has allowed
The world
To have 7 billion
This is what's driving the world towards
12 by 2050
Now we're seeing about a hundred million
Cons of synthetic fertilizer
Produced industrial each year
And that tonniges then moves into our
Food source
Our food source that moves into our bodies
And the rough statistics are that
Half of each of our bodies
Contains nitrogen
From the haber process
No she really
And so in 1918 fitzherbert gets a Nobel Prize
But this is my
An interesting guy
Around the same time
Officials in the US.
Oconomowoc
Alright just back up once
After hybrid nitrogen
He was promoted
You know he takes over the leadership of this institute in Berlin and he starts hobnobbing with a whole different level of society
That stand Charles again mean it's a pretty heady thing for you know Jewish kid from Breslau
To be
Hobnobbing with
The emperor
And cabinet ministers
He's part of the club
A really really relished
And not just cuz he was vain which everyone agrees he was but
Because he loves his country
Did you love the Fatherland and he loves Germany
So when World War 1 begins signs up immediately sends a letter volunteering for Duty singing
Process that I used to make
Food
Well I can use that same process
Explosives
Because the thing that you put into the ground to grow more food is also the thing you can explode to make a bomb that's correct
Cause
It takes such energy and
Pressure to separate it
Trivalent bond is so strong that when it comes back together
That energy is released
You could be used
Life
In any case
Back to World War one trench warfare it gets bogged down
And harbor has an idea
It goes straight to the German High command
Any any pictures
I danced as well
We can drive those enemy soldiers out of trenches
Gas
Chlorine gas
The front
And when the when the wind is right
Will just spraying the generals were not
All that conventin now they didn't like it
A lot of them are like this is not how you fight a war
Play clean dirty
Unsportsmanlike
Organizes
Soldiers he organizes whole gas
Units in WW2 ask
Text command of them partially travels to the
Front
And on April 22nd 1915 1915
Hobart finds himself in a little town in Belgium called
Why pressed Americans
Whatever you call it Arenas on the Western Front
Germans run one side the French the Canadians in the British on the other
And they're behind the German lines is
Rrr friend a frenemy
He has a potbelly he has these spectacles is chomping on a Virginian cigar
He was always smoking cigars and he's wearing the fur coat
But nobody had done what he was about to do on the scale that he
So basically at 6 p.m. on April 22nd
When the wind was just right here
Hopper's gas troops
Unscrew they open the valves
On almost 6000 tanks
And painting
Flooring
That's like an adult blue whale of
Lori just trying to imagine that is that like a
Green Cloud the cloud and then others describe it as just kind of
15 ft
Wall and hugging the land and it just sort of approach
And it's moving at about one meter per second
According to some accounts has it crept across no-man's-land
And the grass was
Turning to the color of metal Birds
Fall from the air
Within minutes gas reach the Allied side as soon as it did
Soldiers began to convulse they were joking
Hundreds of them were falling to the ground but what is a guest doing to them exactly I think what it's doing is it
Breathe it in its irritate your lungs to the extent that they sort of filled up with fluid so quickly that you sort of drowning
Phlegm yellow mucus
Frothing out of their mouth those who could still breathe would turn blue
This is a description of hell
Yeah but Harbor saw it as a wonderful success and wished
Wish that the Germans and better prepared to exploit
Because he felt like they really could have made
Terrific
Advance
If they had
Had more confidence
And
He is celebrated
You get promoted to the rank of
Captain and he goes home for
Today's a hero
But
When he gets there
He has to contend with
With his wife
Clara immerwahr
Clara also from Breslau off
Also from a Jewish Family
And also a scientist
Unusually so in those times she was actually a genius herself she was one of the first women
To earn a
PhD in her country and shortly after his
Return Clara
Allegedly confronts him
And says
You are morally bankrupt
Could you but hey birb just kind of ignored her and
According to Legend
He actually threw a dinner party
In celebration of the big sick
Invited his friends over
We don't actually know if you threw a party but I consider that apocryphal Dan doesn't think so but what's clear
Is it he said no reason to question what you done and that infuriated Clara
Especially because she found out he was
Leaving the next day to direct more gas attack
And they probably had an argument that's historian Fritz turn to also happens to be for toddlers
Got some they had a
World more than that scholar fight and later that night after party
Hubbard take some sleeping pills
Sleep
And
Takes a service revolver it's Havas
Pistol walks outside to the garden
And
Pull the trigger
Choose Yourself
In the chest
And is found by her son
By her son
Yes age
13 I think
Anything directly
Still alive
With a life about to run out of her
Harbor
It's unknown what happened
For the rest of the evening but it is
A well-documented fact that the very next morning on schedule he goes back
Leaving a son
Alone
With this
Dead mother
Cold
Yeah
Heartless
It was a terrible moment did he run away
Was it Duty the sun eventually
African immigration to America
Kill himself
Seen around this point I just don't want to have anything to do with this guy this is a size want to take a shower
Yahweh
YouTube
You on the other hand if you look at the Grand calculus people he's
Helter fad versus people he's killed them he's got that billions of people
I don't know that you could entirely call him back I might even till towards
Saying
He's a little good
To be honest you wouldn't though would you really would you really think that this guy's a good guy
Honestly yeah just because
The mathematical summing up
We're talking billions of people he's standing there on the front pushing the gas into the lungs other human
Beings have smelly it's a war but still
Then he goes in and celebrate
And then walked away from his child and his wife dead in the garden and his tank more of that please
Tasteful about
Factory was too into it
But I do think on some level you have to divorce the man from his deeds and you got to ask
Is the world better with him or without him
I think you got to answer it with him
Right
Well
Judy Cohen story
Yeah
The same what happened to this guy after world
He actually was very humiliated that Germany had lost
And especially humiliated over the fact
That they had to pay enormous War reparations to other countries
So he decided he was going to invent a process to
To pay for these preparation
By himself
And what he decided to do is go into the ocean into seawater
Which contains
Very small levels of gold bites you know over the entire ocean there's a lot of
Gold
Dissolved into the
See he's been 5 years in a futile effort to distill gold from the ocean's Waters
Sounds insane
On the other hand
He wants to do it he was trying to repeat this masterstroke needless to say he fails it was actually a crushing blow
Prayer for him and then
Things really take
1933,
And Hitler takes over
And one of the first
Ax
That
The Nazis do is to basically issue an order that says there shall be no Jews in the civil
Full service car was Jewish
Because it served in World War
He technically would be exempt
But 75% of the people who work for him at the Institute
They were Jewish and they would have to be dismissed
So
He decides to take a stand and says this is intolerable I'm going to resign
He says that he's not he's always been hiring people based on how smart they are
And not
Who their grandparents were
So he sends a letter to the Ministry of Education resigning
Any leaves Germany
Telling a friend
He felt like he'd lost his homeland
And then
He starts this
Period of roaming
He eventually goes to England
But in a famous incident one of England's leading scientists
Refuses to shake his hand
And he is basically homeless
At this point
You know he's a man adrift
Meanwhile
His health is failing in 1934 he takes a trip to Switzerland to a sanatorium that before
We can get there
Heart fails
And he dies
Now there's a footnote
Siri
Strange
I got a little
My advice is my dorsal here stood up whenever the end
Right so during World War I
Hobart Institute had developed a formulation
Of insect
Killing gas called zyklon
Zaycon
Which was originally did the pesticide once again another night.
Compound it was developed in his Institute
He knew about it
In fact his chemist had given this particular pesticide is smells it was a warning
So the people didn't inadvertently breathe it in
And get sick but after the Nazis takeover is after he died
They
Reach back to the shelf and they find us as icons
And they asked for to be reformulated to take out the warning smell
And it becomes zyklon-b
The Killing gas
Of the concentration
Did members in Highbridge family died in the concentration camps
Members of his extended family dead certainly friends of his dick
Does something
Deeply deeply
Wounding
Dressing
Upsetting
It's a thought
Did you get anything to do
What's a plan B
But he did
The use of it
It never match
So
How do you feel about him now
Because
And I can't help it feel bad.
Despite the chlorine gas like he didn't intend for
For that.
He could have never imagined
Battle
What is part of me
Says you know
Here's a guy who just wanted
Do everything better than it ever been done
Whether it was
Feeding
Killing more
Paradox
But
He doesn't with a kind of
Immoral athleticism Noah
Without humility without
Without a lot of doubt
It's a crap
But it's a crafts with crayons
And to approach with kind of crazy Joy
I don't know I would rather have scientists
Carried out with them as they proceed
Maybe it's all about doubt in the end
Thanks to all our great storytellers
Dan Charles Sampson lot of Nasser Fred Kaufman and Fritz Stern
You find out more information about all those guys on our website
Radiolab.org
Alright my name is Josh and I'm coming from Harlem New York Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred
P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of science
Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloan at www.found.org
Thanks
Hey I'm Jared I'm Roberto witches Radiolab and today we're talking about well we're trying to
Think about what goes on in the mind of a bad person
What makes a bad person so bad that he's different from the rest of us
Any kind of agreement with The Hobbit
Craigslist
But you know this question around
Different people
And oddly enough we came and got a really interesting take on
Trunature bad news from the sky James
Shapiro
Professor of
English
At Columbia you
He said to start you want to know about bad
I'll give you back in Titus andronicus there's a character by the name of Aaron the Moor
Play where Aaron gets up on stage looks at the audience and says
Let me just tell you the kinds of things I've been up to Reese
Set daily energy between two friends
Make Poor Man's cattle break their necks
Set fire on Barnes and he Stacks in the night and did the owners question question with the tears
Oft have I digged up
Dead men from their graves
And set them up like at the difference door
Even
Even when the Sorrows almost were forgot
And on the skin is on the bark of trees
Have win my life with my knife
Carved in Roman letters
Let not your Sorrows die
Though I am
Tilly's bath
Here's the interesting thing
Cody James he's not the baddest
In Shakespeare
Because ultimately the play offers up a reason
For his nasty that's the reason why he's telling all the stuff is because
He has cut a deal
They will spare his son
If
Key fashion shopping
And tell them what they need to know so
Is a way in which is a touch
Spark of you mad
Just a little glimmer
Pieces
That's what people want it
They wanted someone who is really thrilling me bad but in the end
Was redeemed of it
Yeah this wasn't just a theater think no cuz if you couldn't afford a ticket for placing all the plays in the 1500 you could always go to
What public hanging can you go
How much the same reason
No States if you're convicted male felon
You are
You know stronger
But you're not allowed to hang until you die
You cut down before then warning this next part's a little graphic
Then the Executioner
Castrates you
Cut you open
And takes out your internal organs and then separate your head witch
Opposed
But even with all that Gore and horribleness
There was often a moment
The people waited
Anyway we wait for it still even now we want what Elizabethan Scott
At the scaffold
Which was
A confession
Before the guy is
How to shred
He's allowed to confess
You know III Harley you know
Regret the fact that I kill the young Baden or
Defame the king whatever it is the expectation is
Somebody is made to make his peace with his maker before
He dies
That's what you do
That's what Shakespeare did and all his plays
I would give all his bad at least one more
Where they can be understood
Except this one time
So will I
Interrupt
He's a soldier he works for a general the general's name is
Hello
You're supposed to be Chums but
General Othello has no idea that Iago
So he plans to destroy Othello and we don't exactly know why
There are hints of reasons like maybe he thinks a fellow sleeping with his wife or not sure
Weird thing
Is it
Not to take down a fellow but
Everybody
Lie
He stirs up hatred between friends
Between lovers even scheme against his own wife this is just somebody who's performing
BrainSurge
Without anesthesia
Other people
He's a master
And as for why maybe
A fella was sleeping
With Amelia
But as the play goes on you begin to think that maybe that's
Just another lie eventually Iago convinces a fellow that his wife has been disloyal what she hasn't
Identity logos and kills his own white
Smothering her with a pillow this is Jess
At tsunami
Aviva
The past
Through the play
In the very end of the play when
And find out what day I go
Fellow asked
Why
Why did you do this
Iago
He refuses
What
We fully expect and what everybody on stage at that moment
Fully expect
From him
You know what does he say
Demand me nothing
What you know
From this time forth
I never will
Speak word
I'm not saying a word
I'm not going to give you what you were
I'm not going to give you
I am not going to help restore the sense that there is a more order to the world
Animal Noir
What you know
You know
If this is the singular moment in shakes
Spirit he gives you a
An understandably evil
No motifs
No reason
Any idea what the hell he was in
Contending
What you know
You know
Meaning of any idea which was in his mind was he trying to make a commentary
You know damn it good iago's make you want to shower the middle
Sur
Thank you to James Shapiro whose most recent book is called
Contested will
You know what
Yeah well I'm left thinking those like if you could somehow mean that would make believe
Pizza Hut get a real Yago in the room
And subject that person to questioning
Really get the mixer to fess up as to why they did
Would that make a difference
We should say that this next section of the program has some references with your
Extremely graphic and not to everybody
Kids
In the room maybe this is
Come to go faster
Yeah
It comes to us from
Text me to
Alright so who is this guy Bergeron
Jeff Jensen and he's a reporter in LA and he wrote this graphic novel that I write about
One of the most prolific serial killers
In USA
Gary Leon Ridgway
The Green River Killer the first victims of the Green River Killer were found in the summer of 1982
Terrorize Seattle in the 1980s in Seattle today a man called The Green River Killer Ridgway murdered at least
49 women suspected that it could be upwards of 75
Making him the most prolific serial killer in American history all the victims were prostitutes he buried them or
Is there bodies in these little clumps in the woods
And in January of 1984 the Green River task force was formed and my father was recruited the task
Jeff wrote this book because his father Tom Johnson was one of the lead detectives tracking Gary Ridgway
He ultimately spent 17 years searching for this man in December of 2001 my father and his colleagues
Make the arrest DNA testing match them to the crime they arrest Gary Leon Ridgway and
On June 13th 2003
Gary was secretly taken out of his jail cell and brought to
Is there a very nondescript
Concrete ugly office building
And over the next 6 months
From June to early December
Who is Thomas job to get Gary to open up and give up the few details that they really needed to link him sir
Probably all these crime
Today's date is June 17th
Your 2003 the time now is early 36 hours
So every day they would bring them into this conference room
Nutrition of an interview with Gary
Take me on Ridgeway
An interrogator
Remember since we last talked
I got those all at night mostly
But remember
Picking her up at
It immediately became apparent that there was going to be difficulties
Things you would obscure he would dance around things he didn't really want
To everything that he
I got to tell you
I'm not
Only comfortable
That you're providing all the information
Especially
When it came to one particular fact
What my father and his colleagues know
Is that
Something was done to these body many of
After they were
Deceive is he saying what I think he's saying
Necrophilia
Gary is dancing around this time
Gary had denied this to his own lawyer
So
My father
And the other interviewer in that room that morning detective John Matson
They start
Are you using
Illini attactive of interviewing him that was very
Stunningly
Shockingly empathetic
Thousands people.
Not the first one
You know you're not the first person as ever done this
Could be the last
You won't be the last
That's one of the things
We need to know
Fathers trying to like a reach out to him
I know it was more than
It's okay to admit it
You need with me
It's all right
It's one of the things
Afternoon
And
Oh yes I did lie about that
I went back one time before 9, so that I
Like I said
This is a major breakthrough
So handsome
In graphic detail
And it gets even more disturbing for my father as the conversation suddenly pivots to another victim
No close to me
By the name of Carol Christensen
3 * 2 *
Rings represent example of a of a woman that
He actually had strong feelings for
You like to see
As it happens my father has very Vivid memories of investigate
Eating the Carol Christensen
Speaking with Carol's mom
Carol's little daughter
Kill her she was
I knew she had a
Daughter
And so
Alaska Gary starts going through this narrative
What he did
Carol
The last time she was
In a hurry
She like was allegedly in a rush
And like it kind of like
Hurt his feelings
When says bye meme
Make me mad
Very much in a hurry
Remind
Killer
A choker
With my alarm
And
Play killer cared for me before bed
Up until that point
Gary refuse to say
That from the minute I pick these women up
I wanted to kill them
He claimed
They're in the middle of a sex act
Distracted
Something would happen
I need a kind of went crazy
Kids snack
Almost like blaming the victim
And my father
Wasn't buying
Backups
Russell Becker
But the fact that he kept on doing it over
Over and over again was like come on
Been through this
What time is before in
I already told you
You knew what was going to happen
Done this how many times
And I'm 10 15 20 times
You know what's going to happen
Like
If you go in this
Knowing full well that could end up in her death
And Gary just
Yes
That is true
I when I pick them up
I was
Finally acknowledged
Yeah
There's a possum
My father just says
Why
Why did you do this
And that was a question that haunted my father
Protect
Why in that wine that one simple why that he a scary there was a lot of questions you would ask
Why did you inflict all this suffering on them on us why did you take these women off the streets and wanted to
Sweet wine
And
The answer
Is
Unsatisfied
Yes I didn't need to kill killer because
Wait what
I just need
Because of
Then he just
Trails off
To kill because of
That's it
Did you know
Want to kill him
I just needed to kill them
In that moment
My father
He stands up and he says
Text me
You touched me Gary
Touch me
We're going off to eat now
Turn on 24 hours
On June 17th year 2003
He walked out of the room
And just started
They spent the next six months
Interrogating him they brought in psychiatrists in forensic psychologists to try to get an answer Gary's
Because I needed to kill a Niger why and he says because of the rage and we'll why the rage and because women have stepped on me all my life
Well why can't you deal with it and then normal way each answer
Just beg
Another why
And even though in the end they got him to confess to these 49
Murders
They never really get any closer to an answer
Then this first one
That afternoon
He gets in his car
Goes home
Vines my mom
On
The deck
Sits down
Next to her
She says
What happened today
My dad's
And to this day there
If not talked about that day
And he hasn't talked about it
With anyone
Until
I interviewed him
For the buck
Why is it
So important you think
The understand
Why
Behind
Such an evil eye
Haunts me about the why question is that I'm reminded of like one of the oldest stories in the Bible
Stream Joe
The story of Jobe is that one day
Don Satan
We're having a conversation
And they're saying
Have you checked out Jobe
You know I'm really proud of Joe he believes in me and you trust me and so much
He has such great faith
And Satan is like my I bet I can change his mind
Associating basically
Systematically
Destroys job's life
Takes away his wife is children all his material possessions what follows but this ongoing conversation between Joe
Open his friends about
Why does this
Why does God allow this to happen
Only then
Does God speak up and kind of say
Like you're going to question me like you no more you
My point is
Sometimes
When we ask
Hawaii
In the face of profound evil
I kind of wonder
If what we're doing
Is that weird earring guy
And I think what we want out of the Y
Why is
Meaning
Meaning to life
To reveal itself
In a way that restores
Ordering gives
Is Hope.
All of this isn't just
Meaningless
Jeff Jenkins book is the Green River Killer a True Detective story it's a graphic artist Illustrated now
Thanks also to reporter Erin Scott for that store
This is Radiolab thanks for listening
Hi this is Lauren from Winnipeg
Radiolab was created by Johnny Depp andrada and is produced by Soren wheeler Dylan Keith is our director sound design
Maria matches RVD light is our managing director our staff includes
Simon Adler Maggie bartolomeo
Becca Bressler Rachel kuzyk David Cavell
Bethel have t
Tracy hunt
Matt kielty probably Robert krulwich McEwen Latif Nasser
Donald Adrian whack Pat Walters Webster
With help
Kashima O'Leary Carter Hodge and Liza Yeager are fact-checkers Michelle Harris
Because facts matter
Hi I'm Robert krulwich Radiolab is supported by Casper
Check out the Casper or the wave mattress with a support system that mirrors your body shape
Get $50 towards select mattresses by visiting casper.com Radiolab
And using Code Radiolab at checkout
Terms and conditions apply
Hi I'm Robert krulwich Radiolab is supported by Audible
Check out the blank slate
Book by Steven Pinker one of the world's leading experts on language and the mind
Go to audible.com Radiolab or text radio
The lab to 500 500 for a free 30-day trial and a free audiobook