Ouat
Northern listening to Radiolab
Radiolab WNYC
When was Teletubbies first
Auto Bethalto
Davis Radiolab on Chatham rod
Today we're going to share with you a story that we did a few years ago on her sister show
More perfect
Here's why
Couple weeks ago as you may remember
Attorney General William Barr
Announce that the US government was going to begin
Executing federal prisoners again
Last execution was in 2003
Indiana and the Attorney General said
The us is going to start doing it again after a quote
Two-decade-long
It just so happens over it more perfect
We believe this was the first episode ever of more perfect we did a deep dive into
How we execute
People
And
Given the 8th Amendment
Whether or not we should
I like a good time to bring that story back
So here it is
Comes to us from reporter Karen Duffin
And starts with a mystery
Alright so we're starting with
Maya Wright Maya Maya
I am the director
The death penalty team
Reprieve
Okay so my afoa lives in London and when she was about 25 she had graduated from college
She was doing some theater things but she was like having this
Quarter life crisis and didn't know what to do with her life was called boil order but I Central crisis
Please can I be useful to you volunteering at a place called for pre legal organization that
The death penalty cases for they like a bunch of lawyers or what do they do
See they've been working on the death penalty for like years at that point to try to abolish it
I view the death penalty and I
Beautiful at the time instead of the shop ended
Series of
Societal Injustice
Tony Macy's at reprieve
One night this is 2010 I was sat in the office
She sitting there one night and Clive Stafford Smith who's the president of reprieve or the head of reprieve
Calls and says.
Execution tonight
The execution in Arizona tonight
For killing Chester Drive
Which found guilty of strangling and stabbing
In 1989
The client says there's an execution tonight and we just found out that the lethal injection drugs that they're going to use
It came from a pharmacy in England
But we don't know which pharmacy because Arizona refuses to release
Is the name does anyone in the office have some time alone to have some time to figure out where this trucks could have come from
She raises her hand she's like I have 30 minutes you know
I didn't know
What I was starting when
I started
Supplier like why does it help them
What the drugs that they want to use an Arizona have to be FDA
So they can find who made these drugs and prove that they are not FDA-approved and they can probably stop there
Execution do they have any reason to think the drugs weren't FDA-approved is kind of a Hail Mary
Also
I started the half-hour research task it is taking me now five and a half years
I was trying to figure out with
Limited information
Where sodium thiopental could have come from in the UK to get to the US
Sodium thiopental is an anesthetic and for a long time it was one of the most common anesthetics used in surgeries
Is also one of the drugs used in lethal injection
I was so
I didn't
The puppets full reset that I was doing but I was doing it very quickly
Execution last night
Is running out of
Time
And option
It was I was in the UK so
The evening morning Arizona time we had
Number of hours
She's like frantically searching
Medical regulations
And you know she can
Figure out exactly what the name of the company is there's no way to know at that point But ultimately she does figure out that there are
No UK
Companies
Authorized to ship this drug to the US there was no effect Aveeno FDA approved supplier of
Stop whatever this mystery Pharmacy was
It probably wasn't FDA approved
And I remember
Can I email that over I think we had the time to intern affidavit
From me or from 5
They write up a quick affidavit they send it back to the states and
The execution that night
Twist
Stayed
Mike halter
When I went to sleep having stayed and I just thought
You got a bit of time
Next morning
Workout
Couchsurfing
Send someone's
And I turned on World Service Center
Been announced that Jeffrey landrigan
Was executed at 22
26 hours
Yeah
His final meal
Was
A piece of steak
His last words were
Well
I'd like to say thank you to my family
And Boomer Sooner
It turned out well Maya was asleep
The state of
I filled all the way to the
Quartz and late yesterday
The justices by 524 votes
Lifted the stay of execution
Allowing landrigan tube
Be put to death last night
Was put in place due to concern over
Lethal injection drugs one of those drugs obtained from Britain was not FDA-approved but the US Supreme Court
Did rule
That there was no reason to believe that the drug wasn't
Nash up about a rude awakening
Is that rude awakening with
Send my on a journey around the world it would get her called out by the United States
Supreme Court and it would Spark
A global conversation about the American death
Am I felt a little word cruel and unusual
Are embedded in our 8th
Supreme Court of the United States
Autumn United States
United States
Dairy bacteria
The we were in London with Maya who just learned that Jeffrey landrigan had been executed but to understand which
She does next me just give you a little bit of context
In the fall of 2010 when Jeffrey landrigan was executed
The drug that they use
The lethal drug sodium thiopental suddenly in really short supply
Is the only us company that still made that drug was having like a manufacturing problem so they had stopped many
Factoring
Producing this tribe
So you actually see these emails between states like dude you have any sodium thiopental
From right next door
Arizona agreed to lend California a cup of death
And there's actually someone great email exchange between like the California Department of Corrections they send Arizona
Thank you email writing and I quote
You guys in Arizona are Lifesavers go buy you a beer next time I see you
You're a lifesaver at come on
Yeah so when Jeffrey landrigan is set to be executed Arizona is out of that drug
And this is how they end up at this mystery Drug Company in London
So after the execution my is doing all this research she's calling Pharma company on to these documents
And very quickly she learns that the same company that is sending drugs to Arizona accent drugs till I can buy lots of different states
South Carolina Kentucky California and various other places
They actually become one of the primary suppliers that we've won Jackson Drugs to the United States
Tell me again why was it so hard to find out information about this company
So what happens is that anybody involved with an X
Excuse and your name is kept confidential
And states have started keeping companies names confidential to
So next she starts calling suppliers and
Distributors
Like how did the
This drug get to that company thinking that maybe that'll later to it we had figured out
It had come originally from
I was active ingredients made in Austria
Some of those with sent over to Germany
The package put into biles those were sent over to the UK that was one company that had got the marketing with citation
There's also another one that company chasing then
They were sent
Company in England
But you still can't figure out the identity of
But then the real breakthrough came to
Couple months after Jeffrey landrigan was
I think it was a lot of material coming out to that time I'm going to California and the ACLU got a bunch of documents and in one of the
These batches of documents
She finds an invoice
And this invoice
I just
I just remember getting the court documents and I was
I was walking with this internet connection she was actually in Malawi at the time
Perfectly willing the computers down at the document so I could stop even looking through them
Figuring out
The stuff
And those with the document
That had the
Name of
The middle
What was it
Dream farmer
Dreamfarm
Dreamfarm dream farmer
Okay
So
She's in Malawi Sochi
You know brings up her
Calling in sick can you go just look at this place in West London
And it's this residential area but also like with
Sort of warehouses
China middle class you have
A couple of petrol stations a couple of cafes and then
Des Pharmacy
Except that it doesn't look like a pharmacy
Because it's got a big sign on the front that says
Algon Driving Academy
I am no
On the Dog House TV
El Cajon
Driving Academy
This is Nina. She's a freelance producer in London
It doesn't look too good if it's the
Tiny little storefront
I don't see any of the dances
Driving and if you walk in
Hello
You walk in and the frontage
Justice reception area
But in the back
Hi
I'm underneath the dreamfoam
Is that you high
I'm rooting for the guy sitting at a desk
His name is mehdi alavi he's in his 50s
Gray feathered hair going to play
Square glasses
What's a little bit like William Hurt
She is dream Pharma
In other words
The company that is helping prop up the death penalty system in America
It's a one-man operation operating out of the back of a driving
School
One guy
I thought
This can't be true about the
Injections
That you supplied
Do snakes
From the get-go
No comment.
And I still have no
Oh
Aspen
What was it like for you
Are you still
Supplying
All right
It wasn't illegal at that point
Alright then it became illegal
Got this car
It would you mind me asking how you can get involved in that
How they came to find you and you'd find that
They found me
Ashanti
What how
We surprised when they
Prize
I guess the unraveled some more
I've got no friends
Oh thank you very much
Felicia
Enjoyed walking around.
Yeah I got what you want
So now
Irrelevant
Irrelevant to you
You're not into business
Irrelevant
Well thank you very much for make sure
You know my name if not find
The once Maya and reprieve found that guy mehdi alavi and his pharmaceutical broom closet
That's the next step was pretty simple went to the UK government and they told them because in the UK it's Ali
Legal to be part of capital punishment in any way
We have a dual sport
Edge products
For the facilitation of capital punishment
Regulation and deregulation
The fight against the death penalty
And
When they realized
That the sole purpose of the ex
Sports of this drug
Was
Executions they put an Xbox controller
And just like that the supply of this drug
Turned off to the states are
Just out of luck
Well I mean 60% of Americans support the death penalty
He said that they're not going to give this up
Without a fight
And so
Over the next few years you have like this arms race Missouri says we're going to find the drug in Germany so
Migrants to Germany
And then she hears that a company called hospira is about to make the drug in
Italian government
Really didn't want drugs made in the seat of the Pope
2 p.m.
Dyspraxic you expressing said we cannot take the risk that we will be held liable by the
Italian authorities if the product is diverted for use in capital punishment
And then
Denmark
Bunch of stage of Florida Ohio Alabama 11 other states they all decide they're going to get their drug from this company called
Meijer
Remember my first cool with that she's like I'm did you know that your drugs being used in x
Houston they were like what
Richard Leakey
Play Shoot surprise for all of his vice president for communications at Boone
We have been in the farm industry for a little more than hundred years
And we are here
To shave
People's lives
Dishwasher complete orbit
Offer
The intention of
For this product
Amaya says that she heard the same thing all over the world
Even when States like Nebraska and South Dakota go to India to get their drugs
Interesting in India because
India have capital punishment
So this isn't an objection.
The punishment
This is
From every company has spoken to a ninja
They say
Why
Why would they use medicine
Like if you're going to kill someone just
Kill them
Why are you using something that saves lives to do it
And actually there's a really interesting story about why we do it that way
So what is the answer to life
Why do dancers that goes back to this guy named Bill Wiseman
It's a terrible thing
To have one's
Reputation B&B based on on
Coming up with a noob
Way to kill people
Bill Weisman was a rising star
Back then
He loved
Wiseman died in a plane crash in 2007 and this is him in an interview with reporter named Scott Thompson
Nkotb in Tulsa back in 2005
What is what
Spell story
So he grew up his dad's a minister is Grandpa's a minister and he's like I don't want the family business and he want
First four years he buy his account wonders 3 like 2 and 1/2 literature degrees he becomes a poet
He drinks a lot of corn liquor and you know he finally end up in construction where he starts working with politicians and he's like oh
This is my calling I want to be a politician so he gets elected to the Oklahoma State Legislature in 19
1874 end
Opposed to the death penalty and luckily for him this to just happen
Supreme Court
What declared the death penalty unconstitutional today and spare the lives of six hundred men in death row cells across
What's the country in 1972 the Supreme Court actually abolished the death penalty
Cuz they said it was being applied unfairly herb
Haphazard
In a way that could only be called
Cricket
So Bill Wiseman is an Oklahoma Legislature and he's like
Great this is not a problem we'll ever have to worry about
The problem is the public is furious about this decision
Support goes from 50 to 63% in just two years
Absolutely I
Very much in favor and favor of it we get some Law & Order into this country.
I don't think I should have taken away in the first place and almost immediately 35 States rewrite their death penalty laws essentially saying like
We can do this right
End in 1976
The Supreme Court says
All right
If you can administer the death penalty fairly and humanely you can have it back
So 9072a death penalty abolished 1976 it's reinstated
Bill Wiseman get selected smack-dab in the middle of this
So you know 1976
Suddenly
There's a bill in Oklahoma State Legislature about whether to reinstate the death penalty and bilhah
Have to vote on that
I know
The capital punishment
Interested it doesn't work doesn't
I couldn't see any way to justify I also knew
Terrified voted against it from my district
I would
Run a high chance of getting whooped
Cuz 80% of his constituents were in favor of the death penalty
All that wondering
20 found this job that you love
Last time I didn't want to get whooped so I was
In a real dilemma
What you do
The wrong thing
Devoted to reinstate the death penalty
For whatever reason
Ego or vanity or need or the motivation to get reelected whatever the reasons
I knowingly made it
A decision
When I know is wrong
And ice
Who's in the legislature and he's feeling like he just sold his soul
And as they're debating various amendments to this law someone brings up something sort of vaguely about a more humane
Anyway to execute people and he's like that yes that
And he becomes obsessed with this idea
I was like a way to assuage his guilt
Yeah so he brings up some anesthesiologist and doctors and says I want to find a better way to do this and they say we can't help you cuz the
Hippocratic Oath Do no harm death
Is a little bit of firearms 3 goes to the State medical examiner a guy named Jay Chapman
And Jay just sort of like freestyles has one line that that bill
Literally just sits with a yellow legal pad and rights word for word it should
I'm an intravenous saline drip should be established
High-end which be introduced
Hey
Ultra short-acting barbiturate
In combination
Michael paralytic
The idea is that these three drugs would allow them to execute people but but painlessly
And right there in that office with just like
Does yellow legal pad
They invent lethal injection in America
It's it would be
Hard to overstate just how important this
Moment in this offices because
The supreme court of justice
Given the country back the death penalty on the
Grounds and the idea that we could we could do this right
And what bill has just handed America
Is is it a way to have the death penalty but but how to be humane
The ideal death metal
Yeah
Oklahoma adopted and then the very next date
Texas does and then dozens of states and
Since that moment
88% of all executions
Baidu
Injection
I don't hear the word lethal injection or execution or anything else without
Feeling a tug
It's tied to me
I mean I'll always be
Which he live to regret he thinks that he actually extended the life of the death penalty and he actually eventually quit
This job becomes a pastor and becomes a very
A strong anti-death penalty
Advocate
How does a man
Who came up with the recipe
For lethal injection
What does he do on judging
The same thing everyone else does
So ourselves on the mercy of God
Say that way
Have done wrong and where
Nothing that I find really interesting is that if you look at the Modern lethal injection cocktail
Three drugs affect drug special needs Society II drug paralyzes you
And the Third Reich is the actor that stops the heart in
Kelsey in this drug cocktail you kind of see everything that we want and need from the death penalty just kind of all
Together
The third drug that stops your heart that's kind of our sense of justice
The first drug the anesthetic
Kind of our sense of humanity or kindness
That second drug
The one that paralyzes their muscle
I told the second draw
Is purely cosmetic
It sucks
No medical purpose
The reason it was put into the lethal injection cocktail in the first place was
So that
It's the first truck doesn't work effectively
The second drug will mask any signs of
Visible suffering and it would be extremely significant
Because potassium chloride
Potent acid that people have described as being like fire going through your veins and beings
Bentley from the inside
She said just imagine that that's happening to you
But something is wrong with the anesthetic and you become conscious
You have this
Burning acid going through your body
And you're paralyzed all your voluntary muscles are paralyzed
So you can't say
I'm awake I can feel everything this is agony
She says that it's that second drug that is both the thing that could make the execution most torturous
And the thing that meant that
Tweed Witnesses reviews
Public
Wouldn't know that it was torture
Because we weren't supposed to know that
Two does she end up going after that second Reich the paralytic no actually seek she goes after the first ride the anesthetic and it's
A total coincidence this is just
The one that had manufacturing problems with starter
The arms race
But it turns out that this drug
Sodium fire
The anesthetic is the one that's
The most constitutionally important Drive
Because in 2008 when the Supreme Court ruled on lethal injection they said
The first drug is necessary to prevent the prisoner
From experiencing severe pain
So there's no anesthetic
There is pain
Which would be too severe and then be there for what an Eighth Amendment violation
Cool unusual punishment exactly
So that drug the anesthetic is the key drug
But over the past five and a half years is Maya has like Wacom old her way across these different companies
She just made it harder and harder to get
There now 20 + companies
Who have they said we disapprove of the misuse of medicines and executions and we're going to take steps to prevent
And that has States scrambling the drug use and it's 32 death penalty States or now
Running out they have run out of drugs and it's a result of what you've seen is that things have gotten very DIY
I'm trying new procedures never used before in the history of execution
Prison officials are in a difficult position
Human have the DEA start raiding prison
Their Central using illegal drugs at this point until reporters are just starting to pay more attention and
In the middle of all that he began kicking his feet lifting his head in his chest off the gurney grimacing
How do you also get
Seems like this
High Country cast season in and a couple moments he actually mumbled
He would open his mouth and you'd see his chest move and we'll go all the way down to stomach so so clear gas
April 29th 2014 in Oklahoma a man in Clayton Lockett was being executed for murder rape in
Kidnapping Lockett execution used a new drug combination whose source is unknown he was sedated and declared unconstitutional
Conscious but
Started thrashing
Clenching his teeth and start moving the arm
43 minutes to die
Risley horrific spectacle
Happening after an hour and 57 minutes
Your situations like this in Arizona Ohio this drug formula is unconstitutional because boobs
Started filing a bunch of lawsuits and one of these eventually got to the
Supreme Court
1479 55in interesting Lee when it got to the Supreme Court
Honest about what's going on
Things got very tense
This is Justice Alito
Is saying essentially
Actually a problem you made it a problem
Executions could be carried out
Actually there many jurisdictions
Their jurisdictions in this country their jurisdiction
By the Abolitionist Movement
And this is Justice Scalia
So that the states cannot obtain
Vote to Other Drugs
And now you want to come before the court and say well
It's not 100% sure
Is it appropriate for the Judiciary
To countenance what amounts
To a guerrilla War
Against
What you think it means by Guerilla War
Thank you
Trying to say there are ways to 2 if you want to make the death penalty illegal you have ways to do it
You can call your legislator you can pressure them think about
The law but you're trying to like hide in the trees and like pulled
Drugs off
And
Make themselves scarce
That you're forcing
Illegal problem that doesn't exist
Without you answer to the question
You've been interrupted
Does justice has called you guys out kind of
Yeah
It's
Look into this a lot of narrative around this being
Thriller activity
But this is nothing to do
With me or anyone else
It's that the companies
Don't want that medicines ucinet
Executions the manufacturers that Distributors the pharmacist anesthesiologist
Whoever else it might be the Indian industry
None of them has to be positive
Ohio capital punishment machine
Listen to an argument to be made here I mean I get what you're saying that like all these different people in different countries have been like unknowingly
Grafted onto Ohio sex
Execution team which doesn't seem fair but is there an argument to be made that like
Even so
The effect is that she has taken a death penalty that is
Kind of Humane Maybe
And made it more cruel
Because that's kind of the accusation in the air
It's
I'm going to say two things one of them throw away
She didn't cause it she's the states are chasing the companies and she's chasing the states right so like you can't say that
She caused it but what you more importantly what you also can't say is that it is actually more cruel
Because
There's no evidence
That there's been an increase
Christen Bachelor
Executions what I think is happening is just that we're paying
More attention to Lisa Lynch
Tonight we're just
Looking at it more
Oh you mean like a
Bosch excuses been happening forever and we're just now noticing
Yeah
Nonetheless people do accuse her of making this more cruel and not just because of
The drugs
Because
States in their sort of desperation to
To still be able to do this are looking for other ways
To do it
And some of those ways
Might seem like we're going
The lady that was
Spearheaded they getting rid of the injections all she did is basically force people to be shot
This Paul Wray state representative house district 13 Utah
He says one day he was sitting in his office
I was actually listening to the local NPR station and federal judge in Oklahoma is
And they were talking about European pharmaceutical companies used to provide this controversy
Drug but now refused to sell it to America
Do prisons have the European drug companies no longer selling the drug cocktail
So I called our department of corrections and says hey do we have access to the drug and they said no we don't
How you know we have a set amount and then we're out
He says he hung up the phone did a little thinking a little bit of research
Kind of deep into the history and
Eventually
Came to the conclusion to the firing squad
Play me like firing squad John Wayne firing squad like line up against the wall know it's like they have a chair and they bring the
Person into the room and they strap them to the chair they put a hood over their head physician will look at the heart and I'll pin a Target where the heart is
And then there's five men with rifles and one of them had the blank but none of them know which one it is
And they all shoot the individual in the higher
Doughmakers in Utah supposed to bring back executions by firing squad
What is Lethal Injections are not readily available already says he was just trying to solve a problem
I was completely taken off guard by the media frenzy that
That half of cruel relic of Old West Justice International condemnation
Adopting it now is an embarrassment of barbaric
Bob Moses
Why is it that the
Do you think the
The firing squad itself
Created thesaurus
Well it is
It's brutal
You know it's it's certainly not the easy
Give him a couple of injections and
They quietly go down
You know this is calling it for what it is
In fact
I would argue you want to look at
At something that's more Humane and you definitely the firing squad
What caught my attention
Was it it was so sudden so quick
Boom boom just like that he's our reporters talking about witnessing at firing squad
Houston and Utah
It was over
Pretty quickly it was cleaner than I expected
And it was fast
With the firing squad
Yeah your ear dead Within
The seconds of the pulling the trigger
Bible is directly to the heart
It's over
Not the paralytic that hides its is done
Body can be removed
He moved a little bit
To some degree that bothers me
And that seemed to carry on
Alaska
This is how you tie his chosen to solve the whack-a-mole problem
Has already been upheld by the Supreme Court approved
Electrocution
We have approved
Death by firing squad
That's Justice Scalia in 2008 the Supreme Court actually approve the firing squad in 1879
And the people who were part of the firing squad are actually volunteers
Do you have a
Lack of volunteers are in abundance of volunteers
Nobody's forced
Todoist
You know they're there are people that are willing that big Tennessee is their civic duty
Setting of the help carry these out
I'm always down there I actually asked Paul
I really want to talk
Talk to a volunteer
If you put me in touch with somebody who's
Actually been involved with the firing squad
Okay
I wait till this thing
16th and Hill Air Force Base bombing range right I like it the sound of Freedom this is Kenny we agreed not to use his last name
Weekends Dad ran the firing squad for a couple of deck
So as you see there's two cottonwood trees over here those old cottonwood trees made setup
And that's what they would drill the firing
Squad app
These men were selected because for one there
Absolute Marksman
They just had moral clarity.
They
Many of them did not want to be on there but once
They were called
They felt obligated to see it
Ken told me that on
Keisha days he died and the other Shooters they would sit down together at the kitchen table
Family breakfast
His mom should make coffee and
She would do scones or biscuits and gravy and she wanted those men to know
That it wasn't easy and that she appreciated him
I know there was a lot of prayerful times around the house and nose
Mentor over getting ready I know that
Ian
It's pretty solemn moment I prayer
Is it for the person Phoenix
You did the victim with the
The prayer I think you have to pray for strength
The follow through on what you have to
I think that
You know you might need a little guidance and you might need a little understanding and
And something bigger than yous out there
I think that if we're going to have the death penalty people just have to understand that there's some savagery involved in it
And nah
It's unfortunate
But it is but
If we have it to do list
Let's do it let's do it humanely
One of the things that I found kind of striking is that
Maya foa is against the death penalty in Europe
The folks in Utah that are for it
But everyone seems to agree that
We shouldn't fool ourselves favors the death penalty but one thing I've never favored in some common ground between
When me and the abolitionists
Is that lethal injection is a terrible method of x
Execution
That's Robert blecker at a New York law school Professor sounding a little bit like Maya
But he says he objects to lethal injection not because it's cruel not because it might cause pain
But because it certainly causes confusion I attended
An execution in Florida
Bennie Demps
And I also was with my father-in-law when he was in a hospice dying
From an incurable and very painful
Cancer
And the death scene in both
Situations was
Bizarrely similar
In both cases
Served
The person dying was
Lying on a gurney with an IV coming out of his arm
Wrapped in white sheets
Medical technicians at his side
Surrounded by loved one
And it struck me as bizarre
That we are killing Those whom we love
In a fashion
That's so nearly resembles how we are killing those we rightfully
Detest
There should be no resemblance this isn't medicine this is
Punishment
The firing squad
Is honest
And acknowledges
Itself
For what it is
I want objection to the traditional firing squad
That Utah uses he says he doesn't like the fact that one person get the blank and that nobody knows who that poor
Person is that to me is symptomatic
Of our failure once again to take responsibility for what we do
Nobody should have a blank
If we cannot face what we're doing
And acknowledge
Then we shouldn't do it
And we may be coming to a moment where we are about to do that to it look at this and acknowledge
Because
In 2014 in a case that was really just about lethal injection just as viruses look like
Stop
Just talking about the details I questions about which medicine that we use
Eight more basic question
Weather
In other words what he's saying is
It's time to talk about not just like the mechanics
So what we're doing
But whether we should even do it at all
Reporter Karen Duffin
Now when Justice Breyer said that in 2014 he was in The Descent but a lot of people
Heard that statement as kind of an invitation like Briar saying to the lawyers of America
Send us cases about this up next level conversation with a brother and sister
Team of dedicated their lives to studying the death penalty and they'll tell us when we can expect that next big case
Whether or not Spring Court might ultimately Force the country to join the rest of the West
In abolishing the death penalty once and for all back in the moment
Hi my name is Santiago Fernandez from Madrid Spain
Whittier Alaska supported
Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of science
Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloane at wwd
I'm glad this is Radiolab we're back with our story from more perfect
About the death penalty which were we playing
Because of the attorney-general's recent announcement
I just a moment ago at the conclusion that second we heard Justice Breyer inviting cases about the death penalty up to the sky
Supreme Court saying basically it's
Time for the court to revisit the question
Constitutionality
At the time we first reported this we wanted to find out a little more about that
What exactly does that mean when will it happen when might it happen I should say
What might it look like
So we set
Reporter Sean rameswaram out
To look into that
What are you to stand on the death penalty
Guess
I figured I'd just ask and we found two siblings actually who dedicated their lives
Studying capital punishment in America
I'm Carol steiker I'm a professor at Harvard Law School
Earlier in my career I was
Law Clerk
For justice Thurgood Marshall
For him Jordan also collect two years later
My name is Jordan steiker I'm a professor of the universe
City of Texas School of Law
And I'm the direct
Picture of the University of Texas
Toccoa Falls camping
Punishments
And you two are related
We are most people think we're married but in fact we're brother and sister
How do I exact but most people think you're married to your brother
We have a great line people often ask us how we met
And I say our parents brought him home from the hospital
I wasn't very impressed
So our story
Starts
With
This execution
Being halted
And then eventually being resumed in what sounded the middle of the night it's happening like after hours
Satf prison
How is it that the
Supreme Court
The most
Vaunted and in our nation
Deals
Local life or death
Last-minute calls at all hours of the days
Is
RBG on call all day and all night.
Everyone knows now
The US
Supreme Court
Is the last
Stop for a second
Execution
That's just a
Fact of life
When we were Locklear
On the court
Late 1980s
We would stay until late in the evening it was the job of
Whoever.
The clerk was in each Chambers
Who was
Responsible for that
Mycase
Just stay in Chambers
Until the case
Made it
To the court and was either
Stayed or
The Condemned with x
Okay there was
Prominent
Clerk in the
Clerk's Office
Of the Supreme Court who is known as the deathclaw
His job was to keep track is to keep
Keep track of all of the death cases that are coming to the court
Their execution date
And to stay in touch
With the attorneys on both sides
Do we think a death clerk gets paid more than a regular clerk for having maybe the worst job in the building
Good question don't know the answer.
Okay
I'm curious where are
Current 9 Justice
Is come down
On the death penalty right
Evenly
Split the train
Justices
To just a quick note obviously that conversation happened a little while ago
The story of Justice Antonin Scalia passed away
Justice Anthony Kennedy retired
To New Jersey
This is her now on the court Neil Gorsuch and Brett Kavanaugh which means
Course the court looks
A bit different
When we check back in with Carol
She said that while she thinks that this court is much less likely to strike down the death penalty
She still thinks that given recent events in States like
California
We're Governor Newsom recently stay all X
Executions
There is
Still a general movement away from the desk
Carol also pointed out that while the Attorney General's announcement may seem to be pointing Us in the opposite direction
There are only six federal prisoners on death row where is in California
That stay of execution
Applied to more than
Death row
We do think
That the death penalty will eventually
Be struck down as
Unconstitutional under the 8th Amendment
Simply because the way the court has thought about it and the cases in which has narrowed the death penalty recently
So that in the last 15 years the Supreme Court has said that people
With intellectual disability
Can't get the death penalty that juvenile offenders
Can't get the death penalty
That people who commit interpersonal crimes other than murder
In these cases where the Supreme Court has
Constrained
The scope of the death penalty
They made it clear that
The analysis involves considering weather
The practice
Violates evolving standards of decency
It seems like
The death penalty is on a collision course
With the Supreme Court's
Eighth Amendment jurisprudence
And it's close court-watchers and
People have service clerks in the court
Yourselves
When do you think that case
Coming
It's hard to say 2 years ago many people thought then when that when justices
Breyer and Ginsburg
Signed on to that $0.02
They were signaling that the time was nigh and that there were
Perhaps five votes
On the court why else would they call for the court to take this
Issue up
Record
Not A legislature
Bacon
Cruel
And unusual
Punishment
And
With a specific constraint
Set the Constitution imposes
Process
Namely
Through the 8th Amendment
In the two years since there have been many opportunities
Is for the court to do so
And it has
So that suggests
That the time is last night
Court watch
I thought it might be 2 years ago
We also think that the one major difference
This time which makes it so much more likely
At the death penalty will eventually be abolished
If the extent to which the United States
Stands virtually alone
In a few
And retention of the death penalty
Among
Western democracy
All of our peer Nations
Have
Jettison the death penalty
And it's not
The outlier status is more remarkable than that it's not just that we're the only Western democracy
Say to retain the death penalty
We're still one of the world's leaders in executions even with the
Decline and executions the United States were
In a very small Club of active
Executing countries
Along with countries like
Iraq around China
United States is really in a very
Small group of Nations that
Uses the death penalty
An irregular way
Seabright who's a anti-death penalty lawyer for most of his career is quite well known
He used to joke that in 1970
If you would ask anyone in 1970 which of the following three countries would be the only one
That would still have the death penalty at the turn of the millennium
Russia South Africa
And United States
Yeah nobody
Would have picked the United States
Bread in the 1970s
Only sixteen countries in the world
We're fully abolitionist
By law
Today more than 2/3
Of the countries in the world
Are abolitionists by law
Last I heard 60% of people approve of the death
Is that true
Well depends on how you ask
The question the Gallup polling organization
Has been asking people the same very simple
Question
Do you support the death penalty
Kiefer murder
For almost a hundred years
So it's easy to compare you're comparing Apples to Apples
And
Support for the death penalty is around
60th percent now
Which is down from 80 something percent
In the early 1990s
But if you ask
The question in a different way for example if you ask
People whether they support the death penalty
Or life without possibility of parole
I see you got very close to 50/50
And if you ask people
Whether they support the death penalty or
Life without parole
With a
Prisoner working for restitution to the victim's family
Support for the death penalty drops below
It's one of the more striking
Figures is the number of states that have legislatively repealed the death
Penalty
In recent years so seven states
Passed repeal bills
In the last
10 or so years
One of them Nebraska really the only Red State to do so
Brought the death penalty back to a referendum procedure last November
But the fact that it's Republican legislature repealed the states that pain
And then the Republican Governor veto that repeal
And then the Republican legislature overrode the governor's veto bike with a two-thirds majority
Is a pretty striking indication
Of change
And public attitude
So what do we think is change
I think there are a couple of things that have accounted for the decline in public
Support
One thing that happened in the 1990s with there was a
Growing awareness
Of wrongful
Write the decline in violent crime
The 1970s and 80s
An extraordinary Rising
Violent crime in the United
Stay tuned.
That trend has reversed
Took some significant extent
And I also think that the concern about
Ordinary crime has been displaced Abid
I concern about
Terrorism in
And other threats
Better
More X
Existential than ordinary crime in the United
It's also been the case that
Because of the Court's intervention the death penalty the death penalty has become
Extraordinary expenses
Yeah just
Put a figure on that
If you look at how much
The state of California
Has spent on a death penalty
Trials appeals maintaining death row
And you add that money up
And you divide it by the 13
Situations that California has
Has carried out
In the last 40 years
You got a price tag
Of more than a quarter of a billion dollars
Rice serious
Did you give everyone in America knew that we'd still be a 60% it's kind of hard to imagine
What you could do
To address legitimate concerns about
Crime and Public Safety
With a quarter of a billion dollars
Other than execute another person
I think it's important to realize that in
All of our Pure Country
Is that abolish the death
A majority of the public
Supported the death penalty
At the time of abolition
The
Support for the death penalty in Western Europe
Tell only after
The abolition
Have the death penalty
Not before
But those countries have much more
Parliamentary procedures
They're more insulated from populist lawmaking
And they tend to defer to Elites
And to expertise on criminal justice
The policy
The other
Truly extraordinary exceptional
Facet
The American death penalty in the modern era is that
And I think most people my age I'm 32 I was born in the 1980s
I feel like most people my age don't even really know
Is that we got rid of it for 4 years
We got rid of it actually for longer than that
Because the litigation that led up to the case Furman versus Georgia that abolished the death
Penalty
Brought the death penalty to a halt for five years
Prior to that ruling so there were no X
Secretions in the United States
Between 1960
87 and 1972 when the Supreme Court abolished at
524 again
What's the death penalty
Justices Brennan and Marshall
Unusual
They would prohibit
Entirely
Wouldn't go quite
He said the death penalty
More than half of
And then there were no executions
Between 1972 and 1976 when the Supreme Court brought it back
And then the first execution after the Revival of the death penalty was actually Gary Gilmore
Who volunteered gave up all his
Appeals
Wanted to BX
In Utah in 1977
So there was a ten year period 1967 to 1977
In which there were no executions in the United
What's the longest.
You guys
Site were alive in that. Some of it all of it
Children but we were alive
I mean thank you very much you're welcome so curious I mean
What was that like what was what was in the air then and
Was it just a fight to bring it back the whole time or did it
Free
Criminal justice reformers up to worry about
Overpopulation of Prisons or
The sword
Prison industrial complex in this country did it
Did it make the country function better in some way or was it just a really bad I mean
The moment
At which the death penalty was
Spend it
Was
One of the most turbulent moments in American history
It was
You know right in the wake of
Violence of the late 1960s
That brought that swept Richard Nixon into
The presidency
And his promise was to restore Law and Order
There was
An enormous
Political backlash when the Supreme Court
Struct down the prevailing death penalty statutes in 1972
So even though it was a. Without X
Profusion
It was not a. Free
No pro-death penalty
Agitation impact it might have been
The most extreme. A pro death penalty agitation
Because of the perception that the Supreme Court
Was taking away the
Best power from the state
Anythink
If your
Hypothesis Bears out in the
Supreme Court
What does abolish
The death penalty
In the neck
10 20 30 40 50 years
Do you think it will be gone
For good
This time
I do think that this time would be different
Last time when the Supreme Court abolished
And then four years later blinked and brought it back
It did so in a way
Of saying
Well
These new statutes look like they're going to fix
Some of the concerns about arbitrariness and
Discrimination and lack of adequate
Process
That was 40 years ago
It's pretty clear those statutes
Didn't do what many p
People who pooped that they would do
I don't think it's possible for the court
To take another mend it don't end it approach you know they tried that and we've all tried that for really
Long time if it happened next year
If the Supreme Court abolished
The death penalty
Next year
With some
Degree of finality
What do you think you guys would do what's the second what's the second biggest issue for
Oh there's so many Sean
I'd say probably
The two biggest issues are
Mass incarceration the number of people that the United States
Loksatta
And for how long wear an outlier
In that area as well
And the ways in which our criminal justice policies really punish people for poverty
The incredible fees and fines and bail amounts that end up locking people up in prayer
Prisons and jails
Not actually for the crimes which are often pedi that they've committed
Because they can't pay
Court cost for court fines or bail in order to get out
I'll just add that I would be thrilled for the captain
Punishment Center at the University of Texas
To go out of business
Rihanna
Supreme Court of the United States
Sean rameswaram speaking with brother and sister Carolyn
Jordan steiker from Harvard in Texas while respectively
Sean Moore perfect has gone on to
Host an amazing podcast called today explained
Definitely check it out in fact
Last week they didn't episode on the Attorney General's decision it's called Reviving death
Also when I ask you for a little favor
Get Radiolab we are clicking some feedback
So we can optimize the way that we get you to show how we interact with you guys
How we can reach new audiences
We would love to hear from you guys please go to radiolab.org survey
Good chance for us to know how we're doing what you would like to hear and not here
Radiolab.org survey
This episode of more perfect was originally produced by me Jad abumrad with Susie lechtenberg Karen Duffin Sean run
Forum Tobin low Kelsey Padgett storm wheeler Alex overington and Elie mystal
Fact-checking by Michelle Harris