Radio WNYC
Okay ready alright Chad Roberts
Radiolab
So Robert
Yessir the day is here the day is here it is here getting ready for this
Spell people
That Chad last year produced with amazing team a spin-off from Radiolab it is as it is
888 series about the law the law of the Supreme Court of the United States
Court in the land yet the idea was to take
To take the Radiolab thing the way of looking the way seen the way sounding producing
Flight to
Bizarre opaque
Body
Of Robin
Figures Robitussin people who wear black robes romad
You guys not English weird but isn't but I know it's an Old English word actually it's actually sort of tea
Common-law words they used to
Buspar robe snowed so that the show is called more perfect the idea behind it is could we tell
Personal
Human
Surprising
Thought-provoking stories about not just the justices with the people in the ideas to get
In front of the court
In the process can we give ourselves a new way of thinking about this country though that was the idea
Was pretty well too I thought it was alright the first season which was enormously popular I think was
Enormously popular because these as you call them aroubd people that you're going to Black
Pulsing Hearts you know they would sit down and Blake's by themselves and go crazy with concern they would have thought they were
Throbbing Heart full
Nutty
Passionate
Angry
They are beautiful people I was really quite something. Thank you
Okay so now what Robert I would love to play you the first episode
The very first episode of season
And one of the central ideas of the Season were perfect is that that
Did these moments in history that we thought were gone
They're never really gone
They will always swing back into the now and one of the cases
It is very much swinging back into the now is it
Watch movie Split
As you're listening know that there are already a couple more extra episodes already in the more perfect feed Radiolab
. org / more perfect or
More perfect on iTunes Google play whatever
Okay here it is
Episode number 1 season 2
In February of 2017
Supreme Court Justice Ruth Bader Ginsburg
Said something that surprised a lot of people would say Italy or not
Experiencing the best of times
She stepped
Straight into the political Fray and addressed this political moment
A1 said
Did the
True symbol of the United States is not the bald eagle it is the pendulum
And when the pendulum swings too far in One Direction it will go back
Some terrible things have happened in the United States but
Lincoln only
Hope that we learn from those bad thing
Today we're going to ride the pendulum to the dark side
Start with one of the most infamous decisions the court has ever made
Korematsu decision you might imagine it's not going to be the happiest of situations but
Story that we're going to tell you today and tomorrow as well actually
They're not stories of bitterness
Because this curious thing happens in both cases
Characters can't find Justice inside the Supreme Court
Stop looking for it there
And if I did somewhere else entirely
Producer Julia Longoria start this off
The year is 1967 and the place
Is San Lorenzo High School in East Bay of California
And we're in a
U.s. history classroom I was actually a junior in high school this is Karen korematsu
I'm the executive director and founder of the Fred T korematsu Institute in San Francisco
So on this particular day
Karen is sitting at the back of the classroom and our teacher had assigned each of
My classmates a little paperback
Book to read you know books about American history government in the assignment was to
Then I get up in front of the class and give an oral book report to me this is a long time ago so that's the way they used to do
Do things
I don't even remember what my my book was are my subject but Karen said she was just sitting there in class listen
As one by one classmate Scott up
Talk about George Washington or Abraham Lincoln or whatever and then my friend
Maya who is Japanese-American 3rd Generation like myself got up in front of the class
And her book was called concentration camps USA
About the Japanese-American internment
And I thought
No that's
Interesting I hadn't heard about that before what's that about
My book report went something like this
In 1941 the United States of America with attached
And the president's President Roosevelt had to respond
All measures be taken broadband
So in terms of Defense
One of the big questions for Roosevelt was what happens if the Japanese invade the continental US
America's founding
They probably come in on the West Coast
And you had more than a hundred thousand Japanese-Americans living on the West Coast
Like what they turn against the United States
They didn't know
And so her friend my explained to the class on February 19th 1942
President Roosevelt issued executive order 90066
That gave the military the authority
To forcibly remove anyone of Japanese ancestry from the West Coast
She goes on to explain these the horrific circumstances and
How you a hundred twenty thousand people of Japanese ancestry had been real forcibly
Removed from their homes
She explained they were put into these
Detention camps really without any due process of law but then she went on to say but there was this one
One man
Who refused to go to the camps and
He was arrested and sue the government
And took his case all the way to the Supreme Court and then he became a landmark Supreme Court case
And that man's name
Is Fred korematsu
I said to myself
That's my name
She says the class got really quiet
And I had 35 pairs of eyes turn around looking at me okay yes she thought my last
Name is karma to my dad's name is Fred but no way
There's no way it's my dad someone would have told me
So
Corson I go running home and
Confronting my mother and asking her
What she say
Well I got the standard to answer wait till your father gets home and you can ask him
My voice you heard by the way was Elie mystal our legal editor by the time he
I got home it was 8 in the evening and so that's a long time after you know 3:30 in the afternoon
And I calm down a little bit and I asked him in and he said
It happened a long time ago
And what he did he thought was right
And the government was wrong
And it was at clear and simple
I could just see
This hurt
Going over his face and I just couldn't ask him
Any more questions
Karen says it wasn't until years later that she learned what really happened
And why her dad never wanted to talk
Well
I was 21 then
This is
Fred korematsu at stapleton from the densho archives
And I was up on the hill
Sunday morning
My girlfriend
And Fred story starts
Out on a date when you're that age you know you have a girlfriend just like anybody else
And she was more important to me than anything
Fred and his girlfriend Ida are driving in the Hills above San Francisco looking down on the city
The Golden Gate Bridge you've been dating this girl for a while now
Italian-American most of his friends were Caucasian
And we were deciding what to do with such a nice day
Is it Go picnicking or something like that
And then all sudden diarrhea
We interrupt this program to bring you
Pokemon are newer car radio
Cloud right now
Japanese Embassy
And I was quite shocked we both were
Fred knew there was a war on and that the US was likely to get involved
Even try to enlist in the US military but was denied because he was Japanese-American
This is sitting there one of his first thoughts was
Why does it have to be Japan
Some country was going to attack Pearl Harbor
I wish it was Russia
You know
I just thought about that
I was bitter with the pan-fried having this happen
So I took her home
And then I went home
So
He gets home
Central shock
They're all sitting around the living room
The house is just in the spare his mom is in tears they were proud of being Japanese
You know they obey the law
They did everything that supposed to mean
To have this happen
I put them in chain
It was even hard to talk to them after that
Fred had a traditional immigrant Japanese American family
His parents were born in Japan and then all his brothers were born here in the US born in Oakland California
He was the third out of four brothers and being the 3rd not the 2nd or the 1st
That matter
Absolutely
Fred wasn't unique position as the third
Son he could resist
We asked Lorraine Vani I teach at Seattle University School of Law for some contacts
Kiawah professor and a friend of Fred's family the cultural tradition is that the first son is the favorite son
The oldest was going to inherit the family garden and Nursery business
II would help out with that business
Brad as a third son was very low on the totem pole is parents and have the same expectations
Love him relatively speaking he was kind of the hook
Unlike his older brothers he didn't speak much Japanese and he felt more American than anything else
When I was in school we started each day for the Pledge of Allegiance
I studied American history
Always been a good American citizen
So when he came home that Sunday when Pearl Harbor was attacked
Is family's response to the whole thing was
Unsettling
I am
I didn't know what to do
And Fred says pretty soon after
Things got very weird
Within a few days I put spotlights on the whole Nursery at night
And they had a guard standing right now
Our home there around the fence there watching us
Cuz I went out one night to have a cigarette and I was staying on the park tonight
But a cigarette
And God y'all. If I was singling somebody
Ridiculous
Then came Roosevelt executive order
That big order 906 6
Authorized the military to make a series of smaller ones
The first set of orders was a curfew order
Saying that Japanese Italians and Germans were subject to a curfew the second order was a freeze order
Directed just at the Japanese on the West Coast
They weren't allowed to leave the area and then the third order
Wasn't order that they could not
We met
On the West Coast
Except for in the custody of an approved location by the army
They're about 15 of these assembly centers
Japanese-Americans were told to report to one of these centers by a certain date
Fred's family began to scramble to worry about what they were going to take what was going to happen to the nursery
And so expecting my mother you know the tension and worries
For his family left
Fred made a decision
Me being the third son you know
I am I had my own worries
I had mom girlfriend my own problems
He decided not to go with his family
Talk to them bedtime
That I don't want to
I won't be with you
You didn't want to leave item behind
I thought maybe the two of them could make a break for it later on leave the state
Before the evacuation deadline
And
They said fine if you can do it
Go ahead
She was the third son
So he knew that
His older brothers would be able to take care of the family and they said he was a grown-up and he should make his own
Sessions
And so he did he went off and got his own apartment
His own job as a welder
I'm kind of lived under the radar
Lewis Brothers would be there to take care of his parents if you're with a family like my family or any
A Japanese family
You feel the pressure in the
Sadness
But on the outside is different just like a normal
What if you know
Just like we've been living all the time
I felt right at home
You know I'm an American citizen to you know
I didn't feel guilty
Cuz I don't think I did anything wrong
Sense of humor politically aware at this point
If you're asking me about whether he
Refuse to go as an act of political resistance
I don't think initially
Unconsciously he probably
New that what was happening to Japanese-Americans was wrong
But I don't think he had the words for that we might have today
Is on his way home from work one day that he reads in the newspaper about his parents
And all the other Japanese-Americans in the area being taken away to camp
Baby's sick to my stomach and on that
I can see my parents going in Yunnan my brothers
Going to camp
And I'm not there you know
But that was the only time that I felt
Kind of lonely you know like what what am I going to do now you know
It begins to slowly down on him what he's done
By staying in the Bay Area he is officially breaking the law
And he and I aren't sure what that means like will they be thrown in jail or worse
He talks in the archives about how he's worried
And I was worried to
Because now he could get arrested
So they start to think about their options Fred decides to get an ID with a Spanish sounding last name on it so we won't be recognized
Nice to Japanese
And then I decided
Essentially that might not be enough
Chapul. An article
We're going to plastic surgery
And
What do you think of this
I looked it over
And well
I didn't
Think I was a good idea but she said hey why don't you think about
That's this might be a good thing that will allow you to stay here
So the idea would be that he
You don't have his eyes doubled or something like that a plastic surgery procedure where you put a fold in the eye
Eyelid
So you look more white less Japanese-American
And I guess I don't know
Well
She said she'll be looking to it
And
Why is it that I'm going to lose so we decide to try it
So Fred gets into his car and he drives into the city into San Francisco and he
Just stops in front of the doctor's office
Amsart spacing
Walking up the steps of this Victorian and then
Walking down the steps to leave and he was a really crummy idea and then
Walking back up the steps
Thinking well yeah maybe I was right it's a good idea and the down the steps
This is a ridiculous idea giving some doctor your hard-earned money to
Change your face
So it goes up
And down
And I
Down and up
Down until
He decided to just
Going
And have the procedure done
He really did it as a way to
Protect them as they try to leave the state
The doctor said he was going to work on his eyes and then also fix
Broken nose I had a broken nose
I'm playing football in the never had it fixed
And
So you could do a pretty good work on me
But it turned out he didn't do everything he said he would
Regis
Took my money that's what it was
Actually
There wasn't anything change except
I didn't have a broken nose anymore
So he drives back to the East Bay with a new nose but the same eyes
And shortly after that day at the doctor's office he's out buying cigarettes at a convenience store
Leclerc
Recognized him
Reported him
And one day walking down the street he was stopped and arrested
And
Spent his Memorial Day and 1942 in the San Leandro jail
When we got caught
They called her into
Yeah
And
I see the police chief
Talking to her
Quite a while
I imagine it's a small jail and he's just been admitted so he's sitting in the lobby and he sees I to come in to the front desk
He's just out of earshot he can't make out exactly what they're saying but at a certain point
A stop talking
She just walks out
So
That was the end of it
I never did see her again
Never saw each other
So he sitting there alone in the San Leandro jail
And they end up transferring him to Oakland jail for some reason and then he ends up at
Federal
Prison in San Francisco because resisting the order was a federal offense
Anyway
One day I got to
Call from the guard
And tell me I had a visitor
And I didn't know it was you know
I knew all my friends were in can't or they were in the military but Fred Goes Down to the visiting room anyway
And
There's this man there New Yorker
Well I believe in civil liberties
Right of people
Is being denied
This is something that i'm concerned about the man says his name is ernest besig
Very nice phone
Easier to talk to me
He asked if I needed some cigarettes or something like that too
Just to break the ice
By the way I asked him
Who do you represent
And Earnest response well
ACLU or something like that
We have no way of knowing what exactly was said between Fred and Ernest best
Both men have passed away
But it seems like something important must have happened in this conversation because
If I was Lori Benitez I don't think he had the words for that we might have today
Fred didn't have
Language of resistance before this moment
Something in that conversation must have given it to him
Because when Earnest Pathak asked him
Do you want
Me to represent you in a court of law
Fred says
Yes
What do you mention the words worth it
Might have turned him in that moment
Imagine
That
Message must have said to fraud
We think that what's happened to Japanese Americans
Is unconstitutional
We'd like to bring a lawsuit
To say the Japanese Americans
Are being sent away
Only because of their race
And in that
Gay pride language
For what I think Fred knew was wrong
Basic try to get Fred out of jail but the military stepped in and said he had
Had to join his family and camp
They were at a place called Tanforan race tracks
It was a temporary holding spot
So that meant that the first place that Fred went after jail was
A converted horse stall
Alpha adorned in their gapping holes on the walls the wind just blew in there in the dust
Blue in there and everything
And this was a small horse dog because Fred had asked for his own
Wanted to sit and think about what to say to his family
We're also at Tanforan sat and looked at the single loan
Bear light bulb above and the smell of manure and hay
How many spray for horses not for human beings
And then all sudden I hear a knock on the door
And I'll open it with my brother
Is hey you can't stay here you
You got coming
Cedar Park
Walk spread over to the Star Wars families been living
And I was surprised the way they fixed up their stalls
The
Solar panel cracks
And they put newspaper for the walls in the paper that all up
This was a common thing for these families
Thousands of them were transferred to more permanent camps and many stay there for up to 3 years
Overtime
The community
Kind of tried to build lives for themselves
You hear stories
MC pictures
People building small Japanese gardens
Out of
What they found in the area
She saw newsreels about the people who made the Desert Bloom
Eventually saw
People forming you know baseball teams
My brother has he was involved in various Japanese activities
And
He thought it might be a good idea for me to
Get some suggestions and opinions regarding to
If I should fight the case or not
So Fred's brother calls a meeting
He got about 30 young people together
Imagine it was f****** a mess hall or something like that
And they discussed Frets case
They were
Discussion into themselves or in little groups
And I stood around and I waited for someone to speak
But no one actually came out to speak to me
I can see Fred
Can I standing in the corner as people are gathered in small groups
Whispering to each other
Stealing glances at him
But no one says a word to him
Finding one dead and You Said Fred.
We're undecided on
If I should buy
Acacia not because
They don't want to
Make any more disturbance
Anything to upset
The parents right at the time because they were too upset already and think
Just being in Camp
They told him their parents have been through enough
Leaving their lives behind
Basically they said we can't help you
But there was one Japanese American group that did decide to say something about Fred's case
What's the name of the group
Jacl
Ernest bethak had a nickname for this group
The Japanese-American Citizens League
I meant
With a leadership of that group
Several of them
I purged them
To oppose
The explosion
But they didn't seem to be particularly interested
The JCL condemned Frets case
And anyone else who fought against the government orders
Said it would not support any of these individuals were fighting the orders
And called them
Self-styled martyrs
Wow
They use that phrase
Yes
They would basically
Get everyone else into trouble
To do this by myself
I just wonder if I was doing wrong or
I'll maybe putting them in Shame by
I'm bringing the issue up again
Because of Japanese people lay their peaceful
People when they they like to leave things alone if they can
Because
They were in enough trouble as it is because of this Pearl Harbor attack
And the country blame them
So they have the sort of a guilty complex
Even though
They have nothing to do with it
Majority I'm just avoided me so therefore I assume that
That
I got myself in this problem
And
That was my problem in the end not there
Reddit continue to fight his case he argued that basically rounding up
Thousands of Japanese-Americans American citizens without a trial without due process
Basically amounted to racial discrimination
Is case made its way up and down the courts and eventually
Two-and-a-half years after he met an asbestos in that jail cell
The case arrives
At the Supreme Court
Yo he thought that by the time his case got to the
Supreme Court
That's Fred's daughter Karen again he would
Be able to vindicate his family and everyone that had been incarcerated
And that's how much he believed in the Supreme Court
And so when that didn't happen he felt like
If he felt like it was his fault
It's a big burden to carry around
What ends up happening is
On December 18th 1944
The Supreme Court ruled against Fred
It's kind of a complicated decision
The Supreme Court
Said
Racial distinctions
When the government is making racial distinction
It's serious
We need to look at this very very carefully
And that was a big president
Sun a lot of ways
It's
Kind of
Victory for people fighting racial discrimination
But then the court turned around and said
Even though racial distinctions are serious
This one
Is not
Strictly racial
We are at war with the Japanese Empire Fair for rounding up Japanese-American Citizens
Is a way to
Defend the nation
How's your friend at this point
Like it sounds like it sounds like lonely and then I can almost imagine because you're
You're by yourself
Pretty-much on all fronts
The country that you feel so part of that you want to actually enlist in the military to fight for
Doesn't seem to want you at that moment
Your own Community doesn't seem to want you
Your family
It's a Shame by you
Your girlfriend
Is gone
I can't imagine being more alone at this
Point
Any never shared that with my brother I
He shared it with my mother but
But we didn't that wasn't part of our pentateuch conversation
You know
What is
This is the crazy thing about the korematsu decision
It is
Still on the books
That guy Carl Higbie got on Megyn Kelly and
Said this stuff about korematsu and the very next day he got on and apologize for saying that
But he's right
Korematsu is technically still good law
Justice Antonin Scalia
One said
That sherp korematsu was wrongly decided
But if you think that it's not going to happen again
You're kidding yourself
The courtesan
Isn't it across the president
CNN International
Would you like it to
I think so
No
That's not injured in school yet it's a judge named Richard Posner
Not the time that we talked to him he was on the 7th Circuit Court
Appeals
He was widely considered by people on both the left and the right to be one of the most influential judges in the country
He sometimes called the 10th Supreme Court Justice
And he's a big Defender
At the korematsu decision
What do you say then to Fred korematsu what do you say then to to a Japanese-American about
Kind of the law and the court
Well they were given compensation
Right I mean Thursday Thursday
There is no pain
There there's an anguish right that we can
Exactly commodify
Yeah but
At the time it all happened
Shortly after Pearl Harbor
It seemed like the right thing to do and probably was the right
And I imagine that the officials
Federal government in
They probably
Didn't know anything about Japanese-Americans on the West Coast
Roosevelt ever compared to Japanese-American I doubt it
The fact that he had never met anybody
I might have been a reason for him to be more restrained in his executive orders right now
No because all he cares about is
Defense of the United States
If there's any
Possibility of Japanese-Americans somehow cooperating with a Japanese invasion Force
That he has to
Move the Japanese
What's this
I'm sure that's all he would have thought of
I think it's all he did think of
But what else could you have thought of
That's the only thing
He is going to focus on
And if he doesn't he could be impeached
Or he could also
Worried about citizens right I think one of the look you're not you
You're missing the priorities the priority is defense
That's the priority that's what these people are thinking about
You think they have time to be thinking about any
Any
Kind of nice ideas for protecting people
Any more than
Lincoln did
What he's referring to there is a moment in 1861 when Abraham Lincoln basically tossed this alleged Confederate and
Jail without due process
And then Justified it by saying he had to save the Union
Nikes
Supreme Court Justice Roger Taney ruled against him
Cheerleaders at all well Tony he's the Chief Justice and he said this
Jerk should be released
I guess I have to do that he's the Chief Justice
No you do that enough time
As the president you're out
It seems to me that
That's why we have court
We have no, that is not why we have
We do not have cords
So that presidents can be checked
In situations of a national emergency
That was my courts were set up
Then what I mean
I'm flailing now but
Then what stops then what
If Court
Congress can't stop a man that's the courts can't stop them like what can stop a president in a time of War
There's nobody that nobody can check
The president's responsibilities
Obviously I'd like a do-over
Because somehow In the Heat of the Moment
I forgot
That
I'm talking about defending the rights of actual American citizens
And Posner is talking about
People who are Rebels
To touch
There is probably a way where I could have said
Pointed that out to him
Friends of the Court stepping in I mean it happens it happened to Truman
But you know judge Posner is right
But it doesn't happen a lot
Which is why he gets to be judge Posner and I'm the guy that had to check Wikipedia
And by the way do you think these Supreme Court Justices are great big brains
Pink Stars
Who are selected because of the best lawyers in the United States
And their decisions are
Are usually great you think all that
I don't I don't have a high respect for the Supreme Court at all
You look at them how they are appointed who appoints
This is so why do you think the Supreme Court has such a great balance
To the
Present in a war
This is what gets me up at
Gets me going because
I still think it can be used as a precedent
So your ears you're still worried that it can be used
And that it
Do you think it will be like you don't like you know I think we cannot take this for granted
Wow that's just quieter I mean
That judge is as revered and as thought highly of as
As you guys said
Yeah you just actually think we don't mention I vote on her he will he just retired
Yeah he just like I think within a within the last month but you know I mean I'm listening to that and I'm thinking wow
Not only is there a distinction to be made between people who are American citizens and people who are traitors but there's also this
Hugeback
If you are German Americans
By the tens of thousands in this country at that time
We were at war with Germany to end Germans
Held big rally in Madison Square Garden with swastikas and
Supported Hitler out loud and marched for him for a while wish they had it
Every right to do
But
They were not
Getting quite the same degree of Suspicion is the Japanese and that's a question
I think for
For the court
So there is an argument for justice wasn't but there's an argument against him for sure
Yeah
Wow that's really
So now
Fred has to solve his problem elsewhere
Rights when the next part of the story the question really is like since Fred can't get Justice in the court
Can you find it on the outside
And he does in this
Place that you wouldn't expect
Come back we'll find out where that place is yeah
Aries will continue in a moment with our featuring of radiolab's first-ever spin-off more perfect
Season 2 episode 1 morning moment this is Kevin Murray from Fort Collins Colorado Radiolab distance
Boarded in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world more information about Sloan at w
Ww.w. Sloan. Org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help this summer I'm hosting a show
And I request for those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teacher
We're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments childhood brilliance
Did something that just means you lean back and say whoa
Maybe it was the moment that a kid you've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons and you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed they're ready music in the margin of their geometry homework we're interested in the
Epic moments where a kid does something super smart but it doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story please share it with us
Go to radiolab.org Brilliance and record a short audio message for us
Again that's radiolab.org / Brilliance thank you so much
Hey I'm Chad album run Radiolab we're previewing the first episode of more perfect season 2 so we
We go back to Fred korematsu who as you just heard lost his case before The Supreme Court did not get the REM
Maybe he wanted them so now he is I don't know what he's going to do
Will now end up getting a kind of Remedy you said it was something you did that it's not
Some judges involved with this this this I find really really moving
I got to say just personally
The whole reason to tell the story is where it ends
So
So pretty sure Julie Longoria is going to
Pick back up the story with
What happened to Fred after the decision
So the
Internment camp where Fred was staying
Clothes in 1945
And Fred have gotten permission by that point to work
At a steel mill in Detroit
So he was living in Detroit
He fell in love with a woman named Katherine
They got married moved back to the Bay Area and had two kids
And Karen his daughter says that they were kind of ostracized from the Japanese American Community they grew up
Outside of the Japanese Community he was involved in Boy Scouts
Girl Scouts so I was a girl scout so we all the camps when we had to open the camp he would work on that
The Presbyterian Church in Oakland and then he became an elder
Even join the Lions Club and he was President twice
And Karen says throughout
The 40s
The fifties the 60s
She never heard him talk about his case
No never
Hit he just
Never he never seen ever
Tell the story even after she confronted him about it in high school yeah it's that's it
But she says in like 1969 ish
68 or 69 when the world was in a very different place
They got a phone call back in those days you know you my parents
Phone number was in the phone book
Of all things
Get me my father we get phone calls from
Boston when it interview on but he really didn't want to talk about his case much
She just
It was just too painful
But this time there was a professor on the line from the University of California Berkeley
It was a Japanese guy actually
And I told Fred
I really really want you to come into my class
There was a ethnic studies
Class that was actually off campus
Ethnic studies was not even recognize that
So he he talked
Yeah that this ethnic studies class and these kids were brutal
Me UC Berkeley at that time had the snow
Notorious
Reputation of being very radical for asking questions during the whole hour
This is Jean Quan former mayor of Oakland she was in the class that day and it was important
Different country like you have to learn up stand up to Authority and certainly these students were like DLC astounding say
Well why didn't you
Why didn't you protest why didn't you do this why didn't you do that why didn't you fight harder and we're almost
You're angry that we he wasn't angry I think
You got to remember that a lot of these students even know anything about the
Accounts
Many many kids had not had Frank discussions with their own Tara and so
Was korematsu it was probably a surrogate for like
Your parents
How could they have gone to that and never told me they had no right not to
To tell me
And so they're really angry at their parents
Surrogate or not
Red felt like he was being indicted all over again it it was such a painful experience for my father he never one
Want to speak to anyone again
Redwood ultimately challenge his conviction in a lower court
And you would win
The Supreme Court decision still stands
But he was able to clear his own personal name
Around 1990
Again the world in a very different place
He finds himself again on a college campus
This time the University of
Michigan
My father and mother were walking with some other students
Across campus
To see the newly renovated library and
Beyond my father loved architecture was very old Gothic
Library so they're walking through this sort of open quad looking at the architecture
And then they come upon this group of students
A group of
Arab
American students
The student start walking toward him they
All of a sudden kind of surrounding my father and they had this
Certificate
To give to my father
To thank him for speaking up
So that was meaningful to him
Why why did that make you emotional
Why that story
Because it meant so much to my father
That this group really honored him
That
Also had been racially profiled
Y'all to think that he would be able to
Touch their lives it it kind of reinforced what he
He was doing
Do you have the same faith in the Constitution that your dad did that.
Have great faith
In our constitution
It is a great document
It
It so happened so that it's the way that certain people in
Interpreted
That gets us into trouble
Yes
Definitely
3.0 coming here tonight the Trump Administration on billing
New travel restrictions on certain foreign Nationals from eight countries
Is everything with a feeling we're thinking they going to start a new line in United States
This is what we want we want
We want to deliver TV1 the people we are the people
There are many many lawyers here they're all working pro bono today they're from different organization
What resistance looks like sends a message that they cannot do
Away with constitutional protections without people standing up for the Constitution so
I think this is inspirational I think it's wonderful and I think we need to be vigilant and keep fighting
We know it's interesting it's like not only
To the courts
You know eventually go back and forth
On these
Deeper questions
So do all of us
Shandong
The verdict of history is always going to be a little bit shifting but eventually
You kind of hope
At the Arkansas to move just far enough along you can't go back
You can go all the way back
Eventually you get to a better place
You get a little bit more perfect
Nice more perfect by the way is produced by me
And Susie lechtenberg Jenny Lawton the amazing Julia Longoria Kelly Prime Sean ROMs firm Alex over
Sarkari with Elie mystal Cristian farias Linda Hershman David Gable and Michelle Harris
Special thanks to the den show archives for the tape of Fred korematsu in earnest besig
Supreme Court audio is from oil-free law project in collaboration with Legal Information Institute of Cornell
Leadership sport for more perfect is provided by the Joyce Foundation additional funding is provided by the Charles Evans Hughes
Hughes Memorial foundation so yeah I guess I am just close
Let me know if you know this. Was the first that that was the first episode of more perfect season 2 there are already two other episodes in the
Feet and there'll be many more coming so if you like that if you wanted to keep up with it.
Go to radiolab.org more perfect or search for more perfect
ITunes or Google play or whatever this season we will be releasing a lot more episodes of better way
Way more ambitious we're just going for it so tell everybody tell everybody it's out and spread the word
Yeah because I don't think I think this is
This is very much of its moment so we'll see.
Thanks for listening