Weight units
Listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
And NPR
An upscale Mall in Nairobi has turned into a Battleground
Armed men stormed Westgate Mall in the Kenyan capital
For lunchtime firing weapons and throwing grenade what appears to witness has to be at least a dozen gunmen
Have taken hostages inside others have reported that the
There have been reports there have been unsubstantiated reports Canyon police and
Counter-terrorism officers are hoping I would feel like I need to start with the caveat that all these other stories that we
You know gotten to do together gunfire have been me telling you a story as a journalist
Feel like this story is going to be a story where I'm going to have to stop being a journalist
Hey I'm Jared I'm Ron I'm Robert krulwich this is Radiolab
We got you just heard that was NPR's East Africa correspondent Greg Warner
Recently he came to us with another one
It was all about a struggle he was having
Trying to figure out how to tell a story
That is true
I'm sleep with that
Sexy story about
The aftermath of an event that
Probably got more media coverage than almost any events in East Africa last year that is the
The terrorist attack on Westgate Mall in Nairobi
This was September 21st 2013 was a
Balmy Saturday afternoon Westgate Shopping Mall
Crowded with more than a thousand shoppers
Even more families than usual were there that day because there was a children's cooking competition in fact the kids were just sitting up
Dairy ingredients
Parents just taking their seats when shortly after noon
Gunman
Entered the building shooting AK-47 is going Florida for killing people and the seats would last for four days
4 days
Central Ein
Like dozens of
International independent and local journalists are outside the mall
Listening to sounds of gunfire
Trying to guess
What's happening inside because the prices of course not allowed in while this for this battle is ongoing
Meanwhile I'm getting on the air every hour
Trying to piece things together
Coming my way
So I'm going to
Gregory movers you need to move Wyoming
But my point is that there was no information at the scene other than this gunfire
What there was were
A whole bunch of Survivor
How do you feel
Helpless
Help us a fact all the journalists were racing around interviewing eyewitnesses
Buddy was I'm in everybody was really running for their lives
Pocket dammit officials
To get a picture of what happened in the story
That emerges from the those interviews is basically.
Stat
The number of terrorist inside that mall or at least in the beginning was 10 to 15 gunmen
And I'm 15 gunmen 10 to 15 attackers to 15 armed militants with her profile is multi-ethnic
Cancel the United Kingdom end
Somalis
Canyon aeroad
Mostly men but also including a British woman that young British
Eyewitnesses eyewitnesses on different floors in the mall all talking about the Dare gun that the people they saw
And it's this multi-ethnic group
And then of course perhaps most alarmingly for the both of us living in Nairobi there's reports that at least one gun
Had
After shooting some people thrown away his gun and actually escaped
With the fling Shoppers we hear that from a couple Witness
So that's the
Initial story
But it's not really until 8 weeks later
In November
That us officials in fights
About
Dozen
British and American journalist into a conference room in the US Embassy
And
We need an official there from the FBI
Now we've known that the FBI was involved in the post-mortem analysis
Senora join
Shazam
This is like a global terrorism event so
Can you head invited Scotland Yard and the FBI to figure out who these terrorists were but the FBI had not actual
Said anything official
In this meeting inside the US Embassy what on what's called Deep background
Which isn't even off the Record it's it's a it's a deeper level of secrecy we weren't at that time even allowed to say that
The Us official had said any of this stuff this was just information for us to know
Since then I can talk about this meeting because everything that was repealed there has now become
A part of the public record in fact the FBI's
Has come out publicly and said all these
But at the time this was new
End
What the FBI
Person
Set the time was that his team
Had access to all the closed-circuit camera footage
Is the mall
The modern moth there's cameras everywhere
He seen it from the beginning to the end of the attack from all those different perspectives
And according to that footage
Everything
That we have reported
In those first few days
Was Roth
Ronnie running away
Well friends in 10 to 15 terrorists
Now they weren't 1015 terrorist it were for
For they also said okay you've been reporting this
This multi-ethnic Coalition of Arabs Kenyans and somalis that so many eye witnesses told you know
They're all somalis are all Somali ethnicity all four of them
And there's also no evidence in any of the gunmen Escape
Mcqs from his perspective with words
He trying to
I don't know what we should read on this
And I actually felt
China weather
People in that room felt
Huge
Sense of relief
Because here we are all are trying to do the work of Journalism in a trying to get
Credible testimony
And
Suddenly here's a guy
Saying
Okay take away all that speculation all those contradictory stories all those different reports
Here's some objective evidence
You can't see this day because it's secret for very Saints terrorism reasons but
This is
Solid
And after that time everybody was reporting the same thing
Unreleased surveillance video shows
Four armed assailants for terrorist
Text are believed to be from Somalia are all somalis will confirm
All four were killed
So you kind of put a cap on all those kids
Scary theories
Speculations that were really feeling the media the slightest bit curious about what might have been left out
No I mean
Well I guess I really felt was
Was sort of empty
Because
And I'm not only a reporter
In Nairobi
I'm also a person living in Nairobi to go to dinner parties I take my kid to
Birthday parties end
Special event in the first month after Westgate or so many
People in that mall invariably somebody would be there at the party you had
Their own survivors
And it's one thing to say oh well
That was all this eyewitness testimony no it's not
Accurate but it's another thing to look into the
The eyes of somebody
Who is
Sitting there
With a paper plate of cake
In their hand telling you that the terrorist
The base
Is not the terrorist
They saw on this bit of footage that have been released and was playing and heavy rotation on Kenyan television
Is that happened more than once he was much more than what I mean
Is your only your first name
They put my nickname former neighbor Vine in Nairobi
Saturday morning to the Westgate Mall to get
Present for her friend's daughter
I think it was a puzzle a little puzzle for a 4 year old girl
And I'm standing that I'm just about to pay
And then automatic weapons
Shooting the grenade tonight
Competition didn't have much time to think I just ducked under one of those tables and then
You could hear people praying muttering prayers
She said she had a man gasping for breath
And she says at one point
Another woman was under the table with her and I were literally squeezed together
She was pregnant
And that's the first thing she said she's like
I'm pregnant and I'm shot I didn't have the presence of mind to help her she basically
Took one of those grapes
And wrap it around
To stop the bleeding
Later on I mean
Cuz we were there for quite some time she said to me I'm dying
And yeah that point of stroking her hair saying no you're not you're fine it's just your leg is just your leg
Increases that while she was under that table she would try to peek up through the cloth and for the longest time I couldn't see anything
Finally I see
I see the guys
To those two young boys
Cute little young innocent-looking boys
You know it's hard to imagine you can't reconcile what they're doing with how they look
One of them was was kind of I don't know maybe a 17 18 year old kid and cute
I could just
See him as being the son of one of my friends
This particular one was closest to us was wearing a red t-shirt
And here's where you get to a small but significant discrepancies
Still haunts booty
She said she is sure
That the two guys she saw and pictures
Few feet away from her
Wearing short sleeve shirts
And afterwards
Keep seeing these
Images
4 guys
None of them were wearing shorts
We're at the beginning if you remember there was saying there was 15 guys so then it kind of made sense that well the two guys that I saw
What different from the floor that were seeing on TV
But then when people like me start to report that there were only four
Categorically only for guys
Then I started to say wait wait a minute
I saw their arms
I know I saw a short
Sleeve t-shirt
You know it just does not make sense nothing adds up
Am I crazy
Is my mind playing tricks on me I think I saw one thing and then I didn't but I'm quite sure I saw this I mean
Everyday every moment of the day you're thinking about
What happened
What happened that day with these parties of your all these story
Grace like ponies
Is the word
The official narrative
And yet
It felt real
All the details seemed weird enough to be true
Surreal enough
Picture of you know another person was talking about
Yeah it's powerful story wear it with
Man was shooting and then he got a phone call and
Stop shooting long enough
To answer the phone
And then hang up and
Start shooting again
Music
You don't make details like that up
And this is what I think made things so awkward
At those conversations because they knew that the terrorists
They saw
Was Jeff
Then on the video
And
What that left them was
Was two things one is that
That I might think that they were lying
End to that the
Terrorist
That
Haunts them is still out there
You know that guy could just be around
He could see me again
And here's where things get a little
Weird okay so this is 4 months later
Definitely the new cyclist kind of moved on as a journalist I don't really have to report I must get anymore it's Saturday afternoon again
Like she just at home with my kids
And
I get a phone call
To call the
Kind of offended the whole story for
And that's after the break
This is Darlene calling from Kampala Uganda
Rachel app is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation enhancing public understanding of
Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloane at www.aa.org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help this summer I'm hosting a show
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
About what we're calling Brilliance basically I want to hear about this
Yo did something
That just means you lean back and say whoa how did they do that maybe it was the moment that I can
Kids you've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of their musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed are ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the
Epic moments where
Kid does something super smart but doesn't have anything to do with the test
If you have a story please share it with us
Go to radiolab.org brilliance
And record a short audio message
And that's where you're at. Org / brilliance
Thank you so much
Hey I'm Jared I'm rod iron Robert Kovac
Is Radiolab and we'll get back to Greg reporter Greg Warner's story of the aftermath of the Westgate
Terror attack in Nairobi Kenya you just heard the beginning we're not going to tell you the end
If there is a man
Will pick things up with Greg getting a phone call
I get a phone call
Some guy we haven't met yet the guy named Farooq Farooq is not his real name he has Greg to change name for the
The story
Bill becomes clear why
And evidently
Note 4 root
One of the first people I met in the parking lot on that first day of the attack
Sunflower gunshots in outer space
Everybody was running away when I met him he was actually trying to reach his fiance
Still in there
She's not picking the phone
Ivan Reitman the message how are you
Even I lost my specs he lost his eye glasses as he was fleeing
So let me see if you want me to come looking for
Yangon to text
Naruto messages
No reply
Then I called her
What happened to Henderson
Wish you killed was later found among the bodies at the morgue
But then
A week later and it backup was for real
He told me something.
That he has not told me that morning
Everybody was going to second floor
Sister with this moment
In the mall
Underpants
We're a bunch of people were running up the escalator
And one of the terrorists
Came down the opposite way
Down the escalator
What's pushing everybody down
Somehow he says he got spun around the opposite direction of the crowd
And then I saw him he gets a good look at this guy
I saw the person
Very clearly
This person who was an Arab guy
He says he's sure but yes
And then he says that he ran and found a hiding spot and also something he pokes his head out
And he saw him again
When I saw this guy
Houston Tennis Club
April 20
What do tomatoes grow
Then he was wearing another clock inside
When do the clocks change
Basically says that
After that
First party
The guy changed his clothes
Dropped his gun
And then
Insinuating himself
And when we came out this guy joined us
He joined us
So when I swim outside and I was telling everybody he's one of them it was one of them but everybody was in shock
Nobody Cuda
See what I'm saying
NN do you know what happened to him
No I don't
Midea
Okay so
Back to the phone call in January that I was telling you about
Farooqi calls me out of the blue
He says hey I'm sitting at a bar at a place called Diamond Plaza
Which
Is interesting because Diamond Plaza happens to be one of
The perspective
Terrorist Targets in Nairobi a known terrorist Target besides West
And he says across from him
Few tables away is V
Gunman the guy got away
I see him he's at the next table
And he says
Can you come
And you actually what
First they told him
Finish your beer and go home
I actually
Hung up
Then I thought I probably shouldn't blow this guy off
If This Were happening in the United States I could have just said that the guy look if you're so sure about this why don't you just call nine one
But there is no 911 in in Kenya and so he called me
And I basically said to him a woody would you want me to do and he said just let the police know
And then I did I'd I called the source that I know in the police department and he called his people and they did
We're going to be right there where is this location
You know they treated it seriously so
Once there was this amazing possibility
I feel like I'm going to wait downstairs until the police show up and then you know cops style I'm going to rain
Race up with them and sort of
Be behind the police so I'll be able to witness it but I'll be safe but I get there in the police are like
Not there yet
So I'm waiting downstairs bar
Hertz calling me like where are you man and I said well I'm downstairs I'll keep come up
I don't think this is a good idea
As I'm sitting there arguing with
We have to hurry because
I've invited this guy this was supposed terrorist to sit with me at my table
What
Golden City
Yeah I guess the guy was about to leave and fruit in monthly if so
He jumped up and somehow convinced this guy
Stranger
Did Fitbit have a drink with him at the table
I think it's going to
Come up I walk into the bar
Far past the pool table
Out outdoor bars will you bring to the table and indict
Yeah yeah yeah there's this guy late 20s
Fairly slender
He was wearing a t-shirt black jeans
I detail it stood out to me was that he was wearing two watches
Really
So sit down order beer
Makeup
Terribly lame story that why I'm there
Phone case from my wife.
We'll talk to the guy didn't speak English
Joey
This kind of conversation you didn't really understand
What I say except for very basic stuff
But within a few minutes my sitting down the police finally arrived
Brooke jumps up IDs the guy who is completely confused but what's going on
He was at the mall the day of the attack
And so the police
The question again
It is very suspicious
They asked him where he's promises Nairobi
Even though he had told us that he's from Yemen and then
They asking for passport and then he says oh I don't have my passport but then he does and then he says I want from Yemen so
Anyway so that's enough for the police that they put the rubber handcuffs on him and they take him away
He didn't say he seemed kind of belt
You seem high actually
Coming ahead and mention with it
The guy Ben
Shooting
Narcotic leaf
It's called Mira
Cot
And so
He
He seemed no
Like a scared High person
You know where you're scared but you're kind of numb
Do whatever
Everything is happening all seems like a dream
What was not
Conjectural with it as the police were leading him out
Farooq
Just
Lose it
White guy you know
Anyone anyone at the bar.
You still want all we could do to kind of calm him down
You know my family saying
Looking at life in prison I love my life
I saw him and he was watching me
You showed my love man
How can I
Let It Go
This is the day
Under 10%
That's when the call to prayer comes out of the speakers from a nearby mosque
All the way through it
Directly from the bar to go to the police station to give a statement
And I
I felt really bad
Actually
I never felt like I was doing something
Wrong per se
But I felt that
Had come
To this person
And actually
At that point I didn't feel that he was a terrorist and I just hope
That the system
To which I had helped commit him
Would treat him fairly
After that I kept calling the police station
Every few days about 10 days later I found out
The guy was released
And he hadn't been charged with anything and it's that point I was like
Alright Grace
Is all worked out fine
Poor guy was in the wrong place at the wrong time and you know got falsely ID possibly but
Book everything is done everything kind of worked out the way it was supposed
And that's what I sent you know for 4 months basic
Went off to do other kinds of reporting other stories
But a few months later
I was talking to a police Source again
And I happen to mention we're taking a different story said yeah whatever happened to that
Black guy from
Yemen that fellow it was picked up at Diamond Plaza and he said only knows funny that the witness that you told us about
You never showed up
Didn't show up
I said what fruit never showed up to give his testimony you can hear from the tape
The one thing that's so clear
He said he's on his way over to police station full barrels blazing and so I called
Farooq
Annies phone is off
And then
I called his phone still off
A few minutes late
This phone number is no longer in service kind of thing
So it's actually not until close to the year anniversary
Of the Westgate that I get a call
Your number
Another word for weak
And it's
Fruit candy
Very nervous he says are you alone
Asking me
Not to record this
Conversation natale's me
He had gone to the police station just as likes
Suspected he marched right over to the police station
And they told him I will know this is being handled by the X terrorism police
So
You leave your phone number and then it's terrorism police will give you a call
A week later
He started getting calls several calls from unknown numbers
Where people who did not identify themselves
Threatened
Told him not to say anything
About this guy he had arrest
Not to talk to the Press
Or
He be sorry and his family would be
Sorry
He was extremely rattled by these phone calls and ultimately
She turned off
This phone if I couldn't get a hold of him
Left the country
4 short bed
It come back
Was laying very low and it's
Why I'm using an assumed
Name Prim when I'm not telling you
Full name
Doesn't want that
And you believe the stories about
Threats and
Absolutely no way of knowing for sure
That
Part of his story though
Seemed
The most likely to be true
The fact that the anti-terrorism police
Had called him
Allegedly and made threats
That does not sound strange
And fortunately to me I've heard that story from lots of very credible people does this make what he saw.
Drawer
Country where we go I don't know
Suddenly I found myself less willing to discount the story
And
I was less comfortable with the
Official narrative
Then
I wanted to be at that
So
I called up
One more
Guy a guy who is not a government official
Who's not the FBI
And yes quit
Seen all the videotape
From the mall can you just give me your name and your
And your title and read I'm a producer and director of documentaries most recently Terror the mole which was
Tonight's HBO and the BBC
And for that documentary Dan got
Exclusive access to
All the surveillance footage
Inside that mall
If there were more to this
Story
You can tell me so how much footage
Did you get if I can ask him and how many hours are the footage we obtained added up to about
Mom $2,000 while when we analyze the timeline where the cameras weren't we
The offsets between different cameras we really did a huge forensic job
It's mind-numbingly tedious to watch a lot of it
But if you
Dugite writ you do get the key to another the mysteries of Westgate
Like me you got into this project
Open mindedness very kind of
Eunice OBO
Sensible people who said the other was 7 Paris
I saw 7 Terrace
I mean you dream of
Be able to confirm that they were seven government you dream of being able to confirm that they will escape what if that were true what if
If we could
Find
Evidence some evidence that that were true
But in the end
He didn't know as well as we
Progressed further and further with our
Forensic analysis it became harder and harder to give any credit to some of the wild two pieces of
Have eyewitness
He says what you see on those tapes is what the FBI said you'd say
4 guys
All Somali
Xi an
Exactly was in how does he
Square of the stories
You were hearing with the stories
You are reporting
Well that part was actually fighting
We are little people say yeah there was a woman
When I was going through this footage my wife looked over my shoulder
Pointed to one of the four terrorists on the screen that won't push it or is that it go
And we came to the conclusion that that one of the gunmen was in a very slender and he actually does sachet alone in in
What is Frankie quite an effeminate way and similarly he says you can
Justify some of the reports that one of the gunmen was an Arab because one of them did in fact have
Lighter skin
Then your average Somali
And you can explain the people thought that they were
More gunmen 10 or 15 gunmen because they were a lot of guys
Two guns running around
Pudding
Security guards
And later
Policeman there were a lot more policemen than they were gunman
I did speak with one eye witness
Who said it it that he saw one of the terrorists
She may change clothes and Escape
Well I know that doesn't that doesn't match anything that we saw
I didn't think the question to ask your eyewitnesses is is how do you know this person with a weapon who changed codes
Was a terrorist
It may have been a policeman recently had
Stories of policemen taking off
Changing clothes will take note of any any distinctive clothing I don't know if those stories were true but we we had stories
Uniformed policeman
Took off their uniform even more fight I guess yeah I mean that but that's feel Greg. Fuel I mean
Speculation and did not see that on the any of the securities
I just had so many conversations like people sing to me know their skates and I'm like why do you think that
You know these guys don't come to escape if you escape you failed
He says take the 2008 terrorist attack in Mumbai
They had murdered 35 people at the hotel
There's a moment in that film where one of the gunmen
One of the last remaining gunman in hotel room next to use in the bathtub next to
Is his accommodate his dad is dying
He's talking to one of his handlers on the cell phone
Recording that call ended
The handlers free call me Satan you know you what your mission
Successful to you or kill
And then they say to him
Please leave your phone on switch on the line open in your pocket
So that we can hear when you go out and I'll killed by the
Enemy security Force
So there is a whole script
So this kind of operation and it ends with the death
All of the gunmen at the hands of the enemy
Ma
That's how
He knows they didn't Escape
Not just because there's no evidence on the film but because
It's the last thing they would have wanted
And yet we don't need these
The rumors that the Terrace Escape the Room is that there was a woman amongst in the room is that they got change the room is
They don't seem to go away even when confronted by quite solid evidence
It's almost
Is it the Faxton Masa
So I called Farooq
Still sticking to his story
He says he saw a saw though
He's really
Too nervous to go on tape
But I did run it by puni
My former
Neighbor in Nairobi who's
100%
Still pretty sure that the guy she saw in the mall
Hasn't been accounted for
I think I'm sure about it but
What is the government said
Here's the bodies here the DNA evidence here's the four they'd all die they died on the second day
Or third day whatever was this is how they died and here's the DNA proof
Really make me happy is if
They even asked the questions
Beat the media beat the government
Why did we go from 15
To 4
Quickly tell you how we arrived at 4 cuz I told her about the meeting with the FBI
And how we got this information then I told her about
Dan Reed watching 2000 hours of video tape
I told her about how I investigated Farooq story and
Mostly came up empty I told her not to
Everything that I know all these facts but
How I got to
Because
In the end
Maybe the facts Aren't Enough
Fax need to make sense
Especially for people who
But I can imagine for anybody was not there anybody was reading it yet the evidence says and then you move on
Listen to I feel like I'm I'm learning much more about my job and
Being a journalist and maybe it's not so pretty because I feel like that
That day coming out of that meeting with the FBI and feeling like okay now we
We have some solid evidence that can be reported and we can move on felt
Good I mean it felt like
Offering instead of offering shaky as a testimony we could offer Truth at least his
Best we can understand it but it feels like maybe that was too sudden and too
Due to an inquisitive in a way to match the emotions that we're still
In the air in the rub it that time maybe it felt like abandonment even though it was meant to feel like clarity
Xiaomi
It's still there's a little
Glimmer of maybe that's not
The full story
I am inclined to believe
That they were four
But then it's like what I saw does not make sense
And that I'll never be able to really reconcile and I just kind of have
Leave it at that
Lot of people think for the story of course Greg Warner
First foremost in PRC
East Africa correspondent
And also thanks very much to Jason straziuso blogger Robert Ally I devote NPR intern
National Edgar D skanky and Senior International editor Edith Chapin for allowing us to borrow Greg Hunter
I'm Jedi Cam'ron
Thanks for listening