Are you weightless
Radio WNYC
And NPR
This is Radiolab on Jedi camera
There is no leaks by DIY got
Custard with this
You were some kind of an affair to tell you how I was at a party party
It was a it was a
Conference were there a lot of different people with different disciplines come together
You know one of those
Are panel discussions various things as we were at one of those functions
And
It was a situation where like dinner hadn't yet been served and there was
A lot of booze being serious everybody was like drunk on an empty stomach
So I was standing there with some violin
Are the other fun ones
The jump Palace
My people fairly and they they started to lose their ship
Like genuinely lose their s***
About this thing called
And like I've never seen scientist this
Excited about anything I was like what is this
What is crispr
Trying to explain to me what they couldn't slow down enough for me to get it
I gathered it had something to do with genetics and then at one point one of the biologist tournament is like
I'll tell you what it is
I can use crispr to take a little dog
And poof make it to a big dog give me a Chihuahua I could turn it into the size of a Great Dane and was like no you can't
He's like yes I can I could do it with crispr I was like what the hell is this thing
To sit here is you
I will get up
No no no no
So what happened was I came back and I immediately called science writer Carl Zimmer
Because I just figured for this kind of thing
The car thing I got to talk to Carl
So I guess I'm like why all the fuss
Maybe it was just the alcohol or but maybe there's something really happening here
Oh there's something totally happening there I mean it's
He started at the begin
So that
You you can actually find like the
The first reference
Spur in a 1987 paper
And some Japanese scientist
They basically
Describe something weird and E coli and they said we don't know what this is
E.coli are bacteria inside human
And like all living things
Equalize made up of DNA and T's and C's Angie's and what happened was it the scientist
Breeding a chunk of that genetic code
When
They found this really strange
Stretch of DNA
Stretch out well so basically what it was
5 identical sequences
In a row
And then they were separated by very short
Sequences in between them that were
All different from each other
The little blurb should be like
And they look at that sound like what
But this is nothing like we've seen before repeated
Sequences in bacterial genomes are kind of unusual
Seems very strange some biologists felt that there must be a purpose
Among those purple sneakers Jennifer doudna University of California Berkeley cell biology
Yeah so it's not dude it's down used to be called the dude
Sometimes it's cool in the movie she will be played by Jeff
Right anyhow
Xango's on scientist are single repeat Loop repeats
Everywhere
Releasing bacteria lots and lots of lots of species of bacteria
They say okay wait a minute it's kind of cool your findings it so often
Is this where the name Christopher comes from
The full official name is
Clustered
Regularly interspaced
Short
Palindromic repeats
My God, I don't know why they called it
It's kind of a
Furniture
It sounds like an app
But now
Scientist had the puzzle
If nature at this level preserve something intact
Here and here
And here and here and here and here
And some of these here
Creatures that have been around for
Hundreds of millions of years you figure out
Whatever this is
Doing something
But what it doesn't take very long
Before the first big clue
Comes up
Pirate password
2005 now scientist have these big searchable databases
Of DNA sequences are some scientists
Bank elasticsearch
Let's see if these repeating patterns we keep finding match anything else
It's out there in the world
And
The scientist guitar
Using computers to just line up these stretches of DNA with thousands upon thousands of different species and then
Click
I'm sudden
Discover
Did those bits of DNA between the repeats
Stuck in the Middle does blurt
These
Are matching virus DNA
Like you can find viruses
With
Jeanswear
The little you know these little to the bacteria had virus inside of them
Is that what that mean that it was a virus brought it
Into this the first recognition was
This is virus DNA
Somehow all these bacteria
A little snippet the virus DNA
West Indies
Particular places
Energy no
Which is a little weird if you think about that means are totally different creatures
It would be like inside a human finding a little bit of mosquito DNA
How do we interpret this well
Actually there was one scientist named Eugene koonin
To look at these results and just had
Okay I guess
Is it offensive
Why would you think that cuz he's a brilliant man I went to her if I went to a large
Sanitation dump
And I found a teeny bit of
Human hair why would I think
I wouldn't know it just like a beauty human
Well you see
That metaphor my
Sort of betray at your lack
Skill in microbiology I'm just saying like this is not a dump all right this is
Bacteria are not going to just
Let virus DNA
Get into their jeans willy-nilly
Okay remember
Viruses are the big anime
If your bacteria
Viruses make your life a nightmare
Think about in the ocean okay the the ocean is
Full of viruses and end
Viruses kill up to 40%
Of all of those bacteria
Everyday
Yeah
And
We know that they have defenses
When Eugene koonin said was
Okay
I'm going to bet that
These bacteria
Are somehow grabbing pieces of DNA
From viruses
And then they're storing it
And now they have a way of recognizing those viruses of
They come in later
Polaroid shots of the enemy
Write know thy enemy
Poster
What do you call the mugshot
This is Eugene koonin leader of the evolutionary genomics group at the national Center for biotechnology
Information
He's the guy that called reference to
Stunk up the whole idea that maybe these bits of virus DNA inside the bacteria
Is the bacteria trying to defend itself
But but really if I if I if I
If I could eat myself anything
It was not so much kissing
Because you know
Read gif
Figuring
How the mechanism of likely to be
So can you
Walk us through
How the mechanism is likely to work
All right
What happens if
You know when the virus comes in
LaSalle
I just kind of
Explodes in Skyrim releases naked jeans basically
If you're this bacteria these things might take over yourself you've got to respond
You can multiple
Weapons of Defense
If you've never seen this virus before using the first thing you do says Eugene as you send out these enzymes
Pack the viruses they're sort of like the ground troops
And they fight really hard
But much of the time
Date fail and then nobody else you are here about
You're not terribly sophisticated fighter so very often
Taurus takes over
Bacteria die
Bought
But there is some
Nonzero probability
Did you actually survive at
If you do then with the bacterial do with sending some new enzymes to basically cleanup
Go out find any stray viruses.
The enemy DNA into
Beautiful small piece
And here he says when you get to the storage part
Does enzymes women take those little bits of virus and shove them into the bacteria's own DNA
Right in those little spaces between the reef
Right there and nobody else
So I use those spaces in my own DNA as a storage facility
You use a different memory device
Cuz here's what happened
Next time that virus shows up
Express jeans everywhere now
You are prepared
This is where the crisper really gets going
Cuz instead of sending out the ground troops were probably going to get their asses beat now you can actually send out the big
Guns
In fact with the cell does it will manufacture these
Special molecular assassins
And we'll give those assassin a copy
Of that little bit of virus DNA it hasn't storage spaces thing here take this mugshot
If you see anything that matches this pattern
Chilling
And these attackers do we know what they look but one of them looks like
Actually looks I would describe it a little bit like a clamshell
Turn imagine Pac-Man become misshapen and rough
Which one of these guys
What it has is
A copy
That virus DNA
It's got the mugshot that is kind of waving around
What then happens is that whenever the Pac-Man bumps into some virus DNA it pulls apart
The DNA
Unzips it
Read it
It's not the right one goes on
Nope
And if that RNA has the same sequence then
Digital locks in the DNA is trapped
And molecular blades
Come out and shop
So this is smart scissors to it's like you're like the thing I got
Snip
All right now we're going to kill
It has to be exact has to be an exact match
When scientist first discovered this whole system
They're fascinated they were like
Still working it out there like I'm okay then
What happens when this happens at 7
Cool
But then
In walks the dude Jennifer doudna with a crazy idea
What are the crazy radical this could be an amazing technology
This is a tool right this is a tool that we can use to cut DNA
Where we want to cut DNA
Her basic thought was when we turn this defense
Into office
These things they seem to be really good at cutting
Give me the only thing to cut the things that are on their mugs
So
Maybe I could just replace what's on their mugshots instead of them going after viruses
Maybe they could go after a gene that causes
Huntingdon
Disease or haemophilia
For example a mouse with something like haemophilia
This is a diseases caused by one bad Gene
So it is you take seasonal surgeon to give them the mugshot for the badge then you stick the surgeon with the new mugshot in Emmaus
Can you set it loose
Just like this program to
Find that Jean and
The scissors will end up
Cutting exactly
Virginia wanted
The bad genes gone
Now the question is how do you put in the good G
Right right
It turns out actually going to Jennifer doudna
Actually not as hard as you would think
Really yeah apparently what you do is just
Throw this new good Jean
Kind of in the neighborhood
Where they will genius
Just in the general vicinity you don't have to get super-precise and it turns out that you know there are repair enzymes that are
Probably continually
Surveying and checking for brakes
She says will happen is it inside the cell
Is repair Crews
Come along to see the break
The CD good Jean just sitting there next to the break to be like all right
I'll just take it in with the pretty guy in this space
So so we take advantage of a natural repair pathway that cells have
Dietrich both the Cutters and the Fig
Yeah now we're not assassinating anymore
Now we're actually
Engineering
Oregon from killing to refashioning
Designing jeans doing genetic
Form of genetic engineering for
30 years yes but
Not like
Genome editing technologies have been around for a long time but none of them have been as powerful as crispr is
That's Beth Shapiro from UC Santa Cruz she was actually one of the biologists that I
Drunkenly talk to it that thing Modern Art Museum I can't even really remember it
What's the evening setting be so vague
Back in the day
This is just like two years ago you would have these jeanatta things you would take one put in a cell and what happened before was
You would give it
Some instructions about where to go
And it might go there
But Michael did somewhere that's a kind of related to where that was
Ridiculous
Not only would it take left Staten Island did not find there but it would have cost you a fortune and taking up 6 months of your time to get that thing
You know it's really easy to just give it that mugshot
And it goes I'm going to find that guy exactly
It seems to be pretty precise
And it's
Cheap like the old tools would set you back about five grand to use them once crispr
The 75 bucks
And here's the kicker says Carl it seems
At the moment that you can take these things out of bacteria
Stickman to almost any other creature
It still works you can use the same crispr system
Can you like do it if
Hornets
Vulnerable in anything I have not I'm waiting for someone to say
Crispr doesn't work in species
And I have not heard of that
So basically what you have for the first time in science
Is Gene editing technology that is
Is cheap
Precise
Possible universe
Jennifer doudna says the moment
Full impact of that
Landed on ER
I really I literally had you know the hairs on the back of my neck worse in
Just processing the fact that this thing exists
You know that you could actually
Program it
To cut DNA and
Just like this
Molecular scissors and I can just program it cuts DNA where everyone
It is amazing
Unless
Think about it
Further
Which we will doing just
I feel a cloud coming in over there
Don't you see I see you
Over there but will be right
Hi this is Lauren from Atlanta Georgia Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloan at www.slha.org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help this summer I'm hosting
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
About what we're calling tiny moments childhood Brilliance basically I want to hear about those times
So did something
It just means you lean back and say whoa how did they do that maybe it was the moment that I can
Kids you've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons and you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed are ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the specific moments where a kid does something super smart
Don't have anything to do with the test if you have a story please share it with us
Go to radiolab.org brilliance
Record short audio message for us
And that's where you live. Org / brilliance
Thank you so much
Is Radiolab on get up and run
Okay so
Clearly the possibilities are there to use crispr
Tree diseases
What if you could
Get a little more fanciful
Write like what if you can actually go back in time and resurrect long-lost creature
Is talked about a lot we Could reconstruct using a computer
What did genome sequence of the ancestor of all birds was and that would have been
Kind of dinosaur
Anime could use crispr to turn the chicken into that thing
For what if you could take an elephant
And
Snip snip snip
Gradually turn it into his long-lost relative
The woolly mammoth
Cuz they're related
But if they're there but if you know the woolly mammoth Gina which they do cuz they
Play Family Guy.
Awesome boner some hair
Then you could
Compare the number of differences use crispr to crispr out
The different parts of the elephant and put in woolly mammoth
If you can infect go backwards in Thai
Time and make changes in obviously I think you can go the other way to item mean
Humans are
Good design word designing animals
So if
It doesn't seem to me to be a
Crazy notion to imagine parents all over the world
Taller children so silencing the short jeans and favoring the taller jeans
Getting rid of wheat
Muscles and going for stronger ones
And on and on and on
And I don't know where the designing stop
We sorta got into all of this with a
Carl Zimmer
If
If you can
Be very very jeans
Specific and you learn more and more about genes over time
Why couldn't you invent
Why couldn't you make a
Pig with wings you you might one day get supposed to get enough to do that there's no Wing in pig lab
You know the best you can hope for right now is a woolly mammoth lab and that's down the hall from where the
Where the the
The real action is is it now there's a hall and at the end of the phone
It may be 20 years from now but that's what you looking at
Well yeah I think but the thing is
Well because you can't make weight
Baby Winnie the Pooh
Just because it's her evolutionary barrier
Okay
Okay I don't think that we need
Federal
Department of Homeland Security I think we're okay there all right
But we do need
Is like
We do need to like figure out what are we going to do about
Crispr
I mean they're going to be using crispr for cancer
Okay I'm going to take me to take people's immune cells out of their body
Unable to use crispr
To basically allow them to make proteins going to be able to
Grab onto cancer cell
And attack their own cancer
What animal are you for that is your you're
Uart Inc
You are tinkering with someone's own body
You are altering their own
Sal's
Dude
Where do I
It's just I can't even with this is
Meet I don't know if it's a religious thought or just
The thought of Atkins
Conservative person
Coming up in the
In the test tube baby error
I now know many wonderful
Adult farmer liter
Test tube babies
I remember being astonished
Set
Knows I can't
I don't know where the sacred begins and ends anymore
I'm not particular.
I guess what I'm instead on is I'm on
On
A hobbesian view of human beings are there
Something about human beings including scientist
Volume means
There is there's a darkness and a light beer
There is an Angelic side to Being Human on his
Very very
Difficult synonym
The human beings get more and more
Create an
Zayn and
Essentially
Creative
Future
The future will include the imaginations both like
End.
Humans
And that would be new in the world
I don't think it is new because if you go back to the start of the Scientific Revolution some like Francis Bacon would say explicitly like
Science
Is
Going to be both about learning about how the world works
And
Using that knowledge
How to control it
This has been discovered this is been published
Everybody knows it
If you if you can send it okay now we're going to all we're going to outlaw.
I'm not the same testing
What what are you suggesting we should
Cringe Lewis A123
What do we do now I don't know we all come
If that's what you are you cringe
You Chris
Shoe creams with attitude
Dial Beijing with with dragons
You're saying
You're saying oh my God
Forget to that conversation with Carl was 4 months ago
And a lot has happened in the
And that time because of the question that you asked like where does the sacred begin and end with one of the lines that have been drawn
By Jennifer doudna and others was that we should not
Use the technology on humans who haven't been born yet meaning not on sperm cells or egg cells
Because if you crispr say an embryo not that is it that is a permanent change
Right that is a change to the DNA that will be passed on to their children
And their children's children and their children's children's children you can't ask
The
Person if that's okay
Because you're doing it before they're born
Send
Becomes a real issue
Imagine making these changes
Is and a cat
Skate through generation after generation
You could affect the evolution of organisms
And it's
I want to say trivial but it's you know it's fairly easy to do it
Wow kind of profound I feel it's really profound
Profound but it was just an idea
That is until for the first time in history researchers in China have successfully edit the human genome in it
Embryo just two months ago
It was announced that a Chinese team used a technique called crispr
To edit DNA in human embryos
Now these embryos the Chinese team if they were created through IVF and they were not viable embryos
Are not going to actually develop into a person so they're they're going to be discarded anyway I can figure it out with those
Embryos what's the stop anyone from going further
Physicians that they crossed an ethical line
Just sort of thing could be sort of a slippery slope towards
Okay
Now that the Grinch party is
It's bread and Robertsons cement
We called up Carl again we have to revisit we have to revisit because in our Armageddon conversation
Getting which I believe I was extremely alarmist and you were extremely down putting I feel that I should do a small
Small little parade
Kobe
Remember the Alamo remember remember China
And you have to close you should just begin anytime you want like getting on your knees and saying how sorry you are going to start from there
I'm sorry so are we actually surrounded by an army of clones with soup
Super powers
Yeah but I think the Dyke has been opened I believe I'm going to quote somebody who said
Maybe a few weeks ago I think he went maybe was last week even writing for naturally
I think it was maybe with somebody named Carl
Who said that the news from China and that news
Could probably
The beginning of an entire New Era and I think I said it was a historical moment
And I and I still stand by that
Do you feel differently now than the first time we talked
I don't feel
Different actually because
Didn't really know
Scientifics
Surprise here
He says people been doing all these crispr experiments and all these different mammals
We're mammals this is bound to have
In fact it may be happening more than we think
One account in the journal Nature has said that for other Chinese labs
They're doing this kind of work
Carlyle Soto
Which she said was unsurprising to buttocks
Surprising that the crispr work this Chinese team did
Didn't work very well
Kind of
I mean in only a few of the cases
Did they
Really get
Exactly what they want
They tried using crispr in about 86 embryos and they only got to work right and maybe 28
A lot of them Christmas made the wrong cuts and screwed up the cells and that led them to conclude that this is a technology that's not
Not ready right now
Replication in the human germline
And
I agree
We still are in this kind of fortunate position where we can say oh well it's dangerous
So we shouldn't
Use it
I am human embryos
I just don't think that we're going to be able to certify find Refuge there in like 10 or 20 years
Dinner 20 years you know christopher wilby
So sophisticated
The people will be able to say
I can get you
The change you want
And I can do it safely
I can guarantee you that you will have human embryos that have
The alteration in the
Particular Gene Yuan
So then what
Is that Jennifer doudna told us that this experiment similar experiments have been repeated in mice
With more advanced crispr systems cuz apparently there
And there it was done with almost no error
Sometimes I feel like we're certain displacing or ethical concerns on to
Something that hasn't happened yet
We really are concerned about what we're doing to the human gene pool you know it's already here
Take as an example in vitro fertilization
About 60000 kids are born a year through IVF and it
Probable that
Some of those
Parents chose what they wanted a boy or a girl and when people start doing IVF there was a huge controversy
See people said this was dangerous
This is unnatural
I don't see
Peoples
Who are unable to sleep at night because of the existence of IVF
Now I'm going to sound like I'm on Roberts out of this I mean okay so
So I don't hurt okay alright okay
So you guys know about all the stuff going on Iceland where they're looking
DNA and you know they're looking for
Disease genes and so on
And
When they're looking at these Icelandic people they found that some people
Had a gene that
Text them
Against Alzheimer
President reduces our odds of getting also
Let's imagine your doctor said no if you'd like
For an extra $1,000
We will take these IVF embryos and we will
Use crispr
To give them the Alzheimer
Protecting
Variant
Would you like that you want to add that to your to your procedure
Or would you like your child to
Two-Face
Teacher of of
Alzheimer's
Your choice
Teachers might here's my thing here is anything with this whole this whole thing
I'm a little bit haunted by the thing you said which is that
When it's not dangerous anymore
What will we do and I'm afraid we've already answered
That question
It's not it's not a
Question that's open NE
Because if we're already doing this kind of
Stuff and who's going to say no to that
Who's going to say no to that
Yeah we've already answered the question
Yeah
We may have
Many thanks to science writer Carl Zimmer how many books you can check them out of car
Call Zimmer. Com radiolab.org this piece was produced by Molly Webster we had original music
By Eric wolski otherwise known as the casino versus Japan special
Does Lee Mcguire Dr Blake wiedenheft
Dr. Luciano marraffini dr. John Burgess and dr. Jen Wei Shi
I'm Jared I'm Rod I'm Robert krulwich thanks for listening
To hear the message again press 2
Delete at start of message
Radiolab is produced by
Ellenhorn
Not guilty
Melissa O'Donnell
County pageant Ariane whack Molly Webster
Jamie York
With help from Gabby Lewis Kelly Prime and Damiano marchetti
Fact Checkers are evil doctor
And Michelle Harris
And this message