Are you awake
Listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
I'm Robert krulwich this is Radiolab and I have the host of note to self with me that's another
WNYC podcast that comes out of here I'll bring it one
Can the brilliant s person who does it all
When your son Brody is with me hello Robert and I asked you to come and just because I wanted you to search set this up
Happy to so we did Radiolab note to self did a joint episode last year called
Eye in the Sky
Disturbing story but
Definitely a spy Thriller and it turns out a lot has happened since that episode was first put out
Urban Development switches
Truly
Surprise me
And I
I don't want to give any details so just listen to what's about to happen to them don't go away at the end stay
Okay
Publican
So how did you guys ever find out about
How to get into it
I think it was somebody was reading about it
This is manoush zomorodi
Was we are we with you reading about it right
MSR producer Alex goldmark
His name is McNutt
Name at least
And dimes please
Like we actually read it and it was
Weird an interest
Staying and brought up
Lots
Technology is remaking what is possible for individuals
And for institutions and for the international order
Young Jedi runtime rubber Co which is Radiolab so here we are at this moment in time where we at we are face
Eastwood these decisions
About what we want our future to
To look like
There are fewer and fewer technical constraints on what we can do
That place is
A special obligation on us to ask question
About what
Should
With our friends down the hall manoush zomorodi and Alex goldmark there in a great podcast called
Note to self pay will be our guides
Into the world
Of McNutt yes my name is Ross McNutt
Sub McNutt
If I refer to him
He's an ex-military guy 20 years in the Air Force I enjoyed it
I did a lot of good like combat military
Yah mean
I think he's actually special
My background I've got a PhD in Rapid product development out of MIT
And what I do is I teach young people how to build new systems
And the new system that's a system that we want to talk about that kind of began in 2004
Ross was teaching a course at a Military College
Was that the Air Force Institute of Technology here in Wright-Patterson
Shannon Dayton does one day in 2004
Are the whole school gathered together
Pharrell
And our commander got up in front of the whole school and said we need to do something
To help the war effort
Terrible violence today in the city of Basra
Cut that time in the Iraq War not going well
Buildings in city streets
IEDs going off
All over the place is going off everywhere soldiers being blown up
Weak I got blown up
Recon
Going to be honest with you in 2004 it looks like we are going to lose
Psoriasis he gets together some of the students on his colleague and they decide Lena let's sit down and see if we can find
Find a solution quickly find a solution
To figuring out who is planting all these roadside bomb
Yeah
Bombs going off of pretty easy to detect
And images
The problem is
How do you go from
Bomb going off
Backwards in time
To be able to figure out who planted it
So
Somehow
It just came out
Are you guys sitting around
It was at a bar
We're working on the back of the napkin
And withdrawing out different ideas and turning around and seeing what happens
They're just like hey let's he's playing just try this let's try that
They had this one stock and we sort of
Through this out on the back of an MBA
Making it
Took a little while
38 students working
Confirm me for 2 years
But eventually they developed what became known as
Project Angel Fire
Outwork you take a small plane and on the belly of the
The plane they hook up his array of cameras
Start the camera system we design and build
Super hayat
Then the pilot
Takes off
Flies the plane High over Fallujah
Military we were up at about 15 to 16 thousand feet to stay out of the Missile Range
On the ground in Fallujah and I look up what would I say
You wouldn't see us
You wouldn't hear us or you wouldn't see us
Over Fallujah circle circle circle
Click
Click every second takes a still image of the entire city of Fallujah 25 square miles
And then teams it down to an operator we take a picture
Process it Down Lincoln
Processing
Down like it
Every single second
To the plaintiff snapping picture after picture after picture
Pictures what makes the system so powerful
The operator on the ground has what say an entire day's worth
Of the high-res pictures of the entire city of Fallujah
I don't say there's an explosion people were killed in explosions at a market
11 others
First the operator would pull up the most current image of the
Zoom into the place with in Fallujah where it happened
And then click
Click click
In one second increments go back in time
And see who was there what happened the last time somebody fiddled around in that
Yeah you like okay I might have gone back to ours and
It's bat car
Fast forward
Click the canal follow that car forward
In time
To see where it goes
You see that it went to
House in another neighborhood 2 miles away
Well that's where you dispatcher Troop
Right then basically we be able to send either the Special Forces then I the Marines in
Intuitive
Take a program
Now look the military doesn't really statistics on how well some of its
Military technology works
But there are officers who will be quoted saying that yeah
Project Angel Fire
Saved
But the reason why we decided to do the story is because it's not just a military thing right like with a lot of
These Technologies they maybe start in the military
But then they trickle down all the way down
Dollar bus
Actually in this case
Trickle-down
To Dayton Ohio
Ross Group Incorporated
Yeah be weird producer and emails and I actually went to Dayton Ohio
To visit Ross
At his best
Persistent surveillance systems persistent surveillance
Rite Aid pills
Orwellian
These are the lenses and the motors here basically control it
The first we went over to his Workshop where he actually works and makes the camera
These are more powerful than some of the best military systems
Like we could see him actually making them and how they get attached to the bottom
The airplane
Oh so many airplanes
Then we went over to the hangar where he has all the airplanes
Beautiful dobro
27 airplane
He owns his own Airport
Yeah
After you guys
Oh my God it's big and then he showed us their Command Center
And this is where you have a bunch of people sitting in front of these enormous screen
This is like your viewing room
Yeah and this is where all the
Plane pictures end up
Because Ross is basic idea and taking this technology from Fallujah to a city like Dayton Ohio
Basically this is just as large a problem
As we doing
Afghanistan and Iraq
Only it's not IED zits
Pride major events this year we've had four officer-involved shooting so far this year are homicides
Interrupt this year so this is Dayton Police Chief Richard Biehl
Talk to him last summer
Couple years ago
Ross called them up
Was like look a city like Dayton Ohio we've got 28,000 crimes a year
About ten thousand part 1
Murder rape
Assault 10,000 part 1 crime
Comes out to be 480 million dollars
A year but McKnight is like for the out the price of a police helicopter we believe that we would be able to decrease
Crime by 30 to 40
Percent
30% decrease
Tonight is 155 million-dollar
The Dayton Police were like
Basically setup
Attest
In June of 20
12 for a five-day flight
Hip Hop
Just see for ourselves
What it was capable of doing
Isn't the plane up in the air
Started doing a thing
Buju
And within just a few hours
There is a
Call of this a breaking entering
In progress
Description of an older white box truck just a regular Brandon moving truck
This is Angie horn
She's the one who called 911
Almanor lunch break
And she
She see the moving van
Pull up in front of her neighbor's house
Guy gets out
Breaks in
Start smoothie
Are we meeting we immediately called the police and they got their relatively quickly from what I remember
He had already taken off
Now normally in a case like this the police would be like
Well how do we follow
We don't know where he went
But in this case
The police contact persistent surveillance systems
Alex blasingame I'm the senior analyst for the company
Words about 5 minutes until he sees this little grainy white. Appear in front of her neighbor's house
Is the vehicle here that we're wanting to Trackside what vehicle I don't I barely see anything so the image looks blurry
But the human brain in the human eyes are very very evolved to pick out movie
You got to understand that from two miles up a car looks just like a random shape
People they look like
Alex has trained himself to
Pick out Lube
How to put a tag down and where he's at places in Orange Circle over that random little shape
And then quickly quickly moves forward forward forward follow him to his real time location
Alex follows it up some roads finds out that it is parked in a parking lot six blocks away he calls up the people in the field
Does go over there they get there they see the guy
Is your truck full of stuff
They send different cap over to pick up the witness
Witness Goes yep that's the guy
Yeah this is minutes later
No kidding
That could have been a murderer
Right I could have been armed robbery
I could have been a lot of things
Sings this is so weird just like having a superpower but it is actually better than Batman you can't go back for the
Time
Superhero
I just feel sad
It's like
We're all just these little dots
It just seems like the antithesis of what a lot of
Police Department seem to be trying to do in the aftermath of
Other
Horrific things
To have happened
Which is
Getting the police
On the streets
Making personal connections
Creating relationship
There's nothing in this cyst
It prevents you
I'm having effective
Community policing
At the same time
Battle by the way this Major Medical
Please help
That community relations
The reason they're putting body cams on police officers
Is try to get the police officers to be
More respectful
Because they can be seen
Well this let's
Watch all the
25 squared
Area
But then you can watch so many other people
Here's other things that people in Dayton do
Like Romeo and Juliet they sometimes meet
Without their parents permission
The playground
Smooch
There are going to be divorce lawyers or going to be
We tracking Aaron spouses there are going to be
Traffic police
Watching who goes through the red light there going to be Realtors were wondering who are how many tenants do
You really have in that building and I guess
This thought might beat it
If the information exists
That will show what my pixel was actually doing
Then then I'm a little less
Free
There is a a clear trade-off between
Security and privacy
And you know
In our major cities where we have
Tens of thousands
The major crime
You are a lot less free when you can't leave your house
Is obviously a
A huge advantage
To knowing what you
You know
But then you say
Huge
Ping
To knowingly
Like knowledge itself is sort of
Is pregnant with
Funny
You know what here's my problem
Potato
Was it all of these privacy
It's like when you talk about these Technologies
Advantages are always so concrete
And the trade-offs
Always feel so happy
Extract
I feel like there is there certain there's something being lost here but I can never quite put my finger on it
Twitter
Oh Dad that weirdness that you're feeling
It's
Can I get
Blue Rat Pack
Hey this is Jenny Lanahan from Round Lake New York
Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloan @www
Phone. Org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here I'm a producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help this summer I'm hosting
And I request for those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
We're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments
Brilliance
Basically I want to hear about those times when I did something
It just means you lean back and say wow how did they do that
Maybe it was the moment that our kids you've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons and you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed are ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the
Specific moments where
Kid does something super smart but it doesn't have anything to do with the test
If you have a story
Go to radiolab.org brilliance
Record short audio message
And that's where you're at. Org / brilliance
Thank you so much
Hey I'm Jared I'm Robert krulwich Radiolab and
Continue our collaboration with manouse emirati and Alex goldmark from note to self and their subject is and remains
Eyes in the sky
In the situation we left it is at mnuchin one of our producers and emails have gone down to Dayton Ohio to talk with Ross McNutt
Check out his technology
How are you feeling
I was feeling like
You have not convinced me I do I am not
And then I saw was Max
And that
Well
I mean that's what made me start to think otherwise
Where is especially the time we did this the average
300 murders a month
52 kidnappings a week
McNutt the gang they got a contract we've been asked not to say
For home
And they went down south set themselves up in a hotel room got the plane up in the sky and then whoever the
Client was started bringing them crime reports
So this is kind of what you never want to see happen but
This is kind of why the system was up
Alex pulled up on the screen is very grainy aerial shot of Juarez
This is where is Mecca
It looks like
Right you've got like grids of streets
Cars and houses and then like over on the left of the screen
Key points to this dark little square
The vehicle
It's going down the
This is a female police officer she was X
Headed to work
On this morning
All kind of go through it here
There's her house
Your car is parked outside
You see that like
Noodle pixel gets in her car
She pulls out of her driveway that was her home starts to drive to work
And then right when
She leaves
If you look up here in the upper left
Several cars were parked
Up on the corner
Soon as you left your driveway those cars be
Become active
So this is a Stakeout
Yeah they were waiting for her to leave
He's so zoomed in that you can see it's like a Tic Tac
Moving down the street
And then two more Tic Tacs come alongside
Until they get right about here looking forward on the photo and you see
These cars just inch closer
What kind of hesitate there which is
Unfortunate
So she's driving down the street
And there's these cars following behind her
And then
There's this car up ahead of her
A vehicle that had been
I'm parked here for
15 20 30 minutes
All the sudden
Backs out into traffic
And seemingly slows them down almost gets in an accident right here
Which gives these guys
Enough time
To catch up
This is where they
Pull up beside her
And then suddenly
Alex says
Right there this is the point
Where the first car pulls up and shoots her multiple times she was shot in the head multiple times in the head right
Right here
She's actually going to roll through the intersection
Her car continues to go even though she
She's been shot in the head
Had there's a parked car behind this tree
And you actually see this
Parked car move
When she runs
And then these guys
Takeoff
It was
Not fun
To watch it was
But
What happens next
Maybe
Really start to understand what this
Technologies
Real quickly
Show you some of the
Ross walks in he takes that moment
Horrible moment and then he starts to like shoot back and forth in time
Before the murder hears his path after the murders
The two cars from that murder and you see he draws on the map you see that they meet up with two other cars
See that guy there that were involved in a different now one murder becomes two two cars become four
Stop and if you follow all four of these cars drawing lines as they move through the city
You find out who they meet up with him for becomes KAIT8 becomes so on and so on and you have all these
These lines crisscrossing the city and then you see that a whole bunch of those cars
Are headed to one play
This house
This house appears to be there cartel headquarters
And
That's when you start to think
Well that's how you have to take something like
This town
It's not
A One-Shot thing like solving the crime
It's about
Cracking an entire system
In fact
This is Andy here at the when I was
Doing some research
Into this
I'd be able to calls and I spoke with this one government
Who told me that this information that rosset
Showed us
It was one of the primary tools
Used to dismantle
An entire cartel
War is in that
Apparently
The leader of that cartel
Was responsible
Something like
Murders
Cigarettes again so how are you feeling at the
This point are you
Happier
Scared
Feel ashamed of myself
Because I thought
All the reason why I'm so excited about it is it
Because it's in a country
Where I don't live
And I'm an outsider and I think of it as being messed up
So it's okay for them
But it's still not okay for us
What did you think any
I mean
Like this is where I
Stop being a good journalist
Because I picked
Decide
It feels wrong
Tinashe
Solve these crimes
That we can solve
And what if his plane is on top of New York
Good
God really
From me it became
Look at you remember like after 9/11 when you'd walk down the street and you cure the F6
16 circling over the city
I just remember the feeling in my stomach was like nausea like I felt sick
It felt
Gross
It felt like we had no
Autonomy over ourselves in at that point I was scared enough that I could live with it but right now I don't feel that way
And
Look at it's a very privileged position
To be able to say that we shouldn't have
I get that
I've became a convert
Because
Somebody got kidnapped today
And if we had an eye in the sky we might be able to get the kids back in a few
Minutes hours
Compared to like you see the stats on Amber Alerts they're not good
What we're talking about is like and I'm not saying that I'm like anti McNutt at all but what I'm saying is like
It's very easy to paint it as we're going to get bad guys and I just don't think it's that Z
McNutt & Co
They seem like decent people they have set limitations for themselves they have said they will not use photography that could get any closer
Leave me the moral choice
How do we know other people will make the same world
Joyce and
Even though this thing might solve
Ton of crime
I save lives
It's still not worth the risk
Because
It just ask
Level of
Trust
In government
That we shouldn't
We shouldn't give
Is that what you're saying
For now yes
So
Back to dating what would happen in Dayton
Well I was pretty impressed
After that five-day demo
The police chief
Richard Beale
I recommended
That we
Enter into
A contract
Is veiled sister
So
They took it to the city Commission
It's minutiae New York
According to Carrie gray director of the city Commission office for the city of Dayton Ohio
The city commission was interested in the in the presentation but they decided that before they go forward they should have a public
So they can
Hear from the
There was about 75 or so people there and he says that the people of Dayton
People of Radiolab
Note to self
I'm very divided a quarter of the people
Work
Supportive of this technology and they were frustrated with the amount of crime their belief was I'm not doing anything wrong
So I don't care what the people see me doing
We want this implemented and we want it implemented very broadly you know Bring It On they were basically
But
Then there was another group
Slightly smaller but not my mind maybe 15% that was the Robert benucch Camp believe
That
This was
Is a grotesque
Invasion of privacy and some of the people spoke in
Very impassioned
Terms
So
Yay
I think they calling it grotesque invasion of privacy would pretty much reflect the weight and the way this group was feeling
And that there was no way that you could trust government
With is volume of information and this breath of information
So you had your Pros in your car
The rest of the people like the majority maybe had some feelings one way or another but just didn't have enough information and
And so they came and kind of
Eye mask Quest
Like how long will persistent surveillance systems keep the images
90 days
How far can they zoom in can they see my face
Know something it'll ask questions
Which carry seems to think that they could have answered they could have gotten everybody on board
But in the end
Even though the room was basically divided into
Three parts
The naysayers we're so loud
And so impassioned
That these would have defined the combo
As we do
So we took that lesson to understand that
They was going to
To be
Some significant
Education that was going to be needed and some significant hurdles that we're going to have to be crossed
Before that we were able to do a broad-based implementation
And
Based on the amount of time it was going to have to be spent
We decided there were other more immediate techniques that could be used it could be invested in
And we took the money that could have been spent on this
And spend it on some other activities
It seems like what you're saying is it like
It was just going to be too hard to get people of the heart also like a snot worth
Yeah
I think that's probably probably accurate So the plan is off
Table saw
It's off the table for right now
But that doesn't mean that it's never coming back on
I think it's fair to say
Frustrating to him
Right now we've got about a hundred fifty million dollars for the proposal sitting out there
For a large number of cities Baltimore Philadelphia to Moscow with their were waiting for them to make
We've done Compton and Jerome
Compton's like maybe or is it like maybe dating is like maybe a whole lot of babies out there
What McKnight and his team were doing now and this is actually what they were doing when we went to visit them
They're analyzing as we are looking at a
Turnpike or something yet traffic in New Jersey
Understanding traffic
We look at congested areas which are typically especially in that part of the country
Exits and on-ramps any kind of Junction in a highway sometimes you just
Ice cream
Since we did that story things have happened manoush
Did they have
That's why I've invited you back
Here to fill us in on further developments of which there have been gigantic one
Very recently yes and McNutt says not just
Since we heard that episode but because we are that
Episode
After this episode first one out
It turns out that there were a couple very wealthy philanthropist listening to Radiolab
And they pick up the phone
They called him and he said
We would like to be the people that bankroll
You giving us a try in a in an American city somewhere
So they he's biggest hits
Will write you a check if you can land the city will give you the money
Pretty much we decided who are these people they are Laura and John Arnold their young they're in their early forties they're
Are in Texas
And by the time that they contacted McNutt
He already done as
As we said he'd already done a very expensive look at
Cities Across the Nation
Looking for the one that had the biggest crime issue and is he puts it the strongest
Political leadership somebody who would be
Willing to put up with The Firestorm that would inevitably ensue Baltimore fit the bill it had a
Mayor who said she was very tough on crime
Shootings were actually up in Baltimore by 72% last year
So he went
Back to Baltimore instead
If I can get the money for this are you game
And they were like
Sure
So the rich folks were willing to give money to the mayor of Baltimore
To put a plane in the sky to take pictures of Voldemort for a discrete. No not quite
So it didn't go to the government or any elected officials
Nobody needed to sign off on this in the city of Baltimore
Other than the police commissioner which is why he was able to do it
Without telling any of the city council members or
The mayor War II Baltimore Police Department without telling the mayor of the city council Rio
Besides the contract with this
Fellow supported by two people in Texas to put a plane in the sky to gaze down in Baltimore in every
Everyone in Baltimore I mean just don't mention this
To the mayor
Did McNutt move to Baltimore and do this
He moved to Baltimore
And they set up across the street
From the police station and had about a dozen analyst sitting there
For two months looking at everything that was going on in Baltimore
So
They did see some stuff during the street like a give me an a example of
Something
Bad that happened this day
Everyone that we know about
Which is that there was an elderly brother and sister the woman is 90 years old
The brothers 82 and they work right there near this bus stop and they actually got in the line of fire they got gun
Down by a shooter
And so they end up tracking a couple cars
But then later they think the police say actually we think he got away on foot
I think it was a witness
On the ground who said that they thought that he had left on foot
And so
Rewind and they see a. Scrambling to get away from the scene
It goes
Down the street it passes a Subway sandwich shop it goes between these two houses
I'm stopped at a car that's parked
And then it ends up at
They later discovered the home of a woman and turns out
Her boyfriend is somebody who has a long criminal record
And so there are over 700 CCTV cameras on the streets
In Baltimore and to the idea is that it's sort of a support mechanism right like they get the high-level then it goes to the store
Street then you got the officers on the ground and then shooter shoots man gets into a car and goes down Elm Street
You have cameras down on Elm Street
And you can see maybe the car and then the driver's license and maybe even capture the face
And did they eventually arrest
This person so he cries
State lines and the FEDS pick them up
Okay so they made the arrest
They going to court and they say to the judge okay we obtain information about the suspect in
Heart to Aspire plane does the stuff that they gathered during this
Few months
Is that now going before judges in becoming evidence and arrests and prosecution
Well not yet we talk to the State's Attorney's office they got a briefing about a month ago from the police about what McNutt had
Been up to
And they also told us that there are five open and pending cases
Where this surveillance technology
With you
The police are using it
And
They say this is the State's Attorney's office that they're looking forward to learning more about what
McNutt actually does
And they are trying to determine whether in fact
All those pictures
Could be used in some way at trial but they're not ready to say yes this absolutely will pass illegal
Muster in a trial
The other objection I guess I was thinking about was that the defense
The people as a matter of Justice as a matter of the Fourth Amendment
So you know this is going to come up with something
Yeah then
The defense lawyers would say wait a second
This
Evidence against my client was obtained without not only his or her
Permission but without anybody
Permission and the entire town
Is now
In a
React searchable
During
Just on sunny days
And did the founding fathers want that to happen he hasn't seen a ton of these
Master violence cases but actually Robert I mean
I happen to have the Fourth Amendment here and I want to read it to you
It's got you says you can't the searches and seizures are prohibited the right of the people to be secure in their persons house
Houses papers and effects against unreasonable searches and seizures shall not be violated and no warrants shall issue
Issue but upon probable cause
Supported by oath or affirmation and particularly describing the place to be searched and the persons or things to be seen
So by that token inside
People to be searched
Everyone in Baltimore
Places to be looked at
Every place in Baltimore
Oath to be
Obtained
Ahead of time
Blanket
That's a pretty radical thing
Yeah and when you put it like that no wonder there's
Very likely to be
Inevitable
Big legal
Public debate over whether this is the answer to Baltimore's crime problem
McNutt says
He thinks very very soon
The police are going to release
An evaluation report
Looking at the effectiveness
Of his Planes
He thinks
That
Whatever Baltimore decides
That's going to set a precedent
For mid-sized cities that are struggling across the United States
I'm rubber Colwich and imma need some Rhody from note to self you can go to
To radiolab.org for more information about the McNutt and also please I hope you'll check
Check out note to self radio. Org special thanks to Alex goldmark also to Dan Tucker and George
George Shultz by the way the piece that we just listen to was produced by Andy Mills he is produced
Any number of Radiolab stories over the years and he has decided to move
To the New York Times
He's been a tremendous Boon to us
Over and over again
He's brought
A worldview
And a sensibility that we can have
Before he can not really
And I was going to work for that obscure newspaper
But nevertheless
We wish him all all the best
And
Thank you
And thanks
I'm here
To register my concern regarding the Airborne surveillance that was discussed earlier
A great eye Littlest restit Play
Do military contractors watch over the globe
I'd also like to register my concern with the
Show called surveillance program stuff of science
Fiction
When Orwell wrote 1984
What policies did Satan have in place to prevent
Using the data
In a racially biased way
To go to the next message Preston the host of note to self
Calling you from the
X4
And I think you need me to tell everyone that Radiolab is produced by dad album Rod filling pieces
Director of sound design store on Wheeler is senior editor Jamie York is our senior producer our staff includes
Simon Adler Brenna Farrell David gebel Max guilty Robert krulwich anemic
Healing La Canasta
Melissa O'Donnell Ariana whack and Molly Webster with help from naggar
Alexandra Lee Young Charleston, W Harry Fortuna and purse
Berlin Wall save and make my name is down to Kizi are fact Checkers are Eva Dasher and
And Michelle Harris
Andy Mills we will miss you by
And this message