Are you awake
Radiolab
Radio WNYC
Hey I'm Jenna Boomer Robert krulwich Radiolab and today we've got to borrow from more perfect we don't have to buy
Going to bathroom or purple
We will we might as well it is our great pleasure to yes
Have more perfect sit on our laps with a tribute to a woman
Who
What you said again last couple of months in last 3 months 2 months less too much she's had three broken ribs
I had two cancerous nodules removed from her left
Long
But despite some reports to the contrary she's still going
Mystery predates the documentary the movie by the
The way
And I think it's still really offers
And a unique portrait of like
How do you actually make change
In the world
Story comes from
You search Julie Longoria
Okay
So let me outline the
Basic dilemma that's
At the heart of the story here and I'm going to put it to you as a question bring it
If you were to
Do a Ctrl F in the Constitution like how many times do you think the words
How
Sex
What is one one time in the 19th
Amendment which
Grants people the right to vote
FaceTime
Really
Yes that's the only time that's the only time which is crazy cuz we are looking.
Is there a sex where that's not sex like gender or something something
Nothing
Is there like ladies in the condition of women no women have a problem
What does that basically we're not in the
Except like in this one little spot
So when it comes to discriminating against women some people have argued that
You
There's nothing in the Constitution
That says you can't do it
Certainly in the constitution does not require sexual discrimination
Discrimination on the basis
Sex
Constitution doesn't require it it simply doesn't forbid it
Fatboy Justice Antonin Scalia
It doesn't mean nobody ever voted for that
Where did you get it from there was nothing it said that I mean not not those words
Possibly but there's nothing that says you can't discriminate
Not on the basis of sex
That's legal editor Cristian farias
We had a 14th amendment that told people that we are
Equal under the law that everyone is equal protection of the laws
14th Amendment
Identify the 15th that's Martha Griffis congresswoman when you think about the history of the Fourteenth Amendment
As legal editor Linda Hershman says the 14th amendment was passed in the aftermath of the Civil War
Along with the 13th and 15
13th Amendment abolishing slavery and 15th amendment giving black people
Free black men the right to vote
If you understand the 14th Amendment to be
A part of that Trio of amendments okay it was meant to
Bring equality to black people
When the Fifteenth Amendment have been written which that every citizen could vote
In the name of Heavens why couldn't women vote
Why don't you why don't you have to have the 19th Amendment
Of course the answer why is he didn't consider women people
There was this basic assumption in the law
That you know
Equality for black people is one thing but men and women
They're different
It was
The case that the Supreme Court had never once met a distinction between men and women in it
I didn't like Wendy Williams law professor emeritus at Georgetown
Ridiculous distinction
The case called Bradwell and it was 1873 or 4
In that case a woman wanted to become
A lawyer
Illinois Bar said and the justices said that that that was a perfectly good rule because
The justice system
Could be seen as not appropriate for women
Now let's jump clear into the next Century here 1948
Okay it was called gessert versus
Cleary that went to the Supreme Court
And the issue was
Weather women could be bartender
The court thought that was
Pretty humorous
That it made sense
That women could not be bartenders
Unless their husbands or fathers
We're in charge of the bar both of those laws
Women are not supposed to be at the bar at either bar
Attitudes almost 80 years apart
Women belonged in the private
Fear
That was not only the place it was built into their
Bodies
And that was the assumption
Bro bong
Long time
But just about
There a lot of women in this country who feel it there
Being pushed around
Things things had started to
Come to a boil
Sex and race
Because they are easy visible differences have been the primary ways of organizing human beings into Superior and in
Interior group
So in the late sixties and early seventies people like Gloria Steinem
No rules other than those chosen from the diseases of racism
Stop sexism up to get some traction
Saying okay
It's time to put us in the Constitution hurry up and historians say it's a constitutional convention for women
I move the adoption of the following resolution
For something called the Equal Rights Amendment
What are your hopes what do you think of it will be ratified the stratified early next year
A1975 it will be ratified
But it's
Didn't get the boats in 1975
1976 will be the year
Or in 1976
4 in 1977 and the movement is stalled
Why what
What stalled
Well
A lot
But much of the credit goes to this woman
Come out in Illinois
Sloppily my husband Fred for letting me come today
I love to say that because it irritates the women's libbers more than anything that I said
She was a lawyer and a
Self-described housewife
Who started a movement
Cold stop
Yaris
The whole thing is misrepresented as a woman's rights amendment in fact the principal beneficiary will be mad
Give man a great opportunity
How to get out from under their obligation
Her position was that the Equal Rights Amendment would actually strip women
The special privilege that they have that comes from being a woman
Why not I think though the laws of our country have given a very wonderful status to the married woman and the wife has a great day
Mini rights
For example she has the legal right
To be supported by her husband
And she said
If this amendment passes
It will be certain unintended consequences
Amendment says you cannot discriminate on account of facts and if you wanted to know
Marriage license to a man and a man or deny homosexual the right to teach in the school
It is on account of facts that you would deny it and that would be unconstitutional under era
And that argument
Caught on
They are things that could happen from the passage of an era time in
None of us would like to see happen generation after generation 2 tier
I think that there would be homosexual to expect preferential treatment
He said that it would endanger you got to hear what I have to say cuz you know what's going to happen if
There will be women and all of my bathroom stall
Capacity RAV4
Had the Equal Rights Amendment passed
Legal editor Lynn Hershman against it would have looked a lot like the racial Civil Rights Movement
But the Equal Rights Amendment did not pass
It fell three
States
Short
To get a constitutional amendment passed without any 3/4 of State legislatures
How to say they wanted
That is
38 out of 50
They only ever got 35
Dude
So the question is
If you want to get equal rights
For women
Written into the law
What do you do
There's no era
The women's lib movement sparked a backlash
What
Do you do
Well
Enter stage left
The notorious RBG
Ruth Bader Ginsburg RBG can do 20 push-ups and not the so-called girl kind snap before
Or she was a Supreme Court Justice or a workout sensation before all that
Ruth Ginsburg
She was
At the ACLU this was in the 70
And one of the characteristics of Ruth Ginsburg which exists to this day
You can hear this
It's the first time she argued in front of the Supreme Court in 1973
When you ask her a question there would be
Silent
Enough silence
To make a person nervous and start trying to help her answer the question
Kuwait
But
We can imagine
It was in one of those long top
At Ruth Bader Ginsburg
Rescued from the key principles behind the era
Repackage them
And March them in through a side door sex like race
Is a visible characteristics
Bearing no necessary relationship to ability
Send library has been the major bases for unjustified for at least
It's like what what exactly did RBG do so let me walk you through an app
It's beautiful
The era fight is underway
And RBG and her colleagues are watching
Right and they're getting worried
What if the array doesn't pass
What are we going to do if that's the
The case how are we going to get
Equal rights for women
So they decided
Okay
As an alternate approach let's go back to the 14th Amendment
The 14th amendments
Immediate object
What's to provide nasty
Protection
For the newly freed slaves
You know which
As we said was designed from the beginning to be only about race
Suggest broader object
The states were prevented from depriving any person
Equal protection
Of the ball
Well
It says the word person
So that
Should include women
If they could just get the courts to see it that way then by default almost
We would have a sort of era
And accordingly
The task
Was showing that the racially inflected
14th Amendment apply to
2 secs the what about the law is she trying to change what what does she want the court
She say she wants the court to say
That sex would be treated just like race
And here's why that's so important
And the court sees racial discrimination happening
Under the Fourteenth Amendment it takes a really hard line
Looks at it really really closely
At least it's supposed to
Whereas other kinds of discrimination
Not so much
Is actually some discrimination is necessary
It has to
It discriminates between 18 year old and 17 year old
Between criminal and non-criminal otherwise
But the courts decided that race is going to be a big red flag
They're going to ask governments legislators presidents
To have a compelling reason a compelling State interest to do race discrimination
Otherwise
It's going to be unconstitutional
With me so far
Yes
To discriminate based on race you need to pass it release
Super hard test
By the way the legal name for this test
Strict
Scrutiny
Call the lake
We mean business there's only like
But anyway the point was
But like they took it seriously
Which you know back in the day they weren't doing with sex
Discrimination at all
Because when legislators would come up with these Lots like this women can't be bartenders law
Supreme Court would be like
You know
I probably have a good reason for that
Listen to review reason it can just be a reason
Doesn't have to be very good this up to be good
We could even maybe even make it up on the fly it just has to be a reason
For upholding this law like in the case of the bartenders law
Bars are dangerous
Women need more protection in cordless be like okay
So RBG needed a way to convince the court
To be as
Intense
About sex
Discrimination
As they were about Reese
How do you convince an audience of men
Were used to discriminate on the base
Sex
Who been doing it for years
How do you convince them
That discrimination is a bad
I think of people who want to keep women down would like nothing better than to women go off in the corner
I speak only to win
Nothing would happen
This is her giving a recent talk about her 1970 strategy
You need to persuade
Men
If this is right for society
Part one of her strategy
Choose your words carefully
The head of Secretariat Columbia
Who said I'm typing these things for you and jumping out all over the
Pages
Texas
Don't you know
The audience you are addressing
The first Association of those men
What the word sex
He's not what you're talking about
So you use a drama book
Charm use gender
Cuz you know the word sex has a charge to it
Gender
Cooler
I'm parked over strategy
Choose your
Paces carefully
This is all happening in the 70
Please when RBG is the head of ACLU women's rights project
So she's deciding which kinds of cases the ACLU is going to support
As they make their way to an all-male
Supreme Court
Your strategy was
If we live in a man's world right now
We need to find cases
But nine men at this moment
Can handle so for example early on in her tenure at the women's rights project the other
Lefty lawyers are suggesting that the women's movement needs to take up the cause of us being right
And she says
Not
Yes and I think
Go slow
Is the right approach
She said first
We need to go after that
Small
Insidious idea
At the Supreme Court had been keeping alive for
4 years old the laws of our country have given a very wonderful status to the married woman
That Phyllis Schlafly idea
That discrimination is actually good for women gender classifications
Will always rationalize
As favors
Two women
And so
RBG decided not just to bring cases where women were the victims of discrimination
Okay
My name is Curtis Craig she brought cases
Where men wear the badge
Who were you as an 18 year old
Now that's a great question
That was like any 18
You're old
Young man
Invincible
Get out of thought I was quite the ladies man if you name it I mean
You made it into Lambda Chi Alpha at Oklahoma State
He was living at the frat house
Arab
A fraternity was
Primarily made up of wrestlers so was when you went down the hall
You're about to be taken down at any moment you be thrown into the wall
You leave a body print
What do you mean like an indentation literally in the wall or like
It was it was amazing
There was a lot of partying going on
Lot of beer yard would be filled with beer cans here's the key if they wanted to get all that beer
They have to enlist the help
Adelaide
Yeah I mean you know the sorority sisters yes you would have a female buy you a beer and you'd go out and
Party they need the women to buy beer in Oklahoma
State at the time
Philly
Girls could buy
At age 18 but the boys had to wait
Until
21 was something about the level of maturity I guess for women versus men at that time
Principal was that
Boys got into more car accidents so they should be trusted with blessed beer
Did that make you angry or absolutely
Well I was extremely unfair yeah I would say
It made I think most men angry at the time
I'm a Supreme Court case
Was born
So the 3rd
60 Boyz
I brought this
Case
To the RBG RBG gets involved in this computer case
Yes but this is this is a this is a situation where women have rights men don't have
Why would she want
Argue this case
Matcha tea want the office
Well
This is
Where
Chris strategy is kind of like
A trojan horse
You look at this case right on the outside
It looks like
A case about men being discriminated
But if you think about it
Beneath that discrimination
Is actually this kind of unspoken idea about women so go with me on this right if men
AR
Irresponsible they can't handle beer then women girls are more responsible and well-behaved
More delicate they can be trusted
With something like beer cuz they want abused it
You know so
With that line of thinking
It's not long before you're
Trying to put
Women
Them from
You know scary places like
Bars or courtrooms for
Political office
Using this case
RBG is able to walk into the court
Is discrimination about men but also the discrimination against women that's
Attached to it
In or inside of it
Clever
We're just getting started
In just a minute
This is Melissa Gutierrez in Evergreen Colorado
Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan foundation and Hanson public understanding of science
Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloan at www.slha.org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
About what we're calling tiny moments of brilliance
Basically I want to hear about those times when I kids you know did something
It just means you bring back and say whoa how did they do that maybe it was the moment that I can
Kid you've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of their musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed are ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the
Epic moments where a kid does something super smart but it doesn't have anything to do with the test if you
Please share with us
Go to radiolab.org brilliance
Record a short audio message for us
Again that's radiolab.org / brilliance
Thank you so much
Jad Robert Radiolab
Telling us a story of a case involving boys
And beer and
Illegal move which reminds you of the Wily Odysseus
Yeah and and that horse it's true
This case rocks that describe became something of a trojan horse
In the battle for women's rights
Know the story of the Trojan Horse maybe you know this it's you know ancient Greece
You got Sparta fighting Troy the Spartans want to get into the city of Troy
Giant walled City
Too big they can't get in
It's so Odysseus comes up with this clever plan
Give the Trojans this giant wooden horse
They'll bring it to their City
Don't think it's a gift
We're retreating
What they thought
Are soldiers were hidden inside the horse will come out
And they will take the city
Now in our case Odysseus is as RBG
She said she's trying to get into is the all-male Supreme Court
What
In order for this
Very
Admittedly imperfect we need someone in the horse to come out the warrior in the horse the woman warrior
And
In our case
That woman warrior
She didn't even know she was going to go into battle
Julia you take from here
So
I got in the car
And I drove a long time tiny little crab
Road
Leading up to
Narrow Street of houses two
Sparta North Carolina
Scott Sparta house and horses and Trump sign
Tractor up
Front
UltraStar
And so I walk up to this house it's this beautiful cream colored Cottage perched on top of a mountain
Wow
Can I come here
Whitney Houston Saving All My Love For You
Blasting
I know I didn't
You Caroline
Hi very nice to meet you and I meet
Carolyn whitener
6 simbi 77
She
Immediately offers me a course
Yeah
Will you have a beer with me
No I can't I'm a diabetic
I can drink a little but not much
What she look like describer
Reddish blonde hair green eyes
Wrinkled and hoops
She has like this
This air about her that she could have been a beauty queen you know
But she also could have been
A car mechanics
So we get to talkin I tell a little bit about who I am about to
The story
She actually told me like a French Lick that I'm proud of the young women I have a granddaughter there
Proud of you your generation they're finishing the fight I started
When I was supposed to be like
No no no no
Stop like your story has like a huge impact on like
Women like me you know
Generate imagine
Embassy my name was never tied in with it
Was always Craig's name
So
You know it wasn't that big a deal
She told me she grew up
Bouncing around different oil
I feel tall is Anna won't feel
Crash
That's what we were called oilfield trash
Batman Carolyn and her brother and sister split the school year between two or three schools a year
Jesus school didn't come easily to her but my dad he taught all three of us had a whale he was a welder
How to work on a car is there a independent and when she was about 13 they moved to Chickasha Oklahoma
What happened in Nola
Oklahoma time.
Is where she met
Dwayne that was a first for I went with they met in high school
And they were roughly the same age but he was three years ahead of her
School and know what attracted you to him
His mind
He had an excellent mind
And he was just a farm boy
With no education
He ain't never went to college
He could have been about
Anything he wanted to Ben what do you think attracted
Him to you like what do you think he saw in you
I was somebody new in town
Talking to Carolina I got to send
She did not have any shortage of suitors betta not married him when turned a thing
And when I married
My husband I was equal to him except the money and he didn't think anybody
Can handle that but him
He acted like he was Raising me and he probably was
She says she was really comfortable with him
Supercell
Quiet Man whiskey
Brilliant mind
But
He just
What he was pure German girl
Have you ever met a German man
Okay they are in total control
And how does Carolyn connect to the case with the Frat Boys in RBT
Okay so here's what happened
It's 1962 Carolyn and Wayne are about 20 years old at this point
Remove to a town called Stillwater Oklahoma
Open a business
Stillwater
Is a college down it's that color Stonegate got Oklahoma State University right there tons of
Fraternities including Lambda with the wrestlers
Huge homecoming drawing over 40000 alumni
We didn't know what homecoming was
Had no idea what homecoming was but shortly after moving to Stillwater
They open the doors
To the honk and holler
And where we went in was just about three blocks four blocks from the college
And we went into business there
A drive-through convenience
Real old gas station with oil pit in the floor years old work
Customers pull up to the side of the convenience store and
The drive-thru
Honk their horn
Holler their order and you'd have to go out and wait on them come back in and get what they wanted and take it back
Took a lot of in and out and in and out
All night long you wear tennis shoes out real fast so he was all sheer energy
Being gutsy
Homecoming night we were supposed to close its 11 the store is flooded with
Customers till
I think
Two or three in the morning they're like thrilled because they've never run a business by themselves before
And all these college kids are coming in and buying Coors beer
Including of course a steady stream of girls buying
Ear presumably for their boyfriend and it is yeah I never did get to see homecoming
All I saw was cars coming in and out
Fast forward a few years
Back at the University Inn at all
Had long blonde hair Curtis Craig buddy named Mark Walker
The time is it a political science class
And the professor starts talking about the whole fight for the era which is happening right at that moment
And at this point Oklahoma hasn't ratified the era
Somehow the conversation turns to
MRSA
Talk about discrimination this beer law
Is discrimination against us in the professor challenged him about doing something about the beer laws if he was go
Going to complain about him
The one day
I was behind the counter people coming in and out Mark Walker walks into the honk and holler the young man
Came in to talk to me she doesn't really have time to talk she's running in and out but
They stood there
Waiting patiently I bet he was in there for hours and he was looking at the beer license you looked at the lights
A nurse is that Caroline's name
Is the one on it
Because actually my husband lost his license after he sold beer to a young man
So he put them in my name
Anyway at a certain point
In between all the hunks and hollers he asked me
What I thought about the beer laws
And I told him
I was very vocal about it I always had been she says it doesn't make any sense we send these young men off to war
We're being drafted at 18 we don't let them drink beer when they come back
Was that jazz
At The Mention the liability issues you have these 18 year old girls coming in buying beer slipping into their boyfriends
How am I supposed to stop at your you can't prove
Who buys what
So eventually when Mark Walker asked
For her help he
Said he was going to do a term paper
She's like sure why not I was always willing to help them
Because they had help
Get started
And I still thought it was a term paper
So was he not being completely honest with you then
Well I didn't hear half of what he said
I was busy every time he came in
So you know
It wasn't that important at the time
So I didn't think any more about it
He left my husband was gone
He was the out-of-state working
And I know I didn't say anything to him about it it wasn't important
You know I just thought it was a conversation
But it wasn't just a conversation
Because before that meeting
Mark had gone out
Looking for a lawyer
That's correct
And Curtis and Mark and the other frat brothers
I tried to race the money that was flawed in a campus town
Her body
Use their last dollar for that last beer
But they managed to find his lawyer who would do it
I'm a sheep
Alright well I'm just Fred Gilbert attorney at law
No big signal nobigdyl
Remember I'm always wearing his military boots
Actually I'm bleeding
Moorim even to the Supreme Court Fred had worked on another male discrimination case
In the past
And this case was pretty straightforward
Most irresponsible and drunken woman in the state could buy it and limited quantities that 18
Well that was discrimination
Become more male rights
Case
What was
And do you remember corresponding with Ruth Ruth Bader Ginsburg
Ruth Bader Ginsburg
Before she was on the court
Somehow Ruth Bader Ginsburg noticed
And she watched
As Fred made his way up the courts
Losing at every level
And by this point
Ruth Bader Ginsburg with head of the women's rights project at the ACLU
She's already argued a few cases before The Supreme Court
Which had in the courts
Slowly
For the idea that sex
Was like race
And she thought that this case
Was interested
She gave protocol
We have a problem in a personal relationship has no question
I was something of an unreconstructed male chauvinist
She was not
Fred did not see this as a women's rights
Was just kind of an unnecessary insult a man for no reason
Looking at this case
Got no Fred
It's more than that
It didn't matter to her
If the plaintiff was a man or a woman because in most of those cases
The discrimination against the man was derivative
Of a prior and worst discrimination against the woman
Here's to the ladies the fair and the weak
How do they do
Where do I find all that energy
That's seemingly inexhaustible store of Pep and Ginger
Again
Bruce was after the stereotype about women that was nestled inside the beer law
That women are more responsible and well-behaved
But in order for her to make that connection she needed Fred to write his brief in a way that would be useful for
So prefer not just to male discrimination
But discrimination based on gender
Well
I supported her
I just never was
Shall we say a militant feminist
To like
Ruth had her work cut out for her
What you was getting sort of used to dealing with these robes
So with other local lawyers that she'd worked with in the past
Ruth have been more forceful
Insisting that she make the argument
But that had backfired
So she likes like okay you argue it right she was afraid telling him that she didn't need to be the one to present or large
Before the court
She was fine if he'd do it
But she very gently very persistently
I was able to convince him to let her help him with his legal brief
Betta
I think it was a
Couple months later cuz my husband was out-of-state every month
Meanwhile back at the honk and holler Carolyn has no idea what's going on
No
No idea
And I got a phone call
My husband was on the phone
We'll have salesman in and I had people coming in and out
And
He was
I right
Furious
I couldn't figure out what was going on she was like
Case are you talking about well he had picked up a newspaper
In North Carolina and a bank
And it was on the front page of the newspaper
With my name and
About us suing
It look like we sued everybody in the state of Oklahoma that was in office
All way down to the
Garbage man he's like
What did you do how are you we don't want to get mixed up in this we don't want her name on this we don't want to make a fuss like this could hurt
Business like how dare you you know I didn't know what happened I really didn't know and eventually she figured out
It must have been that kid came in here
And now it's like at the Supreme Court
What I was back and forth on that phone with him trying to wait on customers and I bet that
I took about three hours and he would not let up I mean he kept calling back and call him back
He called the lawyer he was mad
And then the last phone call he said I am flying back in and he said you pick me up
Couple nights later
Drove to the airport
Picked him up
Anna
He was still mad
That was the longest
Car ride
As they drove back
She says he just
Lectured her
The whole ride
I just listened to him
What did he say
I don't know what he said word to word
Yeah I just know he was strong with what he said
With my husband it was best to just be silent
I was never afraid of him
But
I knew how far to push it
Tommy got from the airport to the other side it was about an hour and 20 minutes
That's a long an hour and 20 minutes in the car where you can't get out
And
Over the course of that hour and 20 minutes
She said something in her
Shifted
And at a certain point she
Basically turned to him and was like
No
Like I know you want me to drop this case
But I'm going to fight this out he threatened me Every Witch Way
I didn't budge
Probably
The reason why I didn't budge
Because he fought me so hard on it
You know I believed in it
That I had never step
Out like that that's the first time I really
Put my foot down and didn't budge
I gave so much to him
I mean
I didn't get a salary for 25 years
I didn't ask for
I figured we were equal
I figured I work the same hours he did
And I figured I stood
Deciding
Not behind him and not in front of them
October 5th 1976
Day of oral arguments
The lawyer Fred Gilbert across very many people that I didn't care for him I didn't care for
He was so
Pushy
Insist
That Caroline needs to come to the
I didn't have the money to go and I didn't want to go and never traveled anywhere by myself what I recall that day
Curtis Craig came to I was dressed up
Suitandtie had borrowed address
Plastic look like leather
Walking up those stairs high heels I remember that distinctly it was so big beautiful building
I felt like I was walking forever up those stairs I was burning up I was sweating
Will hear arguments next
75628 Craig against Florida
Whenever you're ready
Fred Gilbert starts things off
Walks up to the podium in his combat boots
Broad
Females even those are the most drunk
Most alcoholic most immature
Most irresponsible
My purchase 3.2% beer at age 8
Absolutely unlimited point
And by all accounts
You didn't exactly kill it
The words
Justices just kept hammering
Movies age backing track
Hammering
Before the court
What's before the cord is your
Curtis was sitting beside me and I kept punching what does that mean what are they talking about what is that
Mayonnaise kept saying
Be quiet
Who is over I'll tell you
I didn't understand what they were doing it
18 night but she says what caught her ear was a moment when just
Shrine quests when you call me
You're referring to your client who is the tavern keeper
Saloonkeeper
Sognare standing up and corrected him and I've always wondered to this day when I did
As arguments went on Fred did at least try to do the thing that roof when I can
You could pass a law saying
No negro
Compare sex discrimination to race
Discrimination
How this relates to the public thing but the thing is you can't discriminate
Even for something like public safety on the basis of certain criteria
What is the court ever held the Discrimination of this sort is of the same class as discrimination on the basis of race
Got to this court has come very very I ask you a question has it ever held
I just totally
Be treated the same as rice
To make a long story short
By the end of oral argument
Things weren't looking great
4 fret
1.2 even interrupt
A Supreme Court Justice
You don't do that
Denial of fear
It just
Yeah wasn't happening
Well
You win some you lose some
Right
Ladies
What no no no
Here Comes
The craziest part of the story
Double trojan horse horse within a horse because
After the Fred Gilbert debacle
There was another case at the Supreme Court that afternoon
So happened that it was a case being argued
By none other than Ruth
Bader Ginsburg organize I've not forgotten how
To get that August
The same day that was on purpose
Yeah oh yeah oh my God
Genius
You somehow managed to get herself in the port on another case on the same day so I couldn't confirm
Firm that for sure
I don't even know how you would do that but what I can tell you is that
She arranged to go second
Because she knew there was probably a good chance that Fred just be completely incompetent lawyer
Was going to be
You know less than amazing
The car
Was asking him questions he was completely incapable of answering NVM
Turn up to argue her case they ask her about Greg people
Concrete involving
Emails to make certain emails
Discrimination against
My question is whether we should examine that law under the same or a difference
In part because such a loss
Impact against
And then she told Justice Stevens
Even in this case
It seems like men are the ones who are being discriminated against
I need that discrimination is a more Insidious 1
Compliance safety
Discrimination against female
Is it your view that there is no discrimination against male
I think there is
Discrimination against
My response to that
Justice Stevens
That almost every discrimination that operates against males operates
Females as well
Is that a yes or no answer
I just don't understand you and I are you trying to avoid the question or
Avoid the question
I'm trying to
Popeye the position
But I don't know of any line that doesn't
It doesn't work as a
They go back and forth a bit
Jessey Stevens is basically like
Why do you keep insisting on this
Why do you keep saying that discrimination
Against men contains within it
Discrimination against women
You're different and you like no they're not different
Is it discrimination against me
If my case depends on your recognition
That
Using gender
As a classification
Resorting to. Classic
Scotty questionable
And should be
Closely
Reviews
Makes this point again and again
All discrimination based on gender is bad
HP checked with something at least approaching that
Hardcore standard
At the court uses for race
That was really something
Seeing this little woman
Get out
Gmail
Discrimination
I'll never forget that because she was small
Yes
She's so small in person
Had a lot of force
Cases submitted
About two months later
December 20th 1976
Craig
Justice William Brennan announces that the
The court
Is breaking down the beer law
We hold that Oklahoma's gender-based differential
Does constitute
An invidious violation
Billy beer case
Was basically the first time the court
Clearly set
That when you discriminate based on gender
Need to pass
Heart attack
It wasn't as rigorous as race
It wasn't
Strict scrutiny
They settled on a standard that we now call intermediate scrutiny
But pretty damn close
RBG would go on to strengthen the standard overtime
But this was the case
That first
Got us a kind of Equal Rights Amendment
Suicide door
We wish
That the court had picked
Alaska property case
Make that announcement
But of course
Very pleased that
The day the decision was announced
I had just came in from work I was at home
By myself here in Stillwater
She's by herself in the kitchen
The phone rings and who calls
Called
National news call to tell me that
We had one
I didn't ask
What we had one
I didn't ask anything
I just said okay
She hung up
Stood there for a little bit and then Craig called and he wanted me to come down and celebrate with the guys there at his
Fraternity fraternity
She told them
No thanks
And then she hangs up the phone
Did you get the one more phone call
And it was my husband he was in
North
Caroline again
And he heard
He heard something about the case but he didn't hear it all
And he said what's going on now and I said
We won
And he says
Is it over
I said is over
Totally over with
He said good
And he hung up
I fix me a very
Good
Drinks
Vodka and Coke
Set down the middle of the floor and that's the way I celebrated
I drank that drank all by myself and it was over with
It was over with
Caroline says that
Decades
After this case
She didn't understand what it meant
She didn't understand
Is it legal principle or that it ushered in this new era
For women in this country
But even so
In
Her own life
This case
Was it beginning
A couple of years after we won that case
I went into China
Right after it opened up
She saved up money and went with her sister-in-law
Brandon 1
I did I was so curious
And we never went like the tourist went
We get on a train and if we saw something we wanted to stop and see
We would stop
We never had a schedule
And I never did really go to shop I was just
Curious about the people
And how they lived
That's so so much
And I talked to so many people while I was gone
That
It was like a hunger
And you grow from it
And I just wanted to see things
And that was just that just open the doors for me
What happened to Caroline at the end
Xi'an Duane divorce in mm
And and when you and when you said she didn't know
The effector KSAT
For decades like when did she figure it out or what
What what how
So
In around 1996
This professor guy named Bob Darcy called her up
And invite her to speak
At
Class
End
She is kind of learning from the students and from the professor like what the keys actually
We stood for
And then eventually.
Professor Putzer
In touch with Ruth Bader Ginsburg and they meet
Again
In person
And
It's sort of starts to. On her
One of the letters
I don't know if that's the one
When were sitting in her bedroom
She was looking through some old letters and pulled out one with the Supreme Court
Still on it
No I don't have my glasses you'll have to read the cashier Carolyn as I told you in 1996 and we celebrated the 20th and
York Rite vs born
You are the true heroine of that case
Although no financial gain with us
Steak for you you realize the potential the case had in Paving the way
For the Court's recognition of equal citizenship stature of men and women
Wisconsin
Principal
How about I was going to go
Framed
I haven't done it yet
And Ruth Bader Ginsburg I need to get it laminated for I have your Prime
Producer
Julia Longoria
What's her to hits me hearing this episode is
I think the phrase radical gradualism
That I I was trying to Source it before I walked in but there's a kind of did there's an emotional disa
The blind to her approach that I'm just not just in but that I crave
In this in this very tumultuous moment
It also like the empathy of it that's the trick because she figures okay
These guys are going to understand if their group gets
Discriminated against
And it's a very short step to say same same but I'm going to have to live in their heads before I take them out
What is their heads for an advocate
SDF to think about what's going on in the person's head that's across the table from you that you can do some
Nothing in their heads but shaping the world around them see that
That's what brian boitano
Thanks again to Julia
The entire more perfect team check out all the more perfect episodes at radiolab.org more perfect
All three seasons there okay Robert I guess we should go
Thanks for listening