Are you awake
Northern listening to Radiolab
Radiolab WNYC
Okay so we're going to begin with
Conversation between jadco there you're okay there you are
And Lulu Miller
Fiona take your life here on here that you know
She's a writer radio producer co-created invisibilia and. Years ago used to work
Here at Radiolab
With me
Do it and I back when we were just getting started thinking about this series
I blew Cambridge add because she had the story she'd been working on still alive
Inactivate
Wild Boy from Lulu
You got it included in this
Serious you doing
So here we go
I guess so this whole thing begins
With a guy
His name is Mark bold
My fault
Mark bald
Makes you yell diebold
Oh no
Who is the director of the Christian law is
The toot and I met him at his offices in Lynchburg Virginia he's a big guy bald head bright blue eyes kind of be
Babyface yeah okay so I guess
Take me back
Law school that the seeing how old are you where are you
How old am I
It's going to be
About 39
So back in 2010 he was in law school with the Liberty University School of Law
It was his first year of law school he was taking his
Classical Foundation
It's just some of these foundational laws that we have been the basic Brown versus Board of Education
He had this moment that like
We have all probably had
This moment we are sitting in class and you
You're kind of tuning out and then you hear something that's like
What
What it what did they just say
Is Professor had just mentioned the Supreme Court case look for
Spell gazebo
Wasn't Buck V Bell
Infrared for sterilization
I never heard of the case but that
Circassian
What's a 1927 and originally started
Supreme Court held 8 to 1 that it is legal for a
State to forcibly sterilized its own citizens who are demons
Quote unquote
Unfit
Three generations of imbeciles
Exactly exactly three generations of imbeciles are enough
And I was blown away
By that decision
That reminded me of Germany cannot see this
Idea that we're going to
You know forcibly sterilized are citizens of constitutional to do that for the betterment of its citizens for the betterment of
Society but the thing that really shocked him the most which again you might also be aware cuz you are now illegal
But that I didn't know
When I first heard about this about 2 years ago
Is that
Buck V Bell has never been overturned
Totally dumbfounded if you will that we
Bilby
The book
I feel like I should say that like if you look at the law
You will find it there all kinds
The bad
Rulings like that these days
Terrible
Laws
Horrible past
Did it somehow stuck around with the idea is that no one's going to act on it
It just it's just sitting there
So that
Okay so that
Soundbite what you just said
That wasn't enough for Mark I became obsessed with
Obsessed with
Wanting to know more about Buck vs. Bell what is it
Dan today
And that question
Would end up sending mark off on this journey
Pizza places in America
People in America or buck V Bell has not stayed buried in some book
What was Bushey house in here Sterling
What does case has been very alive
And Kicking
I'm at Walters
This is episode 4 of G
Baby Dory from Booboo about sterilization laws in the United States
Darkside attempts to measure the human mind and fit people into boxes and
Reaches out into the present-day in ways I honestly never expect
And also
Because the story of how we got the buck V Bell
Is all tangled up in the history of the IQ test that we got into an ER first episode
It begins with this guy who sort of moons over all of it
A guy I first heard about from writer Siddhartha Mukherjee
Francis Galton
Yes galten
British gentleman in the 1880s that is historian Paul Lombardo
Anyway Francis Galton he was a British scientist
Have a polymath categorize a revolving thing
Walked around London with a pen in his pocket and a piece of paper
Quantifying the number of women that he found her attractive
On the left side of his pocket and that's in the Box full story and on the right side Fifi women that he did not find it
Attracted to get a statistical measure
IOffer tracking
Everything kind of crazy thing is that he was related
To Charles Darwin cousins and publishes his Opus on the origin of
Species
Princeton picks up his cousin
Isabella
And I could completely shut him
And his idea was that this mysterious Falls of natural selection which seems to kind of invisible
Naturally
Sheep creatures into their most perfect
Formed
Man could harness this
And do the work of nature
Faster
Better
Because through his measuring the statistics his research cotton had become convinced that it wasn't just
Unilec
Physical traits that got passed down from generation to generation
But also mental traits the ability to think clearly the ability to remember well
Almost certain all those things
Could be inherited
And not just physical and mental but moral characteristics and traits could be inherited
If you could measure everything is good measure these human qualities
Then you could read people just like you bread animals bring out the ones you don't
Selectively eue really thought that he would make a better human race and he comes up with the word Eugenics which is Greek
For good birth
Is that what eugenics means
He wants Eugenics to be a program of better breeding
City Stars unit touring Europe giving these lectures on this idea of
How you could create a happier healthy
Her Society any publishes Magazine with posters magazine articles about it for describe
Or how this would work
Practically like how we go about doing it
Yeah he this
Part I feel like less people know about he actually goes and writes
Sci-fi novel
Called
Hats they wear
Can't say where
And just never published it
But his and then after he died his Anis
Tried to destroy it but a lot of it has been salvaged and typed up do you want to hear some of it I actually have it
Should say I really am tempted to do this in a Brit fake British accent but what do you think
Okay okay
OKC
I should say that they lay much
Aesthetic side of things that can't stay where
Sunset in a fictional town called can't say where
Of the girls make the people themselves of can't they where he described them as promising mothers of a noble race
The good stock has for the men they are well-built
Practice both in military drill and Athletics are very handsome and very loyal but very modestly dressed
Gay without
Frivolity
Friendly without gush
Urgent without
And see if they never they never gossip hello just boy and an awkward girl
Hardly exist
In this place
And the reason why people
Are so perfect in can't say where is that everyone who enters the society has to take
All sorts of physical test medical test
Athletic test
Static test and
If you do well
You're giving all this money and encouraged
To have tons of babies
But if you don't do well
Such persons are undesirable as individuals
Dangerous
Community you are sent to a labor camp
Told you are never allowed to have babies
And if you do the crime against
The state it is considered a
Criminal act
Owing to the Practical certainty that they will propagate their kind if unchecked
So go strolling around with this
Fanciful idea
But people thought this is a very good idea that I caught fire intellectual Scholars science
Just came to celebrate this idea
Write the missing right
It is not my friend it went to
American
First
So
This was something I did not realize at all there was a huge
Eugenics
Praise in America
Early nineteen hundreds
And what historians have explained is that there were all these
Things
Going on
There was this
Wave of immigration there were
Yes just after the Civil War so there
Freed slaves integrating into
Society there were Christians freaking out about crime and
Promiscuity and drinking and
So all kinds of people really important people
Thought that these things were problems and that the way to solve it
What are eugenics
And that one of these people with whom I'm writing a book about
This is how I cry at all this so this is your Stanford guy
I'm not seeing about this guy David Starr Jordan yeah
My dude was like one of the earliest loudest most
Powerful proponents of eugenics you can see like in the late 1800s which is decades before most
American nugenesis got the fever he's slipping it into his courses at
Stanford so he's like telling
Smart
People these ideas that
Poverty is linked to the blood
And can be exterminated. These ideas out in front of like
Benjamin Franklin's 200th birthday party in the late 1800s where there's hundreds of politicians gathered
And he says
You know
This is a matter of life and death for the nation
And
He said that the Republic will endure only as long as the human Harvest
Is good
That's a horrible
Vista
What's the weather
Then you decide to write a whole book about it called the human Harvest and holding it right here
Portable title
It's
It's it's horrible inside
She told to scare people he tells people about this town in Italy called aosta
Which four
About 1300 years was the start of refugee
4 people
You know with disabilities or deformities people send them there in the church would take care of them and then they can often get married in the
Work the fields and have families in their helps by the church and some people see that as this beautiful tail
I like helping society's most vulnerable and he went there and he wrote about it as a veritable chamber of Horrors
Basically he says he describes
The people living there and say they have less decency than the pig
And he like
Says that it's a different is a subspecies of human
And he said this is where you know America's going to be going if we don't take
Action
Which
I totally did
So that day that I was with Mark gold he drove me to this place that it's just a couple miles from his office
Call the Central Virginia Training Center
It's ominous
It is
Campus on a Hilltop dozens of brick building
All turrets
They're all starting to rot iron to become dilapidated as you can see these are some of the first buildings there's acres and Acres
Acres here at one point
Place was
A very real version of Dalton sci-fi
Dream
What does it say
This is established in 1910 as the Virginia state epileptic colony
The center admitted
Its first patients in May 1911
Sony richmeister persons with epilepsy
Began accepting individuals with mental retardation in 1913
A very little in there about the start of sins of
Of what
They've done in the past nothing in there
Was established in Beijing
Can really as a
Eugenics facility in the condos at the colony really for
There
Epileptic
Cope feeble-minded
There's nothing in there
That really
Talks about it
Its main purpose was
How's individuals from the community in in
Strip them from society and put them here
So they don't propagate their kind that's really the
The fundamental
Reason for its existence
And this Colony wasn't like alone net worth
Tons of them popping up all over the country like
Is high-walled
Holding tanks
Where people would be kept away from the rest of society
And in some cases
Sterilized
Which
When you think about what that really is
It's a form of extermination
Like
Fully wiping out
A certain kind
People with disabilities
People with mental illness
People who are immigrants
People of color because they were are seen as
Not good
This is Ivan Nova Smith and activist Advocate and
Historian the University of wash
10 inch explain that people who arrived at these sorts of
Colonies would be given
Extensive
And they had different categories
And they use this concept called mental age Theory
To explain these different categories
Moron
Imbecile idiot
And these were all diagnostic terms that were used to put us in it
The two cents
And then we used to justify
Austria still alive
Do you said us
What do you mean by that
That's why I identify with the until I saw disability Community I want to bet that I would have
Bald cat
I'm autistic
11 twice with disabilities
Do you think
In the eugenesis
This day like
Would you have been someone who is sterilized
I think I would have
Because
Are they there
They honestly it cuz the sterilization Ebola to the early 20th century because
We will more likely to be sexually active
Savannah
Ghetto game
Judo fighting boys
Boys by the girls you know which brings us back to Buckley Bell was she house in here Sterling
Any particular
The kapok was a girl who grew up in Charlottesville Virginia
Is born in 1906 and she's mostly raised by her foster
Your parents
She lived a kind of
Totally normal childhood saying in the
Church choir
High School
But when she was 17 she said she was raped
And she became pregnant out of wedlock
And as a result her foster parents sent her to the Central Virginia Training Center which in those days was called the
Colony
For epileptics
And feeble minded
And when she got there she met this guy
Superintendent
Albert
So Albert pretty was a passionate eugenicist
And at the time 1924 there was starting to be some pushback
About Eugenics from churches social institutions politicians
And so
Pretty was on the hunt
For the case
That would help to legalize
Eugenic sterilization at the national level
I'm pretty mcherry he felt like
She had hit the jackpot because he realized her mom was there at the colony her name is Emma buck
And she was allegedly a prostitute so
Did Carrie tested deemter feeble-minded
And then when he heard that a social worker had called carry bucks baby the product of this rape
Peculiar
He believed he had on his hands proof
At feeble-mindedness or unfitness
It linked to the blood
So he found her
He gives a he arranges to have a lawyer appointed to her you have to get up before you sterilize you have like a mini trial
And so the lawyer appointed to her was the sky Whitehead likely are you dentist
Didn't give her a good defense
Didn't call forward any witnesses that makes it all the way up to the Supreme Court
Where we get that ruling
Carrie and Vivian
Is 3 real people and people make it nationalized it where you could sterilize
I say so her case
Pave the way for over 60000 sterilizations
Performed all over the country and that ruling
Still sits on the book
Today
Never over
Well
All right
Knuckle crack we have made it through that horrific history we're coming back
Too bold
Coming back to me
The Bold
Is sitting in law school
What
Exactly just
Totally
Dumbfounded if you will that we can go to professor and he's like how
Never been overturned and end in the professor says
Every
State has since overturned it
So it hasn't been overturned because we don't have another
Quote case or controversy
Before us
Which is you know the thing that like all the legal Scholars they would you like was technically
Extended kind of purgatory don't worry
I ain't stupid
Stupid ruling
Like
CarMax
Brat Twitter
Which basically like Roundup a whole bunch of citizens that are American citizens but
Are Japanese
Japanese American
For no other reason than their Japanese that's constitutionally wrong but they did it
And it's still technically good law so it's kind of in that like
Oh that sucks.
No it's like I've been there other case
This is the other really terrible
Positions that are in that space
So that
Tons of people said that
Tim Tebow
The thing was that
Well a lot of my free time if you could say that as if you don't have enough
The doing law school right
Just started searching the the code of each state
Using keywords of feeble-minded and undesirable and sterilization and Eugenics and it's
Start looking at each and every state law alphabetically
Arizona Arkansas California Colorado Connecticut Delaware Florida Georgia Hawaii
Idaho Illinois Indiana Iowa Kansas Kentucky Louisiana Maine Maryland Massachusetts Michigan Minnesota Mississippi going through all the codes
Searching New Hampshire New Jersey New York Carolina North Dakota Ohio
Daniel Island South Carolina South Dakota Tennessee Vermont Virginia Washington
Finally
You gots to
West Virginia and
There he sees it in this West Virginia Statute
Chapter 27
Article 16
Entitled sterilization of mental defectives
Talking about sterilization
For the best interest of society
The year 2012
Totally dumbfounded
Something in the code that basically still said
You could be forcibly sterilized if you're unfit something or
Then you in the best interest of society can be sterilized
Like oversight
Fortnite in use so he didn't know what I did is I wanted to find out
Do we
Don't do that
If I was a father
Oh babe
Childhood
Had a disability some type of intellectual disability
Can I forcibly sterilized my daughter
So you like to get himself in his own where he
Wants to pretend that he has an adult daughter over the age of 21
Who he wants to sterilize
So I called this Circuit Court
What we he was
He was pretending so he's doing kind of like a sting like a one-man staying like let me see if
I called the state house and say I have a daughter who wants
Sterilizing
Will you do it for me or is that legal
Any record the call if you would like to
To hear it from you
Yeah that be great thank you
Thank you think maybe the second time
Justin Mark I talked to you earlier this morning here when I was
Driving you called and you
Told me to call you back if I had any questions or
What have you it is in regards to
My handicapped daughter and sister location
So I'm
Now have the chance to obviously sit down at the desk I took some time off work
And wanted to
Find out what steps
What
Come to me
I don't think
Can I have a problem
Okay
I'll get it to her and she'll give you a call
I just write a letter it is that what I need to do
What she says most of the time the judge that this was 2012
Yeah
And under that motion
Okay so safe mode
The number on the bottom
Okay this is not a
We're not going to be the first one to do this okay that's white because to us we feel weird about it you know what I mean it's just
You're not the first one
Exactly I don't think people understand this type you know these type of people they're difficult
Okay
Basically the answer is a
Resounding yes
Needs to be done
It's common
Don't worry about it I even
Concern but what if people know with my neighbor's no no
No it's sealed
And get everything
Okay alright well thank you so much okay alright bye bye now
Get the guy
Really quick a couple of things first of all to be fair to her
It is not officially her job to judge whether or not so much to be sterilized it's her job to get that
Question to judge
And second of all there is a legal difference
Between sterilizing someone for eugenic purpose
For the good of
Society
Like there's something wrong with them that may
He passed down to the Next Generation and threaten the race
Versus sterilizing someone for their own
Quote unquote best interest
And there actually are a number of states today that allow
For a parent or Guardian to have their disabled child sterilized
For medical purposes
Even if that person doesn't give
Cuz if they have a child they might die, thing
Yeah and some of the laws even talk about that person's inability to adequately care for a child
Do you think the woman who is
Responding to mark
Sing oh yeah we've done this before with that kind of case in mind or with more Eugenics beef-flavored case in mind
Honestly I don't I don't know I was able to find her but she said she couldn't comment on this
Case for the story
And numbers
How frequently sterilizations are done
Are really hard to find
But what is clear is that at the
Time of that call the lies It Was Written In the book
One of the reasons why a judge could approve of a sterilization
Procedure is and I quote
That the individual is mentally impaired and that such defect
Genetic nature that it's likely to be passed on to any children
Which is just
Pure eugenic
Reasoning
Right so it's
The general welfare what's in the best interest of
Society not about what's in the person's best interests
And so I found a disturbed
So he was
Horrified
And I wanted to put the nail in the coffin. He also this was kind of his like
Hero Genesis moment is a press release
Wanted to pick a fight
The Christian lost his considering suing West Virginia Etc universe
Eugenics forced sterilization law
The Charleston
Gazette pick it up
And his idea was
I was really hoping
That
State
Wood
Innocence defendant that we can together
Get it before this
Supreme Court said hey
Overturn this
So his dream was like
I'm going to reach out to West Virginia and say let's do this thing and you defend the law
And then we'll get it the Supreme Court has his legal strategy was
Suet
Make them up to something and just going to work its way up
But right after the article came out before the legislature and they just unanimously refill this
How fast did that happen with notified about a couple months after
Immediately
Overturned because they were like we're West Virginia we don't want to be seen as up
Holding
Eugenic sterilization
The great for the people of West Virginia
But Mark's bigger plan to overturn Buck V Bell
Spoiled and so
He starts thinking all right if I can't
Find Justice for people in the future
I reach back into the past
If I find it there
Will join him on that search after Point Break
Play Radiolab
It's Audrey calling from Asheville North Carolina
Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan foundation and Hanson public understanding of science
And technology in the modern world
More information about slow at www.slha.org
Listen to your favorite podcasts on any device
With Pocket Casts
You can start an episode on your phone during your commute
Pick up where you left off on your laptop at work then finish at home on a smart speaker like Alexa without missing a
The beat download Pocket Casts today for Android or iOS and find us on the Lexus Chromecast Sonos
Apple watch and carplay
Learn more at Pocket Cast. Com WNYC
Hate this is Radiolab we're back with Lulu Miller Story for G
Before the break
Mark bold had gotten his West Virginia law struck down which he was excited about
But it also meant he couldn't use it to challenge a buck V Bell at the Supreme Court
Alright so mark
Start noticing that West Virginia wasn't some kind of outlier there were all these other states that had their eugenic sterilization
Laws on the books until the 80s 90s
Thousands show
I started looking into finding victim
Thinking he could maybe do something to help them
Get them some money
Something
And pretty quickly he found some people
Regency you introduced me to a bunch of them including this one woman and a seal
I don't know how you feel about pie
Coconut cream
Who is just a couple miles from the Central Virginia Training Center
To the Colony were Carrie Buck was sterilized
She's a sunny two bedroom apartments
Philipp Plein
With two birds actually
Her best friend Mary who she met at the Virginia colony
When she was young
We will keys in the throat
Pokebean hats
V1
Small Ebonite
Can explain it growing up
Her family was really poor
And think of their parents
Forbade
Dead drink all time
And all these she said that she and her brothers
Like often didn't have any clothes
300 Club of David have one of the neighbors
Reported that the kids were living it up
Pain behind house
Jibacoa now
Heating up and pretty soon the authorities came
Take them away
And I was 7
Do you remember that what did they come in like a police car or truck or
A prank call
Gino Brothers were driven to the Central Virginia Training Center she's giving a bunch of tests
And they decided that Anna was
Feeble retard
Yeah
They issued her an inmate number
Cut her hair to happen
They were often forced to wait outside in the cold rain to wait
Food
It'll work with Note
Hey
Years went by
And I was told she could leave
Agree to be sterilized
But she said no
She had always wanted to have kids
And
So she said no
And ironically all that time her job at the colony
Care4kids
I just get mad for no help getting back up at night
You would give them a bath
Alipay
That one you know
Yeah
And one day when she was 19 years old
Two nurses came and said they were going to give her a checkup
And they gave
You should give her a math
I wish she thinks was ether and she felt the world slipping away and she was like
She figured she was being euthanized
I woke up and did you know when you woke up when it happened
What is it
Is it still do you still have a scar
I'm feeling very upset you know
It's over about two years mark
I found about a dozen people who'd been sterilized in Virginia if you know what my
Listen to them tell their stories about how they were taken from their families and in what happened here
And you know
If he goes down to the Virginia State Assembly General Assembly
Bring them rexana with him she remembers it
So what
He wants at this point is an apology
He wants a bill
To get some type of compensation
4 victims who were forcibly sterile
To go down to the Virginia state government and he makes this appeal he says Virginia was where the first supreme court sanctions there
Elevation happen
Virginia should be the first
To compensate
Victims
And they basically pass
Like I said no thank you
Yeah what did what did they say in his opinion he thinks it was
Pretty much about
Money comes of conservative but it's so fiscally conservative
So frustrating about this was that he didn't really have the support of like
People
People who
I'm Republican just a phone just
For what it's worth
We have this idea of pro-family and here you have these guys please Champion that one more profound how about the right to have a fan
Taking a babysitter pro-family you know
Get pro-life about the right to give life
I'm saying
And
So just saying so hypocritical to me
Just find it
Repugnant
Still make me angry
To this day right face change it's like a
Install this app
Yeah yeah because
The house budget set aside about just a few months later
Shalimar schools with the justice for sterilization victims project
Carolina
Providing relief to those citizens
That this state has injured
Is the just
And righteous
Things to do
Time is running out
And they award everyone who's been sterilized
$50,000
And they say they're sorry
And then a couple years later Virginia passes it but then Virginia only gives $25,000 which
You just felt like with such an unnecessary slight
But
For Anna we got paid
So what does that mean is it like
The help
She gets about $50 a week
And she uses it to
Help with the groceries
The Bells
Medicaid
And she used a chunk of it
To treat her friend married to a present
Oh hello little okay
After married got some hard news
She went out and got her a hamster
Sugar Puffs
Sugarfoot
You should get the cheer her up
And spend their time hanging out with their neighbors
Seacoast Church
Giphy the birds
Did you do that one
Yeah I did
Colors okay what's this guy
A bear
Surfing
Embear to
And his foot swims kayaking
Wow they're really bright
Does that mean she takes care of her best friend Mary do you know when I was there she was constantly getting up
To refill Mary's
Drink may walk with a cane now and aniket
Refreshing her glass of ice
He
She even set up Mary with her most recent boyfriend
How do you know if I had you Rita
But this is a looking for friends or friends
But how much is this apartment is filled with laughter and life
Can still see that this loss
That
Really
She carries it
Okay so what's up so what are we looking at
We we got
Owl babies
Doll babies on your bed a boy and a girl
Good evening
Yeah
F Bobby
Bobby
Edible Mari
That's married and one who's this Anna
And who's is yours
This mom will hear
Yours is married
America's Inn
Incident
She said she brings a doll with her to church
On the bus
Do bringer like
Shopping grocery store
FY
I mean is it like
I want to happy if I could then I want to you know
Settle down and getting married
Butt enhancer
Is it kind of like she's become
A kid
Yeah
Music ID
For me
What
Downs me the most is like
The way that you're Genesis talk it's always about the good of society saving the race saving the nation
Obsession with the future and with perfection a master race
They say that it's
Science
That if you just look if you read Darwin and you apply his principles this is how we make a better race
But the thing that like they all
Somehow happened to miss
In On the Origin of Species
Is
How
Frequently
Darwin talks about 1
Sing this one ingredient
That he marveled that he doesn't understand why it's there
But it is the thing to which we all
Oh
Our existence on Earth what is that one ingredient
Variation
It is the engine
Of natural selection of of beings being created more perfectly it when it is what
You know when a gene pool is
Two homogeneous it's weaker and so the Genesis by breeding out
Variation
We're in a way for oiling their very own plot
Building a master race
Yeah
Like who gets to say what we need
You know
Does the humidity built into it
The theory of nature
Selection
Yes it is immediately
Immediately distorted with social Darwinism
Rightly but we decide
Exactly and I think that often times
The story seems like it's past tense like it's over
But that hubris is
Still
In our laws today I mean I talked earlier about those laws which are
Supposedly different from the eugenic sterilization laws
The laws
Where you're allowed to stare like someone in their best interest
Does
Statutes are so controversial
As Paul Lombardo explains when you really dig down into the language these laws are still saying
There are sometimes when we should be making the decision
For someone else
About whether or not
They should have children
I think your inclination is correct there are reports of abuse and there certainly are opportunities
For abuse in this case
These are powers of the state which we should
Which way should be incredibly
Suspicious of
Hey this is Pat I did I just want to jump in quick
I have
Personal this destroys so intense
But I guess I just kind of one question at the end of that about that last thing you're talking about Lulu
Yeah
So so they're these
These laws that are different
The new eugenics
Sterilization laws bat
I guess still allow for
Involuntary sterilization like
Buy a parent or Guardian
I guess I just wanted like to have you heard of that
Yeah I know I talked to parents I talked to parents
Do parents actually who are struggling with this
Right now
Are you talk to a mom who has a son with severe disabilities and
Approaching adulthood
I'm she's like watching him
Piano grow into a man's body with men
Desires and thinking about sex
And she's like worried that he would
Get someone pregnant
Beyond wearing that like
She doesn't think there'd be any way he'd be able to care for a kid
I'm so in her mind she has entertain the thought like would he
Audrey be able to live a freer life
If you could have sex and have romantic relationships without the worry
Of getting
Somebody pregnant
Yeah
Yeah widget that is just like a
An impossibly
Difficult place to
Sitting as a parent
Yeah I think
That there are
Parents family members grappling with this question in a really private
Hardway like
Is there some wine
Where someone is so severely disabled they should not be allowed to
Kids
Okay so no type of situations
This is Ivan Nova Smith the historian and disabilities Advocate we heard from before
When I talked to her about this she says that when it comes to looking for that line
I think it's really dangerous
Cuz that line moves
And so
Alvin. Lying
Is it
I get what you're saying that the needs to be aligned and needs to be
Some point
But
At the same time
My fear in
Meaning of people in the disability community
Is that
Is ABBA today and it it all depends on like
The policy is in a politics in the couch deciding where that line is a
Parent Guardian someone appointed by the
All of that is scary for us I guess for the disability community
It's scary to talk about the line because
That means we have to leave somebody out
Ivanova says if she had been born in a different time or even
Slightly different circumstances
She would have been love
If I had not been adopted I would have been way below that lot
Wow so where did you go where were you in order
I was
In Soviet occupied last
Pheaa
I was born with
Club feet
In both of my feet
And they diagnosed me with my developmental disabilities
And they diagnosed me with autism in
I never learn my native language
Because the the orphanage was never able to teach me in my native language
And I'm living the word from you weren't speaking
At all I want I was ovulating when I 5 and 1/2
And soon after that she was adopted by an American couple I can't walk
Statistics
And
Eventually learn to talk
Went to school which could be
Difficult because she put that she had a very visible disability
Does she be sitting there in her chair moving her body back and forth
Ways up my movement solids
Kind of
Awkward had learning disabilities
I have a hard time
Regulating my emotions sometimes she have little Outburst break down in tears so sometimes I need lights.
Supporting
She kept going
School eventually started dating
We dated
For ten years before we got married and then
I had no idea that that one Valentine's Day that we
Decided not to use a condom
In 2017 she got pregnant
And she was terrified
Dilaudid my prayers
Well-liked
Shouldn't have kids in
Her whole life basically people have been telling her like you can't be a mother you would be dangerous
And she had started to believe that I agree
She worried about all these things
Yeah like I wouldn't like I would forget to feed them
All like
I have depth perception issues
I feel the songs like afraid that I would like Trump over them
All like
Drop them
And worse than that I don't understand other people's emotions
SOI
Mascara that I would not have that nurturing
Feeling like she look at the baby and just filled
Suffused
Nothing
Phone number calling my mom when I found out that you know I was pregnant
I told my mom I was
Scared but my mom was like
I'll be here for you in
We're going to get through this and this is going to be a minister we are so excited like they was so excited
When I first went to the doctor to confirm the pregnancy test there was a nurse trying to give me paperwork
About the abortion pill
And I said it to them then
It looks like human being inside me
I'm going to do my best to love them I'm scared to death I'm terrified
But I'm going to do the best I can and I didn't stop really enjoying it
Until she came out of me
As I put it on me
Little tiny little thing looks little peanut
She has the biggest eyes like I usually cannot look at people in the eyes
Butthole eyes which is so big
Assume
Why I'd at me
And
Have
I just
I like all of those like Natural Instincts I think it is
Came up once
I knew what to do
Go to cuddle her and snuggles snuggles
She doesn't care that Iraq and see the care that I talk to myself seats at the happy little snow
Not going to see loves me unconditionally and
I love hun
I think she's made me a better person
Creating that little human
It was the most amazing moment of my life
She's just such a blessing
You know I can't imagine life without that little girl
And
It'll do that was at one time
Well I would have been told that
It would have been for my best interests have been sterilized
What do you say to somebody who just says you know
Oh
You you know you rock or you stem and you got you get so you have a meltdown
Getting on the bus
You might not you can't drive her and
And you shouldn't that they worry about her safety on and what do you see
Say to them what do you say to someone who's still
Thanks
Ono is your little girl going to be okay
Senior Care
I would say to them that
Do you see that my little girl's face
Peanut
Tattoos
Do you see that one
She's laughing
A little heart out I'm giving her a hug
Yellow cheeks
Do you see that when
She's coming to me saying
Moody moody moody
You know
That's right
Yep that's yellow that's the OG
I will I will tell them but to presume competence
Step assume that we could be good parents
Give us a chance
Reporter
Lulu has a book coming out soon it's called why fish don't exist and it's all about the
Dangers of trying to order the world partly about that scientist David Starr Jordan and partly about home
You can find a link to pre-order it on our website radiolab.org
For hers Liu x twoo.com
This episode was produced by Matt kielty Lulu Miller and me
And special thanks to Sara luterman Lynn rainville
Alex ministered Steve Silberman and Lydia XZ Brown
Who is reporting was partially supported by the international women's media Foundation Howard G Buffett fund for
Journalist
And Radiology is supported in part by science sandbox
Simons Foundation initiative dedicated to engaging everyone in the process
Will be back next week with V episode
Pubg
To play the message press to start of Messi
This is
Ivanova Smith
Radiolab
Was created
Dave
Albemarle
Is it supposed to buy 7 wheelers
Dylan
This is our Celestial of sound design
Susie
List his book
Is on Saturdays Paducah
Falstaff include
Xiamen
How does
Becca
Bristol
Test this
David
Google
Fastenal
House please
Lacey
Hunty
Zola
Stella
Goatee
Costless
Banana
Galen
Less
Nessa
Melissa O'Daniel
Barrel
Bella
Going
Alina
Why
Walker
Is Molly Webster
With the help
Fila
Only
I eat
The View
Heavy
Fortuna
Boots
Samuel
Moana
Linda Linda
Neil
Does salsa
An All-Star
Cesca
Yzma
Cell
Harris
And this message