Northern listening to Radiolab
Radiolab wnyc
Hello
Primavera
Oh my God
Okay great
Why do I feel like I'm
Literally talking to another world
This is Radiolab and today we are reconnecting with an old producer of ours Brenna Farrell
Pats Place
Who sings Leaving Radiolab
She's been busy with work but also raising two kids is crazy hard and family
The China Lake
Take my vitamins in life
Exist on a low grade
Panic attack
Well I guess we should
Start by
Let's just try to recall like what it was
I don't even know how you bumped in like you don't normally okay so back in
My husband Nick and I
In our tiny apartment
Back in Brooklyn and we were new parents are
Son Marty was 18 months old at the time
And
One morning I think it was about 5 a.m.
Like still dark Marty woke up and he was just
Crying crying crying and so
Tapped my husband it was his turn to get up early and go get Marty
So he got out of bed
I fell right back to
To sleep and the next thing I knew
I would like
Felt somebody tapping me and I sort of rolled over in my bed and there was just this little person looking up at me
Covered it this
Greasy stuff all over his face with shiny
And he was laughing and he held up in his hand
Giants
Jar of
Diaper
Appointment
The special medicated stuff that we had bought just that last week and I just
Oh my God
He just ate all this medicine and I have no idea how much he ate and then I look around in my husband
We got enough of them changed his diaper and they put him down in the Florida Play had because he was exhausted falling asleep in the chair
While watching him
So I just
Flung myself to the end of the bed and I grabbed Marty in one arm and started
Frantically searching the label which was filled with words like
Petrolatum
Saracen
Panthenol glycerin
Isabel law
Brenda said she didn't register any of those
Because right underneath that list of ingredients I just saw this
Bold type that said if swallowed
Call your doctor Poison Control Center immediately
Touching my son and I'm clutching his jar and then I yelled my husband to wake him up and I'm like I need you to
Find the number and call Poison Control while I hold Marty
And Sonic
Snap into action leaps off the chair into the other room
So you make a call Brenna is left sitting there in the bed holding her 18-month old son
Who is about to
Throw up
Pass out die
She's not sure like have you ever felt that Hollow feeling or like your whole chest
Drops
And you just it's like it feels like missing a step here
Just utterly sick
And then just like all
Sweaty up in my temple
Sitting on the edge of our bed and my lap and I'm Eagle I watching for
Like whatever's about Tuesday
And I had always heard that like
You have your mother's instinct or whatever that is in like moms know best and moms can tell when something's wrong with their kid and like
Sometimes maybe that's true but for me
Rose
I was imagining like
This huge like
Glop of ointment has worked its way down your esophagus and now it what is it doing to your stomach lining and what's going to happen when it like
I was just begun I can't take it back like what do I do
Nick has gone to the Next Room
And I hear that he's on the phone with someone and then just moments later
Blackout
I said well
That was the most Pleasant phone call I've had in ages
There he was
Completely calm kind of like smiling at me and the doorway
And I'm just still hunched over the bed like hanging on the Marty thinking
What is going on
So Nick
Straightened up
And then went into the lake okay
Here's what happened I called
They immediately picked up
Brennan said that he told her you talk to this man the guy asked him super matter fact how much
Marty Wade
I told him
20 lb
Whatever yes then what brand of diaper ointment did Marty eat
Then the guy did a little mental math and said
Your child's going to be fun
Totally fine this will probably not a big deal at all was really common
No
Vomiting no no nothing
He was like just like a slippery little piglet at that point I cleaned him up and then let him play
But for the rest of the day I just kept thinking
What the hell is Poison Control I honestly didn't think we still live in a world where you can just call a hotline like
Get on the telephone and talk to a live Human who somehow knows everything about this one specific brand of diaper ointment
And then bam like 45 seconds later this full-blown crisis in my mind was just
Thoughts
And then you know
I just was having this weird moment of like
There's this invisible network out there that was just
Kind of primed and waiting
To help
Are these people
So
A few months later I'm totally obsessed with poison control
I ended up in a skyscraper in downtown Chicago
19 floors gummies for twisty-turny quarter to the oldest Poison Control Center in America
We're here
When I got there and our staff wish there was something
Carol the senior director took me on a tour smaller than a
No it's not a dumb
But definitely is enough
I think I was expecting like the banks of the chi Tech
Lee Min computers and instead that phone has
So there it was
Narrow
Office with brick
Carpet
Crusty
Mushroom poster up there a cubicles I don't know whose Cubs hat that is but
Like a basement
College computer lab you know like where all the machines are kind of still running Windows 95 or something like that
I'm sitting in front of those computers with poison specialist
I'm I'm I'm the snake by percentile of paneling
There's Aaron snakes like the little old lady who is like working her backyard there was a snake and she chopped off his head
Shuffle and then she brings a snake head into the ER to show them what bitter and there's Connie
How I look at it she take mushroom called even when she's on vacation is that true
Yes excited about it
Extend TV to work in the ER nurse by background is Jessica
Make a phone call
Tony
Hello honey bee expert
In everything
Illinois poison Center
And while I was there the stream calls was just nonstop.
As soon as one of them would hang up the phone another call would come in at 5
Normally healthy
Okay
Gently wipe off
Little warm
Water on a washcloth
Give him something to
To drink they told me that in order to work here
Eat a background of medicine special training
Toxicology on top of that
Hope to have a good memory could math skills
But more importantly
What you really need
Is to be able to stay
I usually tell people they're going to be overwhelmed by the
The first 3 months
Glow stick
It's not going to be a problem are adorable
The other times a boy
They're like this
He has a temperature of 100
For this is an ER call a sugar again
The hospital was calling about a male patient
Who been found unconscious
Completely sweaty diaphoretic at home
So the Medics are assessing him his blood sugar was 40
Tylenol
Pupils she said her bouncing all over the place
I don't know what that mean
After she hung up ask Cindy if it was a self-harm call it's believed to be yes
She was saying that his wife just died of cancer
Is it somewhat rare
Not at all we get them all the time
At least
Poison Center
Can you spell that
Can you spell the name of that
And how many milligrams
Spending about 12 hours
There that day end if you send the Poison Control
Spinner that long just
Poison Center
Alder watching over there he's coming and coming and coming you start to feel just kind of overwhelmed
Every single time the phone rings
There's somebody on the other side of the line in there in a moment of uncertainty
Appendix
Tylenol over
Prices this could be pretty serious and the scale of that
It's just kind of shocking we manage
80000 calls a year out of this room
And that's just this once
Just Chicago
If you take the poison centers
All across the country they handle almost 3 million cases a year
So you get a call like mine
Or much worse
About every 14-second
You know
Very poisonous plants
End
Thinking about just how many of us are bumping into these things that we think might be poisoning arsenic Mercury
Are poisoning US Gold is poisonous to some extent silver not so poisonous pedal Turn You Blue I decided to call up
Deborah Blum
Director of a knight science journalism program at MIT
And poison enthusiast
I love poisonous
Even heard about called
The poisoner's handbook you're my husband worries about that a lot in fact he has not let me pour him a cup of coffee
Coffee for the last
6 years since my
Are you serious right knee really was seriously he's always like
So
Never said that helps the kind of think of poison control as part of this much larger back and forth
What kind of a dance involving dance that we've been doing with our poisonous planet
Thousands of years we've been dancing with them
And different ways for a very long time if you go back and look
The hieroglyph
Fixing Egypt
There is actually references to death by Peach
And that refers to cyanide poisoning because cyanides
Are the primary poison in the pits of peaches FYI peaches actually written in a wall of a temple somewhere or
Endeavor says
Go back to the beginning of that dance
You'll find that like with so many things it starts
With murder
Because we humans first got really interested in poisons
When you realize we could use them
Kill each other and one of my favorite examples is actually arsenic
Which in early nineteenth-century Europe was by all accounts the perfect, decided poisoned it was tasteless
It was odorless you could put it into vanilla pudding or oatmeal natural illness
Gioconda look like they had a bad gastroenteritis and at the
The time we had no way of detecting it literally only comments in the 19th century
Science has not figured out a way to detect a single poison in a quart
Bowser what ruined this
Perfect well there was a chemist in Britain named James Marshall
Worked out the sink
Credibly
Tell me about the Sanders today primitive test
Which involve mincing up the tissue from the dead person and
Adding some acid and heating it up and Distilling it and then
Is this Vapor comes out
Cool
Onto glass
And if there was any arsenic in the original
That are sick form
Tiny dark
Krystal's
And you got us there.
Blackish
Silver mirror
Forming over the glass
And
That
Was actually the first
Great test
A forensic toxicology the marsh test
This is sort of the moment Deborah says
The modern science joins our dance with poison
Because if you see the rise of industrial chemistry and and our ability to synthesize Cyanide and
Strychnine in some of these amazing life
Toxic elements you also see people's realization of how you
Well they are
Antlers
So cool around
Where is West
West Soho opening was
Beginning of the 20th century
They're all these new cleaning products hitting the market
It designed to kill germs
And pharmaceutical products
Designed to kill
Headaches or whatever
And suddenly
All these poisons that you should just be out there in nature
We're in our homes or in the drugstore
Alfred Apple
Here are producers Annie McEwen I'm actually taking a jaunt
Okay here we are in Hudson
Pharmacy on our time on Tuesday afternoons during working hours
Local drugstore
Cleaning I
So
Drano bottomless Shelf
Easy for kids to read
Contains sodium
Hypochlorite
Sodium
And sodium
Okay
Quickchek online sodium hydroxide
According to Wikipedia it's you
Used to digest tissue
Say there's like roadkill in a landfill put the roadkill in a sealed container with
Bladder
Breaking Bad
Yeah it in the body
He turns into a liquid with
Apparently
Segment people into coffee
Little higher on the Shelf
Everybody's favorite childhood cartoon mr. clean Meadows and Rain scent
Sodium hydroxide
Is if okay
Noun
There's Windex
Windex
Just called ammonia
If you mix ammonia and bleach
What happens
A poisonous gas
Results
Also occurs naturally the atmospheres of Jupiter and
That's
Next little grey bottle up on the highest Shelf
Goodall's brass and copper polish
Brass and copper polish
Contains two to talk
It has a suite
Ether like odor
Open it and smell it
Okay well it says it can cause adrenal tumors in animals
It's carcinogenic in rodents
I hope I didn't smell too much of it
Matt
You know what to get
Chips
All right
We're very comfortable
With the fact that we walk down the grocery
Tri-Star tile are open up the medicine chest and we're surrounded by these different
You know in pill form or liquid form a spray form or whatever but these different compounds
That actually are dangerous reused
That we live
Riot
Which brings us to a guy
Actually I saw this
Plaque dedicated to him on the wall at the poison Center in Chicago station
Initiative and devoted service
Founder of the poison and drug information
I'm a guy named Lewis condolement Louis kedalaman who is they
Brilliant scientist in this
State of Illinois
Lewis passed away back in 1995 but it's like Katherine and yes it's still very much alive
Absolutely he's 98 now but she met Lewis back when she was a 20 year old nurse working in St Luke's Hospital in Chicago
It was 1940
He was the pharmacy
In the hospital and everybody nulu
And we all love them and I was looking
I caught him
Northland swordfish order man dark hair
Big dark eyebrows
Great personality and he would take care of everything that came along friendly but when it came to his work
To get very serious
The pharmacy was directly across
Saul from the emergence
What's are happening is
You don't even notice this trend
I just about got this is the 1940s and doctors are totally winning against infectious diseases
And what that meant was that as far as the public was concerned
Keeping your family healthy and germ-free
Is a big deal
And that meant keeping your home
Super
Complete duper
It really looks clean.
And at the same time there's just this explosion of new cleaning products coming into the market
Than any other
New blue cheer
Raven dishes as well as long as our kitchen cabinets
In cupboard under the bathroom sink
Just getting like filled up with all of these things
Powders and liquids brightly colored bottles and boxes
Never put into a box
And getting back to Lewis what he began to notice was that
More and more these doctors were coming across the hall of his Pharmacy the first one and then more and more and you know they're saying the k
We got this kid over in the ER Heat
Just got into this new cleaning
Stop and we have no idea what
Can you help us
So the interns and residents and they emerge
PC room with naturally come across the hall to
And Lou help them find out what the child is taken for example if a child has swallowed a jacks
That meant he'd actually eaten
Sodium carbonate and sodium dodecylbenzene sulfonate
Wicked mean Dodger diarrhea
Or vomiting and Lewis
To keep cards on every
Product that was brought into the emergency room
Lloyd Wright Avenue card white sail bleach
Sodium hypochlorite
Chest pain vomiting
Safety gulou decided this was a
It was very needed because of the 1950's
3 / 250,000 different trade name substances on the market
The doctors they just couldn't keep up
And so loose stack of cards it grew taller and taller and taller and pretty soon
Workout
Dog across the country would hear that there's this guy in Chicago who gives out help on poisoning
So many calls are coming in at all hours of the day and night eventually could only just started telling the switchboard operator they could go ahead and transfer the call
She was home
We would get calls from all the different little love
Emergency rooms in the hospitals in the state and what was what was it like
Once you're doing this then
It seems to me that you don't really have normal hours
Because emergencies will take place whenever they take place
So yes
How did what was he going to be on call 24 hours a day
You leave yet
Yes he was
Bleyblades get calls in the middle of the night
It already even during dinner time
So what happens if you know he's in the tub
And you're cooking dinner
And the phone rings
I would take the phone to him
A tender
That's the way it started
Eventually
Little operation became the first Poison Control Center in the United States
In Chicago
102 to 21222
1 800
Boysen is the kind of thing you'll know
Not supposed to touch
Old prescriptions cleaning stuff for spider bites and such
If you swallowed something bad or think you took too much
Call the Poison Control Center hotline will the people you can try
Supposed
Hi there this is Kirsten recording from Orlando Florida
Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred
P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology
In the modern world
More information about Sloan
At www
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your
And I've requests
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents
Aunts and uncles teachers
We're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments
Basically I want to hear about this
Did you know did something
It just means you lean back and say
Wow
Maybe it was the moment that our kids you've been reading to 4 month started reading back
To you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin
Or maybe the kids in math
In the margin of their geometry
We're interested in the
Epic moments where
A kid does something super smart
It doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story
T-shirt
Go to radiolab.org
Brilliance
Record short audio message
Again that's radiolab.org
Splash Brillion
Thank you so much
21 Chad Robert
Radiolab so we are back with reporter Brenda Farrell who is continuing
In to mm
To inquire into things poisonous before the break we just learned about Louis God Amun who started the oldest boys
Control center in the country back in 1950
53 in Chicago today now we have
55 poison control centers
All across the country
And it's one phone number that anyone anywhere in the US can call
Whenever they need
Are there at certain times
Is there a rhythm to the day generally
Pattern it's busy in the morning and our kids are getting ready for school and Apache language for work for brushing your teeth
With muscle rub
Cream kids drinking a little mouthwash
Need some sunscreen eating some old mayonnaise
In the morning healthy parent will give the kids a adhd medication
In the mid-afternoon
Kind of tapers down a little bit
Is the slowest
And then the evening
Busiest time of the day overall
What is like between 6 p.m. and 10 p.m.
People coming home from work trying to get dinner super glue instead of eye drops super glue in
Lip gloss
People take the
The Dodger cast Medicine by mistake instead of the normal medication
Yeah that that's a frequent scenario it gets to be
Adults I have literally
Care of all the things that have been used inside
It's just busy
You know just the heck
The schedule that we're living in
And right now
Romans old stack of
The car that become this huge database
Facebook tracking like in real time
These things that are cropping up
Salmonella
Weather that salmonella outbreak
Or like
That's nice
A weird drug reaction that people are having or maybe it's a new product at
Unexpectedly dangerous or laundry detergent pods
Candy
Now they are being linked
Tragic death of a child they can see that
In real-time Inlet Health officials or whoever else knowing
Which is pretty cool but
I mean honestly just selfishly thinking about myself as a mom
Coming out of the trip to poison control I remember writing down
Miss feeling of like
What if I just approached
All the scary decisions in my life the way that poison control
Like what like kind of thinking like
What would Poison Control do you like I just
It felt like
Such a relief to be experiencing
Phenobarbital
64.89
And how much does she weigh is super rational place because just completely rational
And when did it happen
How long ago
We have this data we're going to
What's the name of The Prado
Take these questions from you
Let me see if this is even going to be a pro
And then we're going to
Tell you
This is what we think is going to happen
Back pain nausea
And they'll let you make a decision or they'll tell you like straight up don't worry about it
She's going to be a okay
I'm here on out and then take it again but you will be okay
Okay
It just felt like it's it's
Stripped Away a lot of the
Like the guild and the anxiety and the like should I do this and politics and all those other things that have often swear
Around even seemingly
Tumi inocuos questions about
How do I keep this person with little person safe and healthy
There's all the stuff swirling around it and they just
We didn't have to get into any of that
The iso range for me the most interesting part of this is that
The idea that we're supposed to know things like
You know I talked about this with my dad I mean
There was this time in medicine when
It was all about the doctor
In the white coat is
Paternalistic
Doctor knows best
And no one wants to go back there about that that there was something emotionally clean about that
Where is now
We have all the information it's right there is
Hand in hand
With the rise of the internet
It's so increasingly
We're expected
To be our own
Experts
And it's usually presented as
This sort of simple idea that information is power
And it isn't power I mean it is but it's also paralysis
Yeah
Actually had a rule where I wouldn't I would only let Nick look things up
Cuz I couldn't like I was not certain I was pregnant I like but have a panic attack
Is there so many different things and like always the top searches are the ones that like you're going to die
Oh yeah and he's really eat you like you get to the comments field
Right
I mean there's something about when you look at an answer on a
Screen and you just one click away from an exact opposite answer
And then when you're on the phone with someone it's just you and that person
Like there is no other.
Traction
I guess something built into the technology
The crates
Exactly the kind of connection you need it that much
Little people when they call you it's emergency there there
They're panicking and I think half the battle is getting them
Settle down
So this is Tony Berta the know everything I we mentioned earlier
81 then that calm voice for 30 years
And while he was in pharmacy school he had an accident
I actually started pharmacy school
As excited
Person but I finished as a blind
Individual
What what happened
He didn't want to say
But sitting there
Scene of doing all of this math and spitting out these numbers receptor sites and half lives and volumes of distribution
Totally incomprehensible to me
But he told me that he also look pretty quickly and too
Discovered early on that there was this whole other
Part of doing this job
Since September of 82
Lucy I would have
Probably head like a year-and-a-half
Experience at that time
I remember I was
Sitting in the poison Center
Another Pharmacy
And we had the news radio
I am station on
It's about 10:30 in the morning
News flash
A bizarre and terrifying stories in the Chicago suburbs
Golan Heights and elk grove village
A twelve-year-old girl and two men who were brothers
Poison capsules of extra strength Tylenol
Several people died from
Sinai that the belief was
Tylenol
Chicago that
Number might be changed
What's Cyanide and the terrifying moments
Thousands of people just simultaneously were all thinking oh my God this thing I brought into my home and make me feel better
You can kill me
Today across
Tylenol products were being pulled from the show
The police are like driving that car slowly down the street with loudspeakers real eggs
Take back your Tylenol.
Restraints the time being until you hear otherwise
I thought you know till he told me he's sitting there hearing these news broadcast going across the radio and you just turn to the guy sitting next
To him in the Poison Control Center is that
We're going to get killed
Has been ringing off the hook at rush Presbyterian
St Luke's Medical Center in Chicago
Since you hung up the phone on the phone ring again
15 seconds color of Pharmacists and I just grabbed the references and
Try to make ourselves cyanide expert Co real fast
An interesting thing about
This case
Is that in every single one of these calls that was coming in
Provides almost panicked
But they weren't actually in any danger
If anyone has taken
So in some way this moment if you think about it it it really kind of
High like this thing that
It is really at the heart of poison
The Specialist
Not only were, but they hate their job was to just reassure like they were letting people know it was going to be okay
But if you flash forward to now that's changing it
They're getting more calls that are more serious I getting calls from hospitals
Again calls from people who've taken multiple drugs and so does that mean that they're getting less calls from like
Normal
People and parents and I are going down and that end my calls overall
Sense like that in the past decade there been fewer calls
The Poison Control
Do you know why
My son
We don't like to make phone calls anymore but people don't there that you know the internet is there
And that's what we're used to and that's easy
Until they are they just launched this new
But instead of calling you can go to the website and plug-in answers to the questions
That they roll through
And it will give you the same answer based on
Hopefully the same knowledge but then
As a person who's lived
Through it I'm like oh my God please don't take away that phone call cuz it
When you're in that Panic the thought of having to sit and type an answer out while you're holding your kid and like wondering if you real
Really screwed up
And it's like you're taking away something really valuable that maybe
We're not valuing here
I did have this one event
When my older son I've got
Tucson
It was very little we were living in Sacramento
That by the way is author Deborah Blum again and
They didn't have fluoridated water
So
Doc gave them
Honey Mead
Cute they were really cute fruit flavored fluoride pills
What kind of thing you could get a toddler to take
I don't know that we were doing but somehow we
Have you given him his daily fluoride pill and then like idiots left it on the kitchen counter
And he grabbed it and pretty much inhaled the whole bottle
And I was
Really
I just didn't know how poisonous that was going to be like oh poison control
Am I supposed to know what I wanted to know was whether I should pan
Right I mean
He seemed fine it wasn't like he was getting sick and anyway
And they were completely non freaked out about
Yeah you remember here
Did you hear their words or did you hear their tone
It was the tone
They were so calm
Add
They could tell I was
And Anakin just
Tell you I'm standing in the kitchen we had this phone
My son's by me you know he can tell I'm free but he doesn't really know I'm free and I sat on the
After I talk to them
Sat down on the floor with him
Just so great
And I was
And that's what I remember
Is how grateful
Hello my my two-and-a-half-year-old daughter just ate most of the tube of a
.85 Oz
Fingers crossed
12 1/2 milliliters of Children's Motrin
He is about 25 to 30
Pointe shoes for 3%
Is others
4.25. Yr 5 percentage
5. Why
Maybe yes 5.4
Yes definitely not even close to the boss.
Send all the time
She said they find you alright well thank you so much
Petechiae
You just put it
Netease and I appreciate you very much
2221 +222-800-222-1222
I get mad before then
Why isn't is the kind of thing you'll know
Supposed to touch vitabyte sensor
If you swallowed something bad or think you took too much
1 800 2 2 2
Calls to poison control our confidential by the way are we got permission from the colors you hurt
To use the audio
If you should ever need to
Call Poison Control the number is one 800-222-1222 and
If you text the word poison to
79797 9
You'll save a number in your phone
Deborah Blum latest book the poison Squad is going to come out this fall and you can find out more on our website
Thank you also to Nick capodici a Wendy Blair Stephan Marianne Mozart
Andrew perella
Bennington Ridge
Your dark and Natalie weed
This episode was reported by Brenna Farrell and produced by Annie McEwen with help from Jay Carlo
I'm glad I've been run Village
Thanks for listening
If you think it might be poisoned what to do
Express 2
Start of Meth
Everybody is Brian calling in the staff credits with Marty will see how far we get ready
Baby Alive
Introduced by Tory Lanez
Barney
Director of sound cuckoo
Dracula sound
Leah
Little Rock
Include
Katmai
Mac
Karaoke
Knock knock
Melissa O'Donnell
Amali brookster
I d
Alien Covenant
Hi
And this message