Are you awake
Northern listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
Hey I'm Jared I'm Rod I'm Robert krulwich this is Radiolab well today we're going to tell you a story witch
We hope does not become your future but it raises a simp
We all have computers we love computers we depend upon computers but what is the cost of using your
Becomes
More than you're willing to
2 stories
Today
Which suggests
Puppy might be
The very beginning
The first
Comes from Journal Salina Samone and her mother
When do you want to start with my mom cuz it really happened to her as you know she
She only got in touch with me maybe on Desi Parents of him to me yeah
Okay
So what ya day one
What was the first
Endive one
One tampon then I called to talk to University it service
Says because my husband feels
Complaining that
My computer is unbearably unbearably slow I don't know what's going on everytime I try
Can open windows
Click
Practically.
Working what do I do
I'm probably nothing rebooted to did not
Basic
Then
She went away for the weekend
And when I came back
I turned the computer on
And
Like it was doing something
And they so many many windows covering your screen
Those windows X cannot open any of them
And I could not figure but it was
Vera latest 9
So
You in bed
Got the next day called
Again asking for help
Windows Vista
The end
Except now anytime she tried to click any of her files
Pictures videos I cannot open any of them every time this
Message pop up
In the message
Says
What happened to your files
Encrypted using cryptowall
This means that the structure and data within your files have been irrevocably changed
And in order to give them back you must pay 500
US dollars if you really value your data
Then we suggest that you do not waste valuable time searching for the solutions because they do not exist
You're saying Somebody went into your computer and locked up all of your things yeah they
Give me the exact
Call
5726 files encrypted
When will you say they
Did you have any image in your head of who's my feel thought
Was Russia
Or Ukraine
Beaches
Even better
Why because
Did you know everybody talks about excellence and test
Education
Especially math I am from that I know
You know she's right they surpassed the US and educating their kids
Csun math and science
And they've got us
Severe underemployment problem
Especially outside of the mange
Please which is where these viruses often
Trace down to not Moscow
What we're talking about
Eno Backwater
I was supposed to
That
It comes from their part of the world
That I wrote them
In the rush
Add provider a link to a website where
You know
I wrote them
How to translate it in English more accurately Simpson Lake I wish you all.
In Russian language
There is a V-Rod
To die for cumin or another word for animals
Yes no
But they got them
Nina says she thought about just wiping a computer clean so that she wouldn't have to pay
Events occur to her that her husband had all these files on there
You're like business receipt City hadn't filed
Did she is lazy to do so he has cancer
An end she's right that like you know she has this
Is tax information
Reimbursement information
Ultimately it's worth more than $500 my husband didn't respond to pay overalls
Tokina decides to follow the instructions base
1 download and install Tor Browser
Is Moltres about
Rhonda browser and wait for initialization
She does that
3 Type in the address bar Cape a 7-way CR7 jet skis
Walter luck if you don't trust
Savvy can decrypt
One of your files
For free
Is a sample that when you pay us
If you would know that you could
Really get
All your files back
I was curious
I decided that I will try
So she clicked the button that said yes
And one
File back
But as soon as I did
Are there clocks that thicken
Literally she says I will clock appear.
The top of the browser
They give me example S7
167 hours
59 minutes
59 seconds
So you decrypt a thing and then suddenly it's a countdown to the yes they say if you won't pay by this
Is this them Define
Will be doubled and it won't be in the 1 movie
Then you will lose your files forever
And you will never get it back
Now in the message should have told Gina that she had to pay that $500 fine not in dollars
Button bit
You know I
The Disco Victorious
Time
In my life ever
I saw the tumba.
So I
The phone this
The website
Called Queen Cafe where you can buy Bitcoin
A.m. to buy this Bitcoins is it nice
It's at 4
What you needed to do with exchange five hundred bucks for the requisite amount of Bitcoins
And at the time 500 bucks equal to 1.37 bit
But before she could even make that Exchange
Chittor Philadelphia
Forms of the questions
What happened what did the reason to buy
Bitcoin everything is well listed one of them was rims
Yes I told the first reason to pay
A ransom to the criminal
Next
Forms you have to make it big
And send them a photograph
Through the internet
Okay
I did not give a camera because
She says her camera and having to be in the shop
More than that
I have to
Make a picture
Of my husband holding the driver's license
Send them
This picture back
Place the bank where the criminals are there
People
Who sell you Bitcoin exchange for your money
I told you that it's a torches
Unbelievable
But eventually she was able to find a neighbor borrow the camera take
Russia news attack
Then she had to get the money she wanted to exchange to coincafe and it turns out
Preferred way to do it the most secure way to do it is not online but
Do a money order
Abyssal the day right before Thanksgiving
Wednesday
Still had about six days before the deadline
Pop down to the post office get a money order
But Boston
Lexington and the cool Massachusetts
Could the terrible terrible smell
Storm for a lot of us this could be the biggest storm so far this winter undrivable
Get snowy wet snow I have to go
So that. So she plows
Through the snow almost kills herself but gets there gets everything together send it off
So finally
I send everything
Tune out
The post office
Assured me that they will get it
On Friday
Which is the first working day
Up The Descent
Okay so
On Friday they did not get it
On Saturday if they did not get it
On Monday in the morning nothing was delivered
And I was deaf
Because
My deadline was
Used a Samsung like 12:00 and I said calling the post office whatever
But there is no guarantee
Finally waclaw
In the afternoon on Monday 24 hours for the deadline
They send me Bitcoin
Election because they got my money
But
She says when she went online to check her Bitcoin at
Account I'm searching Dallas
Troy
Hundred and I stop
Cortland basically the exchange rate of change. Her if she'd bought it at 500 now it was worth for 87
Do them how old do chin
The exchange rate
And they said that every minute
What does smooth ER joke every minute I said
Are you crazy
I wasn't that Bella victim
I was
Wisdom
Square
Cube
You see what I mean
Because driving was terrible take him to stand on my head
To get the camera and then I was struggling
Sam them that's the problem with this
Crime like the criminals need a better way to get money from the victim has traceable
I'm on the edge of my seat here so it's that your $13
Sure they they said there is one more
One more way
Invoices at Vee Quiva ATM
You said what
Yeah because of an ATM
Machine
1 LeBron
Am I said where is it
It's in Brooklyn
Brooklyn New York 200 miles away
There is 180
BM that is in the borough of Brooklyn Bridge
You do not live but luckily her daughter Alina lives in Brooklyn
You asked me to call my daughter goes in Little Bits go
So she called Selena my mom called me the night
Before the ransom was dusan you aware of any of this
No no I remember you know I was at night I had the TV on and have a toddler anus
Things going on I was probably on my laptop to I was doing like 12 things and my mom called and she was like upset with a capital
So you just started ranting about criminals and Ransom I literally thought she was like talking and Eric
Cuz I'm like oh yeah I know when I go to text her and like yeah that's that's extortion
And my mom was like no like no it's really a rancid up there really criminals a Google crypto
That was like
Holy this is really a thing
Plus I started
Googling as she suggested I do and found out the police department's had paid this
That Sheriff's Department in dick
Dickson Tennessee had just
Paytakht unlock
Like me no 70
Plus thousand
Case Files Pediatrics go after Police Department on after governments universities Corp
Operation Police Department's by my mom
With this very thing
Anyhow
Next day less than 6 hours left
Aniceto Molina please go to the ATM so we can just be done with this whole thing
Tell you
This in the morning and she said
A canvas date
For my granddaughter.
Duplicated
I won't be able to do it until 12:00
The maid call again I said I was crazy
Don't have time so I go out to Greenpoint
This ATM I just want to add that have your blade
Why can't I hold my poop
Givenchy I called you
Jewel shortening
Okay so I should I cut my playdate short
Sorry
Forget that crucial detail
And they haven't ate
Yeah I'm and I'm just worried that this going to be V
7 people all lined up at the single ATM that you guys were totally not 50
Most people do take care of this remote
Like there was no
What was funny about the HMS like I'm expecting the cast into an ATM like I have a Capital One account I know what
10 ATM is like the second floor of a work share space in Brooklyn is like
In the hallway there was like a bike hanging from a wall kind of blocking and there's like a paper sign
Taped to the wall that just
Had a printout from a computer that just said Bitcoin ATM all lowercase letters in an arrow to this
Phone but it looked very Soviet
Like if you've seen photos of those phones with no buttons and there's two
Just a receiver and it's totally scary and quite like you just pick it up and like somebody's always on the other line
It was like that it was just
Justice box
The screen and no button
And a camera I and what you do is you hold up your
QVC code is that what they
They're called cutie
What are they called
QRC
Barcode thingy
QRC code in
My mom had emailed it to me
This out in this is
Ascent this is
Gives you access to my account
To top it off
You know until I put this
QRC code up to the camera online
And then it was like
We are asked
Accessing your account
And then
I got a
Spinny wheel you got the wheel of death no starts
Play dialing her mom the guys at Queen Cafe I called you know I left like three phone messages and then left
5 Sol
Finally they called me back
Play 20 minutes later
Said okay we're sending a text
Mission over
Machine
Very cool I didn't
I think that would happen and so you know the technician was there and he fixed the machine and he
Helps me deposit
$95
And then he was there talking and he was
He was like yeah you know he knew my mom
Casquito he'd been talking to on the phone he's like I feel so bad for your mom we've been getting so many of these cases and I'm like
Why are you why are cases
Guys getting so why is that
And he's like oh I know why because in the ransom note that they give a list of preferred
Vendors and we are number one or two the introduction with a bad introduction
What's a bitcoin
Like we're going to hold you ransom for all your information until you
Yeah we use this new currency to pay house off
Play me not so terrible
This is my coats and John ha they are the co-owners of
Coincafe
A few weeks back
The grandmother
Who was in tears she was going to lose all of her family photos
Because the deadline is come
Crying on the phone to me
Got it
Acrylic people who sell Bitcoin just believe that there should be a digital currency that is decentralized
It doesn't rely on the banks
But unfortunately has become the currency of choice
Ransom
Hey there in this weird position so it's a tricky thing because
Like I can't sell Bitcoin to someone who I know is going to do something illegal with it right that's will wheeler who run the Bitcoin exchange
Call Express he says he and the other exchanges are really worried right
Is it they keep helping little guys pay the ransom
Nor to get their files back
They are in effect making themselves
Accessories to a crime I finally got a call back from fencing
Which is the federal Authority for
Financial crime enforcement Network
They said that
We could perceive
Paying a ransom
Unlawful activity
And so
They might choose to use that against
The company
Who helps out right
Unlikely
Until we get a straight answer from Vince and we'll take the overly cautious approach and
Start the cleaning these transactions
Even though in your heart you want to help
Do you want to risk being indicted for helping you get your travel route
Reimbursed
And I mean to me answers now
In any case
After Alina deposits the extra 25 bucks in her mom's
Bitcoin account Nina the mom goes online
And it was gone
But
Then
About an hour later
Went to my computer
And there was another message
That you're late
No doubt that I was doing the half
You have to pay
$300
Roughly
I did not have anybody to turn to
So she went to that same website where you can write them
I wrote them that I was laid but I mentioned the snow storm
The things given which they probably
And the
The wonderful us
Mail service
I said that I tried and I was only two
Hours
Late
And then all of a sudden
I'm getting the message
You paid
In full
Without any explanation nothing Cupid
This it
And I got all my files back
They took pity on her
Maybe I found
That it's
Finally
Really woman
Make you wonder why
These people
We've a story about that up next
Hello this is Michelle from
Kakaako
What
Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding
Meaning of science
Send technology
In the modern world
More information about Sloan @www
Slam.org
Mahalo
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help this summer I'm hosting
And I request for those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
We're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments
Childhood Brilliance basically I want to hear about this
It just means you lean back and say wow how did they do that maybe it was the moment that a kid
You've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons and you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed they're writing music in the margin of their geometry homework we're interested in
Epic moments where a kid does something super smart but doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story please share it with us
Go to radiolab.org brilliance
Record a short audio message for us
Again that's radiolab.org / brilliance
Thank you so much
Hey I'm Jenna Cam'ron I'm Robert krulwich
It says Radiolab but here's the next obvious question who did this to you nor do we know anything about them we put that question to
Joseph Mann investigative reporter for Reuters
Ton of work it is
Syria and his hunt
Was the
It is right there talking people
Russian-speaking Folks by and large
Your book called fatal
System error which
Just heard of a deep dive into the Russian hacking scene and much of it is as you'd expect
Second young guys
Early twenties
Kind of grubby by and large they do not live the lavish
Lifestyle there are guys at the top of these criminal organizations
That are very flashy
And if they're like sword
Stop
Icon some of them in the same way that rap stars
Are in the US
There's a hacker magazine
Viccino's as Gaz
Has guys with their sports cars in the supermodels
And whatever you know
Buying bottle service if you know disco's between them
What are the guys who hire the 20 year olds they hired a 20 year olds for their franchise
And says the twenty-year-old runts
Work at office
Yeah that's like a call
Is there like
Keno
The producer Kelsey
Apache maven
In a cubicle
Artist computer
Bored
His meeting later with Judy in HR
He's mad about it
Is that the kind of like environment
These people are in for the most part I think so yes
The larger point is that it's not just like your Lone Wolf pimp
Ugly face hacker
Any more cyber crime is now
Super organized
It is awesome
Incorporate
It is Big Business
In the hole
Economy seems to revolve around the secret sites
Where people come together to buy and sell things like
That ransomware story Underground
Webforms
The end there's a right
Some are available you can reach you on the open internet
The more impressive ones are password
Protected you know you have to know somebody to get in
The really really
Fancy one
You have to have a couple of people vouch for
Apply with your resume at your hackers resume here are the things I can bring these are the kinds of
Hacking exploit that I've had in there for I should be part of your
Let's Dina temple-raston NPR cybercrime corresponding
She's been tracking the government
Attempts to shut down
Lights which she describes as
Hackers
Black Market Bazaar to let's say someone is looking for a bunch of credit card numbers
You can get it
There's one price if their master
Jacquard gold and
And another price
No higher-level credit whatever I say
You wanted to know about a boss
Skyward employee
Dior
You can get this piece of software that allows you to turn on their phone anytime you could basically eavesdrop on them cuz you're in the pocket
And for $300 a month
You would actually get
Customer service
And the price is actually keep coming out it's a very very
Evolved
Fluid Market
There's feedback
And there's escrow there are feedback forms going to ask you that Thief was not really there
I didn't didn't do the fever
The robbery right absolutely
Protect me for something you'll see it a lot for freshness
Credit cards
Cuz you know it's easy to say y'all here 10000 credit card
But if their credit card numbers
After while
And get the client every
You just wasted
Your money and these people called Rippers
As in they're ripping you off
And they will get banned
Wow so it's reputational just like everywhere else it's as good as
If you feel safe
Doing business on eBay there's no reason you shouldn't
All of this
To me frankly felt like just a sexy hacker talk
Until a couple of months ago dinosaur telling us about this one
Particular site actually the biggest
Of these kind of sites
It's out there it's called Dark code the way it has been described by law enforcement is sort of an amazon.com
Phone for hackers specifically how us attorney David Hicks
Describe to her in an interview
Darkode
Is the largest English-speaking
Criminal cyber crime Forum in the world
When did I think most people know Silk Road and they know for example
So you could get a contract hit
Silk Road drugs
Some guns and everything else
So would it be right for me to say that this was sort of a silk road for hackers
Yeah I wouldn't want to drive that direct comparison I think it's probably accurate I would say that all measure of cybercrime
That you see and watch
Around the world was in some form or fashion connected to it
So we got really interested in this world of this site darkode into
People in it
And so with Dina
We started calling around trying to find anyone that would talk
After weeks of searching and calling and loitering we found a guy who agreed to go on the rack
My name is Daniel placek
And
I am a reformed hacker
As far as We Know Dan has never talked about this
So how did you get involved with dark
Well I was
One of the people who created it
A very long time ago
Daniel Story begins not in Russia but in Milwaukee sure will let me start with a little account small middle-class suburb
Right outside Milwaukee
Your brothers and sisters
Two younger brothers and two younger sister
Big family
Did you have to share rooms with them or will you and your own
Kingdom High share the room with both my brothers
Search for a lot of years
Becca syrup lazy to the story cuz he says what he would do
Escape
Please go to the basement
Play video game
So yes the the stereotypical hacker in his parents basement
I know
Quite hilarious
Densetsu hacking began innocently enough when he would monkey with games like Age of Empire
I'd change the graphics change the artificial intelligence in the game the way it plays
Rework it create new maps that type
Something I enjoyed
And slowly on throughout my teenage years that
Develop into something more
Do not get along well with
A lot of my peers
Creighton Middle School
So
I spent
A lot more time you know on the computer and
I myself and I did
Socially at least at that age
And he says one day he was in a chat room internet chat room
It's called game search talking with a bunch of other people out video games
And at some point along the way
Can meet this guy you know this for this particular guy was into
In a botanist
Oh yes spotnitz we all try yes you just remind us
Sorry no malware viruses installed on computers
Sand
Bob netzkino are the way to centrally control
Whole lot of
Computers just to put this in context
X-Force exiting satolli fascinating
Joseph man says this whole botnet
Situation
It started with fam
One of the easiest ways
How to make money on the internet back pre-2000
Was
Spam is in a penis extension
What happened was that the
In the olden days most
Servers mail servers
I acted is open relay
Meaning the mail people wouldn't really pay attention to who was sending one
To the spammers with Spam with abandon
And then spam got to be enough
Sofa problem
Is that the techies of the world
Decided
They started to block
Like if they found a guy who is
They thought was standing too many product emails or whatever
They would block his IP address
Couldn't send any more
So what the spammers and their contractors that need
Needed to do was to have a bunch of
Clean IP address
Ants in Spanish
From that so what they did
Totally genius totally evil
Is a hired a bunch of programmers to create a bunch of virus
Disseminated those viruses across the internet
People with
Accidentally clicker open something
Get them onto their
Computer
And then suddenly the spammers couldn't remote control
ARROW computers
At a distance
I really wanted to maybe just
An hour to an eye
To send out their spam cuz he's work clean IP address
Of course what happened
Is it once the spammers
How do you spot
Is there thinking I could do something else with
And that the next thing that came along
You can have all of them try to contact
Ebay.com
Gametime
And knock over
The first gentleman that I ran to he had about nuts
Well over a thousand
Which
I know what the time was amazing
You know by today's standards
Provide medicine
It's nothing now they can get him into the millions but
Back then it was quite incredible
Comedian Disney tattoos
This guy would get into fights
Anytime you did
He point his
1000 computer drone Army at that enemy in a few man I'm going to knock your internet off
There's nothing you can do about it
You know if it was something in a game he could knock
The game server that they're playing on offline and stop their game
Things like that it's like you can take away your ball back in 1935
That is exactly at
Taking away someone else's ball over the
So this for some reason intrigued
Yes
Was amazing
I'm like your control a thousand computers wow
You know how how did you do this you know I I I
Timeout
Never heard about that so I didn't know about any of this stuff like how did you
How did you get the software to do this how did you get it on to all these computers only quite happy to tell you
We certainly was this
This particular gentleman
Have very large
You go and did you see him as a
Bad guy
To be honest
I think at that age
Guy
Didn't really
Think about it
It's the Internet it's
It's a lot harder.
Quantify right and wrong
Now it's easy to look back
Yeah this is
Wrong but it's not like going up to someone and punching them in the face
There's no
Human connection there you don't see these people are feel these people
He said at the time it was just sheer curiosity
So he says he asked
Ask this Pied Piper guide
To send him somewhere
We bought soft
The botnet
And that really intrigued
No digging through the source code trying to understand
What is this thing doing how does it work how does a tick
This guy was you could koetter
Like isn't he good at it
Was he good at it yet
No no II would you know in hindsight now
You know he's what I would classify as a
Play script Kitty
You know someone who
Script Kitty
So ask Kitty is
Is someone who
Just enough technical ability to
Going to take some tools and software that other people have
Created in
Fast forward
As Dan went the opposite direction of the script kiddies and God
Better and better
Start making me the spot Nets that could
Literally
Spy on people as they were using their computers
Thing to see all the pouring that people are watching that type of thing
He says he found himself in another chat
That was called
Place where hackers swap tips Bragg take a look what I did by 2face this website take a look and he says Monday
He was talking with a friend of his
Is there. We were talking and
Why do we set up a community
Where we can really filter who gets the
What all is script kiddies in idiots
I actually chose the name
I came up with that
My slime name
I just think it's pretty good what's the name again
Dark coated AR k o d e s
I think right seems cooler with a k
Yes so you chose the name and started getting the site set
The rules were it would be invite only
She had an invite and each new person would be required to demonstrate their skill
He's a piece of software that I created
Here's a video of my botnet and action
And at some point
I'm not too long after
It was decided for one reason or another that
Hey we got all these programmers on here that's great but
They also want to be able to
Sell some stuff
Think so
Let's invite some people who would be willing to buy
This sound like a fairy so I have
A burglar
True up do you have a door you want a burger
I'll get you my tool what's a simplification but yeah
People with post
And say
I'm looking to buy a
Or here's a piece of software I created he resolved
Things that does here's some screenshots button action
Here's price
Could be
Certain type of botnet software
It could be buying a bond that itself
You know if you don't want to build one yourself
Someone that somebody else
Wheaton has going to me I can get you onto 200,000 or 20,000 computers
Just give me a check
Yeah what they called them were install
It's all your hey guys I've got installs
And they're $10 /
Something like that
Now this is some sort of surprising to us then when it comes to find that there's this whole rental
It's frightened Lee affordable
Bargain Basement
Integra talking with one reporter Kelly Jackson Higgins
Who is the executive editor of dark reading.com witches
Cyber security news site
She told us you can actually rent to buy
If you really wanted to you could rent
About net for 1 hour
About $38 a month
I can rent a botnet for 20 bucks a month if you could
Like renting space here you want to use this to go do damage somewhere or you want to make a statement or
You have some plan for our do you want to send some spam here you go you could go online right now
Probably find somewhere out there in the net
Somebody who will sell you access to computers for
Sense of Peace like people's computers like your computer my computer and Dan says as dark code got bigger in
Bigger
More of this kind of activity on the site
Like some kind of a botnet of 5000 computers another guy would have some software like the ransomware
Suffragette within rent botnet and guy one install his ransomware
Rental these poor people then move on to know some of the people
Where
You're doing some pretty unpleasant things
And I'm moving more into the
Financial crime
Pretoria matches
There's something that I really never had a desire to be involved in
It was largely because of that he says that in 2009
He decided to get a
But unfortunately the next year
I got a lovely visit from the
FBI
They promptly
With it at like a kick down your door type situation
They knocked
Was that like
Pretty terrifying
You know what's up what's going to happen to me what's going to happen next
What did happen
I don't know how much of that I can
Talk about
But
I did
Cooperate with the government
And I have cooperated with them for the last
5 + years now
Is a kick in the butt so you know my parents
Kind of kicked me out not. Kicked me hours
Assisted me with a rapid move out
I've been living on my own
Stan and
Became gainfully employed
Had a few jobs
Became a little more serious with my my then-girlfriend who is now my wife
So
You know it's give me an opportunity over the last five years to really
Make some serious changes to my life
Meanwhile over the same five years darkhold grew into
And it's massive
Cybercriminals swap meet
Where tens of thousands of stolen social
Security numbers were bought and sold
Huge database of personal information and emails were bought and sold malware and software various kinds are bought and sold and
Punta Cana temple-raston right up until
July 15th
Of this year
Today marks
In our efforts to bring to Justice some of the most significant
Cyber criminals in the world ended up happening on July 15th
Is that the FBI actually got into dark hole with a number of intelligent service
System around the world
And they had an 18-month
Investigation in which they took
Down
In the end
28 people
Effectively
And we are in the process of rounding up
And charging the Hornets
It's amazing right so they take down
More than two dozen people
2 weeks later
Dark code is up
Tupac back up just popped
A deep gratitude to in Paris.
Temple Reston who's reporting really got us going on this whole project give props to Kelsey Padgett a producer first segment and
Mills who produced the second segment and you can from memory give you the extended family tree of dark code
Just got out of his head original music
Thanks also to Andrews Ali Michael shamos on their own
Austin Kathy don't forget attorney David the car and the whole crew at the Microsoft cyber crimes unit
Robert think of you
Highway me because you're part of my body
Because
Thanks for listening
Message
New
Hey this is Dina temple-raston
And I'm reading the credits
Radiolab is produced by Jad Adam rod
Doesn't close
Ramos
Pharaoh
David Gable
Matt kielty Andy Mills
Master
Hedges
Arianne wack
Molly Webster torn wheeler ending York
From Simon
Tesla
Alexandra
Young
Abigail
Feel & Alexandra Brennan
Harris
And this message