Are you awake
Radiolab
From WNYC
And NPR hey I'm Chatham run this is Radiolab
Cast and
I'm usually want to do today
You know what we just did the hour-long show about the
Ghost
And in the middle of that show hit on this idea that there are so many of us on the planet now doing so many different things
Which affect the air and the water that the creatures on the planet
Can no longer really
Uninfluenced by our presence
Truly Wild
That made me wonder will
If you want to give the other creatures on earth a little more
Groom-to-be
Be wild and independent than what do we have to give
How much are we willing
To give up to make IHOP
I don't know these are
Tough question
I mean you know when I get it the answer part right so this is John moala I'm John
I read a book called wild ones and I'm a writer with the New York Times magazine
And being a writer he told me a story
This is a story would shed some light on this question but I think it's
Sated
Difficult
So there was a family of whooping cranes that
Had been part of the story revolves around a project
Create a wild
Flock of whooping
One of the most spectacular birds in the world 5 foot tall is pitch white thing with black wingtips going to 7 Foot
Wingspan beautiful Flyers is Joe Duff I'm the co-founder of operation migration the currency
Now we've done it story of operation migration before and Radiolab but here's the here's the gist
At one point the whooping crane population in North America was down to like
15 bird
One flock
SoJO with a bunch of other folks decided to see if they could start anew
Flock of crows
So they raise some cranes in Wisconsin and then they teach them
A new migration route
Florida
By leaving there
In ultralight airplane Joe in addition to being founder and CEO is also the lead pile
How long have you been you been doing this for a while
I started flying with birds in 93
20 years and the key to this whole project
Joe says
Is to eliminate all things human
These are wild creatures you know we do this whole thing in full costume so the birds
Don't hear voices they don't touch
I don't see buildings or any other human paraphernalia in order to
Maintain their Wild
Still even wears an all white
Crane-like costume when he's up there in the ultra
Feeding the birds
Come to Florida
And when they get the flu
Florida crane they're supposed to know they're brought to this some chassahowitzka National Wildlife Refuge it's a coastal wetland
And it's all a salt marsh in the Tampa area and the birds are put into Squad release Panda Tennessee
12 foot high fence is protected by electric wire but the whole complex is not talking at it
And so on
After a while the birds realize they can fly out then they go seek
Shout their own territories
It's called a gentle release Into the Wild
Or
The Nights Watch
And here's where the problem starts it's the winter of 2007 and we got a particular bunch of cranes this
Family they were called the first family cuz they were the first trains in the population to have a have a chick that they LED South
Wild hatch migratory whooping crane in the US since the last Nest was reported in 1878
These cranes head wound up in on this little subdivision Wetland complex that was surrounded by houses
It was perfect crane habitat it was it was basically a March
Just so happened that it was in this
This one is backyard
And so the birds which had been the product of this
You know very intensive effort and tons of money hundreds of thousands of dollars an hour to be wild whooping cranes were now just
In our backyard and there was there was free food there she had all these bird feeders whole array of different bird feeders
Aprender yard and that's not good sign why the why is this a problem
Well the problem is we're worried that the birds are going to become acclimated to people to be really safe Joseph these bridge should be
Freedpeople 6mm have been shot
Hmmm by Vandals
636 whooping cranes have been shot
In this project by vandals a so what are you doing we asked people to
Stop timer
Feeling with jellicoe a reverse phone directory awake give us
So we tracked the birds are not tracked I said they knew exactly where they where they were and they were able to figure out that the cranes work
In the backyard of
Someone named
Gibbs
Clarisse Clarisse
Yes Clarice Gibbs
And you know they knocked on our door in and explains you know the whole engine out to the project and would you please take your
Bird feeders down
And she said she said no
No yeah
Why don't you say no
Well done tok
The people who went to see her and I didn't say crazy but you got the sense that there was this you know crazy old bird lady lived in this house with wooden
Not take her feeders down thought you was acting kind of your attic and things just keep getting worse
Words
Gone in and put a plastic fence around one of her feeders at 1 playing with it what she thought she had given permission but she had no memory of that
It got it got better pretty fast and so John decided
Self for a you know crazy old bird lady who lived in this house
But I will but I went to go see her
And
You know it was a
How do I get taco time is it really
The emotional day for me
Massager under dining room table and she was having a lot of trouble remembering the exact chronology of what happened when
Cheetah
You know she said excuse me I'm just hard for me to kind of
Piece things together around that
Toronto time
And and basically the story emerged
Oh gosh
When we heard that story we decided we needed to talk to Clarice
Cartels
So we called her up out of it
Kind of the blue and asked if we could record the conversation
Record we would love to do it
Well you know it wouldn't bother me at all I wouldn't mind
Louis hotels
Surprising version of this Tale
Injustice
My name is Zachary is Mo from Sarasota Florida
Radiolab is supported in part by the National Science Foundation and by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world more information books loan at www
Scott Sloan. Org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
About what we're calling tiny moments of Brilliance basically I want to hear about those times when a kid
No did something
It just means you bring back and say whoa how did they do that maybe it was the moment that I can
Kid you've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons and you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed they're ready music in the margin of their geometry homework were interested in the
Epic moments where a kid does something super smart but doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story please share it with us
Go to radiolab.org brilliance
Record a short audio message for us
Again that's radiolab.org / brilliance
Thank you so much
We're back and we've just called up
Clarice gif
No it wouldn't bother me at all I wouldn't mind okay
So you're about to say that you're
Fishball the description you eat
How many
Bird feeders did you have in the backyard would you say rough
At that time
I think I had two or three in an oak tree that's here in our backyard and where we live
It's just
You know it's a peaceful area in birds like things like that they don't like to be alone around a lot of
Congestion and stuffy nose
We enjoy them well I say we home
And my husband and his alive with you know we both enjoyed the birds and
This is where the story flip for me because when those conservationists were knocking at clarice's door
Her husband
I'm more than 50 years
See hear all timers
They were sort of hunker down at their house waiting for his
Bree life to end
You know the Alzheimer's cooking really bad and what they were doing was spending a lot of time on their back porch
Looking at the birds we would come out here and
It was Artie or lemonade he would he would just kind of watch
Our back porch of course faces the lake
We have a beautiful yard we have oak trees
And as I'm sitting here talking to you there's all kinds of birds around right now feeding
We even have sandhill cranes that have to
Babies with them
So the reason your husband would be there
On the porch and if you had this disease in your family
You know how painful it is because he is her husband
And he's just disappearing
A little bit
A little bit more
And then he's mostly not there
But when a bird
Or a bunch of birds
Come by the bird feeder
From wherever he was
He's back
As soon as he would spot something needs a baby there it is there's something bird
And when the whooping crane showed up
Pekin
White
Wild
And that would really get his attention cuz they are such big beautiful birds
You know I could see the
Oh gosh like I happiness in his eyes and
He would smile
Oh
To me it was like you know he came back to me for a little bit when
When he would see things like this it would just
It would make him so happy and it would make me happy to to see
How it affected him
I'm sorry I just fight
I get a kind of choked up when I talk about him
We were married for 56 years then
That disease took him in
It was hard
From her point of view is like a miracle to see a bird like that
And in the way that our husband responded to them and just the other way they that they took his breath away
When really you know he wasn't responding to a
To a lot else in the world
You know when when they seem to recognize things and
And then you lose them again you know
So that's why when the crane people showed up at her door and said please take the bird feeder down
She said
No
You know I left that house
Just you know I just couldn't figure out how to make sense at all once it once it left
Have the people who visited her
Having read your account have they changed their minds at all about
Her or what they do because
It's a toughie
Yeah I'm sure they would still believe that the bird shouldn't have been fed but I don't know if they would be any more sympathy
Her husband at least Bruce Ali and Ivar the trigger so I told Joe Ferguson story
So now what do you say
Well you know my father died of Alzheimer's so I can respect it exactly what she's going through and how different
It is however the cost of that is
The demise of a bird
That that
Other people have spent a huge amount of time in 24 hours a day 7 days a week for that entire Birds license
Let me see year old
Putting in the wild
To help save a space but it but if you put yourself in her
Shoes she says
She by the way
Was very carefully I was very very emphatically
That we didn't
Mess with the birds because
I knew they didn't want them being confronted with with people you know they
Because they are a wild thing and and
Is it
Is it to me it is I don't know why we've always loved nature
We just always loved nature and
And Wildlife
She stayed where
What she felt
You'd want her to stay
But
It's a hard one
To ask the chi
Give up
A glimpse at her husband
For the
Sake of the bird
Espo's
I'm a little more pragmatic than that unfortunately
You would want you would have him make an exception for her
Well at the very least I would have him cuz I understand but she's in a new unique
Place that he's no I don't think it's Unique
Well maybe she is in her particulars
But
That is precisely the problem he has to deal with it are people like her she means well we all mean well
It's not a case of like
People with guns shooting these birds I mean that does happen but I don't think that's the big problem now these are two people who both love the bird book
Can't agree on something right
And he sing in order to love the bird you have to negate
You have to just you have to disappear and we can't as human beings
We don't seem to be able to do that we all have our own personal
Requirements and we put those over and above anything else including wildlife and that's why
Wildlife
Is this
Inside peril
He's asking her
To say goodbye to her husband for the sake
Of
A bird species
How do I get to I just worry that if everybody in the world
Is like her than those birds don't have a chance
I would love it if these birds could just exist on their own somewhere and
Nnnnn in Deepwater marshes where they don't ever encounter people that's never going to happen
Just not going to happen
And that's the struggle it's never going to go away you know no matter what
What happens if any of these species conservation project
We're not going to strike some balance wear
We never have to think about
The power that were exerting in the world this give-and-take. That's what it is
That's the endgame it's is that forever
Special thanks to Simon Adler who who whom
Fairy dust through this whole project and also to
Jon mooallem book
The Wild Ones
Is a
The source
The story I am Robert krulwich
Jennifer Franco be back
Next time