Are you weightless
Radio WNYC
Robert
Alright Robert season 2 finale
More perfect
Long overdue
But much-anticipated maybe
Among those who care
Want want to know
Give me a Mother's Day today and see how it it's it's Tuesday it's Tuesday
MRSA Tuesday
I guess I want to bring you a story from the more perfect
The final story of seasons
This story fulfill the promise I made to myself
The very beginning
Oh my God
This question of yours isn't that old and that deep 22 years old
Sexy girls what the question is
Their eyeballs will be rubbed I don't know what was it two years ago that stuck you
At the quest you've never been able to let go
My first question I bumped into and learning by the Supreme Court
Was why does everybody keep talking about this thing called Commerce Clause
The Commerce
Yes that had a Dazzle for you
No I just wanted to know what the hell is it well
It's Article 1 Section 8 Clause 3 of The Constitution 16 words
Two commas Congress shall have the power to regulate
Commerce with foreign Nations
Among the several States
And with the Indian tribe the power to regulate commerce
Four nations and among the several States and with the Indian tribes there are no more sexier words in the English language
Better words for wooing we're never written
That's Jamie Floyd savitsky Wilmington properly in a second
Okay so
Turns out that question of like what is it
Is pretty easy in words
In the Constitution this a
Congress has the power to regulate
Commerce from one state to another
Like as soon as it goes between states across state borders
Besides
Regulate I think there was a sigh would begin and end and that would be the other it's all good
Yes
But here's the thing
Within that she'll of boring
Impolitely silence here is
I didn't mazing story
Of a kind of cosmic power that develops from very humble beginnings to something truly extraordinary and maybe traveling
New York
A cosmic power you mean this phrase from the Constitution has had consequences
That surprised you a hoe boy
Oh boy here's how I've been thinking about it in the more perfect story
For me
The experience I had learning by the Commerce Clause was a little bit like watching the X-Men movies
Initially it was like my name is Magneto why is Magneto the head of the bad guys
Was why were they follow him he has the most boring power
Mega control metal OK Google like Mystique can shift into any shape she wants storm can
Control lightning initially his power seem like you have the worst one
Sup we start with the Commerce Clause
And we asked the riddle of Magneto trying to cross the bridge getting I'm getting there
All I'm saying is that like initially I didn't understand the true deep nature of his power but then
You see the seats where he's like being attacked by a thousand policemen and he just kind of
Mixed are bullets freeze in midair for a pics of a whole Bridge with lights
Pointing at it and then hit you up
He has the best power
Because the whole world is made of metal she can control the world
If we build the world a different way baby not but
In this world you say I'm Frankenstein's monster
Periodic table baby periodic table baby
For me what it was like to learn about the Commerce Clause
What initially seems stupid and boring
Extraordinary powerful once you understand the world in which it is situated is that mean you're about to take a
On a journey which begins with something that feels utterly trivial
And ends up with being
Something
Enormously powerful
Wow
Has a question to which I simply must answer
Yes
What's the weather out there
Tell you the story of the Commerce Clause everything we fight
America
Is in the 16 words
United States
Supreme Court of the United States
Alright I'm going to I'm going to start you good
Do you even explain why
Something like the Commerce Clause exist
Split a dollar bill issued by
A central bank
Are you looking at dollar bill right now
Stop looking dollar bill
Citizens Federal Reserve Note United States of America
That is James Chen professor of law at Michigan State University now the
Sing about
A dollar bill the awesome obvious thing is that you can
Take a dollar bill and buy
Some Sour Patch Kids or whatever dollar buys these days anywhere in America
But in the late 18th
Century back all the way through
220 century
Was like that no no no no no all the states have their own Banks
Their own bills different sizes colors example there's a moment when South Carolina has it pretty little green South
South Carolina Bill same time Rhode Island
Has this giant
Pink
Square thing and if you are a South Carolinian in Rhode Island trying to buy some
Carrots and potatoes let's say while you hand them your South Carolina bill
Well the Rhode Islanders would look at that and say why don't know what this is
Who's the trust this bank right and so they would
Discount the note based on the distance
From their own home they would discount the note based on
How it looks how professionally drawn up it was
They might look at that $10 and say
That's only worth 8 to me I feel horrible
Horrible way to do business
That sucks for the person holding the note right
Until what the government decided to do is to say 8 words is one bill
Swindell
To be so much easier
This is one of the ways God was going to pull all these
Different states
Together they're going to regulate the current
And not just the currency itself they were going to regulate the flow
Event currency
And this is where the Commerce Clause comes in
This is Jamie Floyd
Journalist
Host of all things considered here early in the Republic now we're at 1820s
Now just to hit pause for 1 second to the Commerce Clause with a pre-existing
Thank ya in the US Constitution really like
Thought about her or where where is it in the minds of people a day
You know we're pretty much where it is right now
No we're not other people
She says 1824 to Steamboat operators get into a thing it's a business
Are you going back and forth between New York and New Jersey that you think they should be the only one allowed to do that and it makes its way as we say
All the way to the US Supreme Court
Who's sitting up there will a big bad dude named John Marshall
Marshall is the sort of Rambo
Of the course
He look at those 16 words have the power to regulate commerce with foreign Nations
He look at those 16 words and a couple of, Sandra. You decide
Pretty much for the first time
Did those words give Congress the power
To regulate
Commerce
Between and among states
This boat is going from one state to the other the only way to resolve that
Is for the federal government to come in
And controller
Again the idea is it this is the only way for the country
To function as a unified thing
John Marshall's decision
He says
You look we have United States of America
We don't have a divided States of America or independent States of America
Or New Jersey and New York existing separately
We decided
To organize
As a United States
And so what
John Marshall says his beak
Cause of that
There has to be a power to regulate trade between those days in amongst those days
When there are disputes
Otherwise it's all going to fall apart
It was at that point that the Commerce Clause
Began to Glow
Womb very faintly
For the next hundred years the government experiment with Commerce Clause in cases involving trade with a Native American tribe
Navigation but if you want to talk about power
Like real
Raw
Weird
Penn Power
That power got Unleashed at a very specific moment around 1941
In a wheat field
Well what happened in the weekly okay well let me introduce you to
My father was a farmer I'd like to say all of his life
Pride in the fact that he never he never work for another man he would tell me that
Well my name is the same as my father at
Roscoe Curtis filbrun
I'm a junior Roscoe filburn the time use a 5th generation farmer
In Montgomery Ohio our farm was just right next to Dayton OH
While moscow
Is about 40 year old man
At this point
Can we talk about 1941-42 good-looking
Sturdy
Fiercely independent I never worked
For another man in my life
Apparently that was his motto
He would tell me that many times over the years if you had to put like Captain America with a pitchfork
This is
So Roscoe's got this far more than a hundred cows on it
He would milk cows until both of these arms when practically now catch chickens mm
And a we had a very big Garden he would plant things you know light string beans lime
Angie's sweet corn potato carrot radishes all different kinds of apples
Trees are strawberries and raspberries
Different kinds of Halo and of course
Sweet sweet
Okay set up out of the way here's what happened
It's 1941
Roscoe
Senior my dad was out in the field I think on his tractor
That day he was plowing the weed or something and
Apparently must have been some guy
From the
Department of Agriculture locally
I guess going around to various farmers in our community
Wanting the farmers to answer
Several pages I think of questions
And this particular day this government gentleman came out into the field
You looked around
And he said Roscoe
Oceans you got 22 Acres
You're over your quota
He was 11.1 Acres over
What was permitted
Roughly inside with the guy tells him he have to pay a fine
A really big fine
My dad looked over and he was just as sober as a judge in a courtroom on a murder case
And what happened next
We change the country forever
Ways that we are still literally living with but make sure to fill in the gaps here
Play what you need to know about why they're they were even having this conversation
And to help me with that my name is
Sorry savitsky and I'm an attorney at law
An important thing to understand is that you know when our story starts with Roscoe filburn
Pictures of the Great Depression is happening
And the Dust Bowl
And so you have a lot of people who rely on selling crops and buying crops and so wheat prices to matter of life
Millions of Americans
This nation is asking for action and action now
1938 Congress in Acts was called the agricultural adjustment act to reboot
The economy so the 1938 agricultural adjustment act got the federal government into the
Regulating wheat
Busy with the government did was they said to the farmers America we are going to give you essentially alone we're going to
Guarantee you a certain minimum price
For wheat
We're going to give you X number of dollars per bushel or whatever it is
That will help lift you out of poverty
In exchange for that
You have to promise US
To only grow a certain amount
It's in the big fear was it they grew too much
There be the
Flood of Supply on the wheat market prices would crash
And that would be bad for everyone you know weed is sort of a collective action problem right everyone's going to sell as much weed as they can but that
That means prices go down and everyone makes less
So what the government decides to do in addition to giving out loans is that they placed a cap on how much wheat a person could grow
So quote
Straight up quotes
That way you ensure the supply of wheat is steady and you insured
That that the prices don't crash
And whole reason the government could do this
Regulate the entire wheat Market
What's by henredon the Commerce
Colossus 16 words
Basically said
That when something like wheat is bought and sold and moved from one place to another one state to another cross state lines
Well that's Interstate Commerce and that's something that Congress can regulate
So my father having his back to Roscoe filburn without inspector
On his farm
Spectra says
Look Roscoe you've grown too much weed my dad looked over and he was just as sober as a judge in a courtroom
Romano murder case
And what do you think he says back he says wait a minute I'm going to show you exactly how I feel about that
No
That's how I feel know you government might have been a family guy she says I don't get it
I'm not I'm not have nothing to do with interstate commerce
And
This is the key
Explain to the inspector that yes
According to the government quota I'm only supposed to grow about 11 acres a week and I am growing 23
The next R12
I'm not selling it to anybody
He doesn't sell them
He doesn't trade the way
What's he doing with this week he uses all the wheat to feed his animals
Feeding it to the farm animals the weight
He said the sum of the week to the stairs I
I was just keeping it on the farm well yeah so it send it
Sweetly internal operation I'd like the poor guy gets kind of Dragon 2
National case inspector I have nothing to do with interstate commerce
I'm on my phone I'm doing my business
Big Brother leave me alone but
Big brother does not leave me alone
The inspector
Says we're the government that's the law
Please uphold it
Pay
The fine
50 Cent
For every excess bushel I think it is
Yeah 239 excess bushels of wheat for which she was unifying about 117 bucks
In today's dollars
It's about two grand
2 Grand
My my father
Apparently he wasn't real crazy about that and I guess he didn't like that too much
If I'd have been 20 or 25 years old
I would have probably advised my father not to do what he did but I guess they sue the federal government
Huh
His army was like look I'm just trying to feed my cows come on I guess it went to our core
Church in Dayton Ohio
That was the first and I believe
That he wants round1 to Roscoe the Ohio court agreed there's no
Commerce of any kind going on your unlike the original case with the boat price I believe I even remember
My sister telling me that the he came a home
And he was just delighted that he did win
But then
Government feels the case and of course the one that got to the Supreme Court of the United
It states
He he did he lost
Key lost
Any decisions that I think it's fair to say
Still
Drives conservatives and Libertarians bonkers
Either one of those things but I get it
What does Supreme Court set
Is it Roscoe filburn growing that extra weed and not selling it still
Counts as interstate commerce
Could have that extra week causes him to not
On the market
He needs less wheat from the market in all the farmers of America did that
Cannot be really bad for the market the idea is that if you need more wheat than the quota
You go on the market and buy it
Even though you can grow it yourself
Everyone can produce their quota and then whatever extra they need
I'm pretty soon the regulation breaks down
Which means it's a government intervention in the wheat Market will have failed
You will have to
Beaded our attempt to regulate this Market therefore we have to regulate even the things you don't do
That is so weird it's such a mine frankly it's like
He's not doing anything
What was the term literally known Behavior this is Obamacare
Getting heated over Health Care individual mandate
Just explain that's a reference to Barack Obama's healthcare plan hotly-debated
Couple years ago still hotly debated
What are the key ideas without plan is it in order for health care to be affordable for everyone
Everyone should have to buy it so we're going to require people
To buy insurance
Where else you pay a penalty
Which made a lot of people mad cuz they're like hey the government force me to buy something I don't want my decision not to get Healthcare
Is not
Participation in interstate
It's not even economic activity
I'm sitting here on my couch not buying
You sitting here
From the individual perspective that makes perfect sense but if you can out
And Justice Kagan said this in court
It's not so simple uninsured people are increasing
Normal family premium Congress
$5 a year
The price that everybody pays for the service
Obamacare makes sense to me away but getting back to Roscoe
Things you're not because you cannot know farmers and Island this is the case
In which
Congress
Receives a tremendous amount of power from the US Supreme Court
Essentially this case
It says that Congress can regulate
Almost anything
And that is
D single
Most significant precedent
In the area of the Commerce Clause the Big Bang
Did anyone try to raise their hand in the
Camillus be like whoa if you can regulate the non behavior of this American Farmer
Then that's not even a slippery slope that's like a cliff that goes right down like there's no slope to that
Times editorial from November 13 1942
Set the farmer who grows feed for consumption on his own Farm competes with Commerce
Would not the housewife who makes herself address suzhou equally
The net of the ruling in short seems to be
The Congress can regulate every form of economic activity if it's so decide
Would not the housewife who makes herself address
You so you got to say yeah it's like yeah if you make something like shoot I've my wife and I with our kids made these little like
A miniature stuffed animals for them to play with the other day are we then in violation of some
Oh my God
So like what happened here essentially Robert Issa thiam
The definition of Commerce
Changed and is in a sneaky but it really powerful way
Is now it wasn't just like the buying and selling of stuff
It was the not buying and selling
Yeah it was your negative
Commercial acting all the things you don't do is a much bigger territory than the things you do do
Yeah
Extension of
And that expansion would continue over the next few decades and it would move them just weeds
To something much deeper to like
Beyond markets into the into matters
The heart
You mean like people hating on each other people
Trusting people being bred people
All will become clear after the break myaurora and after the break
Excuse me while I get myself of this sizzling drink and settle down in my black leather couch
Couch yeah alright season 2 finale of more perfect here on Radiolab
Will continue in a moment
This is Nicole from Corning New York
Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in
In the modern world
More information about Sloan at www.slha.org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help this summer I'm hosting
And I request for those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
We're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments of childhood Brilliance basically I want to hear
Did something
It just means you lean back and say wow how did they do that maybe it was the moment that I can
Kids you've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons and you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of the musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed are ready music in the margin of their geometry homework were interested in the
Epic moments where a kid does something super smart but doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story please share it with us
Go to radiolab.org Brilliance and record a short audio message for us
Again that's radiolab.org / Brilliance thank you so much
I'm Jedi which this is what we're featuring the final episode of more perfect season 2
Huron Radiolab strange and Hartfield salute
To the Commerce Clause of the US Constitution
Yes and a previously we had the big bang in the Wheatfield but that was still about markets in Commerce and all that
Right
There was a moment
But two decades after the Wii case
Where you might say
The Commerce Clause got weaponized
Hello hey can you hear me
Yes this is Jad from Radiolab more perfect in New York
Jack
Jad Jad
Jad Jad okay
Well Andrew is here and he's
Really understand what I mean
Can you do to yourself tell me who you are
Your name
Cassius Ali McClung Junior
And how old are you
And where are you speaking to us from right now
Time in Birmingham Alabama
You were born Birmingham
Yes
Aside from some time at college in Florida and a stint in the Coast Guard Ali jr.
Has lived in Birmingham in his entire life
And the reason we call them up is that for 75 years
His family ran
A Famous BBQ joint
Name dali
This is your dad's birthday
From what I understand right yes my grandfather founded it
Oh really what was that
1926 to this was passed to your dad who passed
To you yes
Okay we were in business together till he died
Holley's BBQ was located on Birmingham Southside the building we were in its time you're talk
1949 till 68
It was concrete
Blocker
Big sign outside said world's best barbecue good for today
Barely during lunch
Align with stretch out the door
Ollie's was famous for its slow-cooked pork and chicken and for its spicy vinegar BBQ sauce
In the pie baking chocolate pies in a lot of pies
But all these was also famous or would become famous
For something else entirely
McAllister the times
The way things were
At that time course
Throughout South Birmingham
We had
Carryout business
As well as
Sit down Bass
And
Those
How are Black customers came in and
I order from the carryout counter
But their food out
And
Truth fact history
Take it on
Witham Tito supposed to
Just sitting down and eat
What he saying is that all these barbecue with segregated if you were white you can eat inside if you are black
You couldn't remain that way
The way to work
So what is the temperature of the Commerce Clause okay so the Federal
At the time this will be the Kennedy administration and LBJ
They want to come down and places like Ollie's barbecue but their hands were sort of tied
We have this thing called the Fourteenth Amendment says no State shall deprive any person
Life liberty or property without due process of law nor shall any state the night equal protection of the laws
Stephanie person
4 written
Basically outlaw
Things like segregation
Corseted work
We have another 80 plus years of Jim Crow and the reason for that
Is it the Supreme Court shortly after the 14th amendment was passed
Kind of neutered it not kind if they did
What they did was by insisting that we read the 14th Amendment as being targeted
Only at States if you look at that sentence II says the Fourteenth Amendment says no state knost
State shall deprive any person of life liberty or property without depressive problem is is when
A restaurant owner like Ali McClung deny service to Black patrons
It's not Alabama doing the damage
Just private business of Alabama ordered McClung family to discriminate against black patrons they just
So if the 14th amendment can only get two states
Hear it has no reach because there's no State action there is nothing to regulate at the state level
So
The best decided to do
If that's a dating
Legal gymnastics is they decided to use
Commerce Clause
Congress passes the most sweeping Civil Rights bill ever to be written into the law
July 2nd 1964 Congress passes
Sweeping Civil Rights bill that was hinged on those
16 words and I will explain to you how
It's kind of fascinating
It just a second
The first
Just to get us to that point
So 1964 Civil Rights
Act
Past
Did you desegregate right away
No
Can we work we were not happy with it obviously
I want to read you something that you said in nineteen
54 I believe you sir
Serve your account of something that happened in
Indian restaurant
Day after the Civil Rights Act was
Past
A black man comes into the restaurant asking to be served
And
And you turn him away
45 minutes later comes back with young girl for all the black people they say
Sit down at the counter they want to know
Why
You why all these wouldn't serve them
And they were taking notes
And your CO2 the same esteem like agitators
Yeah exactly where they
They were folks and came
And when around several places
Just
Test the law basically yeah
And you were and you were turning those folks away
Yes
Kick them out
Why
I'm just because that's way
Had always done this way
Until the law
Got to judicate it
We weren't going to
Unilaterally
Change light that you know that from their perspectives are there because the laws been changed
Yeah
Yes
Holly says right after the Civil Rights Act
Pass
Serving emergency meeting was called of the Birmingham
Restaurants association
Penis adwin
I discussed with the
With an executive of it
This was
Going to be such a
Potentially
Harmful to the
Restaurant businesses make you an ass all your way customers is that what you worried about
I mean that was a possibility
And
Somebody ought to do something
So we can end up being
Wants to do something
IFR filing suit
Today file the suit
Basically saying to the federal government you have no right to barge into our
Small
Independent
Local business
Start was
They can't really
Tell us what to do because we're not in Interstate business and that's all that the federal government regulates and
Up until that point that was all they had regular
The case went to the US District Court for the Northern District of Alabama
Panel
We had a unanimous
Decision
Our favor
The Alabama Court agreed
There was
No interstate commerce happening year
And that always did not have to desegregate
They can sell their ribs to whoever they wanted
And we were
Optimistic about that
Government that Appeals
And the case
They say it goes all the way to the Supreme Court
Alright let me know explain to you how the government made this arguments they made it in court
October 5th 1964 General Archibald Cox
Lays it out why the government should be allowed to use the Commerce Clause of all things to desegregate
Napoli's operate a restaurant in Birmingham Alabama specializing in Barber
He said this is a business that sells and buys a lot of meat
Yeah please prices about $70,000 worth of meat 60 9680
$3 to be exact
Tim Alabama
Song that that plan
Came from other states so did move to another state
In other words you think you're a local business but you're not meat is sourced from places other than
In Alabama what about your ketchup aesthetically
Not mine in Alabama so even though we bought it from a local vendor that local vendor probably bought it from somebody who
Bought it from somebody that they were reaching beyond what it ever been done before basically
Gavin was basically telling them the same thing they told Roscoe Phil breath
You are not an island
And that was only the government's first argument they had another argument
That is a second then still more directly
It was even more
Radical
Trans racial discrimination
Restaurant
Interstate
Which is caused by the artificial narrowing of the
Supermarket
Resulting from the
So here's the argument
If you deny black people access to restaurants and hotels
You are effectively shutting down interstate travel by them
Imports of the country where this practice
Is commonplace
Entire
Deep South you're limiting their ability to cross state lines and
The central argument
Suggestion is that
When you discriminate against someone
You create
Down
Stream
Negative
Commercial effects
Like you create a chilling effect
Because the person you're discriminating against is then less likely to travel a
Across state lines
Send money
So in effect you are
Depressing their future
Interstate commerce
If you ask
Black people
With this experience
From this time.
They were universally say
We never left home unless
Every
Tire
Was triple checked
Every
Belt was triple checked in the car
Because we did not
Want to have a car breakdown in a hostile southern town
And get lynched
Right right
It is an entire system
Of travel and commerce that's
At stake here
Essentially the argument was discrimination is bad for business
Is expensive
And
Ultimately in a unanimous decision
The Supreme Court
Same court that 100 years earlier had basically gutted the 14th Amendment
Supreme Court
Agreed
That discrimination in restaurants pose significant burdens on the quote
Interstate flow of food and upon the movement of products China
Remember that decision coming down
I'm certainly
Where were you
Pause at work
Can you tell me a little bit about how you and your dad
Process that decision
Simply
Heard anyone who came in after that
And they were
The very next day there was a group of local law civil rights leaders who came in and ate lunch
I knew some of them by
Haven't seen him in the news that sort of thing
They were not our regular customers
Orlando actor
Franklin
Lay
Celebrated our what even want to say
Tested I don't know what the motive was because I came in late lunch
They got served
It's like anybody else
They came in and it was fine
The law was recited seoul
That was it
With a tent
No
I don't know why Tricia was waiting on those
She was a little
Answer about it
And it was at this way just to see a black woman yes
It was now but she was
Like most my employees been there a very long time
Panda
Have never
Served other black folks
In a sit-down situation and
And Quest
It was surreal
Little bit
Say upsetting but
Different cute little hesitant at first sight
What's the right hand side of abdomen
She didn't we didn't
That was not a problem
After the ruling it's not as if a lot of Black customers 70/30 coming into Ali's BBQ
They didn't
A guy named Nathan Turner Jr put it
2014 he was interviewed
Turn into herpes
He grew up nearby Ollie's
Just a fact of olive
Pushed it that far
To take it to the
Supreme Court
It left a bad taste
Pun intended
In the mouth of a lot of black
People in Burma
In-N-Out 53 years later
How do you think about that Supreme Court decision
Well
You're at if you're asking about segregation that's one thing we asked about Supreme Court and
Seasoning on the Commerce Clause I still disagree with
Let me put it real
Real succinctly
I think
What you had
And that
Decision
Was it rather than
Can affect my
Civics
Correct but I don't know
It rather than three-quarters of the Congress
And 3/5 of the states I believe it is having two
Or maybe 2/3 Carlos whatever it is
Having to vote to
Repeal an amendment to the car
Constitution
You had basically 9 appointees who repeal the 10th Amendment
The Tenth Amendment basically says that the powers not given to the feds
Are reserved
The states
For the people
That's about as succinct as I can
Would you understand how this is going to sound to a lot of our listeners
I mean that you are making a states rights argument
As a not-so-veiled weight
To continue to discriminate
They're really in the end this is not about
States rights I think that's going to I was going to sound to a lot of people
Well it may very well but it's not the case
Was there segregation yes
Where we going to voluntarily
And that
Probably not
Would we go back and reinstate if we could
No apps
Not
But
The
Issue that you're talkin about with the
Commerce Clause in the
Constitutional
Issue
Are still just what I said
So you still believe 53 years later that the Supreme Court got it wrong that they should have never
Use the Commerce Clause to make you desegregate Ali
Yep that is correct
But don't hear me say that I don't want to go back to have segregation again
That's
Separate issue
But is it separate I guess is my question you know
My God grant you
If you think of it in the abstract
Federal government being able
How to regulate
Commerce across
All boundaries
Is an enormous power
And he could be a scary power so I grant you that at the same time
You have a Civil Rights Act
That
It speaks to a different amendment in the Constitution
Egyptian writing that you and your father were not willing to follow so how is the government going to get you to
To pay attention
And again line
They've got to use the Commerce Clause
So on some level isn't it
Isn't
Power
Present
Because the other principles
It would otherwise regulate your Behaviour
Just aren't working
That's the point
Choose which
Which is the priority
Basically
I understand that you would which is the priority
I will
Which is the priority of
Those amendments
Until for you the 10th Amendment that grants states rights
For everything. Enumerated
Outweighs
The Dignity of black people
No
Will put so say to me differently then
Well
The 10th Amendment
Lieutenant
The states
The Fourth Amendment yes
An agreement to take the 14th amend
Guess
People rights
Everyone rides
But here's the thing about rights
It's kind of like the first law of thermodynamics
There's only
And people don't realize this a lot of times they only so many rights
Only a finite number rights
If you take some
Give something to someone
They come from someone else or somewhere
Now
It's very well to say that
The end of segregation
Was a higher
Right
And more importantly
Then
They misuse of the Commerce Clause
Whatever you want to say
But you're still a balance and just
Which one you
Think it's most important
Today's products become a zero-sum
Bali's basic point
We talked about this for another hour
Was it in achieving desegregation that
By the way
Civil Rights Act
54 dramatically alter
Without the desegregated huge parts of the South
By doing it that way
Says with the converse
Something was sacked
Feisty calls it a zero-sum I wouldn't call it that
I don't think most people
Call it that
Treating people with dignity
Quality is a net win
.
But
It is legitimately strange
Did the government had to take such
Around about ass-backward way
To fix this
To fix this grave Injustice
What what what you would think would be the obvious
That you would go right to those civil rights
Parts of the Constitution
It was weird is it we have the 14th Amendment and yet we go to the
Commerce clause for something
That is so clearly stated in one of the amendments
Search Jamie Floyd Again by the way
The lawyers in those cases
Is that what they wanted to win
They wanted to win more than they wanted to make a social statement about
Equal justice equal rights the 14th Amendment I mean those things matter
Most of all they wanted to win
They wanted to shut down discrimination
Athos lunch counters and if Congress could shut them down or require them to open their doors to all them
Americans using
Those 16 words
I'm okay with that
Yeah yeah
No I mean obviously the if the ends do justify the means in that case
But it does make you if you should have put that case and the weak case in your mind as a kind of split screen
It's
It's a little strange because I do think okay we have
I didn't mean it I said it
Hopefully we're Americans with principles
Does it matter you know that we believe in equality believe in racial
Call Justice
But really we just believe in money
And we can do all the other stuff by bootstrapping it
E-commerce
But somehow as as pure principles
Play what don't have teeth while it's deeply troubling that we have to use
Commerce to achieve our
Higher values
That is weird to me that is
Fundamentally weird
It's kind of cynical
Well yeah I mean
I
You are right we are
At least in large part about
Commerce in the sky
But if that's who we are
Then we should embrace it and use it to our advantage
And if we can use it to our advantage perhaps it does take us
Two are higher princess
How to understand why it's not all bad
What if Jamie's points actually thought it was that
Legislating morality
Fletchling what is good and what is bad
Doesn't always go well
Cuz we very often don't agree
Galaxy there been times where people kept slaves and thought that was
That was right
400 years you had the 14th amendment in place but it couldn't solve all these barbecue
And here was a way
For the government without going at the moral questions head-on
Government can reach its hand all the way into the barbecue joints in the hotels in the restaurants and the houses and now the cake shops of America
Reached an all the way down into the local
And it was because of this increasingly expensive idea of Commerce
That was now no longer the buying and selling of things or the knot
Buying and selling of things it was now
Any Behavior
They could create a kind of butterfly
That might one
Day many steps Downstream
Have a future effect
On the buying and selling of things
Has right his case
That was a massive shift
It shifted totally the federal government's role Beyond business even if you
You think it's good then that's fine
And it's for the better
But just asked me realize that it was a
MasterChef from
The way
The country been up before that time
After the McClung case James Chen says
Service governments use
Of the Commerce Clause pretty much when Y no real limit
Begin wave those 16 word sort of like a magic want to pass laws on everything
Fair labor standards to schedule drugs
68 guns Justice for victims of trafficking Act
Lions in the wild species 1592 professional and amateur sports protection
Magwitch forbid State authorized Sports gambling
Even had to make the argument itself
What's the government even has to defend itself
James Chen says there were times when the government would pass a law it get taken to court in the government would basically
Not show up
And he would still with the government even has to argue
So you can see the McClung case as sort of a second big bang but then
You get to the midnight
At this point 1994 U of a democratic President Bill Clinton Democratic majorities in both houses of Congress
And
Together they pass
The violence against women act
Today is the first day of
Spring and I think it's appropriate that we begin a new season of Hope
In the fight against domestic violence
I thank you all for being here
This is an important day
The Act was service sweeping rethink of the federal government's role in trying to prevent violence against with
Minit beefed-up investigations
Of violent crimes against women prosecution's it allowed women to sue their alleged attackers in federal court
We had to take
Responsibility domestic violence is now the number one health risk for women between the ages of 15 and 44 in
North Country
And the law was hinged on the Commerce Clause same essential argument is in the barbecue
That same fault my name is Christy brzonkala I'm 19 years old
A woman named Christy brzonkala starts her freshman year at Virginia Tech and just weeks in September 1990
Before I was raped by two football players in my own dorm
I'd met them for the first time just 15 minutes before they assaulted me
These two football players she alleged had raped her repeatedly on a single night in 1994
She went to the local campus authorities
She told her story
College held their own hearings didn't go to the police
What is suspended one of the two students
Key Peele
And when he returned
Christy brzonkala dropped out of
Christy brzonkala
Ultimately decides
Sue her alleged attackers and the school
Under this new law of the violence against women act
And the case
Ultimately makes it to the Supreme Court
Will hear arguments number 99 5 Christy brzonkala vs Antonio Morrison
When Christie's case got to Supreme Court her lawyer made the same argument
About women that the government is made in the Ollie's barbecue case about black people
That discrimination
Or in this case outright violin
Has a huge Downstream effect on the economy
Substantially affects the national economy
Gender-based violence and the fear of that discriminatory violence
Deters women's travel interstate
Restricts women's choice of jobs and ability to perform those jobs
Reduces National productivity
An increases medical and other costs
And again the court was given tons of evidence about the economic effects
Congress heard from women
Whose batter is kept their partners for morphine
Every year this cost the country billions of dollars and that economic Downstream effect was not hard
How to prove in this case
She dropped out if you ever get it right it's not just her
Is everyone else who similarly situated but in this case
Yarygin what's happening in a very different time in the country very different mood
In front of an increasingly conservative Supreme Court
It just wasn't buying it anymore and Arbors on Carla's complaint alleges that she was the victim of a
Chief justice rehnquist reading the majority opinion
Justice could fail to provide her a remedy for Morrison's conduct but gender motivated crimes
Economic activity
Another word for very sorry for what may have happened to Christine broccolibutt
This is not Commerce this is violence suggestion was at least in the Ali's case there was
Something bought sold in here they felt like I was too thin
Accordingly reject the argument that Congress May regulate non-economic violence coming all time.
Based solely on that conducts remote effect on interstate commerce
Chief justice rehnquist. His majority
2 * 2
Chipaway
At the Commerce
Power
YouTube Tiny teeny teeny weeny little bit
Jamie Floyd says that tempt
To roll it back
Continue Suites rolling back
It is rolling back
Still pretty powerful don't get us wrong but where were left
At the end of the day
Is it a really confusing place
Ali
McClung excluding black people from his
Dining room
Yeah commercial actor
We can sit reprehensible but I would like to think that raping Christine would be at least as bad
Totally
This kind of like
Absurd abstraction gets us to
And in
A coherent Ideal World
Can't be right
I don't know when you win that win the
The reasoning behind something gets a little Rocky and the soul of thing
It's called into question like what are you doing judges yeah for me that's what happens when you make everything
In about money
A little bit rotten at their core All Rights
So I'm going to die before I before I submit the credits
Robert thank you for being a party to this adventure this episode was produced by
Mysore akari more perfect is produced by me Jedi Vim rod and an amazing team Susie lechtenberg Jenny
Lawton Julia Longoria Kelly Prime Alex overington and sarkari with Elie mystal Christian Fair
Sirius and Hershman Dave Gable and Michelle Harris we had production help from Derek John and Louis Mitchell
Supreme Court audio is from Oye free law project collaboration with Legal Information Institute at Cornell
Leadership support more perfect provided by the Joyce Foundation
Additional funding is provided by the Charles Evans Hughes Memorial Foundation
Time to Say Goodbye Time to Say Goodbye
I'm Jared I'm run I'm Robert krulwich
Thanks for listening