Are you awake
Listening to Radiolab
Radiolab WNYC
And NPR
How did you even get onto
I feel I feel like buttons
Fixture how did the okay what can I eat let me let me let me start
This is reported lot of Nasser and today on radio live lobsters and I are bringing Jad and you three
Wildly different stories
About
Literally my power and freedom
DuckTales
This all started
Because
I could not
Convince
Any of my friends
To go to the elevator history me
Museum with me
There was not a single person out of the eight and a half million people living in New York who wanted to
To go to the bottom
But you found one except around recall
I'll go to anything
Jamie told me
Never to stop recording
So we go to Long Island City
Is entirely tax
See yellow only thing we saw was a big old boring building covered with
With with taxis
We have no interest in
We found some guy on the street yes there is
You got to go up the stairs
I'll take you there anyway all right
Ragnarok
Thank you very much
Haha wow that's quite a son elevator Museum founded 2011
So we open up the door
I have no idea what could be
Hello
This is different from what
Large room where only are you building up to something
It's filled with
What is it
What stop elevator match
Pens or witches and warlocks
Random
Stop is the things you get with sales
Yeah the Rosenberg lubricant
Small brass objects of one kind or another giant painting of escalators and moving
Sidewalk
And sitting in a corner
Hi I'm lucky
Across the room
We see a guy
Sitting is it an older guy got your car
He has his glasses
Is down on his nose and he's in charge of
Play something call me if they want to come visit 718-361-8683 apparently you're supposed to make
And if I'm in the movies I'll get a saw
Patrick is being the lead singer in the number of bands and he even studied cons
This is a man for all seasons
He's got so much elevators
Stop asking questions of living years old because when you were seven years old you walk into an elevator and had a
Emil nier
I went to college got a couple degrees
Stay in the elevator
Never left
I actually my first
Item is over I want the walls here
Let me show you something
Announce we're walking along a button
We come inevitably
You do a series of elevator button panel
Here's a golden up-and-down here's a bronze up and down
He has all kinds of ants
Speak buttons that I mean from a different era songs one where you go
Inches into feet
So this
Is the Genesis
The insults begins and it is an insult because what is about to happen
Cuz he's about to tell us that we are
Googles and have no power in the world in which we inhabit
He does that by pointing to the
Close door button you push in the bush.
He says
Just says matter-of-factly
About 80% of the van on function
Oh wow
Because they are broken and on fix them because they wasn't never wire
They would never ever wire to never
What's the time we going to do it
But 80%
I just assumed they don't work
You assume they don't lie so yeah I sweat no no no no no
Know what I cannot be right we make cannot be right have you ever board close button that yeah that has had any
Psychological tool for you you need me button to go back up there something but that's not too but he said also
He had also a very
Fan series
Most expensive
They're extremely intelligent
Yellow is actually remember what happens everyday
So the elevator system knows that
Between
855 + 9
Wechat 373
People in an average morning come
So we're going to return to cars to the main floor as soon as
We possibly can
We're not going to park anything up
But it knows that
At 4:45
Because 650 people leaving the building you get three wheelchairs to get to old people that and so we programmed
Timing of the elevator to accommodate the whole
All you doing is screwing up our timing by touching that thing I mean you have thousands and thousands of people
Anxiously trying to urge the machine to do their will watching people just stupid
This is cruel I have to tell you
His idea that we would somehow have the authority or the power to close the door with a pencil
Am I building they work
I'm sympathetic to that Viewpoint to be sympathetic
The crazy ass vertical stack of humanity
How is that going to work if not for
Beautifully designed
Systems like the
This is about Freedom. This is about who
Began looking around for some
Little Chute
Song of poop
To give the Radiolab distance
Some tiny bit of power they can have back in this other Leaf assisted suicide
And you found it
You did we get what did you find
We have those we have packed the close button
Really
Wait. I'm suddenly in for the first time I missed it what what what did you discover the next time chat
If you walk into an elevator
The door closes
Mysteriously although you're going to the 8th floor
Apps on five
The door open
Upir out
There's nobody there
English
Will robots
Leaving you powerless on hapless
But not anymore
Now here's what you can do
I will check this and it's
You can put your arm
Through the door
Breaking the beam with your arm and then get your own back Teresa
That will convince
Stupid stupid supine elevator
That you have just
Someone who just entered the elevator
And now it will close that was shaving amazing 3 5 Seconds
We will give you that sense of using Superman and 45 minutes of your life.
You're welcome
I should just say
Patrick was actually really awesome guy send everyone into the elevator History Museum
So the next story
This is maybe the most
Valuable
I button
Exactly it's
The he was a guy and his name was
Button Gwinnett
What is it
Button Gwinnett button
Is that his real name that's his real name
That's Bobby Livingston from R&R auction house in Boston
Button Gwinnett
Button Gwinnett is one of two signers of the Declaration of Independence that
We're born in England and moved to the United States were moved to the colonies
He is a founding fathers founding fathers signature thousands of times
And anything about that signature gets interesting in a minute
Button Gwinnett was born in England in the early seventies
890 moved
Did George Anthony
55 Bar and Island and
I believe he began
A import
St. Catherines Island
Debtor actually and everybody
He don't have anybody money
He failed in his business
He became a radicalized revolutionary and he joined Georgia politics late in the
17 six
And when it got to be 1776
In Philadelphia he was in Independence Hall
And he sang
The
Really it's the left
And below
John Hancock
But then he goes home to Georgia
And gets in a duel with his political rival and it killed in 1777
And
Then
I believe in 1780
His wife passed
Is away leaving only his daughter
And then by 18.
His daughter passes away in his lineage
Is disappeared
So listen to history
Yes
But his signature is on that
Very important piece of paper
True which becomes important
Because around the 1820s the last
Of the signers of Declaration of Independence were dying
So there was a nostalgia
Who are the founding fathers and that's when people began collecting signatures that replaced on that document
So people collect the Jefferson
Adams
Hancock
And they started thinking okay I want a whole set of the 56 men that sign that document people want
That they want the separate American
I don't think there was any more important signature than them
Signatures that replaced on that.
Get them all
In a problem
A rose
Button Gwinnett signature they were almost impossible to find a hundred and some-odd years later
I went to see his collection and get a beautiful house in Florida
Overlooking the bay I won't tell you which Bae but
You show me some great stuff and it's what else you got Nico's I swear he pushes a button on a wall begins to ride
He's got like
Incredible in a Wilbur Wright
George Washington button
I could see in the middle of my eye goes right to it the unmistakable signature
Button Gwinnett is like the centerpiece of a secret walk
And I don't like goodness that was pretty amazing the autograph equivalent of some really famous
Miss Diamond do you know where something like that it
You know it's the Holy Grail still exist
There are 50 51
51 non examples
In the world mostly things big sister I owe you
If you have one of these things what's it was where they worth I'll tell you this it is more valuable
Golden Lincoln much more
100 times more than
What about George Washington Ben Franklin yes
Yes let machine it outside
Abscess Ben Ben Franklin was a world-famous
Ben Franklin
Was a man of letters he wrote tons of letters he was president of Pennsylvania he was there bastard or France
He wrote and wrote and wrote and sign and sign and sign so there's
With the exception possible
Exception of
William Shakespeare
Describe a Button Gwinnett
Rent a bunch that did basically nothing else in his life
Mosto
Valuable signature
In the world today what makes it
Extremely hard to complete a set of side of the Declaration dependence because of the 5141 are in libraries or
Institutions in the never be able to get it so that only 10
Examples
In public hands
Hello sir
Hello sir how are you doing
Okay you checked your
Your bags are
That there are
Gwinnett Public Library
I believe the reading room is still closed but we're going to a kind of
Super secret place where you know
I need to ring a bell to get a
Really
Thomas Lannon I work in the main switch narcos division at the new Republic
He took us into a special room on the top
On the top floor
Wow
Awesome all by yourself
What does I got to put him on the wood
Representing it up at a wooden what kind of beautiful old wooden table
And we have
On the table
Button
Gwinnett
Fourth wave on Justice
Appreciate
Tell me one of these is worth you don't know until they're sold cuz they're different quality but the last one that we know of that was
Sold here in New York
What's sold for
720 2500. I'm not in the business of estimating value of things
But I can say that Button Gwinnett autographs at the New York
Public Library hours
Classified
Splendid
Highest-ranking splendid
They're not they're not
Simply
Cut autograph
Document
Sign
Best looking fish
This is the most
Extravagant
Seals on it like red wax seals
So for me that the impulse impulse I'm having right here is not
Just putting it in my pocket running away like a damn plus I'm having and I'm being totally Frank here
Is that is the same impulse I have like you know when you want to pull the
Fire alarm like I just wanted to tear these all up right now
Kind of
I just wanted to
Take all of these papers
That we're honest
Table
And just tear them all to shreds I guess I can speak to your desire to 22 Destroyer
And then the guy really looked alarmed but I really don't really want to
It's so arbitrarily valuable like
I could just rip it up
But it is
Okay so taking a cue from love it when we come back we're going to take a decidedly
Auntie button turn
We'll be right back
This is Adrian Stein from
New Brunswick New Jersey
Radiolab
Supported in part by the
The natural sign
Find Foundation
And by the Alfred p
Keith Sloan found
Enhancing public understanding of science
And Technology
In the modern world
More information about slowness
Www.
Sloan.
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
And I've requests
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
We're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments
Williams
Basically I want to hear about this
Did you know did something
It just means you lean back and say whoa
How do they do that
Maybe it was the moment that our kids you've been reading to 4 month started reading back
To you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lesson
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of the musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed are ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the specific moments where a kid does something super smart
Have anything to do with it
If you have a story
T-shirt with us
Go to radiolab.org
Brilliance
Record a short audio mess
Again that's radiolab.org / brilliance
Thank you so much
Is Radiolab on Jedi penrod's in the podcast lot of Nasser Robert krulwich
Are talking buttons
So
We have one more
Button tail
This sort of
Once we
We're onto buttons this
Serta presented itself because it is V most high stakes
Button
Ever
Yeah Mr President we have a crisis situation
One of our missiles silencer a thermonuclear button
Is it a boy
I mean that's what we want everyone in Hollywood
We just figured okay let's go find the button
That
Destroys the world
We brought in a friend of mine Alex wellerstein
All things
Nuclear weapon related
He sat down in
The first thing he
With that
No button
There has never been a single
But when you get to like 1950
T2 1950
T3
In ordinary parlance people say where the president has his finger on the button
And I don't know where that phrase comes from the butt
It's older it's much older than the bomb
Real so 1910s is when all of the stuff
HG Wells
The famous but there's there's all this literature about
The crazy scientist who invented a new form of gas that can like Kill Everybody
And he has a button
I need a red button I don't know if they say read
But it's definitely a button
According to Alex by the time we develop nuclear weapons existing imagery about
The scientist can blow up the world using their button
Transfers to the president can blow up the world use
In his butt
I meant Alex told us something that we
Surprises
He said when the US government dropped the first bombs on Japan so
The bomb that they dropped on Hiroshima and they didn't take off with the bomb armed
They took off
What's a bomb missing a piece
And the missing piece is except
It's a chunk of uranium
And then one of the scientists who was also a military guy
Crawled into the back of the
Displaying while it was in route
Opened up the bomb
Put the missing piece back into it and then close the back up again and turned on all the electrical switches
Zedd
If we drop you off a plane you're going to have to detonate it will explode when it's a certain number of feet off the ground so presh
And as for finger on the button
The finger which belong to Harry Truman president of states
With 11 time zones removed
And frankly unaware of the app
Truman
He didn't issue an order himself he started
Approved
An order that was already being issued from the Secretary of War to the Commander's out there and it said
You have two of these special bombs
Special bombs
And here are your four targets you can drop them off
You could drop them on Hiroshima Nagasaki
Quora and you could drop them on niigata
Any day after August
Third eye drops
What
He said here's a
A couple of different options choose choose for some days
Go for it
No way. The only considerations are operational so the bombing order says you have
Have to be able to see the target before you draw
And that's it
One of the interesting thing is that I
I cannot later there was it a town called
Okura
And that was the
Plan B
Town
Far city rather for her Oshima
But the weather that they happened to be good in Russian
So they dropped it there
And then
The next time it was I was actually the plan a city
For Nagasaki but the weather was bad there
Incidentally the bomb Nagasaki
The city of Corrigan got speared twice like you
It was so close
And so true and doesn't even know
He he gets hold oh by the way we dropped
The bomb yesterday
Give me when the bomb dropped on Hiroshima he had no idea if he didn't know what day
The second bomb he seems to have been caught off guard
And he actually issues this is his only way of getting involved issues
An order with says
Stop dropping atomic bombs
Until I tell you to
I feel like if you're if you're a president and you're going to do that to that many people
I feel like you should be directly responsible should not be an arbitrary decision
Like I kind of want to but in this case no
No no no
You wouldn't actually want there to be a bug
You can bump up
Make a button to easy
Right you don't want to be easy enough that you set your coffee down on the Oval Office table and like
Kill the world right like obviously nobody wants to do that nobody wants tonight
I think it's you know I have to admit when you first
Bitching about
Where are they going to go
And the more I was thinking about
It's a deep concert right it's about the ease in which
You could actually
Destroy all of civilization
Because of the technology
What you could not do in the 19 century you could not do with Genghis Khan you could do a lot of damage
But he could not kill
You know
All the people in the
The button is the symbol of how easy that is and the reason this becomes kind of crew
I'm moving to the 50s into the 60s
Are vulnerable early 60s the United States is in a face-to-face with with over
Cuban missiles
Really really close to Annihilation that works at this time is it the president has an assistant
Who has all the nuclear codes
In a briefcase
Handcuffs
To the assistant
I'm your system if the president is in the bathroom the assistant is outside the door in the Carter if this present is at a ballgame
The suitcase is called the football and I believe the
Page with the nuclear launch codes on it is called the biscuit
Why
I have no idea where it got the name
So it's the sixties and things between the US and Soviet Union are very tense and there are generals on The Joint Chiefs Curtis
Bombs away Lemay all troubled by the possibility that this would be
They would use and they advocated very specifically in very specific case there are no buttons and there are
These code people are still worried at the time about just how easy it would be for the president to launch a nuke
Types of in one guy in particular guy Roger Fisher
Academic policy
He's a Harvard Law School Professor he advised secretary
Update on.
Iran hostage crisis on the israel-egypt peace Accord he he definitely had the ear of the
He
Trouble by this idea that
The president could
Prairie dispassionately
Start nuclear war
Italy proposes
I'll jump in the ocean comes from his long interest in reducing the risk of War
Roger Fisher passed away but we were able to talk to him
Amelia Fisher I'm a professor at Dartmouth and I'm Peter Fisher I'm a senior fellow at the tuck School of Business at Dartmouth
His
Solution to this by the way this would be just in the case of a
WS
Surprise attacks
Call the first strike
Was
2 instead of having all the codes be just a suitcase
This idea was together volunteer who have the codes
Put under their heart
You embed the codes
And some sort of caps you all in the guy's heart
Surgically any carry around a briefcase with a knife in it
Butcher knife
And if the president ever felt the urge
The fire off the missiles he has to go to the guy and say
Well now it's time
Give me the knife
And then you have to take the nightstand
Drive it into the guy's chest
The president has to
Chop out
Xcode from the sky
Parked where they don't have to kill someone and pull the code out of their body
Then he would have to first kill one person
In order to get at the codes that would let him kill millions of people
You have to look at someone and realize what death is
What an innocent death is
Blood on the White House
Carpet
It's reality brought home
Fisherman says that he suggested this to friends in the Pentagon and their reply was
My God
That's terrible having to kill someone to distort the president's judgment
He might never push the button
Big strongest objection is it might work
But even now I think you know
Gosh
Not a crazy idea at all to have the president be
If they're going to pull the trigger and blow the world
Kill one person
Cuz you're just about to kill tens of Millions
Mostly innocent people
And the button is just too easy
So what does make it harder
Buttons too easy
Yeah
The butcher knife
Is the ultimate anti button
But how you can find a guy to put
Codes inside his heart I would volunteer I would volunteer to be
Really what
I totally Miss 2nd of May
You would volunteer
To be
Stabbed in the Heart by the president of the United
And you know what I would do I would be best friends
The president we would take walks we would go swimming together fuel be great we would be best friends
I would I would that would be my mission would be to make it as hard as humanly possible for him to car
Okay we have some thank-yous to make here why don't you go ahead all right
First monkey to Catherine kilchevsky of the elevator Historical Society Museum in Long Island City New York
Elevator company and pride and service elevator company booked in Europe for helping us
Learn things
And your friend Steve will help us understand what goes on among autograph collectors very indulgent
New York public library archives and manuscripts Division and Alex wellerstein has a nuclear history block equals
Restricted data check that out house intern wanted us to
Thank John Coster Mullen Michael Gordon Eric Schlosser and
Spencer Ware
Special thanks to actor Michael chernus and Noah Robbins
And also let's not forget Damiana marchetti thought we would just go out
With the
Our final salute to buttons by the one
Mechanism Man created
That hates it
The music you are hearing was arranged by the composer Keith Harrison it is a
Zipper rag
The first being mortal enemies
On that note
Kiki weirdos
We should go I'm Jenna from run
And I'm left with nothing
Thanks for listening