Is Jesse this is an episode coming up that we originally had about 3 years ago
But the issues in here
Seem to be serviced in the air
Still
Part of it kind of an ongoing
NeverEnding National conversation touches on some cases before The Supreme Court
So
We certainly have been able to stop thinking about it so we thought we would share this with you again and at the very end of the hour
We have a little update
Super interesting
To hear this
Are you awake
Listening to Radiolab from WNYC
How can you hear me
Yeah okay good
So we're just doing this because
Because that article you wrote we hope you'd one of the most amazing things I've ever read
Okay I'm Jedi Cam'ron I'm Robert krulwich Radiolab and today
A story about
A decision
About a decision that we as human beings we've only recently begun to consider
There are stories like this elsewhere but somehow
Not too many
So we're going to devote the entire hour to just this one story which I think is a first pressing it is and the story comes to us from
Woman named Kelly Benham she's a reporter for the Tampa Bay Times in Florida
Maybe going to do this is chronologically just sort of
Across time
Where were you and who
What did you want to do
When I decide to have a baby with you one of those people who
Ever since you were young
You knew that you would be a mom
Yeah I did but I wasn't like I didn't play with a lot of dolls or babysit
I bet I always just kind of had this weird
Certainty that
I have a daughter
I'm a daughter not a son
Maybe son too but I don't know I think I was I would have a daughter and a sword had this image of her in my head
Image
Like really feisty mischievous
Dark hair
Dirty face
Okay we've left princess lanzhou not a princess at all
Weimaraner dog chaser
I really want to have a baby
I wanted one very badly but I just
Couldn't see how it made sense for me to be the father
That's Tom French also journalists at the Tampa Bay Times or he was a dime he and Kelly have been dating for a few years
Years but he was a good 10 years older than her
I had two kids
Suns
Approaching the end of college
And I was ready to travel I wanted to see you Spain and
Greeson the world going to err on the
On the cruise ship where you get to be the mail pokermaster whatever you need or I would have an issue with Springsteen
Bring me falling Springsteen around Europe
I've made up my mind
No more kids but she was insistent I stuck to it she saw our daughter very clearly oh yeah
Saw that I was destined to be that little girl's father
And was that at happy gentle disagreement or the other kind
I was brutal
He broke up and when we worked at the same place there's kind of invisible line and then
The Newsroom that neither of us would cross the mailboxes
It really was alive it was a horrible time we called the dark era the dark.
It was the worst Halloween section of Target
I am my son's and I have loved Halloween forever I love it when I was a little kid and
I just wanted to see what they have anything new cuz I had
You know I usually check out there gargoyles now There Staffing
So I just was kind of walking through the Section browsing and then something
Just stopped me in my tracks
Apparently was it was really like kind of a lightning bolt Epiphany just so wait a minute maybe you are
Thinking about the straight you're acting as though
You're 80
And then it hit me that
Nobody knows how much time they have
To have a child is to embrace a future that you can't control
Remember those words so I had to come to Jesus meeting with myself among the Gargoyles
And that was when I realized I need to just take a step back and try to restart the conversation with
You know I went home and wrote me this long letter and I just
I was over by that point on
I wasn't looking back
So you know over a few months with a little while
They patched things up eventually got married and started trying to make a baby
We thought that this would just happen right away
And then of course it didn't
You're trying and trying the regular way she took drugs that make you
Drop a bunch of eggs at one time after that the turkey baster method there's like kind of a process that they walk you through
After turkey baster IVF
Yeah
I never thought that it would get that far but it would go farther because after trying IVF three times
Stetson work so they said we can try with an egg donor meaning you get a friend's would be willing to donate the egg take the egg put it in the day
Dish forcibly impregnated with Tom sperm then you insert the egg into your kind of the Magic Bullet
Infertility
Kind of like
You don't know what's wrong with your car you just replace the whole engine
Kelly asked a good friend to be an egg donor they implanted the egg
Shortly after she took a pregnancy test
I said way too early it's at the line was super super faint
Wasn't even sure I could see it at all
So I took a photograph of the pregnancy test and I put it into Photoshop
And I actually had to dial up the contrast
To make the the line appear that is everything
This is so high-tech right
I was like oh my God I think there's two lines there
So I waited and I and I did it a second time
And then I
But I told Tom
Did you go into like the expectant parent mode and
Oh yeah
Touch up the paint
You know I patch the little holes in the wall everything was perfect everything
Was absolutely
Perfect
Until it wasn't
5 months into her pregnancy 20 weeks which is just about halfway cuz a full-term is 40 Kelly was at a park
Playing with her dog and I just felt a little bit
Weird
And
Just started to bleed
But not a lot
But
Any amount of blood is not a good thing and I called the doctor's office and they didn't seem too concerned they're like
Yeah you probably want to go to the hospital and get that checked and I went to pick her up and
By the time we got to the hospital she was in a lot of pain
Cramping cramping cramping I knew something was really really wrong they got me nowhere
What is wheelchairs they wheeled me into the surf triage room and by that point like blood was just
Coming out of me chunks of blood coming out of me and I didn't know I thought it was baby Parts like falling
And I thought I'm having a miscarriage like the baby's going to drop out on the floor
I was throwing up
And then the doctor came in and he looked scared
Does the doctor say something or what happens
The doctor
Explain to me quietly there was something it was making it difficult
To stop Kelly's bleeding
And if they couldn't stop it we might lose Kelly
And Kelly heard the doctor say this and I need to tell you Kelly is the toughest
Most Fearless person I've ever known
But she grabbed my arm
It's hard as anyone has ever grabbed my arm and I remember just
Don't let me down
Please don't let me die
It was terrifying and then
Sandpoint they
They brought in an ultrasound machine to see what was going on with the baby and I assume the baby was long dead I'm going to have her baby Parts on the floor
Or I didn't know
And they hooked up his machine and they were moving on and around and around and trying to pick up heartbeat in there was nothing
Adam
I was apologizing to Tom
I'm sorry like you know I just knew the baby was gone
Then all of a sudden
There was just this heartbeat
Recorded on her cell phone
Baby's heartbeat super super fast so it sounds like a rabbit or something
Yeah this heartbeat pops up and then there's the baby and you can see it and she looks fine she's too
Totally oblivious she says right there
Now I thought oh my God I'm going to watch her die
I'm going to watch you die in front of me Anna
Then they started just pumping me full of drugs to try to get this labor stop
There's this drug called magnesium sulfate in one of the effects of it is it just makes you
Can a boil from the inside
But eventually
They got the contraction stop they got the bleeding stopped they put me in the hospital room
And they said
Get to 24 weeks
Cuz that's that's the limit
So 4 more weeks
Yeah
Sounds like they got a line in the sand like you must get to 24 or there's no
Ny-24 what's special about them that number they told me that
24 weeks is kind of pill abuse
Definition of viability
That sort of grew out of
When they were
Fighting out
Roe v Wade
Example the Court ruled that a woman who commits an abortion on herself is guilty of no crime against
Stories I understand a robber
In Roe v Wade the Supreme Court was trying to strike this balance they wanted to protect a woman's right to choose as we
But they also want to say that there are limits to that right
If there is some moment in the development of the fetus in the course of this pregnant
We cross this line in
At least no longer just about to women's rights now you have to think about the state's interest in The Unborn Child
The problem of course is weird you draw that line
Not now that is the million-dollar question
Duke University
So that kind of bass
Gas at that point the best
Medical objective standard that the justices could come up with the 1973 was
Liability
And the word viable in this case means can it survive on its own
Outside of the woman's womb a fetus is developed enough that you can take it out of the mother's womb and it can still see
Survive
That liquid suggested is the point when it is no longer okay to have an abortion
Because across that line a fetus is
Quotes viable
Send the question was when does a fetus cross that line
When can it survive on its own
Well we begin but you got this in our brief with the development of the
Human
Embryo
Here's where you get to the 24-week thing what ended up happening was the court considered what was known about fetal development
And their trucks that show this
Feel like this 3 weeks a fetus has brain and heart begin to develop a tweaks nerve fibers 13 to 16 weeks the fetus begin
Removing them kick at 23 weeks some fetuses respond to familiar sounds like a mother's voice and at 24 weeks
Air sacs form in the lungs
And thinking was maybe that's the point
The minimum point
Where the fetus is viable straps breathe on its own butt
This was just a theoretical idea
No one was testing it no one was trying to take the fetus
Out of a mother at 24 weeks to see if it would survive
In fact
Throughout the 70s and 80s most hospitals according to Kelly
Drew the line of viability back a little bit farther
28 weeks
And that is because
Somewhere around the
28th week of gestation the lungs start to produce
Eye fluid called surfactant
Which prevents the lungs from collapsing and sticking together between breaths
That's a really important thing
Super a long time the actual viability line not the theoretical one
What's 28 weeks
But then
In the late seventies someone invented an artificial lung surfactant kind of a slippery white stuff that they shoot
Down the ventilator tube in the baby's born and that combined with
IV nutrition new super small ventilators moved the line of viability back
2 round where does now
Where does now is
Generally around 24 but here's the thing depending on what hospital you're in
In what doctor is on call sometimes it can be 23
Cases 22 so
Given modern technology
Imagine says need a one-day the line could jump way back
Will make things really
Tricky if for example we get to the point where modern signs able to develop an artificial womb
Does viability start at the points of a fertilized egg
The standard is
The point at which the developing child can actually survive outside of the womb using any psychological intervention
Apple that is a slippery line indeed
They said
Get to 24 weeks
Cuz that's the limit
Which made the doctors have to pump Kelly full of drugs
Keep her feet elevated for at least
Another 4 weeks
But I just
Kept going into labor
In and out of it and they felt like they couldn't hold it off anymore
And at 23 weeks and 4 days
A doctor tells her that
There's nothing more they can do the baby is going to come
A day
Maybe to a guy comes in
Adam
I hate he
He seems a little uncomfortable like this was not pleasant for him
He said you know your baby's probably coming in 24 to 48 hours and we know how hard
You work to have his baby and we know how much you want this baby and we assume that you want everything done
Does that mean we have no idea
So we said
We're not sure if we do when everything done paint the picture for us doctor
And he said
Now there's about a 53% chance that the baby will die no matter what we do
53 yeah
Whatever we do whatever we do
There was a small chance that she could be fine
What were those chances
About 20
I felt like like 20%
You know it
It's not a
It's not a possibility it seems like a like a reasonable
It seems like worth a gamble until you really think about what the 80% means I mean
He could be on a ventilator for the rest of her life
She have a massive
Bleed in her brain and it was like eat holes in her brain and
Affect her ability to think
Or talk or walk
She could
Pretty good chance she could be blind
Or death
And
There was no way for the doctors to predict
But the doctor said no is it when the baby came
The world
It would need a ton of medical
It may even need to be revived and so the question for the
Kelly was
Do they want the doctors to do that they want them to pursue every measure possible or
No
Just left
Nature take its course
And he said it would be we should decide
Before the baby came because once the baby came
We saw the baby it would be really hard to say no
So if if no was going to be the answer we need to just say that before the baby came
The worst night ever
You trying to make up your mind
About what
What's right
Like what we be torturing this baby
For nothing
We didn't want her to be born out of life that she would
Hate us for having
There have been instances where children with birth defects are genetic diseases
I filed wrongful life suits
Essentially claiming they should have never been born
We had to really debate what was
In her best interest
What would she want
I started to
Really struggle with
Whether I was being selfish whether I had already pushed too far
And this was like
God or the universe
Pushing back
Warehouse
Marriage might break up
We lose our ability to
Try again for another child I felt like
I might get a baby but I would lose everything else and
I think I got pretty close
Uno
All night as we're talking this through and
I'm trying to figure it out
We could hear
The baby's heartbeat to the monitor
Baby was letting us know all night right here I'm right here
Where you had to say yes
Are now out loud
I will ask for second opinion or
A second opinion but another console we had some more questions
And a nurse practitioner from the NICU came to the room yes my name is Diane lysel I'm a neonate
Little nurse practitioner this is the next day had asked
To speak to someone again and instead of just
Fighting numbers in statistics
I don't give numbers different for each baby she kind of started to paint a picture
This is what I've seen I've been doing this 30 years
But more importantly I also told them that
It wasn't
Oh yes or no decision
She said you know you don't have to decide right now
They could have the baby
Baby came out crying
An active then we should do everything we can for the baby
But the baby came out blue and length intraventricular hemorrhage
We could stop
We didn't have to keep
Going
Something goes horribly wrong we can withdraw the support and then you can hold her baby until it dies
But you can give your baby a chance and see how it goes
In other words
In a very real way
They could give this decision
To the baby
That same night
I was feeling like I'm just uncomfortable
Couple hours later discomfort turns the pain finally a doctor came in and was like
Yeah your labor we have to go right now so that it was like super super quick or
Light shot in spine cutting me open and then
Oh my God there's a third
Person in this room
But not really not quite almost I mean
Trousseau
So early
What did she look like
Why didn't see her
Then
I just saw like her kind of Wiz buy an incubator
And she just doing a little dark smear
And a hat
And in did you make it to 24 weeks
Swimmer one day shift
23 weeks
And 6 days
Will be back in just a moment hi this is Kelly Friend
OK Google
Radiolab supported
I'm parked by the National Science Foundation
Science and technology in the modern world more information about Sloan
Sound at www.slha.org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help this summer I'm hosting a show and I've request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
About what we're calling tiny moments of Brilliance basically I want to hear about this
So did something
It just means you bring back and say whoa how did they do that maybe it was the moment that I can
Kids you've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you or maybe the kid was a piano lessons and you
Suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the musical score or maybe the math class
Reading music in the margin of their geometry homework
Does something super smart but it doesn't have anything to do with the test if you have a story with us
Go to radiolab.org Brilliance and record a short audio message for us again that's
Radiolab.org / Brilliance thank you so much
Hey I'm Jared I'm Ron I'm Robert krulwich Radiolab today we're spending the entire hour on a single story
We saw in the Tampa Bay Times Kelley Benham a journalist published an unbelievably
Wonderful set of articles
About her and her husband Tom French was also a journalist
They had a baby
Except their baby came very
Very early so full term as we mention is 40 weeks their daughter arrived
23 weeks and 6 days would be just a little bit over halfway
No just to put that in context
If a baby is born before 22 weeks it's generally considered a miscarriage
Pretty much no doctor is going to interview
If a baby is born after 25 weeks
They've been all kinds of studies which show that doctors then feel morally obliged to save that life no matter what the parents
Say so before 22
And after 25
Things are pretty clear but between 22 and 25
Dillon danis
Gray Zone
This strange little liminal space between life and death
We have to answer some really tough
Like
Should my baby live
At what cost
Who gets to decide and ultimately Windows life
Begin
Kelly and Tom like many parents who land in this Zone decided for the hardest question to the baby
The baby will tell them whether it's going to stay or whether it's going to go
So they delivered by C-section and their daughter
Sweet that boy didn't have a name was whisked off to the
Neonatal intensive care unit for the NICU
Eventually they went to see her
And they need to beat her
For the first time
And she was
Like
Like weirdly perfect
She had all the parts
Lisa
Long fingers
Long feet
Delicate little nose and she had hair and fingernails and
Eyebrows and you all the things that they're supposed to have
But she was
Translucent
You could just see right through you can see all the veins running on her skin you could see her heart
Thumping in her chest
And her eyes were sealed shut
Like a puppy
And I'm
She was
Bike Meetup
She had bruises all over her body and she had a black eye
Just from the you know they were very
Careful with them when they're born but
Just that very delicate handling
Kind of batteries these babies because they're so fragile
I mean it was
We are lucky to know how it's supposed to feel
I mean you want to
Believe that
The minute you meet your daughter there's going to be like
Butterflies Sido or like unicorns
Supposed to be the best moment your life
But they were so much Terror
Inside that moment
I was terrified because
I love being a father my relationship with my son is
Extremely bored
And I was really terrified that she would be so alien
Haven't been born at 23 weeks
6 days
That I wouldn't
Recognize her as
My daughter
And I wouldn't bond with her that I was now. Thought was
Filled with the real dread
Andam
I wanted to see her
I could see that
She was
Only
Have finished
Barely a pound that point
So training my brain couldn't even process
House martial arts
And
The nurse Quinn
You can touch her you know
Stunt I didn't think I would be able to and so she had me
Washington Starlight my hands once Shamy do it again
She showed me how to reach in through this little round portal
I think you better
And explain how to touch her you don't rub the skin because the skin will come off if you do that when they're born that early
You just press gently
And so
The baby was lying there not with her fist but with her arms extended
The Palms open
So her right palm was right there when I reach my left hand and I just
Put my
My left
Gently into her palm and she just
Wrapping tight and in that
Moment
All my fears about not being able to bond with her washed away
Panda
Oh yeah what what got to me was
How
I could be so afraid
When she was so strong
At that point to
She was the most beef
And I told her
Hippie
Daddy
When a baby is this early
Parents and the doctors
Are watching very carefully trying to guess is this baby ready to be out in the world
Is it going to make it
Tom says when she grabbed his finger
That wasn't just been bonding he felt
Like she was saying something
She made her will very very clear to live
And that was a phrase We heard again and again some babies will
Can use a Tempe plasma cells over the first few hours and days of their life
That's a neonatologist we spoke to Keith Berrington get a gut feeling
I'm at Stanley's Allegan the nurse practitioner
After meeting the baby that
This one looks very fragile
Or
This one can do it
Babies declared itself
What does that mean
What are you seeing
When something that premature declares itself
And here we ran into a real difference parents will often see will in a credible
Will and resolve doctors and nurses
Nothing much
That sounds a bit too mystical for me I wouldn't take it
As there's a
Voice inside the baby saying I'm going to be a fighter I'm not
One is sick enough not to be able to fight and one isn't
Can you see a spirit in a in a kid
Can I think you can see if some fight I call it's Punk a lot of times
That is Tracy Howlett registered nurse
She was Kelly and Tom's primary nurse at All Children's Hospital and like everyone we spoke to on the hospital side when it comes to this issue
She chooses her words very carefully
Maybe try to keep things a little bit more neutral than talking about their will to live
Easy no baby at 23 weeks barely has folds on the outside of its brain it's Brandon. Smooth
Pinellas Park
So who knows what it's capable of thinking or feeling well that's a difficult question in the truth is
Things like fights Punk may just boil down to physiology maybe that baby had a few more lung buds to start
Start with an easier time in utero may have nothing to do with Will in fact that they be grasping the finger
Eva Peron
It's actually a reflex
The babies have a grasp reflex I never tell a parent that because they think it's an intentional
Movement because you're putting yourself in the parents had it if you've got to decide how much my going to put how much of my heart
I'm going to pour into this little creature
If you can see something like will or something like intention if you see oh that's a person in there
Maybe you don't see it
Maybe it's the only way you got to make this decision
Is my wife the professional messages often says
We don't make
Important decisions in our life the rational reasons very often
Keith and his wife any janvier have done a huge amount of research into the ethics of extremely premature birth
But one of the primary reasons we going to talk to him
Is that
Addition to being a neonatologist and a guy who publishes a lot of stuff in this area
He and his wife recently had a baby girl
Who is born at 24 weeks and 5 days
Shwetha 720g
One and a half pounds
She's actually in my own and I see you
Oh wow
I was I see the director of the unit where she was
So he was in his unit in the place where he usually work
He saw babies make it
Not make it and now suddenly he was
Apparent in that place
And several weeks after his baby was born
There is a very very big complication xian she didn't move
I told for about 36 hours
How many thought maybe it was a little lamb
Maybe it's time
So they decided he and his wife
To Let Her Go
Peacefully
But
I went back into the NICU to see you
And something happened he look down
Any saw
Her lips move
Barely started sucking on the shoes of the nested put in their mouth
She was sucking on a pacifier
I was just a reflex
The most basic baby reflexes sucking reflex
He knew that
But
Just that movement to sucking on the zoo the
Changed his mind completely when I went back to Annie and said them be constipated really need to
Continuing and give her the chance
Too but you knew that
Suck the sucking response is not that's a fairly
Deep-brain yes is a very basic is just the brain stem is not snowing and you need a lot more than be able to suck
Look to It To Em to do well
As I was trying to be the parent there not many Nate elegist
What can you remember if the doctor and you was surprised that the father in you
Yeah I think I was actually a little
Yeah I think if I do
Ben Moore
Evidence-based and rational and scientific, I thought I could have
Gone either way
But just as a father I couldn't do that Point Mexico
I just didn't really know how to process it
I felt like
She was
I just had this very acute sense that she had just been like a violently ripped out of my body
I could just feel where they cut her out
You know
And
Like I just wanted to put her back
Pitmaker safe
Yeah yeah
And I and how these questions going through my head like
How long does she have to live for us to get a birth certificate
It has to be real
Like I felt like she might die and
And like it wouldn't count
And I wouldn't be a mother
You don't even
Like what if she died like what would have happened
Like when we have a funeral
They make caskets a size of shoe boxes
I'm always like
So
Screwed up the
That's the stuff you think about but your brain goes
Places you just can't control or predict
And if she
I wondered like
If she knew
She really aware that I was even standing there like
Which is a reflex that made her got my finger
When she grabbed it and she know
Did you know I was there and she didn't know I was there. She wonder where I've gone
Did she feel alone and is she scared
All she could really do at that point
Sit with us
And it just became this waiting game
Will continue in a moment
Hey I'm Jared I'm Robert krulwich this is Radiolab and we are spending the whole hour
With Tampa Bay Times Reporter at Kelley Benham and her husband Tom French
A story that they're telling us
Tibet this limbo
A a space that's that's literally between life and death
We have to tackle some really big questions yeah
Well there's anyone I dump when did you decide to name your daughter Juniper
About
About five days after she was born
Now in those 5 days pretty much everything in their lives changed
The most superficial level they began their Hospital stay Day Zero
In the maternity ward
Can butterflies on the walls and images of roses opening
Adam
Everyone's really good looking like in an ER sort away or are they going to Grey's Anatomy kind of way we had
Like one superhot we call her cupcake
And she had this like glossy hair and you know people would visit me and they be like hey is cupcake here
What is cupcake coming by
And so that's where their Hospital Journey began the 5 days later
Everything Has Changed they find themselves on a different
Florida Hospital
Stranded in this unit
It is perhaps more than any other place on Earth the physical embodiment of this limbo the neonatal intensive
Square unit the NICU
Where they just have to wait
And hope that that will or whatever it was they saw on Juniper
Takes hold
We have been like
Yanked out of our lives
And out of everything that we recognized
LIRR jobs at her house
And we just been
Got to do this
Science fiction
Nothing was recognizable
Babysitting look like babies you know
There's one baby that had his intestines being outside of his body
Piled up on his belly like in this bag
Everyone's wearing uniform don't know who anyone is
And everything's like be big humming and
I don't know how you're going to be there and you don't have any sense of time
Like day and night don't mean anything
Yeah we're sort of dimly aware of the Sun
Rising and setting out the window
Other than that
It's just
Just like
Minute to minute hour to hour
You're afraid to leave even for
You for an hour to get some lunch because the baby could die
You know if we went home to get some sleep when she
Wichita is that critical and
She had roughly
Five six days that went pretty well
And then that next weekend
Blue horn Destin's beginning of a lot of problems
And her belly turned dark and got real distended inserting drains in the belly
To try to drain away stool and donk
And she just had this little straw sticking out of her belly and then they couldn't maintain your blood pressure
So I was thinking of everything I could do cuz you don't want to feel powerless in a situation like that you want to feel like there's something Uke
Can do
So in Quiet Moments what time we do chapter 1
The boy who left
Is he would stand over Juniper's incubator
And you would read her Harry Potter mr. and mrs. dursley of number four privet Drive
We're proud to say that they were perfectly normal
Thank you very much they were the last people you'd expect
To be involved in anything strange or mysterious
As I start reading to her
And as the days went on
She has no idea what I'm reading right but there is something there that
She responded to I want to say she like because her her sat number would go High. Point
Pursat number what is it like for oxygen saturation of oxygen are blood
Temp says that number on the monitor was one of the only ways they can get feedback but how she's doing
Because your eyes are still closed there be times when she wasn't moving around alot
The higher the number the better
He says when he would read to her
Remembers would go up not just slowly but in stomach
But then
When I got deeper into the story
I read in Hagrid's voice biotic Professor Dumbledore sir
Set the Giant
Climbing carefully off the motorcycle as he spoke
And
She decided instantly
It is larger just going off and going off a cliff and Kelly hit me and she said you're scaring the baby
And I'm like what what
You could see
Even before Horizon
But she was really responding to what we were doing
She didn't know what chapter is but she was in her own way
Very eagerly waiting for the next job
And I don't know a better way to describe one to be a lie
Then you want to find out what happens next
Unfortunately what happens next is that one night around 2 in the morning
A rear night that they actually went to sleep at home
They got a call from their doctor
His first question was how far do you live from the hospital
Daniel that's not a question you want to hear from your child
We'd like Rush Hospital
When they get there they were told that she did again she got another hole
Another holder Destin's and she started to really spiral
I really go downhill her blood pressure and oxygen levels were crashing she was on 100%
Oxygen the ventilator settings are turnips high as they can go and she was still struggling and faltering and you know once they are giving her baby
100% oxygen they can't give her anymore at that point that done everything that I could possibly two
This is Bowser Shaquille Hospital
Everything she could think of blood pressure medicine antibiotics she put a drain in her abdomen that obviously was not enough
What's wrong baby wrong we might lose her.
The only option left to take her to the operating room with car open clear the intestines
Relieve the pressure
How do you do a surgery on a 1-pound baby it seems exactly
I mean you don't either so extremely premature
So fragile
So tiny that operating
Same kind of crazy
Dr. Shakil began to really consider the idea that
Maybe this was it
Headed that point
I was in bed side
Looking at her
Trying to figure out what to do
And
All of a sudden
Cuban rice
Really yeah she opened her eyes
Why didn't she looked at us
Rise were like wide open and she was looking right at the doctor directly
Exterior hard
And it was very proud of the moment
Dr. shakeel says she decided right then and there
Surgery
I think she deserves a chance
Tell me more about why you made a decision typically babies who are that
Critical
Identity and responsive because they're just fighting for every breath and Divinity 2
Just
Open her eyes at that stage in our life when she had no blood pressure that I could barely record when she
He had hardly any Oxygen
For her to just open your eyes and look at us
Was a very powerful statement that I'm still here
I'm here
I am still here don't give up
Dr Shakil summon the Pediatric surgeon told her
They want to move forward with the operation
Surgeon said no
The surgeon was adamant that she did not want to do it he said it's it's if it's futile and it's
Is she her blood pressure is so unstable that she would not make it out of the or
Insurgent Elder even if I can open her up and do the job your skin is so papery that I might not be able to
So we're back up there are guidelines that
Medical Industries have you been
Basic things like the Hippocratic oath to do no harm that's law professor an ethicist Nita farahany again
Many Physicians
Legitimately believe that if you have a preterm infants and that infant is
In serious Peril of spending a life of
Suffering and pain the only way to do know how I meant to feel your road
He's not to do the surgery
But she says if you ask the court show right now the law favors
Life
The courts have seen very few cases that involve disputes like this but in everyone's so far she says
They've supported the person who's arguing to keep the Child Alive
It whenever there's life There's Hope
So
This is our windows we should do it now
Productor Shaquille the argument that ultimately won the day
Basically what I told her was that if you think she's going to die
Well she is dying right now
As we speak in the unit
So we can either do nothing and she definitely dies or we can do something and she probably dies but
You never know there is a slim chance
So there we landed incubator with the baby in it
And hold their little hand and she's getting ready to go into surgery and she was looking right at me
And
She hadn't done that before
It really seemed like she was aware that I was there
Very clearly and she was a lock on my face
So I can lie down try to give her a little kiss on her forehead
Adopted the same thing and then they wheeled her way
How long is the operation
It was
We think they call a page does much more quickly than we expected to come back so we knew
Something was wrong
The nurse assured Tom and Kelly into a separate room this little windowless
Conference room
And the surgeon came in and
She said you know I
She's supposed to go in and
Clean everything out and runs everything off and find the hole and Patch it in and do all these things
And she said when she cut the baby open
And touched the baby's intestines with her little probe
She's the way she described it was everything fell apart
It was just falling apart falling apart
And you're hearing this
Yeah
Jennifer had survived the operation
But barely
So we're thinking like okay this was an incredibly risky surgery
And we just threw it for nothing
Anna
Either I thought there was no way that they was going to live till morning
I've been really working hard to avoid
Thinking about all the bad things that were
That's waiting to happen here
Just trying to hold on you know and let certified with my job to do that
And dumb
Stereotypical email with me and
And Tom says they were in the car
Around the time of the surgery
We're driving
Bedtime
June bug and I were
About two-thirds of the way to the first book
And the thought just snuck in on me which was
What if I don't
Get to finish reading her
Facebook
What if she doesn't get here then
She never finds out you know
What happens to Harry
Hermione and Ron
That thought
Letting the other
Very difficult thoughts about all the things we wouldn't get to do it
She would never get to know
And I had this terrible thought that you know she was in this incubator the sisal add plastic box and I
Had this terrible thought that she was just going to go from one box to another
I had to pull over
I just lost it and
At that point I wasn't maintaining there was no holding back this flood of
We had a rule Kelly languages that only one of us got to lose it at a time
That was my turn to loosen
We're in a very unnatural situation of neonatal intensive care which is so
Recent in the developed world and still doesn't exist too much of the world
And
Working so hard to save babies is very new
Neonatologists
Keith Arrington and evolutionary history newborn babies very frequently died
And most parents who have any significant number of children
Head West one or two or three or more
And in order to be able to carry on with your life and to provide for the rest of your family
We have to be able to adapt to the death of a Pious and now that has become much less common to lose a baby
Miscarriages and stillbirths so now we realizing
How much that hurts in the past maybe we've hit and some of them for myself
No way the day was Callisto morning
But what happened was
Really strange
She continued to just
Not die
And the next day she
You know she was still there
The surgeon was surprised and
No one could quite explain it the more I thought about it the more I found it
I like surprising an interesting
You know because she doesn't know
If there's a better place
You know but she's just in this box
And she's got needles coming out of
Every Witch Way and
Tube down her throat
She has no idea that
One day you know she'll just be
Held
Rockton
I'll take her out for ice cream and
So play with the dog
And I just wonder like what is she fighting for
So that became you know our job
The best that we can articulate it was to try to give her some sense of something Beyond
On that place after the surgery things did not get
She would stop breathing many times a day
Teams with Russian to come back come back
I just remember the room spinning and then she started to swell her like weeks and weeks
But you continue to not die but you began to gain weight
And you know nurses are very superstitious lot of them
They won't say the word home for some reason when the babies hear that word to Tracy Hall it again primary nurse
They get sick and we just
It's a Superstition obviously but
Something happens
And sometimes it can be
Devastating
So what do you say instead
Riverside that place that the baby's going to go when they leave here
Sometimes we spell it which makes no sense at all
After about
4 and a half months
Diana nurse practitioner
Told us that we might want to think about buying a car seat
That was
First
Inclination
That we might
We'll take her out of there that's the first time I've ever imagined a choir of angels singing around mention of
Car seat car seats right but when you're at when you want to have a baby really bad everybody else has a baby but you and you can't have a baby
Baby things like shopping for car seats become like fantasies you know
And finally you know the doctor gave the
All clear and
We took the monitors off of her
And she was completely free
An untethered AutoAnything
Hawaii straps are in his car seat and I put a little pair of sunglasses on her
Cuz I didn't know of her
I should be okay in the sunlight
She never seen the Sun
I we all kind of
Walked out and
Tracy's really not a hugger but
We like
Grabbed her and hugged her and cried and
Oliver hazard
Luke baby the Karan
It was Chick-fil-A
That was totally before the gay thing before I stopped going to Chick-fil-A
And all in all how long were you in the hospital for
6 and a half months
196 days
How is gyro pronounced
What it what is
Videos of snapshot of her morning
Sure actually time in California
Nice enough to allow it to send a reporter to their house
To meet her
She's 2 years old now
Good morning Jennifer
When we got there she was still she was
Doing better was just waking up
Snappy
But then she just sprung up jumped out of bed and took off
Daddy funny
Come on show me where Katie is
I know you want to give a kitty a hug Jeezy don't
Nice hug
She's kind of your typical two-year-old
Gentle and because we were there Juniper
Kind of important
See some chicks she's learned
Who sell results radio so they have no idea what you just did
You spend a lot of time chronicling
Sometimes very terrible things and
What's interesting is that
Yesterday morning
Journalistic standards
You know we need to do is change a diaper
It was it was it was wouldn't even be on journalistic radar
But what you know as a parent
Especially after you've been through what we went through was
Everything and nothing you can do about it
Everything happened yesterday and now it's not a couple hours the entire world was contain
Inside of her
All the blank chapters of her life were inside that morning
Which what you want this book
End
Do you feel like you're out of the woods
Well
Both Tom and Kelly said
No way
And then Thom Tillis about these flu shots
Jennifer gadd
They're not just flu shots they're like gum
Flu shots
Like super flu shots and they
The sports shots you yet
And I swear to God they cost $14,000 for this Porsche
And
That is that the real number if you just said that's a fact
They are designed to help protect her from
RSV
Which is a virus that in most people just presentas a common cold
But I'm sure her lungs are still recovering and are still developing end
RSV can be devastating
And there's some other concerns it
Concealed Creepin down the road
Some Studies have shown that the kids were born prematurely
Struggle more in school with reading and math
That's
Often they're more susceptible to
Depression and anxiety but I will say that
We took her to visit a preschool the other day
We took her there and set her down and she just took off and like
Went up to the
Giant children
And started taking their toys and
They were singing The Wheels On The Bus you could see it in her eyes I know that song
And she didn't care about Tom Rye one bit
You know she was totally there with those kids and she was
So ready
And I thought
Wow
She might be okay
She is okay
And now for an update
Originally aired this story in 2013 when Juniper was to
You stay from just a few months ago
How old are you
40 my gosh
You're about to turn 5 in April
What's going to happen when you turn 5
Canopy
When I don't either going to be this time
Juniper is about to start kindergarten and
Her and Tom and Kelly live
In Indiana knauertown Kelly teach journalism at the Indiana University Media School actually happen to be in Indy
Just yesterday so I hooked up with Tom and Kelly we stood on the side of a busy Street in downtown Bloomington
And they gave me an update they told me that in the nearly three years since we are this story this is generally not what you would expect
Text my baby born that early
Physically
We have had
Shockingly few problems like she she hasn't had any I got a knock on some wood somewhere
A horrible bout of the flu or it was never back in the hospital
These are a little bit small and they're watching that but there's a staff
Savagery to her true that is amazing so extremely
Headstrong
Active Child really in the climbing trees
How do you get up there
Declined
But you're so high up
Ghost horseback riding she does gymnastics have some awareness of The Incredible Journey
She went through just to be for 1/2 you guys talk about it later we talk about it because every night
She asked
Tell me the story about when I was a little tiny baby in the hospital
But is it
Tell me about when I was sick tell me about what I had to hold in my tummy
So
You know for a long time I would just tell her the story when you're born you're born
Very early
A lot more early than you were supposed to be born
Super extra small
I called
The hospital
Over the summer and I said hey like every night we're talking about this can I show her the NICU like would you let me
Just show her the space and what an incubator looks like and they were amazing about it and so
Have an incubator in an empty room and they let her come in and just play in the room and
Took her little doll baby that I
Ordered for her on preemie doll baby, whatever that's like this size and weight that she was when she was a baby
Is that a real thing
So she could get an idea of how small she was I don't know if that'll be useful someday
So she took it to the NICU and she put it in the incubator and we showed her how we would reach our hands through the little
Portholes
And hold her hand and she reached in and held her little babies little cloth and then because she's due to veranda
Where she would do this she climbed into the freaking incubator and laid down
And ask Tracy the nurse to close the lid
Yeah
Like she was I like that like that like that like
And she said at one point during the visit this woman walked by the room
She had that look about her like
She's a couple days
Postpartum
I thought oh God you know
Tracy kind of whisper in her ear Tracy the nurse and
She looked at dinner and she said
Oh my God she's so beautiful
And then she told us that she just had a baby a few days before that was born at 20
3 weeks and 6 days
Hippity hop hippity hop
Hey baby hey hippity hop
Nap speaking of that specific chocolate I'm 23 weeks 6 days we ended up checking back in with Annie different
Funny professor of lawn phosphate Duke University about that whole viability question like that line of wind
Preterm infant comes viable which at the time we did the stories seem to be roughly around 24 weeks
Peaks on average has that changed at all
It's pointless to study that was in a 2015 we should serve a big survey
Of outcomes
For preterm infants and it basically argued that
We might want to push that line back even further study author believes the 22 weeks is the new standard for viability
Reborns that's 23 weeks and my 3 weeks and 6 days if that's too late
She says this is now the new conversation
22 weeks
24 you know this is something that's
Physicians and hospitals are being educated about and look at where he at 22 weeks
You know in and it has been what two years since we last talked about this three years at most
I mean so in three years if we've moved back two weeks
Then talk to me in another quarter of a century and will be at the beginning
I think it's just a matter of time before we get to that artificial womb a case blessing I'll say by way of updates is it
Tom and Kelly
Are about to release a book about their experience call Juniper
Normally I'm not one to gossip but this book is something else like
We got into the story because of some
Wheely hunting articles that Kelly has written
For the Tampa Bay Times in this book takes his article so much for either goes into way more detail than we could ever get into
It is
Yeah it's totally worth reading
If you want to pre-order it there is a link on our website
Go to radiolab.org
Radiolab is produced by Jad appenrod really loud
Baghdad on map
Perfect
Soren wheeler is senior editor
Dylan Keith
Dairy Queen
Is director of sound design
Challenger
Dylan Keith
Really loud though
Is director
Andre Berto
Founded
Jamie your Casino producer. Includes
Simon Adler David double
Alexandra Lee
Stephanie Tam
Fact Checkers are Eva Dasher
Add Michelle Harris
Special thanks to Lynn Paltrow Jennifer jonkers John lantis
And Pat Walters
I got you