Are you awake
Northern listening to Radiolab
Radiolab
From WNYC
And NPR
Is Radiolab a I'm Jedi from rod iron Robert krulwich I'm Soren wheeler
And this
Do you want to say that okay
And I didn't hear anyone can I hear anyone oh my God
She's a
Old friend of mine went to school together long time ago but these days she's an editor at New Scientist
In London because of
What happened to her when she was working on
Story for them this was a story that I've been chasing for years and years for her in 2007
At DARPA Tech
Which is a big Gathering of like weapons developers and researchers it's like 5000
It's from The Matrix you know looking at the
The latest war toys drones Bazookas anyway at some point she starts talking to this woman and she was telling me about
Her program which was that they had figured out how to apply for electrical current
To the brain in order to
Accelerate the learning process
I was like no sweat Sally it stumbled into a something called PDC
DS games for transcranial Direct
Current stimulation
Daddy is
You take a couple little
Electrodes are placed on your scalp connected with wires to a battery you send a little bit of electricity into your brain and
Then
All kinds of things happen
If you believe the claims
But
Porcelli started with a casual afternoon of
Sniper training
So after that
Conversation with a conference she tracked down a group in Carlsbad California
About an hour and a half south of La using this brain zapping stuff to train snipers
And I actually got new scientist agreed send me to LA from London which is not an insignificant
Expense after a late night international flight in some LA traffic
Stuff at a place called Advanced Brain Monitoring
Where they have
Little room little room where they set up a little sort of
360 degree training simulation to kind of like a video game
But it's like the full
Kind of like the full room in front of you
And so wall is a screen
Yes. She says but all around you in this room are these
Props your behind real sandbags
You know in proper position they teach you how to hold the rifle properly and rifled except for the fact that it shoots blanks is basically the
Real deal yeah and then Scott a laser
Laser sight they told you know
Okay before we do this brain stimulation thing we're actually going to have you
You do some training without it so they
Get her all set up they put her behind the sandbags and they hit cup
It starts out with really easy stuff like you're shooting virtual Target that aren't
Kickback from the CO2 cartridge and then you get this like sound from when you hit you know the virtual metal Target and then it starts getting hot
Carter so there's people instead of targets and and more and more people until the highest level is you are at at
Point Rocky checkpoint and everything's fine and then all sudden
Humvee in front of you blows up and then from all over the place up dozens of people in suicide
Start running at you with air rifle shooting you and I'm just
Being blown
Stop I can't
I can't make the decisions fast enough or just too many of them she couldn't figure out who to shoot first it was so
I'm so tired and I'm so jet-lagged and I was so bad at it and it's funny because you think like or whatever
What's the video game
It's amazing how
Stress ball that gets in a certain point
Stress
Started getting
Stop let's just end this start thinking like
How am I doing here anyway like oh my God this is going to be a story and really you just flew out to California for the
She was not very good at in that kind of stressed her out and then this guy walked in the room
Yes likewise
Mike weisend neuroscience
It looks like Gregg Allman
Super long hair and fairly clean cut at the moment but I had hair down to my belt buckle
Mike weisend has put together this
Contraption what is the big boxes sitting in your lap
There's a big red
Tool box that we got literally from Sears Mike was actually passing through New York city so we invited him into the studio
We have electrodes
That allows to deliver current you legit wires a song and a whole bunch of batter
So we take
A set of electrodes one electrode is attached
2 mi
Right
Temple
And the other electrode is attached by different wire to my
Left
Darned we turn on the juice
Did it hurt it wasn't so much that I suddenly tasted metal in my mouth tasted tasted like I'd like to
The inside of an aluminum can and then he's like
I'm not exactly expecting different results
Today's date
Start me out again right at the really hard checkpoint 1 the thing blows up
And then people start coming from all over the place
And I feel like they must have put it on an easy setting
Everything is just a little more straightforward it's more obvious who I should pick off first
And I'm thinking to myself a little bit like
You know when it's going to get really hard again
And then
You know intern or whoever comes in and turns on the lights
She's like okay you're done Michael wait
That's not that's not
I've only been here for like 3 minutes
That was 20 minutes
Like no that's not true and I look up in the clocks of all shifted by 20 minutes
And I swear to God it was 3 minutes almost every person that would put this on so they get into what they call us
State of
Hello
Where they don't recognize of the time is going by there just boom boom boom boom
And I was like did you guys make it easier Stellino same
Same level
I think you guys made it easier when Sally did it with
Brain stimulation
She performed at 100%
100%
I didn't leave anyone alive
How what was she before
I don't know but she wasn't very good at roughly 3 out of 20 of the first time in
20th 20th
Yeah
So you're saying with just a little electricity she went from being like totally an app to
Train killer
Mountain end of one so we can't go too far but I mean this was just Sally's experience during this one.
Sound like a controlled study
But Mike has now use this device in a bunch of studies
Military had one city with people looking at those black and white
Radar in
Trying to pick out you know
What's an enemy vehicle and what isn't and if he puts this device on their head while they're trying to learn how to
To do that we can double the rate of learning
Really
Wow what is it doing
Okay so what I think is that early on when you are learning Something Mike says that when you're trying to learn how to do something is kind of
What's happening is that your
Trying a bunch of different things
You try all kinds of different ways to solve the problem
And
He usually your brain is stumbling across
Ideal
Sequence of neurons every so often as you're practicing all sent your brain is like
Okay that's it
But then it struggles to find that again it keeps messing up and whatever and if you look at an expert brain you actually see
See that preferred circuit dialed in
Like they just do that over and over and over again no more stumbling around until what mic does he figured out
Where that circuit is and he gives it a little extra
Juice to an innocent
Prime the pump
So that that expert circuit
Is more likely to fire
And you're more likely to stumble into it and when you do stumble into it you're more likely to stick with it that's right
That's how
We think it works
Where are you are you sure what you're hitting I mean like you're putting electricity on the outs
Side of
People's heads
Are you able to Target
Just a small cluster of brain cells or
Is it a region that you're hitting or like
Thousand cell phone number
That's out that's a lot
Is that precise enough
To Target
The place where a task is being done in a brain If it's a million
An artwork yes
Am I claims that even though it's a blunt tool this is not a scalpel this is a sledgehammer
If you know the right
Group of neurons are region of the brain to Target
This can work with almost any task
If you want to Target
Visual-spatial learning for example searching an image
You put this on the right
Decide
Of your head roughly near the temple
But if you wanted to learn text you on material you can put this on the left
Side of your head and it will have a similar effect
Do you want to learn text from here Beach
If I'm if I want to learn irregular verbs in French
I keep getting your things I stick another part of my hair but as good of a grammar we haven't tested it with learning for inline
Languages for native English speakers learning a long English Center
They can recall it with greater fidelity
If they have this on their head while they
Study listen
And if you go right parietal
Back over
Just behind your ear and up above your ear
You can learn math better
We are all kind of like
I don't know
But since my cat has a vice there with him should we try it
Sure I'm ready.
I mean Robert actually pretended he had an appointment I left
Viniq
Take me to the team here
I don't do fear
Yeah you should be
Stick around because we're going to put electricity right into the man's hat I'm talking about
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
About what we're calling
Brilliance
Basically I want to hear about those times when I did something
It just means you lean back and say whoa how did they do that
Maybe it was the moment that our kids you've been reading to 4 month started reading back
To you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lesson
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of their musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed are ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the specific moments where a kid does something super smart
Have anything to do with it
If you have a story
T-shirt with us
Go to radiolab.org
Brilliance
Record short audio message for us
Again that's radiolab.org / brilliance
Thank you so much
Alright so you've got here in front of me you have two little circles
Electrostatic
Red wires and
Black wax I get two of these on my head
One on your
Upper arm one of my
For the demo
Mike showed me a bunch of stereo
Alright so what am I doing here I'm looking at a bunch of
Marbles annoying
Where are you staring at this 2D picture of like
Repeating pattern the marbles
Or something
You supposed to unfocus your eyes and just the right way so that
3D picture
What's a mountain merge from background
Yeah
Take me my eyes go bad
So the idea that stem I was like let's see if I can train my eyes to
Figure out how to
Cool 3D pictures
Is it
I've never
I get headaches when I go to 3D movies and it took me like 10 minutes
To get one
As a butterfly there you
Stussy like just
Look at that
Alright so now you can choose me
Alright I'm going to turn it on
Okay
Yeah okay there it is
Weather feel like feels like a bunch of mosquitoes are biting me in my temple
It's love
And I could taste it now too
The people get that
Alright so now I'm going to I'm going to look at the stereoscopic images one more time here we are we've got a green and pink whoa
That just became the world
That
Suddenly a 3D globe
Pops out of the back row
Okay
Next one
Alright so now I'm looking at a big green grass
Blades of grass repeating repeating repeating
Pepsi
Swan
Swans origami swans
3D swans
Now I'm looking at a good set of a Trippy Paisley background and Sandy
3D Bambi
Next one
Right now we have flower background to the yellow and pink flower Thailand background whoa
Foxes foxes floating in space next
Whoa
A little ballerina doing a handstand on the balance beam
Will Hershey's Kisses popping right now it's coming out really fast big pretzel
Coiled snake
Wow
That's what it feels
Okay
I definitely felt like I could you couldn't give them to me fast enough
I feel very
Very awake
Okay so in the end I ended up being something
50 stereogram
They're really short
So I didn't think something was going on by
Adriana Cimino
Skeptical
You skeptical even when you were
Flying free
I don't entirely trust experience I had cuz it could simply be like
Placebo could you drenalin I don't know
Yeah I mean that's the thing is I just
No matter what it just seems like
The next
Flavor of new age
Think so
Started calling around my name is Peter Reiner and I'm professor at the University of British Columbia
So
So Peter actually
Studies this whole field
Keep WhatsApp public perception in the quality of research and I just
Basically asked aminos
For real like if you have a healthy brain you put a little
Electricity into a has it been proven that that will enhance learning or whatever else they claim
Well
Maybe the best way to answer that it is that
Part of the reason that there is all this interests
Set tdcs
Christy Ralph
Effective
Because this is based on a lot of different studies in a lot of different areas such a key to what I just said is relative
So the caveat that I have to add is that
Much all of the studies
That have been done today.
Relatively small
He says it's
Early days in the studies have been done have only been done with a few such a
Maybe 20 people
Larger study
40 or 50
Now these days to find a positive effect but if you're a hard-nosed scientist
You know those small sample sizes Aren't Enough
To make a very big claim
Even so
Cats
Kind of already out of the bag cuz if you go on YouTube
Really brief
Really quick
It's cool you can find a surprisingly large number of videos of
People experimenting with these devices
I instantly feel very
Good
Very
Converse
Saying it's not really worried about anyting videos show you how to make your own
Diagram go to RadioShack by few simple parts
That's going to be your 9 volt
Alligator clips since I don't have any starter with me although I have a switch in the circuit YouTube Jessie
Be filled with people who are trying to hotwire their own brain
Howard Zinn
I have probably below average rainfall compared to normal people
I want
Starting your Sciences but as many of you I don't have the resources to go to school right now
To do is I like to use tdcs
While I'm learning my
Vocabulary list I want to give you an update on
How to learn a foreign language
Which people are using this
Thanksgiving how flexible
That's Nick fits he works with Peter Runner the guy we talked to her earlier and he says not only can you do a lot of different kinds of things
This device on top of that
Dirt cheap
The time that it takes me to listen to one of your episodes
I can probably go to the store
Come back and build a tdcs device around $20
$20
I said something that makes you nervous
I'll say first I think the DIY Community is quite
But it does make me nervous that some people react report loss of consciousness after using it
Healing Burns
There's actually one report of somebody going temporarily blind
This guy on YouTube young Asian kid wear
Where which places are my head would improve memory about how he spent a year Canada
Experimenting with it he put it in one place and after about 5 minutes
I started to really like really angry and depressed
Put in another place
Tellagami a really high score on Lumosity
And I've only been stimulating my brain
It's like he's playing Russian roulette with
Which brings up a larger point you know that
Lit devices
Possibly hard to regulate
The kid like this can put it anywhere he wants in his head and if he moves it just a couple of inches
It could have a
Drastically different effect and that's really what
Is a
Because according to Peter Reiner
Well we might like to think of the brain as
Was being a bunch of separate
Circus
Except
Tasks
Really
It's a Neko
Every part affects every other part
In some way and when you put your electrodes on head
You affecting serious small area of the brain right under the electrodes but it's already been shown that
That's perfect can bed multiply and spread throughout the nervous system even down to your spinal
There's a theory out there is called the zero-sum theory of the brain that some people use
Framework for thinking about all this which is like
No one part goes up another part goes like there's only so much juice in the brain so if you
Send juice One Direction there's less juice somewhere else and a su then if you were enhancing one part year by definition
Diminishing another
Maybe be honest it was definitely in After Effects
Kind of why
I ended up talking to Sally about
This why I got so interested in this
He's in the first place
This is because
What happened to her
After the snap
For training so
Driving down from LA to Carlsbad
Citgo
Do this
Was an absolute nightmare I hadn't driven in like a year cuz I've been living in London where I just do public transportation
But on the way up
It's kind of like
Negative compared to Mario Kart but it's
Extremely pleasant experience
I feel like I drove better that day than I ever drove before
I think it was very obvious where I
Capaz people without
Irritating them and I don't know it's a weird
The weird memory but I think I had more fun driving
That day than I ever did
Since
And some point she realized it wasn't just about her driving a bit
So
I would say that
I mean I don't know how much I want to get into sort of in public on the radio
About
You know being a bit anxious
I guess that's not particularly controversial
Probably all writers
Liquor should have riddled with anxiety but you know I have
This
Constant
Struggle with all the little
Angry gnomes in my head
You know populating my head and telling me I like all the things that I don't do right
You know all the things that I've done wrong that day they
Keep this incredibly like
Comprehensive Taliesin
And then you know if they want to worry about the future than you know the ones who tell me I'm going to be living in a cardboard box
I mean it's just like an amazing
Cacophony
But she says
Sitting in that car they were they were just completely turned off I think
For a couple of days
And it was a really
For a couple days or couple of days and to tell you the truth
It's kind of like everything just
I was just this
Person that I hadn't
Experience before and I thought
Actual start of core person who I am
When all my baggage isn't just
It was like somebody had died
What's a really steamy window
Able to look at the world for what it was
Curious weather like
There's a connection there that like
Good
Former
Goes along with shutting down
The parts of yourself that say I don't know I don't think maybe I can't
Maybe I shouldn't
And that's like there's actually a real connection between
Amping up one and tamping down the other
Makes sense if you take giving one circuit more power you might be taken away from other place
It's funny I mean it does I find this like you know since you and I are just been on stage
One of the things I struggle with most
During the performances has been sitting there with busting there we've got our Scripts
And I have the
Box of buttons and afternoon which buttons
What things and there's like the musician.
Restaurant where they come in and out
And all of these things
They become competing voices
They become visible
Shattering
Gnomes the Sally pussy
State of my head
What is a Hellcat Network when does that come in where are we
Come on
Why you keep doing and I get like kind of crazy
So I can't actually even focus
What you're saying
It's not a good feeling and then there are other times where something happens almost like a mode
And suddenly it's like
Right there I know I'm right with you
It's the easiest thing in the world to listen to what you're saying and respond instinctively and in the moment
And it literally feel like different
Chemical mode
Maybe electrical mode
You know what I mean
That's really that's
That's very
Maybe cuz I'm going back to the performance stuff
You can't really
Make it
Happen I mean I guess
You could expose but it
It doesn't feel that way it feels like
It somehow feels like it's a gift
You know
Like
Oh thank you universe
I feel really awake
Present right now
Thank you
What happens when it's an expectation
You know what happened to her
Are the way in which we move to the world
If we can just
If we can create that on demand in order it up
Yeah gif
Versus ordering it up
Is priceless pretty deep to me I mean I don't I feel like in a world where you order things out than you're in a
The world where you think you deserve things are you think you've earned them or you think other people have an agree with that completely.
It's a word that's a world that's empty of
True gratitude
To tell you the truth
Worrying things
Tumi
Was
Afterward how
How much I
Craved
Doing it again
It felt like a drug with no side effects
I mean I don't know if I'm
Can I get addicted to electricity
Unlikely
Got to get some shoplifting batteries
Supermarket Corner licking
Thank you sir in no problem and thanks a lot to salieri
Seoul Time to Say Goodbye
Hi this is Emily in Austin Tex
Radiolab is supported in part by the National Science
Foundation
And by the Alfred
P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of science
And Technology
Margie in the modern world
More information about Sloan
At www