Are you awake
Northern listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
List of starting
Can you ready
Sheri Fink who works New York Times and is author of the book five days at Memorial
You can say it all began with
So this was back
Us and other I think NATO allies were involved in a bombing campaign
In Serbia last gasps of war in the Forum
Yugoslavia you had Serbia attacking
Ethnic albanians in Kosovo
NATO was trying to protect them bombing Serbia
Which is creating a huge Exodus refugee
Now Sherry
At the time was not yet
Fully a reporter
She was
Fresh out of med school
Volunteering at a human rights organization
Working on a book
About a war Hospital in Bosnia
And said she knew the landscape
She was able to convince this organization to let her go to Macedonia
The document what was happening
The document potential War crime
So I remember I went to the border of Kosovo Macedonia and
Refugees had shown up
They were
Trying to cross the border into Macedonia
But the Macedonian government had
Closed its border with Kosovo so people who were
Fling got trap
They got stuck in this
Muddy no man's land between the two borders
Said police in riot gear were basically in lining the Macedonian side
She had all of these people
Crammed into this muddy Channel
And
The Macedonian Red Cross
And this one charity
Had gotten permission to
Set up
Mix of medical station
In that border area
Between
These two countries
This is sort of grumpy Brown Medical.
Now Sherry was there
To conduct interview
Nothing to do with medicine
I was there
To collect information but when I got there
I literally remember walking up to this border
And a doctor who I had interviewed previously this really tall
Albanian Kosovo Albanian doctor looked out
And he told the Macedonian Border guard
Let her in we need her she's a doctor
Describe being pulled into the 10
What's what you just said
Finish med school
Suddenly she says she was tossed in with all these War doctors
And here's the key
Eventually she gets posted
At the door of the tent and what I ended up doing or what
They put me in charge of was
Triage
No
It's a it's a French word
Nice accent
I-88 means to sort or to sort for koala
Originally it was a reference to sorting coffee beans actually sweating different kinds of coffee
But a few hundred years ago the word started being applied to people to actually sorting different kinds of casualties
Battlefield
I'm not suddenly what's her job
Literally I stood outside of this
Makeshift
Medical station
And every minute every couple minutes there would be another
Patient brought
To the door of our Medical
And so my job was to stand outside that door and decide who gets in and who
Who doesn't
How did you do that how did you make that choice
I don't remember having guidelines I remember just having to wing it
She said she just went on Insta
And so
The people who seem like they might be having a heart attack or seizure those were the ones who went into that
At 10th but you know people with physical disabilities know people who have chronic conditions psychiatric issue
Everybody else I had to direct
To this
Other tents
And
Someone
Ended up calling it the 10th of the Damned
I remember but peeling for help
From the Macedonian Health Ministry sing
No take these people into Macedonia they're not a threat
Open your border take them in they need
Care
And
The health Ministry
Refusing and so they stayed in this tent day after
Today
Sometimes for 4
6 days
And several the people in
This tent
They died
Cherry says this experience
Haunted
And years later
When she was a full-blown reporter and traveling all around the world looking at triage in different scenarios
She would return to this memory again and again in wonder
How
Do people
In that situation make that decision how should they
Today a collaboration with the New York Giants wear
Going to follow reporter Sheri Fink the ins-and-outs of triage in three different situations three
Different places in the world that she tries to understand what it means to play God
I'm jamming Rod I am Robert krulwich this is Radiolab
Stay with us
Always in case of water
Bailey when you were going to start with Coast level when did you as a writer be
Well this
This
This Obsession of
About triage
Came about when I was working on my
Last book
Five days at Memorial which was about
Triage in the emergency in Hurricane Katrina
This is the scenario that people in New Orleans have been fearing for a long time
A category 5 hurricane headed right toward the city
I've heard the story of Katrina told and retold certainly it's hard not to think about now with what's happening
Baton Rouge
But in this story
The hurricane is really just
Really really focusing on one
This Hospital Memorial Medical
Call Center built in 1920s
In one of the lowest parts
Types of that city which is really like a bull
Is a sturdy brick building a stories tall
Stretching over two city blocks
Served in every storm until that point it was really seen it somewhere safe
And this Hospital became for Sherry a kind of portal into these questions about triage
She ended up spending six and a half years
Interviewing doctors at the hospital patients nurses family members government officials ethicist Hospital
You know she conducted over 500 interviews to reconstruct moment for moment
What happened at the hospital during Hurricane
Get ready this the most intense part of the storm is getting ready to come across
Day 1 Monday August 29th
Around 6 a.m.
Katrina hit
I've never seen anything in my life like this and
They get through the storm okay
City power's gone but they've got their backup power
But this hospital it has a boner ability a lot of American hospitals have which is that they had moved the generator
To the second floor so that they would be higher up
Is playing but electricity is all about
Circuits
And they had elements of that backup power system that were below
Flood level things like switches and other electrical material
But they got through the first day okay
And it seemed to that point that the worst was over
And then
When do the sun rise
Water surrounds this Hospital
But it feels New Orleans and as the Water started to rise around the hospital that is the moment
That the people in charge new
They were in big big trouble
They knew
What their vulnerability was
How many patients are in the hospital is it
There were
250 patients
They're about 2000 people because you had so many
Wow staff and then all the visitors who had come with the staff members and with
The patients
Sherry says mid-morning on that second day
Tuesday August 30th
Just as the waters are starting to rise
A group of doctors got together and they did come up with a system which evolved a little bit over the crisis
But stay
Decided
First
Get the babies out
Get the critic
Who care Patients Out
Chandni
Knew that they had
To high water truck
From the National Guard in the water wasn't so so high yet at that point it was only part way up
The sloping emergency room rap
And they decided to put patients who could walk on those
So
Helicopter start to arrive
Medical staff start to bundle tiny babies in incubators
ICU patients in wheelchairs
Onto the elevator
And up to the helipad
How many patients can a single helicopter take in like the ones that were Landing how many can they do one or two
Slow going
Yeah it was late evening
Before they got all the Intensive Care Unit Patients Out the babies and the babies
All in all that second day they evacuated about 60 people
Critical path
Although we should also say that
If a patient has signed a DNR do not resuscitate
Are the doctors decided those patient
Should not go for
And they were held back
Explain their thinking on that
OKC Darkness Falls Hyundai
The doctors and nurses are exhausted
They've been working really really hard carrying patients in the heat
Many of them lay down on
Cotton bacon bits
To rest for the night and then
Before the sun rises 2 hours before about 2 a.m.
The buzz of the generators suddenly just
Stopped
Quiet
The water had reached
There's electrical switches in the base
Doctor doctor cook
Yuan cook long-time ICU doctor he was lying not far from where those generators were
He said to me it was
Quote the sickest
Sound of a
His life
Sound apps
And
That is when it became an absolute emergency in this house
Pitch blackness
Some of the medical equipment they have backup batteries they started beeping
To warn that the electrical power heads
Stop you still had nine patients who relied on ventilators to breathe
It became a hive of activity at got to get everyone out everybody was
Running around with flashlights
Beams in the blackness
Trying desperately to move those patients
Down the stairs now there's no elevators that's the other big thing fortunately somebody found a hole in them
Machine room wall on the second floor that led directly to a parking garage
And so they figured out the path patients through this roughly 3 by 3 foot hold on to the
The back of a pickup truck drive them up
To the 8th story of that parking garage and then carry them up three rickety lights of
Steps to the
Formerly unused helipad
And
Five of the nine
Patients on ventilators died
Just right then
Just like I said I've been trying to
I want to make
This is tape of an interview that Sherry did back in 2018 she was doing research
Story
My name is Gina
Gina was a nursing director working on the 7th floor of the hospital that day she text me to tending to those now
9 patients that didn't make the first helicopter run
And she described to Sherry that right
After the power went out and after the ventilator shutdown
One of her patients Flatline
And um
The guy in back
We had fun out of oxygen
That's what you've been told
And so we brought him down
Stairs
2 second floor
They brought him down in the dark and then got in line to wait for their turn to go through the hole in the wall
To the heliport
And she says that since his ventilator wasn't working any
The whole time they were standing there they had the hands
Squeezes ventilator
Keybar
Tony to his lungs
You know he kept twitching in
Oxygen
Television line
And it was my turn at the window
One of the Physicians came over
You do know that he needs oxygen
Yes sir
They don't have any eyes
We can't get any
And at that point
Are you do this
Why did you just let him go
He was right
Me to do it with neurologic
Going to make it without it
Massages
Argument
Shopkins hair
I waited
Had to take him out
Of the Boiler Room
Odin
Log was full
The chaplain came over to
Took the body into the chapel
And he just how bad
Aetna
What do you laugh I just said that
A few minutes
Try to compose
I doubt people
Say people
You know
Just not enough
Everything you've done is just not enough
Day 3
Wednesday August 31st
Sunrises
And
That's when
There
Expecting all the helicopters come back
They wait
And they wait
Anyway
And an occasional helicopter comes
But this
Concerted rescue efforts that had taken place the evening before
Has stopped
Now
We know now looking back
Did on that Wednesday the helicopters were doing their own triage
Rescuing people from looking at people on rooftops waving rags
The people inside the hospital
Most of them had no idea
All the new
Was
We're in this horrific situation
Where are the helicopters
At this point they're still nearly 200 patients at the
And
Some of the staff
Panics because it takes them so long to move the patients
The top of the parking garage just below that helipad
So she says on that third day at about 7 in the morning
Bunch of doctors in hospital administrator
Maybe a dozen
Dozen and a half
They got together and they decided that they needed a system
The way of organizing their patients so that when those helicopter
Started to show up again
They wouldn't waste any time at all.
I know exactly who to evacuate in what order
Another words
Who are we going to get out
That was the question and that's the moment where they come up with the ones
Twos and threes
This is
Triage
There are a limited number of resources in this case helicopters in a few boats
And we have to decide which people get access
Castillo's resources
There are a couple of ways to look at this
Siri says if you go back to the very beginning of triage
The first conception of it 1790
Napoleon's Chief surgeon
Baron Larry I think
Give me the rule
On the battlefield
That you take the people were in the acute need first
So the tickets are going to be treated first
And with the most resource
And this is the way it works in most emergency rooms there's a long waiting line
Hotspot
If you got a heart attack you get right to the front of the line
Another way to look at it is the utilitarian concept
It's got its start with some philosophers in the 18th and 19th centuries
The core of this idea seems simple
Try to do the greatest good
You want to maximize some sort of
Good outcome amongst
The population
So rather than think about what one individual needs you think
How can I save the most
Number of lives are the most number of years
I'm going to Max my years of life we might
Want to pick people who are have a better chance of surviving or younger people
And this method of triage
Swear you often see in a war zone where I say there's a bombing
And you have
More injured victims than there are ambulances hermetics
So 1
Imagine a library in a hospital waiting area
Cherry says in this case with the doctors did they ask the staff
To get everyone out of their rooms
Bring them down to that second floor Lobby
And then some doctors including one whose name
Might be relevant for later dr. Ana Polo
She and another doctor
They stationed themselves
On the landing where the patients were brought down to on that second floor and as the nurses would bring them
They would look
Quickly at the patient's chart look at
Patient and decide on a number
And the nurses would take magic marker and a piece
Paper and write either one two or three on that paper
And then she says
They would take that number
Onto the patient's gown
So the ones
Where you're relatively healthy patients
Patient maybe who had an appendicitis and their appendix out there
Looking good they could even be discharged
The ones would be rescued by boat presumably among the first
The twos were you're more typical Hospital patient
Patient maybe who had a heart attack who wasn't
Fully recovered who
Would need
Ongoing care
They would go by helicopter presumably second
And industries were those
Super sick patients or anyone with a do not resuscitate order
Those patients are golang
One of the doctors when I said
Why did you choose
The sickest patients to go last
One of them said while I figured
Anyone with a do not resuscitate order
Would have a
Terminal or irreversible condition which by the way isn't always the case
And he said I thought that that patient would have
Quote the least to lose
So it sounds like in some way they went to more of a utilitarian wave
Yeah
And you could see everything that follows
Flowing from
Utilitarian decision and actually made it a few different
Prioritize the healthiest people first
And the sickest people laugh
He's choices ultimately did become
Very consequential
10 case all three groups
Are placed in different parts of the hospital
And the threes were kept in the lobby
The second floor Lobby
To jest
Wait
So as the day goes on the area started to get really full
Patient next
The patient on these cots
She says you had about 18 people lined up side-by-side and Caesar
People with heart conditions symptoms of pneumonia
Stroke there were nurses
It just
But it was so so hot
Some people gas
The temperature inside the building must have been on
I don't know if there's any way for me to do
Describe to you
How intense the heat was
This is doctor anapo in an interview with 60 minutes
Choose one of the doctors who
It was relentless
It was suffocating
It made it extremely difficult to breathe
And with the heat
The terrible smell
Started to smell really bad and the bathroom
Sewage was sort of backing up in the toilet and they just say it's the word everywhere
On the ground everywhere
Personally I didn't want to eat or drink anything cuz I didn't want to have to use the bathroom
As the day went on some people started really feeling abandoned
Why are they here why aren't they helping us
On the 7th floor
Weather was this radio that was playing in the quarter
8 minutes
Iww local talk stations and the radio was
One of the only ways they were getting information from the outside
The rage is growing among some of the nurses have carts that they would roll around and they have the little radio
On the cart and they'd be listening jungle human instincts are beginning to creep in and
Nevertales on the radio that were alarming the stash merchandise
These people should be shocked that turned out not to be true like
Had declared martial law
There was literally a deputy sheriff
Who got on there and told people that
He saw a shark
Swimming around a hotel there walking like zombies
Five nights of the Living Dead that whole imagine how that would feel if you were in this hospital that was the only word you were having
About what was going on outside
Just Like Heaven
Breakdown
Freaking out
In the garage
Buy afternoon of that third day that Wednesday
Some of the staff for having nervous breakdowns
Morales really really low because
All these patients are still there Bass
Patients were so hot you know they were just kind of drift off to
Sleepy have to wake him up
And make them take sips of water
Subservient
Whatever we had you know
City of New Orleans will never be the same
Help someone while crying for their mom
One of the nurse
Told me she was worried that they could be brain damage
Lasting effects
Afdah
Severe overheating
So there's this level of
Of panic
There is also the situation of the pets
And
This may make no sense
Too much people but
They would offer staff members
They could bring their pets
If they were coming in to work
Storm and they turned medical records over into a kennel
And
People start to worry about their
Apparently on that Wednesday one of the larger.
What's a Newfoundland
Started having seizures from the Heat
So
Some of the staff
Chose to have
Doctors euthanized
And then just
Try to imagine if you can
Looters are running free
Hot people are dying your hair gunshots in the neighborhood you're afraid
I don't know if there's real violence breaking out in
City
Stop floating in the water there how many rescue resources are going to come tonight time
And your colleague walks up to you and says
Do you know
For euthanizing
Pets to put them out of their misery
What about the suffering patient
Shouldn't we put some of them
Out of their misery
And I interviewed all these people and trying to figure out like where did this idea
Come from and tracing it back and there were all these
Little informal conversations
And
This starts just going around the hospital
The sort of idea
Of putting patients out of their misery
I don't know who told me that
But that's what I heard
And you know in those
Circumstances
What are you doing
If you're at War and you have someone
It's not going to be picked
Safety
Live leading the deaf
What are you doing
Cherry says that as this idea spread around the hospital
People fell into different camps
Some people thought this was
The most Humane thing they
Do
It would be criminal to let people
Will suffer more
Other people when they heard about it
We're outraged
For example dr. Bryant King who's colleague doctor
Fournier
She walks up to him and
Says there's this
Discussion going on and you know what do you think and he says
Idea
This is Doc
Burger King in an interview on CNN
Day for Thursday September 1st
Here's would end up
And accounts here are
The vegan industry
According to dr. King who spoke about this
Json CNN
He says
And other people say
Say they saw this as well
He said he saw one of the doctors we talked about earlier
Dr. Ana Polo who still there that Thursday morning
Caring for patients please
Patience on the second floor
Who were chosen to go last
He says he saw her
Talking to patients
While holding a handful of syringe
Anna standing over there with handful of syringes talking to a patient
And
Herbivores
That I heard her say were
I want to give you something to make you feel better
Macy had a handful of syringes I don't
And
Nobody nobody walks around with a handful of syringes and goes and gets the same thing these patient that this is not how we do it
Jump forward 4 be after this whole ordeal was over and the rescue teams in the
Mortuary teams arrived
Many bodies were found in this house
Hospital
About 45 bodies found
And so there was an investigation launched
They found these bodies
They tested these bodies for drugs
And what they found was that nearly two dozen patients had received
Either morphine or versed
A powerful sedative
Or combination of the two
In a very short time. On that Thursday September 1st 2005
It was
I think 21 in the end
But
It's complicated
In medicine
What is Comfort Inn what is murder
Depends to a large degree
On the intentions of the doctor
It's called the principle of the double effect is sometimes credited to St Thomas
Aquinas
And
It's this idea that
An act
It's that that can cause harm but if your intention is to do good
Ethical
Dr Anna Poe those patients
As the Attorney General
No
I did not
Murder
Those patient
I don't want everybody to know
That I am not a murderer
That we
Or not
Murderous
In that 60 Minutes interview dr. Pope
Flatly denies euthanizing anybody
Various points in the interview she is
Clearly distraught
At the accusation
It completely
Ripped
My heart out
Because my entire
Life
I've tried to do good
Am I tired all life
I have given everything that I have Within Me
To take care of
Of my patience
Mishary did talk to One doctor dr. Ewing
We mentioned him earlier when we were talking about the other generators
He's a doctor who do you love
End-of-life
He was very open with her
About the decision
He had gone upstairs visited mrs. progess
Canterbury
See how she was doing and he was just thinking to himself
She's so so sick she's got Advanced cancer
I can't imagine she would have more than maybe a week to live at the best
Circumstances
She is weighted down with fluid which can happen for the end of life
So she weighs a lot
She's on the 8th floor
So we'd have to
Carry her downstairs and plus there's four nurses up here taking care of her
Could we use them somewhere else so he literally turned to one of the nurses and said
Can you give her enough morphine till she goes
And that nurse charting
Huge
Increasing
Morphine
For her and she died
And
That was
Thought so he made this decision until this day or at least the last time we spoke he felt he did the right thing
He said to me he thought it was desperate he saw only two choices Quicken their deaths
Or abandon them
I mean if that was the real situation there's some at the sea
This would say either of those choices would be
No not justified but excusable
But one of the arguments you could make
Is that when you give up on one person
Then becomes
A little bit easier to give up on the next
And then the next
First and then suddenly you're on the slippery slope
Ensure he did tell us about this one
His case was very haunting
Emmett Everett 61 year old
Doting grandfather
Very very heavy
He weighed 380 lb and he was up on the 7th floor of the hospital
He was conscious alert
Set himself breakfast
Baptist nurses are we ready to rock and roll
He said to one nurse
Poop never forgot it
Cindy don't let them leave me behind don't let them leave me behind
He had had a spinal cord
Stroke he couldn't walk
He was on the 7th floor of the hospital with no working elevators
And the staff told me they couldn't imagine how they would
To carry him down
Those flights
Upstairs let alone with a helicopter take a man of his size
And he was one of the patients who was found with this drug combination in his body
David Bowie died
He.
Found his body was found
And by the way the other tragedy was just as those injections took
The place was when the helicopter
Finally we're folks
Gaston the song
Did a judge or jury find anyone guilty of manslaughter or murder or
Second degree murder
No nobody
And again just to remind you how quickly
A hospital can go from a normal American
Well-regarded functioning Hospital
To a place where this was even
Considered
Cast
Was so short
Monday morning the storm hits Tuesday Morning the water rises
Early Wednesday morning all power goes out
And this is Thursday
Kind of chilling to think
God of all of that begin with a triage decision about which patients
Should go first
I'm trying to put myself in the position of the
People at that hospital
I'm thinking to myself
How do you guys have like a checklist
Make a checklist on a wall that says here's how you do this so that I can just check the boxes
I wouldn't be able to take my way through that so that's where I go next
I wonder
Wasn't this story you've just told us bleeds us anywhere the first place it would lead me
Would be to ask
Is there a system that people could set up
People are reasonable and who have the expectation of something like this is going to happen again
Somehow somewhere
Maybe in my town my hospital my
So what could we do
To make this now
Well it's interesting you ask because of course after Katrina there have been efforts since then to come up with a protocol
Going to share the experience and Katrina was basically a wake-up call for
Doctors in
Hospitals
State governments to think about
Triage like how should we ration medical resource
Something bad happens again
Which patients we prioritize
First which patients don't we prioritize
How do we do this
And
One of the interesting things was that the state of Maryland decided
We're going to throw this open to our population and have what they called deliberative democracy
So pull people together in a room from all walks of life
And have them grapple with
And
I was there oh you went to the very first one
Did I mention like a town hall meeting was it like that
Or no
Yeah, just imagine the church basement
Intercity Baltimore or a conference room in Bobby Howard County
Saturday
What we think is a really really important conversation
Refreshments
At about 12:15
Will take a break for you all to get lunch bring it back to you
People have been recruited to be a part of this and when I say people it's just regular folks
So that researchers let's call them that they get people together and
Good morning
Set the sort of scenario is laid out
Skin and we're going to be talking about today is
How we make decisions about
Who gets life-saving resource
In a situation when you literally cannot take care of everyone
Today the scenario will talk about is pandemic influenza tell people okay imagine a flu is sweeping
In the country
Millions of people are sick
Coughing some are dying the only way the folks are going to get better they say
Is it they have a ventilator to help them breathe but the problem is
There just aren't enough.
This is a terrible situation were talking about so here you have too many patients too few resources
How do we choose
Who gets those ventilators
Might be the right
The researchers then essentially layout three different kinds of options
Number one
Try to save the most lives or years of Life by picking people the best chance of surviving the pandemic
And later see young people or healthier people
Number to bacon people who will be the most helpful during the pandemic
So First Responders Health Care Providers vaccine work
Four number three
Something like first-come first-serve or a lottery
See people that make sense
Okay
And then they say we're here to answer your questions Talk Amongst yourself
You know
Where it was or what
What my immediate reaction to the lottery was
It's a leveler
It's all the same I think it is typically least responsible way to go
Ultimately it's fair if somebody's going to live but the very sick is that should that go into the decision
If we set of guidelines then yes if every kind of doctor you know what I mean going to be essential
Now the good news is a ventilator and a four-year-old wouldn't I just think that would be this.
People are willing to engage in this question
And this was right at the time you guys remember all the Death panel discussion
Sarah Palin
In black and white started at that time
And the word emphasize
But as you can also hear
You get it first because you'd and I got there half a second and I are there wasn't a lot
Lot of agreement
I respect your opinion but I'm just dealing with
I suppose there's no room for emotion
Dubai person-to-person is exception to the rule that's emotion coffee
Anything that's going on and that's why we have those setup
It's one of the
The big findings was that there are certain ways in which we will not make these
There were things that the researchers wanted to be off the table like not even
Come into the
Discussion
We're not going to make decisions based on gender race socioeconomic status like people's jobs and ink
Comes and citizenship status
You know whether they had a criminal history or were they upstanding members of society
Just want to say upfront that's not
That's not up for grabs
But those things kept popping up
You wouldn't have it like a young pastor and you might have a reprehensible
Alcoholic criminal type person
And he might have more years to live
Pastor are going to be more beneficial
Societies in the ears of a criminal reprehensible alcoholic
Well you are
Australian territories
That is it
Dad is a personalized there were people who thought that undocumented immigrants shouldn't get ventilators
Alcoholic smokers the world will be a better place
Do you deserve to survive
Can I say to you but should I try and save you
What's interesting is that
People really comfortable making utilitarian choices like saying yeah that person should get the ventilator because
They're going to benefit the greater good in some way
But if that ever got formulated in a slightly different way which is to say that person should get the ventilator because they deserve
Bit more than another their life has more value
Another person
Well then people like
We're not cool
And yet you would hear people say it that way again and again and then immediately be repulsed
When they heard someone else
Say that way
I don't think you can determine who's done what in their life and how that valuable I might think
My hairdresser is more important
All right I want to look for during my pants at my situation
And this was particularly acute when participants were asked the second
Controversial topics really hard question
Would it be acceptable to you do you think it's acceptable to ever
Remove a ventilator from one patient
To give it to somebody else
This one I definitely don't have a clear answer myself
Some people
Fayetteville
Of course. Doesn't seem like someone is going to make it through the treatments
Then we need to
Kevin cut their treatment short in Kansai ventilator on a someone else but
You're going to murder my father they were other people who said no
You are going to be
I've never going to sign up for that
So
Complicate
Did they come to a conclusion
Hear a conclusion
I listen to this
Here's what I heard I heard
Thoughtful people
Struggling with a problem that is so
Hard to struggle with
At what the end up doing is going I don't know how I don't want to do this
I pay no attention to your guidelines cuz I can't deal with what I loved about it
The number one response was
Try to get out of this
Situation and
Find ways to avoid having to ration
That's the most important part of this
What is it the researchers are going to take away from all this
Well a couple of things that they got out of it
Number one
Remember we talked about the different ways of
Deciding that they put out for people to discuss well it turns out they wanted to combine some of those
Different perspectives and they carry a lot of people
Thought sure let's start out utilitarian let's try and
Save the most Lies by picking the people who are most likely to survive
If they're likely to survive and they need it
But chances are they're going to be a lot of people who fit in that category
So if everybody is just about the same as we can't we don't have like great science that allows us to know which patient
It is going to survive and which ones not going to
The 4th at 2nd tier
Let's do it randomly let's just being really really fair and give everyone an equal chance
So it's like you introduce a little bit of faith.
Keep things on
Exactly and that in the research you said you know what this is a good idea let's see if we could
Maybe put this concept into the protocol
Am I right in thinking that these guidelines whatever they end up being are designed to avoid that sort of like
Sorting based on
Who deserves a new does
Yeah I mean
There's some fairness
And having
Guidelines
Especially guidelines that were developed with the input of lots of people
So even if
We don't like
The choices
That are made and we
Don't end up getting the ventilator where our loved one doesn't
Overall if you know that there's a protocol out there and this is the rule
Here's why we had to adopt this rule
It's being applied to everybody and you're not
Canby advantage or disadvantage
Over money or over of these
Other sayings
It sort of helps you accepted
My in theory that sounds
Plausible
But when you put Theory to practice
That's what you can do
Right after the break
Things get
Very
Heart
That's coming up
This is Jerome calling from Silver Spring Maryland Radiolab
Supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the
Modern world more information about Sloan and www.delone.org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here I'm a producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
And I request for those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents
Aunts and uncles teachers
We're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments
Basically I want to hear about this
I kid you know did something
It just means you lean back and say
Well
Maybe it was the moment that our kids you've been reading to 4 month started reading
Back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons and you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin
Or maybe the kids in math
Music in the margin of their geometry
We're interested in the
Specific moments where
Kid does something super smart
It doesn't have anything to do with the test
If you have a story
Go to radiolab.org
Flash brilliance
Record a short audio message
And that's where you're at. Org / really
Thank you so much
Hey I'm Jared I'm Robert krulwich Radiolab and returning now to our collaboration with a New York time
Times Reporter Sheri Fink
Our final stop many ways are hard to stop
Cuz
It's the closest we're going to come to stir the
Heart
Of the issues we've been talking about
And you realize that when you get
Close
Pictures about 2
Sometimes what
What's a success what's a failure
Hard to measure
Test
I remember being in Haiti after the Haiti earthquake
Back in 2010
I was embedded with a group of us disaster responders
The International Medical and surgical Response Team insert
10th hospital and AT-AT
Point maybe about a week and a half after the earthquake there were
So so many casualties
Thousand people could be dead
A patient kind of lined up in a row
Festering wounds open fractures and they didn't have enough resources and they were running out of
Oxygen tanks
And then they were also trying to use these oxygen concentrators with pull oxygen from the environment
But they rely on Power and they was running out of diesel for the generators
Logistics where the critical level with our diesel Supply and oxygen for the
So I'm freaking today I mean I am freaking pray for us and Logistics today
This was a hospital that had
Set up to do surgery they needed oxygen they didn't have enough so the question became
Who were they going to give it to and who were they not
At one point when I see you
We walked into this tent
And we met this woman
She had braided hair a white nightgown on and this too
Running into her nose
How old are you
What's the same age how are you feeling today
Good of a bad if I say in speaking to her I found out that she was from Port-au-Prince the
And that during the earthquake
Her house had collapsed
Everyone inside it she said
Which is most of her extended family
The guide
Live in yesterday between Ocala
So sorry she told me that amazingly she had survived
Italian-American
She wasn't at home when the earthquake hit she checked into this Hospital
Very shortly before the earthquake happened because she had had chronic
Lung problems so
She was there to get treatment
And after the earthquake She was transferred to this American Hospital. How do you feel about the treatment that you got here
Way better than
Anywhere that she's been.
I'm in charge of all the thing that's going on
I'm happy to see a smile on your face
I started to speak with the staff about her even taking care of her
When I found out that Natalie had just
Who won the hearts of the surgical staff there
People loved her she was so thankful but she has a chronic illness which is severe heart failure
Hypertension in pregnancy relief
They told me they had plans to
Take her off
Oxygen
They were going to turn down the oxygen slowly
To try to make it
More comfortable
And then they were going to send her off
Patient facility that didn't have oxygen but where she would
Presumably die
And
If your thinking in terms of cold hard
Triage Theory
You know this makes sense because they were trying to save oxygen she has a chronic problem that probably won't get better so that's
The theory of it
But the practice of it
Was quite different
She absolutely no idea that they were about to do this
She
Had all this hope for her funeral
Have an opportunity to earn a living
Once you do the hospital is there any way possible that the people would give her like somewhere to stay.
I mean I'm a journalist and I don't know the answer to that but
I don't know what to say it's such a hard situation right now and I remember the nurse who was
Doing the triage
Should made that
Decision to cut off her oxygen on the team
I've never met her
I never met the patient
But that's the role that a net we're running out of oxygen
The country itself doesn't have oxygen so I have to make the decision no she can't have KNOX
I have to look at the greater
Good that we can provide
With the limited resources we have
And so
Then I followed that woman
I wanted to see
Just on a human level as well as on the abstract level
The Transporters came a few hours later
That service
Amazing and they came to pick her up
She was on oxygen
Okay we're going to
Are there portable oxygen tanks
And the representative from the hospital said oh no
She doesn't get oxygen so they yanked the oxygen
Toronto structure
Lifted her up
Stuck on the back of this Humvee ambulance
Cargo Humvee
I rode with her
She started getting short of breath
American oxygen
Put his asthma inhaler in her mouth and she kept hitting it over and over again she thought it was oxygen
Twitterrific
To watch her start to suffer
I felt complicit
I was doing a story and I knew very well
That
They had chosen for her to
To die and
Just watching didn't feel
It didn't feel right
And so sorry
Stopped at this hospital and I nodded over toward her and some of the medical staff when
To look at her
She was really struggling to breathe but then
I saw one of my medical school professors
Emergency doctor in
I told him about her
Cooking Mama
And
Supervise
Tricks to get fluid off of lung and he found one
Think of oxygen that had a teeny bit life in it
Okay
He was able to extend her life
Ultimately I actually
Felt responsibility for her that outlasted
The story that I did and so after that came out I
I did attempt to help her
Really yeah
Well
I found a
Charitable group that was willing to bring her to the US under a certain type of Visa program that allowed for
Humanitarian
I'd like a Medical Treatments
And
That the cardiologist who had examined her and Haiti had thought she had a
Rheumatic heart
Disease that was causing her lung problems and that it could be
Surgically corrected but when she came to the US
In fact
It was found that she had much more serious
Condition and she really needed a transplant and she
Didn't
Didn't make it
Does this make you
Wonder
So you've got a rule
And maybe in some Broadway it's helping but
In that
Vehicle looking at
This woman
You wanted to
Break the rules
Premier League
Moral and decent reason
In these extreme circumstance
This is where life and death
Wrestling
Each other
Can you make
Rules
I mean I am because
It's like you can't fall if you offer taking her off yet
And you can't fault you for trying to get her on the ox
What's the conclusion to draw
Well let's not give up you know the conclusion is let's not give up
Like it turns out there was there were options for this woman it turns out that somebody
Was able to extend her life now you could
Very well argue that she should have died in that moment because look at all the resources that were spent
But I just feel like like there was some value in her existence there was so much value
She came to the US and my God she took up a collection for all the patients back in the Haitian.
Hospital who she was friends with
She contributed till the day she died
She changed my life too so I don't know how to do the math on this one you know the problem
Guidelines require like a lack of compassion the cold hard rigidness of it and
Everything your tiny butt has to do with compassion
This is Simon Adler by the way our producer
And how do you make compassion work on that large of a scale
Without caring about people and then you care about some people more than other people in the night
Check now or never hurting people so very good point
If you don't systematized it you you risk
Choosing people based on factors that are really not fair
Spider-Man does Wonder like what if Natalie weren't such a nice person
Wood
Her without a change things
Well you know if Natalie was a mean person that I don't think I would have felt any better watching her suffer its
It's just about the person in front of you
And I think that the more unbearable it is so the more you have to look someone in the eyes the more
It makes us
Try to figure out creative ways to avoid doing it
You you somehow refusing to acknowledge the subject when it really really gets tough
Avoid that
Over and over again let's not facing the real problem which is that it's a problem to have to ration
We're not going to figure out the best way to ration because there is no one best way because everyone in society will have a different view on that
I think that's in some way unimpeachable I think you're absolutely right we should always strive to not have to make the
We do have to make the choice
How do we do it
Well that's a very tough question
Let me tell you that I think what you hit upon here
Is an impossible
Piece of human piss
Rationing triage whatever you call it
Is a NeNe
Human act which
Humans
Are trying to do but if the fact of their Humanity makes it
Impossible
Toby got here is because
In a real deep problem
We have a god roll
And nobody fits it
We have so many people to thank for this hour
I will start with Lily Sullivan and Pat Walters for really getting us thinking about all of this
Thank you Lily thank you Pat thank you also to PRI the world a version of Haiti story first appeared on that show
Huge snakes to New York Times correspondent Sheri Fink
All the stories you heard in this our came as a result of her reporting for the book five days at Memorial
Sherry has an article that coincides with the podcast
About the Maryland project we will link you to it from radiolab.org nytimes
Times.com triage
I'm thinking your times for letting this Sherry for a bit of time
Yes this story was produced by Simon banned4life Adler Annie there can be only one MacEwan we had originally
Music about Simon in Annie
Also from Taylor to free antenna Kirchner I'm Jedi Cam'ron
I'm Robert krulwich listening
Message twice
Radiolab is produced by Chad Adam run
Director of sound design
Where's that include Simon Adler
Robert krulwich
Chelsea Padgett
Jackson Road
Michelle Harris