Are you weightless
Radio WNYC
Hey I'm Jared I'm Robert krulwich this is Radiolab and today we're going to
So we're going to feature a story from our friends over at reply-all just a podcast produced by gimlet media
House by PJ Vogt Alex Goldman bring let you hear a taste of reply-all because it's an amazing show
Every other the entire staff's like secret favorite show not even Secret
And this story it just kind of grabbed us we're not going to pay you the whole story that they
We're going to play the most of it
We might intervene from time to time just to sort of because we did bubble over with questions
Exactly and this the story actually
Doesn't come from PJ now it comes from
One of The Producers Shruti pinnamaneni the story service centers are in a couple and their son
Tell let me
Start by introducing you to the couple
Amy green
And Ryan green
No I already ate those I think that's why I'm suffering this morning
They live in a small house in Loveland Colorado
They fell in love chatting online got married as soon as I turn 21
Images of this house
The very next day
Response to my emails and then we'll head down
They had their first son Caleb
Their second son Isaac
Ryan was
Computer programmer and Amy take care of a cat
They were just living in a mess of diapers and toys
Going to church every Sunday and then
In 2009
Agile
When Joel was born
How old are you
If I was 25 when Kayla was born and then Isaac was born I would have been like 20
7 - 28
I was 2800
Everything was normal sign
And then just a little before his first birthday
Amy noticed that his head was a little boy
Tilted
Decock to one side
A couple days later he starts throwing up
Can't keep any food down
And so they do a bunch of tests and the doctor says listen your son has
Elysian
The counselor
So they biopsy the tumor and then they come back with
Snooze that it's something called in a trt
It's very very difficult to treat so when you have an atrt
You
Go through all the most intense chemotherapy and all the most intense radiation they throw the kitchen sink at it
And doing that you have about a 50% chance of surviving for 5 years
I double check this and it turns out the odds of survival are even Grimmer it's a 50% chance of snow
Surviving just two years
When you hear this kind of news is there any part of you that's like
What are you doing
Do the treatment I remember
Before his first surgery asking them a lot about likely have to have chemotherapy and thinking to myself cuz I can't
We can't we can't do this
This is crazy we can't do this
Botanas timer on and by the time we actually when I heard about that
That tumor
Then you're just thinking like 50% like that's half like we got a good shot that he gets through this
What do you think Isaac he's in the hospital so they're taking care of him
This is from a home video of jewels Brothers meeting him in the hospital
Isaac is two and a half
Looking kind of scared
Jaw is a little over a year old he's lying in a small red wagon
Hooked up to an IV
Skinny and his head is perfectly round
Food
His food goes to that too
Yeah
So they start going through this treatment starts off with intense radiation and then just you know months of chemotherapy
I didn't know what that meant it means that you just hold the baby for 6 7 8 hours a day
You just lying in bed with them while they get these infusions
And so do you like this 8-hour pump and you took it up at night and it would be this
Like this white milky substance
That would provide all of his nutrition because he couldn't swallow very well
One day it was Amy chef
She was holding Joel is sitting in his room with him ever seen him a song and clapping
And he was clapping his hands
And then he was sort of like Babble singing along and so like for me it was just one of those moments that you felt like I'm always
Remember this
Like sometimes you just have a moment and you going to remember this the rest of my life
A man that made me sad because I thought
Old like but the reason I think I'll remember this the rest of my life is because he could die
Until eventually I did just kind of decide like I think I need to be all in like
I think I need to love him like mad and I think we need to live our lives like he's going to live
That's what they did
4 year
And then in November 2010 just before Joel 2nd birthday
The doctors call them in and they say
We're really sorry
Joe has another tumor
All these chemicals we've been pumping into him they didn't do anything and so it's time for us to stop
He will eventually die we're not sure but we thinking about 4 months
But as Shruti Hassan explaining the story
That definitely wasn't it
Cuz there's this one night when situation was
You must had his worst
And something happened to stomach bug you throwing up got dehydrated
So Ryan spend the night with him in the hospital
I just remember I'm really wanting apple juice
Cuz I was one of his favorite things at the hospital but then I give it to him anytime
Throw it up again and he's crying and crying and his prize just got more frantic
An animal and there's nothing that Ryan can do
I just remember like I wanted to hold him and I couldn't put him down because he would get so upset and
Put him down Joel would start hitting his head against the wall of his crib eventually Ryan himself started
You said he was crying too and then in the early hours of the morning he lay down
And prayed
And I remember that's when he stopped crying and he fell asleep
I was just one of those
Smooth few moments in life where
Like it felt like an answer from God
And
It wasn't like I Heard a Voice or saw
You know a burning bush or anything like that but it was just it felt so much like
Mercy
And Beyond just Shear relief Ryan had this
Other thought
Franklin
A weird thought
This whole ordeal reminded him of a video game
Like you have to get the baby to stop crying so you keep trying things give him choose bounce him talk to him
But the weird thing is
This awful game
None of those things actually work they're all like fake choices
Brian thought
What if
I can make a game like this
Where you the player you don't really have control
And so he starts to think like
I wonder if I could make that
I can make that scene we could make the scene of Joel in desperation and then give him an option
Is that the thing is is there any active saving being a no
So he's going to make a video game where everything you do doesn't work baby still cries
I think he was just intrigued by that because it seemed
Bizarre
Yeah
I'll make
Video game where you
Can't do anything
Set prayers
High likelihood of being a popular game popularity
Not essential he wasn't even thinking that cuz he wasn't thinking oh this is a game that I will release it was almost like a thought
Experiment right in his brain where he's thinking
You know usually people come into a game trying to solve it
And I wonder how if I can make this game where they couldn't they would understand me
How I feel right now
I want to make a game about that day that Joel is dehydrated in the hospital
Facebook terrible that's not a game and no I don't want to play that like
Think of that word game men like
Something you do in your leisure time
You know and so who wants to spend their Leisure Time
Reliving the worst moment of a man's life so I said do not make that
That is horrible
He come to the idea so finally Amy said okay I'll give you 3 months
So
A few months later it's the game developers conference in San Francisco
Alongside Assassin's Creed 3
Battlefield 4 the new Oculus Rift VR headset
Hi everybody my name is Ryan
Bear
Was Ryan
My son Joel had just turned one-year-old the day that we found the monster in his brain
Ryan is standing in front of
A bunch of young Tech dudes
You're listening
Half-heartedly
Joel is alive and fighting his eighth tumor are doctors fight for him our family fights for him
And we serve a God that's the god of the living not the dead in the middle of all this pain and suffering and mud in her ass
The cancer is right in our family we have a drink of water
That's made of hope and love and light and we hope to share it with
Amy stayed home
Reading because
They were almost out of money and she was worried that Ryan would come home
Feeling crushed
But that's not what happened
Ryan got back and said it was amazing
This person introduced me to that person that person is just in that one there's two or three different people
Who want to fund my game market for a game like this but different
So I want to be clear it
The world of these kinds of emotional games it's a small one
But
There are people there investors in there who are looking for games
They're doing something different
Meaningful in some way
And so I think a few of them
Wade through the scene this dehydration scene
And they thought
Okay let's let's let's see what a full-fledged version of this will be
End
We're just
It's like a video game generation has grown up right like if you were born in the 80s
The seventies
But you played games for certain reasons when you're a kid and now we're grown up and we're having these different experiences like I'm child going through
Cancer
You know the death of my father or
These things which suddenly you're like
Why can't I tell the stories with video game
And what was Amy's reaction when she heard people wanted to fund the game
Because of your dehydration game that I told you to never make and he realizes like
You never played it like you never play this mean
So I put on the headphones
She finds herself
Back in the house
You don't see Joe
You see an empty crib and you can hear him cry
You're playing as Ryan
Move your mouse around the screen
And options
Appear
You can give him choose you can try to bounce him you can
Walking to the bathroom
Look at the window but no matter what
You do
Trying to fix worse and worse hold you please
Stop
After five or six minutes of this
Brian sits in a chair
Drops his head into a glass
And praise still here
And then
The crying stops
So I put on the headphones
And I just lost it and I was just
Is crying and crying and I knew Joel was okay and he was like right there like Jones right there with us and
And yet
Brought me back to that space in a much
More
Real way that I thought that a video game
Amy didn't need any more convincing she said okay let's do this
Pull the rest of our savings and make this game
They named it that Dragon cancer
I'm just use the same teas that reply all using their podcast coming up
Ryan and Amy encounter what might be the world's biggest design problem
This is Riley Lawrence from Woodland Hills California
Radiolab
Is supported in part by the Alfred
Stone foundation
Enhancing public understanding
Science and technology in the
Modern world
More information about
Sloan
Wwd
You. Sloan.
I hate everybody Pat Walters here I'm a producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers were looking for stories
About what we're calling tiny moments of Brilliance basically I want to hear about those two
So did something
It just means you lean back and say whoa how did they do that maybe it was the moment that I can
Kid you've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons and you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed they're ready music in the margin of their geometry homework were interested in the
Epic moments where a kid does something super smart but doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story please share it with us and go to radiolab.org Brilliance and record
Short audio message for us
And that's radiolab.org Brilliance thank you so much
Hey I'm Jared I'm run I'm Robert Provost Radiolab and we are back with again reply-all story it's about
A couple who have a key
Who's fighting cancer
And the mom and dad have decided to express the experiences there going through interval things a video
You're so Amy and Ryan and their 6-person team they begin to build the scenes of the games
Surreal
Vignette
Were you the player
You take on different characters and every senior
Job Your Role basically is to
Can you take care of baby Joel
Let's not go back to
The peace and two swords
The first scene is at the pond
You start off as a duck
You paddle two words a little boy it's Joel
Or the origami version of him
He doesn't have eyes or mouth but he has a voice
And that is actually Joel's laugh
As you hand them pieces of bread
A throws them in Stillwater
I know you try
Goldilocks 5-light
Yeah kid speaking Heroes Isaac Jones brother
But you can't talk
True
Do you want to talk
Nano
Don't got sick right after eating one
Volume down a little bit buddy
There's other vignettes
Like
There's one time in a hospital when to keep juul entertained
Ryan blew up surgical gloves like balloons it's this for Justine where you see Joel
Loading into the nighttime sky towards the moon holding on to these
Surgical balloons
And then you see these black birds appear from the corner
Doctor cancer
And a pop the balloons on my one
And throughout these scenes
You play Minigames you discover rooms listen to voicemails from Annie there's even little levels you can beat
But the cancer is always around the edges of this world
Barney and black
I'm Creepin in
At one point you'll arrive here
The waiting room where doctors tell Amy and Ryan the jewels cancer is terminal as they break the news
Rain start pouring into the room
And Ryan slowly starts to slip under the water
Monday
We're very good at 8
We're very good at managing cake and masking symptoms at the end
Just jumping one second we asked Rudy so as Ryan and Amy and the team were crafting these scenes
What was happening with Joel
She says what happened
Surprised
Thing that happened was
That tumor where you know the doctor said listen he's terminal
Going to be over soon
The radio
And it goes away
And then a few months later
He gets another tumor
The radiator
I goes away and then this happens again and again and again
And so
He's two years old he's three years old he's four years old he's doing things that the doctors never thought he would do
Bucky Turn 2 and 1/2 and said his first word
Num num
He starts to swallow again
Don't shut the food
Starts
When he's three
He just became this miracle baby somebody in their church that they had a vision
Women in the church told her that she had a vision that Joel would do great things
Another reason they wanted to make this eventual is because they felt as if
He has Christians they were living a miracle
And they wanted to share this with people and show them
And then
A doctor calls a man and he says listen
Joe has a new tumor
The steamer is different
It's in a place that we've already radiated explain to us
That cannot continue to radiate an area too much what can cause brain death
And it was right
On
The brainstem
The doctors say we're not going to radiator
And then what happened
Is condition
Like very rapidly deteriorated
Having more trouble breathing can't swallow again a lot of the things that he was able to do like walk and
B stops
And so
Bay invite their entire church Community to come to their house in
Pray we had a prayer night just praying for him to be healed and
We just had everyone over and we spent hours just worshiping and praying this video footage of the snow
It's in there small living room there's family members friends people from their Church community
Ryan is holding jaw and they're praying
What we have is death here on this Earth
That's all we have
The only hope we have is your Resurrection.
Why would hope
All I have is my disappointment
That's what I start with
But I have hope that that you can fill my disappointment that you make it right that you redeem it
Yes
What's your strongest memory from
I think it's just realizing that he was gone
It's that space of being with a bunch of people that
Desperately want the same thing that you willing are crying out
For that Grace in that Mercy to convey the situation
Joel died later that night it was March 3rd
13 2014 because we were believing that he would be healed and because we were believing even if he died
I maybe should be raised from the dead like
Which is my cousin weird and I don't get that is weird but because
We still believe that he could live I feel like we didn't
Go through all the processes of getting ready for him
To Die the way that maybe you would
If you are certain that this
So at this point
Undertale sweetie tells us well they had to finish the game
Lemonade invested in enormous amount of
Diamond heart
Talent in building this game
But now
The facts of change
It started as a game that was supposed to be about
Experience of
Fighting cancer but also the experience of
Try and think of her
It can't be that game anymore
Like what do you do as
Game designers
Parents
How do you finish a game where you don't have many choices
And you can't win
It fits part as we're talking with treated me so visual
She just
Sat down and walked us through as descriptively as she could
How Ryan Amy Ryan
Try to solve this design bra
The end of the game
North Shore but it was basically going to be a two-part scene
Where there's the moment of his death
Yeah and they weren't sure how to
Do that
There's a moment of his death and right after that a moment where he goes
I have an essentially there was this little Island
And so
Ryan sucks about making
The scene of his death
It starts off
Pretty simple
In a hospital there's
Little Jaws sitting on a green chair
And there's some tubes of this neon fluid feeding into him
And there's pipes
All that rise up above him Witcher like pipe organ pipes and there was a little bit game play where you can play the pipe organ anyway
And then after that
He said
This isn't this isn't enough
This is the scene where
My son dies and so it must be
Just like
Epic
And so he creates this almost european-style like oversized
Cathedral where you know the walls are soaring up in the
Ceilings are intricate and contain all these different
Like
Bod
It's almost as if he's coating Joel's body into the architecture so he is
You know pieces that look like ribs and there's this part that looks like it's heart I can show you guys this picture is its
Sound Transit Howard told your laptop to the glass
I just quickly want to show you this
That's amazing
Is so
Pretty
I was not prepared for the
Who TF is very intricate interlacing arches
Light cascading down.
Catacombs on stained glass
He's very ornate ceilings and sweets. The building that
And it's beautiful and it just gets bigger and bigger and then suddenly feels like you know this is too light and
So then the cathedral becomes a place of darkness and all the lights are neon
Oh so now it's very
Does trees growing into the
Cathedral now that's the cancer
And then he's in the space and he's like so what should people be able to
Doing the space we have all the scene of these tubes and things
Fruit for chemo
I want to put in the machines that we're keeping Joel alive so we were feeding him
With these nutrition IV things we had
Oxygen tanks
And we trust building actual equipment
That the user would have to like
Fiddle with the levers and you know make things just right so that the jewels getting what he needs to stay alive
Does anything
Oh well if they do it wrong then they'll feel as if Joel
Died because of them and that's terrible
Enter Then he says you know what's crap this whole thing
Shruti showed us maybe sixty different sketches
A different iterations of a
Cathedral that were all
Super detailed in a kind of Terry Gilliam on steroids sort away
My friend since there is one sketchware
Ryan head head head head built an entire
Amusement park in the cathedral
And that was supposed to represent all of Joel's favorite things
Now it's all there just like too much stuff it's distracting so then he takes up the whole
Amusement park
And then he puts in
These prayer candles
He's like you know really what I want people to take away is this feeling I had
On the last night of Joel's life
Where
All you can do now is pray
And so you like one of these candles and you hear a prayer from that night
Boys Life returned to him to not let you go and let
And it's been hard I can for both of us to get to a place where we say
It can't say all the things
The cathedral
Can't say all the things we wanted to say just had to cook something else in the game cuz we couldn't finish it
And it's hard cuz you just want to never finish it and make it as beautiful as possible
And I don't know like there's part of it feels like we've betrayed a project by finishing it and by saying it can only be
But of course
They have to finish it
There's investors
There's a release date was disappointing to me
Is how quickly it fades
Dole how did how the memories in the
The person of dulfersitz because he
Start here he's a
He becomes more and more an idea
This
This game is not him it's just an echo of him it's not
It's not even the best echo of him
I think that's the thing that I'm struggling with
As we as we're approaching the end of this
Do all this
Or why it why is it that
Why do we do this
The game is coming out mid January
The cathedral to Ryan will always be
Unfinished
Can you show me the last scene with app
Ryan was able to finish the place that comes right after the cathedral
It's the scene where you say goodbye to Joel
You find yourself in a boat
Next to Joel
There's no oars
You're headed towards an island
You got there
You walk along a small path and you end up in a clearing in the woods
There's a picnic blanket
Angel sitting on it
I'll remember you
Related to
I'm glad you're here
I love it here
I bet you would like it too
And around him all the things he loves about
Pancakes
A huge stack of pancakes way way bigger than him
A little dog
Bubbles
You can call him bubbles
What I can catch one
Simplytoimpress long as you want
Okay
Occasional
Heavy metal
And you just keep blowing bubbles
And at some point
What I can catch one
You just walk away
Maggie's dad catch a bubble like to buy them
I love my Bible
The ground that's the choice you get in the end at the end of this game is to not stop
Kevin lyttle
Budget
Very big thanks to Shruti peed in a mini and the whole team reply all PJ Vogt
Alex Goldman
And
Producer Tim Howard
The abandoned kalila Holt Peter Clowney
First editor and Raekwon
And definitely go check out reply-all you can find them at gimlet media. Com gimlet gima
Keep yourself is so fun is it
Poncho
He did with ladies that we wear on us
On stage with Eminem
Anything
And I we thought we were going to go good with all your good and they were so much better than they were so much better
They had this such a good story
I think it actually might be coming up in their stream next week maybe
Yeah you want to check it out it's about a woman who shoots everybody every night for over and over and over and over
And she's like well I want to go to the
Also thanks to David asset and to Malika zuheily Worrell
Who made a documentary also about Ryan Amy
They called are
Thank you for
Playing
Thank you for listening and chine up and run by Robert krulwich
We'll see you next time new messages to play the message
Presstube
Hey hey Radiolab for the year
Freedom Credit
Radiolab is produced by Dada perm rod
The staff includes Brenna Farrell David Gable
Not guilty Robert krulwich and emails Ortiz Nasser Kelsey Padgett
Webster's Barn wheeler and Jamie York
What help from Simon Adler Alexandra Lee Young Abigail kill Stephanie town and
Michael
Lone Ranger
A fact Checkers are Ava Dasher and Michelle Harris by guys
And this message