Hey this is Jack before we start let me tell you about
About a week ago we
Sent out a message
To the database
People
Subscribers Radiolab newsletter and who our new contributors to Radiolab
We are we sent a message
That list of people
He said
Sort out of the blue we said hey here's a number to call
If you're willing
Gosip today
Tell us a couple things first who are you I'm Fiona it is 4:20 here in
California where are you in the world
Houston Texas
Terminate Nashville Tennessee Narragansett Rhode Island Davidson North Carolina
Kansas City Missouri Chicago
Massachusetts is kind of amazing and it's just a short. Time we had almost a thousand calls from all over the world
World end
One of the questions we sprung on peep
Was
On this particular day I think it was December 11th
What are you grateful for
Tilling grateful for my children if no one crying
Delta by Mumford today where you felt
Grateful
For something I felt grateful
I woke up and it was raining
Went to pick up my son from daycare
It's Always Alright
Special moment when I
Pick him up and he sees me and he's happy
Today a moment where I felt grateful
It was a hard day
And when I got home
I just
Pride and
My husband help me
I feel really grateful.
I have somebody who loves me that way the moment that I felt gratitude
A little something different in my hair
And my coworker
First thing this morning it was so
Sweet of her to notice
Great father day because my step dad is still alive and seeming to be recovering and
That is one of the best
Things I can say about today because it's been a really long hard week I'm on it when I felt grateful today
Sally's driving home tonight
On the interstate on a clear night
And listening to podcast
Stop by the store
Let me tell you what I'm grateful for
I'm grateful that I get to do this work
With this incredible team best team in journalist
They literally pay the salaries of when you donate
Did we get to make these stories that I hope
Move you make you think differently about the world maybe even make you feel grateful
That describes you in any way we need to hear from you
We need to hear it that you want more of this
And the way that you got a lot of snow is by donating of course in fact
We need 4000 people to step up for January 1st
So that we can have the money we need to fund Radiolab into 2019 anyone who does that
Any of the four thousand of you who I hope will do that
Will get a special gift from us
Beautiful set of cards with beautiful
Fart
Onnit that commemorates a lot of the stories we had on Radiolab in 2018
The small way that we can say how grateful we are to you
For helping us do this
Go to radiolab.org
Click that donate button or just text the word Radiolab to 70101
That's the Radiolab to 70101
Take just a minute and it's a choice only you can make
So make it
Are you awake
Listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
Here Wego I'm Jared I'm Robert krulwich this is Radio 11 today we are
Sorry Millie
Play Sorry exactly
For more on that here is producer animation
Hello I how did you get into all this
A good question as you know I'm not
One of you I am Canadian
So many very radio
That's right we are invading
And you know I moved to the states that you know a few years ago and you know when you go to new place and you able to
Turn around and look back at the old place and you kind of see it with Clarity Clarity of distant that's right
And there was this one moment that happened about a month after I got to America that just
Turn off the mini butter doesn't really
Rumi
What was
Will let me set up for you so it's so it's
May 18th 2016
George be open the Speaker of the House
Order
Alarm
Kohl's the session into order
Cuz in the house that day
They're going to vote on a bill
So the speaker Rings is electric bill that let everyone know it's time to vote and as is Canadian tradition
Do people notice
Walk up the aisle and then it is kind of bow and then the voting can begin
But for this particular approach the liberal whip guess the front and he turns it was right and he did not see that
Gordon Brown
He's like where is this man and he turns left behind me see is a Gordon Brown has tried his very best
To make his way to the front of the house
But he is stuck
And you stuck because
There is a clump
Of MPS
They're standing in his way
Purposefully or just accidentally I think it's debated but I would say very confidently that it was extremely
Purposeful
They're pretending they don't see him and they're using their little their butts like shuffling their butt and you can see he's like dodging this way
Ellen scaring that way and then it's kind of complicated
Basically we have
3 minutes we have a deadline
Sears washing machine
It's ridiculous and I sort of hate everything
And then you see the front of the room this figure
Stance
All
Dressing a three piece suit
Fittingly handsome very nice hair
Disfigure strides towards this Clump get three piece suit flapping open
The cowlick of his hair moving in the breeze of his own motion
Justin Trudeau playing games on the road
He pushes his way
Through this collection of people and in this moment I am cheering for Trudeau yes you are
You're making government happened get the vote done
So Trudeau grabs Gordon Brown by the arm
But in doing so he elbows
This woman doesn't see behind them in Cebu
Yeah
Did she go with some pain she grabs her chest and she has to leave and sitting
And collect yourself
Trudeau sees none of this
And I at East riding up yellow bile with little Gordon until there is a
Chaos
Erupting in house Trudeau turns around
Can you learn you just elbowed this woman in the chest and you can see he's got this mortified look on his face he buttons
Three-piece cutie strides after her called it something like I'm sorry I'm sorry I didn't see you I didn't see you
She's gone though at this point one of the other members does beckoning
Jim how could you ever loved a woman that's pathetic
You're pathetic really ridiculous
Speakers like Bose order order order
Order
Order members will.
Amber Silver Strand themselves
So is it down
Order to the Prime Minister Rising on this serious matter
I admit I came I in physical contact
Number of members as I extended my arm in
Including
At someone behind me who I did not say apologize again
Anyone feel that they were
Impacted by my actions I
Completely apologize I was not my intention to hurt anyone and certainly wasn't
This down his whole side of the room stands up give him a standing ovation but for the opposition the people
Other side of the aisle
This is not good enough
Across the floor
With anger fear in his eyes and face member after member rise from their seats to school
Add my testimonies are the conservatives thinking with Glee
I would use the word charge
Across the floor Whittington people of clutching their pearls with the light Justin is not the perfect
Perfect man that we all thought he was
Someone accused of making it unsafe place for women to work
Best made of steel
Eventually
I was remembering question
The woman who was elbowed Ruth Ellen brosseau she returns and she speaks
I was elbowed in the chest
By the primary
It was very overwhelming
I just wanted to clarify and make sure it's clear to all the members in the house if that did happen
At which points Trudeau again stands up and says what I think is a pretty nice apologies
Take the opportunity at now that the member
It is okay to return to the house right now to be able to express directly to her
Apologies
Up for my behavior unreservedly
He says what he did he says it was wrong
And he says
I'm very sorry
Thank you mister speaker
We got the idea now he said it three times
Will you think so
Right
Something that can be cured by a simple apology
But that wasn't the case that night at a press conference
And indeed I'm going to apologize again for incident in the house
This evening he does it again
And for that I truly regret that at this point the media is going crazy about it
Day of atonement
#elbow elbow Gates
Trudeau got on social media added apologetic tweet
Just in case but even then we're still not done because the next day back in the House of Commons
He apologizes again
I apologize for crossing the floor in his attempt
Take a seat
And again
Against
Apologizing and again
I regret it
Deeply
I made a mistake and
Again
Canadian
Understanding and
I think at this point when I was learning about these I was just like okay
I just I just feel like I guess I just feel like
This posturing end
Volume like for Canada it's not just about
Elbow thing
Feel like every month Trudeau is apologizing to one group or another that has been harmed in the past by Cannon
And you know I should say that actually think he's apologies are very helpful and I think it's very important but you get to a point where they just
Start to pile up and I so I guess like what I'm seeing Alba gate
I'm noticing elbowgate I'm thinking about all of this
Attending to come here
Do America where where we have this President Donald Trump tonight he's refusing
To apologize for anything
Is there anybody you'd like to apologize to know
Funny weird things
Give me a moment in that tiny tiny moment the contrast was
Refreshing
What colloquial
At least I know where you stand that's so funny because as you're telling the story about Canada on the apology is none like
Oh my God I would
We haven't apologized in this country for some really wrong stuff that I'm not down
Not apologizing for stuff but then again we had one too many glasses of wine and we are so
Sorry
Show me the days are just like nothing says sorry like free pizza story not story
Sorry if you felt hurt I'm sorry if I offended you if you're not real
Broken
Sorry
Yeah
And I guess I could
Found myself getting to this whole thing about like
How to figure out first of all
How did it get broken how to re break it
End
What can we do to get it back
Yeah well maybe it
It might be worth our time to back up a little bit to get aware that notion of I'm sorry and apologies come from
And what they are because take me back
I'm the chair of the floss department at the University of New Hampshire
He's an expert in the history and philosophy of contrition
We got these
Ancient traditions
Usually grounded and some kind of religious
Practice
Pretty much all the world religions have some kind of repentance
Tencent
Turn to God never again
You do something wrong and wrong is identified by you know whatever the holy book say whatever and you say there are some
There's some things you need to do that kind of make it right
Admit to regret to ask for forgiveness than to promise never to do it again
Ain't no repentance is the term that
Is around for most of the history of apologizing and when you think of it in those
Explicitly religious terms you kind of get a sense for the
Full thickness of it because you're talking about like
Your soul
And the afterlife
And you're standing
Before the gods and not just the person you injured right this is
Soul crafting
As we enter
Modern secular
Industrialized living
And as we try to find a way to to do something like repentance
In a secular terms we end up with this
Weird modern soup
Of apology
So Nick says overtime as we started letting go of he's like explicitly religious rules around apology
Sori sort of started to shift
And fuse
In that context is everything alright so what
In Modern Life do we mean
Alright what's a good apology what do we mean by apologies
This is going to be super complicated
Like when we've been hurt
To buy someone
What is it we actually want
And as I was looking around for stories about the role of apologies our lives today
I found
A moment that feels to me like
I like almost sort of inflection points
In a Reckoning with the meaning of
I'm sorry
Inserts oddly enough
With this guy
Hello
Hello are you there
Yep I'm here
Yep
I'm here
Hello
Hi there
Can you hear me
Governor Dukakis
Hello hi
Don't like Michael Dukakis that's who that is
What
Know who Mike Dukakis was before doing a story I had no idea
Olympia Dukakis his cousin before God
React
That's okay
Let me get it give you a tiny little background
I was actually calling him about something that it happens like a couple years
Before he ran for president that was a long time ago and it's not that I'm losing my memory book that was a long time ago
When you've had a pretty eventful life so I wasn't sure whether or not this was the most
Memorable
Moment
Just watching yeah yeah this might have been the second most yeah
So back in 1986 he was governor of Massachusetts and he had a bill sitting on his desk
Window design
Do you remember this
I do indeed
That was the day before Christmas the 24th of December so the bill itself
It had a lot to do with a state senator today bill saltonstall
Did I know Bill songs not personal oh yeah oh yeah we work closely together bill was a very pretty
Progressive Republican
One of us decent people I'd ever
Beto work with in politics
And
I can tell you he was suffering
Terribly he and his
Wife and family
Yeah
I
I never really knew
Exactly what happened I mean I would prefer to pick up Snippets and try to
Imagine what happened
This is Abigail saltonstall send your bill saltonstall as youngest daughter you know we weren't a family that talked
About the circumstances
In detail
But I'll see I was 12
Older sister Clara just had a birthday she had just turned 16 to what
White athletic long hair blue eyes and she has asked permission to bike down to Woods Hole
With the boyfriend
There's going to be a long ride like 70 some miles but for clear that really wasn't that big of an ass
She used to Bicycle to school
You know like
10 miles
And stop at the beach and when it was really cold and swim with her friend and then go to school
She was adventurous and she did love
2 bike
And I am not sure where they started I am
Thinking maybe somewhere near Boston
Did you call
Bikes for a couple of hours
The bike ride from Sherwood
Exciting in
It Adventure but
They had got turned onto a wrong road
And I mean he got luck
And
My understanding of what happened over biking down the road on the shoulder there were two cars that were
Maybe
Maybe playing chicken maybe racing I'm not really sure
But the cars
One of them
Look into the breakdown Lane and just
Took out my sister
And she died
It's always awful
Who is awful
Do you remember where you were when you heard about your sister's death
Yeah I was at
A friend's house
And then my father called and told me what happened
How I found out
Well over the phone
Dad over the phone
Yes
To lose a daughter in on the prime of Life 16 years evasion
Although circumstances
So tragic
Can you can imagine
Billava Sleepless
Was devastated
Eventually the song Sail found out who the driver was this 19 year old guy
And the publisher of taking him to court
And one
Easily
My memory
Is that my family did not press charges
My father says
That he didn't see a reason to ruin to life
But what he did at some level want
Was was just for this guy to reach out to the family
Who caused her death
To say
To say that they were sorry
But he never contacted them so I never knew
Weather person thought
And some point
My father told me that he that he thought that that was
Because they
The law
That's right the driver is afraid of the legal implications of an apology
This is Lisa Lisa
He's a lawyer and a graduate of Harvard Divinity School
And he says that
At that point pretty much across the entire
Tire us
The general rule of law was that if I run a red light
Can I get out of my car and I sent any I'm so sorry it was entirely my fault I was not paying attention I was talking on my
My cell phone
You can use
Mike
Apology
To establish that I caused the accident
So you're Humane empathic reflexes might steer you towards you know saying you're sorry
It was my fault I wasn't looking or I was wiping my kid's nose or something
But
The takeaway is wait don't do that
Because if you
In that moment
Apologize
American Seating
But that you deserve the blame
In other words in the eyes of the Court apology is an admission
And don't sell thought maybe the driver of a car isn't apologizing because he's afraid that would use it against them in court
So we figured was Rectify this situation
Let's just change the law which brings us back.
It was in response to that
Not Bill sitting on Governor Dukakis
It was
Designed to make it possible for people to apologize
Without implicating them
As guilty party
I'm sorry that story cannot be used against you in court
Which only makes sense to me and I think made sense just about everybody and I don't think they had much difficulty in getting through those
Unanimous
Too close to it
And so December 24th 1986 Massachusetts passed the first
Apology legislation
Creating For the First Time the song window that allowed two people to just
Do people enjoy I'm sorry
Without any legal consequence
Do you have any sense of
Whether or not that measures had any effect did you do you hear of it coming up
I honestly don't know
I don't know
I mean I don't know
You know the person even after the law was passed did not apologize
So it didn't accomplish that
Specific goal
I actually found and reached out to the driver
And through his son he declined to comment for the
Story
So didn't work
I never got their apology
Well at me for Abigail and her family know
But what I dug in the history of this
A bit what became clear was it this
Little drop
Of legislation
Created some ripples that are still spreading today
Because it is wake
Other dates
Start to pass legislation
But in the late 90s
The I'm sorry Bill and then in the early 2000 you see a big
First this is Jennifer ravenel's professor of law in Psycho
Ecology at the University of Illinois
According to her one after another states started passing these kinds of rules
Nebraska Colorado does organized
Dakota Tennessee plate variations from state-to-state but by 2012
Of the states that passed one of these laws
Making it okay to say I'm sorry
But now you know that you're saying it without having to
To pay the consequences
You feel like that make it less real to say sorry yes that's
That's
That's not apologizing
What if you don't say you're sorry because you feel like that I'm going to sue you
Until you say nothing
But isn't it better to have
Sorry at least come out even if the sorry little bit less with sorry that point yeah so that's the rub
Write give on the one hand what you want is a mechanism to
Encourage
Good apologies
On the other hand
You know what wait a minute
An apology tells us that this person is responsible if they are responsible than
You know perhaps
One of the things that comes with that is responsibility to
Repair the harm
Yeah this is
This is a real double-edged sword
Because
If you're a sophisticated
Offender
You can manipulate the
Against victims to great effect
Think of it like this
You've suffered a serious injury
Imagine like you be like you wants to tile
Nick says what happens
Is that the people responsible for that death may be accompanied by a lawyer what they do is they show up at your house
Sit down at your table and express
Something that looks like
Like a really deep
Profound
Soul moving
Apology that
They're really sorry for what happened and they take responsibility for it and they admit blame
And honest
But nix's often times has a combination of loitering
Enacting
Because
Once you express enough sympathy than you
You make an offer
And you know you lowball
So victims think they're getting something like a heartfelt repentance or something like that new Fender
When facts negotiation negotiation dressed up as an apology
How do you know that that's the line of thinking I've been in the other rooms
You know where the strategies are
Being discussed of the apologizes
Yes
And Nick says overtime lawyers have realized by going to people's homes
Listening sympathetically
And offering amount
This is way more cost
In fact
One of the major supporters behind that
Groundswell of apology laws in America for lobbyist
A lobbyists
Who advocate for
Corporate interests who seek
To reduce
Liability for Harms
Really
So sorry got weaponized
Yeah particularly by Corporation
Nick says in the early 90s
Also
Sorts of
Industries
Started apologizing as a tactic
Tell me about one company he said he'd
In eight years they save 75 million
S*** and
If you want to follow the money that it's pretty easy to follow the money here
I'm suddenly
Who suddenly starting to argue the other side of my head which is
Isn't isn't a fundamental aspect in an apology like you're making yourself
Smaller or vulnerable to the person you're apologizing to
Not legal repercussions I hate that the laws involved but it is
And they're doing it for their own Financial benefit
Then
They're not actually making themselves vulnerable to the person
And so the
The apology is robbed of something essential Maybe
Yeah
I don't know that IMAX imagine if your corporation
You can stay
It's still a human woman
Be even then you don't even if it seems like you're going well you never know
I don't know
Like that is the thing it all comes down to you when they say they're sorry
Do they mean it
And usually can't really judge someone's apology until like years later
And actually Nick told me a story that really drive this point home so this is a really interesting example
So
So it's 1076 where in medieval Europe Henry the fourth is
The Holy Roman Emperor
And Gregory 1/7
Is
Hope you love the most powerful people on the planet
And at some point the emperor goes behind the folks back
And appoints a bishop
The pope takes particular issue with disappointment
So what the pope does
Is excommunicates the emperor
Which means that
I mean he's not really the emperor anymore because the pope has just said he's not part of the church anymore
Really bad news
Violence is breaking out people are demanding he step down
The emperor does Henry
Henry takes a walk
Lacrosse
The Alps
With his wife
And small child and I know who else is in there their Entourage
Edison winter
It's bitterly cold they March for days and days which are in two weeks
The week
Through snowy valleys across icy rivers and because he's been excommunicated there
He can't go so they have to make take like the most dangerous mode
Approach
Across the aisle
And then finally after months of travel
He arrives
And it's some sort of Castle he arrives at where the Pope
Is staying but
The Pope
Refuses the emperor entry
It is allegedly snowing and something like a blizzard
Standing at the gates of this gas at the gates
In a blizzard
In a blizzard with his wife and small child
He stands there
3 days
Fasting
And the eight I decided to use there's my paintings of this and he's
He said to have taken a penitent posture
Start again
The bottling position in a sentence feeling he's wearing a hair shirt
Which is traditionally associated with repentance and supposed to be painful and
It said that all his family take off their shoes in the snow
It's about the pope as watching this
From the castle from his nice toasty Council
And of course we have to keep in mind right that
And there are long traditions
Within
Christianity
We must forgive
So after 3 days
Of watching this
Republic
The emperor and his Entourage in they reconcile Henry's back in are you back in the church
Apology accepted okay so then that's a very good apology I got to say
Story's not over
Barefoot in the snow the family
Also using his kid this is I want to warn against the temptation to judge apologies in the moment they're given because now I would have
Queso dampers
Races back home
Civil Wars I breaking out
The emperor
Wednesday Civil Wars and drives out
And replaces him
What does own guy
So
What do we actually make of The Emperor's apology
He did something very
Dramatic
And spectacular
Restore his power
That he then used
To destroy the person he was apologizing to
When was God thought of all this
Psycho brother
Matt idle
I feel like I'm never going to trust and another apology again
Butts
Let's take a little break
I'm working take a little break and when you come back
I know I guess I feel like I've got an apology that
Despite
Being at the very center of all this competing stuff even talking about modern corporate legal secular
Stuff
I don't know
It doesn't mean that I really didn't expect
I will be right back
This is Melissa Gutierrez in Evergreen Colorado
Radiolab
Supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan foundation and Hanson public understanding of Science and Technology in the mod
Modern world more information about Sloan at www.slha.org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
About what we're calling
Tiny moments of brilliance
Basically I want to hear about those times when I kids you know did something
It just means you bring back and say whoa how did they do that maybe it was the moment that I can
Kid you've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of their musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed are ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the
Epic moments where
A kid does something super smart but doesn't have anything to do with the test
If you have a story with us
Go to radiolab.org brilliance
Record a short audio message for a
Again that's radiolab.org / brilliant
Thank you so much
And Jenna been Ron I'm Robert krulwich this
She is Radiolab and our still over so a mccuen talking about
Sarees
Hopefully rescuing it from The Quagmire in which you left us with that Pope thing
Kind of dark space and that's how I was in the psych muddy state of apologies what are we doing with this word
Then I stumbled across this
This one story and things that started to shift
Hey Annie
I've got a microphone in my front of my face so fun the lucky
How much does an ice cream cone or something
Doppia
Is Leilani Schweitzer
Right or a shot of tequila right now in 2003
Leilani was living in Reno Nevada
Json
Name Gabriel he was born on December 21st
I remember it
Knowing and like looking out the window of the nursery and
Christmas was playing on the radio in there
Just like the one and just thinking like
What has happened here
When Gabriel was born the doctors had learned that there was something wrong with it
Brain
But they didn't know what yet
I remember I got to go home pretty quickly I don't think I stayed there even a day
And then I would go back
Can see him know so he had to stay there yeah they nearly had a brain bleed and so they've got to look at
What does kids
What did you do for Christmas
Do you celebrate Christmas
Did celebrate Christmas
You know what I hardly remember at all
After couple weeks Leilani was allowed to take him home
And for the first little while everything was pretty normal
Diapers
Long nights
Yep pretty normal baby days and then he ended up where he was diagnosed
With hydrocephalus when he was 4 month old hydrocephalus what it is basically it's
Fluid around the brain as someone says you can called water on them
When you hear your kid has hydrocephalus
What is that how do you envision that their future
I remember the neurosurgeon
And saying that he's never going to play football and he's never going to be drafted into the army
Which
Sounds great yes
Winning right
It's not that serious me not necessarily but the kids is hydrocephalus like
You know they have problems
Vision problems with balance
And after the single to shunt which is sort of a tube that acts like a siphon so it would drain off the excess flow
Fluid in his brain and drain it down into his belly
Wow and I could feel it like on the side of a
His neck and
He had a little tiny incision on his tummy where they
Hold it down
So the shunt it seemed to do the trick
Gabriel's doctors were so pleased with his progress that we went to have an ultrasound done and
The doctor told us
That
Our baby
Had
The actress starred in a commercial with the local hospital
That was very sweet
Sweet commercial
We can help babies
Before they're born
Tiny little baby with a
Scrap of blond hair up being held by a laughing doctor
They've made
Feel like Celia Lonnie talking about her experience
Commercial actually ends with Gabriel
A huge smile on his face
Kind of kicking up his legs and and scooting across
Hospital logo baby
This is undeniably a very
Kit
She would let anyone hold him
His arms were always reaching out to people and so it wasn't unusual for him to get passed around
Making the line at the grocery store or
Seriously oh yeah because he did actually have problems with vision he would always put his hand on your face
Some kind of like turn your face
I don't know if he was doing that so if he
See you better or if he just kind of wanted that was just
It's a little
Like I'll touch you on your cheek and nuts
Great
Like my little sweet blessing I don't know but
He would do that and
And people would recognize him
And people would say oh he's the miracle baby and
I can't he is
When did you first notice that there was a
Problem
Thursday I remember is a Thursday Gabriel was 20 months old and I had been told
That if he started throwing up to take him to the emergency
State Department
And
He was throwing up alot
A lot he had no fever he didn't have diarrhea but he was throwing up alot to come to a nearby house
Hospital rejected the first of two hospitals that will play a role in this story but
Anyway when she got in there the rest of my fleet Haley took an x-ray and everything looked fine
So he ends up being hospitalized
Treated for stomach flu given anti-nausea medication
He was still really sleepy
And
I had a previously
We scheduled an appointment with the neurosurgeon on Monday afternoon this was
4 days later
I walked in and my mom was holding Gabriel and dr. Edwards
Takes one look at him
And he said why did no-one call me
What was he seeing
He just saw a really sleepy beautiful little
Sick baby immediately knew that something had gone wrong with the shunt
The fluid was building up and Gabriel's brain
And
Then it was
Bad
Leilani needed to get him to a specialist fast so she she put them in a car seat in the back of her car and drove all the way
Stanford
5 hours away
Yeah and he sounded like a little kitten
Kind of like
Mm Ewing like not really crying
But just
And I remember getting
Stuck on the Bay Bridge
And just wondering can the Navy Seals come rescue me I have this is a traffic jam near 2nd
Yeah
Cod
Did you make it to the hospital to check in and get a room
Finally Leilani just
Allows yourself
Take a breath so you were sitting in a chair that was like right next to his bed or you given enough
You were okay
Just like a regular one that would like
One of those turquoise blue naugahyde recliners you know like
You're sitting straight or your lying down
Gabriel's lying in bed
We were on the Telemetry unit so that means they're monitoring his heartbeat and is breathing really closely so we had
At the little monitors on him
He falls asleep
And so does she
But any time there would be any change in his breathing or his heart rate or any even little kind of
Twitch
These alarms on the monitors would just go off
Like I would wake him up and it would make
Be up to nurse would come in
Check him
Make sure everything's okay
Leave the room and
Just as they were settling back into sleep
This this kept happening over and over and over again
And so the nurse
When I think about her now I think of like a bird
Leica
Like a swallow one of those really like
Bass
Moving
Birds that's really Nimble and
And quick and can
Switch Direction
Really fast
Because she was
In and Out In and Out in and out
So much and now I know
But she was taking care of another really really sick little girl
And taking care of Gabriel and I at the same time
Sochi
She said I'm going to turn off the
The sound on the alarms
Understand turn the sound off
Thin hair which I
Really appreciated and I thank
Turf or that
Because I really wanted to go see
Sleep
So I fall asleep
And
And then the next thing I remember is she walks in and she grabs the foot of the recliner
With her left hand as she's walking past me and she's
Swings it around
And she said Leilani you have to get up
She could see the flat lines
On the monitor
Because his heart had stopped
Speeding
Then
Code blue is on the intercom and Q
Hooked to machines and he's not
Squeezing my hand and he doesn't
Feel warm and
And someone
Takes me out and I'm in the hallway and
You know I don't know I don't know if I thought about this
Later or if I thought about it in in the time you know how you go back and you
You're sure you remember something in the moment but I don't know that I remember this in
I remember just kind of this like him saying goodbye to me
At that time
Really
Yeah
What what do you mean
Kind of like
Like this gentle sort of
Like this is up to you now Mom
You know
I mean you're connected right it really connected
And when part of that connection
Is gone you feel that
Leilani says in the wake of Gabriel's death
She's all the regular things you do when someone dies
Therapy
And in her case
A lot of snowboarding
Snowboarding
Yeah
White snow and blue sky was
All that really could compute
But she said in those first few days and weeks
Following Gabriel's death
She just kept playing over and over in your mind
What went wrong what what happened at those two Hospital
Yeah
So the first hospital where Gabriel shunt failure was misdiagnosed as stomach
This is the hospital where
The nurses
Parents
The commercial was for this Hospital commercials just stopped
Wow
What is so then yeah what happened next
Nothing happened
She just basically heard nothing from them how did it feel when you were shut out like that
What made me really angry
It made me feel like they
Where did nine that Gabriel even existed or that his life had any importance at all
The fact that
He died
That
Wasn't enough reason for them to
To talk to me I just
It still makes me angry you know I wouldn't I would purposely drive around the house
Hospital I would not drive past it so I reached out to this hospital for comment and they act
Declines to get one so I can't be sure but part of the reason they made out of reach out to Leilani
Is because it's hospital is located in Nevada and Nevada is one of those states that
Does not have apology legislation
So you're not protected if you apologize
But California
Does have a lot
So under the California lot you can say things like
I'm sorry
I feel bad a bee cannot say I'm sorry it was
Our fault we made a mistake
That parking still be used against you in court
Brings us to the second house
Stanford
Reach out to me right away they invited her back to the hospital I had a lot of
Questions and I brought all of them I like print
It's about loud I had photos of Gabriel So at 2 months after Gabriel died
Leilani carrying these photos
Walked into Stanford
Do you remember what the expression on her face was
Just
Caprese chicken
This is Pam Wells you know you just
There's a look about people are crazy stricken
At the time and was head of nursing at Stanford
Not day she two doctors in a hospital administrator set down around a table with Leilani
The small table that could have said maybe eight people have you ever met her before
I've never met her before I really know what
My intention was but I do remember I said after you tell me everything you need to say to me I want
How to say some things to you and they said why don't you say what you have
To say first
I said I felt like I had been prepared to take care of a kid who had hydrocephalus she said on Gabriel and I arrived at Stanford
There was no one waiting for us there
Had to get checked in the neurosurgeon news on call should have seen Gabriel. Night. Come by
End
Just more generally
I trusted you guys I just needed to get in here right like I got him here now somebody else is going to make sure
Sure everything's okay
And that's not what happened
This was a critical moment for Stanford
It wasn't usual that time to meet with families after something that happened
For obvious reasons I mean if a doctor or a nurse said anything in that meeting that even remotely resembled admitting that they screwed up
That could be used against them in court
And so mostly hospital just avoided these meetings all together
But
Right around the time that Gabriel died bar Quality Inn
Bridge Department cabin talking to us about taking a different approach and approach that was actually led by Lee Taft
And the thinking was going to be open
Let's be transparent
Forget the law
And so after this
Is like moments after Leilani cerilles off all of her grievances
Pam
Looks are in the eye
And says
We are
Barry
Let me rephrase that
We are so sorry
This happened in this terrible thing happened
No family
Should ever go through
This kind of loss
Imperfectly not into Beast
Cancel
And we we really want
To be able to help you
And understand what you need from us
In order to help you
Navigate
Devastating event
Were committed
Not only
Answering your questions
We are
Only investigating what happened and
Want to make sure
That
We can put some things in place so that this
Never happens to another child or family
And they went
One step further
The situation that led to
Gabriel's death
Was
The
Gabriel is on a monitor the alarm skip
Going off
The nurse and the room turned the alarm off
Not
Knowing
That it turned off all the alarm
The nurse in the room that night
When she went to turn off the alarm next to Gabriel's bed to allow Leilani and Gabriel to sleep
She also accidentally turned off the alarm on a pager
And at the nurses
Station info
He wasn't being monitored any really needed to be monitored and subsequently
Something in our system contributed to this
Poor Boys.
In other words
We made a mistake
Stanford had just admitted that
Finally
I would have dancing around the issue at all and so with the head just done is
Give Leilani evidence
Evidence that she could
Take the court and use against them
If you want to do I know she was checking me out I know she was trying to understand
Whether she could
Trust me
There's no question in my mind that that was
Going through her head
And
I was doing whatever I could
Communicate that
Yes you can
I'm going to help you
I want to help you
I don't remember a lot of the words
But
I remember how I felt
Imagine like you you like you wants to tile
And the wrong door apologize
Read that can be
Almost like a religious
Moment
I mean really bad has happened to you in the offender is now in a way like
Humbly and vulnerably
Kneeling before
I felt that they listen
Tumi
And I felt that they genuinely cared about me and my family and about Gabriel
And I still feel that
Leilani accepted their apology
She never filed a suit
I should say that that Stanford did a lot more than just apologized they they reach out to other hospitals had this Monitor and
Alerted them of the problems or whatever
Mercante another kid
I'm in also the relationship between Pam and Leilani like
Remain very strong they still are in touch to this day
And all those things are important but
The thing is
Since Leilani is hot
Experience
Stanford and a few other hospitals to do this full disclosure thing
What they found
Time and time again is that people get an explanation and an apology they are far far less likely to see
And therefore those Hospital save
Money
A lot of money
And I guess you know you could think about it and so self-serving way
If it saves money to apologize
You know what is the motivation behind these apologies and humid in the circuit board room at Stanford somewhere with
These people in suits making decisions about whether or not they want their doctors and nurses to apologize
And the motivation behind that I guess
It makes you feel a little
Weird
But but when I asked leahlani about this
She just said like if money is a driving force
I don't care about it at all
I don't care
I don't care about the motivation I would love it
I would love it if
Human connection was the motivation
But I know that it's not
And the fact that this is
Makes good business sense
If that's what drives people
I will get on board
For me
I guess what happened between Leilani
And the doctors and the nurses at Stanford Hospital
I know the cops because I was I was working on this apology piece
Kipling I had to choose between music Bad apologies I was seeing or no apology.
Either of those are good
Or just trying to compare these like super corporate apologies to some sort of moment that the head deep meaning for the
Two people involved these humans faces
And I don't know I guess I guess what does Pam and Leilani apology
Just felt To Me lyrics
This new thing
New Way Forward
It certainly felt that way to Leilani and in fact
Several years after that meeting she became a Patient Liaison
Stanford
Her job is now to sit in that conference room
And do for others what Pam did
And the 20th and 21st century you got
Inhumanity from staring into the abyss
Of
Maybe there is no God and maybe this is all meaningless
You know there is a kind of searching for what are values
Do we have shared values
Are there values other than
The competition for money and resources
I'm what
What do we stand for
When it comes time to die like what
What did my life mean what values does it have
And this is an important like a process that like humanity is going through
And
It's like we're reaching back to these
Traditions of repentance
To try to find some shared ground
Like some shared even secular ground and the call to apologize is like no we have to
To share these values
These are the thing
That's going to hold us together
Nice work
I don't know I I don't know it's a good question but
Actually I think I
Feel like I am beginning to
You peel back the layers of this
Incredibly complicated country
Speaking of which
During my reporting actually stumbled
Upon this
Very very mad
Kerrigan
Little moment in history it's so so apparently during Michael Dukakis run for president
There's this looks very very negative ad campaign guy who got out of prison and this is one of these
Worst negative ads
Of all-time exit one of the first
And it and it I think it ended his campaign
Right there was a man running for president named George Bush
Lee Atwater was his campaign manager they put an ad on television
The television ad said look what's happening in America people are criminals are being released
On furlough and then they're doing terrible things in this case
Play Don to the Democrat Democrat
Sorry it was so unfair like they blamed Governor Dukakis
For essentially
Play causing the rape of the
This woman
When he didn't even create the program that allowed the guy to get out of
But that was created before him
But it was also
Obviously racist Romanian
Black guy attacking a white woman and so on so forth
I mean speaks for itself
So when I was talking to Governor Dukakis the sex
She came up that water was a tough guy
And he was an attacker
And he told me that Lee Atwater years later on his deathbed he decided he wanted to
Repent
Freddy's
Sins that he felt he had done in his life and one of those was making
Willie Horton ad
Really so we actually apologized what did he say
Publicly and
2 mi
Campaign manager
Ready
Regretted it
And what did that mean to you
Well I can't tell you that made me feel great cuz
You know I lost that race
And a lot of it had to do with at a camp
I never
Having
I didn't feel any better but looked at least he was wanting to do that
What does that mean when you say at least he was going to do that
Well I think you
At least it was one of those
Knowledge
Did was racist and he said sewing
And apologize for
That at least deserve some
Some fries but
Came a little late
Well any there's well we should I want to apologize to you
Really
I don't know what I've done but I
Something many things and okay
Okay vehicle
I would like to take you in for both reporting and producing this story with Simon Adler
Rather she reported it and then skip Simon and Annie produced it together
Thanks to Jim Seifert Carol Kelly Donna Bailey Marion Dupree Sarah Hillier
Hannah Chase Travis Sharp
And also special thanks to our ablove departing intern cats Laszlo how to finely a special special things
To Adele Urban who passed away while we were making this but who was of
Of great help to us in an important
Robert coach thanks for listening
Hide Sophia Summerhill I'm Leilani's daughter
Radiolab was created by job Adam rod and is produced by Soren wheeler
Dylan has a director of soundesign Maria matus r5000 is our managing director
Our staff includes finding Albert Becca Bressler Rachel Cusick David Campbell
Bethel happy
Tracy hunt
Mac eat me Robert krulwich any MacEwan Latif Nasser Melissa O'Donnell
Ariane wax
Cat wallpapers
And Molly Webster
With help from FEMA
OVI caps last Slow and Low acetabulum
And this message