Hey today we re podcasting a show with something extra and update
This show which we did a couple years back is called patient zero
Which took
I'll look at
The origins of things not surprisingly disease but also other things too
And you know you're all that
But I wanted to step in and say that in the middle of the show
We're going to slip from looking back at a disease that
Started way long time ago 2
Examining a disease that meow
I speak this happening right now
Irish senior editor sternwheeler will bring you that
Meantime here's the show
Are you awake
Radio WNYC
End NPR
So we said where we are
Starting as off today or are producers Lynn Levy and Sean Cole
Very pretty day to be on abandoned Island where
Victims of contagious disease were quarantined
And
One in particular
Lived here died here never believing that she was in fact
Sick
And dangerous
So this is a story that begins where it starts in 1906
It doesn't start on the island that starts in Oyster Bay
Nice neighbors very nice
There was this one rich
Family
On vacation there and their daughter
Get sick
Get sick for
This is Judy Levitt Ima
Professor emeritus at the University of Wisconsin
And she wrote a book about the story so basically the girl the daughter has a fever
Then her sister comes down with it
Their mom
The maid
About 6 out of 11 in the family get sick
And with this disease the fever
The first part of it both diarrhea or constipation or reported
So it can go either way I guess
What is it
Typhoid
And they couldn't figure out what could cause that
Did you see so they called in the sanitary engineer named George Soper with the public health department he was the go-to guy for outbreaks
Like this back in the Department of Public Health
Thinking you know what you get sick because of
Something dirty near you being in the well or in the pipe
Yeah so he looks into all of that
Did a hole
Test on the house in the water and everything couldn't find anything is so start stalking the family and he
He started quizzing them all and they
Eventually
He builds up this
Full picture
Of of
Several outbreaks
Going back year Mamaroneck
A New York family had a house for the store 1902 Dark Harbor Maine
Autumn 1906 winter 1907 New York City all these cases and they all had one thing in common
What eats
Of these families
Had employed the same
Cook
Which is
Funny
Because when you cook food
You kill the bacteria in the food
But this cook her most famous
Dish was Peach Melba
Which is ice cream and fresh peaches
Fresh peaches
Raw fruit
As a perfect medium and The Cook's name
Was Mary Mallon
Mary Mary Mary II charcoal
Typhoid Mary so we're talking about no you don't know this
Everybody thinks they know this
Story and then when I looked into the first thing about it and when you look into the details
They tell us some very difficult things about who we
War
And
You still are in a lot of ways it's all in the details all of the juice and problem like in like this like this
Like a peach
I remember college
This is Radiolab
And in this hour a series of stories
They're all here that delicious
Story
Archetype we call
Patient
Europe the first
Will try to trace
Ideas and Trends in massive
Social
Traumas like pandemic
Back to that one
Purse or one critter
For if you didn't have this thing but for this thing you wouldn't have the rest of those I like the butt for the butt for
But
Meanwhile back to the pizzas
So
George slippers like I've got to find this woman
And
When he finds her she's in New York
Looking for another family but water has had recently been taken to the Presbyterian hospital with typhoid fever this is from an article
Call Super Bowl called The Curious Case of Typhoid Mary lovely daughter
Was dying
So he goes to the house
Walks into the kitchen
Cease this women 5
Butt sex
Blonde hair
Blue eyes have a good figure and might have been called athletic had she not been a little too heavy Irish immigrant 36 years old
Told not particularly clean and he says Mary Mallon I think you are causing disease in people and
I want
Samples of your urine feces and blood
Good afternoon
And she says what are you accusing me of being sick
Play the role of Mary is Columbia Public Health
How dare you I'm not a sick person they should do
What racism out of the building
With a fork in her hand a serving Fork
A serving for you
I felt rather lucky to escape
But does she have type
Achieve
How would we have time
That's the thing
She never had any symptoms
She felt perfectly healthy
She was actually
The first
Documented case in North America
Of
A healthy carrier
Wishes to say someone who has the disease
Is and is contagious
But never
Actually feels
The symptoms of symptoms
In one weird way super
Real but he's only read about
And then here she is in front of them
But
Think of how all this must have sounded the Mary I mean some guy from outer space
Comes into your kitchen
And says your disease
And you're hurting people
Why do I feel fine I'm living a moral life I'm not a
Vagrant unemployed
I'm a good
Solid citizen
Be traced to what you eating today probably grab your knife
What does he have any evidence of the
She is spreading disease not yet that's why he needs
Poop
So he goes back
Find her at a rooming house
Amounts where it's at in and then the health department
This female doctor s Josephine Baker
Maybe she could ask for blood
PC said here in a little more jet I need to know how you ask her that she tries
And when it doesn't work she comes back a little bit later with cops and they come to the house and
Mary Mallon
When she realizes what's happening
Disappears
Flaming disappears
Completely vanishes
They end up
Searching the entire place
And I can't find her
Finally I think they're about to leave when one of them spots
Skirt at coming outside of a door
It's a little piece of calico
Kind of
Stuck in a
Doorway open the door in their shoes and so they dragged her out and she
Comes out kicking and screaming and
I get her the amulets of Josephine Baker sits on her according to her
It's on her and Baker later said something like it was like being in a cage with an angry lion
So they take her to the hospital they tested her feces and urine
And they found that yes she was in fact
A carrier
Of
Live typhoid
The weird Island that's been awhile on him
So they isolate her and they ultimately move her
From Manhattan to North brother Island
Have a good of a haunted by
And there she is
Thanks man
We went there to
Justed
How to get our heads around what
Must have
Thought
What was yelling like
And everything is
Wheatley overgrown it was really creepy
PP because it was in such
Dissolution yeah yeah
Be careful where you step and went in there all of these medical former medical building including a giant
Hospital where they isolated tuberculosis patients
Big brick
Stately building
None of the other side of the island
They're smaller
Wooden building
Crush
Maybe we're
Wearher
Cottage
Would be if it was still standing but it's not standing anymore
Well it was one room one room
I had a kitchen
Rattata
I guess it's sleeping area and a sitting area
It probably wasn't so bad
If you didn't have to
To stay there
You know any places that you're not free to leave
Becomes like a prison
So we're marching around and then lenses to me
Hey look at the view
And
Holy moly
It's right there
That's when it really hit me
If this is where her cabin was
Then one window of it
Looked exactly on to Manhattan
You could have seen where she
Used to live
You can see the
Traffic on the
Streets
This was like
The most horrible Seaside vacation
Almost the whole time they had her incarcerated
Did they took
Feces 3 times a week
Which is you know it's not pleasant to have to
Do that
And
Sometimes she was negative and sometimes she was Posse
Wait
What
That's that's another thing that they
Figuring out of the X 2
She was probably
An intermittent
What is that mean
The disease is always in her
But sometimes she excretes it and sometimes she doesn't
Of them has been confusing
When I first came here I was so nervous and almost prostrated with
Grief and trouble
My eyes begin
This is from a letter that Mary wrote
From the island I have in fact
Peep show
For everybody
But if you keep reading it and in fact is addressed to a lawyer it's clear that she was fighting this and she have been sending her
Her own feces samples herself
Do a private lab in Manhattan
And each one of those was an egg
Negative tuberculosis man would say
There she is
The kidnapped
Yeah that is poisonous
Shih Tzus the city
And losses
Still there all these questions as to whether any of this
Does legal mean even George super the guy who hunted her down said
It was contrary to the Constitution of the United States to hold her under the
How long was she on this island
3 years
And then
What changed
Was
New health commissioner
And so he says it's just not right that we keep a healthy woman locked
She was not dangerous to anybody if she didn't cook
He lets her go
Back to Manhattan
But he makes a promise she did promise you signed an affidavit saying
She'll never cook
She was released
They gave they bathed set her up with a job as a laundress and they weren't here you go Mary
And then you know
They kept track of her for a while
And then at a certain point they kind of
Stop
So how many years will go by
What happens next
There's an outbreak of typhoid
Where we are at a maternity hospital you're kidding
Ambulance before
She says that she goes and pays a visit
And walks into the kitchen and
She says the first
Person that she encountered
Was Typhoid Mary Mack
Your topper did some legwork on
Where Mary had been and it turned out she had worked at a restaurant
New hotels in in
And a sanatorium as well as the
And at least according
To his account
Two of the
People that she made sick
We're children
She was now a woman who could not claim innocence she was no willfully and deliberately to have taken desperate Chan
Dances with human life cheat abused her privilege
She's broken her parole so then they put her back on North brother Island back in her
Bungalow
And there she sits
She was a dangerous character and must
Be treated according
Absolutely
Oakbrook
She's made a deal and she didn't keep the deal
The thing is is that
At the time she was sent back
To the island
There were hundreds of other healthy carriers identified all over New York
And some of them work
What is mostly men
By the way and if you're cooking
Weather report from cooking but not all of them always listen
And yet Mary was the only one
Who they isolated
In this way why
Why only her
I think it was more about
Making people feel safe
Then
Actually making them safe
The lookout for the stair South humbled
She was what we needed at the time
We're in the hospital
Where the tuberculosis patients were quarantined
This was towards the end
Of linen life is at
The island
Yeah these must be the words
Yeah
Sewing machine
This is where they brought her
After she had a stroke
And this is where she was for the last
6 years of her life
Did she die in here
Hi this is David roster
Radiolab is funded in
Park by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation enhancing public
Technology in the modern world more information about Sloan at www. Sloan.
Radiolab
Just by WNYC and distributed by NPR
Okay that's it thanks bye
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help this summer I'm hosting
And I request for those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
We're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments of childhood Brilliance basically I want to hear about those
When a kid you know did something that just means you lean back and say whoa how did they do that
Maybe it was the moment that our kids you've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons and you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed they're writing music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the specific moments where a kid does something super smart
Doesn't have anything to do with the test if you have a story please share it with us
Go to radiolab.org Brilliance and record a short audio message for us
Again that's radiolab.org / brilliance
Thank you so much
Hey I'm Jared I'm Robert Coolidge this is Radiolab today it's patient zero
Yeah and end this next story
What's it's so huge it's the ultimate patient zero story really many of us have lived through this it was its
Is recent an event
It's such a recent event that it still hurts and it still bleeds
I mean it somewhere is
A literally
The the patient that is
Cold zero
So this is a lot of people going to help us tell the story but starting ass off
Is
Science writer Radiolab regular Carl Zimmer
7 in 1981
Doctors for the first time described syndrome
Actual man
The young man in Los Angeles
Paradigm the number of cases has been growing faster and faster
So far more than 80 Americans have died 258 people have died 625 people have died
Of course this is the part we all know how
From the first few cases in La AIDS became
One of the deadliest pandemics the world has ever seen more dangerous than the plague of the Middle Ages
Story
But I've not been able to shake the last 30 years and it's a story
I want to reimagine right now
Right after
News of this
Syndrome started to break at science writer David quammen who along with Carl will be one of her
Epidemiologist were trying to figure out
Where did it come from
And they were thinking like well maybe it's a sexually transmitted disease the CDC launches the study of a group
Group of about
30 patient
Gay men in New York Los Angeles and San Francisco
To see who had had sexual contact
With whom how do you detach a series of interviews with
Pick me up please name all the people that you that you
Subway
The CDC eventually releases the results of the survey in the form of a
Diagram
With circles representing patients in the lines representing sexual contact in each patient
Diesel circle with numbered New York
7 Los Angeles
12z to know who's who but you could tell immediately
When you look at this
Level 30 or so circles in a circle
It was special
Headlines coming out in every direction
Seven or eight emanating from him let the Hub of a wheel
Except all the spokes on this wheel connected to other Wheels would send shout out and catch the other Wheels
Spanning outward at the center of it all was that one little circle number
Number zero
As far as we know that was the first time
Do you ever get the term
Patient
Patient zero was
Central victim and victim
This is from a 60 Minute special in 1988 that year
A reporter named Randy Schultz has written a book called and the band played on
For the first time revealed the identity
A patient zero
He was a French Canadian
A very handsome Airline
Stewart
Few minutes later in the report Schultz comes on to describe a guy
Unlimited sexual
The sexual athlete who would fly from one hotspot to the next cuz it's job
Having sex with literally thousands of men
And as he knew he was dying
At least according to Randy Shield
He became somewhat Sinister and malicious
He would sleep with a male partner
At a bathhouse in Sanford
Store somewhere else
And then when the light came up according to Randy Schultz he would say
I've got gay cancer
Now you're going to get it too
I talked to him
Mrs. dr. Selma dritz
She was part of that CDC study
He was getting other people sick with it and he said
My right to do whatever I want
Buy civil rights
Suicide please
I've got it why shouldn't they have
This is you can kill yourself you want to be cut no right to take somebody else along with you
Screw you and walked out
Really
Chilling
Moment
I'm pretty much from that moment on
Hindu god he just took on this this aura
As says single-handedly causing a an epidemic
In the United States
Not invite you but I first bumped into the story in the movie version of in the band played on
Thousands of men
Was faces I cannot even remember anyone that's an actor playing getting a gun movie now when I first saw that
Is it already infected two and a half million people into think
Did it all go back
Just seemed
Unreal it was a it was a very potent story there's no doubt
And then he gave HIV to a lot of people
There's no question about that
What we do know is that he was not page
It was not
No he was not the beginning point
He was
Not even close
So here's a question that got me started
Story
Okay so the gay store that was the movie stuck in my head but what's the real movie
What movie can we make about
The beginning of the 8th
You've got something so vast
According to some estimates will have killed 60 million people by the end of the decade
What you need to beginning
You need some way of explaining how this
Zas
Easter happened
What might happen again
How exactly do we know that getting to that wasn't page
Well there are a couple reasons we know it so
So one thing that people started to do
Scientist was
Two started going back and looking at people who died who died mysteriously AIDS like things
In the past might some of them have been early cases and they started finding
A lot 12 years
Before it was recognized in this country in 1959
A sailor and Britain
Died of pneumocystis
Pneumonia and soap for a while you had all these new patient zero
A nurse in Chicago Died of kaposi sarcoma
But the real definitive
Blow to this old patient zero nonsense came by actually looking at the virus
It's out in 1984
Same here that getting to God die
Scientist isolate the virus
HIV
Which is really just a little string of
Genetic code that gets into your body and into your cells and uses your cells
Make copies of
But here's the thing when it replicates within a single patient
It copies itself
Imprecisely
It mutates
Quickly it changes a lot as the virus duplicates itself inside a person that
Often have little copying errors in the movie Temptations
It turns out those errors
They happened at a predictable rate you can
Kind of almost predict how many you're going to see a year or 5 years
And so the amount of changes that you see out there the diverse
Really of the viruses in the eighth population
Will that becomes really good information is there a group of scientists begin to look at the amount of diversity
HIV patients in the US and other parts of the world and the more diversity the longer the virus has been around
Naked use that kind of like a clock
If you have a virus here in a virus there you can measure how different they are and you would know that it would take a certain amount of time for
Them to get that different
To make a long story short the picture they get
Is the date entered the United States
Around 1966
At a time when getting to God was still a virginal adolescent
From their scientists are able to
The trace the virus
Back to Haiti
From Haiti
Africa
It's been there the longest it's had the longest time to become diverse to mutate to evolve
If you want to
Really if you want to get to the
To the real patients are as it were
The most interesting stuff come actually come from Africa
It's a one-way to try to figure out its Origins there is to go looking for the virus
Yep and that takes us back to CR 59
MTR C60
Can we talk about then I'm sure these are the two earliest known HIV positive human stress
And this is where for me at least
Story gets way bigger than a man
Now the first sample
Vr-59 came to light in the late 90s some house scientist on Earth are very old tube of
Blood from hospital in Kinshasa democratic
Congo
When they tested it and it had HIV
This is been taken from a Bantu man in 1959
Yeah nobody knows his name nobody even knows I think what he died of
End
That was the only one for a number of years that was our one
Glimpse into the kind of deep history of HIV
Then Along Comes That Guy Michael Warby he's an evolutionary biologist
At the University of Arizona in a few years ago
Michael went back to Kinshasa and found a second HIV
Virus lurking in a tiny bit of human tissue
It was preserved in paraffin wax
Kind of like
Han Solo in in the Star Wars movie when he's kind of Frozen in in that Carbonite or whatever that stuff is
And this new sample
He was from the same town Kinshasa is the first and also
Importantly
From the same time 1960
And with the two of them
Then you can
Kind of go back in time
May be described before you can measure the differences
Between
Calculate
How long
It would take for those samples to get that different
In the end
You can use these two samples to wind the clock
All the way back
Virus
It started it all
It turned out the most recent common ancestor of those two specimen
Goes back
To do about 1908
That is when it started in human beings
What
1908 South Russell
Give or take a margin of error
Well
So
Around 1908 give or take
Something happy
That moment is this
Spillover
Bill over
Spillovers the term the scientist used
Describe the moment when
A virus
In one species
Passes into another state
New diseases in humans tend to pop up
From
Animals
So people said okay but flu comes from Birds where does HIV come from
To get a dancer you have to look Beyond human beings
You have to look at other viruses that are like HIV
How to search was on a similar disease and research animal turns out right about the time that the HIV virus
Scientists at the New England Primate Research
Some research has found a virus like it in macaque monkeys monkey it was so similar that they called it SIV
Simian immunodeficiency virus
And that's where the origin Quest started
This is Beatrice Han I'm a professor of medicine and microbiology at the University of Pennsylvania
Interested they founded macaques
It took a couple years and still another primate species to sooty mangabey
A few more
The African bring monkeys Mandrill for 40 different species of African monkey
Known to have their own version of SIV so then the question was which one of these monkeys are primates pasta to us
Unexpectedly a researcher named Marty Martin Peters decided to test
Her chip to Orphan chimpanzees
She found it very very close match virus that was the closest relative of hiv-1 so everybody's
Volume
Open championship
Yes but then the question was
Which
Rather
Where where exactly
So Beatrice Han and her colleagues started looking at chimps that came from different parts
Western central Africa
Now getting blood samples from chimps in the wild
Pretty much
It just isn't feasible
Yeah because in the wild
They hide the moment they see us so if you get stuck with fecal sample
The DNA in there
And viruses
So they would just go to where the chimpanzees sleep at night
And they would just
You know collection poop bring it back to the lab and Beatrice would analyze all the viruses
Over 90 different
Wild Community from every part of central Africa over 7000 different people account
And slowly they were able to piece together which communities were infected and which ones have the closest hiv-1
That's when it hit us for the first time
What exactly hit you
The geographic origin of these chumps
In 2006
Her and her colleagues public
The human AIDS virus comes from a group of
Champs very specific group
The live
A very specific place this little corner
Southeastern camera
Between the
Bumba river river in the Congo River
These chips recently
Send it
Between these Three Rivers scenario probably only
100 square miles
Not much more than that
When we're looking at what humans have
I'm looking at what all those chimps in Africa
The most
Perfect match
Is this little territory up there in camera
There is no other virus that is any
Closer so that's that
So can you reconstruct the spillover and the who did it spilled over into
It's Betty no asbestos
You can understand that
And the best
Hypothesis
Is the cut Hunter
Cut Under the Sea UT Hunter
A hunter who gets cut and what we say about this guy
I mean Izzy what do we know about if we had to guess
If we had to guess
That human was
Probably a Bantu man
Living
Very near the forest or in the forest in Southeastern Cameroon
He was hunting
Baby had a bow and arrow maybe he got a
Spear
And
He kills chimpanzee
Bingo here's a big pile of me
And you start the butcher it
Cutting open the chest cavity pulling out
Oregon
And
Customs
And it gets blood to blood contact
Chimpanzee blood against his blood
What happens
Is that the virus in the chimpanzee blood
Found itself in an environment that was
Unexpected that was alien to it
But was not too much different
From
The biochemical environment it had been in
Chimpanzee blood
It could function
And that's the moment
Begin
That human
Is
Patient zero
But why then
Why 1908
I mean presumably people have been hunting ships for a really long time
Why would this guy be patient
7 million
That's another of the big question
People certainly in in central Africa have been eating monkeys
Thousands of years
Larry david scissors
Really no way to know but this could have just been the right virus maybe this particular virus
Evolved in a way that made it more transmissible in humans or
Maybe you just got lucky
Come along at
Precisely the right
What you're looking at
Is Carl again
A time when this part of Africa was
Being heavily colonized the French and the belgians were Building train systems
Populations were on the move
Kinshasa which is then leopoldville it was exploding
It was huge
Cities were attracting people
From the boonies
In those days
So by 1908 all the virus has
To do is get from that tiny village where the cut Hunter live
Tongzhou new city
That happens
Almost certainly
By river
I was
Stirred by the work of Beatrice on in micro RV
To see what this
Scenario look like on the ground
I went to Southeastern camera on a chartered
A little boat about a 30 foot wooden boat with an outboard motor
Trace the path of the virus
We went down the in Cocoa River
And we stopped at a few villages
A couple little village is there one is which has a market
Where you can buy
Monkey meat
Crocodile meat
And he says it wasn't hard to imagine
Have it all
Perhaps the cut Hunter gave the virus to a woman
Who then passed it on to a fisherman that I called the Voyager then got in the boat is David
Carried it down the river
Songo river which is the leading Goku as a tributary of the Tsongas on it becomes a bigger River 200 M wide
Which then flows
To the Congo River
The Big River
And I imagine him
Sliding into brazzaville
Around 1920 the first HIV positive man to arrive
5 p.m.
An urban center
Much greater density of humans were there prostitutes a greater fluidity of Social and sexual
Interactions and that seems to have been
The place
From which
The disease went global
So that's how it happened
We can take it back even farther apus
For his if you want to make a movie about the
Start up
Because we got it from chimps
Right
She could ask
Who is Chip seal
What do we know about chimps
Right yeah I mean everything comes from somewhere
And again by molecular work
Scientists have been able to determine
That the chimp virus is actually
He actually comes from two monkey virus
Two different monkeys
From two completely different species
What
Would they
Have encountered each other somewhere
How to fight
They probably encountered each other in the stomach of a chimp
Well
From the perspective of a chimpanzee
Monkeys
They look
Tasty this is Nathan Wolfe
Professor in human biology
Stanford University he says to fully understand
This part
The patient
You're a rather chimp zero narrative
You have to grasp
How it is that
The Chimps hunt
This is something you witness in the kabali National
Forest Inn in Southwestern Uganda
Describe to us
Watching three male chimps converge
On a tri-fold colobus monkeys which is very small black and white monkey
And one individual
Managed to grab two juveniles
And then the three individuals all met up and began to eat the monkey with
Why was still alive the chimpanzee was going after an Oregon you know that that obviously was a a tasty morsel
I'll bet that he was going after and and the monkey was
Screaming bloody murder
It is quite
Disturbing to watch
One of the things that struck me at that moment
Was
The depth of contact
Between the blood and body fluids of this monkey and the chimpanzee
The Chimps are literally covered in blood they have blood on their face in their eyes and from the viruses respect
This is spillover heaven
Okay so the following is the closest that we can get to a zero point in this entire narrative we don't know where it
And we don't know exactly the time say some hundreds of thousands of years ago from the molecular clock we know it was a lesson
A million years that's all we know but whenever it was
Chimp zero with hunting
He comes upon a monkey call the red-capped mangabey the red-capped mangabey this is a larger primate
Laser tree dwellings little tree dwelling
Little bit of red fur on their heads yes
Gypsy Rose spots one of these monkeys
Eats it
In the process he catches a red-capped mangabey version
Of the AIDS virus
Next sometime after that first kill
Weeks months we don't know maybe the same day chimps zero comes across another month
And this monkey was called a spot nosed guenon yes it's got a spot on its nose I assume there you go.
One of the tiniest monkeys of all the old world monkeys and chips 08 That Monkey
And gets a spot nosed guenon version of the a
HIV
She's got the red-capped mangabey
And you've got the the spot nosed guenon to got a kwena Nana manga be two completely different kinds of SIV
Inside the same chip now
Under normal circumstances according to Nathan both of these SIV viruses would go nowhere
Because when one of these viruses makes the jump they go from a place they've adapted
They know to completely foreign lands
Like a human being dropped off on Mars maybe without a spacesuit
Basically you're entering a
Completely alien habit
Estelle's don't look the same the environment is different in The Chimps immune system would normally kill them
But then once in a blue moon something
Crazy happens
These two viruses
This will end up inside the same cell in the same chimp at the same time literally there is a single cell
Simultaneously infected with both viruses
S'pose on one side of the cell you got the mangabey virus and on the other
Other side of the same cell you got the spot nosed guenon virus
And what happens is
Literally inside the cell you have an enzyme
Call the plumber is on enzyme copying genetic information of the viruses
This is what viruses do they hijack these enzymes to make copies of themselves
Now
Here's the problem these these enzyme they're not necessarily that sticky and while they're in the process of copying
One virus every once in awhile will accidentally fall off mid copy and
Go to the second virus
Just keep on copying and so what it ends up spitting out is a hybrid
Like that
Now this new Mosaic probably won't go anywhere because 99.999999 9
10% of the time
Wendy's hybrids happened to dead end
The Chimps immune system is pretty sophisticated in his evolved defenses against these viruses and it will destroy them
But again once
In a blue moon
So this is a blue moon after Blue Moon after Blue Moon to really get that
Finally you get
One particular mosaic virus
Clean the manga be in the guilin that through sheer random luck
It landed on the exact right combination of genes that
Allow detuve The Chimps immune system one of the amazing things to think about is how many
How many hopeful monsters you had to have in order to get that one that actually survived
Probably trillions
Then boom
Suddenly in a Flash
From these two virus
I can barely survive in the chimp
You get a new virus
Little bit mangabey little bit wine in can only survive in the chimp
Facts for this baby virus
The chimp is the perfect
And that was the virus that ended up
Spreading
Jumping over into humans
And it's been this
Massive incredibly traumatic
Sort of tear in the fabric of humanity
Let me add another event
They're essentially 12 major groups
Of the HIV virus
What David means is it
12 different kinds of HIV virus
Have spilled over 12 different
Times 8 of them came from monkeys
Three of them came from chimps
And one came from Gorillaz
And of those 12
Only one of them
Is responsible for the global pandemic
12 times 12 times that we know about
Probably happened dozens and dozens more time
That we don't know about
So
Spillover is not a highly improbable event these sorts of viruses are constantly paying it us
They're paying us and pinging it us
We see it happening all the time
You see it happening
All time
Nathan is set up a series of monitoring
In places like central Africa and he and his colleagues been tracking what he calls the viral chatter
In the people who hunt these primates we collected specimens from the animals that they were hunting they compared that the boy
Blood samples from Hunters themselves and guess what we found a whole range of new retroviruses that were moving over into these
For example he's been tracking something called the Simian foamy virus
Which is in the same family as HIV and he's seen it hot from an individual gorilla
To an individual human who killed that guy
Yeah these are almost certainly what we call primary transmission events houses you really are looking at the
Potential beginning of something
Yes you want to Patient Zero really clear patient zero
Buy it some of these individuals have been infected with these viruses
And the real question is
How do we stop patient zero
How to avoid patient
Patient one patient exactly
So Nathan is developing a series of
Tools
Like digital surveillance
Some of these places
I work in some places in Democratic Republic of Congo
You basically have to fly in to get there no roads
Electricity
But these places are still have cell phones
So Nathan has begun to track cell phone call patterns in these communities
So he sees a blip
Many calls
The medical center within a short. Of time okay boom now we got to investigate that
We
Continue to find viruses that are completely novel
And we're looking to
Determine if these are
If these are the next HIV
Is anybody says
HIV
Landed in humans at 1908 but we didn't know about it
Until 1981 we had decades
Time on this was a virus
4 thread global
What if we been looking for it
Lot of people to thank for this Eggman
Thanks to Nathan Wolfe
For being Nathan and he has an awesome new book called The Viral storm book on viruses
This is called a planet of viruses and thank you also to him and to Michael Barbie
Are there interview was recorded on a podcast from Meet the scientist what you can find at microworld
Text David quammen who's got a book called spillover coming out very soon which is all about diseases crossing over from animals
And also to Beatrice hangzhou University of Pennsylvania
Letting us use
Hey this is Storm wheeler a senior editor and producer Radiolab with a quick update
David Clements books
Spillovers
Been out for a couple years now and
We all know we are actually now at this moment facing
Tragic consequences
Another spelling
This time it's the Ebola virus and we found ourselves wondering just
How far
Going to spill
Alright okay
So Robert and I called up David climate again he had actually just reprinted with updates
The chapter about a bullet from
Yeah Ebola
The natural and human history of a deadly virus
How old is this disease anyone have any idea
Well is a human disease as far as we know it dates the 1976
There was this outbreak of a strange disease
At the youngbou Commission in Northern Zaire
318 cases
180 people died
And then there was another one
In Sudan at about the same time this time a hundred and fifty-one people die and then it just
Appears
Hiding in the forest Without a Trace
Until
1994 thousands of miles away in Gabon another outbreak
Yes that's what that's the history since 1976 it disappears for
For two or three years at a time sometimes it disappears for a decade and then it spills over
Because it's a human outbreak if something is in the closet and is going to jump out of
Use end of natural question to ask
Where's the class
Where is it high tide
Well then the main suspects
Are bats
We don't know that for sure
Because nobody has ever isolated live Ebola virus
From an African bat have they tried how they looked and lots and lots of bad and all kinds of animals they looked at
Can insects sanlitun snakes it looked in forest
Antelopes they looked in monkeys they looked in Plants literally hundreds of different species they looked in found zero traces of
Live Ebola virus so we really don't know where it's coming from or where it might come from next
No
Can I just
Ask you just added
Describe the Ebola virus
It's apparently at Thursdays are generally teeny is this a teeny teeny teeny one
Yes yeah it's a teeny virus that belongs to
Family they call the filo viruses
Filo is in thread
It's a it's a spaghetti shaped
Virus genome is carried on
Just one strand of the
The genetic material
RNA
And while those jeans have lead
The virus live happily for hundreds of thousands even millions of years and bats or whatever animal lives in
When it gets into humans
Ebola Burns too hot
It makes so many copies of itself so quickly that it
Destroys the body in a person is usually dead within a few weeks
David says is
Actually bad for the fire
Because Ebola can only pass through direct contact with bodily fluids and because it kills so quickly
It doesn't have a lot of opportunities to get
Into the next person so the scientist have a term for that too
They call at least they used to call us a dead end host how's that for afraid
Where the dead end host
Puppy Bowl
And that means that when Ebola gets into us
It has no great future it's either going to burn out and come to an end
Are we going to stop it
But right now we don't seem like a dead end host yeah I'm wondering like you know if we've
We started noticing a 1976
A burst here a burst there
Why
Why now this why is it stupid question for Ebola 2014 this time we've got a very different
Situation has gotten out of control
Why is it going out of control well
Partly because
We recognized it late
It began back in December 2013 with a two year old boy in Southeastern Guinea
At least he's the first known case at this point he died
His mother died about a week later his sister died his grandmother died other people in the village died this went on
From early December until the middle of March by then it spread from these small
Villages into larger cities in part David says because
Well previous outbreaks have been in very remote places it now found itself in a more
Densely
Populated area to Capital Cities
In the small West African countries
I'm not very many miles away from The Villages of the countryside
The virus got into these poor neighborhoods like West Point
How were people were living together in
In crowded
Slum like
Neighborhood
And
And when their loved ones got sick
That people took care of them and their loved ones died
People
Clean the bodies and touch the bodies and said goodbye to him
So the infection spread
And of course those
Dent poor neighborhoods in the capital cities
Are not that far from the International Airport
The suddenly you've got
The opportunity for the almost the first time
For Ebola
To get on an airplane so if if is
People change the way they think about ebola because it is there a mood shift
There's a little bit of a mood shift but the experts of scientist Public Health officials are still saying
This is not that kind of virus
It still is
As far as we know a virus that is only
Transmissible by direct contact with bodily fluids it should be
Easy to stop easy to contain
But according to David the thing that some scientists are worried about is that as Ebola gets into more and more people and makes more more coffee
Change it yes every time it replicates there's a chance
Of a mistake
The chance of the genes for the next virus will come out just a little bit different it'll
You take most mutations are either insignificant
Or they do damage
But occasionally
There can be a mutation
That might possibly help the virus
Can we track these things like can we
Can we take a person who's got sick of Ebola in Sudan
I compared to person sick of Ebola in the Congo competitive person sick of Ebola in Niger and wherever
Can we do that and see whether it's changing yes
And it has been done
Steven Geier
And his
Colleagues published a paper in science in early September which involve doing exactly that and one of the things they say
Francis David is that since this virus has been in US during this outbreak
It's been changing twice as fast
As it has previously when it's living in his animal hiding place
Yeah so it has had more opportunities
To replicate in more different people that hasn't just been in 300 people it's been in 9,000 people now.
What is the more opportunities you have to have a
Good mutation from your point of view
Is it that this is suddenly this disease has gotten an enormous number of opportunities and that is the answer
Operative word yeah
Are there boundaries around that I mean like do we have any sense of
How big leap it would be for this to suddenly be transmissible in the air
Yeah
We know that for this
Spread through the air
They're very special machinery
You know
Grappling hook
Proteins on the outside of
A virus that help it catch hold of particular cells and enter them
An ebola doesn't have the right
Grappling hooks to lay hold of
Cells in the respiratory tract and get in them and then come
Bursting out of them and be carried out word on your breath
To get to that point
Would require
A number of mutations Each of which has infinitesimally
Unlikely and when you is that apply mutation that it would be startling like a what to a what
Been saying that
It would be like mutations
That
Allowed a giraffe
Fly
But they're rather scenarios that are a little more probable
For instance it might mutate and adapt in such a way
That it kills fewer people
Or kills them more slowly
And leave people infectious for a longer period of time
Maybe people are walking around
Three or four weeks with an occasional vomiting episodes but there not dying
That would
Potentially give Ebola
Greater opportunity
To spread among more people
What
This is not a fair question to ask you but what should we be
Doing
I think the most important thing we should be doing is not letting
The public health vs. civil civil liberties issues in the US distract us
From West Africa
Is the case count gets we talked about this is the case count gets higher it has more opportunities
To mutate
And therefore more opportunities to adapt
So we need to end this outbreak
In West Africa
Before this virus learns too much about us
Thanks again to David quammen his book is Ebola
The natural and human history of a deadly virus
I'll be back
And just mama
My name is Brandon Novak and I'm calling for
Reykjavik Iceland
We're about half
What country believes in elves
Radiolab is supported in part by the National Science Foundation
And by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Hanson public understanding of science
Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloan at
Www. Sloan
. org
Aaron Neville at one of my proudest moments of being a dad
Yeah having this morning
A little bit in
Wedding socializes enough well
We were taking him to daycare
And where it gets he's taking his shoes off in this little boy whose
Only there two days a week and he's not a
Testing well
Every time his mother drops
It's a little late cry him offer
Swelling
So meal sit down on this
I'll see to take a
She's off
Mother of this kid puts
Little boy next to a meal
He is
Crying
Trot
Tibet
What happened to
Emil turns this little boy
Looks at him
Sticks out his hand
Incest
Yeah cuz it's like they're at their out in their own societies you know
Yeah okay so let's do the introductions I'm Jared I'm Robert this is Radiolab on the show patient
Zero patience
Exactly
Let's focus instead on invention
On the people
Who bring new ideas into the wall
Yeah the zeros behind the ideas
Contributing writer at the New York Times magazine
Her first high-five is actually about
V
First high five
Ever
One morning a few years ago 2007
Four 2008 John turn down his computer open up his email and found or press release
Movies about the true Undisputed inventor of the high five
Coming you know outline Lisa press release from
National High Five Day which is a kind of a joke holiday
That was invented by a group of high school friends I think and they told the story they told the story of Le Mans
College basketball player Murray State in Kentucky
Is released when something like that deletes his father fought in Vietnam that's part of the 1st Battalion 5th Infantry
Is nicknamed the five
And they've used to greet each other by holding up their hand and saying five
As a kind of prideful
And when Lamont was younger they would also to hang out at the house in Kentucky and you can keep all their names straight so when they walk in
In the door and go 5 he would just hurt not going to hand
Lego hi-five I like high like hello five hello five, you know he has small hands he likes to put the
I'm up against the big hands of the Five Guys and it was years later that he started playing college basketball at Murray State
Started high-fiving all seem really never stopped high-fiving was just something he did when he went around playing away games other team
He's picked it up and it's already spread out so
He was sort of both the inventor of the high five in the kind of Johnny Apple
High five at the same time
And within a few weeks of John getting his press release the story was
Everywhere
Antiviral he wound up sort of all over the Internet there was some local newspapers who you know picked it up
You know Marie states only became very proud of the fact that they were there
The home of the high five if you can sort of party institutional lower in the athletic department
Can you read this
I thought
How's that
Sad
Because I knew the story of Glenn Burke
Turns out John had already been poking around and
This question who invented the
I-5 and he'd stumbled on this photograph
But black and white picture
Two baseball players facing each other afros
Cute smiles
And their hands are in the air right about to connect
Which one of these is Glen Burton
Burke's the guy in the warm-up jacket
I think he's even got his hat on backwards
Glenn Burke was a center fielder for the LA Dodgers
The 70s
Big guy he says he had 17 in
I'll take his word for the
You're the guy in the picture is Dusty Baker he's an outfielder
You can tell
In the picture
Just been the way the glenister throwing his whole body forward the
He's the one initiating the gesture
I mean this is the guy who was
You know the soul of the Dodgers
He just had that type of I'm charisma
This is Luther Burke Davis Glen sister
Woodglen it was like
But he's always be on the stage often said he should have been a comedian
In the club as he used
To do Richard Pryor
Stand-up routines
Search for memories you just genuinely love people
So much so she says that in the year that picture was taken
The Dodgers made him that they should have public face of the team he was there an ambassador of Goodwill
He's the guy they said that to all the Press event you like meet the youngsters on cats
Here's the story about this picture
What was the date
October 5th
Politically enough 1977
Phillies game four bases are loaded Dusty Baker steps to the plate and
Grand Slam Crowd Goes Nuts
Are you coming to the play really high up in Baker
Before you know it Bergen Baker
Smacking
Bam there was
The sportscasters that would you know announcing the game said they had never seen that done in sports before
And from there on the Dodgers started high-fiving and everyone else started by 5
It all began with that one moment the platonic Hi-Fi right there
Unfortunately
That moment that was actually supposed to be getting in and also almost the end of
Berks career wasn't good
He's actually really good even in his rookie season
He was being talked about as the next Willie Mays by the Dodgers organization
But
He was gay
And he
Try to keep that a secret while he was playing
A Dusty Baker actually had kept trying to set him up with his wife's cousins and the birth never want you to never liked any of them and they
These are really good looking women apparently
So there are rumors circulating the rumors reached the front office of of the
The LA Dodgers and and one day Burke was called in by management
And they offered him $75,000
To get married
Why is 75000 to get married
Just like a mop or something like that they didn't regularly offer their players
Money to get to get married in and Burkes response apparently was
He said I suppose you mean to a woman
Shortly after that
The Dodgers traded into the Oakland A's
Pro player who everyone acknowledge was completely inferior
That was confusing for us and I know it had to be confusing for him it was shocking everyone no one understood why
He was traded
Was cuz he was gay
Yeah
Yashow baseball this all American sport
But
You know Lizzy was still going to be able to play ball
Jodeci.
Doesn't get very much playing time
And when he did get on the field
It wasn't very pleasant just get heckled a lot you know some people in the bleachers and
An even worse according to a couple of different people his coach
Billy Martin
What often introduce Glenbrook this way
This is Glenbrook the faggot
Really
Yeah and so Glenbrook retires
Don't like 26 or
Yes he was young within a year of his rookie
Just walks
God that's like
Aborted carrier
Exactly from their hands up in the Castro District
In San Francisco
Is the big gay neighborhood and things go
Okay for a while then one day when he's crossing the street three teenage girls and their mothers car come barreling down the road
And they hitting
And broke his leg in three places
And that kind of ended everything that happened
He starts taking painkillers
One thing leads
Another
He gets hooked on crack can't hold a job because broke
End up living on the streets
And in 1994
Burke is diagnosed with
With HIV or Aids I can say to that point
Last time she didn't sleep well at night
And we will sit up and talk
Put on music in
I danced and he move his arms around cuz he was in the bed
He was bedridden
So you took care of him till he died
Yeah
Glenbrook died in 1995
But what he's left with
At this point is he's left with
The original high five
That's his claim yes
That defined
To some people that lie
Is that the end
And he and he believed
A reporter in Houston
You know if it was true about the high five in and he said yeah I think about the feeling you get when you give someone a high five
I had that feeling before everybody else did
So what did you do when you got this
So I called National High Five Day
Because I wanted to talk to Lamont
Even though I was sad
It seems like okay here's another person's
Prideful
Accomplishment
Let's get his story
Hello eventually
You get this kind of phone
My name is Greg Harrell Edge
Greg is one of the founders and he and John got to talking and John asks him
Sensible first question the Lamont sleep story
True he figured was Buddy night
Don't you at least ask
Reporter
And there was a pause and he said
No frankly
We've been waiting for someone to ask we thought no one would ever ask it's not true it's just something
We can meet up we wanted to see if the media would would run with it and made the whole thing and then they just went to go cast
There we set that we picked
Murray State
That's just kind of a great Sunday school at pops up in the NCAA tournament every few years and they came across this guy Lamont's
YMCA well
It was pretty close to rant
They then told me they had received an email from Le Mans litzas wipes
His wife emailed us and said some of the details that you have or are flat-out wrong
Some of the things you said are right though
But Lamont thinks he probably did invent the high five
What about Glenn I was kind of like
Kana a bit Blown Away
You know
You know here was this guy who is
Proud of this and these guys
Just kind of drifted away from
Do you feel a little guilty
Did I mean like okay to high-five it's kind of a
The silly thing on the other hand
Is life the way he died
I'm lucky Rob. We do feel we do feel
We wish that we had done things slightly different
In putting together this sort of
Collegiate prank
But we didn't really know Glenn Burke at that time
Greg said they hadn't heard of the Glenbrook
Story when they pulled this
Now that they know it
They really feel bad
Sector now organizing a charity event they're calling the national High 5 ortho
Which will raise money for charity including one chosen by
Glenbrooks
Sister Luther very proud anytime I see somebody do a high-five he just really makes me happy
And that seemed like a good end of the story
But
No because then John told us that if you really honestly want to get to the bottom of who invented the high five
We we didn't think we want to but now there were in it what the hell where you got to go
Beyond Glenbrook
I've wanted you to believe
Glenbrook died believing that the high five was his legacy
Add more or less the same moment that he invented it a guy named Eric Smith
A basketball player for the Louisville Cardinals
Was that practice
And a guy named Wiley Brown went up to Derek Smith
And was going to give him just a ordinary low five
Derek Smith looking in the eye
This is what Wiley Brown told me to look him in the eye and said no up high
That yours Lewisville team they were they were known as the doctors of dunk neither high-flying team they played Above the Rim
Who played in the 1980 NCAA finals
I haven't seen it but apparently the broadcaster refer tax
The high five handshake
Handshake
He felt compelled to explain it to America and it did at the moment the Derek Smith did it did an asteroid fall on his head
Well
In 1996 I believe in in the 90s he had an undiagnosed heart condition
And he just died all the sudden donut on a cruise ship
What does
And
He said explicitly the Wiley Brown this is something I'm going to be remembered for
You know our kids and our grandkids are going to talk about this and in fact their kids and grandkids do talk about and they're probably very proud
But we ran into this one
Volleyball in the 1960s years
Before Glenn Burke and Eric Smith
She said with her girls everyone did it
All the time so I do believe that it was volleyball that first started
She says they would high five more on a player screwed up about celebration
Do you need a high five course it's more when you're down so happy
So women's volleyball
There you go
No slip out Infinity
Because then our producer of The Levy also discovered that in the movie Breathless
19:55 in exactly 1 hour 18 minutes into the film you will see to Frenchman
Do a very distinct
Who sang right there
Is anusol like an indication to you
It's maybe
It's one of those things it
Probably is there the dawn of man
Because it might give us pleasure from evolutionary
I think this has the feeling of something that was born and who in this room wants Lindbergh to be the original
Trader and Mia Mimi
It's a better story every time
We look for the original at anything
Disease
Engagement
Chester
We find more than one
So what are you doing
I think you know what you do is you just choose you say which one is the better story
What does go with the best type I forget the first the best and I think we could do that
Glen
Glenn Burke
Invented the high five
Hi Radiolab this is
Radiolab is produced by Jad abumrad includes
Soren wheeler
Pat Walters Tim Howard
Apparel
When will you be in Shawn Cole and help from Jonathan Mitchell Rachel James and Matt kielty
Special thank Mike sellers Chris Condon
MKT Circle
My story and I'm sticking to it