Hey everybody this is Pat Walters senior editor here at Radiolab and I'm really excited to dive into the next step
Episode of our mini series
G all that intelligence
But before we do that I want to say a couple thing
First of all I want to thank everyone who supports this show
Your donations are the only reason we can create a deeply reported multi-part series like this
But thank you
And if you've never given before
Listen
Because we have a great new reason for you to become a member right now
All you have to do to become a member is donate to the show
So last time you for your help a Radiolab podcast listener from Singapore
Was inspired to
Become a member
And now the stoner has laid down a challenge for you
If we can get 2000 few
Two step up before June 30th
Become members
This Anonymous donor will give us an additional
$25,000
The average member gift is just a t box
And if you give at that level you'll get to choose from some very cool Radiolab thank you gifts
But of course every donation counts and we are so grateful for whatever you can contribute
Your donation will help us fill some big exciting plans we have for future episodes
And giving right now will help us unlock that additional $25,000
Go to radiolab.org donate
Vortex
Radiolab
To join in the challenge before June 3rd
Where you live is a team effort it truly doesn't happen without all of us
And that includes you too
Dope
Thank you
Are you awake
Listening to Radiolab
Radiolab wnyc
Pick this is G
I realized miniseries
Episode 2
Pat Walters
That end in episode one we told the story of a guy who was given an IQ test
When he was a boy
And it changed the course
Not for the better
His Name Was Daryl
But he came to be known as Larry.
He took on that pseudonym when he became the center of a court case
That basically put the IQ test itself on trial
4 months lawyers presented evidence that the test
Daryl took were racially biased
And in 1979 a federal judge
Band the IQ test
Are used on African American children
Board making decisions about special education
In the state of California
That could still be given to white kids
Hispanic kids
Asian kid
Just not the bike
Netgear imagine this has caused some issues test test test
Chapter 2 begins about 25 years later okay
Friend
Hayward California
A little town just south of
Oakland not too far from where Daryl live
It starts hello how are you
Tire
With a couple well my name is Pamela Lewis
I am Nicholas Lewis's
Mother I'm the dad
Nicholas
The Sun that we
Fallout 4 to have equal rights
That's it
2004 Camry key have 5 kids
Winton Middle School Winton high school and their youngest
Nicholas is in kindergarten
And how did you learn about this thing
It was just by pure accident I picked up a stupid paper that my husband brought home from work one day because he worked for the day
Daily Review on a job delivering papers to local businesses
Take one
Mainly for the sport
You got all your warriors
Giron
Yes
Go Warriors
Anyhow one-day Ricky comes in with us an extra papers Pam grabs a piece of it
And she says
Article just a little tiny thing about a quart
Not the letter T case a different court case but it mentioned the Larry P case
And it said black kids in California can not be given IQ test
And I seen it and when I was reading it I was like
Can't be true
In this day and age
She said she immediately thought of Nicholas
Didn't look Caucasian out of my kids look Caucasian you can tell their biracial
Is this going to affect him like
Are people going to be making decisions about what test he can and can't have because of the color of his skin is spark me to call the school and find
I doubt this is true
And he told us it was a 1968
Court ruling
And it was true
Now just for the record the case was decided in 79 not 68 but whatever at that point were you thinking
I was dumbfounded
This ruling has lasted all these years he explained that like
The ruling band tests that were found to be biased against African-American students
I did not care
My son was going to have
The same rights
Any other child
My wife and I we
I will just told him that's not right
After that first conversation Pam and Ricky ended up having a series of meetings with
The school
Some of which ended in yelling for I threatened I told him I'll go to his I'll sue you guys
And eventually after a few of these meetings
The school administrator came back to them and said
Basically look we know you're upset
Here's what we can do
Do you do you remember
The offer that was given to us
Well you said that
Our child would be able to take that test
If we just put them down as Caucasian
That ridiculous
Offer if you Mark Nicholas down Caucasian
He will get the test
But if you choose
Tumarkin African-American
And he will not
Superintendent said you had no
Mark
Either or
Bye
Remember this coming up will you track down the school administrator who was on the other end of that conversation my name is
Dr. Blaine cohick in a different School District now
But back when he was meeting with him and Ricky he says
I was in a situation of really having to defend this ruling
He says win10 Ricky got it
Said he actually called the states
School Board
Askmen
What are we supposed to do about this
The
Only resolution I was given to kind of
Help
Was that
The parent
Has the right to determine what race the child is
I turn on looked at him I looked at my husband I look back at him I said so you want me
Didn't I
My husband
Heritage
For my son to have this right
That really got
I
Would agree
You know it really doesn't make a lot of sense and I I was
Totally pissed at this point I've had many friends tell me
That parents became irate
Disappointed very upset like frustrated very upset I ended up talking to a bunch of school psychologists to work
In the California public
I'm James hiramoto Panabaker and they confirmed for me that situations like what happened with Pam and Ricky
They're not
Baton usual
Sometimes
A reaction might be
What why not
Or what if I say that it's okay like as a parent can I just like sign something to prove that it's okay that
I don't care
I know what happens if they check African American and Caucasian
If it's marked anywhere
There is there is no nothing at talks about
Percentage
Have you had
Kids you've assessed
Where you thought like
Well maybe they're African-American and so just to be safe I'm going to not use my IQ test
I have
That's so weird
It is
It is a very awkward situation
Basic question
Two two questions
Refers to schools
Use IQ tests as much these days as they used to
Back in the Larry P days when the band was put in place
Not quite as much as I used to but they still use them at
So
I'm more than a million kids a year
Forgiving the West
Which is that
IQ test that we talked about all of the last episode
This still the most widely used IQ test
Since then
Lots of other IQ tests have been made and released the Arthur point scale
Cattell horn in infant intelligence scale
Columbia Mental maturity scale all of these tests are actually banned for black kids in California still have to get salads
Developmental schedule
Goodenough Harris drawing test Merrill Palmer preschool performance test
What happened
Raven's Progressive matrices
Have the test changed
Mason a while
Have the places that were found to be biased
Biased
Yeah well that question led me to
Name Alan Kaufman
Trying to park
I don't know what no problem
Okay
, is driving he's a professor at the Yale medical school and he says the test
Have changed
And he would know
Because he was one of the first people
To start changing
Victorious
30 + 19
I was working for the psychological Corporation in New York
City Island with a young guy at the time
I start working with a psychologist named David wax
David wechsler invented
The Whisk
The tests we talked about all last episode
David wechsler
Really founder
He was like this giant in the field
And Allen this 20-something nobody
My assignment
Whisker help him
Revised
Now this was happening right at the Larry Petri was getting started
Local Department says the test company had pretty much accepted like
We need to change
But Wexler not too much
Go to his apartment
East side of New York City
And they would go question by question what is the color of Ruby
Goffman argued that question is clearly biased
I mean the correct answer on the test is rubies are red but a
Your family had more money you will more likely
To know what a ruby was
Andy Kaufman says Ruby was a popular name in the black community
So certain kids might think what he was referring to people
Not gen
That item was eliminated but I understand it didn't always go. Either way with them
It was a little vain that he had him his
But I knew when you got upset
It would start
Post a little
And he was
So upset
I thought it was going to
He says they had knock-down-drag-out fight about questions
But many of the questions we talked about in the last episode
Ended up being removed
Bunch of Change by the end of this process how much of the test was different
Probably 40% different
Since that original revision
The whiskey has been revived
Three more time
Hello Susie
Yes this is Susie Rayford I'm the primary developer of the wechsler intelligence scale
I write the questions designed the research plan and Susie says the test today is way different
But it was back in the saddle
Facts about 10 years ago they replaced every question on the
And then we also see
Statistically analyze the items to see if
She says they're now able to do these assertive Advanced statistical comparisons where they can compare the
Have responses of
Black kids to rich white kids
Poor black kids to poor white kids
Go through that kind of scrutiny and one group performs differently on a question they'll get rid of
You you welcome mat because you don't want to put something out that's wrong or that's going to hurt people
The biggest change though is the way the test is standardized
Usually tries to be representative of the sensor
This is Brandon Campbell against the former school psychologist we heard from in the first episode
How many African Americans were included the whiskey
Is a
Port of Call New Orleans
A population that are apparently followed the US Census
Are much better
So
Given how much the test has
Changed
How do you feel about the fact that the band
Still
Dislike
Stihl.
Psychologist from giving IQ test to black kids in California
Yeah it's ridiculous I I think I
When the state
Dictates
What psychologist can and can't do
That to me is a problem
Does Brandon says an IQ test can give him useful information about a kid regardless of their race
When you're talking about IQ test you're talking about
Ability
Your ability to
See things visually
And be able to answer
Questions around
Patterns
Writing so you can
Target
Particular
Skills around
Cognition
Hello are you there now
Yes can you hear me clearly
I can
Admit I didn't completely understand what Brandon meant
Until I talk to this guy
My name is John Cato and I'm a dad
Young man
Who experienced a learning disability in his young life
Johnson Counter with the letter P ban happened about 20 years
Is living in Santa Monica California the time works and transportation he was running the bus system there
And I his son just
He was
Hunting a complete seven or eight is in first grade and his teacher told John that Justin was having a really hard
Hard time with reading
Even if you gave him the simplest of things to read
He couldn't grasp what you read
The teacher wasn't really sure what was going on there wondering if this just a reading specific thing or is there
Broader cognitive disability happening
So John decided to talk to a specialist and he recommended first that I get an IQ test
And so I went to his Elementary School
And requested that from his principal
And she informed me that
He could not have an IQ test because
And the state of California was that legal and when the principal said that what went through your mind
I thought it was crazy I said you know she was trying to explain to me
Why it was not allowed she knew there was some court case has he got it
Understood
Remember 7 to take an IQ test when he was in his 20s
Trying to get ahead and army. Officer on that test I never heard of
Like Magento
Why when you grow up in a very poor neighborhood
Basic colors
Blue red
Purple yellow white
Brown I didn't know what that question meant unless
When it came to his son
If taking a test
Even if it was by
Could help him
Sobeit
And I understand you know that the economic and environmental impact
About IQ test
But
My son needed one that accepting
The argument because of his ethnicity
They were prohibited from giving him a task
I first asked if I could wave it
Is there anyway I can wave
And I was told no
My honesty said well
Okay then he's not African American
His mother is Caucasian and my history of my family
This mix race
So let's reclassify
She said I guess you can do that and then I said to her
Look at the
Certainty of that
Ultimately Justin ended up getting IQ tested by that specialist
Just outside the school system
And in the end the test
Hope revealed that Justin had a very
Pacific problem
What was determined was
Justin has his imagination
So when he was reading when he was younger
He couldn't separate
John says Justin Woods
Start to read a sentence but before he could get too far into it even just a few words
He would start to imagine what was going on and just get lost in that universe
He tried to read
Go off and live it
And you can't do that like he would just never get very far before his imagination we take
And the IQ test help them figure that out
In a way yeah because
Thing about an IQ test is it made up of all these sub test
Into the psychologist with able to use it to figure out that Justin was fine with Matt
It memory was fine
I had a good vocabulary processing speed and
Puzzle solving abilities were fine
So they're able to rule all these things out and investigate the root of the problem
Which turn out
Beat his really active imagination it was a book
One poke
I got Justin Reid
Enemies Harry Potter
He wouldn't put that book down
He was step Layton tonight and stop breathing it
That was the end of his problem
A reading
Brandon gamble cuz he's worked with hundreds of kids like just
When IQ test help to figure out what was going on
The Bedford Brandon says like the Larry P band isn't necessary anymore
He says
The thing that keeps her to keep his eye on now when it comes to these tests isn't so much the racial bias question
But something kind of bigger
The basic idea that an IQ test
Could be used to
Define kid
There's a. And I would say from like the 1930s all the way through the 80s
People would just give
Biq or cognitive pet
This is what happened to Darrell from the first episode
And of course the test was skewed against him because of racial bias
But Brendan says
Even if it wasn't
Even if there had been a white kid
Making a decision any decision about his future by just using an IQ test
Affordable
You really don't know that get it's only a snapshot
Window of sitting down with this kid
The bariatric Clinic
I can't be the totality of who that child is
To really understand who your kid is
And every psychologist I talked to said this
You have to spend a lot of time with
Visiting the home
Like observing a child in the classroom
Like extensive interviews with their families especially if you're working cross-cultural there's some things that you may not
Understand
It sounds like your perspective on the IQ test is that
Like
If you can you can evaluate
Students without.
IQ test if you can't do IQ testing there's 99 other things you can do
Weight sedan
Why do it at all
I mean like I guess
I get
That it can be helpful
Will sometimes like in the case of the kid with Harry Potter
Really what it was it help the kid was Harry Potter
That's what helps the neck Siri better so
If we're in a situation now where we have all of these other tools available
IQ test however
Useful it can be
It also has some very bad mojo
Historically
Attached to it
What is it actually still worth keeping around
Yeah I found myself thinking that a lot
You know just like from a cure
Cost-benefit
Perspective
Maybe it needs to go
Yeah and
And that feeling until we came across this one story that
Pretty much completely change my mind about
After a quick break
Hello this is Kelly from Tokyo
Radiolab is supported in part
By Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing
Public understanding of Science and
Technology
In the modern world
More information about Sloan at
Www.
Loan.
We have an eviction epidemic and too often we fail to grasp what that is
But it isn't sometimes when you look at stuff on the news why she is somewhere on the pole dancing and she should be home
We're children in the answer is if they feel like I need to get a security deposit I'm going to go out there
Can make it happen I'm Brooke Gladstone with the new series The Scarlet unmasking America's
Eviction crisis listen on the media. Org eviction
Hate walking back to g a regular mini-series on Pat Walters
Okay Pat so what is the story that you were referring to the
Totally change your mind about IQ test
At well I'm going to tell you but
First
Let me do a quick digression
Maybe take a step back
First
In talking about the ups and downs of the IQ test
Turns out
So much of it has to do with
How we talk about it
So I want to go back to an interview I did with
Siddhartha Mukherjee
Why is a cancer genetic
Talking about
We talked to Michael G in the first episode of the series about the history of IQ tests and G which is the shorthand for judge
General intelligence
Can an inner interview keycap
Circling back to this
One idea
About
Language
One thing that we learned over and overalls from the history of Medicine
Is that the way you define terms the way you define anything
Makes an enormous difference
As to how you evaluate
At what values
Society places on it
I can give you a thousand examples from the history of cancer
One gave me. It was really interesting
Has to do with breast
The wood radical mastectomy
Contain the word radical in it
Because it was meant to addressed
The term route which apparently is what radical means of or pertaining to the root of something
That amore
Socially and cuts
Culture V
Into a word that meant aggressive and Brazen and therefore the right thing to do for a woman with a terrible disease
Workington extreme Mukherjee says more and more people inside their cancer as a
Extreme start to feel like
That would be the appropriate response
Even if
It might not
Disease
These words that we use in medicine and science are extraordinary important intelligence
The thing you got to remember it right off the bat
Is that the word
Intelligence is a colloquial word
I just cannot emphasize that enough
Like the concept of intelligence we predates modern Western science
Yes you can look at
Ancient literature and you'll see that some people are are smarter than others like Odysseus is really smart intelligent
Port Richey again
China
It has been defined to
Social and cultural practice and varies from one Society to another has varied from one Society to another
And for the history of human beings
We have found that perfectly acceptable
Everybody understood that there are lots of different ways to be intelligent
Be intelligent just meant to be able to understand
Should be a million different things
Until 1904
Mitchell Spearman came along and said we have their flag on intelligence is defined as
Your score
On this test
The fact is
According to both of these guys
It might be a lot more complicated
There is something
Captured in the IQ test called G
I don't have a problem with g
Maybe send a shiver down my spine
Spine because of human history
Problem with it fundamentally it's a fact
But I do have an argument
Making a simple one-to-one translation
Between that idea
And the sting this word that carries
So much
Value and meaning
The word being
Is there a better word
Yeah well
We should have called it something like cold was it function I mean a lot of the researchers I talk
Talk to psychologist even the test makers
Steam to be using words like cognitive function or cognitive ability more when I saw
All I mean is
He look I'm using word intelligence even though I said at the start of the movie
Calling intelligence a lot
Play Mukerji says like what an IQ test measures is your ability to navigate in problems
Your ability to navigate in problems
Yeah I don't really know what that means like I can picture problem space
I can't be more
Pacific done that because that is exactly what it is
Sometimes in an analogy
Switches
You meet a person who is a good General athlete
Premier bike
And when you see them manipulating their way to space
They have a particular way of manipulating themselves through space because they understand
Physical space
According to Mukerji problems faced
Is
I know like that
Bite
Mental
Like how well can you move ideas pictures numbers around your head
Your ability to navigate and problems
Nipple hard
Spell that gives me something
Deputy of space there cuz it's
Boundary
It sounded
A substance
Yeah. Everything is just a space
It a space and it leaves
A lot of stuff out exactly
But regardless of
What you call it
Even if you call it intelligence
G
Whatever
If you use the test in a different way
At
A different altitude let's say
It can change the world
Barry German
And not just
In a bad way
Like if the IQ test has
Heroic moment in American history
It is her like stepped up
And saved a lot of the people that was designed to hurt
Interest
Okay
Tell me more tell me more
It's there early 1970s and the stories about this guy named herb needleman
He was a needleman was pediatrician
In Philadelphia at 6 feet tall brown hair blue eyes intense
Kind of arrogant guy very sure of himself
Beth Lydia denworth I'm a science writer
She wrote a book about her he was really engaging
Did that pointy was fighting the Vietnam War stuff you've gone to Vietnam and started a nonprofit or he would
Bring injured
Kids back to the US for treatment wow
Dislike
Students like hanging out with him in here in history of crazy stories
Anyway
When needleman was
Training to be a pediatrician
I was referred a child who was very sick little girl that's hurting them in talking to Atmore a gun
On the NPR show.
Technician
Needleman actually passed away a few years ago and they were nice enough to let us
Use clips from their interview
This little girl shows up little three-year-old girl and Hispanic girl
From the local neighborhood was a poor neighborhood where the hospital is located
And this little girl was really in terrible shape
She was lethargic
Couldn't talk
It was a cute lead poisoning diagnosis and
I knew what to do because I've had a couple extras on it it was known that led to make
You sick but it was thought
The conventional wisdom was it could only make you sick at really high.
When I started the conventional wisdom was that 60 micrograms per deciliter was a toxic dose
For comparison
Today
The CDC the Centers for Disease Control
Have what color reference level
Which is that anything over 5 micrograms per deciliter
Is
Control arm
Planning fact we know now that there is no safe level of lead
In anybody's body but especially in children
This is an era when lead is all over
Everywhere all the houses were painted with waitlist
Standard instant payment the reason LED was put in paint
Was that made the pink go on the wall more smoothly
Sticky add Sprite and also when paint chips off and you get a big feast
It letting is actually quite Suites real little kids
Sweet and crunchy
Soap herbs are in Philadelphia
Jesus kid with acute lead poisoning
After her
He's another
And another
Another
He knows
High levels of lead are toxic
Restart the Wonder
What about low-level
I decided I would pursue it question was
How so
People knew that lead
In the body went into bones and it went it mimics calcium in the body so it would be anywhere in the body
That calcium would be found the tissue to look at his bone which can't do that you can't stick needles and kids
You certainly can't go cutting out pieces of their bone
He knew we couldn't get bone
And then one day sitting there in his office at this community health clinic
In North Philadelphia
He looked at children playing in the schoolyard of this Elementary School
And he thought
Are the answer
He Partners up with a dentist
Annie at the dentist ask
The parents to bring in their kids
Baby teeth
Right away the parents are like well we've got a little bit of a
Have to Ferry problem here
You know the kids the kids are not just going to
Give away their teeth I'm not going to
Fund your research study
With my tooth fairy money
2 herb like Newman went out and he got all these silver dollars
The dentist Drive the kids to give him the teeth he then tested the teeth Moser due to flood levels
And brings in a bunch of the kids give him a series of tests
Extensive battery of neuropsychological tests
Including
IQ test
And what he discovered the key thing he discover
Is that if you get this a little bit more last in your body
Like for every 10 micrograms per deciliter more lead in your blood
Extremely small amount
Your IQ score
Balls
Four Points
So if you're
Exposed to just a tiny bit more LED you get
Four Points
Go to court Dumber
On the IQ test
Eventually yeah his Four Points a lot so that the thing about it is like
The accused
Test setup
Takana put everybody on this bell curve
Where you at
Most of
Most everybody is in the middle
And then you've got
Assertive Tails rehab
The people who are
Score really high and the people who score
Really low
I would be around 1:30 low would be
Tanner and 70
Enter four points in the middle doesn't make that thing
But if you think about it much larger
What we're actually talking about is Shifting and in Thai
Higher population.
What that means is
The top you end up with
Half as many people were going to score above 130
But I feel like a lot
Yeah and twice as many people
Scoring below
Wow when we published that in the New England Journal of Medicine
1979 it had a considerable impact
It made national news when he he had done it
He had shown
That a long-term low-level lead exposure
With actually connected
Tua kids
Experience
I am in life
The study led the government to ban the use of lead in house paint
Put limits on the amount of gasoline not too surprisingly
The LED Industries
We're not happy
And they tried to discredit
Permuda wynd
Who's the nasty. In our lives
The Houston of scientific misconduct
Big fight over whether his 1979 Boston study
Was accurate
Long story short
They realized it multiple times
And the numbers held up
So then would happen
In the mid-80s 1985 I arrived let have been reduced some
Any environment but then there are no constraints on the human mind
No walls around the human Spirit except those we are ourselves erect
And you decide
Let's cut the industry of break
You know what loosen things back
Back up again
And there was a guy at EPA named Joel Schwartz who had been hired as an economic analyst there Joel Shore
Is asked by his bosses in about 1985
To calculate
How much industry would save
If
The regulations on letting gasoline work
Lessons which was what the Reagan Administration wanted to do
And he says
But what about the health
Effects
And he's told you know
Just the way it is is what they want
So what he does so Joel Schwartz it was a clever guy
He says okay I will do this job I will calculate how much industry will save if they don't have
Regulate letting gasoline
And that number was about a hundred million dollars
But then he did something else he did the first
Major
Cost benefit analysis
Just that linked
Health effects
An economics
Never really
Innovative thing that Joel Schwartz did
Was to also calculate
The cost to Society of leaving lead in the gasoline
And the way he did that
Was that he used those
4 IQ points
They did it and economic analysis where they were able to figure out that for each
Point change in IQ
That equated
To 1% change in the wage rate
Again on a population level
With every step down and IQ
There's a connection to how much money somebody can earn
You got lower levels of educational attainment and ultimately lower levels of learning
So when he did this calculus
The industries could save $109 if they have lead
Society if you count based on needleman's IQ for IQ points the cost
Society of leaving lead in gasoline
Was close to a billion dollars
Well that's based on
Lost education lost wages and increased health
He write this report gives it to one of the
Top officials at the
ETA this guy named Joseph Cannon who had pretty much made up his mind that he was not going to regulate the leather industry anymore
Didn't need regulation there was no need from a regulation for apparently he looks at this report
And he said you just cannot look away
You cannot look away
January 1st 1986
The EPA
Effectively banned LED from gasoline
Over the next few decades
The average blood level of Americans
Dropped by 90%
Blood lead levels around the world the end of forks today
Was a pretty important fact
The thing that sled Story made me realize is that
The IQ test
Certain thinking abilities
Whatever you want to call it
Intelligent
Problem space
And when you need to find out if
Like an environmental toxin is affecting
The wake
I think having the standardized measurement of that
Is really powerful
Enter something like the IQ test
Lets you
See these almost invisible
Like subtle effects
Sunmart groups
Two people and after that led thing
There been many many many studies but you just you can go on PubMed and search like IQ test
Environmental effects and you find all of these amazing
Realities where people use IQ test
To look at the way
Smog effects
Kids thinking abilities or
Or like violence in the neighborhood
Reminds me of what the judge
Said in the last episode in the in the ruling that
Did essentially
IQ tester social evil masquerading as empiricism
This is kind of the universe
And it's basically the same test I mean anything we don't stay in the web story
Patricia dad or stay here
Is that
Herb needleman
He did the studies
Only white kid
People can say like oh the
The poor kids are scoring lower because they're black
He did it only in Waco
You did it only on white kids because he was worried because
A lot of dick
Cork it to her being affected by lead wear black and other minority kids
And he was worried that if you took
A sample of
You know
Affluent white kids
Who had low light exposure
And he took
Group of poor kids
Highlight exposure who also were
Black
The people would say oh the
The poor kid
Squirrel or not because
I've let exposure but because they're black
And black people are less intelligent than white
Wow so he actually he actually segregated his
Is sample
Yeah so that he could avoid bias
Their bias
Exactly
Yes so at the end of the day
I don't think
You can say that the
IQ test
Or even the whole idea of measuring human intelligence
In this way
Is anyone thing
The test isn't inherently evil in this way they thought people
You know not psychologists early but regular people think
About it
But
It does have this
There's some power in it and it was designed to do a certain
Sing a bad
Thing
But if you just go all the way back
The eugenic Roots
That's
Like always
In there but it's not the only thing that's
Sounds like agents
The Shield episode
08 4
Unknown entity that still has power
Centuries
Wait what are you talking about what is NOA for it like what what is that unknown phenomena on
Wiccan Marvel Comics
That was submitted for psychologists Brandon Gimbel throughout an interview he was
Talking about the IQ test but he was referring to this Marvel Comics organization called agents of
Shieldon
Tetrick Homeland interagency Logistics
Division
Because every so often the heroes in that show will find this
Object they called in 08
An unknown phenomenon
It's an object they know is
But you don't understand
What kind of
Or how to use it and sometimes these unknown phenomena can
You know it you don't even know what it is but if you touch it
Take you back in time if you could
Disrupt you
Toxic
You can even kill you
Orchids
It's an inanimate object
South but once
It activated it becomes
Extra
He says
It's a little bit like that
Wiki IQ test
The science
Intelligence
Turn became that the moment G
Walk into the room
Powerful thing
With many different potential
We're still struggling with
This episode was reported by Rachel khoo
Ustick and I and produced by Rachel Nye and Jad abumrad
Without from the kahabka music by Alex overington and fact-checking by diet
Special thanks to Lee Romney and Lee rose beer for these this song all the ants
Relapse mini-series G is supported in part by science sandbox
Assignment Foundation initiative dedicated to engaging everyone with the process of Sia
Oh one last thing
At the end of the show we often have a listener read the credits
Realize it's really proud of listeners all over the world and we would love to hear you on the show
It's super easy if you're interested go to radiolab.org credits
At to record the credits and a message from one of our sponsors
That's radiolab.org
Bosch
Credit
Make the listening will be back with the third episode of G
2 weeks
This is Alex Alder calling from Bozeman Montana on my cross-country Road
Radiolab was created by jad abumrad and is produced by Soren wheeler
Dylan Keith is our director of sound design Susie lechtenberg is our executive producer
Includes Simon Adler
Becca Bressler Rachel Cusick David gamble Bethel have to Traci Hines Nora Keller Mac guilty Robert krulwich
Eddie McEwen lots of Nasser
Pat Walters Molly Webster
With help from shamea Ali Audrey Quinn W Harry Fortuna room Samuel and Bonnie Leonard and Neal.
Car tax checker is Michelle Harris