Are you awake
Northern listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
Are you surprised that this is so popular
Surprised
You know what I'm surprised about I'm surprised that
This morning I was walking the subway and I was like man I want to live
I guess I'm a little surprised that myself
Take a note Robert
Fantastic day and it was amazing
Undeniable
Okay I'm Janice and Robert Radiolab
Today a story
Arab order Alex Jung Hye
You podcast to go about Gary Hart
And the moment
When how we covered politics changed this story is about a similar changes happening right now right in front of her
Rides in South Korea we're going to travel a few thousand miles
Expecting this kind of story
Get totally flipped
It's not about politics this time it's about music
Young fans music pieces you already heard but really it's a puzzle
If you really admire someone and love them is how much
How much do you want to know about
Stop the music
Yeah is it tell me everything
Or tell me nothing
And if someone does try and tell you everything at what point do you say
Stop
Ready I'm ready
Where do where do you wear shoes
Well I think if we get to like the moment that I am very excited about I need to kind of give you guys
A little bit of of the world and which all of this
Is going to happen
And so we're going to start
With this woman when I told my friends about it
I kind of described it as a prison
What is a prison you decide to walk into
Okay so this
This is Sarah Wolfgang I was a former trainee for
K-Pop group in
Korea
And I'm here to talk about that
Sarah is korean-american she was born in America but I actually grew up in Korea
Parents
Both worked for the military and you are living in Seoul
And Sarah says that her whole
Kpop Adventures
It all started with her because when she was growing up I really never liked
School so my parents were kind of wanting me to do so
Something else
You still wanted me to finish
School but
They encourage her to try at acting
2Go. Additions tryout for
School plays
And High School
15 years old
10th grade at her headshots ended up getting passed to a South
Screen record
And
When we were see the phone call they were like oh hey you want to come in audition for a K-Pop group and I was
I actually did I did I really didn't want
To do it but then she thought maybe this will lead to an acting job so I went in and then they're like okay they put me in front of
The camera and then they asked me to
Sing
And I'm not
The best singer
No matter the K-pop
Everything you know can be touched up
Really well
To make a long story short they end up offering
Of more than 5 year
And as part of that contract
We were asked to move into the dorms
What are these
Facilities that's all the agencies
Is Hartford for their idols
Training we described it like a
The boarding school all the kids kind of live together
Or seven other girls
And it was here that Sarah says the company basically kept them under lock and key
Lock Us in there
But we weren't allowed to
It's like one of those cockroach
Prisons
Or like those ant prison
You can walk in but you can't lock out your way why is she doing this again
What
Let me explain to you guys just like how phenomena
Really huge
K-pop
Kpop actually started in Korea in the early 90s
But like in the last five or so years if he's just build out into the
The world
And by some estimates it was generating like around 5
Billion dollars
And then if you throw in like
Kdrama K soap operas
We just called the how you wave
That how you wave in 2012 was valued at 83 billion dollars
Jesus
And nearly all of this
Is based on a kind of
Fantasy
Because K-pop stars are
You know products of fantasy world
That's professor
Computer studies at University of California Santa Barbara I study K-pop industry
You know
Stars are the important forms of Manga and Anime and all these
Unrealistic
Figures
That don't exist in real life
So
They have to have
Just so really beautiful face beautiful body and excessively long legs
Pale skin flowing hair they're not
The creature of this world
They should have been
Yeah what they own that can only
Exist in fantasy world and that fantasy that's what they're trying to manufacture
In those storms
Like they wanted us to lose weight
So
We would wake up at like
For 5 a.m. in the morning and then go hiking Sarah says after the height they'd come back eat breakfast which usually cancel
Turn up lettuce and they have dance classes singing classes and then we have lessons of I think
They're calling humble lessons we're basically this guy would show up to the dorm
To Bow correctly
So like we would have to down Unison so that we seemed as like one big happy group
They weren't allowed to have cell phone computers
Or
A relationship of any kind
All companies pretty much
Don't want you
You to be in a relationship
And in fact
Chicken told me that in 2011
The one of the members of
21 which of the girl group managed by YG Entertainment
Revealed.
The management said they should not be dating before age 29
What
They should be dating because Stars belong to the public to the fam
And I was like a purity thing
Now that pure and angelic
Virgin Madonna image
This by the way is K-pop writer AJ park editor-at-large at soompi.com
Like girl groups
Please call Mike Nations fairies
You know they had this
Securitas
Image to them in the boy bands 2
Because.
Being single
Make some more marketable and appealing
Images of vets that's the main take
Of course there's all kinds of
Cultural observation
Things that you can make about this but the main driver here
Economic
The founders of Kpop new
In the early nineties at the fans would love to starves even more if the stars weren't just beautiful
Perfect
But they also seemed
Somehow available
You would be surprised how many K-pop stars come out and be like I've never had my first kiss
Cadillac 1920
8 years old
I haven't had my first kiss will it be with you you know ink feeding the fantasy kind of thing
America I mean
Didn't you feel weirder
Are stranger or something or what
Win like
I don't know
Catherine Zeta-Jones married that guy
Whatever his name is
Yeah yeah I don't even think about its name
Okay you always going on about Meryl Streep
Is she married for them to me but not she doesn't know it she is married to a to a very quiet man is a Sculptor
How does it make you feel how I look around to show to see
What is he
My point is is it that I mean America the American celebrity culture has fantasy woven into
Yeah but there's a big difference
Friends in Korea
The fantasy world it is
Seoul
Friendly control
Way more than in America
According to Sikhism
And it's controlled not just by the agency
Foot by the fence to the extent that it defies all of our common sense
Meaning I'll give you an example
That's what I heard from Professor
Kim and also writer
Bacco on the editor-in-chief of Soul Beats KPOP
Okay
2008 there was this new girl group
Girls Generation Girls Generation
Girls Generation member all girls group that was like
Ocean appearing on live music shows and like
Variety shows being promoted as like
Cute and you know like the ideal girlfriend kind of idea
Girls Generation would appear with boy bands you know who are also promoting at the same time
Fruit such as Super Junior
Ss501
Dbsk
Like standing next to each other on stage talking to each other during variety shows
And this is where we kind of get into the cultural
There are several times when they're on stage with one or more of these boy band
And there
Kind of taking the microphone from the host or whatever
And kind of just nodding their head where the boy bands are like doing these
Deep bow
Some of the fans are seeing this and they're thinking that
Disrespectful
Why would that be respectful thinking is that since Girls Generation is a new group
They should be buying much more deeply than theirs
In base or there their seniors
Bing
A rookie group is a big deal in Korea because
Seniority is something that people hold very strongly
And so as a rookie you have to show deference to the superior Hino senior groups
Just in the box that's how some of the fans were taking it but I mean aside from all that and this is the key is that
Some of the fans thought that the Girls Generation girls were
Flirting
With some of the boy bands
Little Saigon glances or
Teasing them it so that interaction seeing that
Fans were very very very
Upset about that
And so
All the fans of the
Three groups that three boy bands
Got together
And decided to do a black ocean
What is that
Get that ring
Fast forward to June 7th 2008 all of those bands that were on those TV shows are playing this big
K-pop concert
Event called
Train concert
A huge stadium shows like more than 40000 fans and
Told me that there's one thing you need to know about vans
About K-pop
At Atlanta
They all have lights.
And they come in different colors give each man has its own color
Super Junior for example has and when they appear on stage you see this
Blue light sticks waiting in support of their stars on stage
Do they play for a while
When ss501 comes out
Cool place Jeff turns to light green Show Goes On
TVXQ come from stage they were like the biggest fan of
The time and then up code Thousand thousands of these ruby red
Literally
At some point Girls Generation
And here's a pretty much as soon as they walk on stage
All the people in the audience
Turn off
Their lightstick
What suddenly
It was blackout in the whole Auditorium
Everybody stop clapping screaming
Silence
We seem like a whole like everybody 40,000 people yes
And if you look at look up pictures of it it's it was a stadium performance
The entire stadium was black
No way yes way
What is this picture
Oh my God
So this is totally black
This is a Photoshop no cuz if you look down in the corner you can kind of see the pink
Girls Generation section pink
Nails black
Girls Generation had to sing and dance
Stoodis Island
Krowd
Had anything like this ever happened before
How on Earth did they pull that off
How could you get this many people doing the same thing
Okay so the way that these
Show is happy
At least at these dream concert is at different sections of the auditorium belong to different fan
Oh so they sell it is Zone seating
There's this moment where some of the fan club leaders
I stood up
And held up the signs
Quiet
This that this is.
Setting
Yeah
He soon I've ever heard
A little blink of an eye but that's
Is the difference if you if you would allow me to frame for a second
What are we learned so far we've learned that this is a global phenomenon
Total make the global phenomenon born of the nightmare
Of these Stars
Who seem to be tightly held in check by everybody
Play the fans the agency's everybody
And this sort of tight
Control is how it operated
Quite a few decades
But
And this is why I want to do this whole story in the first place
Just a couple years ago
In walks this guy
And he just messes everything up
Radiolab
We sent interpreter with a makeover
To the Gangnam
Insult
Gangnam Style
Names meaning Young Girl
But you know he told me to call him mister
Hello
Hello hey
I hopped on the line for my studio New York get started
Yeah you
Okay so here's the story in early 2000s
Literally he was working at a news organization called
Sports
We should all kinds of things not
They also
Business
Taemin
Documentary on eating for money
Who's actually in charge of
All the online
While he was there I think
Say that he took
His reporting
Very seriously
What he always had this idea in his
20 month old
Who do I see about in Islam believe any content that can be published that's possible to
Popular should be freely published
What kind of culture that would be better to have but he was a guy who believed in an independent
Real Sonu
That there are certain things that he just couldn't report on
Hamilton
Counselor
Certain subjects like politics
Dangerous
How
Hawaii
What did we talk about
We we actually need to back up a little bit
Put this into a little bit of
Contacts
Between like after the Korean War
Screensavers
Cities in the 80
South Korea was under a series of military dick
And there was
Basically a censorship of the press
Things a lot better in the 90s when
They turn to civilian rule
But even today the government still has a branch that goes around the internet and
And delete website
Further content
So this is this is like
The world in which the
The Press is living in it
So getting back to mr. Lee
Sportsseoul having dreams of Independence
Feels like politics is a little tricky
Three does what to me feels like a little bit of a trojan horse
How you doing
Basically says if I can't do independent reporting
Politics
I'll just
Sneaking into celebrity
So
Hollywood news and media in the UK
Are you finished
The sun has weekly TMZ what he study TMZ that's what he said
You know how they take their pictures how close do they get cuz there isn't there was Paparazzi
And we decided to apply that to South Korea so what kind what kind of tactics did you use to
To get the photos in the first place
Oh Nana.
Hiding in the car
Their first Target were these two stars
John Young who is an idol from a boy band called shiny
Cute band
And an actress
Chester name is shin se-kyung
Thank you. Come get y'all seen in today
To go through
The information gathering Pro
Process to the tailed both these stars on and off
1 months
Well she's dead
Sense of their movement
You know and they figure out they have this pattern of meeting up
In front of her apartment
Really early in the morning like 3 in the morning
And they take these walks
So
Late October 2010 if it came to a point where we could we couldn't miss the opportunity
Call this I guess they call this the D-Day
Could imagine that if you didn't go down
The dating date but I think is
Pretty funny
And on this particular day one of Mr Wiesel
Reporters steaks out the
The apartment
And the two stars meet up to
To take a walk
And
You get the very first
Paparazzi photos
As far as we know in Korea
Where the first look like
The Bistro Reserve
So
But I think they're so cute it's these two items
You know walking down the street
Hand in hand
Under these yellow street lights
Images look like they're in their own little world there's this one photo where he's
Pulling back her hair
And I think he's putting like an earbud in her Pierre and there may be there sharing
The song you're listening to a song together he's got her purse on his shoulder you know he
Holding her bags
What happens when the photographer guy runs up and goes
Sports all kind of Drew this line they're like
We're going to
Keep back into
Distance from the Sun
Guilin
Coming through a car window do they see the guy know they don't and that's why these photos there it's not like that typical like hand in the face
Face photo they just look totally
Serene This Moment Beast
Two Innocents are truly innocent they have no reason to expect anyone to be out there at all right because you know before that
Comment their work paparazzi
Photographers
Stocking celebrity
Please like this
This is eating right here this is eating
Antifa Cedar Android
Ketones
Miserly said right before they published
And this is sort of become their tradition
All of the reporters got together and stayed in the office all night
Pins and needles
Because he knows they didn't know they didn't know what was going to happen
Are people going to be outraged are they going to be
Totally excited about this
They just had no idea what
What is going to happen
And you also will have no idea what's going to happen
Until after the break
Hey this is Mark from Astoria Queens
Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloan
Www
. Sloan
Ductwork
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
We're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments
Brilliance
Basically I want to hear about this
Times when a kid you know did something
It just means you lean back and say
Wow
How did they do that
Maybe it was the moment that I
Kids started reading back
To you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lesson
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of their musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed are ready music
In the margin of the geometry
We're interested in the specific moments where a kid does something super smart
But it doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story
T-shirt
Go to radiolab.org
Brilliance
Record a short Audiomack
Again that's radiolab.org / brilliance
Thank you so much
Jad Robert Radiolab back to our story from reporter Alex
So when we left off we were talking about leaving goo
Mr.lee
And
Steamed hams
Just captured the first
Paparazzi
In South Korea they had taken a picture of
Shistars
The photos were pretty dark and
Super granny
Tulipop ratify
Shot in the night
Probably from a zoom lens
Like thousands of you
Lock on Timberland hard to tell the photograph
Android
They all got together in their office they were just about to publish no idea what was going to happen and
When we first
Publish them
Nothing
Really really
Seriously oh come on I'm kidding
There was General response
People are crazy
Oh my goodness the photos went viral
It just took the whole country
There was an incredible amount of web traffic
So much that our servers were breaking down
Two people click
Oh yeah what it all comes down to it people really want to know
At first they just you know they did
Inundated the website china wiki
Photos
But then they were like oh
Oh no
So then they rushed over to the fancy
And
Four of the websites from the the boy band the guy
Crash
Infections website which is called mini humpy page
It just gets flooded with comments Boomers file comments about how the fence
Betrayed
People were like posting deface pictures of her in
Typical
Texas Waze
She got the
Front
This is always the way it is right
Just like an America that's the way it happens in Korea
You know when I talked to leaving you he was the first one to recognize
Klonopin
Usually when this kind of Scandal breaks it's the
The woman who gets it worse
Yeah yeah
At what time
Vedette
How it go how did the agency
Shock
In the beginning totality
Companies were not
Cuz their official statement would be like weed and talk to
About this like where we had no idea
And you could see that the companies are struggling
There's actually you know a couple times later on where
Got the fans got really crazy and they would actually
Protest
At like their live shows
And then pretty much the next day like after the protest
The idle at the center of that Sandalwood
Kind of vanish
Like they were just
Take a indefinite
Hiatus from Alder
Promotional Act
Like you mean like the agency's just yank them
I mean yeah that was
The suggestion yeah
Did the agency say anything about that to you no one would go on the record
With me but I did talked
To some people over email
And they said that
You know
When fans react
Weather kind of
Forced to
To take drastic action
So they
Kind of confirmed that they were disappearing items confirmed with me that they were
Taking a
But here's my ends up high
Federal-Mogul
Calling says you know that's very first Scandal that they broke yeah they got a lot of backlash but it's
Show them that you what worked in the
Foreign media could also work in South Korea
Keep experimenting so in 2011 we were in Doom and like a couple of the people from Sports off a bridge
Break off and they form this company called dispatch
And then the following year 2012 mm
It is really important
Chunk of time
Where they just start pumping out scandal
Getting more than 10 stories
Small invade you on his list
I do want to hit list.
Xen
She's dating Master P
Para with John Young
Tachyon who gets caught with
Reindeer
And you have you not dating Lee Seung Ki
Sewing chisel that was like a crazy one and of course that we all remember back in and Tejon
But according to pekin Kim
You had so many scandals
Such a short. Of time headlines after headline headline
Such a frequent right that we need fence became somehow
Desensitized by this news
Is Circus
And I'm going to put myself in there now yeah you should go to Ryder AJ Park
You saw after this
Crazy Onslaught scandals is
A couple things so the paparazzi became a trend something that all the crane and payment new starting pay
There starts to be all these other
Paparazzi come
Movies that come out exactly just like dispatch but
A different name but the craziest
Part I think
Is that you start seeing celebrities
Tiptoeing out and
Telling the truth
About their lives
Little by little the celebrities would get more comfortable about revealing at the
Princeton
Winchester 12 on his talk show song He Who is a member of
K-pop boy band
He made waves because he
Celebrities dating car
From all these new Paparazzi they parked by the Han River and they have their dates there and
There a parking lot
For multiple celebrities
Park
And have their secret dates inside the car
This is something that people always started
Suspected was the case but it was kind of the first time he was
Out in the open like that
I think that the audience reaction
It is like super telling
Cuz they're laughing
So he's breaking the spell
And what you expect
Yeah what you get is
Casual laughter
2 years
We have probably say 5 year
Yeah but still I mean if that's
See this sexy bears make me think
Bengals first voltage
Paparazzi
Is liberators
Totally totally
Cuz we used to think
Scump
What does it mean if your pan out
He literally the thought of
Like it's a tendency cuz we're
See what
Happens in
Places like Korea
It's being very different
What's the culturally separate
Yeah
Batista here they changed that quickly makes me think in some way that we're all very similar
How many world headed
To the same place
Tabloid is the great equalizer
And maybe we were all going to just end up
All of us in
Post Kardashian hell like literally like this is how far they traveled in five years and it literally
5 years you will have
Take the Kardashian family of Korea
I also thought the same thing
You know being from America really well this is
Is inevitable but I actually don't see
Think so anymore
AJ told me a story that
Really change my mind
It was like
It was our Watergate
What are K-pop
It was a taint everything
The story of it
Revolves around
This one young female solo artists
Bailey
Jesus
Hugely popular I mean they actually call her the Korean Beyonce
And in 2013 she was just
Killing it by this point a lie has
Albums out her YouTube videos have millions and millions of views
But then
November 2013
A bomb drop
What happens is this
This guy called calls dispatch
Mr.lee Ashley
And he recorded this phone call
Between them
And the guy tells him
I have nude
Pictures of a lie
IndyCar
Mr. Lee tells the guy we need to know how your
Guy says
Perceive them
From hell
The singer
Yes
Why
I was her boyfriend
What is exactly the Eye Associates calling dispatch to see how much these nude photos are worth
And when I was talking to mr. Lee about this
He said that in that moment
When he was on the phone
Britannia
As a reporter
I was greedy about the
Story and the information he said that he
Wanted those
Pictures
But what he ends up telling the guy is
We don't want your
And then if you keep listening to the phone call YouTube
They're getting really upset with the ex
Boyfriend
Like this is not right you're crossing a line
How to make a long story short dispatch turns down the photos
And the photos
Somehow
Make their way to a competitor
This one
American
Kpop website
Call doll
Kpop pretty big number 1
Kpop site at that time
In the world
For English
English speaker
The published naked
Pictures of are the ones
How to publish then the naked pic
Camper if they sent it or not
If they did it wasn't a very good job that you could see
So
The photos come out and what would you expect to happen
Some anger may be a little bit and then basically people
Just click on the pictures
No
What actually happen
Instantly the entire K-pop
World band
Together Black Ocean Style
Comes out against alipay
The agencies they start threatening to Sue this competitor website starts with boycott and Injustice
Few days this figure like 22000 Twitter followers to stop following
Really they're their reputation
It was a warning to that
You don't don't mess with us and so they really haven't
I mean I haven't really followed them in awhile but they haven't
But what I think is the most surprising part of the
3 days after the photos
Come out
Twas the Night of one of his biggest award ceremonies
Called the melon music
And
You know scheduled for that night Haley was supposed to receive
One of these top 10 artists
The Year award
I think everyone's surprise
She actually showed up
Melon Music Awards
The top 10
In about 2 hours in
Yeah they call her name
Costanza
Wausau Center Stage
Lippizaners
The bow and
She looks
I think she looks
Sprouts or at least overwhelmed
But then
She faces the crowd
At one point her face, crack
She puts her head in her elbow
She started crying
She says
It really means a lot
That you supported me
But you believed in me
Beetlejuice
Spy everything
Thunder Valley Hotel
Thank you
And then
She walked off stage
For me the story shows that they're going to draw
A Line in the Sand
That's different from ours
For now
For a long time or
Can you say
I mean
What I asked
AJ Park
The same question do you think that is going to go the way of the West
I mean she said no way I don't think it's ever going to be
That way I know
I mean culturally Korean store a little more strict
And also I think there's also a part where we look at the US
No like we see them as an example of let's not totally go there
So like a u.s. is a cautionary tale or don't ever get to that point guys
And maybe this is one of those ones where you really wonder like
Is there a cultural difference that runs deep enough
To York the part of you that
You think that ultimately there my vehicle
Something part of me thinks that is as the as
Make it so easy to know
The most intimate details about anyone
We'll all give in
I was part of me just feels that way about humans
I don't know I have to go Robert on the
Well I'm going to have to go daily
I'll meet you thank you Alex thank you
This piece was produced by Matt kielty with Alex Young reported by Alex and also Brenna Farrell
Thanks for guests to Kim Kim AJ Park Leslie can block alemian Sarah Wolfgang and very special thanks to
To Stringer an interpreter
REM Kang Joseph Kim Jeremy Bloom Gian Troi
And
The K-pop
A supergroup crayon pop
Rhapsody on Alex's playlist
Spotify playlist
Java has liked Kpop favorites when you hire staff that's it radiolab.org
I slept like a real-life credit
Too late but I'll just tell him maybe there
Not guilty
Robert Goulet
Gmail
Selfie pageant
Molly Webster
Without phone
Alexander DeYoung
Adoption in the shelter
Hey there your laugh again
Rs2