Are you weightless
Radio WNYC
Hey I'm Jared I'm Robert krulwich this is Radiolab and today a story that we
Been working on for close to two years but just before we're about to put on the air
This happened our next story in perspective it's as if someone
One had killed Lassie as you probably know over this past summer a Minnesota dentist named Walter
Sir Palmer paid 55 grand to get permission
Hunt and kill a lion a lion named Cecil
The country of Zimbabwe who's the pretty famous lines or the star of that Park and been in a few studies so immediately there were alligators
The poaching Zimbabwe where Cecil was killed open up an investigation but what really caught our eye
Was the reaction from the public lion killer the words painted on the home of dr. Walter Palmer
People found out his home address started sharing online his livelihood now
Protesters gathered outside his office
He was forced to temporarily close his business across the internet all over social media and YouTube
To bend warning this next minute contains some
Pretty strong language
You are truly scum-of-the-earth wrote One
May you f****** fun to death I want somebody to take f****** with beds
Today we bring you a story that we hope
Will be a little bit of signal and all that noise this is a story about that
Strange relationship between wanting to hunt and kill an animal
And wanting to save it
And it comes from my producers Simon Adler
1 2 3 4 5
Alright so this story really started for me
In Salt Lake City
The past February I went to the Western hunting & conservation Expo sometimes
Referred to as the Super Bowl of hunting from walking through
This airplane Hangar size room is massive Convention Center called the salt
Alice over 40000 people there gun manufacturers ever bowmakers there were
Call makers from the single Reed
Camouflage
Clothing apparel companies
And I hope you're having a good time and if you're having a good time
I want to hear a Big E Hall
As part of the Expo off this main floor
There was a banquet hall where there was an MC who is working
What's today
I want to continue on a couple of thoughts
That we touched on last night
Your greatest
Conservation
President Theodore Roosevelt said
The wild life
And its habitat
Cannot speak for itself
So we
Must
Let me tell you
We have
And we will continue to speak
But we've got to go further than
Speaking
We're going to have to suit up in our armor to go into battle
To protect our wildlife
On our way of life
Let me tell you we are at War brought on by the extreme radical environmental movement
If we're not vigilant
Dangerous enemy
The most endangered species in America
Could be
The American Hunter
Now one of the things that surprised me
Kind of right off the bat was
Talking to people everybody kept
Coming back to the side and hitting on this idea that like if it weren't for us if it weren't for the hunters
The animals would not be alive without us unto him
They would go extinct I got that line over and over
If there would be no animals other hunt basically what they mean by this is
They are the ones that are
Paying to keep these animals around they are doing to our funding conservation
And I saw what that look like on the final night of the Expo Saturday night when the
Organizers held this auction
And Now's the Time to open your wallets
Get out your checkbooks your credit cards
In fact we're leaving take IOU written on the back of a napkin
Let's make some money for wildlife buddy
First couple items that are just like guns rifles
Pearlstone a picture of the sheep pops up on this
Jumbo screen up on the stage as you can see right there right
Big ones
Huge curling horns
Thick brown coat beautiful color
Beauty python The Bucket List brother
That's on the bucket list so the winner of this auction item what they're actually buying
Is the chance to go up
To Canada in a very specific area
Enter shoot one of these sheets
To get a tag to shoot one of these
I have an opening bid of $30,000
32 and a half 32
Community service
I'm 32 and a half down the middle need 35 one time ago to now we can find 35001 diamond last call
Sold them right over here $35,000 The Grind
Number 6 picture of a moose comes on this
Broadview moose Hunters what a great shiras moose antlers
Banout like giant wings
70 and 1/2 20 22 and 1/2
How does a conservation easement work
State has an agency that's responsible for managing its Wild
It's up your Hunter
Basically have to buy a tag from that state agency
In order to shoot just about any how
For example in Arizona Arizona is grid of hunting area
And you apply to a lottery
For Zone B I would really like to be able to shoot a moose you put your $20 in
Christmas typical
And
If your name comes up you get your tag for $20
Spell possible that you're not going to get one
And sometimes you have to wait 10 or 20 years especially for these big game at
So what is agency
Please do
They set aside a certain number of these tags
Every year which are called conservation Tech
And what these conservation tags are is like
If you just give a bunch of money right now you have free range to do what you want
Stop the line
Shoot the animal you want
No way
Freaking better
And then all that money goes back to those State agencies for Land Management habitat restoration
Patient like we're talking millions of dollars raised this way one auction item that I saw I sold that night
Special big game enhancement
Package
Which basically gave
Whoever wanted the right to shoot
Just about any animal in the entire state of New Mexico
Mexico per year
I'm a hundred 75 I'll go 81.
189 + 91
Sold at $230,000
Wow
In fact the whole reason I'd come to this convention
What to talk to guys with done
Intoxalock
But he's gay
The kind of blew up on
Also did not expect to be in the position I am
My name is Corey Knowlton
Cor
Ey
Cayenne
Owl
T o
You know if I move around alot
Quinton has become kind of the poster child of this idea of Hunter conservation
Vici the Texas millionaire
I met him in his hotel room right across the street from the X
White T-shirt blue jeans little bit of stubble on his face and
Story goes back in January 2014
He was an expo super similar to this one
Put on by the Dallas
I have my wife with me
You just walking the floor when
He bumped into a friend of it
Gentleman by the name of John Jackson
Okay and John Jackson
Heads up
A group called
Conservation Force
So anyway John came to me
And he told Corey that he was working
That the Dallas Safari Club
They were auctioning off
Opportunity to hunt
A black rhino
In
Namibia
Namibian Ministry of environment and tourism
I'd given them one tag
Antoine black rice
And they were going to auction it
Now the black rhino is a critically endangered
Species
5000 of them in the world about 2000 mmba
And what the namibian government does is they auction off the older males
What happened to the black rhino gets older
It sees other rhinos
He wants to attack the
Boston time
And kill them
So the government will offer up the
Problem rhinos
For trophy
And then use the money
To protect the others
From poachers
Is poaching of the Black Rhinos a real issue
Huge issue Rhino horn right now
It goes with
$60,000
Yeah it's weird like three times
Per ounce
In any case Cory says the reason that John was so worried
John said Corey there's been a
A giant
Push
People coming out against
It's literally a license to kill people don't want to talk
A permit to hunt down and kill one of the world's most endangered animals
You're not going to have
Someone
To bid this minimum bid
His friend was worried that they're going to be these namibian ministers they are and they didn't want to be embarrassed
So John asked me if it would you at least bit the minimum bid just started like get the auction rolling as a friend
Somebody I've been friends with for
Over decade
I said
Yes
Soap Natalie auction they started this auction
Just like any other rocks
Eventually
$50,000 thinking that way
Told the other bidders that's right I was like you know what I'm going to do what I told you
Fall through my commitment
When all of a sudden going once going twice through Manhattan
You know I'm just me I'm just going home I'm just a guy take people on
But
Immediately
I've got people
Surrounding
You know giant line of people
Congratulating me
She's like
I didn't expect to be the guy who did it
But okay
But
Next 48 hours
We now know who paid $350,000 for a hunting permit
Killing endangered black rhino in Namibia a barrage of threats started coming
Among the thousands of postings I hope the Rhino rips you and 1/2 do your children know what a monster their father
I hope you get what you deserve
Or short
And painful existence
Corey says people threatened to murder his parents
The rape his wife to death from coming to your house
Burn It Down
I'm going to put your kids in a wood chipper
I'm going to do it in front of you
At any point in this have you been super enthralled by the idea
Have you always wanted to shoot a black
Yeah I got to know we're going to
Be quiet
I definitely haven't always wanted to show
YouTube black rhino have I always wanted to hunt for lost my remember
Yes
Okay
Ladder big journey in life
When I was born we had
Literally nothing
He told me he grew up in rural Missouri in a small house
Trailer home
His mom raised a family his dad loaded trucks
Safeway
Okay we're trying to survive as a family
So when Corey with eight
We left Missouri
Witham in a Monte Carlo with $2,500 in the bank in a dream to make it
Is world okay
So by the time I was 15
We moved all over the United States
His dad picked up jobs in Arizona
Texas I'm going from school to school to school
I didn't really have a benefit of get any sports teams or whatever but the one thing I did is I had a dad that worked
His butt off
Everyday
I didn't get to spend much time with him
So then we would get want to go do things like that lets go dove hunting that's Duffy's
You know he loved that
She mentioned this one time
News 11 we go out I have shotgun in my hand
Two doves fly up
And I shoot nothing both of them. One shot fell right there okay
I went over there
Got the dubs
That went through cleaning them
Okay and preparing the cookie
And just being in that moment
And not worrying about
You know other problems that you met that we all go through in life and just having a nice quiet on my dad
I looked at is
Privilege to go hanoi
I didn't look at it like hey it's my right to go out
And take some animals
Looks like I'll look at it like
This is an awesome opportunity I get to go spend with my dad outside
Now
As I became older I became more interested in hunting or learn about both I want to learn about hunting I was eight
Get up with it by the time he's in his mid-20s he says
And this is right around the time his dad hit it big in the oil industry
He was leading Huntsman all around the world from the North Pole to as far south as you could hunt
In New Zealand Nepal Papua New Guinea so I've seen the whole world and he says somewhere in the
The middle of all of those trips
He realize
There's a big fight out there
This large biomass of humanity
Is taking over the world and
Wildlife doesn't exist by accident anymore
And so he started thinking about not just hunting these
But preserving them
And keeping them here all the witches to say when
He won that auction
Without meaning
And started getting all this death threat
He didn't turn back
What on Earth is keeping you
So steadfast in going ahead and doing this
I think I would have
Thought
I should
I was willing to do this
And it may have not been what I planned on
But I was willing to do this based on a commitment I made you a friend
Make meth
Family
Make commitment
The conservation of the whole
Look
This was never about
Me going over
And taking
Black rhinos live
Like Viola I get to achieve the Zenith of life and killing his black rhino give me a break
It was about
Method
A conservation
To keep Black Rhinos on the face
You are saying
That you're doing this for conservation your detractors will say
They will say you say you were only doing it for conservation when you are really doing it for
I'm not saying that's what you said I'm saying that this is what they will throw at you
You were only you were saying you're only doing it for constipation
Well are you actually getting out of it as some sort of satisfaction
Can you talk for a minute about in car for more than a minute about it
Okay alright
Sure
I enjoy the act of hunting can I tell you why
Could I wrap that up in a real pretty burrito for you to be able to eat and understand it taste good
No but I can tell you that
ICare
About
The survival of these
Species and do you understand why
People have a hard time
Wrapping your mind around that
You believing that
And simultaneously wanting
To kill an animal
What it does that just does not compute you at all what point were
We're getting redundant they're missing
The whole boat we don't have one without the other
Okay
If we want Wildlife to be
Around
Future generation
We have to understand
But that Wildlife has
Value
If it doesn't have a bag you
Especially in the continent of Africa
It's going to be gone
I'm sure he made a sort of economic
He said you got to keep in mind that
Living next to a black rhino
Not just talking about it but actually living next to a black rhino
It's a nightmare
I mean who wants to live next door to a raging Psychopathic babysits
Killing thing
No one
Sew-in just very purely economic terms it has a negative value
But what Cory will tell you and what conservation organizations like World Wildlife Fund and various others will tell you
Is by him paying $350,000 to shoot one
He is creating a positive
Value for that animal he's creating jobs for game wardens
Is creating jobs for trackers
She got look at the net benefit
It's there when so what
What is the common ground here because you guys want the same things
And yet there's somehow this
We don't want the same
Conservationist in general do
Common Ground has to be
Do you or do you not want to see
Black Rhinos on the face of the Earth
And I think
Everyone agrees that they do
But I think he'd
No I think they do I are actions are speaking louder than their words
They're all at I think to a lot of people there these neo-colonial
Sentiments
The you are this guy who has a lot of money
And you are paying a lot of money to go to Africa
To shoot this
And I think that
That causes a reaction
Certain people
Do you think the amount of money plays into it or no
Okay
You say you don't answer anything or that I want
To give you the best office plants be understanding I'm really trying
To an emotional level Runway
My god dammit
And I know that the words
Put out means
And
I don't want
People that
Bent
I'm not a radical sign
If you conceived
Get you something I believe in I can believe in these animal
I believe that I want them
But I also understand
But the death of the species.
And so
Putting myself through this because I believe
Embarrassed right cuz I've seen that it
And I'll go down and I will sit next
The people in Africa
Both indigenous and 9
That have the exact same belief
And they want these animals they love them they want their kids here
Dayton OH
That
One night
DeYoung
Stars are above
And
They're sitting there
With their family
And lion roars in a distance
They feel that
They feel what it means to be afraid of it
If it would means
Expected
Play Feel Good Music
Love it
And I want that
Dudeiwantthat
Realistic
View a realist
I believe I have a girl
What it takes
Continue
So that conversation happened over 6 months ago
At that point
The Dodge was totally in limbo
You still receiving death threats
Animal Welfare organizations like Humane Society of the United States were lobbying and petitioning to try to
Stop the hunt
And what it all really hinge Don was
A decision to be made by us Fish and Wildlife
Under The Endangered Species Act it's illegal to import the carcass
Of an endangered species into the United States
Unless you can prove
That by killing and importing that animal
You are helping the species as a whole so that's what US fish and wildlife had to decide
Would Corey killing and importing
That one black rhino help Black Rhinos as a whole
March went by
April
And then
In early May
I got a text from Cory. Just read
Let's talk tomorrow
We take a trip
My name is Courtney and I'm cold
Pulling from Johannesburg South Africa Radiolab is supported by the Alfred P Sloan
Sloan foundation in hunting public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world
Www.org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help this summer I'm hosting the show
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
About what we're calling tiny moments childhood Brilliance basically I want to hear about those times when a kid
So did something
It just means you read back and say whoa how did they do that maybe it was the moment that a kid
Did you been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons and you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed they're writing music in the margin of their geometry homework we're interested in
Epic moments where a kid does something super smart but doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story please share it with us
Go to radiolab.org brilliance
Record short audio message for us
And that's radiolab.org / Brilliance thank you so much
Leisure by
Alright we are off the plane
Walking out into the airport I suppose this would be the first time we've actually stepped foot in the movie yet
Beyond the destination I'm Jenna reporter Simon Adler
So they never getting that text message I land in Namibia meet back up with court today where and when
Maybe it's the 13th of May 2015
This is Simon's Big Data interview local officials professional hunters in any bum
We've been traveling for
Probably like closer than 48 hours now year if you're feeling all right at this point through a lot better now
Just getting off the plane and feeling the wind we get through
Customs and everything and immediately xiamen
Simon I meant a nice to meet you manga met by the pH
Can't even hear the pH I am a professional Hunter
The professional Hunter
The Christopher Cody Knowlton
Do I system on Nissan
He's sort of the manager of this entire Pro
Big dude
Scraggly beard short shorts
We need to come pick up her stuff
He leads us out of the airport
So what does the day's agenda hold for us
Yorkie has just started my friend
So getting the truck start driving and do you mind if I ask you some questions while we drive you
I immediately just realized what a headache putting all this together has been for him
10 million phone calls meetings of the meetings with the ministry of environment and
What is amid office checking with local offices to help them figure out which is the best rhino
4 quart to shoot how many at this point you know exactly which one you'll be going out
After there a couple the Main Place we've identified that is to rhinos we can remove from that area
Both male Progressive post-reproductive we going to try to get on one of these two animals and try to remove
But as professional as we can possibly do
So we're at the ministry of environment and tourism
Is apparently a meet-and-greet
Later that day we stopped to shake hands with
The permanent secretary Simeon negombo
You get this kind of prepared speech
About how trophy hunting is a big part of why Namibia is considered the gold standard of
Conservation in Africa
Disk program
Assisted
To have a wildlife
Troy
Wildlife World Zoo Mosaic climbing
Like it
Elephant with less than 1000
But now we have
Cadence we don't know where to put them in
Sedalia mini now
Deal with a surplus
Fast forward to the next morning 4:46 a.m.
I doubt that Simon
Nor I got any sleep last night
Vital that
Someone's gonna get hurt
He was in high school
I woke up this morning it was drizzling rain
Around curb, passenger train
The truck is firearm and ammunition big knives and things
So we can scan another Rhino was on the phone I taken care of final details
And much to my chagrin there is
This crew of CNN reporters hanging around
Once everything was loaded
Beijing Capital airport
She'll leave you here Corey
And I waved them off okay
Happy Hunting
I wasn't able to go on the Rhino hunt
What I know I know you're using disappointment number one Hunting Party can only be so
Large in the media
And with these three CNN guys there
Did the party was just
But you also have to understand I was in the country
Illegal
I had no press pass I had known
Press video to this is like I've got to keep my head down
What time are you telling me the story is over that we racing
Corey's personal cameraman he promised to give me all of his audio so we do have the audio and we will get to that but will they were headed up
North that actually ended up going east and
Where I went totally unexpectedly made this model of conservation and how it works like
Finally clicked into place for me I do you mind just telling me your name and where we are at home when I was almost wonderful
My name is is Deltona pool
So the owner of these continents
It sounds good Andre and Estelle Swanepoel own the aru game
Which are a series of
Huge wasp
Of land that they
Fenced-in
I'm totally have like over 200 square miles of land
Actually used to be filled with cat on no 15 16 years ago
We converted into a game form basically they decided
How to get rid of all the cattle and bringing all these animals they've got your rafts they've got two different species of zebras will.
The Beast Ultra beasts in all they got 29 different species including how many black rhinos are on the property here
Up until about three weeks ago. Then and now we we've got eleven one of the hunting guides staff
At the auto game mode is in the movie told me that they actually just had a rhino born on the
Property and in fact I've had several throughout the years born on this property and we have to find one
Look for signs and keep our eyes feeling so what should I be looking for if I'm going to be of any help here
Yeah I'm at this until just look like a big gray rock that you really going to have a Keen Eye driving through the
Really tall thick grass that kind of enveloped the car was almost like we're driving through a cloud
This is the calorie Sawgrass and set realistic Summers like the monster on top of it
And after
Searching and searching and searching I was just
Like a hundred yards away oh man okay
They had the vehicle so you know it's still a very safe distance
Can you can put the binoculars man looking
Skip the binoculars and he's just pointed straight at as his head moving left to right left to right I think this is
Does a bull by the looks of things it looks like a dinosaur
Very prehistoric looking animal
Keep trotting away from us started moving away from us
Tiny looking legs so when they run they have to kind of shuffle along I think of the girls was in the
Laughlin Nevada movies
They're lucky to the front one she's at the we were tailing behind it in the crazy thing is
Huge animal that weighs over a ton on it is on the Move thinking move like 30 miles per hour
We're currently driving in about 15 km an hour and he's getting away from us and left us behind
So you want nothing to do about these moving off of at one point before it took off we actually got close enough
That with the binoculars on Steph was able to get a good look at its ear
And this one doesn't actually have an earmark in it so perhaps this one was born on this
Property
What the hell does that work how did
How did the Rhinos get to be on this property
The ministry of environment tourism has been in touch with the owner of Otto Graham Rogers
Government said hey you got all this land will you take a couple of these rhinos and protect them for us
And you know we started off of a couple
3 Donovan the number 3
Strange foster care types
Each year we have to take photos of them and we build up a portfolio and then we can send it into the Met it's interesting that lie
They are breeding here
So there are more of them now than there would have been
If they hadn't been moved here yeah yes he's like
Another thing
We will knuckle assembly actually we lost it runners
Steph said he want to show me something about 10 minutes then he stopped the car at the small clear
Almost no grass one Lone Tree I feel when I
Stumble across the street and can you describe what we're looking at right
I hear bones scattered all over the right side of the kalari bleach white bones again
Read Brett's and see if they can see some positive spine as well as that a rhino skull
It's just unreal
You see that there
We got out of the car and like actually like held these bones of God
Wow
How how did that happen
It was a dominant do I was fighting with a younger boo
The two squared off and the older one ended up
Goring the younger one with its horn
Really sweet
Pushing the envelope passed away
He killed it
Then this this older bowl that it just
Killed the younger one
Steph told me then went up to this female
Wanted to bring the juice and the
Young female wasn't ready she wasn't mature enough yet
She kept forcing himself on her
Over and over until
So she couldn't enjoy longer
That I guess it would happen in nature as well it's just unfortunate that today
Add to beer
See how they would have been even more butt
Nature take its course we can get involved in
How it is
Steve explain to me that it was these type of black rhino
Older aggressive bulls that get
Auctioned up for guys like Cory to come over and shoot
And then all the money that's been paid for it
Is going back
Logang back into
Anti-poaching unit is going back into
Conserving
Rhino send
It's nice to see such a large sum of money coming in
For a good cause
So he believes in this program
Never be able to
Deschutes
Black rhino
Dwight what what about you personally wouldn't
Cheetah rhino
For me
Explain why
Not the notes
Difficult to say
Enough
Doesn't tickle me
Over the next couple days at the lodge
As I was hanging out with kind of these
Tourists
From all over the world would come here to be wined and dined and then
Gotten shoot stuff in the morning and afternoon
Steps ambivalence
30 to make a deep sort of sense
Tiffany toma toma toma toma
For instance I spent a lot of time with this guy
Steven Lindstrom middle-aged there with the family on vacation we decided six years ago that we will
Google
To Africa
So I'm very happy to
Be here today
This is six years in the making for you
Yeah you can say Volvo's corporate office and
Need a big truck
Maybe some picture from my home do you have lots on the wall already
Show me
And now today I can't we have at least
50 more
I got the following a few hun
Him and his got my name is SpongeBob over
Stamina setting
One of the times we spent about 2 and 1/2 hours
Searching for different animals talking different animals
And then in the distance
So very nice what about bull we finally found a water bug
Which is what it's kind of like a reindeer
But
It has he's too big Longhorns
Shoot backwards almost like
Spirit
Big animal
Like a Stone
Norse mythology is just going to close NC
We hop down from the car and just kind of
Slowly moving towards it through the grass
Type of animal is the top for me this weekend and his laundry seven told me he had a list of animals
He was hoping to shoot and this was at the top of this one with the game
Charges $2,800 to shoot
Walking through
Chandelier
Every like 10 minutes weave
Stop to measure how far away it was 12 to 6
Eventually
We got this a couple hundred feet away from it
The animals off in the distance is just kind of pacing
Simple.
Tripod sets it up
And Stephen gets into position
The buck stumbled a few paces and you don't
Fall down
But then again
Right back up and stumbles forward
What's this one
Appreciative
Add appointment seems tense
Cuz like he knows that the animal is suffering
The dog takes off runs after it and just keeps it at babe I kind of circling it and we start moving towards it
Again second shot doesn't kill it
Fall down get back up fall down again
Next Injustice
Benton housing
Pretty upset
I don't know what you said it the first time better
Irvin High
And the third shot
Duncan killer
Discipline
Macadamia nut
I will try
Finally fourth shot
Because
What's the winning shot
I can still kicking a little bit but it is
Done
Oh it's so nice
I'm so happy I'm so happy
What's the top of the list for me this weekend
Movie synopsis perfect
Is very nice feelings
Seeing it up close
It can be
Emotionally difficult
But when you pan out it's pretty clear the numbers show that this namibian model is working
Wildlife numbers on private land have gone up by almost 80% since the government allowed people to
Buy sell and shoot Wildlife on their land and since trophy hunting of the black rhino with legalized
That population has grown by like 30%
Button front of my face not all African conservationists are on board I talked to a guy named
Richard Leakey Super Famous Anthropologist who also directed
Kenya's Wildlife program for a while
And I asked what is your stance on this idea of sustainable use
Listen to me I think it's absolutely ridiculous
If a father cant afford to pay school fees for his children
Does you say to somebody you can rape my daughter so I can get the money to pay for school fees
I don't think we go to set some standards in life and I think was his mom sue for
What this argument is about killing wild animals
So that they can be looked after
Absolutely sends the wrong message
This was the big issue he took
With Namibia strategy
Yes you can you can afford to lose five Runners from a breeding perspective
Does that send the right message
She then told me a story about when he took over Kenya's Wildlife service in 1989
At the time
Things were dire elephants were being killed in her Lobby number and we were going to lose our elephants totally poaching with
Is on the rise and his predecessors had actually confiscated a huge number of elephant tusk
From this boat
Tough.
You said you thought that's another Library
Zelda side remake about 3 million dollars
And then use that money to help fight poaching
But like you said know what he did instead when she built a giant Tower of that ivory
Taken by poachers burn
Puns of contraband
Three days. Television newspapers magazines radio
CPR stat to draw
The world's attention to the
Site of elephants and part of what he was saying in that was like we have to Value these things beyond their dollar value
If the respect the intrinsic value of the
These creatures the wait a second
If you're burning a bunch of ivory aren't you in effect
Increasing the value of the ivory cuz now there's just less of it out there so you're looking at the supply end of it right yes by
Reducing Supply that would push up price leaky was attacking the demand side
What an impact it had to run the world
Opinion changed overnight. He said it woke the public up people stop buying Ivory and the market
For ivory
Is it crashed
Up to that time would be losing about three and a half thousand elephants to four thousand elephants a year
A year later we were losing
At most
Really
Enormous impact boyfriend
Getting a public
Support conservation of Wildlife
That's a huge Challenge and we just can't afford icing
Just send out the wrong messages
But the problem with that is
Finding the right message is getting harder and harder
I called various conservation organizations
And one guy who I talked to told me that
Their average age of donor is getting older
More and more people just living in cities less people are having positive experiences in the natural way
World at a young age and so he said that they're going to have to continue focusing on people focusing on us
This message of
What does Wildlife give us
What does it do for p
Third Day up in the area
Still no luck we're just going to
Keep at it
Back in the media after 3 days of bushwhacking through this
Dance
Vegetation
Up in the north of the country
Corey and his crew finally got on the tracks of the right Ryan
The local guy says wakanda rhino
Better Built another Rhino that it killed another rhino
So we're going to follow this
Like 100% sure that it's the right one
And then we'll try to take if we can
So for the next couple hours they they track the animal looking for
Fiscally footprints
Anywhere that is marked its territory
Play Store
We were at walk at this point just about 12 MI
It was very hot
The grass was so thick that they really couldn't see more than about 30 feet in front of
And eventually they find you can see this is a rhino
A pile of rhino fees
Is that still warm still very moist mean it's practices
We're not more than an hour behind that animal right there you can see the dung beetles and everything in it and so
Set there for a few minutes right gathered our thoughts
You wanted out where and what you say
And then
About two hours later from my left
All I see is running Beast with a giant saber on its head
It was like lightning
So you also didn't get it with the first shot the first
Several shots did not kill the
It ran off and then they have to start tracking
Bonded oil
We followed it
I would say 10 minutes out of
La looked over there I saw it wasn't lying down at this point it was standing up but it has already fallen down twice
It was dying
And then
I shot it
The last thing you do
Is what you really assured its dad you touch its eye
If it doesn't blink
So did you go take your time
Absolutely
Animal like that is there some sort
Is there a conversation going on now that the animal is is dead and you're not know
We just kind of looked at everybody looked at each other make sure we are okay
There wasn't a whole lot of talk I didn't this guy
But it was an emotional moment for me
So
Debate
We've been sitting here skin this animal so far this morning
And now we're about to roll it over skin the other side and then just take the quarters off just like any other animal that you would if your
Hunting trip
They loaded up all the meat to be shipped off to a local Village
And
They
Kept a little bit of it for themselves
So kicking my first piece of black rhino me here on the coals next to the karges
Right here's the moment when
Everybody here has started eating some of those black rhino so it just
Apart of
The part of hunting and a part of being a human
So it's a pretty
Unique an awesome moment right here I'm not really morally outraged by I'm maybe I'm a little but
I think you might be vulnerable if you insist that your enthusiasm for hunting is part of the balance Renee
But I think Robert perfectly
You don't have those k93 and salad and I understand that people don't like it
Any more than they wouldn't like going and killing the lamb
Of the lamb chops I eat
What are dynamic mean it's wrong
Hunting
It's part of who we are now it may be a bigger part of
Who I am then you are
And that's fine
But when
Wildlife populations
Abound is when they're managed by Humans Beings the alternate model might be a view of humans that's
Different from yours I think
You assume
That
Because we are smart and because there are so many of us
That inevitably
We will bump into them
And when we do we will win
And that's your calculator
The alternate model might be
That because we are smart
We might create a space
Willy won't bump
Now you're now you're not in the real world
We're dealing not in reality
Okay I'm glad I'm living in a world that matters and it's real
So it's not it's not a dream scenario and it's not saying okay well let's just create this unfortunately these Ana
Animals don't have that time
So I'm not trying to outsmart anybody it's just a traditional method that's worked
And until
Somebody comes up
With a methodology that we can look at and say this is
In better way
I'm going to continue
Defy in believe in the traditional model
So now we're going to ask ourselves these
How do we really on an individual basis
Value
This animal
Survival
On Earth
Do you really value it
Do you value it past making 75 characters into your iPhone tweeting about it
Devalue it past watching Animal Planet
Tumi
I know
And I care
And I placed an egg
Stream
Value
Financially physically emotionally
On the survival of the black rhino
Reporter and producer Simon Adler
We had considerable Productions 450s from Matthew guilty who also contributed some Ray Charles music
Special thanks to Chris Weaver Ian Wallace Mark Barrel Ryan tarbet the Lindstrom Family and everyone at the RO game law
Lodge in Namibia we also want to take a moment right now to say
Goodbye and good luck to our dear dear dear longtime collaborator Alan horn she was she was
She's been everywhere longer than me right she was there before lyrics I remember when you were going to
When you were bringing her on but we were still having breakfast in oh yeah well you and I were just about to work together she was the first person
Hi
Brought in as an intern and then hired that you came.
User she's brought us to all if you've been to any of the tours
She made those toys happen if you flexing us onstage she made the stage things happen when we're on the tour's yes she's just been that
Third partner from the beginning
And now she takes her awesomeness to audible.com and we think they made a smart move so you should watch your ears cuz I'm about to
Another blast of Beauty from her some other source
Somehow
And now
And that's good because the world can only use more
Absolutely we are so proud and happy and grateful and we love you Ellen
Hi my name is Miss Rogers
I'm calling from Kansas City Missouri
Radiolab is produced by dada.
Are Staffing Foods beneficial
Alan horn
David Gable
Dylan Keith
Matt kielty Andy Mills
Latif Nasser Kelsey Padgett
Arianne wack
Molly Webster
Soren wheeler and Jamie York
Would help for Molly McBride Jacobson Alexandra Lee Young
And Simon Adler
Are fact-checkers are Eva Dasher and Michelle Harris