Before we start the following story contains a moment or two that's
Pretty intense
And may not be suitable for young kids
Are you awake
Listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
Yashow feeder
Matt
But where do you want to launch into this
You're going to deal with this
Call Tuesday
August
Mm
17 biblical from Bath County Eastern Kentucky
1351 + 26
Seconds
Is it called from dispatch to
Bath County EMS station because of the people that are dispatched to Medical emergencies
Hot in the afternoon something like that comes been off for a unresponsive
Male other voices Jeff over partners
Service in Bath County Kentucky first one of the day
Apartment complex they been there before it's this sort of squad two story building
Will get there jump at the clubs on enter the small apartment
Law enforcement center chief of police was there talking to the two people that were Alert in the house a woman
Running a guy sitting on couch if you looked immediately to the right it's just like the kitchen is there
Frascati and JC
Play Leon responsive
He was laying in water about 3 in deep where my guess somebody in the house at taking the sprayer from the
Kitchen sink and had sprayed him down paint Reviving a bring them back to life and it doesn't have
Stand-up guy
He was breathing and he was barely he's taking these really low
Shallow breaths
And then I pulled his eyelids back in Texas pupils are tiny
Pinpoint Sears overdosed
Pretty addictive than opiates
So I said okay
So Jay grabs his medic kit he goes into his bag and he pulls out this nasal spray
Set drug called naloxone is also commonly referred to as Narcan
And it's a drug did stick known as being this Lazarus drug yeah because it
Immediately
Throws an opiate overdose into reverse
And
I like brings people back from the brink of death
2J crashes over this guy and he takes the snail spray
Stix it up one of the guys nostrils
Phrases
Takes it out where to be
Does the same thing to the other nostril
Within seconds
The guy open his eyes
But what's going on I grab a towel and start drying him off and then I pushed him up so I could sit him up
Got them up onto the stretcher loaded in the truck when you take off
St clare Hospital
Guys up from a driving the ambulance stays in the Backwoods
Patient everything was good with him everything was routine with all of a sudden
Scotty hollered to the window
Yell at me
I don't feel right
I can remember a weird
Taste coming into my mouth and
A real
Odd smell hitting
Manos
What do you think
Camp scrub
It was just
Looks like chewing on Steel
Go ahead
Scotty while he's driving he gets on the radio the next County over
Client hi I need help
I need you to send me an angel
10-4
Made it to the bottom of the ramp
Trucking Park
They jumped out of the back and ran up to
The friend went to the passenger side. Scotty he was already slumped over
Unresponsive
Was that quick
L'equipe Stout
Cold
Now waking up anything no no he's not responding at all so what was happening this is like this is the thing that
I don't know what's so shocking to me
Is that when Jay then check out Scotty to pinpoint pupils snoring respiration's East seem to have the exact
Same symptoms
As the patient in the back of the ambulance would overdosed where what
The exact same symptoms that's what it look like the J
How can
How does that even happen
Also
2J explained it to us
Like
He said if you wind back they'd gone in his apartment
To treat this guy who is on the kitchen floor with
He said he believes that when they were helping him up
Scotty had rubbed against his
Skin to skin contact with her
His forearm
NJ City believes
What likely happened in that moment is that whatever drug is
Guy had taken
And now gotten onto Scotty's arm
Absorbed through the skin into a system
And then like
15 minutes later
Github Scotty
Pass out
Wow
That's
That's really strange yeah it seems like a really unusual thing to happen
But the thing is like
I guess what's even weirder is it like this wasn't the first time I'd heard this story has been following us for a while
So yeah I've been keeping a list of these types of incidents
And
But I found this
This wasn't an isolated incident
He said that things are happening a lot
Is reported in North Carolina Florida
Accidental drug overdose West Virginia police officers in southeast Wisconsin Texas California
Massachusetts Vermont New Hampshire
Officers are hospitalized Nebraska
The officer was responding to an overdose has been over a hundred recorded instance
All over the country
I've been reporting on opiates for
For a number of years and I guess I was watching the
These kinds of incidents occurring
Kind of felt like I was watching a Contagion
I like unfold in real-time when I guess when I was reading all these stories
I would I was just thinking like
What is going on here
What's happening
I'm jad abumrad I'm Robert krulwich Radiolab
Today we have a story about
What happened that day in that apartment
That ambulance in Kentucky
Definitely kind of a mystery story but added
Poor
Trulia story about about wanting to do good
Choosing to do good
Having to suddenly bear the cost
I'm doing good
Story comes to us from Peter Smith
Freelance journalist
And it also with Cobra ported by
Peter
I produced your majesty
Hey everybody okay so
So
Kentucky
So we wanted to talk to Scotty and his partner Jay
About what happened that day about what's been happening so we flew into Lexington we drove
About an hour
Have some nice rolling bluegrass
He'll see a lot of green and we drove to this tiny little city called Owingsville
Bath County Emergency Medical Services
Where the bath County EMS is white building
Linoleum siding big garage doors I can see it like an auto shop
Couple big white
Bath County EMS ambulances
Change washer
Dryer
Ash tree on top of it
And attach the garage is a one-story house
Basically three Central just showed up at this place to introduce ourselves and say hey
The real
Few people inside Gary
Who directed The station's they're serving the whole County
284 square miles of think
How big are county is you know that how many people that is a little
Over 12000 I believe
I work overnight at 1 station feel so bad Sinbad
Yeah that's in the back
Yolanda just going to like living here
Yes basically like an apartment
Is the kitchen we were in the living room with Gary sitting on
McAlister's
Beeg
La-z-boy's a ginormous
TV
Billy Bob Thornton Amazon
In the show
No he's at the main dude in real life
Remember that
We went to Willie Nelson concert in his band open for Willie Nelson
And somebody in the audience heckled him
He just about came off the stage after him and he calls him everything with a sewing machine and a milk cow
I mean he made up cuss words
Yeah he's a he's a wiry little Feller
Just hanging around with Gary probably like 15 minutes and then
Scotty locked in
Next to me
Guilty
I got to do it this is the EMT who overdosed yeah Scott he's the guy that supposedly overdose
Descendants 50s white hair tall bright blue eyes
About all of this
I-Ready New York Times
There was one night of the story
About 3 EMS personnel
I don't know if that's the truth truth
Pretty much
Picked up in-store
Insulin
I thought there was something unusual about that
And I was curious
Tahir the real story
Give me just a few minutes
Yeah no rush
Discuss things
So eventually was just the three of us in this living room
I mean maybe I should preface this by saying
That you can't really understand the story unless you understand a little bit
About what
EMS Personnel do
I talked to some other EMTs the
Told me that everybody has their why
Everybody has a thing
They say it's like this is the reason I got into
This is a business
I would say like a very small percentage like don't have second or third jobs like they don't make a lot of money
So everybody has his wife
And so I asked
Scotty what his why was
And
He told me the story
I think it's a really incredible story
The not only explains
Why he does what he does
But
It also explained like why he holds on to certain things
So
September
Of 1999 I was involved in an accident on the Pennsylvania Turnpike
So it's early in the morning
Is raining job during Hurricane Floyd
You got there for work
Cross country Trucking
It was a
Freightliner and flatbed trailer with float python it
Barreling down the turnpike with this
Heavy bloated Steel on the back
And with the weather like disability starts to get bad slowed Motor Speedway down
Probably running the process
55 mile an hour and
He comes through this
Construction site
And something happened
In the front end of the truck here to pop
The front tire has blown out
I basically became passenger at that point there was no key
Stroller
18-wheeler was like
Careening out of control down the turnpike in it
Is likes
Skidding across the wet pavement and a Truck lunge to the right it was concrete wall there that had guardrail attached to it
It knows them to the guardrail plane back across both lanes boktor
The center divider in the truck hit it
Plowed through the center divider began to like roll over and came down and struck a vehicle
Traveling the other with direct
Gary said he doesn't remember much of what happened next
Other than his
Truck finally coming to a stop after that the next thing I remember was
Standing on the frame of the truck watching diesel fuel run underneath of men
How to hear the truck burn
Somehow you
Most got out of the cab and he's standing on this
Helluva the cab
And the truck is on fire
Ilikeweylie standing there like other people were driving down the highway
Stopped and then starts like yell at him screaming at me to get away from the truck
I got off a truck and I'll look up the road and I saw the other vehicle on
And I knew then that it wasn't good it
It was
It was very destroyed bacon
What would happen
And there was a lady had a minivan I have no idea where she came from
She open the side door on her Minivan and had me sit in the floor board until the ambulance
After
I remember looking down at my left hand and
The back of my left hand all the skin was
Probably hanging down
HTM 12 in
Where had melted the skin than
Dangling off
Yeah
I can remember when the ambulance getting there and
There was a a female
Paramedic
And when she walked up and looked at me I remember her going oh my God I like this ain't good at is it
No
She lied to me she said no it's not good
Get rushed to hospital
If I broken ribs
Massive skin burn
I do remember him telling me you're going to lose your left hand
And I told him I said that's not enough
He started doing skin graft
Took skin off my legs and put on my arms and
Am I bi
As you can see I've still got my left hand
The left-handed
I'm still a fan
End
When
You said it was a couple days after the accident when they told you about the other
Their car
How did that conversation
It was an attorney that
Was for the representing the trucking company that I was driving
What's the one that asked
Ashley told me about
Holiday said hey
Had been involved with the ax
That was
I found out
I just remember him walking in the hospital room and he's like hi my name is
Yeah and my name is so and so and I
What's up I'm going to tourney with representing
Help me that you drive for and
Will know if you've been informed of this or not
Street fatality is involved
Oh I hadn't been informed but
Yes I have been now
When when we started into court proceedings
That was when I found out
Names
And where they were from
They were from Connecticut
They had been on vacation in North Carolina
Hurricane coming in they were evacuated out of North Carolina
So they had decided that they were
Don't travel up into
Pennsylvania and
Try to to find a place to
Finish their vacation in Pennsylvania
That's what puts them there
About to travel to
2 miles an hour faster
2 miles an hour slower
We wouldn't have been at the same place at the same time
Scotty eventually went back to Long Haul Trucking
But
He said that he kept thinking about that day
About that accident that the people who were killed never forgot still
I haven't forgotten the other thing that really struck him about that day
Was that
Everybody who showed up
True that scene of the fire department BMS everybody there was volunteer
And that's something he could really shake that people volunteer to come to me and they didn't know who I was thank you
Care who I was
They they didn't pass judgement on me that
Yeah I was in a hurry riffic accident and I might have been the been the cause of that accident
Daycare
They viewed me as someone that needed help
And that was all they viewed me us
Scotty said The more I thought about it the more he felt like he had this the sort of debt to pay back
For the lives that were lost that day or the ones that he
Then he extinguished in the way that way that he's going to do that has become a volunteer he's going to become one of these people
Help those in need that comes to your head
No matter what and as I say you know the rest is history here I am
So we spent a few days with Scotty falling around on on some of his runs and
As an EMT main responsibility is to drive the ambulance but also
Chris's partner is often J
2 calls
Like a three-year-old who's having trouble breathing
Got in Long 6 on Main Bridge Hocking be for something it feels like so small like a cough or or low
Blood sugar for one night
Porch
Mail pick up an elderly woman
You won't feel big poke
Channel 3 we go 1-2-3 big Pope
He's really kind of like the everyday innocuous calls
And of course like there are
Overdoses
By the way am I
Amad
I'm a girl masturbates you
Because
We were like these
Static on reporters everybody
Kept saying that we should go down to the old jail
Which is where we met the county jail Earl
His friend Mitchell
Nice to meet you out already
And so
Sower lettuce in a jail
Abandoned now
Paint peeled off the wall
You walked us into this front room
Full of weed wackers lawn mowers Borough oversees the work release program so the people that are in jail
I heard about this temporary work release program
Do lawn maintenance along the highway
Where they got them
Around the corner
An Earl
Earl gravis
Red bucket
Repeat sat down and took a knee high bucket
Oh my God
But you can say at your house this year
So many syringes
How many you think you got in there last year
All last year
People on work release have been picking his up for like the past year it's just
Litter on the highway
You know what playing at black boy scouts or self-clean it Monroe
British tattoos
Too bad with an Eagles fan
You just can't do it anymore with the way the needles if that's all
Yeah it's all kinds of marine Niger bottling
Pour me another bottle
I probably 20
30 + 9
Here's another one
We got a problem here there's no doubt about that
There's definitely a problem
With her when you
I still got the drugs in there
Huh
Waverly pattern
B24
Did it surprise you to find this money
Really yeah
What did you say
The heroin problem just started just like overnight
Here
I mean it was pills forever and then
And it's out
Nobody even ever seen a needle did you mean
And then just out once they were everywhere
When you win when you start seeing them
But it's been longer than it's been back-to-back two and a half to two and a half years ago and it just
And once it's charging chart to find a river
So what do you think
UC
Tell these needles
District
Tobias scientist
It's Bistro in families and we have somebody down here just all the time I mean it's
Trilobite
Cheyenne
I had a very good friend that I lost
What was Major back lifestyle August
Somewhere I had took him to rehab and he was in there for
A couple months and he got out and done good and then
Finding that happened to him
And I was sort of
The incredible thing
Is it like everybody knew somebody who had been caught up
In using opioids
Somebody in their family end up
I want to buy a
Like I went to yard sale because I love yard sales and
When I tell the women were sitting there on the driveway what we're reporting on
They they said they had lost neighbors friends
Mm
Yeah one day when you're down there we had to take a Lyft
Which
Destroyed my left femur I've got a 12-inch plate 10 screws into pins and hold my left femur together
The driver told us how he'd started using pills
I talked to a woman who work at a thrift store who told me she lost
Cousin to an overdose
Actually Jade told us about a friend of his
He actually relapse he was in
He was in therapy
His sponsor in na Narcotics Anonymous overdose
I have nobody to go to so he relapsed
Was found two days later in a car
Is pretty bad
And I would I would assume that
DMs
Scotty and Jay
Would have seen this
This shift
Yes, he told us around 2017
Overdose calls went from one or two a week to 5/6
One day there was 11
And that was just unheard of in this County it just
To have that many overdoses
Because they would treat the same person
Like five times over a few months
Like this is just
The job
Right there there to save people's lives
This overdose problem in
It's sort of like moral calculus
That an EMS person makes when they show up to help a person who who is OD
It started
When report started emerging about this new
Drug
Distracted made it so
Simply coming into contact with
Person like this
Simply touching them
Could quit an EMS worker
Endanger
Wasn't a lot known about it
We got this guy Jason York about it he's the Emergency Management director for the county
It came out
The reports that we were getting was
Literally airborne
Have you ever seen it
What do you think like
Just hearing about it
What's going through your mind when you hear about it
World War Z
Walking Dead
The drug is called Fentanyl
What is fentanyl like I know that it's an opioid
What is it like
Talk to a guy about this
Can you tell me again like who you are and yeah
I'm in Emergency Physician
I hear at Hennepin County Medical Center
I was just a level 1 Trauma Center in Minneapolis
He's also the director of the Minnesota poison control
Sell fentanyl has been around for decades
We use it almost everyday
My Hospital
So fentanyl is an opioid
It's fully synthetic
Manufactured in Laboratories
Roxanne comes in powder form but
Drug companies reformulated into all sorts of things like fentanyl lollipops
These lollipops are given to
The soldiers on the battlefield there's also Fentanyl patches that people wear to get fentanyl into their body
Through their skin
Oh so you can you can do Fentanyl through the skin
It's a easy way to
Put something on for
People with really bad
Pain
People cancer free
Confuse them
It just is really really effective painkiller
Because fentanyl is really really
I mean a lot of people refer to fentanyl as
Start of the third wave of the opioid crisis
Just for context mean
What are the first two waves if you go back to the beginning of the crisis
The first wave was pills
When I
Early 2000s manufacturers begin flooding communities with pharmaceutical grade opiates
Then the second wave was around 2011 when there was a Crackdown on pills and so
A lot of people that were were using Pharmaceuticals began to migrate to heroin
In the Mexican cartels got very good at delivering that heroin
And then
Round 2013
3rd wave hits
Worst drug crisis
Ever drug dealers
People that are selling heroin
Start looking to fentanyl because fentanyl is so much cheaper
To either make or obtain the
Normal heroin
And most importantly Fentanyl
Is way more potent
Is it basically to to maximize their profit drug dealer start cutting fentanyl into heroin
Problem is that the people who are using they really have no idea what they're getting they think they're just getting heroin
2014 we started to see patients in our emergency department who were over.
Ghost with what they thought was heroin that probably turned out to be Fentanyl and more and more people were overdosing
Fentanyl powerful synthetic opiate about
Powerful Ultra potent synthetic opioid
And there are versions of the molecules changed a little bit and it makes it more potent and by 2016
Even more
Used to tranquilize elephants
And are fed most extremely potent
The same size as just seven grains of salt
Could kill you
John says it was right around this time
2016 started to be reports
I fall backwards law enforcement and I'm tryna
Trying to hold on to anything I can grass Emergency Medical Services
My face started on burning and even nurses in hospitals
I broke out in
Yes we're scribing getting ill when they were
Opposed
Powder that
It turned out later to be fentanyl or some other type of
How do you prestige
How did I hear about it
You guys
The media
Africa
I'm a representative of the media
Sky City
Pressure by carfentanil on Good Morning America started reading articles on it Jace other people in DMs
Reading about it your what is this drug what is going on but that's in the big city that's not going to happen
And then local Law Enforcement Officers budline please read about
Fentanyl I mean I read about it but I didn't think it would come to a small City like this
Chat with lions
What's what happened
Basically I was dispatched to the funeral home
So it's summer 2017 bud got called out
Parking lot of
The funeral home by female had passed out in her car when I got on scene woke her up got her out
Vehicle notice
She had some brown stuff on her face like a powder substance around your
Nostrils
Search the car and took an Evidence $1,000 in cash
And
Several little baggies of brown
Powder substance that turned out to be heroine
And that same night as he was like back in the evidence room going through
Through the money I didn't have no gloves on when I was counting money even funny started feeling really dizzy
Think straight
Drop the money drove his Cruiser up here into the parking lot of the EMS station and when he pulled in
He went down
A couple of EMS were there gave him this
Is Lazarus drug
Rush me to the hospital
Had that ever happened before no
First time it's ever happened
And
You know just a little touch
Basically almost killed me
Just a grain of
Fentanyl got on his skin
He sang that's all it took it like that was that was the story that was starting to emerge
Really across the country that like a tiny grain if you came into contact with it with a tiny grain of the struggle
Take you down so as soon as that happened
Biscotti weed
Made it
Pact between us to carry extra Narcan in the truck for us
In case we ever got exposed
Cuz I knew it was here
In the counting in the city
Then about a month after that
Sure nuff chewing on Steel
Struck in park
Bargain bows
I can remember coming to
And being in another ambulance
JP Mascaro either Narcan did stashed away his dose of Narcan and mine
Because he wouldn't wake up at 4
The first house
Condell Hospital
Scotty was kept under evaluation for about 4 hours
And then eventually
Discharge
The next day it was like
I was wondering hit
On the fact of
No one
Almost died doing my job
And that's essentially win
What began as a call for help
Became crime scene
What do you mean
I will tell you in a minute that's the break hi this is Heidi calling from
Nashville Tennessee Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world more information about Sloan
Www.slha.org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
About what we're calling tiny moments of brilliance
Basically I want to hear about those times when I kids you know did something
It just means you lean back and say wow
How do they do that
Maybe it was the moment that I
A kid you've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of their musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed are ready music in the margin of their geometry
We're interested in the
Epic moments where
A kid does something super smart but it doesn't have anything to do with the test
If you have a story with us
Go to radiolab.org
Flash brilliance
Record short audio message
And that's where you're at. Org / Brillion
Thank you so much
Chad Robert Radiolab back to Peter and Matt in Kentucky
Something that I
Kept thinking about
When are you down there in Kentucky
Driving around
Was that there is like no Duty
To render Aid
Even though there are some exceptions and statutes in some states
For the most part
There's just no
Obligation
We live in a society where you like do not you can sort of watch a person drown
And
You won't be held liable
You can do that
And
That legal
I just kept thinking about that
Salvation
So
When we were down there with
Earl the Jailer in the jail the old Bexar County Jail we just seen the needles and we were coming out to the parking lot
I go to West Cobb
And we
Spent probably
Like 2 or 3 days
Trying to find the people who are actually
In the apartment like a person who overdosed and the other two people who
We learned lived in that apartment at a phone number but nobody was picking up
But bear with arrow and
I just asked him if he knew this guy
Scotty Hatton
Is the difference guy
This is a different Scotty Scotty wightman's EMT
Who responded to call had this
Seeley Lake overdose exposure
I have lived in the apartment he was there the day that
Scott NJ showed up
Yeah I know what y'all want to talk to you more
Yeah I was just finally got the Scotty Whiteland started seriously just curious if what do you want to talk to him about what
What went on that night or get his side of the story I know that
Guaranteed
But then
He was like I can tell you where he is though
Because it turns out that Scotty had had on an ankle monitor
An Earl you know he's the Jailer so he just
Play pulls up his phone and looked up Scotty's GPS location
Total. For the TPS showed exactly where he was
If it's old Cemetery
General said like we could go down there in like maybe
He would talk to us
We get there pretty big and Spa
Brawley Cemetery
That was like
25 minutes out of town
Lots of big trees
Cicadas
Amy Scotty was actually out on this riding lawn mower
And we were standing there talking to his supervisor and Scotty himself like it's off the lawn mower comes over to us
Sunken eyes
Big eyes free skinny guy blue Duke ball cap blue jeans
So Scottie came over is supervisors went on the lawn mower started riding around
And Scotty
Immediately started talking to me like he wanted to tell his side of the story
He said he got sick I'm working online it's like sometimes you can take 24 hours
Oak Tree on a steep slope
I think it's very doubtful
Immediately started telling us that he was like suspicious of Scotty Whiteman
Story Pole
Overdose by touch
I mean because
He only touched the my other co-defendant you know and and I had washed him off you know I didn't know
You're not supposed to wash them on this overdose not but I did
And this guy trying to say he got infected you know got I could buy carfentanil and they didn't even
Find any drugs on the saying I found the
Very little paraphernalia
But
I know I'm done it's just one of those things I'm going to church now
How do I get this ankle monitor off I'm going to get saved I can't get saved and
What time are you can't submerge it
Where you going to get that day
I got a Freedom Church
In Mount Sterling gymnastics
Nirvana bunch of people making kind of nervous
We decided meet up with them later because of the lawn mower or cicadas
I said we went to his own Palace
He was living there he's gotten evicted from is
Apartment after 30
Love you
You don't say Ruby ain't you
Is nice to meet you guys
Depends got his girlfriend a Jessica she was the other person in the apartment
Fidgets overdose
She was also now leaving biscotti at is on but she didn't want to talk to us
So then the three of us sat down on the couch in the living room and Scotty
Just started telling us about his own story
And
I think his story definitely has it is a very like sort of common trajectory
Great Lake where did you grow up with around here in Bath County been here
My whole life pretty much
Just got to grow up in government housing in a small apartment
With his sister is Mom she had another husband by then not my dad he's my stepdad stepdad
This guy named Ricky who dated pretty popular in the story a dragon claw
When I call I get home
And I was like 15 16 I'm going to my grandma and
Love my dad my grandma on
I was in the sports I make decent grades
Now I don't even hardly go see my dad
It got him a case I guess he's got several
Charges pending
So when was the first time you used
First time I ever took narcotics I was 19
He got kidney stones never had a pain worse than that
Hurts so bad I was crying he mentioned it to his dad he had a motorcycle wreck kind of messed him up
Elsa hearing how you can take one of my pain pills it was a Lortab hydrocodone and acetaminophen
Said when he took it before you felt
Total relief
That's like to feel and you know makes me feel really really good at getting his medicine
Take it and take two or three and then it just you know got to experiment and more and more started using
Perc 30s for sure
Definitely flooding into
Places like Kentucky in the
Early 2000s
So this is like the sort of first wave of the
The opioid crisis
Biscotti said it first
You would get pills from Friends people at work and then it just you know got too well you know I started buying pills
Crossover
Probably my mid-20s he started taking
I'm talking bread right he was talking Freddy was also working in the factory quadrat works at Steel
Call somebody and I've always been that way I don't really want to stay off people feel like I can work to make enough money to
It was really hard
I mean I made 5 $600 weekend
Yeah I wouldn't have any left because you expense
All of it on on pills and he was doing that for years and probably about like 2011 or 12
Do heroin come around that's when I start doing it
Because it was cheaper
Cuz it was cheaper and because I was spending
$8,200 into pills
Just two pills is two pills
You know you might get a little behind it might not last very long at all
No Friday or $100 heroin you can get a lot more and it's a lot more powerful
So that it just makes sense
Calculus Heat
He did heroin for like five or six years he didn't inject it but he would do it snort it
And he says he
Tried to quit a couple of times but
Justin
Which is probably just an excuse for I couldn't
Al ahed Rock
Complete rock bottom
Scotty says that was the day
Of the overdoses in an apartment yet
Can you pick up at some point like where where do
Where is it start
If I going to have to ask me
What questions on this cuz I'm going to make sure I back from some of it a little bit
Sauce
Ask me again what you saw Jessica
And your son Gabriel Jessica Scott his girlfriend the two of them have a son together Gabriel
And
It's her apartment
At some point Ricky is with you guys again Ricky is the stepdad or like why is he over there
He's burned all his Bridges
Earned it sounds like he was last living with friends and like that a falling-out yeah seems like everybody else
Sorry giving up on him we felt sorry for him he and where to go so
You know you can stay here a couple days
And that was it
And then
Like I don't know where would you start
But that day
Really don't
Nowhere to go with this
I'm trying to not you know
Red saver
I think I think last time
We spoke it was like
At some point
You noticed Ricky
Like I can go from there probably little bit
You know
Tell Scotty play newest dead he and Jessica were in the living room in the apartment sitting on the couch
And at some point Ricky had gotten up
And gone into the kitchen
And
After the wild Scotty realize
That the kitchen sink the water in the kitchen sink I've been running
For a while
Why is the water running you know so I go in there cuz it's the kitchen and sees Ricky standing over the kitchen sink
And he said he looked
Locked up
Frozen lake lake is arms were really stiff his fist restore like clenched racing grabbing the countertop tongue
Pop my words in his mouth you can come to mouth barely open you can see it I kind of knew what it probably
Was od'ing I get a chair and I getting
Hey I struggle to get him in it
A gaming chair
He's out
We have one of those
Not only a fall so young little spray things
Spring
Yeah I don't spring with cold water or something while you know that might wake him up
I'm washing in the face and
I did smack in the face u x
He just
Are you in like a
So then I knew
We had to make the
Decision
To call the
The ambulance service
What happens next
I started getting a little bit you know
Out of it I guess I don't remember a lot after that
So I said listen to the 911 call
And in Scotty didn't really test us and I don't know
I mean it's not that I don't believe him but I do think there was something
I do think they started like
In that moment they must have been a little like
What do we do next
Tuesday
August
Mm
They weren't the first one to call my home on that day
First person to call Buzz actually Ricky's brother
Which means someone must have called Ricky's brother
Homo is going on they didn't know what to do because when he calls
He said something like
Something about an outstanding warrant
Sir like they're worried about outstanding warrants
Outside
Google
And then another thing you here in these recordings other call
Which is from one of Scotty and Jessica's Neighbors
Scotty is a Scotty could come over to her house
She made him leave
Sounds like their one-year-old son was in the apartment at the timeout wow really
They were worried about the police coming in and losing custody of their kid
And I feel like for them
In that moment
What when Ricky was with lying on the floor
I think there were some questions in their mind like
What's the right thing to do
How do we
How do we do the right thing
Without getting ourselves in trouble
They did make the call
Apartment 301 Jessica called 911
It was two minutes after Ricky's brother made that first call
Goblin show
And I believe one of the reasons that they made the call that day
Was because
They knew about this law I didn't know exactly what it said I did know that it
And came in my mind you will be okay it was designed
Protect people in exactly this situation
The Good Samaritan
Call
The Good Samaritan law
Don't round 2010-2011 12 at this opioid epidemic was escalating
A lot of states started adopting these 911 Good Samaritan laws
46 States
Including Kentucky now have these laws
Which eventually say if using drugs
With someone and that person overdoses
We don't want you fearful
If you make the call that may save their life
He'll be in trouble at least show up you and the person who overdosed won't be charged
Your granted immunity because you essentially did the right thing like you reach out for help or should have like intent of the Good Samaritan laws
Make people who are in the presence of a drug overdose do you want these people to call for
For help because otherwise
You know
There's a good rest of these people are just going to die
Where does where does the Good Samaritan
Music Christian it is a Christian periobrite we got the Bible right here
So I'm
Yeah it's a it's a
The parables in the Gospel of Luke
It's Jesus is telling the story
And
So there's a
That you he's
On the road to Jericho
And
As he's walking along
Some robbers come and they
They steal his money and they beat him up
And I leave them in a ditch
And there's actually left
Don't forget
And then
Another person comes along the road
And
But is that helping him this person like
No crosses the road in the
Keeps on walking
Second person comes by
Same thing
And then a third person comes
End
It's a Samaritan
And like the Jews and the Samaritans were like mortal enemies
Like
They they absolutely detest each other
But when the Samaritan seizes jue Lan in a ditch
Indeed
The Good Samaritan stops and he helps
Help this guy and
Give them money and shelter in
And treats his wounds
And you know like essentially saves his life
So that the story about
Like showing kindness to your enemy
Interesting about this is that
Jesus is talking to a legal scholar
And
So it's true about setting up
I like morality verses
The law
And
And so like what I guess what he's saying is that if if you see somebody that's in need you don't think about what the law says you should have
Do you
You just
You just help the person in need
It's like
You know
Unconditional love
Like takes precedence
Over
Over the letter of the law
Lake but then of course
There is
The law
Ronnie
Does New York reporters are here to stick a microphone of your face
And what seems to be happening across country is prosecutors
Are beginning to push back
Against the Good Samaritan
Thank you
Sweet guy Ronnie Goldy
Is the Commonwealth Attorney
He's off the lead prosecutor in the case against Ricky Jessica
Scotty
Got this from
Adam New York and it's just not something that that I would have expected certain like isn't working for use her own little problems in here and I would assume you
Got bigger problems in New York to deal with them
Then what we were dealing with it
That's fine I mean
Glad that you guys
Got down this way
So what did he say
Say to you about
Asrani starter explained it
To us to go back with our legislature in and the way they they have drafted the
Good Samaritan law the way the law is written in Kentucky is that
If you call 911 for a drug overdose
You're only granted immunity for
Specific types of charges you cannot charge them with possession of controlled substance drug possession or possession of drug paraphernalia drug
Paraphernalia just those two charges
But we didn't charge him with possession we charge them with wanton endangerment
In this way you see this sort of pushed back
Wanted me to take the legal term for when you do something that quit somebody at risk for physical injury or or
Conscious disregard for
What cat
Credit card
It's like driving drunk
So in this situation with fentanyl
You created this number one of the child
I'm being seriously injured or killed by someone overdose or
What other injuries and then also you placed
Paramedics law enforcement
And social workers that you would have to come in
And that's that circumstance
So rather than granting Scotty Ricky and Jessica
Protection
Ronnie Goldy
Commonwealth of Kentucky
Has charge them
With 10 counts
So tell me what endangerment
To each one of them are getting hit with 10 felony charges
Low white n so there was one charge for endangering
The child
So like the the the 1 year old could have gotten into the drug somehow and
And
Become exposed that way
And then there was
Wanted if there are nine additional charges
One for each
Of the the people that came to the house that day
The police
The social workers
And all the EMS that responded
And I think we should stay here that the Jessica who's now facing these 10 felony charges
The day
Of the over dashefsky tested negative
For opiates
But in there getting their kid checked out okay to
Call she was like in the apartment and made the call
The other thing to mention is
That like the thing that she and Scotty
Were scared of which was losing custody of
Their son
That that did happen
I'm not mad about that
I understand that I understand that aspect you
Drug stuff found in the home
They took him I understand that
As far as the other things
10 felonies
I don't understand them
But Ronnie's
Argument is that
Because of the number of people who had been overdosing in the community
Because of the local and national news reporting about heroin being laced with drugs like Fentanyl and carfentanil
But you can argue the rest that you knew was out there but yet you're using anyway
You should know better
But it's up to you it's like I don't know I don't know if loopholes the right word but it's like it's a way in which you can still as you said like your preclude
Booted from bringing charges for possession
Of drugs and paraphernalia but like there is a sort of side door be like well
We can charge you for this
Now that's not the case at all
It's not like we're trying to say okay we don't like to get smeargle always go around it
And that's not how I work that's not how we work
The thing I don't understand it seems like
The net effect of the Good Samaritan laws to sort of reduce fatalities and it seems like
Rather successful in reducing fatality so you are
Encouraging people to call nine-one-one you are reducing fatalities and in this case if they hadn't call 911
Possible that the
Ricky Mays the patient would have died so
In some ways I feel like I totally understand it I don't understand the reason behind it
But what I may think morally or personally
I don't have that luxury
I have a statute that I have to follow because when I took the oath of office it is it I will uphold
The laws of the Commonwealth and if it's a Crime After Crime I don't get to say well but they were trying to do the right thing
Life is a crime it is a crime and I have to pursue it
We actually we talked to another prosecutor mauldin's case
Kim hunt price
Is the county attorney who indicted
Ricky Scott and Jessica have people whose jobs
Are to protect the public who have to be there
You know the message needs to go out there these people are protected
As well
Pressure
People weren't calling you locally or there wasn't somebody from like the state
Like no one calling from the state or anything like that I mean I just had my
Local people you know that were
Concerned about it and was it the people who were there we're calling you early
I kind of think one of them did call me you know just say is there anything
We can do you know with regard to this is there an appropriate criminal charge
Believe mr. Whiteman is so dead
Okay so
My Tata Sky Whiteman
We asked him
Essentially why was it
Did he wanted to see these people charged our view it as a call for
Accountability
They're doing heroin
Will get out here we'll roll around in the yard for a week
I have no issues with that
But when you do something
They could cause harm to me
I've got a problem with that
I think clay KY
Understand that but
Ultimately also feel like
Did they truly didn't
Know that like this is a drug that somebody could like brush up against or something like that and potentially
Have reaction that there's
Just not enough knowledge there for them to
Have
Even even even a sense of the fact that they could be endangering other people
And then said he didn't know that you've been through this
Experience with an accident I would kind of felt like on just surprised
That
That you
What it may be extended them
I sort of Lake
I'm no sympathy the right word but
I think
That if you harm someone
You should be held accountable
If you guys know now that I'm going on vacation
September the
16th is a
The hard day
That the anniversary of his truck accident
Where he killed three people
That Sunday yes cuz yep
So
Sunday I will
Probably lock myself in a room way from everybody
The biggest part of the morning
If I'm scheduled to work
September 16th is the day that I take off
From
From the morning till noon is
It's time for
Made to pay my respects to them
And even though
Here we are coming up on
19 years later
Still do that
Just my way of
Dealing with it I guess
What are you doing that moment
When you're when you isolate
One of those that I reflect on that morning
And I still try to figure out if there was anything that I could have done different
That may have changed the outcome
What I done
May 1st
I still have nightmares I still wake up in cold sweats
I'm just with you steam engine is yes
Lurk not yesterday me last time we were here
That
So nicely I think there was a
There's a lawsuit filed by the family against
Company
But then there was a civil suit that you had to go through
Peter benchley bankrupted you
And
What I'm wondering is Lake
Did you feel that was
Deserve to feel like that was
Justified
Yes
I took three members of that family away from them
That took potential
Earnings wife in that family
Birthdays and Christmases Miss
What's those that were
Tyson that day
So yeah
I feel like very Justified
I was held accountable for my actions of that morning
And then
When you look at the
Exposure case
She needs to be
Accountable for those actions because he knew the risks that were involved
Right just as I think like getting behind the wheel of a
Truck
You know on September 16th 1989
Thank you know that
There could be consequences
His butt
You never
If that's why it's an accident right it's like
The same thing if you'd taken like I don't know
2 mg less of the drug it's like
I seem like really they seem like really similar situation the most and I guess I'm just wondering
Like what
Why is it hard to forgive him
Don't say I didn't
Forgiven for it
It's just
I think
They should be held accountable for his actions
I mean like all of that sort of like brings us to the the big question in the story
What happened that day because if we're going to hold Scotty hadn't accountable for what happened to Scotty Whiteman
You need to be able to show that that the drugs in the apartment or whatever was on Ricky skin
Like could actually
Caused him to overdose
Would you have any
Do you have any reason to doubt that the reason I found this story was it was reported as a credible
Report in the New York Times
Everybody sort of acknowledge that
No First Responders were going down all across the country
But when I
Actor John Cole
Toxicologist from earlier
He said well
I don't doubt any of the symptoms that any of these
Fire EMS
Police officers have
Experience
He was skeptical not 100% clear if that's
Actually due to the
Fentanyl
Or to some other event that occurred in those
And John Cole wasn't alone I mean I I started calling like
Doctors in toxicologist pharmacologist
And they said the like the risk that fence all posed to First Responders
Was extremely low
Why what was there which I think well for one I mean like that the powder doesn't spontaneously aerosol eyes it doesn't
Don't like proof into the air so that makes like breathing it in
Pretty unlikely
As far as the skin to skin contact thing
So poorly absorbed
Feel like substance itself doesn't pass through the skin easily to get fentanyl to absorb through your skin
You have to use
A special Matrix to be able to know if you want to offend I'll pass you have to sort of use the solvent to get the absorption
To even be to the point where it's
Therapeutic
Let alone in Alberta
Even if you put a fentanyl patch on it takes it takes a very long time for the drug to sort of like achieve a meaningful dose
In the body
But something is happening to these people I mean after
Assume so
It's not the drugs
What is it
It says he has he I was John Cole and a couple of other people brought up with this idea that maybe it wasn't that
External situation that they're in there was more it was more something internal
One of these people
Felt symptoms that are very real
Vedanta the symptoms
Don't don't really match the symptoms of a typical opiate overdose
Princeton
Hyperventilating
I hope you answer usually beating slower not breathing faster
Or a lot of First Responders reported feeling a sense of great
Impending doom
Opiates are all about Serenity and pleasure
Not impending doom
And so if you look at the symptoms and started the stories that are being told about these new substances in these new city
Situation in our culture right now
He says
Kind of looks like a mask
A mass panic so there is a condition
Called Mass psychogenic illness
This is the thing that John Cole says that he's actually come across
In his work at the that the Minnesota poison
There was a
A school event in a bunch of
You said that about
45 years ago there was this incident
Republic school in Minnesota
We're about your kids started like killing over cuz
They thought
It was like carbon monoxide poison
Subsequent student after student begin to feel they took all these kids to the hospital and they live
Give them blood test none of the blood levels
Positive for carbonara
I just didn't check out the medical conditions are are ruled out from unknown
Poison
You have to start considering other causes and and that event was consistent with
Actress condition called Mass psychogenic
Illness when you think about you know First Responders showing up the scene of a drug overdose
What's running through their mind is this like
Constant onslaught of news reports another
Anecdotal accounts they've heard about their
They're their friends in their colleagues that are
No passing out it isn't it isn't that anybody's crazy or we gets that
Their mind is
Causing them to be physically ill they really are sick
But it isn't necessarily due to the thing
That they believe that it is
Does that make sense
My response to that is
So what we knew what the scientist
And then thing in Sky says basically like look
They can say whatever they want to in their lives but
This is what I went through I just know
The effects of that day
That
I came in contact with something
That put me in an overdosing situation
An inmate at the Clark County Detention Center
Kentucky
Charges for your call has been accepted
Hello
Hi Ricky this is Peter Smith
I ended up sending a postcard to the jail
Because the jails don't accept
Letters cuz they're afraid of drugs getting in
And a week later I got a call from Ricky Mays
Ricky is
Scotty's stepfather
And he's also the person who overdosed
Biscotti white men treat it
And he told me that it wasn't there wasn't a whole lot of Toxicology have an answer medical records or much
Anything really better
He had agreed to a plea deal
For all 10 wanton endangerment charges
Yes I played you took 3 years I mean
Maurice Forster
You said you were more or less forced
Yes
Because where he's at a repeat felony offender
He was looking at like 20 years
Instead of the three that he took
What's the message you're putting out there is if anybody oldies right here or anything like that so mean to ditch
Illegal
Message sister
Court systems putting out the people
That's what I thought
How to how does that make you feel I mean is that
Yeah
Is it seems like if they didn't call you we wouldn't be talking right now
I said if if if
If they haven't called nine-one-one that day
Like the Good Samaritan law assertive says you can
Doesn't seem like we were talking right now
Hayden real thing
Yeah
For what they done
Anything else you ask
That's why I just ramble on all day
I'm like Ricky Scotty has refused to take a plea deal
Instead he's going to risk
Up to 20 years in jail
By taking his case
Trial I think about everyday
Every day at work
Fur Elise couple hours I think about
And the same
Same answer comes up every day I have
I have to take Anadrol
I don't I don't want him doing this
New everybody man
Let that they're going to be afraid to call 911
I feel like for me like
Give it away it's gone give me the way
People and how they think about
Drugs like I I just I don't
I'm about to have the same sort of like confidence and conviction
I understand where you're coming from that's what my lawyer says to
Think when a few things comes like you know
Like
They may say well he did get sick while we're going to stay while he didn't test positive for anyting
Could have been something else
Every little bit of doubt that you created
Reasonable Doubt
And all you got to do is convince one person that Jerry is saying I'm not doing it
That's all you got to do
Obviously the jury will be making
A decision about
The case
In about what happened in the apartment that day
But
I think there's sort of a bigger sort of more consequential
Message
That they'll be sending about
What people like Scotty and Scotty
Should believe in
What they should fear
And
What they should do
Going forward
50 charges end up getting dismissed
Or
If it goes to trial in and the
People are found not guilty for
Morning intermittently how are you going to feel
If they're found not guilty then I'm going to trust in the judicial system that
There was some things that come to life that maybe I wasn't aware of and
If they're not found guilty then so bad if he goes out and use again
I'm on shift when it happens
I walk in and saying guess what
What job is to do everything within my power to save his life
And that's what I'm going to do
And
Ask the other Scotty
What would you do would you make the same called you think other people to make the same call if like if this is what's on the end of that call Button
Actually
Call Tri do most people
Depending on how the Arlo
Trout probably try to just leave the person
Dragon outside or something like that people in jail was saying do that
Or
No cover up
Everything at the crime scene or whatever you know
Or just not called and said that
If I knew that would have been 10 felonies man
Amanda Steele got a call the guy can't die
That's what I believe I really believe that man
Which I hadn't first got arrested for the wanton endangerment charges he spent six months in jail
African Audino attends church every Sunday with his family oil watches
Veggie veggie tales
And Jessica have partial custody back of their son Gabriel
That's a tomato
Better bundo tomato
The weather
Cambodian Jessica
Have pending trials
Schedule for December
Okay border Peter Smith and Matt kielty also special thanks in this episode 2
Cecil Lawson and Jason York and Gary billiard and all the EMTs in the Medics who generously allowed
How to go around
And ride with them see what they saw exactly end touch out and John Sunderland Chris kipley dr. David your link
Danji
Thomas Williams and Corey S Davis
I'm Jedi
Hi this is James man from Denver Colorado
Dylan Keith is a directory sound design Susie lechtenberg is our executive producer
Gallstones includes Simon Adler Rebecca Breslow Rachel Cusick David Cavell methylheptane
Tracy hunt Nora Keller Robert krulwich Annie McEwen classic NASA
Mariah Carey
Pupusas Emily Webster withheld from Shima Ali-A W Harry Fortuna Pandora
Sequin effect Checker is Michelle Harris