Are you awake
Listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
I'm Jedi bomb run I'm Robert krulwich you know what this is is from
Okay so we can play you a little bit take first just
To set up there what we're going to do today
About a month ago we were doing the thing about
The fake news
Yeah we're worried worried about a lot of things a lot of people I but in the middle of doing that reporting we
We were talking with
I fell from Vanity Fair my name is Nick. And I'm a special correspondent for Vanity Fair in the course of our conversation
And this has nothing to do what we talked about by the way Nick just got into a sort of a
Well he wouldn't do a kind of a nervous reverie
I'd say he was like you know you guys want to talk about fake news
That's not actually with eating at me
The thing that I've been pretty obsessed with lately
Is actually not fake news but it's Automation and artificial intelligence and driverless cars
Because
It's going to
A larger effect on society
Then any technology that has ever been created
History of mankind
I know it's kind of a bold statement but
But you got to imagine that you know
That there will be in the next
10 years
20 to 50 million jobs that were
Call to Spanish. Automation you know
Million truckers that will lose their jobs
They do but it's not we think about like automation drive us cars and we think about
The fact that
They are going to
The people that just drive the cars like the taxi drivers in the truck was going to lose their jobs what we don't realize is that there
Entire industries that are built around
Just cars
Sulfur example
If you are not driving the car
Why do you need insurance
Did the new parking ticket
Because your driver's car knows where I can and cannot park and goes and finds a spot and moves and so on
I'm if there truckers that are no longer using rest stops
Speakers drivers cars don't have to stop and pee or take a nap then
All of those little rest stops all across America who are affected people aren't stopping to use the restroom
Do not bind Burgers they're not staying in these hotels and so on and so forth then
And then
You look a driverless cars to next level
The whole concept of what a car is
What is going to change so for example right now
A car has 5 seats in a wheel
But if I'm not driving
What's the point of having five seats in a wheel you could imagine that you take different cars and maybe when I was on my way here too
To this interview
I wanted to work out so I called a driverless GM car
Or Ivan meeting out in Santa Monica after this and it's an hour or so I call a movie car to watch a movie on the way out there or
Apus car
And I pick up someone else we have a meeting on the way and all of these things are going to happen
Not in a vacuum but simultaneously this you know pizza delivery drivers going to be replaced by robots that will actually cook your pizza on the
The way to your house
In a little box and then deliver it
And so
Kind of a little bit of a along with an answer but I truly do think that
It's going to have a
A massive Mass Effect
Society
Am I stressing you guys out and you are you having heart palpitations over there, so that's a fairly
Compelling description of a of a
Have a very dangerous future
But you know what it's funny one of the things that we couldn't use that tape
Initially at least but we kept thinking about it because it actually weirdly points us
Back
To a story we did
About a decade ago
The story of a moral problem that's about to get
Totally reimagined it maybe the what Nick is worried about
And what we were worried about 10 years ago
Anel coming dangerously close together
So what we thought we could do is weird we're going to play you the story as we did it then
Sir the full segment
And then we're going to a minute on the back end and by way of Justice claiming this was at a moment in our
Development
Where there's just way too many sound effects just gratuitous
Do much
And also like we we talked about the fmri machine like it's just like amazing penguin
Was
Soda cam
We're getting late for you and then talk about it on the back end this we start
With a description of something called
The trolley problem
Unison train track
Go there in your mind
There are five workers
On the tracks work
It got their backs
Turn to the trolley Witch is coming in the distance
Mina repairing the
Unbeknownst
They don't see it
You can't shout to them okay and if you do nothing
Here's what'll happen
How did workers will die
I was a horrible experience I don't want that to happen again but you have a choice
You can do a
Nothing or B
It so happens next to you is a lever
Pull the lever in the trolley will jump onto some sidetracks where there is only one person
So if
Charlie goes on the second check it will kill the one guy so there's your choice.
Kill one man by pulling a lever
Or do you kill five men
By doing
Naturally
Right here
Part 2
You stand near some train tracks
Five guys are in the tracks
4 and there is the trolley, right
Exactly how random a couple changes now you're standing on a foot
The past is over the tracks
You looking down
Onto the tracks
No lever anywhere to be seen except next to you
There is a guy
Leaving is a guy a large guy large individual standing next to you on the bridge looking down with you over the tracks
You realize wait I can save those 5
If I push this man
Heels land on the track since
I'm not going to do that I'm not going to
Do the app that really you realize the math is the same
Email safe for people this way
Yeah but this time I'm pushing the guy
Insane
But here's the thing if you ask people these questions and we did starting with the first
Is it okay to kill one man to save 5 using a lever
9 out of 10 people will say but if you ask them is it okay to kill one
Amanda Seyfried
By pushing the guy
9 out of 10 people will say
Universal
And the thing is if you ask people why is it okay
To murder
That's what it is murder a man with a lever and
Not okay to do with your hands
People don't really know
Pulling a lever to save the five
I know that feels better than
Pushing a wine
We save the five
But I don't really know why so that's a good there's a good
Mohawk laundry Maria
Hahaha
And yet having a moral sense is a unique and
Special human quality than maybe we
We pass to humans anyway you and me can sit at least inquire as to why this
Happens
And I happen to meet somebody
Who has a hunch
He's a young guy at Princeton University wild curly hair for the Mischief in his eye his name is Josh
And he spent the last two years trying to figure out where this inconsistency comes from
How do people make this judgment
Forget whether or not these judgments are right or wrong just what's going on in the brain
That makes people distinguish so naturally and intuitively between these two cases which
Actuarial point of view
AR
Very very very similar
Josh is by the way a philosopher and in Euro size
Scientist so this gives him special powers
Cheers smoke a pipe
Now why you have these differences
Even though I would like to look
Inside people's
Heads
Because in our heads we may find Clues as to where these feelings of revulsion or acceptance come from
In our brains
I so we're here in the control room
We basically
Happens if the basement of Princeton
There was this song
Big circular thing
Hound
Brain scan
Say a funny story
You can't have any metal in
Because the magnet
Tell me this long with the questions we ask
People to make sure they can go in
You have a pacemaker if you ever worked with metal Bowl
Yeah cuz you have little flecks of metal in your eye
But you never even know where they are from having done metal working
And one of the questions is whether or not you wear a wig or anything like that
Because they often has metal wires and with that and there's this very nice woman who does brain research here who's Italian
She's asking to her subjects
Over the phone
All all these freaking question
So I have this person over to dinner
Unit study Brazil
A few weirdest questions This Woman's like
Do you have a hairpiece
And
What does it have to do if I have herpes or not anyway
And she said yes yes you said you have a hair piece
But she at
Anyhow what Josh does it
Is he invite people into this room has them lie down in what is essentially a
Cotton rollers
New rules been into the machine
Their heads are brace
Never done this
Yep several times
I meant tells the story she tells him the same to a note Raleigh Tales you told before and then at the very instant
They decided whether I
Lever weather right now
What's the man that insta
The scanners
Snaps pictures
Of their brain
And what he found in those pictures
Artlink he showed us some
Okay
The picture that I'm looking at
It's a brain look like it's from the top down
Is top-down instead of slice
You know like
In the first slide
You showed me was a human brain being asked
Would you pull the lever and the answering most kids with yes
Little Pine
Peanut shape spots
Yellow and this little guy right
Here and these
Two guys right
Dreams being active in these
Oddly enough whenever
People say yes
The labor question
The very same pattern lit up
Danny showed me another
There's a side of Green saying no
The large man
And this pic
Picture this one we're looking at
Hear this it was totally different constellations
This is the No No No crowd
I think this is part of the No No No Cry
So when people answer yes
Clever question there are there places in the brain which glow
Push the man then you get a completely different part of the brain by
Even though the questions are
Basically the same
What does that mean
What does Josh mean
Ethereal
Theory
Proven but I think this is what I think you have it in
He suggests
That the human brain doesn't hum along with one big Unified
Light system
Define warring tribes
1edisource
Doing a logical sort of accounting kind of thing
You got one part of the brain that says
5 lies worse when life would it be better to say 5 vs 1 and that's the part that would blow when you answer yes
I pulled the lever
If this other part of the brain
Would you really really doesn't like personally killing another human being gets very upset
The Fatman Kate and shouts in effect understand it on that level it says
No no bad don't do no hooks
Okay
Instead of having sitter if one system that just sort of turns out the answer and Bing
We have multiple systems they give different answers they duke it out and hopefully out of that competition
Comes
Morality
This is not a
Trivial discovery that you struggle to find right and wrong
Depending upon what part of your brain is shouting the loudest
Play Bleachers Morales
You buy this
Don't know
I've always
Hina suspected that a sense of right and wrong is mostly stuff
Dipping your mom
And your dad
A dent from Experian
Culturally
For the most part
Joshua
Kind of a radical in this room
Biological
Biological inherit from the Jeep Pass
The sense of right and wrong it's already in our brains
From the gecko before Mommy
Are are primate answer
Before we were
Full-blown humans
How to intensely social lives
They have
Social mechanism
That prevent them from doing all the nasty things that they might otherwise be in
Didn't do it
And so deep in our brain we have what you might call Basic primate morality
And basic primate morality doesn't understand things like tax
But it doesn't understand things like pushing your body off of a cliff
So you're thinking them at the man on the bridge that I'm on the bridge next to the large man
And I have hundreds of thousands of years of training in my brain that says
Don't
Murder the light
We're at even if I'm thinking
If I murdered a large man I'm going to save five lives and only killed women
But there's something deeper damages don't
Murdered Elijah
But that case I think it's a pretty easy case
Even though it's five versus one
In that case
These people just go with
What we might call the Inn
Leadership
But there are other
Matera temperature
Unfortunately of describing an act of goodness
Ten Commandments for energy
But what's interesting is that we think of of basic human morality
As being handed down from on high
And it's probably better to say that it was handed Up From Below
That are most basic
Core moral values
Are not the things that we humans
Have invented
The things that we've actually inherited from other people the stuff that we humans have invented
Are the things that seem more peripheral and variable
Something as basic as
Thou shalt not kill
Which made people think was handed down in tablet form from a Mountaintop
From God directly to humans nochimson ball
You're suggesting that hundreds of thousands of years of on-the-ground training have gotten our brains to think
Don't kill your kitten
You know that should be your default response I mean certainly chimpanzees are
Extremely violent and they do
Kill each other
But they don't do it as matter of
Of course
They so to speak after
Have some contacts NC
Friesen Ford
Profound
Moral position
Maybe somehow embedded
In Braintree
And Josh thinks there are times when these different moral positions that we have embedded inside of us Ann Arbor
Braids
When they can come into conflict
And in the original episode we went into One More Story
This one you might call the crying baby dilemma
The situation is somewhat similar to
The last episode of mash
Familiar with
The way we talk.
It's wartime
You're hiding in the basement with some of your fellow villagers
Achilles life and the enemy soldiers are out
They have orders to
Kill anyone that they fight
Nobody make a sound
So there you are you're huddled in the basement
All around you are enemy troops and you're holding your baby
Your baby with a cold
And you know that your baby could cost at any moment they hear your baby
They're going to find you and the baby and everyone else they're going to kill everybody
And the only way you can stop this from happening is cover the babies
Do that babies going to smother and die
If you don't cover the baby's mouth
Soldiers going to fight everybody and everybody's going to be
Including you including
Can you have the choice
Would you smother your own baby
To save the village
Or would you like your baby
Knowing the consequences
And this is a very tough Quest
People take
A long time to think about it
And some people say yes and some people say no
Children
Blessing and a gift from God
And we do not do that
Next children
I think I would
Put my baby to save everyone else and myself
No I would not kill the baby my baby I have the right
To terminate
The life I'd like to say that I would kill the baby but I don't know if I'd have the Inner Strength if it comes down to killing my own child
Moon daughter my own son
Then I choose that was done in World War 2
When the Germans were coming around
It was a mother that had a baby that was crying and
Better to be found she actually suffocated the baby but the other people live in
No you do not kill your baby
In the final mashup
The Korean woman whose character list
Sluggishly
She killed it
Oh my God
Ridiculous
I just wanted to be quiet
Baby
Darrell Davis
What Josh did
Is he asked
People that question would you murder your own child
While they were
In the brain scan
And it just the moment when they were
Trying to decide what they would do
He took pictures of
Their brains
And what he saw
The contest
Describe before
What's global
It was a whole world
War
That gang of accountants that part of the brain was busy calculating calculating the whole Village Podiatry
But the older and deeper inside
Also
Kill the baby inside the dream was literally divided
Different tribes in the brain literally trying to shout each other out
And this is a different kind of contest in the world
We talked about before remember before when people were pushing a man off of a bridge
Overwhelmingly their brains yellow
No no don't push the man
When people were pulling the lever over
Here
I don't think really anybody win
Who breaks
The time and they have to answer something right
A good Quest
And now
Is there a
You what happened
Is it just two cries that fight each other out or is there a judge
Well that's an interesting question
And that's one of the things that were looking at
When you are in this moment
Parts of your brain contest
There are two green reach of these two areas here
For the front
Right behind your eyebrows left and right that light up
And this is particular to us
He showed me a slide at Snow's sword
Areas that are very highly developed in humans
So when we have a problem that we need to deliberate over
The light
Front of the brain is above my eyebrows
Sort of yeah
Right about there
And there's two of them one on the left and one on the right
And they are the things that monkeys don't have as much of that we have
Certainly these parts of the brain are more highly developed in
I'm looking at these two flashes of light at the
The front of a human brain
You could say we are looking at what makes us special
That's a fair statement
A human being wrestling with a problem
That's what that is
Yeah we're supposed to emotional but there's also a set of a rational attempt to sort of sort through those emotion
Those are the cases that are showing more activity in that area
So in those cases when these
Dots above our eyebrows
What are they doing what he doesn't know for sure
What he found
Is in these
Close contest
It's whenever those nodes
Are very very Act
It appears
That the
Calculating section of the brain
Gets a bit of a boost
And the visceral inner chimp
Section of the brain
Is kind of muff
No
The people who chose to
Kill their children
Who made what is essentially a logical decision over and over those
Subject
Had
Writer glows in these two areas
And longer
Glows in these
Is Terraria so there is a definite Association
Between these two dots above the eyebrow
And the power of the logical brain over the inner chamber of the viscera
Well you know that's the hypothesis was going to take a lot of more research disorder
Tease apart
What these different parts of the brain are doing or if some of these are just sort of activated
Incidental
Kind of way at me really don't know
Dissolve
All very new
Okay so that was the story we put together many many many years ago about a decade ago
And at that point the whole idea of thinking of morality is
Kind of purely a brain thing
It's relatively new
And certainly the idea philosophers working with fmri machines
Super new
But now here we are 10 years later and some updates
Call Josh Green in the long long stream of times I assume now you have a 3-g
Giraffes
To Bob's rats and children kids and we're close to adding a cat we talked to him again he has
Has started a family he's switch labs
From Princeton to Harvard
But that whole time that interim decade he has still been thinking
And working on the trolley problem do you ever write the story differently absolutely
For years he's been trying out different permutations of
The scenario on people like okay
Instead of pushing the guy off the bridge with your hands what if you did it but
Not with your hair
Still in one version we ask people about
Hitting a switch that opens a trap door on the Footbridge and drops
In one version of that place which is right next to the purse
Another version of switches
Far away
And in yet another version you're right next to the person and you don't push them off with your hands but you push them with a pole
Who
And to cut to the chase what Josh is found
Is it the basic results that we talked about that's roughly held up
Still the case that people would like
To save the most number of lives
But not if it means pushing somebody with their own hands or with a pole for that matter
There's something kinda interesting
He and others have found that there are two groups
There are more willing to push the guy off the bridge
They are Buddhist monks
And psychopath
I mean some people just
Don't care very much about hurting other people they don't have that kind of an emotional wreck
Response that would be the Psychopaths where's the Buddhist monks presumably
A really good at shushing there
Inner chimpanzee called it
And just saying to themselves you know I'm aware that this is that
That killing somebody is a terrible thing to do
And I feel that but I recognize that this
Is done for a noble reason
And therefore
It's it's it's okay
So there's all kinds of interesting things you can say about the trolley problem
As a thought experiment at the end of the day it's just that it's a thought experiment
What got us interested in revisiting it
Is that it seems like the thought experiment is about to get real
That's coming up right after the break
This is Amanda Darby
Calling from Rockville Maryland
Radiolab
It is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of
Science and technology in the modern world more information about Sloan
@www. Sloan
. org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here I'm a producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help this summer I'm hosting a show
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
About what we're calling tiny moments
Brilliance basically I want to hear about those times when a kid you know did something
It just means you lean back and say whoa how did they do that maybe it was the moment that a kid
Did you been reading to 4 month started reading back
Do you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lesson
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the musical score or maybe the kids in math class
I noticed their writing music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the small specific moments where a kid does something super smart
It doesn't have anything to do with the test
If you have a story
T-shirt with us
Go to radiolab.org brilliance
Record short audio message for us
Fan that's radiolab.org / brilliance
Thank you so much
Chad Robert Radiolab okay so where we left it at the trolley problem is about to get real
Giselle Josh Green play
You know now as we're entering the age of self-driving cars
This is this is like the trolley problem now finally come to life
The future of the automobile is here
Autonomous vehicles gets here first self-driving Volvo would be offered to
Customers
In 2021
Where did the who this legislation is the first-of-its-kind focused on the car of the future that is more
Supercomputer on Wheels OKC self-driving cars unless you been
Living under a muffler they are coming
It's going to be a little bit of an adjustment for some of us
But what Josh men
What he said it's the trolley problem come to life
He's basically this
Imagine this scenario
Self driving car now
Is a headed towards a bunch of pedestrians in the road the only way to save them
Swerve out of the way but that will run the car into a concrete wall and it will kill the passenger in the car
. what should the car do should the car go straight and run over saying those five people or should it swervin and
Until the one person
That
Suddenly is a real-world question
Are people in the abstract
Like what theoretically should a car in this situation do
They're much more likely to say I think you should sacrifice one for the good of the many they should just try to do the most good
Worldwide the most harm
So it's between one driver and five pedestrians logic review the driver
Be selfless
I think I should kill the driver
But when you ask people
Forget the theory would you want to drive in a car
That would
Potentially sacrifice you to save the lives of more people in order to minimize the total amount of time to say no
No
Absolutely not
That
Would you lie in it
I'm not going I'm not going to buy a car
Hell no
I wouldn't buy it for sure no
I sell it but I want buy it
So there's your problem
People would
Sell a car
And an idea of moral reasoning
That they themselves wouldn't Buy
And last fall
Inexact
Mercedes-Benz
Face planted
Right
Into the middle of this contradiction
Okay October 2016
Paris motor show you had something like a million people coming in over the course of a few days all the major car makers
Were there you can see the Ferrari GT.
Everybody was debuting their new cars
In the one of the big prisoners in this whole affair
Who's this guy in the future you'll have caused but you don't even have to have your hands on the steering wheel anymore
But maybe watch a movie on the head up display or maybe you wanted to get emails
That's really what we're striving for
Krista van Hugo a senior safety manager at Mercedes-Benz he was at the show
They're demonstrating a prototype of a car that gets herself Drive its way through traffic
Embassy class today for example
He's got a maximum of comfort
Support systems being stuck in traffic jam
Of course of course
He's doing doesn't it doesn't even restore the show and it one of those energy
We don't have on
He was asked what would your
Driverless car
Do any trolley problem type dilemma
Or maybe you have to choose
Second one
For many and he answered
Quote
You can say
Eastside
If you know you can save one person
Save that one for
Is the one in the car
This is Michael Taylor corresponder for Car and Driver magazine he was the one that Christoph on Hugo said that to
If you know for sure that
One thing
Mondays can be prevented
Impact your face primer
So when he said this to you
Streator Manor on check did it seem controversial at all in the moment
I mean all he's really doing is saying what's on people's minds which is that
Know who's going to buy a car
The chooses somebody else over them
Danielle he makes that comment Michael Prince it
A kerfuffle
Ensues Christoph Von
Hugo from
Mercedes but then when you leave the questions you sound like a bit of a heel because you want to save yourself as opposed to The Pedestrian
Doesn't it ring go of like just privilege
It's you or pedestrian
And it's just you know I don't know anything about this pedestrians just you or pedestrian just a regular guy walking down the street
Everyone who's not in a Mercedes
There was this kind of
Uproar about that
How dare you drive be selfish you not make you selfish
And then he walked it back and he said no no what I mean is that
Just the weed
With that we have a better chance of protecting the people in the car so we're going to protect them because they're easier to protect
But of course
Yeah there's always going to be trade-offs in that
Does trade-offs could get really really
Tricky
Insult
Because obviously these cars have sensors
Sensors light
Cameras radar
Lasers
Ultrasonic sensors
This is Raj Rajkumar he's a professor at Carnegie Mellon time the GM CMU connect
Autonomous driving collaborative research lab
He's one of the guys that is writing the code that will go inside GM's
Driver
He says yeah
Sensors at the moment on these cars
Still evolving pretty basic
We are very happy today we can actually detect
A pedestrian
Can detect a bicyclist and motorcyclist different Vegas have different shapes sizes and colors that he says it won't be long before
4 lochmoor about
Woody's people are eventually they will be able to detect people of different sizes shapes and colors
Like oh that's a skinny person that's a small person tall person black person white person
That's a little boy that's a little girl
Super get the basic moral math
What is a car do if it has to decide how do I save this
This boy or this girl
What about two girls versus one boy in an adult
But a cat versus a dog
75 year old guy in a suit versus that
Person over there who might be homeless
You can see where this is going
It's conceivable the cars will know our medical records
In back of the car show at that time cost
Call communication cabling Technologies in highly automated driving
80s guy basically said in a couple years the cars will be net
Work that we talking to each other
Just imagine a scenario we're like cars are about to get into accidents in right at the decision point
They're like conferring will who do you have in your car me I got a seven-year-old walstra guy makes 8 figures how about you
How about full of kids kids have more years left you need to move will hold up I see that your kids come from poor neighborhood and have asked
So I don't know so you can visit by yourself or not
Therapeutic paradox
We do not think that any programmer should be given this up measure
Burden of the siding
Who supplies and who
I think these are
Very fundamental deeper
Issues that Society at 2
Decided large
I don't think a programmer eating pizza and sipping Coke swimming
How does society decide
Maine help me imagine that
I think it really has been able to feel your processor
Rice told us to things bass we need to have
First we need to get these Robo cars on the road get more experience
How they interact
With us human drivers and how we interact with them
There to be like industry-wide
Summit no one company is going to solve that
This is Bill Ford Jr
Of the Ford Company giving a speech in October 2016
Economic Club of DC and we have to have because he could you imagine if we had one algorithm and
Toyota had another in General Motors had another and mean it would be
Cuz like what if the Tibetan cars make one decision in the American cars make another we need to have a national discussion
On
Ethics I think
Because
We've never had to think of these things but before birth
The cars will have the time and the ability
Who is this pasta
So far Germany is the only country that we know of
His tackle this head-on
One of the most significant points the ethics commission made
Autonomous and connected driving is an ethical imperative the government is released a code of ethics
It says
Among other things self-driving cars
Are forbidden
To discriminate between humans and almost anyway not on Race not on gender not on age nothing
These are shouldn't be programmed into the cars imagine
How are few classes being added
In the Geneva Convention if you were like what
Lee's Automotive
A globally accepted standard
How we get there
Globally accepted standard
Is anyone's guess
And what it will look like
Weather it'll be like a
Coherent set of
Rules
Or like rice
With the kind of contradictions we see in our own brain
That also remains to be seen
One thing is clear
There are cars coming with her questions
I could never
Where's it going
DMV
Oh my God
Okay we do need a caveat all this by saying that the moral dilemma were talking about in the case of
Driverless cars is going to be super rare
Mostly will probably happen
Is that
Like the
Plane loads full of
People that died every
Day
From car accidents
Well that's just going to hit the floor until you have to balance
Few cases
Where car might make a decision you don't like
Against the massive number of life's a
I was thinking actually a different thing I was thinking
Even though you dramatically bring down the
The
The number of bad things that happened on rug
You dramatically bring down the collisions you dramatically bring down the mortality
You dramatically lower the number of people who are drunk coming home from a party and just Ram someone sideways
Isn't killing three of them and injuring two of them for the rest of their life
Those kind of
Do things go way down
But
They're the ones that remain are engineered
Like they are calculated
Almost with Forsyth
So here's the
Mississippi nutrition website
Oh damn that's so sad that happen
But I got drunk and out of that maybe you should go to jail
But you mean the de Societe engineered this in that is a big difference
What is operatic and seems like the forces of Destiny
And the other seems mechanical and
Thought through meditated something dark about a premeditated
Expected death and I don't know what you do about that everybody's on the killers in the particular
Kiehl's dark is a little bit like when you know should you kill your own baby to say the village like any particular instance of that one child
But against the backdrop of the life saved it's just a tiny pinprick of Darkness
You know how humans are if you argue back
Yes a bunch of smartypants has concocted a mathematical formula which meant that some people had to die in here they are
Are there many fewer than before
A human being just like Josh would tell you
Would have a ruler of feeling out of anger and say how dare you engineer this in no no no no no
In that human being needs to meditate like the monks
Silence that feeling because the feeling in that case
Just getting away yes or no
And that may be impossible unless you a monk
For God's sake
Civil right back where we started now
She said you have to think some people know this
Pizza Spruce Pine Manor on check with help from Bethel hobday
Special thanks to iyad radwan Edmund a wad Sidney Levine from the moral machine group MIT
Also thinks the sertac karaman
Xinjiang and Robo race for all their help
And I guess we should go now yeah
Alum
Jedi home run
Not getting into your car
If you don't mind
Just take my own
I'm going to rig up an autonomous vehicle to the bottom of your bed
You can go to bed and suddenly find yourself on the highway
Driving you
Wherever I want
Do you want
It's okay we should go I'm Jedi
Thanks for listening
Receive today at 2:41 p.m.
This is just been giving you your credit lines is Michael Taylor from here we go Radiolab
Billy cases Out director Rachel Cusick David devil
Bethel have an airport
Overhead
Announcement
Alright I'll keep going
Help from Amanda
Phoebe Wang and Katie Ferguson
I hope it does it for you let me know if you want me to do it again thanks guys looking forward to hearing the Shout by and this message