Are you awake
Listening to Radiolab
Radiolab
From WNYC
And NPR
So a couple days ago we did this thing we got Robert into the studio but I notice
Sabrina's headphones
And we ambushed him
The whole staff rushed in singing cake the whole deal
Robert famously hates his birthday
Such a long time trying to hide my birthday is there anybody in there
Good Fortune to work with this man for over 10 years so
If you'll excuse us just this once we want to take this podcast to celebrate
Mr. Robert krulwich
The Robert we didn't just for you in here for
Que Canta listen to thing to rectum
But we would love to
To share some of your earlier work as the next podcast
That's our executive producer Eleanor and she dug up a bunch of his old work in the archives and he eventually agreed to let us play some and three
Really interesting to hear the stuff because
I'm not sure a lot of people who listen to Radiolab really get how much Robert sensibility drives the show
Like his combination of theater and
Play in his desire to sound different than other stuff on the radio and took Northern rules
In all ways always in service of a genuine attempt to understand
Explain something
It also just amazing how many creative lives he lived before he came to Radiolab
I like here's one here's a piece from 1979
Which is just a few years after NPR began
Thanks these days you've noticed they're trying out new systems more and more we're being asked to deal with machine
Instead of tellers
And that's the way the banks wanted according to our business correspondence
Robert krulwich
Right here in Washington a few doors away from National Public Radio there's a chance at a color television
Sunset and they have a treasure chest
With 10 Susan B Anthony Dollars inside which could be yours if you are willing to stand
Do a 3-minute demonstration of their new automatic teller assist
I don't know. I went to powerful
In the pieces actually about how banks are starting these crazy things called ATMs
People are a little freaked out these machines eating my card from time to time
In a one-point Robert in order to explain why the bank
Swirl lobbying so hard for these ATMs
He almost burst into song
Okay you send the check to Sears Sears deposit the check in the bank
Regional Bank from there it goes to your Regional Bank in your very own area
Meet me in the back to your hometown Banks meals and back to you
In a statement to get at the end of the month to check shows up in the packet hopefully now remember you listen to the whole thing through that is for
Different meanings for just one chat with all that post it and I wouldn't it be cheaper the banks are you
Stop mailing the check from place to place place
And tried another system
That system is called electronic
Fun transfer in already
To cut down on Postage and handling
Painful for me use another one we listen to it's also from 1979
Soon as they report about
A report in quotes about interest rates
There is intense pressure from two different groups for changes in interest rates
One group was from down the other group wants them up even higher both sides are
Powerful and important to our economy
And the ins-and-outs of their struggles are worthy of an opera
In fact they are an opera
I know from the Palazzo Verde
We present this live performance of Alfredo Tucci's Immortal Opera
Erato interesting
And here is our host
Sewer Joplin
Thank you very much
There aren't very many offers the deal exclusively with the subject of interest rates for this one I think is the most magma
Any person to vote
Tucci related with toad in a single afternoon after a traumatic event according to his biography of Standish Library
Scarred him for life
Beaches that stood she was walking along the road in the city when passing by in the tram he saw the exquisite
Beautiful Sylvia fine
Dashie ribeye can you what
Do you want to test
To meet at
Well then he was at pool composer he decided
If you would send to the gift
At what temperature
And he chose wall to wall carpet
In order to get the money for the carpet that we had to get the household finance loan
To his horror
He found out what the interest rates when I'm alone and it's writing is Aria a KK
Office tasks today personally follow these real life events
Lupines waiting the Italian section of Louisville Kentucky
Where Angelina will she want to watch World Cup
Names of the interest rate is
18 and a half percent
This scene begins as she gasped in astonishment and resolved not to buy the carpet normal
Gina tell this to the carpet seller perugino's
Gino is 52 stabbed in his usual value of the business management
Has Angelina then that she cannot afford.
Now that
Codependency no he's not happy
Here's the thing about this
A Paul volcker
At the time was the chairman of the Federal Reserve board
And what I do in act 3 is I take
Paul
And I from a press conference that he
Which I was at
And I cut him into
The
Opera
Ladies and gentlemen
We're face-to-face with economically
Difficulties really unique
In our experience
Interest rates is
It is just one of those walking on a razor edge right now
3doodler Alfredo to chase International
Vistakon
I can't believe that that was on national public radio that was a crazy day
We could we do things then like I interviewed an anchovy they are taller
So there is no what there's no Gatekeepers were like no
After the Opera we listen to something from 1992
We should be just after I graduated high school and hear Robert
Teams up with a couple of actors and comedians to do a story about a yearly recap thing
I'm Robert krulwich and welcome to the second annual edition of backfire this program has been a tradition on NPR since
And this is the occasion when We Gather to review the events of the year in this case the year 1992 and once again we were able
Go to round up our regular Observers
Buck Henry is a screenwriter and a pundit
You got the movie The Graduate by by Jane Curtin was an actress and a funded original cast Saturday Night Live Tony Hendra a pundit
Famous satirist and a pundit
And all three of you now
A double punt a double ended in Tony's case
Let's have the first Quest
Alberto which pundit
What was the real explanation
What President Bush's collapse
All the way back a year ago at the state dinner at Tokyo
You would call the event
Buck
I do indeed he collapsed and more importantly he vomited
On the
He was at the prime minister of the foreign minister in the prime minister's lap
But push as you know is
Name anyway
Bush is the
Sound that you make
Can you throw up so we could have simply been responding to someone saying by the way what is your name
And the sushi came with it
It is also
As I have read my history at Costco
A world leader
From time to time
To throw up
On the lap of the minister of a friendly governor
It demonstrates
Confidence in your host
A sense of the excellent
Sunday dinner being served
And a
Tradition of giving back something you've been given
Equipping the consummate politician of giving his fall
How do you account for the
Surprised expression and an end the lack of delight really on the face of the time in a few when receiving this
Gift
From President Bush
I think it was because it was done
After the first course is supposed to have to be completing me like that
Piece of your host before ingest
By the way there is some misconception here which is
It was just that this was a single event it's actually
Habit of throwing up in
The nearest Rangers lapis
It's not just a question of how to say it's something that's a bush has done ever since he was a little boy
Origin of his his nickname Poppy
Because he's not a Mumsy used to refer to as in better habitat
Up Trucking and septic pumping his original family has projectile puppy
What we would do this like for for 2 hours in manoli was alright
She would not even
Smile
Where we went like this was the least listen to program in all of NPR
Reduce dust from 12 Years to 2 years
21 only on New Year's Eve
At 10 p.m. you know what it's like
2B schedule
4:10 p.m. on New Year's Eve that means you have
Failed
Then
This is how life works
Sitting in my house and the phone rings
That's the White House
And some guy says
Do you is your group available
Next
March 3rd
Of the White House
Trivia I said well
I don't think you
I said maybe you should just ask whoever's idea this was
To like that adore
Write about 2 weeks pass and then that he's about as good news and that is I listen to it
And yes
It isn't Fun
But
The people who think it's
Honey is a person
And this president
So
That's the end so we went
We went to the east room
And
It was incredible
My wife was there
You look across that your wife
The White House
The president laughing
Dumb joke
There's certain moments
Will you feel
Strangely black
Like
Either you were really great giraffe
Previous
This life is a journey
Reward or
Every so often
God just leans down to the clouds
Kisses you
This will be
Just
A chance for you to be
Enjoy
So that night I just
It was a big deal
There's a couple pieces that you've done
Free radio
Where
Like as a as a young radio
Reporter you know how you were in your nose face
We also are starting some
Idea of what we should sound like
What we should do what
What's permissible
And then you hear this thing come out of the radio
And you're like
I didn't know you could do that
I just didn't know you that was allowed to play a one
Piece of yours that had that effect on me
You did this in 1981
I heard it you know years later when it was featured on this website
But this is pre Radiolab so I heard that we had met yet
This is multiplayer
The story of the krasilovsky is one of the great commercial rivalries in New York history
Began when Sam razumovsky open a moving company years and years and years ago
Wayback
I can understand him
Well my time and I've been
Peterbrooke also runs the office at the krasilovsky trucking company in Brooklyn
I imagine there was a big family
Brother's uncle's cousin
Very competitive competitive is putting it mildly
The Firm started in 1904 when Sam krasilovsky and his brother Dave grazulis
Formed a Hauling Company
Call Sam krasilovsky and bro bro is for brother
And they would do move heavy things like church bells and statue
And help them they hired their nephew
Microsoft
420 years everything was fine
Mike until Uncle Dave decided to bring his son's into
The business under the circumstances Mike
Had to disassociate himself from the uncles
Fence. On his own
That is Mike's brother who will serve as our narrator
It is the late 1930s there are now two krasilovsky moving companies Mike's and his uncles
To remind customers that he was now in business for himself Mike took out a series of display ads in the New York
Phone book on very page
Weather krasilovsky Czar list
Me Ed's
Remember Mike there is only one cries a lot
In addition
Remember Mike
On all the
The truck started in work
Too many customers could not remember which krasilovsky with which they just open the phone book and call any Chrysler
Husky and that is when Mike got this
Incredible idea
He said
If you could move ahead of his uncles in the telephone book
People would see his name first and then they call him first instead of the other present
So he decided
Do I add a new listing in the telephone but he took out the v in krasilovsky
I'm put in a u that made it crash lowsky
KRA Silo you moved him one entry ahead of his uncle seems by the alphabet
You'll always be
CVS
But Mike Kozlowski
Is now called was not prepared for the perfidy
Of his cousin Milton krasilovsky
Milton Milton krasilovsky was another young son son of David krasilovsky in the early 90s
What is Milton
Started a new trucking company called
Crescent house key with a you as was the case with Mike but to move ahead of Mikey changed his
First name
From Milton to
Mick Mick krasilovsky what are you hoping
That he would be ahead of Mike in the listings which of course she was
Bianco's meanwhile anxious to catch up join forces with Milton or Mick
I'm created the
Krasilovsky
Safe Company they dropped
Did the v in Kozlowski but in a no-sew the uncle's krasilovsky
Moved ahead of Mike's Crab House
Ski bike
But it's quite upset as well he might have been
For Revenge
He countered with a great leap taking over the atlas safety company which moved him to the front of the telephone book
Leaving the case behind to be finer air of the AC
But one year later
The uncles were on the same page
The Acme
Safe Company was a division of
Krasilovsky and brothers
According to Mike's brother by the mid-1950s even though Mike still had only one moving business in Brooklyn
Metropolitan Avenue
Mike krasilovsky by this time had 18 listings under 18 different names in the telephone book of the uncles
Yes we have listings
Throughout the Yellow Pages and
White Pages
For one company
So that we could get all the listings ahead of the other relatives
Did you do it
For fun or
No
This was not
The fun this was very serious they were
Was no reason we felt
That another member of the family that has
Has just walked in
Should capitalize on the name of krasilovsky
The final Salvo was fired by the uncle's actually was
Cousin on the uncle side named Marvin
He created
The AAA Acme krasilovsky safe
After that the public
Was so completely confused it according to Richard krasilovsky all the krasilovsky businesses
Has began losing custom
It does affect the business
Jose who
Who are you and who do you belong to
Mike died in the
His wife sold the business
Listen changed her name from
Keselowski
Keep the crass and then move to Florida
Mike's brother Monroe stayed in the business he now calls his friend whoever the
Empire
Safe Company he and his son Richard would like to use
It is after all their name
But they don't dare
Because there is now a whole new generation of krasilovsky is moving into the
The phone book the original
Acme company
Has now been
Split
So they are all over the lot
There are now more Suns
And there are more names
Here with my colleague Margot Adler going to read you the latest set of list
From the current New York telephone book and the New York yellow
AAA Acme krasilovsky
Craig Alaska division of Hackney safe
Grabowski Mike
Trucking and Millwright company Brothers Mike and Monroe
Other Safe Company Division of safe Smith stink
Krestovsky division of Acme safe
Mike Kozlowski saved
Monroe krasilovsky safe brother lost you Safe Company Inc collection safe
Company Craigslist Univision not connected with any other krasilovsky
Will be back in a month
Hi this is Shaolin ilaria and I'm calling from Piscataway New Jersey
Radiolab is supported in part by the National Science Foundation and by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world
Information about Sloan at www.slha.org
Thanks
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help this summer I'm hosting
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
About what we're calling tiny moments childhood Brilliance basically I want to hear about those times
So did something
It just means you lean back and say whoa how did they do that maybe it was the moment that I can
Kids you've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons and you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed are ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the specific moments where a kid does something super smart but doesn't have
Anything to do with the test if you have a story please share it with us
Go to radiolab.org brilliance
Record short audio message for us
And that's where you live. Org / brilliance
Thank you so much
Jackie or so after Eleanor denying the whole staff Ambush Robert in the studio and play top stories towards the end of the whole thing
Robert went off on this insane digression
And it happens all the time in the studio like he'll go off on something and unfortunately cut it out cuz it's not part of the story we're telling but this
Case we're going to put it in
None of his birthday and also cuz it just
It just illustrates
What an insanely curious duty is
Look at this incredible curiosity that makes him like
Heat-seeking missile
Or weirdo Adventures
And that is what is attracted me to him and the entire staff to him and probably a lot of people who listen to him
So here's a random digression of his it's him telling the story of his first
Television piece for ABC News
This is one of the Great
I'm sitting on an airplane
And the man next
You just ask
What are you doing today I'm in golf ball
I'm in golf ball with
Lincoln golf courses yeah
Noah gather
Golf ball
That's something people make lots of money do you make soup while we make out
What we making a dime
For everybody we recover
We pay that
Open and we can sell it in
Quieter I said what's your promise about the problem we have
The only really one
They live in the water hole
And the kids
Who do this work
As well
You mean you hire teenage
Is and the wild animals
Atoms were obvious
We have to remove the Gators
Was thinking where's ball retriever what an interesting story that would be great story
Then he suddenly talking about
Gatorade
Gator Bowl
What we use we use guy name is
Campbell
There's a guy who specialize yet
Flight attack
California
Do I got to go meet
Campbell
So I call mr.
The phone is answered by some persons not much
Elitches
Very angry wife
He had had has skipped out with some floozy
And she's like pissed at
So she says well
If you're calling he's not here
He's out with her
Oh I am sorry I didn't know I could I was I was thinking maybe he
December interview I would talk about
Alligator
Retrieval
Did he ever mention
The Grosse Pointe Zoo
No food
Occasionally
Turn out
That when they lived in Grosse Pointe Michigan a very fan
They had created the law that he had collected the largest correct
Alligators
In in North America
In his basement in the series of cubs
Andy Reid
Every kid in the neighborhood
Whose parents role at General Motors
All knew about the secret
The police didn't
The adults do
Put the kids to bed
And she said
In the question
This conversation until
The Sewing in
You can imagine the fever I have gone from golf ball retrieval to Alligator removal
Tune out secret zoo in basement of fancy suburb and suddenly there's now the sewing machine
It turns out there was a sewing Circle
What is house that misses
Campbell be aggravated
Ran
And in this sewing store
They would bring
Singer sewing machine
And one lady
Turn on her Singer sewing machine
And it's vibration cause the alligator in the base
All of the Alec
It sounded like
A jungle riot
From the basement so you're saying they were upstairs sewing and Below them these alligators were alligators
When is a trans on her
So
George Campbell
Figures out
That it was a B-flat
So is his
Theory that it was a bee flap that cause
Is that like the sound they make when they major when they fight or Woodrow buddy knew a if it were true and no
What new white would be true if a
So I tell this poor girl Barbara 50
From
ABCD producer
3 or something
Higher
A marching band
High School Marching In Full plumage
Are we going to go
To Florida
To a place that is without
Wildlife
And I'm going to have
These plumed high school
Poki Bowl played
B flat and there's going to be
So
I get high school band they get on a bus I get the ABC crew and I get the very nerve
What is 5 / 50
Don't know what I'm doing
We all we all go out to the Autobahn
We arrived
And if this Mass
Grass
Who could see alligators in the band gets off
Extremity vp's
Bill Porter
Cypress Lake High School marching band
Play a B-flat
On the French horn
We have no response
Is the portal now play a B flat on the tuba
And there's not a sound not a Russell not interest I look at all these alligators
They don't win that are blank that are move they don't care
And Barbara Street is like
Like what am I going
At that moment
A bus pulls
Filled with French
Tourists
Who get out
About to go look at Alex
I'm down the thing and they see all these gaily dressed
Americans
Olive green and large
Pumas coming out of their head
Is there a friend Jason's already a Fellini film to describe
I'm a little bit sad and any adjustments about 3:30 going on for
And it's the winter time so we only have till about 6
Before they have sunshine
And I say to them this is the situation so they they let this time
Francis
OUC this season
In Michigan that had
That was you.
BDubs items in taobao
Jocelyn
So the sound
Game of Thrones the sewing machine
Down
Shooting today
That's he's a grass and water and mud
Is a different thing
You need to go to one of those
Parks
Hubzu
Will they put old alligator in
Complete
So it's like
It's like the dub
Okay that's the thing to do so now the people from France
They getting their bus the bus that the musicians they get in the bus there bus
George his wife their hangers-on and the ABC to end by retreating
And we all drive to
I went Sunday centerpiece Everglades Wonder Gardens
50 alligators in
Poured concrete sitting in Iowa
My camera crew is so certain that nothing is going to happen
Did they get into the pit standing on his concrete
Crete Islands not interest for these alligators and the Sun is now
Kissing the tops of the trees
Sofa deda says
Robert we have one shot
Hiring Houston
I can't go back to New York with nothing I have nothing
And if I need you to put it in
We are
We're standing there
And one more time
First
The French horn
Okay the tuba
There's a kind of quiet
The first thing an alligator does when it's about to bail out
Shakes its rib cage
So all of a sudden
It's like the whole
Cool water turn to Ginger
And then all the males
Half of them
People animals
All them all at once make that
This is the sound of mrs. Campbell sewing
Circle heard coming up through the basement
Vegeta
Start spreadsheet for North Africa in Wichita
Android
When that piece aired it was my frizzies it got it
Because it was so hot people you don't like you got a bass
You got an audience
Oxy for a half million or something a prime time show
Can you get all the people are clicking true
The desert called the butterfly
So I was given I still have
The chart
What happened that night on television
Like people but
Looking and clicking in Mac this man with a pole with a tuba and alligators the home of the French president
I'm heading like 3 million people every minute
A high whatever that score is the next week
I did something on the Internet and pouring and it went actually actually opposite direction
Which of the
But for that week
I was like
Urk I was
And
You still is
Happy birthday
Was it wasn't unpleasant
Inexpensive
No talking about myself is it something I did
Don't mind doing
Thanks for listening