Before we get started just to note
This episode contains some strong language
As well as content that may not be suitable or at least ready
For younger years
It is an episode about
Sex ed
Okay thanks
Ouat
Northern listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
Hey I Molly Webster
This is gonads episode 6
And it's our last episode
I'm going to go cry after this is done but first
I want to share with you this really
Fun thing that team gonads did in May
And that is we did a live event on sex ed
You know if you've been listening to this series we have been looking at the biology of biological sex and sex tutor
Termination
And one of the things he kept thinking was like
Pan
Now that we know how complicated it is like how do we teach this stuff
And how do we teach this
Staff
In a climate where
People are really polarized and divided
And thinking about all this
Text said it just felt like more than radio story you know if you bring up sex ad with anybody they have store
No worries they get excited they get animated
It really felt like something that would live quite beautifully in a live
Space in a live event you know almost like a recreate the sex-ed classes we all may or may not
Have gone through
So today we'll be bringing you clips of that show and it starts
Which atom rod
Hello hello how are you guys doing
All right
So so so excited you were here so
I guess I should just say welcome to Radiolab sex ed
That is a sentence I never thought I would say
In the 15 years I've been doing the show I never anticipated this moment where I be on stage
Thing that you alive
Group of humans
But you know here we are
So I actually didn't have sex ed
So I am looking forward to learning something tonight
Please welcome to the stage Radiolab Molly Webster
Hello hello hello hello
Well this kind of feels like my sex ed class which was like
Like nerve-racking and you're not sure how it's going to go
So to start the night
We are going to go down South
Mississippi
The state
Passes a law that places some
Restrictions on sex set
Notably when it comes to talking about
Condoms
The Lofts
No instruction or demonstration on that
So that's
Sanford Johnson he is a sex educator in Mississippi
And so on the one hand you might think
No big deal right
Plastic kids can figure out how use it we don't know
Map to show them everything
Sanford says
It's not really that easy
I will tell you a story when I was a high school
Teacher
Delta
Because I'm
The school brought in
A guest
Certified sex educator to talk to the kids about sex
It is stuck with me
Reset when you make cock
Make a call
In the time it takes you to drive
Store
Really said that
In the time it takes you to driver
Store
To your house
Aluminum 1/2
And every time it takes you to take it out of the wrapper and
Put it all
Illuminati
And I was thinking that's how fast work
Does Sanford and all of his teacher friends were like well if this is what kids are being told maybe we really do need to
To do this kind of damage
Castration
But the question is
How
Surfer stand for this all came to a head
Teacher training
He was at so the teacher training was to
Train teachers
And how to
Teach sex ed
And is part of the training
One of the teachers was like up in front of the group and she was supposed to explain
How to use a condo
Because this is the caveat in the law
You can talk about a condom
You can explain or like a show
How to use one
Answer this teacher
So as she talks
An SUV
You couldn't help but ask
Panama
Somebody from the state park
I don't think
To do that I really don't
Talking with your hands
Was now illegal
And I got that
NSC
And
So we thought
It's hilarious yes but it's also like
You need to tell me
The kids about condoms we don't really know how to do it
And just thinking about this the next
Gay Sanford came up with something
That
I think might be one of my most favorite things on the internet
Right now
In the shadows
IPhone video in which Sanford Johnson standing there
I was 1 foot bear
While
He's holding a white tube socks
And a sneaker
And remember
According to Missy
Mississippi law
He's not allowed to
Perform an act
What kind of damage
Castration
With a condo
So what he does he holds
Does tube socks with Cameron
He says
I want to make sure that you come out
Cuz I want to make sure there's room for my television
When am I
And all I do is your problem now
If you want to roll it
This video lives on our website and you should absolutely go watch it when you're done with this episode
This video is delightful but it served a larger purpose for us which is that it reminded us
There are a lot of different ways to have conversations about sex
And the body
And we thought okay
What if for our lives show
We try to reframe the conversations happening around sexy
What if we use metaphor and euphemism and comedy maybe even a little meditation
As a way to navigate all the stuff
Swirling around sex ed weather that's a lot in Mississippi or just the general awkwardness that comes with this
Topic
So to do this
One thing Sanford and sex Educators from all across the country told us was that a key part of
Assassin classroom
Was
Question box where students could drop in anonymous questions
And then the teachers would pull them out an answer them to try and facilitate
Discussion
So we thought what if we make our own question box
And try and answer the questions
With this reframing
So we gathered questions from listeners Reddit Sanford
Fifth graders
It's in no way comprehensive but we gave it a try
To kick us off
Here's Majel Connery singing the first question this is just
Turn a mic and a vocoder
.
Thank you
It's really
Unbelievable
Feels like someone
Shoving a knife up inside me
Slowly
But
With no rhythm that I can track
But you never quite get my head on top of it of predicting it
If you'll like
Angel and I can't move
Baxton daroga
She's twenty-four of filmmaker and she's talking about what she goes through every month when she gets her
Now
.
Sort of the weird topic still a little taboo hush-hush
Isave paternalism Maybe
Like it is a little hard though roughly half the planet doesn't get them
And even if you do
Every. Is so different they're kind of hard to talk about butts in the
Has seemingly found a new language for discussing her. And it's with
Kind of an unexpected companion
Some background
So
I have endometriosis which is a reproductive illness that one in 10 American women have
Where your endometrium which is usually
Lining of your uterus that gets shed during your period
Start going all these places it's not supposed to
So on your organs
We did actually such growing outside of your uterus
Each month
And I have no idea about this I feel embarrassed is a 35 year-old woman to have gotten to the
Disappointed not known this
But each month your body tries to
Push out all that extra tissue that
Since places
The cat that would have been
And so it's very painful
And you can take birth control to help eliminate the
The pain which attended did for many years but then she started getting depressions and all these complications and so she had
How to stop
And as soon as she did the pain came Rush
King back I got my first period off of birth control I was
Maybe 20
2 years old
Hit me when I was at
The airport in Casablanca in Morocco alone
Is traveling back in Liberia
Cheap in making a documentary for the BBC and was about
Fly home
And then I had like 30 minutes to get to JFK
And all of the night
Couldn't move
She said she just started froze in place in front of the food court
Naming like
Are you okay in Arabic Translate
Columbia grafonola to the are you okay in French
Sarasponda nosing
Key. In French
He was very helpful but the pain was so bad she was just like I have to call somebody and I still have Wi-Fi
President called my dad
Which
I was kind of surprised about like I'm pretty close to my dad but he's not the. Guy
Maybe World fashion I don't know so we call them both into the studio.
To talk about it
All right
Okay so I'm a colada I'm
Professor
I asked him what was it like to get that phone call
Couples hiding from me because I couldn't do anything but a helpless
You can do this
Feel emotions but not able to
I feel really bad for you
School said that I'm not call
Lucinda was in the Casablanca airport and he was all the way in Illinois
He just started trying to do
Everything
Close your eyes.
What are you feeling meanwhile sendas literally
Baby like being in the labor room
She was crying and moaning in Goulds trying to make her feel better as a tossing out all these ideas
The pain still really bad
And then my dad said
Think about a color
I think about the color red
And then shifted to different color in your brain
In that moment
Send it became 11 years old
It was her first. And the pain was
Terrible
I was
Laying in bed
My mom couldn't be there and she was almost right there but she had to be at work as having really bad cramps
So was my dad and my uncle
Leaning over me trying to help me I was just like
Mortified that I wasn't really worried about it
And
You're my dad
Turn on Gregorian chants
And
Burn some incense and surveying over my head and he was staying alive
Just
Track the smoke
Figure rise and
Just follow it all the way up
Imagine you are the smoke and you're just
Bloating and I feel like committing suicide
And then he was like
Okay
Close your eyes
Imagine
A color what color are you seeing
Send a realize
In that moment she could actually
See the pain it was a
A thing that had a shape to it that she could identify
And then
Like okay and now
Time to change it into a different color with your brain
Like ice blue
Cindy found herself thinking back to that moment and once again talking to her dad in
I'm trying to transform the color of
The pain I remember seeing them on the little
Staircase that leads up to the
Playing
And I was like ripping on to the
Bar
Try not to fall over
Migrating my
He just like clenching my job
Fascistic
The color red
Okay I see it yeah I see it all right
Okay come on turn into something else
Pink baby
Okay alright
And she says standing there
About to board the 7-hour flight
It actually helped
And then I'm still in really bad pain
But mentally I can
I can stay here
Fit inside of it
It's like it's very non-judgmental it's like okay I'm feeling pain let's really feeling
Because in his in sushi
Traditional Sindhi culture Linda and her dad are from Southern Pakistan
You don't like
Try to avoid buffering
Instead of just try to
Breathitt like when someone dies
There's literally professional Wailers
That you
Higher
Come
Wale and cry with right or maybe I'll pay them that you were telling me about the
Yeah that did that is common yet
Yes
Somebody comes visiting that will still use repeated and then
I'll be there start crying if their job to like
Express suffering game
Keep going through it
To sit with the pain
That's Point number one
In point number two is
Pain to me seems pretty dark
I don't know about you but I don't know if I would actually think
About a color
But Cindy said
For her family
It's not that surprising cuz your dad like a little obsessed
The color
Post-it note hot pink
Bright orange lily
Purple Rain Purple Rain
Is that cultures that just Unity
Ranmore Common
Send us laughing here but if she was being honest she would say that when she was a
The kid
Color palette
Open sister really embarrass me
Sorry
In the end
Color was
The place that she and her dad were able to meet
And then just keep meeting
Because the month after Morocco
Another. More pain she called her dad
The next month another. More page called your dad
And then the next month
Yeah what are you saying doing in this moment
The first thing I'm trying to do is just to get closer to
To be in the color rather than trying to switch it right away
I'll close my eyes and
Focus in on
Where the pain is and what it feels like
And I let it just kind of
Shoot up into my brain and it feels like kind of like
You watched like a watercolor palak watch across the page you know and everything
Read all the sudden and the first thing
I think James
Haha yeah that's it later
To be one with it in Nevada
And then
I try
Suggest
Kind of a shift to the Colorado start like no changing with him a little bit and
Orange that's like mixing with the red and then pushing it all the way to something
You know it's like a wash and it gets like
And all the sudden the wave is coming in a different color
At this point in the live show onto the screen these amazing images
They're hyper saturated
Happy
Surreal
And they are made by Cinda
If you want to see them you can go to radiolab.org gonads
And and check them out
Cinda's inspiration for these photographs is what she sees in her Mind's Eye when she's in
Incredible
Pain
And she's able to capture the images write them down as her dad is coaching her through
The color meditation
The clouds
Pikachu
Flask distribution
That's a classic
Cuz on and on
Babes, babe School
My dad
He thinks a lot about the scaling
The universe in this game of all time
And then our smallness
Significant or unhappiness in our suffering is anything about all of that
It's coming babe
And he just makes me feel
It sounds weird very loving but
You like makes me feel how little I got it
It calms me down
Hospice of you cuz only non
Beijing Canadian School
Material injury it's gone
Please come and leave school
To see if true
Imagine
Good-looking teens
Facebook
Reaction
You still call him
How do you like
Schedule that looks like for you
I would almost be like oh crap is today the day she's going to call
How do I book my afternoon
My beard is in my dad's calendar
Crochet
That was filmmaker sindha Agha and her father Galaga
Will be back with Radiolab live sex ed the final episode in the doughnut series
We've been talking about the biology of
Sex in sex determination and I can't help but think that the one place this all plays out is
Dating remember our summer
Single
Oh my God I do
Mine was very short as yours lasted like a week
This is why we're excited that our good friends over at Death Sex and Money led by Anna sale
Are taking on the topic of dating
The following a group of listeners for the entire summer a variety of Ages summer straight summer gay summer
Online dating some art
And
They're all over the country
Through the stories will be thinking about all sorts of things that come up and dating are you attracted to like
When it becomes intimate like
What kind of intimacy feels right and all of these things feel like right now they're like
Very much
Up for grabs and also something a lot of us are talking about
Abstract
Please don't listen you can check out hot dates
Cuz it's dating in the summertime on the Death Sex and Money podcast
Feet go get it
Hi this is Emily in Louisville KY
Kentucky Radiolab presents
Gonads
Is supported in part by science sandbox
A Simons Foundation initiative dedicated to engaging everyone with the process
Science
Additional support for Radiolab is
Provided by the alpha
Pizza
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
And I request
For those of you who
Who spend a lot of time with kids parents
Aunts and uncles
Teachers looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments
Brilliant
Basically I want to hear about this
When a kid you know did something
It just means you lean back and say
How do they do that
Maybe it was the moment that I
A kid you've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of their musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class
Are ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the
Epic moments where
A kid does something super smart
It doesn't have anything to do with
If you have a story
Go to radiolab.org
Flash brilliance
Mrecorder short
Audio message
And that's radiolab.org
Flash Brewing
Thank you so much
This is gonads episode 6
This is our live show about sex at
So far we've talked about condom demos without any condoms
.
We even went on to talk about the deeply important topic of what happens to all the bananas after condom
Banana demos
But
We ultimately went on
To discuss
Question that is one of the primary reasons
I wanted to do this show
Annies
Anythink
Is there anything off-limits
What you find is you can get together a room full of people who you think
Have the same opinion on what should be taught in sex ed in schools
But once you boil it down to the nitty-gritty and the fine details
You realize everybody dress a-line
Somewhere
Enter wrestle with outline drawing
We got together a panel of really smart people who think about this
And we presented them with real-world scenarios we ran into while recording this issue and we tried to have
Have them do something where they like waved Flags
For when they saw the line was crossed or 4 when they supported the line that was being drawn
I'm not sure if the flag thing work too but you may hear reference to it
And so I would like to welcome to the stage I'm going to move
Maybe I shouldn't
I'm going to stand here and then milk
Education historian and author the sex-ed book too hot to handle John Zimmerman
Muslim youth activist Dahlia
And sex educator Erica Hart
Okay so the first one
December 1st 1994
Surgeon General Jocelyn elders
Who is appointed by Bill Clinton
Teaching school children to masturbate as a way of avoiding the spread of AIDS
She was asked by
Dr. Rob Clark a psychologist and a unaids conference about the
The prospects of a more explicit discussion and promotion of masturbation as a means to limit the spread of the virus
And she began her reply by saying she's a very strong advocate for sex ed in schools and early age
Quote as per your specific request in regard to masturbation I think that is something that is part of
Human sexuality and is something that should be taught
I think masturbation is really really important
That's part of like a sex ed curriculum but for this reason absolutely not
Like she really liked politicize that reason and it was used not for her own sexual benefits but as like
A way to downplay AIDS and be like this is terrible I don't want anyone to know about this deal with this
Like I don't this seems like
A red flag to me
Interesting episode was invented
Comedian on
It was cast it was reported as joycelyn Elders saying that she thought that in schools
Teacher should
Teach students
How to masturbate that is not what you were saying
What you were saying was masturbation support of human sexuality
A people should be informed about that that's very different than saying we're going to teach them
Which I would then posed to the panel is like would you go as far as doing a how to
In a sex ed class
How to masturbate or do you just introduce it as an idea
Well we can talk about what if if there's a yes in there I want to know what a gif
There's a curious if that's age-related you can't necessarily teach how to and I think also speaking to what you said about
Jocelyn Elders this is another example of how
Race and sexuality gets
Completed or not necessarily completed but definitely comes to the table is at
Jocelyn Elders was like literally
Essentially lost her career talking about this was just shows the
Anti-black origins of ever talking about sex and how our bodies are used in on the lines but when we start talking
Timeout ways that we can actually own them is now a problem
And the other part of that is that you don't necessarily cheap someone
How to have how to masturbate hashtag Cosmo you can't really do that because
Everybody has a different
Body right and everybody's body is function differently
Like for example me I'm a breast cancer survivor I don't have nipples
So to be like oh you can stimulate your nipples that would be
Triggering for me cuz I don't
Have that body parts that feel good for you like I told my fifth graders
Yesterday
I never like what like what does that mean I'm like any part of your body you could touch in that is called masturbation right
So now we know what it means and there's not this
Weird thing around this
I'm am I doing it right Miss which I get questions about oh yeah am I doing it right it feel good to you
Yes
This has been a hugely contested question across American history
Masturbation
Specifically and
If you
If you don't want to read about masturbation don't study sex education because
Define it's the most contested subject
Explicitly in only about pleasure
Right
It's not about procreation
Even though I expect that many people in this audience think that
It sex is for pleasure it's important understand that there are
Some 330 million Americans
Write some of them think that it's only reserved for heterosexual marriage and it's only reserved for procreation
Discussion
I was going to say what's the role that
That
Like religion has Miss coz masturbation is so tightly.
Hi to you know I was raised Catholic
Definite No-No right
It said there's bits so tightly tied to that I wonder
How do you respect
Assertive like religious space when you want to introduce a topic like
Masturbation
I mean a lot of my students will say things like well
For example God is a man
And I don't necessarily agree with that but I have to kind of hold space for that that their understanding of it so say
Same thing with masturbation where it's like I can't masturbate because I'm
Christian or I'm Catholic
Okay so you will not masturbate then
Still have to talk about masturbation as you are in
My sex ed class
And that's a topic going to be to talk about it not necessarily not talk about because there's some students who are religious
So you don't have to opt-in to everything that I'm saying
It's just knowledge for you
So you don't go around shaving yourself or someone else for engaging in such Behavior
It's really it's really difficult you know I mean there's shockingly little sex at in the sky
And a lot of reasons for that but one reason is that we differ so fundamentally about sex and sexuality
Or here in lower Manhattan this is not a representative already
And and sexist
Tide to use a loaded
Word are most intimate ideas of ourselves as human beings
And so if you look at
Western democracies
What you find is people that objective sex education monster among two groups white Evangelical Christian
And also recent immigrants
Especially immigrants from
You know I mean these are often groups that agree about nothing else
But in the UK and Sweden and Canada United States
Every account if they are shared objection
Every newspaper account must use the headline
Strange bedfellows I've never seen a single journalistic account
These are people that basically group that nothing including immigration
Write up this is hard and it should be hard for people like myself on the left because we say we value diversity
But we also want this thing called comprehensive sex education
Square that Circle
You're not into anything
Yeah so I was raised Muslim and I think it's not
Don't teach your kids about sex it's more of us an unspoken heterosexual we use it to procreate
Safeway and I hate like feeding into this like American narrative like Muslims are like all straight cisheterosexual
What are Generations coming and we're like all clear and whatnot but
But
It's hard to navigate
Sex in general let alone masturbation because there is a stigma that's tied not just within the religion but within our own communities
Okay so this one
What happened at
Charter School Rocklin California
So a kindergarten class
Student can bring it a book
Can a book have you read during story time
And so for one of the week
A transgender student brought in a book called I am jazz
Is a book about a transgender
The teacher read the book in class
And then
There was a really interesting reaction from the parent
Like a holy crap while we were not prepared for this our kids came home with
Very confused and tons of questions
And I thought this was an interesting one because a lot of what we've been talking about a serf formalize sex ed
And this is informal sex at
Informal per say I mean it's just about
A person's experience and what
Cisnormativity does which assist meaning like
The world is very stiff
Gender dominance
Is like
This is weird now we're going to maybe we should have had a letter about this even need a letter about talking
About George Washington
Or the Civil War
Or the Vietnam War or World War so why is it that we are talking about
Trans person that now you need to be warned
That you're going to talk about this
Tell you what about you I know we were talking backstage you said
You could go either way on this
Yeah because my only saying my only qualm is like says people don't know how to facilitate discussion support under with their kids
Especially if your kindergarten
My boy my girl like these questions that you said this yard to ask so I can wish that
The parents knew about it justly be able to facilitate evaporation
It would have been like a productive experience for the kindergarten
A letter like if
I'm kind of like a letter
So that way they would have been able to know about this beforehand so like the kid wouldn't come in at like 4 p.m. to be like I don't know what's happening this is what happened at school
You about it beforehand I feel like it could have been a more productive conversation
Look it's really hard
I share the sentiments that we just heard about cisnormativity and I'm deeply support of a trans rights
But I'm also supported the public schools and I understand they are under threat
All right and I think that there's a really delicate balance here if you want people to support your public
Schools UK
At the same time transmit the message it's somehow
They just didn't get this thing this sex
Sting right and weed school have to intervene
There is a fear I mean I think and what you were saying there's a centering of institutions in this country
It's like up the institution needs to be upheld like don't mess up the school the school is going to fall apart
And if the school for the part that we have nothing rather than centering the most marginalized
And I think
To think
Combat a school is going to fall apart but not
Trans folks and non-binary people and genderqueer people. Think about their experience
Is is
My mind f***
For lack of better words I think
What is missing in sex education is talking about
Intersectionality which is not just a celebration of
Various identities were talking about the ways in which people are impacted
Systems of Oppression
So actually talking about that when you talk about masturbation is this really something that someone has access to if you're talkin about
Putting on a condom why is it that Mississippi the poorest country in this country
Have no what cannot talk about condoms
Like that is really a function of race and class right and really being mindful of that really bringing that into your
Classrooms of people
Don't necessarily do that they're like up let's just talk about sex and let's just have this conversation and be mindful
Of the things in which like people are also bringing to the table yet John
An honest intersectional approach would also acknowledge
Seems anathema
Don't think they belong to the public school
Believe that their familial and religious matters and not school matter
I'm not saying I agree with them
I am saying though that an honest intersectional approach
Would have to acknowledge that would have to take
Account of the fact
We are a diverse society and many of our recent immigrants not all
But many
Find these themes inappropriate for a public
What I said I said it matters that you actually talk about where people are
You actually get interested and if someone is dealing with
Being documented they probably don't want to talk about masturbation
As the conversation went on I wouldn't say that we ever actually came to a consensus on any single cell
Scenario
You can feel it gets torn
But what was brought into the room all of the different things that go
Into thinking about how lines are drawn insects said so race immigration class maturity
Body type
We went on to discuss other scenario some of my favorites are
Bondage and 9th
Introducing bondage to 9th graders
12th grade or live
BDSM demonstrations
Attendees were
Five 2 because yes that has actually happened on a college campus somewhere
We aren't able to play all those for you
Here on this podcast but we are going to do is play you the final segment
Of the night
Which is a batch of questions
From
What is sort of the
Quintessential
Sex ed
Target population
Lightning rod
Okay
Stop
I'll just do a little thing
So last week we heard
About the sex educator
Who made
An amazing discovery
This educator is teaching a workshop at a middle school in Southern Maine
And they were talking to the school nurse
And as they talk they saw that on the nurse's desk there was just like
Overflowing
Envelope
At she asked what it was
And it turns out
The nurse said oh those are my fifth graders
And so we obviously were like we want those
Thank you very much for telling us the story
And they're pretty great
And so
We're coming to the end of the night
And like all sex ed classes we've only gotten through about 5 Quest
So one of the things Sanford tells me that they do
Is odoo a lightning round
They just try and like whip out answer
So to help us out
From The Tonight Show + Comedy Central please welcome our very own self
Proclaim sex-ed expert
Jo Firestone
3 p.m. to pick between us are coming apart or closer
We should
Okay
SoJO
Need you
Are sex expert
Where are you asking I just said it and
I don't I actually really enjoyed sex less than everybody here
But you felt ready
I'm at that level I think I could handle it
Service
Today
Okay
Is a lightning round
Is raining outside
I'm ready
Okay
There's no chicken
Unless you wanted
Ready
Does breast milk taste like cotton mill
I take long hot tubs
Does that mean I won't make a lot of
Sperm
Of course
So much sperm
Do you have sex for 2:20
Put the time of his lightning round
I heard my friend lives off Donuts in McDonough
What do I do
Passionate love
How big can a penis get
Why do we do this anyway
We don't want to do math
Books that answers my questions I still want to ask her my questions but I don't want her to get me
What should I do
Other girls have developed but I haven't
Can I use a cream
I think creams are always good especially in winter
I would say go for it a little coconut butter it's going to happen eventually just keep moisturized it right
What happens when two sperm reach an egg at the same time
Can people have sex
Flip object
How does a girl not get the sperm
Ashley shoes away
Why do kids start to
Like each other in
Fifth grade
Exposure youth around him long enough Egypt has horrible psychological homeschool
How does a penis fit in a vagina
It's really hard but there's there's a lot of maneuvering and I would say use
Use each other
When girls are still young does milk come out of their breasts
When they squash them
I guess it depends how hard you squash them
Why do girls have the baby and feed it and help make it in the boys don't have to do anything but help make it
So f***** up
Yeah
Can I keep that one yeah
What is a rain a rain related one
Can a penis shrink or grow because of the weather
Anyway
Yes
I have a crush on someone how do I tell her
Obviously
Hidden messages
Definitely don't be direct
I was a gift
I have the white
Clear oily substance on my underwear what should I do
Laundry
Why when a boy sees
The girl he likes
Penis hardness
Except
It's the Eternal question
The answer is
The penis is guiding you
Towards
Imagine show
Birth control
Radiolab team gonads is Rachel Cusick Pat Walters me Molly Webster and Jad appenrod
Live music along with the gonads theme was written performed and produced by Majel Connery and Alex overington
With live event production help from Alyssa with case and Aleisha Allen and Engineering by Ed Haber and George well
Burlington
Special things to Upright Citizens Brigade featuring Logan's Alles Molly Thomas and Alexander Dickson
And to our panelists
Delia marcu
John Zimmerman in Ericka Hart
Before we go to Corrections
Jocelyn Elders quote red
As per your specific question in regard to masturbation
I think that is something that is part of human sexuality and it's a part of something that perhaps should be
Plus sindha Agha is actually 25 years old we said 24
Go to our website to see cinda's images Sanford's video and check out
Are listener created sex ed bookshelf
It's awesome and it's for all ages
Thanks so much for listening to gonads the series
See you soon
This is Jennifer like calling from
Berkeley California
Radiolab was created by Jad abumrad
Don't keep is our director of sound design
Catia is our managing director
Our staff includes
Simon Adler
Maggie bartolomeo
Rachel Cusick
David Gamble
Bethel Hoppity
Kasie hunt
Matt kielty Robert krulwich
Annie McEwen Leticia Nasser Melissa O'Donnell
Pat Walters
Emily Webster
With help from Shima Olie
Carter High
And Lisa Yeager
Fact Checker is Michelle