Are you awake
Radio WNYC
End NPR
What up ladies
Hey
How's it going Chad it is it is indeed
This Radiolab
Robert Nye invited to folks into the studio are former producer loomiller basically started the
Show with us sleeping in the Sonic ID
You're right there
Weather in and also Elise Spiegel reported NPR
Because Lulu Annaliese together are starting new radio show the podcast and everyone's very excited about
What it's called invisibilia look like a Latin word was that the Latin word it's a name that my mother
Came up with this is Elise talking
Cuz she's a French beautiful historian so they just like no stuff like that under what circumstances did
Just come up since you know hanging the way that this beagles hang in like her bedroom
The show is about it's about all these
Invisible things are invisible but they're expecting you in
What's the name and she was just like why don't you just call out invisibilia
I was like
And misled for what
Invisible things
So the show promises to be sort of an investigation
Of all the invisible things that
Guide our behavior that we generally don't see now
They've been sharing some stories that they've been working on as they're going
A lot of it is
Amazing
So we we ask them for the preview one of their stories for you guys
This one they're going to hear
Comes from an hour that they're producing on the topic of
Categories
Like the different boxes that we put
Things in our world into and the first piece in the show looks at one of the most
Basic categories that there is
The first question that any
But he asks a parent who has a new baby is it a boy
Or girl
I have to say in my career I have done a number of stories about a blurring between
Boy and girl but the story I'm about to tell you is that a kind of flooring that I have never heard of
This is a person I met who calls herself Paige abendroth abendroth means the color of
The sky when it's that deep red right before the sunset
Paige had bright blue eyes long black hair in a ponytail
Good make yourself
We were in San Diego by the way setting ourselves up to talk I'm going to make you scoot
Skit skit skit skit
Caduceus good
So after we sat down I asked page
Show me some pictures of herself
From about a decade before
So there aren't many
In the pictures
Was a man
A man in a naval uniform
He was very buff
Strapping military
High and tight haircut
And there they were
Those bright blue eyes
You look very you look pretty conservative here to yes I do
Page
But the first three decades of her life as a man
But let me be clear from the top
Paige's story is not a transgender story that you typically hear
Typically
People who are transgender feel like they are one gender trapped in the body
Of the other gender
Their internal gender identity is misaligned with their biological sex
But
It's static
It stays the same
But when I was talking to Paige
That
Didn't capture
Her experience
At all
Because when I met her
Paige was flipping
Flipping between the category mail
And the category female
My foot back and forth multiple times a day
Snab spend
Percent
Of my time
In game mode and the rest of it and female mode one morning page would wake up feeling strongly that the gender at
Core of her being with female
But then suddenly it's just kind of like
There was a change
And Paige
Was in die mode
When that happened
All kinds of things about page change
Her posture changed
In my weight kind of moves up to my shoulders
Like my center of gravity is kind of up here more significantly she told me
There was a real psychological ship
The way I see the world in the way I interpret the world is different
When Paige was in mail mode
Page was less interested in people and talking to them and making eye contact with them
One more introverted him a lot more
I'm quieter button female mode
She was much more
Expensive
And sights sounds smells likes dislikes
They were all different when I'm female
All might
Emotions are like this really Vivid
Eye colors
Basically
Page with constantly and very abruptly
Bounce
Between two starkly different ways of being in in filtering the world
Paige wasn't able to dictate
When or where this happened I really have no control over it
She be sitting in her office talking to her boss and
Damn
She'd be walking down the street
Now when this happened
It wasn't like page was an entirely different person I'm always the same person
I experience the world differently
But I'm still me I still in the control of myself I still have my same
Wants and desires
There was just as profound
Difference
Beneath everything
It's just a sense of knowing like
The way that you know you're a female right now without having to be told
It's the same way that I know that I'm a female and when I'm a guy it's the same way I know I'm a guy it's just
This instinctual knowing
What I am
By the way right now are you male or female
And how long have you been in girl mode right now
About an hour
I'd say
So
Maybe you're thinking that page
Seems nuts
Peter self
Has had that thought I thought that I was going crazy
Yeah I mean some people first
Sure about this
You don't think me wonder if it's dissociative identity disorder which is formerly known as multiple personality disorder
Or a form of psychosis
This is Laura case
A researcher who has worked in the lab of a very famous neurologist a minion
Vs ramachandran UCSD and a couple years ago they got an email from a woman describing exact
Actually the same kind of experience that page describes
Someone who experiences
The switching back
Come forth and while on the one hand they were dubious
Get a lot of interesting emails and our lab emails from people claiming all kinds of
Wild sounding experiences on the other hand
They study the brain and they have seen brains
Do all kinds of things they've seen brands
That suddenly stopped recognizing faces
Brands that think their owner has a mysterious limb
So they were curious
Here's a person who goes back and forth in terms of what their brain seems to be telling them about whether male or female
How fascinating would that be to look and see what could be changing in the brain
Or the environment to
Be causing that shift and identity
So they decided to look into it
The past couple years case has found
Dozens of people with experience
And cheese has started testing them in different ways
Including getting them psychological screening
And what she found was that as a group
These people are not mentally unstable
They simply don't have dissociative disorder none of them had any form of psychosis or anything like that they
Table that bipolar schizophrenia
And saw some other interesting things
They were actually a little bit more ambidextrous
In the general population
Basically they found enough to suggest that there might be something neurological going on so they
They published a very very small study of columnar SRT-4 part in a journal called medical hypotheses
And then started on another study but we're not not ready to
Talk about the data from that study
I did though get one
Tidbit
About this from case
And again this is very very very very preliminary
But she found that the same person will perform differently on certain tasks depending on whether they are
Are in male or female mode
For example
She gave the same person these mental puzzles
The test
Spatial and language abilities
And Lulu you know how men are really good at supposedly
Men are really good at kind of
Spatial directions
They're like spatial manipulation
What does that mean
I don't know how to explain it exactly but like you're a woman so you wouldn't understand so I wouldn't understand it
Great Wall right
Like take a geometric shape rotated in your mind
Stuff like that okay
They found when they gave these tests to these people
When they were in their difference
States that have different abilities so wow
So like when they were men they performed more as men and when they were women they performed more as women
Yeah we did see some
Differences between gender states that were intriguing but not conclusive
Here's the point
There's some evidence
That the shift these people say that they are
Experiencing
Could
B-real
Which brings us back
2 page
And I wake up in the morning like a my male and a female I wanted to talk to her about what it was like
To move in this way
Between categories
So let's just start with
Like your childhood
Now page didn't start off
Swag
She started off as a he
Who really
Didn't even have that experience that you sometimes hear about
Where people describe feeling from a very early age like
They're trapped in the wrong body
He was a boy obsessed with the things
That most boys are obsessed with I always thought about women
You never thought you were yet
Paige said there were these strange momentary flashes
That were disturbing
I remember looking at
Girls
Not just being attracted to them but thinking that I was supposed to be
Them
And wishing that I could kind of go over to the girl group and be accepted because that's the way I felt I should be
But these thoughts are really inconsistent it's not
I didn't always feel that way
Grows up graduates from high school
Goes to college and then really starts to struggle the Flash's RC
Still there college is hard page drops out and begins to feel really really
And then in a somewhat odd place
Paige finds relief
In the Navy by love the discipline of it the structure of it
Football for some reason
Those flashes
Go way down
Why
I don't know I saw myself as being more of a guy than I ever did before
But really
It was while stationed at a naval base in Japan
The page found relief
In a way that will be familiar to many of you I walked around the corner and I saw her and she's kind of bouncing around and she
She's very energetic and
It was love at first sight
Immediately I knew that there is something like special about her
And even though Cajun never been a very aggressive person
Page completely went after this girl I was smitten
I was immediately smitten
And it worked
We're just like this we're so in tune with one another
I mean we knew each other so good we can communicate like with a series of clicks
Like what do you mean
Unlike the other first of an answer back and we know what we are like
Getting at and sometimes with mean like someone like how are you or it could just be acknowledging that
You know you're there
So began the best chapter in Pages life
They get married
Skinless cat
Fornia
Got a home car at a steady job I had everything
Did I ever wanted
What does that mean
It depends on the context
And then page turns 30
And all of a sudden
Start feeling really really tired
I'd means coming up the steps I would run out of breath
So page
Goes to see the doctor
And eventually what they finally figured out was that my body thought it'd be really fun joke on me
To us stop producing testosterone
Basically at 30 years old
I had a testosterone level of an 80 plus year old man
To the doctors put page on testosterone replacement therapy
And very quickly
The exhaustion went away I felt like I had before
But
The flashes
They're back
With a vengeance
I would have those feelings again where I thought I was supposed to be female except
It wasn't there isn't anything subtle about it it was very strong
Feeling that something had gone terribly wrong
And that
I was not supposed to be male
In these moments page would look down at her body this hard
Torso covered in hair
And feel better discussed imagine you woke up in your body was
Cockroach it was really unsettling did you so did you start talking to
Your wife about it
No I was terrified
I thought I was going crazy
I didn't want her to think less of me
And that is something that I kept inside
Page started telling me that occasionally during this.
He's this feeling of disgust that came over her when she flipped into female mode but had a male body
She would secretly put on women's clothing
She felt the need to cover this body that felt so wrong
With clothes from the right side
It's just I was just trying to do anything I could to
To make myself feel more female
So
I started asking questions about the
Remember the first time you decided to do that
But suddenly
The whole tone of the conversation changed
I want to talk about it
The wind was so after that one
Do you need to take a break
Uncle
Yes you're cool you want to do
Paige got up
And disappeared around the corner
I could hear the faucet running in the bathroom
And when she came back she wanted me to know something if it matters I flipped back into game mode
Okay so that is that why you don't want to talk
It's just kind of like
It's different now
Live in Tagalog I mode
Was it when your eyes closed that you flip into car mode
I don't know
So are you in a bad mood right this second
So is it hard to answer questions
Okay
I'll be okay I just need like
We sat awkwardly for a while neither of us
Quite sure what to do
It did feel like there was a difference in
Even in the way that she talk
How to how are you doing I'm good
Are you male or female
Okay is that okay
Text you when you do it in just one minute after we take a quick break
This is Candice currently calling from her bicycle
Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloan at www.slha.org
Thank you
I hate everybody Pat Walters here I'm a producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help this summer I'm hosting a show and I've request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
About what we're calling tiny moments of Brilliance basically I want to hear about those times when
So did something
It just means you lean back and say whoa how did they do that maybe it was the moment that a kid
Did you been reading to 4 month started reading back to you or maybe the kid was a piano lessons and you said
Suddenly noticed they were doing math class
Reading music in the margin of their geometry homework we're interested in the
Does something super smart but doesn't have anything to do with the test if you have a story please share it with us
Go to radiolab.org Brilliance and record a short audio message for us
And that's radiolab.org / Brilliance thank you so much
Go back this is Radiolab bringing you a preview of the new NPR show invisibilia
And will continue with our story about page Ave and Roth
Gears Elise Spiegel 2
The tale
Page explained that the next chapter of her life involved finding a name for what was going on with her
Bigender
People who consider themselves both female and male
At the same time
She found it in the by gender website
And though only a small portion of
People on the website
Describe
Flipping like page
It felt like
This could be an explanation
The way I felt was
Other people felt that way and it was it was real it wasn't you know just some weird psychological constructs
But with this validation
Came a horrible realization
Page
Had to tell her what
I told her that we needed to talk and so sat down and separate chairs
I think I was on the couch and she was on a
Recliner
Paige was terrified
She was certain that our marriage would be over
And she was very visibly upset
Sorry
I was just
Begging her to
Not believing
Accept me for who I was
I couldn't live for her for so long
I didn't know I could love
But two pages surprise
Her wife said it's okay
She told me that everything is going to be okay
And that
You know we're going to make this work and
She wasn't going to give up on me
Paige couldn't believe how lucky she was
Together
They walk into the space between categories
Some mornings pagewood wake up male
The husband her wife and married
That man would put on male clothes
Go to work
Other mornings
Pagewood wake up female
A woman trapped in this strange body
And they were doing it
Helping each other through life in this odd space
But one problem
As much as the two of them could get used to the idea of flipping
Page
Couldn't get used to the physical experience of it
I came out of the shower one day and I'd gone in and game-mode I came out and female moan
She was standing there beginning to dry off and I saw myself in the mirror
And I was so disgusted that I threw up
These kinds of feelings
Happened all the time
Had come across a potential cure for this
I sort of Homespun remedy that some of the bigender folks handwritten about online
Involves hormones
Page would go on estrogen
To make her body more androgynous
Bring my body to
Androgynous point
Or I could resent
Both as either male or female it would reduce the shock
Of being thrown between category so violently
If her body was in a permanent state of in between
So page
Decided to try it
She began estrogen treatments
And it worked
That the first time I got my first injection
I just felt this immense relief like I was finally on the right track
There was no longer the same physical discomfort
But
As page finally was becoming comfortable in her own body
Page's wife
Started to turn away
The begin sleeping in different bedrooms it was almost like we're becoming strangers
And the point where I realized that
You know she wasn't suddenly going to
I don't know
Tried really hard
But it's really difficult
When things don't have a clear category
That's scary
For us all
There a ship we don't recognize
I felt like
Monster
Who is terrible like alien creature that
It come down
And take it over
Her husband's life in
Taking him away from her
One night I heard a crying in the bathroom
And I asked if everything was okay and she said no
She said it's over isn't it
And I think the next day she told me to move out
I am mourn for my marriage the same way I would mourn for like
You know the death of
None of my mother or someone who I was really really close with
In Tennessee right now
It's really hard to talk about still
Sitting there in Paige's apartment
The afternoon light fitting in the window behind her
I was just struck
My how hard her situation was
It's not just the fact that page
Wasn't in one clear gender category
She was stuck between categories in other ways as well
In the weeks before and after our visit
I had called around
Trying to get a handle on how to make sense of this experience
The people like page describe
I had spoken to all kinds of people
Therapist historians gender researchers
But it seems like a lot of the people that I spoke to
We're convinced
The experience I was describing
Didn't
Really exist
There's no way they're actually flipping between genders I was told
By two different gender researchers into different European countries
These people are just psychotic
Both of the men who told me this
And worked in gender research
For their entire professional careers
And they sounded extremely confident
A gender therapist in San Francisco with also skeptical
But she had a different reason
These people are actually just normal transgendered people she explained in the sense that the Earth
Experiencing the same thing that any transgender person experiences
They've just developed a different way of describing it
Same experience
Different label seem to be her argument
In other words
It's not just the page
Was existing between genders
Problem was even more
Most of the people that I talked
Didn't seem to believe that the experience that page
Was saying that she had
Was real
Why do you think this happened to you
Where does this come from in you
I don't know
I have stopped asking myself that because it doesn't matter anymore
I just kind of animal I am
When we talked
Paige seemed as mystified by what was happening to her than anyone else
But her experience
She concluded
Was her experience
There wasn't that much he could do about it
But my biggest worry is that I'm never going to really fit in
Tell a female spaces or male spaces are afraid that I'm going to be
Living the rest of my life and some kind of weird gender Twilight Zone
What will you do then
I don't know
I keep on doing my best
More than a year after we first met I called
On page app on the phone
I wanted to check in and see how she was doing
It was clear from the very first moment she answered
But something was different
Her voice sounded different
Higher
Hi can you hear me
Turns out about six months after I went to San Diego
The flipping started to fade
And eventually
Paige had settled full-time and being a woman
The last time page and flipped
In tubing psychological email
Was in the fast food restaurant Five Guys
And she said it took her completely by surprise
I've gotten so used to
Country sayings like I am
I like a woman that
I thought it had stopped
And I remember I slept really hard
It was it was really bizarre felt like I was wearing
I really uncomfortable sweater or something like that
The page couldn't really explain why the flipping had stopped any better than she could explain why it it started
She said she saw the estrogen hormones you taken to make your body more androgynous
Probably had affected her
And Laura case the researcher who's been studying people like page agrees that hormones do effect
Brain
But still there was no way to be absolutely certain
But it was one thing
The page seemed absolutely clear about
Living in one category
Even if it's a category that's often discriminated against like transgendered women
Is way better
And having no category
Oh my goodness
It's so much easier it's so much more manageable
The world
Tumi just in makes so much more sense
Now page new which was supposed
To do
Where she could place her foot
She didn't have a wife
But she did have that
What I really want to know since I have never heard of anybody like
Like I didn't know this was this was in the inhuman experience are there a lot of these
People is is there at 3 so I have spoken
To maybe six people who have alternating gender incongruity who flipped their by gender and they kind of
Move between their genders in this white cuz there are lots of different ways of being bigender right
And click thing is I differ
Yes
So they they had that too
Any idea what
Causes those sudden flips at exactly what lowercase is trying to understand
Think she has about 26 of these people that she has been talking to and
So she has been talking to these people but I don't know that it's
Clear yet it could be biological or
It could be
A different kind of disorder it could simply be a different way of
Conceptualizing and experience that a lot of different people have we can't even say
This is a condition with a strong in Sharpie marker
Declaration of now there's a name
And now this exists like there could be
Hundreds of thousands of people privately
Sitting with this
And if
If that name came out
Maybe they'd suddenly have a place but the name right now itself is like
In Gray translucence what is the name again it's alternating gender incongruity
Boy you're saying is this is really a mystery
You don't really know what happened in the story really
What is the scientist
I mean that's
That's it is in no
Category
All right if you want to check out invisibilia you can do it on the radio
They'll be airing a bunch of episodes on a couple hundred stations in the next few weeks but the best way to find him his good eye
ITunes or Stitcher whatever and check out the podcast they have hours
Coming up about fear about trying to control your thoughts it's all pretty fantastic check them out
Thanks for checking us out Radiolab will see in 2 weeks