Hey Radiolab producer Simon Adler here and before we get to the show
A quick word from
A mccuen Harris's Kelly Prime this is Pat Walters
Am the technical producer production manager associate producer.
Self-conscious embarrassed by the fact that I'm speaking to my phone
Okay
So we reached out to you guys for listeners do we have that four
End of u-thor Radiolab 4000 review
In fact what is 5000 you gave people who hate
Are we want to thank every one of you became a member during that drive so thank you so much
Thank you thank you thank you so much thank you thank you
Thank you thank you thank you thank you thank you thank you
Thank you thank you thank you so much
Too late for welcome your support year-round at radiolab.org. Org Radiolab
. org thanks
Okay under the show
Weight units
Listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
I guess our prescriptions like
What what
Conceivable set of circumstance
Led to you
Doing
What you did
I just thought it would be a weird thing to do
Yeah I was like well that would be weird we don't know if it's funny but
We try it out so is it going to be weird will do it
Is it going to alienate half the audience
Thank you so much images to send things up a do better
Confess to people that you just heard they are
Medians
That's it
We first heard about the bet you're about to hear from Jesse thorn
Host of The Sound of Young America
Okay check my phone okay yeah
So much so you sit up when curtain Kristen walk onstage what happened well there's a couple of jokes
What's up top
You know they joke about this this TV show that they hosted in the 70s
Courthouse
I did explain the American judicial system was canceled immediately
And so the audience is kind of laughing at the jokes
Thanking my call this is going to be a regular comedy sketch
Invent
They go into this song
Does this
Maniacal singing and clapping in Christian is doing this horsey dance
Can you do this before in like why
After the third repetition people laugh
Maybe they get it like oh they can just going to do that and then somewhere around like forever on the 4th time
It's not really not funny
Quiet. I'm done with that I'm done I don't want to watch this anymore why are they still doing
And then and then that changes
Factual hatred
Stupid people you to stupid people but somewhere between like
9 + 11
Then they then they're like a like these
You get this next level which they can't continue
And then they do continue doing it
You really their eyes are starting to cross
Dripping sweat christened angry that I've gone that long
I mean you can hear it in that thing like losing track of the song because he's going to
Dentist on Tiger Woods today
I've have Catherine stage whisper
Stop it
Baby my favorite thing in the history of the world
What I love about it is
Your brain is trying to make it into what you wanted to be which is a joke
But there is no joke happening and sowed what these two people are doing is creating the expectation
The expectation is going to be broken
But then breaking that expectation that the expectation is going to be broken by just delivering the thing that they've been delivering over
4 and over for the past 10 minutes what's the longest you take it
10 minutes
In Australia
You were drunk
Yeah
It seems like it seem like 10 minutes at we can't be sure
You if it was 10 minutes it seems like there's no way 10 minutes 10 minutes
And the audience
When
Crazy
Hey I'm Jared I'm rod
I've never told it
This is Radiolab and today today is all about
Things that happen over and over
Scare you
Hooks and loops
The incomplete you
So weird where are you guys
San Francisco bus you're not in Texas
Now just sounds like where in Texas can you guys actually just if you don't mind
Yourself so we know
We have your name and all that shirt and Mary Sue Campbell
I live in Novato California
And my daughter Christine is
30 years old I live in
In San Francisco
And I was raised in the bottom in the house set
Said this couldn't have been that Shall We Begin
Okay tell me the beginning How The Story start
I
It was odd Christine actually call me Tuesday morning about
And just said what are you doing Mom and said oh I'm just going to go out in the yard and do some yard work and run some errands
How to do the yard work early because
Going to be hot today
Now it's wearing in the summertime August 24th and apparently
What 10 minutes later half hour later
Cheese
Said I called her she had left me a voicemail
Something like
Hey Christine it's Mom something
Something's not right
Something's wrong
I need you to call me back
So I gave her a call back and
And she said
At something about the house isn't right there
Things look weird in here
What's weird what what are you talking about
And then she said
One looking at the calendar and it says August 2010
And I'm like
Aha
That he's like
Well that's not right and I said
Well yes it is
August 24th 2010 and as soon as I said that out loud I grabbed my purse
Talev
Oh my God she's had a stroke that was my
My my first reaction and
Oh that makes me feel emotional
And so
Christine said she walked out of her house to the car keeping your mom on the phone
All the while your mom's telling her one thing after another just doesn't look right
She says there's a strange black
Truck on the driveway
Which is the truck that belongs to her boyfriend that has been parked there for 10 years
And of course the increasingly I mean I'm just
Freaking out at
So she hangs up with her mom and then calls the paramedics
And a half hour later Christine
Arrives at the house
By the time I walked in she had been there
For 5 or 10 minutes at the most
As soon as I walked in the doctor greeted me and said
This is her doctor Jonathan Vallejo
Christine
It's immediately evident
It's not a stroke
Not an infection that's that's a huge relief but I said
Your mother has has
Transient global amnesia Global transient
I'll be honest with you I had no idea what that meant
I think the word I heard the most was Amnesia your mother has
Lost her ability
The Forum
New memory
Can't remember but
It's not going to last
Last forever
It usually last
Between 1 and 24 hours and we're not sure what
At this point where the story goes from something kind of frightening
Something a little more surreal
Yeah so when I came in mother is sitting up in bed and
She immediately started asking questions
Tuesday
August 24th
Of course we have a video on YouTube
My birthday
I'm trying to remember the last date I remember
Yeah
We hung out you came over to my house and we watched a video that I made for you and I was in Texas
And all your sisters and
Your brother said happy birthday to you on the video but we still have the video again but you're going to remember
They say it's just temporary
Here at home
Yep you're at home
Jackson gardening and you called me and you're feeling confused
Call the paramedics
I can come and get you
And we came here
Stepped on you
What's the date
August 24th
Tuesday
I'm trying to remember the last
Read and remember
You don't remember my birthday
Yeah couple weeks ago
Name I missed it but
This conversation they're having
Just started over
Because every 90 seconds Mary Sue's memory reset
What's strange the repetition like we started that last clip you heard with her saying this
90 seconds later after her memory reset she says
Seconds later
Remember
The last
Read and remember miss you watch this video for a few minutes you realize What's Happening Here is it Mary Sue
Is in a loop
It goes like this
First the date
What's the date
August 24th
She didn't respond
In almost the same way every time
Yep
And every time she says that
Darn in exactly the same way it was
Fast forward
If I pass my birthday
You must enjoy your birthday quite a bit then she laughs
NBA recap
You're working in the gardens and you gave me a call I'm just saying it's usually when she says the word paramedic
Call the paramedics
And had them come and pick you up
The Mary Sue's eyes get really wide in this look of sheer
Butter
Disbelief isn't that creepy I mean every single time
Weepy 90 seconds later
Is stomach sleeping
90 seconds later
Repeat itself at this point
Right after creepy
Pachira sets
Okay so I don't know what day it is
Like somebody put it on rewind over and over and over again
I had repeated the birthday so much
That the nurse
Apparently was behind me now doing the words my birthday
Groundhog's Day
We're doing a little yes we do that we have had the same conversation over and over again
Two and a half hours
Danny Phantom
That is what we're talking about today
What day is it
Tuesday
August 24th
You didn't miss that you were there
Watching it
I wanted to slap me
I want to bring it out and let me inside
Damn it I just
Told you that for the record you would never see my mother. I know she would.
This is a person who's lost
Commemorate
But why would her
Heath
Once I go to the next piece soap
Precisely and cancer
Systole the same
Exactly the same
DIY
I think what it is is one of the things nurses said
Is that when you have something like this your true self
Comes out
Huh
Your true the word true isn't
I think so yeah
Oh yeah I mean I got my mom through and through right there made
What Christine means is not the repetition
But their mom keeps asking so many questions just wants to know what's going on with with all
Across-the-board I love
Problems I love
Puzzles
Are you like a sudoku fiend you know
I am I am I hate to admit this God
Iplate escape room games
On the internet
Escape room what are those they're stupid little games where they have little hidden pixels that you find
You're you're stuck in a room and you have to get out
Got to find the key to the door
And there's all these little
Hidden places is the perfect escape room
There's a different way of saying this
First of all Jonathan blajos that ER doctor who seen a bunch of these cases
He said well that Puzzler Instinct that's not just marysue what everybody does
Is
Struggle over and over again
Where am I
And when
Just a brain in survival mode
And another thing that everybody does
You see about six of these patients so far is it everybody
Not just Mary Sue but everybody
The Lee comes a broken record
Right down to the
Phrasing of the sentences
Which keeps them out a little
Admit you to make sure the brain seemed a little bit more like
A machine you know you give the machine exact same set of input
Every 90 seconds given the same doctor the same hospital room
Steeping machines
See if the output never varies and it does
It almost seems like the patient
Has no free well
And so sometimes
In the back of his head he thinks
Thought if I had that condition at someone videotape me
I would love to see
See my own tape
Why you know I think
I want to see
Could I somehow ask
Or or would I would I end up
End up with the rest of us
Now thankfully according to Jonathan what normally happens in this condition is that as time goes on. 92nd
Lutz starts to slowly expand more like 2 minutes
Soar 3 minutes eventually 4 minutes
Now it's 5 minutes into a Mary Sue after a few hours at our Loop got longer and longer old memories
Start to creep back in
By that evening she was remembering up until
Like that Sunday
Few hours later her memory began to extend into Monday morning
She remembered Monday night
And then
Finally Shall We Begin
Tell me the beginning
How The Story start
I
It was odd Christine actually call me Tuesday morning about
I just said you doing Mom and apparently
I'm a village from Jen
Message
Radiolab by Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Public understanding of Science and Technology
Mrs Mary Sue Campbell here we go more information about loan at www
Loan. Org
And this message
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help this summer I'm hosting a show
And I request for those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
We're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments of childhood Brilliance basically I want to hear about this
A kid you know did something
It just means you lean back and say wow how did they do that maybe it was the moment that I can
Kids you've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons and you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed they're writing music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the specific moments where a kid does something super smart
Anything to do with the test if you have a story please share it with us
Go to radiolab.org brilliance
Record a short audio message for us
Again that's radiolab.org / brilliance
Thank you so much
Hey I'm Jenna Radiolab and this hour we're talking about loops loops loops
Okay
Nothing
Is 1.0 is the obviously
Panda sleep shaping
Palliative y00
Who's this this is Alex Bellos tonight
Here's looking at Euclid
When I was a kid I used to think
A 06 Tahoe with nothing in it
But actually zero
Chosen by the Indians
That's kind of reflecting
The Eternal cycle of the phases of Heaven
Raymond's
The Greeks and the Jews
We going to have a zero
We just had units. Everything started at 1
One reason why we didn't
Is that
I'm kind of afraid of The Voice
Afraid of the Void
How would you describe something
It isn't there
Nothing
There's nothing to say yeah it's an emptiness
Anna nothing is in a means you're so long you don't even know where you are a psychological
Barrett's was grasping the zero in India
Everything and nothing was the same thing that have the first of the fluidity and then growls decided that nothing this was something
And I'm leaving the way they decided to represent the nothing
What is a piece of nothing and they drew a circle around it which turns the nothing
And do something
Alexa Loop
So
This idea of Eternity in continuity and infinity is actually contained with
The onion evil
Cut50
My Kind of Love
God damn it was actually his
One of the most mystical
Magical
Parrot show
Digit of that mole
We use everyday
So here's to other Workhorse
Next up
A story from reporter Mark Phillips right
As you can see here there
All these containers
Tape Bluetooth
Okay set this up who is this guy
His name is William basinski
He's a musician who makes this
Really hard to describe music
I'm doing it for about 30 years and basically what he does is
He take a little bit of
Classical music or music
Recorded on tape
Analog tape
Terrible and he looped
If I can find some
He cuts the beginning the end keeps it together into a circle brezza through tape machine
Speed and you get something that sounds like this
This little phrase that just repeats over and over and over again and never
Changes oops her everywhere their Cycles there in nature there just universe
And if you can find a loop that can repeat without becoming redundant
Then you can sort of fall into a different space and time it open
Sort of like a bubble of Eternity or something I don't know
So that's what that's how
Well in the summer of 2001
I was
Archiving all these old tape loops
Transferring them
2 digit
And something kind of weird happened you grab this one piece of tape put it on
And it was so
Wonderful grave
Very stately
Lupine
Totally forgot
Can I set it up and turn down the
Garnerin
Left the control room went to the kitchen.
Coffee
Came back and
Started realizing something was changing
I love to see that
The tape was
Shredding
The thing to understand about tape
Is that when you record music onto analog tape onto a bit of it
That music but it is it's
Iron oxide powder glue
Did just a piece of plastic
So the iron powder is
Actually the music but after 20-30 years
The glue loses its strength in the
Just falls off
On the floor
His music is actually falling on the floor and I thought of my God was going to happen
What happened was in the course of about an hour
The music
You put more loops on and it kept happening
But the really interesting thing was
While some disintegrated quickly some slowly
They all sort of had the same
Pattern
What do you mean
Just listen to this one
So this is one of those loops
At the beginning
And after went around and around 4:20
Minutes or so the dust are the fall off and then it sounded like this
All the all the notes are still there
But the tales are getting shorter
Yeah and that's what always happens
Sustains and decays of the notes seem to fall away like from the back
Moving
Backwards backwards
It gets shorter and shorter instead of being held for 4 seconds help for 3 seconds
2 second
Finally just really here
Like the attacks in the
Just the beginning for the notes
Only the beginning
Hold on
At least for a little while
I was
Thinking wow this is like
I'm recording
The life and death
Have a melody
It just made me think of
Human beings
How we
Die
You can really hear that
Disintegration on this particular
Number 5 it starts sounding like the rest like this
But after
Just 15 minutes
Basically completely gone
And the tape on this one
You know tape is normally Brown
Right now it's
Clear
Big Scotch tape
The dust is gone
Little bit of brown here
Announce
Clear
It's almost all gone
This next group is is a Sly one and you're going to have to wait for it loopiness
Kick in
Ready
Born Ready
Pretty single Navy
The smell of a dead whale as you have to experience the note to know what it's like it's like nothing I've ever smelled
Does Craig Smith
Professor of Ocean Ave
Giants really
Putrid
Back when Craig was a grudge
This is a 1982
Putting off the coast of San Diego
About a third of the water was
Supersonic picking at it
How big
Around 25 to 30 feet long
So is that like a train car more like a size of a small yacht I guess
Freaking well I wanted to think that well studied
What happens when a whale sinks of the seafloor people just speculated about it's anyone ever followed it down to the bottom
No one is followed the well down to the bottom
So we we told the carcass out to see and they had all these little scraps of Steel
That they tied to the whale's tail one at a time about 2000 pounds
And
Nothing
It wasn't enough to
Just think the whale whale kept sitting there like Biggs
Smelly balloon
Awful decomposition of gas and the captain of the ship goes well
IPhone
This also doesn't work doesn't really do anything
The Craig try it again and again and eventually
Not with that well but with others
You got to see something
So cool
So a whale dies and sinks down into the the dark
And and then
This incredible cycle begins within minutes
Scavengers will be at the carcass
They smell within hours but may well have hundreds of hagfish on it
They're terrified you like animals
They have grinding plates instead of teeth and they burrow into the carcass
Hundreds like a hagfish conventions really massive of heels what is that look like well it looks like
Like I'm a giant Medusa head
Over the next few days a bunch of other scavengers show up including
Stone crab shrimp feast gud dark station
Flash flying everywhere
Sometimes the hagfish get ticked off and they tried to defend their territory very interesting ability to
Reduce mucus you can put a couple of hagfish into a bucket of water and
Kick it and I can produce enough mucus to essentially turn the bucket of water into
Nothing like gelatin wow just like Medusa head in a cloud of mucus and all that is just the first
Stage the mobile scavenger stage
Okay
So what happens after that
Well after the mobile scavenger stage
Is Ben Richmond opportunist 8
The whale
Is beginning to look pretty dilapidated little bits of
Well soft tissue implanted in the seafloor and so the ground around the whale becomes like
Start of its own little ecosystem
A bunch of new animals show up there worms
Are there really little worms like tons of them we can we can get 30 or 40 thousand of them per square meter
Sometimes the sentiment around a whale fall looks like
A lot of grass for these worms I just wriggling sticking up out of the settlement and
Waving back and forth these worms
Tinker White
Sofia the White Worm like grass
Ghostly
And finally
Glass stage something we call the sulfur loving stage
At this point the whale looks like a skeleton
Covered with this actually beautiful mad of white bacteria
5 minutes
Fluffy and just looks like a polar bear's fur
Covering the bones of the whale
Yeah
Think about a whale skeleton draped in a polar bear fur coat
Sulfur's coming out of the bones and the bacteria or just clustering around
Picking it up
4 years
When you step back and look at it
These dead whales may become like planet and you find creatures living on them
That you don't find anywhere else
There now about
55 species
That haven't been found in any other habitats
Species of animals that only live on well fall
Does that mean that these creatures
Like the whale is their entire world they don't know anything else
For some of them yeah
Where they do
The rest of time in this can't happen that often
Well
That's a good question maybe that they are living is what we fugitive species in other words
Drift around
Waiting
Can I say hoping
And when that happens they grow quickly produce
Hundreds thousands maybe even millions of RV that they then broadcast out into the water column
The darkness
Waiting
Until she will find another such habitat
Hundreds of kilometers away
And repeat
So altogether how long can
Can a whale fall last
Well I well for Ken last
A large whale skeleton that of a blue large blue whale or fin whale
Can support a community for 50 to 75 years
Which really
Astana de and how does that compare to the lifespan of a whale
Well it's probably pretty comprable actually whales live
By the order of
5270 years
Something kind of poetic about that the idea that you know for the same amount of time that the whale live
It's going to support this
Life
Yeah it is it is very
Appealing
This is Radiolab
Today were talking about loops I'm Robert krulwich run
Is Radiolab it's all about Luke
Yep I'm Chad, I'm Robert you're listening to Radiolab today were talking about Luke and it's all about
I'm jamming Robert like my lips and speaking things that happen over and over and over again
Hello.
Hi Jad paste
Steve Stephens
How are you
How's it going I'm good and Steve told us a story about a mathematical Loop
The through mathematicians all over the world far
Story starts way back with a guy named got LOB frigga
Got La brega how do you spell yeah it's not it's not Gottlieb its it seems to be lob at the end
Typo in every book I've ever seen
Not to set this up very quickly God was a mathematician back in the eighteen seventies and eighties any had a dream
Mathematics could unlock
The secrets
That you could maybe even build a machine beaded some basic mathematical rule
And it would just start
Churning out
Discovery
When you need a human being that's how powerful he thought math could be a question if math
Is the most fundamental thing in the universe
What is the most fundamental Park
Map what's at the foundation is it numbers is it
In a 1-2-3 that's what you would think
But God love you said no there's a deeper thing the number
The deepest thing of all is
Is what today we call Seth
The set
Of things
You know so
Yes I like what's a set
Steve explain it to us using all things
Sesame Street
Really old episodes
Far is it to set it up here at
Two people working at
The furry Arms Hotel there's Humphrey who's got a green nose and a pink face and his
Girlfriend
I actually know what she
She might be his wife Ingrid
Cancel their hotel
Keepers and Ernie is in the background
Dan Humphrey are taking an order
Room service order from a room full of penguins
You know Humphrey says I'll take your order
Mr. penguin sir
Spanish Spanish
Dan Humphrey said let me check if I got that right
Fish fish fish
Fish fish
And then he calls over to Ingrid he's going to call it in to the kitchen so he tells Ingrid
Fish fish fish fish fish fish
Fish fish
No that's not right
Paseo Pointe says A5 times but then
Journey explained
Excuse me
Ingrid and Humphrey
I have a better way for you to do this
A better way
Count the fish
6 fish
They both realize Ingrid and Humphrey how powerful this is in they say does it work for
Say cinnamon roll
Spark plugs
Absolutely
That's the point that what's cinnamon buns and spark plugs and fish the sets
Have in common is that there are six in each
I mean if you try to say what is 6 really mean it
It's the thing that those sets have in common
According to Steve it's not so much the number
Sick that's important here again that's the label
For this characteristic that all these piles seem to share it's the pilot itself the set that is
The most basic things
Shapes are the Bedrock I've been looking for that we can build the rest of math
On top of it yeah and I can make my meth machine that the Universe and I think he published a book sort of shell
Knowing how this might work
Except that Russell Bertrand Musselman application
Then found a
Devastating Paradox that ended up
Well annihilating what to do
Russell's Paradox is now become known as the barber paradox
In this case the set is
Account
Atomic people
Yep one Barber with the following in this town the barber shaves everyone
Who doesn't shave himself
The bar
Who doesn't shave himself to some people save himself some people go to the barber
That's the universe we're in a town where everyone who doesn't shave himself is shaving by this Barber and now the question is
Who shaves the barber
Remember the barber the barber has the property that he shaves everyone who doesn't shave himself so he can shave himself
But on the other hand
He doesn't shave himself
Then he's one of those people who doesn't shave himself and is therefore shaving by the bar put maybe the barber here's to solutions for you guys
Barber cut not shave
Could you just not shave
Nino or Maybelline Township maybe he could set up some sort of mechanical device that sort of like one of them
Can't do that you can't change that answer sensibly what happens to the barber and no one has there's nothing to say
Either does or doesn't shave himself by ordinary Aristotelian logic
Because the barber
Can't shave himself and he can't not shave himself
So
So there's something to it ruined that's what ruined the machine that would solve the universe
Afternoon to wait for a couple hours like after lunch before you go swimming but I can't see that by overthrowing
All lights work but does it does it turns out to be a very very problematic for the foundations
The map
Cuz what does barber paradox
The reason was so annoying to mathematicians was that
Math is supposed to be this logical
Thing right
Logic is the lifeblood of Matt and you here
You had this little bit of math
It was a logical a cell. Contradict contradicting
Set with Bertrand Russell that I came up with all this
He didn't lose Faith he's all of this is just a problem with set theory
So then he spent a long time trying to make
A theory I think he called it a theory of types
Instead of sets
These he had certain admission rules that he thought would prevent paradoxes from happening
Under Bertrand Russell system it was no logical problems no paradoxes
Until it's gone evil German guy comes along and you say his name
I don't speak German but
Mathematicians often say it like the woman
Piece of clothing you know from the old days
Google
Jana down 11 she has written a book about good and I'm up
Professor physics and astronomy
Barnard college she says the point at which Goodwill enters our story it's 1930s Vienna Austria
Recently finished his
What would be equivalent to like a doctoral degree a peach
HD smart people around him understood
But he was also maybe
Little bit off he had real brakes
Swift you know
Reality he was
In the biography said call him a paranoid schizophrenic
But he seems more kind of
Obsessive
Depressive I don't know but
But he was in and out of sanatoria and and and he had real difficulties
Being sure what was real the only reality he really trusted
With math circle shapes
Prime numbers formulas axioms he got into paradoxes
Perhaps if the barber paradox the Lord The Men We don't know but he began to think about an actual experiment with
Some of these
Paradoxical loops
He took something like the Paradox of the liar
Turn off the light or says
This statement is a lie
Right
If it's true then it's false
And if it's false then it's true
Statement is a lie
If you think about that too much
You might try to cuddle with interested in that phrase and
For various reasons he took it
Tweaked a little bit to come up with the following statement
This
Statement is unprovable
Which is very important to notice if it's
If it's provable
Then
It's Unforgivable.
Forget words what would happen if I converted this statement into math
Because in math things are either provable or unprovable they cannot be both at the same time as other true
Or false if it's true
Damn it you should be able to prove it yeah so he said I'm going to assign a special number unique number
To make that a purely mathematical statement
By coating it in a very clever way into arithmetic
To be honest
Very very clever
He did his Matthew stuff
Had a rigorous mathematical statement right there on the page he looked at it and you realize that what he just
In math
Is it the following statement
This
Statement is unprovable
Is it's true
Because it's actually unprovable meaning
In math
Which statement actually is unprovable because it is true the logic of
Math will not let you prove that it is
Trousseau might be true
What's never know nothing like that is supposed to happen in math things are supposed to be true or not true and you supposed to be able to prove
Every true thing that stays up
If there's something true that you
Improve
That means that the math
Strangely
Alphalete
It's always called his incompleteness the
That's the phrase the Godel incompleteness theorem is that if you have a system of axioms that are
Consistent
Meaning they don't contradict themselves
They're necessarily incomplete
That is there a certain statements you can make
Within that system that you can't prove or disprove
And all of math has this character
This is the big shock that this is not just about word games about
Logic puzzles with Barbara This Is Us
Devastating for even just
Counting
Another word math is shot through and through
With these kind of statements that you can't either prove or disprove
Seriously the Deep thinkers at the time were amazed at this it was recognized as
One of the great ideas of
Of the twentieth century for sure maybe of all time
Maybe I should make it more concrete there's a question that as far as I know it's still not solved
Steve gave us this example of a problem something called gold box
Conjecture
Kind of gives you a sense of what incompleteness
Feels like
So goldbach's conjecture says that you can always right
Any even number as a sum of two prime number
So let me give you some
That likes a
Yeah, remember for sale prime number means you can / 1 and by itself
The prime numbers
1 and 7 but nothing else
All right. Well which isn't even number is 7 + 5
Desert
Another one help out
What's 11 + 30
Or
19 + 7
Any even number now this has been checked out to I don't know what billions trillions
Maybe hundreds of trillions so no one has ever found a counterexample
Apple II Gold box
Conjecture and here's the thing
You might think that either it's true
Or it's false
It might be
That
This statement
Every
Even number is the sum of two prime it might be neither
Crew Norfolk
But what we today call undecidable
Undecidable is a term that comes from gradle
I mean suppose in some
Ethereal
Are transcendental sense
Like that is
Suppose that there's God and God knows that this is
Then you know what about us here among the world of human being
All we can do is check each
Even number
Every time we check it
True with that that would never constitute a proof
Because we've never run out of numbers
You then say
You got to understand everything
You either
Have to defer to God who doesn't attend everything if you believe in God but if you don't believe in God
You didn't have to live with mystery and not knowing
That's all you can say
I'm going to say yes I think you've been capsulated a perfectly and I think that
Girdle himself
Was
I think a believer in all kinds of mystical things
Like it's for him this was very freeing and liberating because it meant that there were
That we couldn't be mechanized
There was profound mystery forever
Coca-Cola
I'm on your team here but me just point on something
GoNoodle when he died
He was not exactly liberated he was a paranoid
Like he thought people trying to poison him he's starving self to that he was exactly liberated but I choose to believe
It's somewhere in his tortured mind and
This is my mother
Pretty torture
There was a little fellow humming
The song a song
Liberation
Problems
Thanks to Steve strogatz she has a new book
Called
Infinite Powers how calculus reveals the secrets of the universe
And also thanks to Janna Levin her book about doodle is called
A Madman dreams of Turing machines
And finally our last
Lupe's yeah this one like the last one involves things feeding back on themselves
Kind of
Like a classic positive feedback loop
Which is what exactly was like when you can do with audio you take a speaker in a mic you put the feed the sound from the speaker into the mic and
Speaking into the mic X the most liked and then you get something like
Painful is painful but
That kind of feedback loop like in the case of her neck story
Can also
Take the pain away
Yes
Comes to us from this lady I Melanie thernstrom is a writer the author of a book on pain called the
Pain Chronicles which is a book
That began as a chronicling of her own pain
Which has been suffering from every day for the last 15 years
And what sort of pain
Om pain in my neck
And right shoulder and right side of my head
All at once
Yeah Yeah Yeahs
Start with something that you hid it there how did it start
It didn't start with an injury of any
Kind but it is Friday discrete
Time goes back to 1997 she was Upstate New York at a country house
On a date with our first date and I wanted to impress him
So I swam across of
Pond by the mile across
Is this your idea or was it his idea
It was my idea
Wow that's a different kind of fish that
And you made it all the way there and back
Yes
And nothing happened
But that night
What you got in the bed
I was kept awake by this strange burning sensation in my
Shoulder
Knack
I didn't get that
That
Head pain
Like four more years
And that
Testicular pain
Never went away and got worse
Time
I'm burning so it's like a nerve a nerve was
Yeah I mean
Eventually I got an MRI
Couple years later
And there was none
Impingement knife
Binance
She says she's tried everything
Drugs in
Physical Therapy shoes
Distraction like I'll go to a matinee and if it's
Scary movie
I just don't stay full
Focus on the pain to distract you can work but then she says as soon as she gets out of the movie
Its back
And it's angry
For being ignored
Sensation
Like that.
Right
Side of my head
Dying Light
React not
Image with kayak frighten me
Find it that thought would make the pain worse
And making the pain worse
Will
Inspire further negative fantasy
Which will make
Inspiremore fantasies
Positive feedback loop
Negative
And eventually Melanie's the decided okay I'm going to write a book about this
Do some research
I was reading a lot about
Self-inflicted pain in religious
And I actually went to witness
Hindi fast
How to say I'm in Kuala Lumpur
What she saw a really changed your mind about things
You can see video of this Festival on YouTube
What you see is a dense crowd
Doing insane acts of devotion literally like
Read needles through their tongue
Irritated cheeks
Weighted Fish House
Daniel from their back
And yet she says when she would look in their faces they seemed
Relax
Really relaxed
Was it just that they were
Already in the pants actually seemed like they weren't
At all
And I would think
Okay
This person here has a skewer in his mouth
You know you can't
Become
A religious Hindi in order
To experience this
Analgesic penerbit like that's cheating but I did feel like okay to one way to describe
I bet it stays but for every
Wavy fan
Describing religion
There's also a way you can
Describe things in in scientific terms
And the reality is all of our pain
Is in our head
Which means it's this guy this is Sean Mackey chief of the Stanford pain management division
He will tell you that one of the most basic facts about pain is it is not purely physical
We've got
Signals coming up from the body they're sending sms
Like if you whack a toe the signal shoots up some nerves in your leg into your spine and those signals converge Ann Arbor
Before you even feel a thing there are multitude of what I refer to as little amplifier throughout our brain
The turn up and turn down
The overall pain experience
Annie's amplifiers are things like your mood
Anxiety depression
Attention expectations all of these things
Feedback on to that signal coming up from the body and they can either boosted
Papa past a certain point where
You get a sensation of pain
Or they can dead nits down down down down down down down down
Point is pain is a conversation between the brain and the body and Shawn thought
What would happen if I actually let people
See that
Could they
Take control of it yes we did a study in Melanie signed up so describe what happens in the six
If you're putting this
MRI machine
We put somebody into a scanner and brain scanner
And you have a screen in front of
What you see on the screen is something that normally only the researcher
You see your own brain
In real-time yeah you're just seeing one p call the anterior cingulate cortex
How many parts of the brain
Respond to pain but that's the one that it's an area that has been shown to be involved with pain perception turning pain
Hang up and down it's thought to give
Pain it's emotional
Bayland it's negative
And you actually see an image of this little piece of your brain right there in front of you on the screen to meet you at your looking at your brain
Oh no it's confusing to everybody
So instead we give a visual metaphor EC an image of
I'm fire plane in a nice case of a cartoon flying but it looks realistic
Flickering flame do they leap into the activation
I'm there is in that region
Higher than planes go
So Melanie is lying in the scanner watching her own pain flames
And Sean gives her a set of instructions we say okay
We want you to imagine that you're sitting in a nice warm soothing jacuzzi
You know this printing is a warm bath is burning is very relaxing I'm relaxing into it
I presume it was like
Before she knew it the Flames were Riley
Okay okay
How about your lying on a beautiful beach
Yes
You know this writing is
Suntan and the sand is nice and warm and pleasant
Angular
Have been in my new bathing suit if I
I'm getting front like this
Sunburn
And then the flames
Kind of go
Crazy
Our thoughts keep slipping out of her control
Every time she would see those Flames rise
To think Ono the Flames are rising which would make them rise
That's even more and then more and more until she had this bonfire on this
Screen your immediately struck by they look like the Flames where you're going to
The Flames were you're burned at the stake
I've been reading a lot of lies
Negative
And flip it then I started
Trying to move into the idea of being
St. Peter Martyr
That I
Believe that I
With hive
Pokemon that I was
Protected by my faith
And it's Melanie started thinking about this
She could see the flames
Dying down
Just little bit
But you thought okay I'll try this might need
Going in that
Kind of feeling
I was trying to pick one of the few pairs I
I knew
I mean I I didn't
I'm half-jewish
And how Christian
I went through them not settled in until what kind of
Margaret Atwood
You know I start thinking
And if you have to ask him about us
Jewish wedding Kristen and I think about Jewish Martyrs like what prayers do they say she added and revived
Nice details
The Flames go down
Okay I'm in the right brain State let me do more of that
To Melanie finally decided okay I'm going to be this one
Particular Jewish Martyrs names
Eva ben-joseph
He's burned at the stake by the Romans for teaching the Torah
And this particular Legend. Just as the execution is about to set fire to the logs right underneath his feet Akiva
Stare the Executioner in the eyes
And smile
And the Executioner
Why are you smiling you're about to be burned alive
A kippah set
All my life
When I said those words
You shall love the Lord
Your God with all your heart with all your soul
I was sad
Cuz I thought
When should I be able to feel that command
And now
But I'm giving my life and my resolution remains firm
Why shouldn't I smile
And by the time Melanie had this fantasy buildup in her mind
She looked over at the fair
She noticed
They were almost gone
0k
For the first time
She taking control of it I felt like
Wow
I am
Watching my brain
Thinking my thoughts
And I am
Changing my thoughts
By thinking and watching myself
So you are looking at yourself looking at yourself
Looking at yourself
Yes it's like hearing inside and seeing the ghost in the machine
Step on the moon like I am
Watching my brain
Thinking my thoughts
And I am thinking my thoughts
Changing my thoughts by thinking and watching my thoughts
Watching my
Brain changing my thoughts
By thinking and watching myself do this
Well I needed to stop at I need to stop at this.
Once you were
Did your two sessions on your in between exercise
Without this all these gizmos could you
Could you
Address your pain
Yeah better
No
Like you think well okay
Can't you just get the feedback from your own body
But somehow this is satanism
White
Direct enough that I think
That you could do it without the visual
Feedback
For that moment
In that machine
It was
An hour
Burrito very special thanks to our singers who joined us this hour from the new music Ensemble at LaGuardia high school they are
Kelly efthimiou Eli greenhoe
Ruby from those guys wrote and performed all the music between the pieces you guys rock and thanks to the guy who teaches them at work
Organize this mr. Robert apostle
Let's begin
Did is the formal greeting cards this is Jake holling from the other side of the planet in Adelaide South Australia
Australia Radiolab was created by Jed album Rod and it's produced by Soren wheeler Dylan came to the directory
Sound design
Gigi lechtenberg is Arctic
Osthoff include Simon Adler Becca Bressler Rachel Cusick David devil methylheptane
Tracy hunt
Matt kielty
Robert krulwich
Julia Longoria
Annie McEwen Latif Nasser
Melissa O'Donnell
Kelly Prime
Sarakari Ariane whack
Pat Walters Emily Webster
Without from Shima Ali Orchard Quinn and Neil denature affect Checker is Michelle Harris
Thank you guys