Are you awake
Northern listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
Hey I'm Jonathan Rod I'm rubber Chromebook should Radiolab and today we have a start with a Prelude
Hello hello England are you there from our producer Annie McEwen
Rosetta annies
It is just well done this is Reaper
Pennant race
Write hello everyone very busy very successful career
Yes perhaps the two most prominent things I've done I was on the stuff of The Economist for many years
I then went from there to the bank of England where I was Deputy Governor
Taking imagine Rupert is a very knowledgeable guy absolutely
Exchange rates
Commodity prices and haha
Super successful guy
He's been living with his one big cavernous
Yeah no very recently Rupert new absolutely nothing
About sign
I'm going to say nothing I mean like
Kid no clue about how the natural world around him work
In any way
Literally
Princeton
The periodic table
I never heard of the periodic table
In the last year
And when one day his wife
Told him he was a mammal had no idea
I told she was using it as a term of abuse
The cable many many times
Oh that's Radioactive
When describing something he felt was bad or dangerous
Without
What I meant by that
Appraised
I guess like what was it like to be a very important person in the very important circles
But have this Gap
Well I'll tell you what I became good at bluffing
I was on the board of
Number of Mining Company
And I hope none of my colleagues
From those companies a listening
Part of being on the board met yet read all these geologist reports
Intelligence reports
And then we would have board
Discussions about a lisp
And I would sit there striking my chin in the way I hoped would look like a wise
Jeff
But I didn't really have a clue what people were talking about that you didn't have
This is where it all began of course
I come from Zimbabwe and I went to school there
It was a boarding school the kind of school where you eat wear uniforms you play cricket
And for some reason if
Extra clever
Instead of sitting any signs at all you said he Greek
Greek Couture
So it's not as they did me a huge amount of favor
So he'd always thought soon as I have time
That's what I'm doing now I'm studying science
For the first time the age of 71
And he's really going for it he's got a tutor for 3 hours a week
Studying physics
Biology and
The favourite
I have been really absorbed by Kem
I guess you are married
To a scientist is that
Crab I am case of what is is that influencing your studies at all or
The Desert Sun point I would put this right coupled with another agreement that she would be a very helpful
Shoot it to me it was indeed she's proving to be
But I think there's a danger now that she's going to rather wish this she'd never encouraged me to do this cuz I
I know I never stop singing while have you noticed this
Something it was Polly the periodic table
When I first discovered
I couldn't believe how elegant it was how come
Preston beautifully defined it or was
But I am
Very very devoted to it the end you have a copy of it close by most of the day
Very committed this is amazing then there are other things
Principle of electricity and how it lights up bulbs and how it then moves on in
Casual around the house
Who comes out at the other end and
Things like
Speed and velocity
Italian accelerator
I'm cells and you talking about plants and you took about animals something as simple as that gossip water I've got
Put on the table by me now
I know look at it
With a huge amount of respect
And I think my card if any I could have a look with microscope ice and see those little
Molecules
Agenda
Single
Atoms of
Oxygen and how they will join.
Together
Be such a delight
I can see why your wives like rolling her eyes would
Buford go to bed
It sounds very much to me like you falling in love
Yeah it does it feels like that is so refreshing wonderful and exciting and you know you can
Really believe it
It's like one day having a
Miracles laser surgery on your eyes Sunday
Turn from being color-blind to
Being fully functional and seeing the richness of the world around you
I'm thinking my God in there I was
In that one dimensional
Color
I know I got all of this
To Revel in
I picture you in a musical sort of like swinging
Your briefcase is about as
No jump home from work and dance around
Lamppost
That would be nice I wouldn't recommend my dancing but anyway I
I do like the image
Thanks Annie
Speaking of reveling
And reveling in reveling in the Wonder getting back to basics
You'll like asking the questions you never get a chance to ask
That's what we're going to do this is one in a series of all of us are curious about
This that and the other
And some of the visitors and the Vets has and the others won't go away
I want to go to the
Show either
Investigative thing right
Feels like okay let's make a space for this that and the other
So we did we decided to just devote a few shows
Small questions
Ask my our people that wouldn't go away so what the heck would just answer
Yeah and it may be in the process you get back to that repair Therrien
State of renewal
Of wonder
All right so you ready Baba k i Am
We're going to start things off with hello hello hello interrogatory duet
Producers Molly Webster this is Molly
Ariana
We had with this research
All right well my name is Oriana Aragon and I'm an assistant professor here
Clemson University ok
She studies human behavior and emotion
So maybe you can just tell me like what made you first run into this
Question
Well
It was
Summer 2011 orellana was a grad student
Yale at the time and one night she was just sitting around watching late-night television
Conan O'Brien
Before Leslie Bibb very beautiful talented woman you're very talented and and lovely ad
Actress was on
And she was talking about having encounter this
Cute puppy woman
I was just at that
Hair salon
Little dog
Ugly dog
It was like a Maltese
Apache
Tok
Like this little curly hair and she must have straightened with a flat iron
And then she put one ponytail holder and then another ponytail holder
The kind of look like a water ox
Yeah
And then
Rihanna says
Leslie did something that just sort of
Struck her she started like
Gritting your teeth scrunching her face
Squeezing our hands I just walked
Dog is making me so mad
I'm going to punch it it's so cute you know she's like it's so cute you just want to smash it
I want to punch you make me so mad at me
And Oriana was just sitting there watching the show and she was like wow that's a strange reaction like Leslie saw this
Just wanted to kick it in the ass
Which might seem odd
But is Oriana kept thinking about this moment she was like
Yeah we do this we do this sort of thing all the time I do that I totally do that sign out Ariana's new
When I see my baby
Steve's like little body
My joints tense up in my hands my fingers start to curl
MIT start declensions
I just need to eat his face and I need to figure out what's going on here this sort of like a feeling with cuteness
What is it that we're doing and why do we do that
Back in 2011 orellana set out to answer those questions
And the conventional thinking of the time was that you know if this is there is an aggressive expression like gritting teeth
A clenched fist
Or wanting to
Squeeze something must be representing some sort of
Aggression
Underneath that there's a little bit of violence
You want to hurt
That thing yes
Which
Sure makes sense to me because I think my first thought is we were all cannibals at some point and I'd there
There's something in there coming through
And I'm in and it's not good in flights
Society in that
Is just
The urge
Sneaking out
In some way
No I think it's a
Work is work is continued
For the last six years on this and I've found a lot I've understood a lot now about
What these Expressions communicate
And what they represent
So when Oriana first started researching this
One of the things she said figure out was
When we see something
Do we actually want to squeeze
Or is this just a
Russian
Figure of speech I want to squeeze you
And so
She started doing these experiments where she would bring people into the lab and she would show them these pictures like a little baby duck
A little baby fluffy puppy and then give them bubble wrap
It's like really quiet Hall and throughout the entire semester
You could hear papapapapapapapa and for the really cute pics like baby
Ducklings you sure that's like they was just being ringing out she's above a rat that I identify with that
I was like bubble wrap would not cut it for me so Oriana was like okay
It looks like there's real aggression here but
I made it this isn't that much of a shocker
At the same time
There's actually nothing negative going on inside the
These people they were actually full of joy and happiness while they were
Turn bubble wrap
So
It's not about
An actual latent aggression we're just we're just sort of
Expressing it this way but we don't mean it
That we're aggressive at all
But that's so
Strange to have this sort of
Weird
Schism where you're at
Happy on the inside but aggressive on the outside
It's actually not as weird as you would
No no Briana pointed out that in some ways it's so, and we don't even notice it
Happens all the time you see athletes for sports fans looks like absolute
Fury
Punching the air screaming or weeping
When something great happens
And that's another thing
Think about you know
Tears of joy you see brides and nuc
Lottery winners
Or
You see people weeping at the off nature
Double complete rainbow think about all the times when
What happens on the outside the disk
Play
Doesn't match
What's going on on the inside
I saw it but I still feel like I'm at why why would you want to punch the cute puppy
We put the rainbow started to look at all this stuff
And having tested everything that I can think of everything that's in the literature there is a through-line to what these Express
Represent and communicate
So according to Oriana
When you see tears like all kinds of Tears
Weather for winning the medal for looking at the beautiful sunset it's the same as tears at a funeral
Greece communicate
Wanting to stop
Wanting to be
Still
Wanting to pause
And Oriana said that when it comes to these like Expressions cuz you know
Now you see a cute puppy or you scored a goal or you act
Actually want to fight somebody
That's about wanting to
Go
Wanting to move
Wanting to approach wanting to get close to
It's about
Moving forward or momentum
That's funny cuz I like when I
See my baby at 4 in the morning when he
Cat that wants to nurse
I'm exhaust
It's but it's not until like ice
See him in like his
Face lights up like you so excited to see me and if I want Alex mushroom and buy them right
Like that
The thing that
Get on going
Pause moments
Right cuz it's
That's definitely it is
It's a listener of those care behaviors
EXO
Just nice to know that in situations where like we may not know what's going on we may not be able
Motel like
Read our own emotions are know how to respond to the world
Most basic
Bodily instincts
Bailey
Boil down to this
Really
Simple set of
Choices or like urges
You know what I think is I find myself thinking
In a way that I appreciate is
You know I'm not even going to get all these right but do you know what we like remember when like humans used to think of themselves
Discomposed
Like fire water wind and somehow in this conversation I feel
You like all right all along it might not have been fire
It could have just been go yeah I know and maybe it wasn't water but it was
Stop
Yeah
That's why I'm telling you we need
Self-help book
Thank you Molly Webster thank you Ariana
Movies like you're welcome I'm I'm now disclaimer Molly which is
To say that Leslie Bibb is actually been on Conan
Number of times talking about how she wants to
Punch
Dogs and and and and punch babies and in one she wants to slash Anjelica Huston face
All motivated by the same cute aggression Rihanna and her face is how she introduce yourself to an
Anjelica Huston
So that's just to say that at the top of the Peace
Call happen if you got just turned around and walked away
Is what my as one might want to say at the top of this piece
While Oriana was in
Fired in 2011 by a Leslie and appearance
We use
A scene from 2018
Okay there was a black outfit in one
And a red outfit another got it
Got it all right
Okay have fun
Hey Tracy
Should we ask you how you
Do Caillou got the idea to do this
Wait. The right question
Start a timer but it is a question and it will do for right now
Okay Tracy
Facing the challenge of a completely blank
Page where any question at all might be legitimate
How did you land Upon This Way
So one of my friends my hair
Is cat child I'm a reporter with code-switch a Tema and fear that covers racing culture and so I started tweeting one day
Cuz outside keep up with all my friends I just look at what they're tweeting and she was feeding how she's feeling very vulnerable right now cuz she's
Is breaking out a story that was going to involve Samson yes and so I want to know a little bit about
How did you meet Samson
I got Samson in 25
And
In 2015
This weird thing happened we're all of a sudden I became obsessed
With just wanting a dog
All of a sudden all I could do was
Browse
These dog adoption websites in the DC area so there was like a lot of like
You know going to shelters and going to rescue groups in
Finally this rescue group that I think she's been in contact with email turned said
Want to come meet Samson and I clicked on his profile and he was really really adorable beagle mix
They had this a cute video on YouTube are you
Jumping around and he looks so happy and he's cramping in a field playing with other dogs
And the profile didn't really say much about him just said that he was a little shy he was a stray and South Carolina
And so I arranged to
You know go meet him up
Adoption event
And
When my partner and I go to the event
We find Samson and
He is just as cute in person
Except we noticed that he's
Super super
Scared
Where he's like shaking and
He can't even stand on his own and the people at the adoption event at the house
The flap
So I don't know maybe that should have been a red flag for
Who knows.
For me I was like I don't like
Keep that going to come out
So I'm going to be the one to bring him out of his shell
And so
Samson was living with The Fosters
Family and they wanted to do a home visit
So if I still came over with Samson to my apartment my little basement apartment in DC
And we gon this walk a little exploratory walk around the neighborhood
And while they're walking we passed by a man who is black and he's wearing a sweatshirt
Scanza Foster turns to me and goes
Oh
He doesn't like men in hoodies
So cat is thinking
And I'm thinking it was you sent me this
Are you saying that he's scared of guys in hoodies or are you saying that he's afraid of
Black men
Right
But
Samson was also afraid of me
And
Tell Philly badly wanted a dog and Samson seemed
You know just like
Like he needed me
And I don't know maybe this is
Patronizing
Human
Adopt a dog think I don't know I don't know and so I decided my partner and I decided to adopt him
And
We loved him so much and we love him we love him
Present tense
So
Cat her partner take sanzen-in and almost
Immediately
Cat would have a friend over who is black-market her friends who are brown
For a long time that he especially did not like what if I create an American friend when they would go outside
He just was afraid of anybody who was an American or you know like
Let them out but then it became this
Clarify just one thing
You yourself are not white
I am I am Asian American and Chinese Americans you think that's maybe because you said he was afraid of you at first
Do you think that he maybe was afraid of you because you weren't like
I don't know he is so at he did like my partner more and my partner is white
In MCAT did put Santa in training in butt
That didn't seem to work so she was just left looking at this adorable little dog that she just taking in thinking
Is he racist
And I should be quick
This is like a question that a lot of people have
You know you know what's going on
This is not the first time I've heard like this morning my mom called me
This idea that dogs can be racist is racist
Chose all the time he's going to get really aggressive towards people with darker color skin
Huffington Post in Psychology today and actually what parks and
Jacksonville dog owners have you ever heard of this idea that a dog can like you're racist and they're a bunch of people who were like I have
Oh yeah
Totally wants long time ago you know I heard stories about
Play somebody there like he doesn't like a white girl dogs that maybe didn't like white women you be bottom and just black women
Black men I guess all this is just a long ways that this is definitely you know
So my question is
Is it actually a thing now I'm rolling so this is going to be kind of
A fun conversation about race
Can I sat down with this woman sure
Sure I'm Alexandra Horowitz I
Study at the dog cognition lab and Barnard does research and dogs think about dogs. Dogs all things dogs
Okay
So go to jump in Cattails Alexandra
That how she is taking Sampson in
Barca seems to be
Ina races
But like you know is that even possible I don't know can a dog be
Recess
She was like
Well
Obviously
Dogs aren't racist
The way humans are racist
I mean racism is rooted in our history the history of our country and how we've dealt with different
Groups of people
But dogs do not know about that
What the dog knows about comes
From
Its own life
That dog's own life
But
Ancira talking through what dogs can do
We ended up having this conversation
About
The most basic elements of being a racist
Erase it erase it anything about it
You know step one is just
Putting people in these different groups in your head
Can dogs
Remember types of
People or just well I do think the dogs are sensitive to new things and differences
And one thing that Alexander told us that she's seen in her work is that dogs do seem to play differently with diff
Different breeds for instance they play better with ones that kind of look
Like them wait so dogs have a bye at the good they are purchased for there on time
They do and partly might be because they have the same kind of equipment the same length tail the same time
Ear shape the same body size
So they understand each other's cues a little better might just be easier but that's what I'm saying is dogs notice difference
Census in the world
And when it come to noticing differences between people
There's some at least anecdotal evidence that dogs can see can tell men and women apart
They can't see differences in skin color
Right cuz I are dogs colorblind solutely can see
Color differences
What is the world look like to a dog
Best approximation is that there's probably seeing something like the color spectrum when it's
Dusk and feels like yellow
Sense of worth in oranges
Have disappeared or have been muted
Okay so the dog can see color yeah so it seems like it's possible that maybe dogs can tell the difference between skin
But then the next question is
Can a dog
Then
Make associations you know like light-skinned people like this and dark-skinned people are like this
And then carry that forward and all this other interactions whenever it meets another person
Like that person
Ingroup bias
And can it do that with dark-skinned people in question
Well
That's okay I actually did this
Did us-34 code-switch okay
It's rainy and afraid of that she
She found 20 Mori
Laurie Santos she is another dog cognition expert except this time she's at Yale
Call and I'm like
Hi I think my dog is ready
And she comes to the same thing as Alexandra
I think the word racist has a lot and it you know the history of race in America and all these
But in her work
She has been trying to answer
This is very basic
Can a dog show preferences for certain racial groups the Lorry designed a study a dog
Dog version of a very famous human study known as an IAT which is the implicit association test
I don't think I've ever heard of this test
I don't know what it is okay so the implicit association test that is put up my heart rate right so basically that test
You can take it online it kind of feels like a computer game where you get these words and have to sort whether they are positive
Dave or negative
And then you're also getting faces
Like to speak to the people and you have to sort weather Bay AR
Black or white
Basically they're kind of test to see if you would like associate certain groups of people with certain kind of negative or positive
Images of thought
Tracks yes yes
How on Earth would you give this to a dog
Well
I think our dog is here right now so we can
Lori found with implicit bias research similar kinds of Studies have been done with human babies
He's just to see if they have racial preferences and since their babies
They can't use computers with words
Researchers use photos photos of different human faces
So
Adidas for dogs
Lori had this Pit Bull mix named Vader come in and what she does is she
Bring the dog into this little room
And they have a dog sit
I live near the center of the room where there is a reason
And she
Hatha Spa
And it kind of reminds me of like a little Puppet Theater
Where
It's open on one side
And you can slide in different images
At the front that the dog will see
So the research assistant gets his box ready
Life in a picture
And then
Gold office cover to show Vader a picture of a black person
Just a straight face
Yeah kind of headshot
And then
They said the same picture to Vader over and over
Over again
You seem straight face
Black person
But then
The researcher shows Vader this picture of a
Smiling
Happy looking German Shepherd
And then
Black person
Smiling German Shepherd
It's all very randomized
So sometimes it is
Black person black person then smiling dog
The boy
What is it that they're looking for here they only showed black faces and happy dogs
And you don't
When data comes it again the Lively show him other kinds of combinations
White faces angry dogs
Angry dogs and then if you know
So on
And what they're looking for and in this is the same thing they're looking for when they
Did the test on babies
Is to see whether the dog is attentive and focused
Or bored and unfocused
Basically how is the dog reacting to
These two different pictures being put together
The way Lori but it was
You know if a dog shows like a pro white bias then
They should find the categories of white faces look happy dogs easier to process
And therefore more boring
So they might like Look Away more or
They might not be able to stay focused boredom implies that that dog might have a preference for white people
But then if they see a black face a happy dog and they stay really focused on it and they're not bored
That could possibly mean that maybe they're surprised that these two things go together
And maybe that's evidence of a little bit of prejudice
So so what is Lori learned
Will Dad here it is
The big news
And it's too soon to tell it's still too early to tell
Yeah I mean we're really at such an early stages it's really hard to say I guess one thing we have learned is that
Are so many people are interested in the results of the study your people really want to know the answer to the question of how dogs
CDC categories
And that's been really compelling just to realize
How fascinated people are with this question
How often do you get the is my dog racist question
Shure again Alexandra Horowitz you know because we see dogs as mirrors of ourselves
Our dog
Books as mirrors of ourselves
And
They are
Because regardless of what a dog
Can see or not see
Or whether they associate negative feelings with
Different faces
The one thing that dogs are very very good at
And in this is something that both Lori and Alexandra made a plaintiff
Is
Paying attention to us
And more specifically
How we behave
For instance remember this idea that thoughts and tell men and women apart well she was like
Probably has nothing to do with what men and women look like but instead it's how we behave men and women.
Deal with dogs a little bit different
On the whole
You should bring treats
Women are more effusive
More likely to talk to dogs
In a higher pitch voice women might be more likely to crouch down
To a dog instead of kind of coming right up to a dog so these are obviously generalizations
I think a dog is very sensitive to
Does behavioral differences in Alexandria says the person who dogs are the most sensitive to
Who sponsored their King the closest amount of attention to
Is you
You the guardian
You the owner
We have
To be sensitive
When we feel
Tents
I wonder if
You know I suspected this thing
Became dislike
Sort of funny but not really funny thing that I always wondered
And somehow convey
Confirmed it or made it happen to spy
You know
Just the anxiety of
Oh my gosh is my dog actually
Is he racist
Well so if for instance and I don't want to
Put behaviors in your
I don't want to say you're doing something or not but if you tense up
When you see your dog's going to have a reaction
To somebody
And your Dogs Unleashed sure they're at some level in your control
Then the dog will feed off of that
Cat do you think that that's something you do do you think that your
That you have almost as pre reaction
To Samson's reaction that might sell Samson to react
Nothing no I don't know
Could be a situation where
This has become such a running joke among
Our friends you know
That are friends who
You know many of our friends are people of color they come over and they're already like all this
This finds like this stupid.
This dog
You going to bark at me he might bite
I don't want to touch him really yeah I do
And so maybe that like
Maybe a host of things reinforce to Sampson
I may be cancerous
But like there is a potential that
I have created this world
My dog
Now sees the construct of race through me
Just because I have taught them to him through my
Like that all nonverbal cues of
A lot
Esta
If only we could talk to dogs
Understand
If you had 5 minutes apart not going to make it harder if you had
2 1/2 minutes to talk to Sampson what am I
What questions would be so hard to do but
Like I would want to know about his history but that would obviously take up way too much time cuz I feel like
Being a southern boy he would have like a really hard time
So I think I would just spend those two and a half minutes being like
You are such a
Acute dog everybody in general regardless of race I don't even know if you can tell the difference between
People they would love you
And
He loves attention so much and you know like when he does get settled into a situation he can be such a
A cute and I like
Devour he always wants at some scratches
Sam said if you were this nice
Every single person you met on the street
And you just didn't let fear dominate you
People would love you so much
Watch
I know I wish I could give him that pep talk
I wish someone would give me that
Good boy okay
Good job
Kaiser Tracy hunt thanks also to Cat Chow from NPR code switch you can find a live
Link to her original story at radiolab.org thanks also to Samson
Tolerant dogs everywhere
Natural waist
K9
Chandelure
Inattentively pooping in public
What a title
Speaking with dogs
Another beat
Ruffle here Raphael Kroger
I read for Harper's magazine
Has had a long-standing question when it was answered
By a German scientist
Highest gross
In that scientific paper he just
So
This began for
The author of the paper must
The same way that it began for me it was an idle curiosity
Paucity
He was
Raising
3 kids
He would take them to the park
Their children and families around
But there was also
Assertive
Crisis level
Dog poop
He sees people letting their dogs
Poop
And then
Just walk away
And he starts to wonder
How can you
Just leave.
Do something so
So specifically antisocial
As leaving
Feces
On the sidewalk
What's with these people
What's what's going on in people's heads
And so
On the way to work in the morning
He would
Follow people at a certain distance
Without talking to them and take notes
You have to study there in front of you I have the sitting in front of me
And I quote
Neighbors watch
Poop falling out of the dog
What it means
Poop in public huge pile of excrement on the ground and on the way back I'll go owners look away from their poop
In the afternoon he does
The same thing through the medium of poop
The earlier science
I had my God the fact that those previous studies
Great
In the previous studies on this
Russia size
The typical distinction is between people who pick up
The poop and
People who
Just leave the
Wet
Babe categorized as
Responsible and irresponsible
Dog owners
But
After he's observed these people for a while
You start to recognize
But there was
Something more complicated
Intriguing
And
Battle going on
The 101 of the behaviors he observes
Is
People bagging the poop going to that trouble and then just leaving
Scooping the poop up
Putting it into an envelope
Plastic envelope
And then they
Don't throw it away yes
People will bagging the Bandit
Sometimes right next to
Garbage cans that are not overflowing
And then
D'Amore
Intriguing
Version he observes his people baguette
And then display it
Prominent Place sometimes hung on a fence
Sometimes
Hanging in bushes are ship trees
Switches be actual vernacular term
Yeah actually my favorite mysterious example and got the paper points to
People
Hanging the bags
Poop on construction fencing
With flashing lights on it so that at night
It creates a kind of disco
For the Pooh
Nuts.com
She describes a
And
What the author reason to this is that it's a kind of Middle Ground
Between
Responsible and irresponsible
Action
Maybe you bagged
The poop to begin with
It's because someone's watching you you want to be
Seen as
A good citizen
But
Then later
It switches
A
Form of rebellion
Against the unnatural constraints
Civilization
And so leaving the poop returns humans to Nature in a way
Humans can no longer
Run around
Pooping freely in the wilderness
So
The dog
Becomes a kind of proxy
Through which this
Aggressive mischievous
Atavistic desire can be played out
So I want to drop my pants and just poop on the street but my dog does it
Good for me
Something like that yes
Is that mean
When you see a man or woman with a dog who poops on the street
You should be getting those cheat just pooped
Well
It's
At the very least
If you decide to get into it and
Tell somebody pick up your poop
The U is ambiguous
Weird
I'm honestly speechless by that
Robert I did Nazi that coming
Well I will just walked in and an end
And left it there for us
And then it was picked up by
Adler who
Back and put it
On display
As sometimes happens of course it's time introduced
And I guess
Time to take
Yes but you got to take a break
We're back a few more questions
And answers coming up right after
This is Chelsea Gibson
Calling from Dayton Ohio
Radiolab
Supported in part
By the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of
Science and technology in the modern world
More information about Sloan
At www
. Sloan. Org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
We're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments
Brilliance
Basically I want to hear about this
Times when a kid you know did something
It just means you lean back and say
Well
How did they do that
Maybe it was the moment that I
Kids you've been reading to 4 month started reading back
To you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lesson
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of their music
Or maybe the kids in math class you notice their writing used
Taking the margin of their geometry
We're interested in the specific moments where a kid does something super smart
It doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story
T-shirt
Go to radiolab.org
Brilliance
Amber Court
Short audio
Again that's radiolab.org / brilliance
Thank you so much
Chad Robert Radiolab Cavalcade of questions and answers and the next
Comes from producer Pat Walters hello Emily are you there
I'm here
Alright a few months ago I called this
Tree sign
My test and Emily Burns and I'm the science director with save the Redwoods League
I have so many questions about trees for you
But I really just had one
So I I read this
A little tiny article in the spring I think
Which artifact in it that really shocked me
Ian the fact
Was
That redwood trees have
12 *
As much
DNA as humans
Is that true well it looks like it is turning out to be at eight times bigger than the human genome
Okay. So 12 is closed a little overestimated name is not a reliable source
But the idea that like these trees would have so much more DNA than I
Just kind of like
Twisted my brain up in 7 different ways
It's pretty crazy
Cuz you usually think of genes that means something to do with complexity exactly so if your Mozart
Oh you're a Tall Tree like who's going to have the most genes
Don't like what is all that extra DNA even doing well I'm not a geneticist
Forest conservation
One thing Emily was able to tell me
Is that I was missing the forest for the trees
So to speak and why is that
Well family told me that Chris Treadwell it does have a very large genome there are
Tons of things that have way more DNA than us
Anime bowling
You just got a new.
Like a rundown
So
An onion has five times as much
An onion apus salamanders with 40 times as much
Let's hear things like lungfish has a cockroach red meat Lobster
I love to just lies in the bottom of a cold seeing bolt at the top of the list arguably the
Prison with the most DNA in the world
With 50 times more DNA than a human
Is a tiny not so remarkable looking
Little Japanese
Flower that's deeply strange
It's puzzling by the way is biologist Ryan Gregory professor at the University of Guelph
In Canada and my area of study is why certain salamanders have 40 times more DNA
Then you and I do
Am I told me like no one knows exactly why that's the case
Well that's why I still have a job is because this is something we're trying to figure out what
According to Ryan
Here's what we do now
So in your genome and I I say yours and I mean that in a mine too I'm not going to single you out take the human genome
Your genome is about
1 1/2 to 2% jeans
Only about 1 to 2% of your DNA is involved in making the stuff that makes
Up you
That's the stuff we called jeans
Now there's another couple percent that we now think are there to turn those jeans on and off switch
Is important but the vast majority of your DNA is accumulated
Detritus could be a gene that sort of mutates into grades and no longer works in might be random
Redundant copies of other DNA example of might be
80 80 80 80 a million times
Became essentially stock
In the genome and so now they're passed on from parent to offspring but the key thing is that all these little random bits of
DNA
Turn a hanging around there not really doing anything
Which princess is how you can end up with a huge genome even though you're just a
The tree or frog or a worm or even single cell
That's right but if they're not doing anything to help me why well
They would be doing things to help themselves
Help them
Sounds a bit like
You think about
The bacteria in your gut
Most of them are probably just
There because you're a nice warm bag of nutrients that is a great place to live if you're bacterium
That would be kind of the same sort of thing that might be happening in the genome which is
But they're not like
Alive
Really right like there
Where are they
Well I don't I don't know I think it depends a lot on your definition of a live so I mean are viruses alive
That that's a philosophical question that
Is pretty difficult
But the shift that you have to
Kind of make
And thinking about the genome is less that its it's
It's basically the recipe for making you or the blueprint for
A human or any of those kinds of things and think of it
Almost more like a little ecosystem
A jungle with all kinds of different entities
Doing their own thing
But
The one thing that they all do
Is used us
To make copies of themselves
So
In this vast
Ecosystem
In some part of your DNA you get some
Ancient fire
It just keeps
Happy
Little further down the line
Another one
Do the same thing
And then in some other part of your DNA 80 80 80 80 80 80 80
Just copying itself again and again and again and again
Almost everywhere you look you have these dumb bits and TNA just
Copying themselves over and over again
Building up yourselves with useless DNA looks like a hitchhiker that gets into your car you turn around suddenly
Is it a Fred there's now Fred and Fred
Yeah and then turn around again this Fred and Fred and Fred right I mean Fred and Fred and Fred and Fred and
That's pretty much how you end up with these super huge dinos
Sometimes
Back and bi Pride
Okay so
Brian told me about this particular sound
Certain group of salamanders
Caballito glycemia
Is part of the
Very large family of salamanders that live all over the Western half of
North America
A long long time ago something happened in the environment that made the salamanders get
Littler
Define
Except for this one problem they have big genomes
And the more DNA there is
The bigger the cell is
Saumur DNA
Hagerstown
Because
All the DNA have to go in the nucleus
Of every single cell
So as the salmon start getting smaller and smaller and smaller
Their bodies are getting smaller
And their heads are getting smaller
Because they have these huge dinos
They tend to have
Ignorance
And now you're trying to cram a whole bunch of big neurons
Into a tiny little skull
Well you're not going to fit as many and so
Relative
Two other salamanders
That haven't been man tries
Their Vision starts to degrade slightly their ability to
Look around in the world and distinguish like
What's an insect and what's a leaf
Gets worse Conte I can't do the kind of visual predation that you normally
See you in there was a relative
Instead they
Shifted to
Being lie in wait predators
Basically but having a huge genome
Maybe salamanders get dumb
And I couldn't help but think about you know all the extra stuff you accumulate so.
It's almost hard to get in
And close the door behind
I like my partner and I have the storage closet that's just
With crap a watering can the broom and a car battery
Pile of button-down shirt
I want a little bit too small ones
It's kind of boring how old is very uncomfortable
A lot of it I don't even know why we happening there's like a three and a half foot tall roll
Brown paper several unfinished art project rubric
. right now on top of that is a flower pot or air conditioner
Oh there's another backpack
Remember when I was in my twenties and like everything I own fit in a couple of suitcases I was light
Agile free
What now
Tupperware
Bucket
Full of paint
Charcoal infused fabric
I have so much of this stuff at least you don't have
A closet in which
Shoes replicate
Themselves over and over again
And you don't want to complain and feel very lucky to have all these possession but
Sometimes it's a pile up starts to feel like
A bird it doesn't that feels like a bird like I feel like I'm going down the sound and it wrote just getting bigger
Dumber
Slower
Bigger and Dumber
There are definitely
Surprises
But then I talk to science writer Carl Zimmer and he made me feel a little bit better about all the extra
Junk
In my closet
In myself
Literally none of us would be here
If not for that one gene
Because he says there's one little bit of DNA that
Climbed out of the junk closet
And made all of us
What what is it
Well you've actually heard about it before
Really special about mammals is that
Female mammal
Placental mammal
Carrie young around inside
David quammen told us about it in a little while ago called infective heredity and it's basically this
Gene that makes a protein
Which helps makes himself
Elsie's very special layers of cells in placenta
Cells that let it
Grab onto
The mother's uterus and pull nutrients in to feed
The embryo has nutrients
In
It protects the fetus from the mother's immune system
Now when we talk to David about it and how did we get that good idea
We got that good idea from a virus
We should have a maze that this Gene had come from a virus
But what I learned from Carla is that this little Jean sat in the junk closet of our DNA for millions of
Years
Doing nothing making little copies of
It's not
Keeping me at all
Until suddenly millions of years later there's a mutation and that little useless
Strip of DNA got repurpose
Co-opted it
It took on a new job
For us
That's amazing
And now we evolve a dependence on it so that we have to have
BS
About it
Big boxes
A picture frame
Guitar case
That's the motto of this room is like
You never know
Whatever the hell this is
What is this
The peace of God
Traffic
Where's the traffic
Do we bring it back
Pennsylvania
What's in that extra room
I know this feeling I know this feeling completely what's that like rummaging around for this don't like to let things go because I thought
I think that they will always bounce back it's not like I just left in placental Revival at some point
The bike
I have tight pants that I waiting for me to get skinnier
Sitting in the corner of the street about
Optimism better than the way you carry
Is actually one day going to come back and make you light and Airy and beautiful
That is a perfect Segway to our next question Robert that's
Which is it which is itself a imbued with the spirit of optimism hope and Reconciliation and it's very dark
Crowded and ugly place yes
Hi karta hai
Hello cover
Hi guys how are you calling us from
But I'm in the studio at wunc in Chapel Hill
The flick Broadway
Yes in a territory which usually s choose it
Oh in a what are you
Talking about your fervent hatred
Top American songs
I thought we were talking about the subway noise
This has nothing to do with me
It has a little to do with Broadway
Carter what is it maybe you should
Did this Begin by
Framing the question
The Deep mystery
A short
The Deep Mysteries around this sound that I've been here
Hearing in the subway
Since I was a younger person probably since I was in Middle
School
To sound that you hear when you're standing on the platform
And the train is just about to leave the station
And
And you sure these three pure Hi-Tone
Yeah that's annoying oh my God. That is the New York sound yeah it's a very New York
Sound
And
If you're a fan of musicals
You can only hear that sound as one thing
That's totally unmistakable as the opening notes to like the most
Famous song in West Side Story
Somewhere
Pretty sure that it
Truck music
First few times that I heard it
Die die die.
There's a place for us and we just as soon as I heard it
In the course of reporting this story I talked to a bunch of different New Yorkers my name is Julie town I'm a
Writer and director for all curious about this sound is it supposed to be West Side Story is that intentional
Ways to look around the subway car and wonder
You guys
Did you notice that that sounded just like somewhere from West Side Story. I almost wanted to stand up and make
I got a feeling
That's Jamie Bernstein
Her dad is Leonard Bernstein who wrote the music for West Side Story
I've talked to my brother and sister about it a lot
All kinds of
No friends
We just randomly
Email me
You noticed
Map of subway plays the opening notes
YouTube somewhere like people were really not
How to sing it around New York
Okay so
The question is there's a sound in the subway
Right
There's a sound in the subway
Where does it originate
From and is there anything
Interesting and beautiful about
Why it exists
That's my question
And do you have any I guess what makes that sound
Is it the train that is singing this to me or is it the steel rails under the train that's what I thought it was
I thought maybe it was it was you listening
Actually
I thought it was a train coming
Rounding the
The corner as its
Coming in
To the platform
It's scraping its side against the incoming think
And that's creating a
Squeal
It just so happened to always hit that pitch
No
But that's not it
This isn't
Did you solve the mystery
Well
Just going to have to listen and find out
Okay
So sarkari the blizzard been helping me
Make a call to the MTA
And they told us
That we were supposed to hop on a train a train and go way uptown
To this warehouse this big train Warehouse
We were just told to find a guy named Sheldon
Hello
Car hits
Show me this engineer who works for the MTA he's been there like 13 years
And who's really excited
It took us into this massive
Train repair room oh my goodness
And there were
All of these
Subway cars up on the lift
Wow and they just kind of look like these like empty shells of train cars
We're walking into the electronic component shop
And then Sheldon pulled us into this room off to the side through these sort of
Heavy doors electric electric control
Houston by here so are you bringing us here because
Part of what
We're interested in has to do with an electric component
He took us over to a corner
The sun is generated by Beach
Any pointed down at this
Rectangular
Piece of metal
The size of a suitcase
Call Face mods
Chris Maggio wine caffe
H change DC to 3-phase
What is the sing this is the part of the train
Honestly was a little hard to know because he just launched right into like engineering language
Back to the Future
But yes
It's part of the train
It's a little box
That sits next to the motor
And from here on out
I would like for
Be referred to
As the singing box
But as for
Wyatt sings the song
Comes from
To explain to you why it has the sound
Sheldon Cana Punta
I'm so
We had to reach out to someone for some help
Oh yeah I could tell you
Absolutely sorry and I called up
Jeff hackner
Patrick professorville
Electrical Computer Engineering at Cooper Union
Where I fought for 25 years
Who works at the end
NTA and they referred to as a legend in
Transit Circle
I'm not sure I'm not sure who said that and
How much they had to drink when they said that but
But
I've been involved for many years
And Jeff broke down the
The singing box for us like this
You started by telling us how the Box even got into the trance to begin with
Stand clear of the closing doors
So what happened is about the year 2000
Thousand around the time America was obsessed with
Computer bugs go bald
Stolen elections
Decided
They needed to radically redesign the cars
Bente was like we need a massive upgrade
So they brought in all of these new train cars or 142s
Call them the new tech train new technology train
It was going to be a whole new era
These trains were going to be more energy efficient
But
One big problem
The newer train
Those require alternating current
The system is a direct current system
The third rail is direct current
In other words
There's a power mismatch
The new trains run on
AC power
The subway system could only provide
DC power
Wait they brought in trains
It ran on the wrong kind of power
Yes
When was AC when was DC
What exactly is the difference between AC and DC again
It's all based on the flow of invisible electricity when you have BC
Power of the fluids long smooth but steady like a straight line with a C
Play pulsing kind of
Find weight of a sinusoidal wave
The same shape that governs
The tides
The phase of the moon
The angle of the Sun
Someone is smooth and what is Anjali
Exact
Play an AC and DC don't play well together definitely not
And they knew this when they introduce the new cars
Yeah they knew
The tracks have been
Providing.
DC power for like
96 years so they weren't going to remake the
The tracks cuz then you'd have to shut down
The whole Subway for years
But they needed to use
AC for these new cars because there was so much more energy
Efficient and so
It was a disconnect
The sharks in the
The Jets anyways MTA had to figure out a way to take this kind of electricity
And turn it into this
Not interested
The song is General where the singing box comes in threes module 8 strange DC
To a safe place
The box of Sheldon showed us
That's what translates the electricity from one kinds the other
And basically what these boxes do
Is that when the train is cruising along
Drawing and DC power from the third rail
Power goes into that little box in the engine and inside that box
Are these little transistors as switches
Like like light switches
The switches go on and off on and off on and off really fast and in the process take that DC current
And I guess you could say like chop it up
Where does the sound come in
Okay so this is the part
That I don't
Fully
In my soul understand
But it's Jeff explained it to us
Flow of current in and out of these devices
Creates mechanical stresses within them
When you feed electricity into the box
The transistors on the inside of the box
Any inductors in the various things
It gets sort of Jaws
And when they do but act like little loudspeakers
They're not designed as loud speakers
But any of these devices when you flow alternating current flow through them will have
Some tone
Admitted
And it's the current interacting with these like physical parts
Yeah that's what's making the sound
Okay then a bunch of very complicated stuff happy
But all you really need to know is that
When you run current through the box
The stuff on the inside of the Box gets stress
Vibrate
I guess
And that creates
High-pitched whining sound
The changes
Pitch depending on
And that's
Kind of the key to the melody
The transistors chop up the electricity at different rates
Depending on how fast the train is
It's going
And the train has
3 gears
Well you can think of them like gears
Gear one is when
It starts out
Twin sisters are doing their thing and this is the sound that comes out
I meant the train shift to a higher gear as it accelerates and then this is the sound that comes out
And then is a train settles into a Groove the transistors slow and then this is
Sound that comes out
Which gives you that Melody
And now we get to the real Quest
Sandwiches
Is that a fluke
Or could that Melody be intention
So
We asked Sheldon from the MTA
Do you think that those
Notes are like
Just
Coincidence like that's just the sound that it makes or like could they have been select
No it's not
It's not on purpose to keep
To like to hear that song
It's not to let us hear West Side Story in the subway
But then we talked to Jeff hackner
He told us
The when you're designing a system like
That singing box with the three gears
Each gear
Does have its own settings
Frequency of electricity
And if you're the engineer you're setting that
For each of the three gears
And
You're picking a frequency
That
Is
Knocking overheat the equipment
And at the same time is
Is fast enough
That it's going to average out to this nice smooth sine wave
I think it's interesting that you use the word
Kik
What does a part of your kids
Conspiracy Theory
That that that somebody design these
3 notes
Guess what
What I want to know is
Whether or not
Possible to
To have that kind
Control
Choose the frequency
Yes
Engineer codes
Say I could pick a frequency between 1500
I'm going to
Pick a DA in the 6th octave because I think that's funny
What so that is totally possible or because you have a little bit of wiggle room within the design
Interested
So he sang
Possible
But the engineer who designed the singing box
Set the gears at
At just the right frequency
He's to make just the right size
So what you saying
Yes
Did you find
The person who made the design choice
Well you know we made a lot of calls
But
Yeah we totally didn't Carter can you hear this high
Yes hello can you hear me
Yeah of course sorry my minutes to track down this
My name is Matthew Vanessa Tavares
French name
We found him in Montreal my friends call me Madison my enemies call me mats
Just go from Matt and he works for this Canadian manufacturer
Which is the original equipment manufacturer for the so-called
R142
These days he's the head of Vehicle Arkansas
Actor for all the different kinds of subway trains that Bombardier make
What so he is the guy one of the guys
Yeah back in about 2000 time
I was young and cocky design engineer
And for propulsion and breaking
Matt told us he was part of the team that designs that are 142 and all the stuff that goes in
Since I got all the equipment setup including the motors
Single aspect of the design
Including the singing box
And when we asked him about the sound
This is a very distinct sound that everybody talks
Yeah I'm not only that he's a Musician musician way before I was an engineer
Enough in a couple of hours I'm going to have to leave you if you're not bored to death by your story
To practice with with a band were giving a concert in a couple of days in Montreal
What's your van then what are you play actually replace very
Quirky
Bizarre funny
French song that you would not understand but
Dirt bike funny
Home visits
His band
Playing ACDC
In French
AC DC
Very appropriate and some of the other stuff is
Very musical theater e
Which made us think what is this West Side Story stuff was intentional
Do you have this musician turned engineer slipping in a little Easter egg
A little gift
All the New Yorkers
The ride the subway every single day
And in fact Matthew told us that after the Subways were unveiled
People began to notice
Sound
Even wrote a white page
Paper
Where he came clean
And here's a spoiler out of
The punch
Of this white paper was
Choice of notes is a
Pure coincidence
I know II Des is this is this is a this is really
Spoiling your shirt
I'm totally sure
So they did choose the notes
But not for any musical reason
Write in fact
Just a sort of
Twist the knife a little bit
She told us the first time I watch
West Side Story was probably
A couple of days ago and found it way too cheesy for me
Yeah what about is it possible some of the other engineers in the room had
You don't know one in that room recognized
Those intervals
I can
Sure you
That I'm on my deathbed
I will continue saying that
No one
At the time really cared or reading you
But even though my fantasy wasn't
Real
I think what is what is real is the way it is received
Gina Anselmo
It's their weather by
Buy incident or
On purpose boat
The way it's received as by all these people who
Are either
Unconsciously or consciously hearing this like
More pleasant melody in the horrible you know
Reaching for the subway
Truth is like
Lovely reminiscent Melody that
That's so many of us are familiar with
And it's
This
Romantic Anthem to reconciling difference
Wait remind me what is the story that they sing in that song Somewhere
When at the end of the play
Tony and Maria
Across the Great values of
Culture index
A love so Supreme
Stay With Me
What's your name
Whatever you want
Just when Tony and Maria
Are finally
Together in Maria's
Does bedroom
Does Jamie Bernstein again and
Is everything around us
Always terrible
Cool stuff is just happened they had the rumble and
They're dealing with all the
Joshua tragedy
I'm trying to
To rise above it
And so they sing this song
Play
And they imagine this place that doesn't yet
Exist for them
They imagined
The song
That that doesn't fact raise them all above the horror in the
Tragedy in the violence
Right it's it's it's
The characters are all about
Reconciling difference in finding this like
Geographical space
It's for like accepting
It's an in finding loving and I don't know it's it's a very
Romantic anthem for these like horrible Subways and such a lovely City
Address to
Meaning of that metal
For the subway platform is this like democratizing space
Is everybody right there
That is the place for all of us
You know nnn
You know just not to belabor the point
But
To belabor the point
There's also
This third level
Hope you know that the generation of the noisettes
Self it's sort of poetic
The noise itself is
Created
Buy something
I think that is reconciling
Old system of wave into a new motor
To be efficient
And something in that in that translation process is creating me
It's like a little West Side Story of electricity
Now a truce
Storyville true story a couple of years after we were using the same technology
Are Ford the Long Island Railroad
The M7
From Long Island
The attraction packages made by Mitsubishi Electronics
And that the guys from Melco Mitsubishi Electronics Corporation I'd figured out that this thing could sing
And the demonstration they always do with their inverter is that the they make it sing
The odd to the Joy you know what man
Wow
Alright well thank you so much the car Hodge and two sarkari for helping Carter producing reports at store
And Temecula for putting the whole thing together and to the folks at NPR's code
That's what you let us work with cash offer story about Samson and Andre Berman and Amy Brown
Yes you say it to them before I say to them
Okay cuz I have the advantage of
I will remember the email address what you will never do
Let's see where this let me do the first part everybody listening to this show
Cuz probably at some point but I have a question to something has entered my head
And I can't get it out cuz I don't know the answer when I want to know the answer
Anime we've been embarrassed to ask
But that embarrassment is no longer a problem just write us here
At Radiolab
Slash hat at
Yes
Ww.w
. org
Racine WI
NYC. You got there eventually if you have the idea
Radiolab app
Wnyc.org
Email addresses when you want to catch some particular Gretchen's Yu-Gi-Oh
Radioactive nyc.org /
Stupid questions oh my God damn we put them all and I don't do that with email address
What's the website website yes I do
Somewhere there's a place for
The internet
If you have a question send it to us Radiolab wnyc.org
Maybe on our next go-round who knows when that will be but we will we will try it
I'm jealous
To play the message press to start of message
Is Ryan Gregory from the University of Guelph
Hi my name is I'm calling
Lisbon Portugal
Cat-cow here to read the credits
Whitney Houston
Radio Lab was created by Jad mrad and
It's produced by Soren wheeler
Diamond teeth
Is alright director of sound design
Who's Alexa
Is executive producer
Bethel Baptist
Tracy hunt
Matt kielty
Robert krulwich
Julia Longoria
Annie McEwen
Melissa O'Donnell
Kelly Prime
Pat Walters and Molly
With help
Audrey Quinn
Anil Ganesha
Fact Checker Michelle Harris
You're very good night
Thank you
Seek
Simpson
Okay nevermind
And this message