Are you awake
Radio WNYC
This is on the media I'm Bob Garfield Gladstone
Play who you say who you are okay this is radio live on chat
I'm Robert. Jasmine going for westmed forgotten that but he's here again
So glad to be back and today today we are featuring are you just heard from down the hall
Call at on the media
The part 3 of our series
Busted America's poverty because a little while back
Brooklyn style she put together a wonderful set of Story 5 and all I believe about poverty in the United States
It's pretty
Pretty amazing series and we figure
Part of what we should do here always is present not just our work but great work that's happening around us
So we decided to bring Brooke
Into our studio hello
Nice to see you in our territory to talk about what she found in to play a spa
Parts of the series
I have to say that except for my comic book
Which tells you a lot
This it was the hardest thing I've ever done professionally
Really you know it's breaking down a ridiculously complex story into little
Yeah yeah components and then putting it through the on the media Play-Doh extruder so they came out media shape
And the thing is is
What we do what on the media is we
Examine the
Prevailing narrative and use those as a way to discuss the reality
I forever be a beggar if you haven't heard on the media you definitely need to listen to
Non-immediate
Wired listening
These days these days
But in this series what Brook
Does is C sort of
Goes episode-by-episode in examines
One by one that does a big
Media myths when it comes to Poverty you know like that
In 1 episodes.
You know the myth of laziness
Poor people art
Just lazy and another episode she tackles the myth of the social safety net and it's only going to catch you when you fall
That's right
The upward Mobility myth
The one that paints America is a nation where
Everyone has an equal chance.
To surmount any obstacle
Dance from Rags to Riches
It's an idea phone on our Shores by a founding father and self born into poverty
Benjamin Franklin
He's the youngest of 10 sons and his sister
Jane is the youngest of Seven Daughters
Benny and Jenny there called when they're little
Your father's a Candle Maker in a soap boiler historian Jill Lepore author of Book of Ages the life
Opinions of Jane Franklin
Rights that Jenny and Benny Ark
Quotes he teaches her to read they spend their childhood making soap and dipping candles
Benjamin is an apprentice to his brother who's a printer
And when he's 16 or 17 year runs away to Philadelphia
Sofia and he eventually opens up his own printing
And he does so well that Franklin actually manufactures most of the paper
The colonies in the 18th century opens up
Owns
A whole lot of paper mills
Tiffany 18th century is made from Rye
Enzo Franklin in his newspaper the Pennsylvania Gazette
Princess little notices
Bring in your rags
Cash for rags
Then sends them to his mail to people
Franklinville also get the license
In Pennsylvania to print paper currency
The Franklin literally
Turn Rags to Riches
And that's really where the notion comes from
Just think about the phrase Rags to Riches
Comes
From Ben Franklin having opened up a bunch of paper plants and then paper was made from rags
And he printed currency and made tons of money doing that hence
Literally Rags to Riches
That's enriched and of course is
Fiend for his service to the new nation
He recounts his Rags to Riches Saga in a groundbreaking memoir
The only
Stories of lies at that point
Are the stories of the great of kings and princes
Franklin starts out as a popper
Essentially
So he published his autobiography
Be a model
For young men
He wantsto story
Having made his own ride
This is not to slight the man
Helped draft the Declaration of Independence
Invent the lightning rod his
Stove bifocals
The flexible catheter and the glass armonica you're hearing now
And who also launched the first lending library and also the first publicly supported Hospital
Clearly Ben does not want the poor struggling
Starbucks medicine
What is the general principle
He's okay with struggle
He famously wrote
The best way of doing good to the poor is not making them easy in poverty but leading or
Driving them out of it
And that
The less was done for them where they did for them
He's responsible for himself and his great success in his success
Alone and people in his life
Depend on him
On whom he may have depended for support he erased
And that becomes
So much apart of
The lyric tradition of American autobiography
So it's like the original pick yourself up by your bootstraps story is like a Ben Franklin
Dimensions of a piece
One notable absence from Ben's book
Is Sister Jane married off at 6:15 to a Nair do well with a history of mental illness
Cast onto two of their sons
And when most of her 12 children died too young
Jane races there
And their children
Children
Her whole life is constantly trying to Scrabble together
Some kind of living by taking in boarders taking in laundry
Making the family soap
Pop anything in Remembering how important that story is to our sense of
The American past is
Benjamin Franklin sister
Indoors the Fate
Almost
Everybody else in the 18th century does she remains in the station to which she's born and she writes with love to Ben
Epsom impediments
Are just too hard to break
Through and that's far too much
Potentialist
Squandered
Through an accident of birth
And that's the story of Jane Franklin pushes His Brilliant woman
Struggling you know gif
Figure out how to get firewood
For her many many many many children taken care of Franklin's parents him he abandoned who are sick and destitute in their old age
He comes to Boston anorexic giant Monument to their memory that really just celebrates him and his generosity
Did the historical record is asymmetrical we know so much more
About the people who thrive
And so little about the
The people who don't
You really have to think hard
What is a story tell me what is it not telling what is Franklin's RV tell me what is it not tummy
Who's missing here
I love that part by the way I did too but it occurred to me that the myth
Activism
The story that Ben Franklin told about being an American Boy
Annabelle
The upward potential of that
Or if you started poor
Butt shot
You couldn't make your voice at the top end
That story is still
Pruitt in many people's minds and it started with Ben Franklin but that's exact
Play the point we're making in the shower
Ever since the self-made man has been the Avatar of the American Spirit
Especially in politics
Starting with Old Hickory Andrew Jackson right up to Hillary Clinton's fighting her draped making dad
And Donald Trump claiming he grew his fortune from nothing
But up
Small multi-million dollar loan from his father
Likewise the 2004 election feature Dick Gephardt son of a milk truck driver John Edwards
Son of a mill worker
And Barack Obama
Son of a goat herder
Reading Jon Stewart to ask Daily Show senior political analyst Stephen Colbert
Thick does it ring Halo
If everyone
Trumpets this
Bootstrap
Story
Wow
That's pretty cynical John
I for one connected with what they were saying
Then again I myself
I'm from Humble Origins
My father was a poor Virginia turd Miner
I'm sorry
Reminder John that's why I believe in the promise of America
Son of a turd Miner from one day leave those worthless text behind while still using their store
Enhance my own credibility
In terms of the idea of the American idea of upward Mobility the bootstraps myth
Clearly it happens enough
So that it persists
But what what is the case you would make happen enough to make it
More likely to be in America than to be in the Philippines or in Argentina or
Mexico or is there some kind of analysis that says how many people
Born into a certain
Social place
End up
Moving up like how many what percentage of Americans
Throughout the course of their life
Actually do better
Well
The way that you measure this generally
Is how many people go from the bottom of the fifth
Income bracket
To the top
I'm from America on the average is about
7 and a half percent
That's
If you are
Is it really sounds low to me
It really
I would imagine it I was hoping for sugar from the bottom to the very top why is that in Canada
Lights that nearly and in Denmark better and less
So we decided to look at the numbers of hard numbers
Denmark is 11.7 it's much better than America is at 13.4 which is
Roughly double
You know there's a bunch of countries all across Europe that do better than we do so you know
When it comes to the basic measure of upward Mobility
Not only are we not unique
Resort at the bottom of the pile when measured against them other countries while you sure yeah
Crucial thing to remember is that even within the US your chances of moving up there he's
Subway from one place to another there's a
Famous researcher named Roth
Chatty at Stanford
And he showed that in some regions of the country your chances of moving up
A really good the best in the world
Places like
San Jose San Francisco Seattle
Salt Lake City to San Jose 12.9% San Francisco 12.2 dc11
Seattle 10.9 saltlake 10.8 when you get to
Columbus or 9 Atlanta Milwaukee Charlotte Four Points
4 in Memphis
It's closer to 3% this is the percentage
Of people who are able to sort of move on up
Yeah it sounds like the bootstraps myth
Is pretty much not there except if you like born in San Jose
Place like that
Yeah so that just shows that
Your likelihood of moving up
Is based on where you are even more than Who You Are
Let's listen to more of that story Teddy the worst-performing neighborhood sarkar later
Did with segregation income inequality
Single parent families
Poor schools and lack of social cohesion
These neighborhoods
Are very often black
And overlooked when official set budget priorities
Teddy says that government
Can effectively begin to Boost mobility
By investing in and fixing those neighborhood
Meanwhile I can do a better job of moving families
Especially with young kids
I would have some
25% of the Gap Band Yearning between blacks and whites
Is driven simply by the fact that blacks
Tend to grow up in neighborhoods that are much worse on average
Cny
The government already spends more than 20 billion dollars annually
On housing vouchers calculated to enable poor families to rent in better areas
But they can take years
Even decades
To get
And when they get them Most states allowed landlords to refuse vouchers and they often do
Sobeys families wind up where they started
Paying a Savvy slumlord much more for much less
Because there's no place else for them to go
In 1863
The Negro was told that he was free as a result of
The Emancipation Proclamation being signed by Abraham Lincoln
He was not given any land
To make that
Freedom meaningful
Martin Luther King at the National Cathedral in Washington 1968
It was something like keeping a person in prison for the number of years and
Suddenly discovering that
That person is not
Guilty of the crime for which he was convicted
Just go up to him and say now you are free
But you don't give him any bus fare to get to town
And the irony of it all is that at the
Same time
The nation
Failed to do anything from the Black
It was giving away millions of acres of land in the West in the middle
Which meant that it was willing to undergo that's right persons from Europe with an economic floor but not only did it give the land
Built
Land
Grant colleges
Teach them how to farm
It provided
Low interest rate so that they could mechanize out forms
And to this day
Thousands of these bad persons are receiving
Millions of dollars in federal subsidies every year not the phone
American soil from the vet people
Tell Negros that they must lift themselves
By their own bootstraps
It's all right to tell a man to lift himself by his own bootstraps
But it is a cruel jest
Say to a bootless man
That he ought to lift himself
By his own bootstraps
In 2003 the National Bureau of economic research published a famous study
In which researchers responded to help wanted ads
Clerical administrative in customer service jobs in the Chicago Tribune and the Boston Globe
Applied with names associated with whites like
Greg or blacks like Jamal
Based on naming data for babies born in the late 70s
The white names produced 50% more call back
A white name yielded as many more callbacks is an extra eight years of experience on a black resume
In another study based in New York whites with criminal records
Got more callbacks than blacks with clean records
So much for bootstrap
EB White Once Road
Luck is not something you can mention in the presence of self-made men
Indeed surveys find that
Wealthy people are far more likely than poor ones to say hard work is what leads to
6s and 2 credit hard work above all
So they're happy lot in life
Of course hard work and talent matter
But they offer no guarantee
Has Robert Frank
Professor of Economics at Cornell University observes in 6s
And luck
Good fortune and the myth of meritocracy
He said success may also hang on the month or location of your birth not to mention the wealth you're born with
But when we compose our personal narratives
Those things recede into the Mist
As Frank found when confronted by Fox News host
Stuart Varney
You are lucky
That's outrageous
That is outrageous
What about the risk
You know what risk is involved in Coming To America with absolutely nothing
You know what risk
With a British accent
A total Foreigner you know what
I do
Is it luck
You hold a tenured position
Yes
I'm insulted
If you come to America
How do you play by the rules
You work hard
You get discipline inside yourself
That's not true
I got in my cab leaving the studio and of course only then that I
Think about all of it
Fat pictures he'd thrown my way that I've completely failed even to swing it but I'm speaking sometime later at New York
University
He said he'd come to the USA with nothing
He had a degree from the London School of Economics that's that's coming to the US with nothing
He had
Somehow overcome the handicap of working in America with a British accent
Americans love British accents
He said he took risks
What what's a risk I looked it up
Merriam Webster
Risk is the possibility that something bad or unpleasant
Such as an injury or loss what happened
Who took risks
Any 6 seater
Well that means by definition that he was lucky
.
But I didn't have the wit to point that out
What does it matter pointing it out
Well as Frank notes
Several studies suggest
That when we
Feel gratitude
Play more generous to strangers
When were reminded of Lux importance
We are more likely to plow some of our own Good Fortune back into the common good
We under play lock
Because we can recall our own
Struggles far better than the faithful but fuzzy role of chance
And because the very idea corrodes our face and free will
But mostly because
Like Penny Franklin
But deeply invested in our own autobiographies
Take me
My parents went broke a couple of times once we had to put all our stuff out on the lawn to be auctioned
I went to college almost totally on 8th
But I always knew
I was going to college
Even on nights when supper with leftover Kentucky Fried Chicken I brought home from the job
I knew
This was temporary
So I can say wow I'm really self-made
But I know I'm not
Sure
I always kind of knew I was lucky
But not into working on this
Series
Did I really begin to understand what that meant
Hard work is
Real
Bootstraps are bunk
And social Mobility
Unless a nation chooses to build the infrastructure the roads
On which a person can move upward
The pretty much can't get there from here
Where to take a quick break and when we come back we'll take a look at another myth about poverty
Brooke Gladstone and
You'll
Hear an interview that just
When I heard it
Like stop me cold
This is Sam calling from Denver Colorado Radiolab
Supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloan at www. Sloan. Org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers were looking for stories
About what we're calling tiny moments of Brilliance basically I want to hear about those times when I
So did something
It just means you lean back and say whoa how did they do that maybe it was the moment that I can
Did you been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons and you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed they're writing music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the specific moments where a kid does something super smart
It doesn't have anything to do with the test if you have a story
T-shirt with us
Go to radiolab.org brilliance
Record a short audio message for us
And that's radiolab.org brilliance
Thank you so much
Hey back I'm Jedi Cam'ron I'm Robert krulwich says Radiolab
Series of stories that
They broadcast called busted America's poverty myths already going through the upward Mobility but
This next one
It gets a little more
Personal
Let me just say that
What is the most important
Hearts
This whole Enterprise for me
Was to let people
Tell their stories
Bully as they could
In their own voice
And I
And that was the case was Margaret Smith
She started doing with me and end in chat in chapter 4
Yes can you can you set up
Set up the conceit
So we did the myth of bootstraps
And this was the myth of the safety-net
That's what this was about
And I'm Brooke Gladstone busted America's poverty myths
This time it's limited America's social safety net so imperfect still is able to catch p
People eating conomic freefall before they slam the pavement but there's no way to confront that
Without conveying how that
So prepare yourself for the narrative equivalent of black
And I talked about
How
Many many people only have
$1,000 or less in savings
And that a majority of people
Would not be able to
Save themselves from
A relatively inexpensive from her point of view
Short-term emergency
I'm so what I was trying to do in that episode
Was to describe the way that people put their lives together
And how fragile
Those arrangements are
And Margaret was an example of that
So get ready for that
Boom Splat I mentioned at the top
The sound of someone
Crashing through the safety net
How are you
We're at the YWCA Family Center order Lyon
Columbus Ohio
My name is Margaret
And I have
6 children
5 boys and 1 Girl
The reason I ended up in the shelter
Because
My son was shot outside of our house
P17
He knew the girl
He's the dater and he didn't want to be with her anymore
She came with some guys
And they shot my son six times
He like Mom help me I feel like I'm about to die
So you're not going to die on me today
All the kids were sitting in a tree watching
I'm seeing this Plus
Good shot of his neck
Hog rider blanket put around his neck
Put a mod in it
I told my 15 year old daughter I need you
To put your hands right here and apply pressure to his neck
11 year old went to get a pillow off the couch to elevate his head
He says sissy keep talkin to me talk to me talk to me
Timeless finally got there
As he is in ICU fighting for his life
I go home three days later go to the landlord to pay the rent
She tells me did you get the eviction notice
I said what eviction notice
She said we have a three-day eviction notice
So I called the attorney that was over the property
My day was made a mutual decision
To leave in 45 days by let him know that I can't leave in 3
Because I'm still at the hospital
You had violated your agreement in their view because you had committed a crime at once
For lack of
Payment it was
Because
A crime was committed on the property
But it wasn't
The people that live in the property that committed the crime
He was a victim
So I ended up in the shelter
I lost my job
I worked at a customer rep
Southern Connecticut Gas gas pump
They could hold my position they had me go through Aetna
To see if they will get it approved
Under Disability
They denied it
Sunny can't hold my position
44 week I need to take care of my son
Set a timer knighted me
So not only did I lose my place
I lost my job and I ended in the shelter
And not only that
All my kids are spread out in different places
My son is still healing
He still had nurses
Physical therapy
It is just breaking my heart that I can't be with my kids
Where are they
My son is at my mother's
My daughter is at our aunts
And my other son is out of cousin
And I have the two youngest ones with me here
It's just been a nightmare
I've been trying to find places
But everytime I go to the place
3x
Well how are you going to
Continue to pay the rent
I'm going to go to work
And pay the rent like any other normal person
Badoo
Just right now
My main focus is getting my children
Back together
In the house
Me and my family were victims
Apocrine
So why should we
Lose everything
Because of what someone else
Created for us
It's not fair
Tell me about you
My oldest son
That's why I'm he's a diabetic
Very good kid
He helps me with the children while I work
My other son
Raymond cook
Is the one that was shot he was 17 years old
Every morning
He would
Get the kids off the school which is down the street from my house
And then he will go to school
So by him being in the hospital
That
I didn't have the kids in daycare
Because I feel like I had enough older kids
We can put together
And make this work
So everything is just
Screwed up
My 15-year is my daughter
Tiara cook
Straight Outta roasted in
Tigers basketball
She wants to be a lawyer when she grow up she's trying to get a scholarship
11 year old
What time is the alarm
He
Is so supportive
When I was at the shelter in my room
I just broke down crying
He grabbed me
Mommy is going to be okay
Can you put my big head on his little shoulder
UC with some skilful juggling should maintain a stable if fragile life for her family
But lethal ex-girlfriend
Sweating like a hurricane in
Blew it apart
Margaret has health insurance
The kids and food stamps
But no money
There's a lifetime limit on cash assistance of 60 months and Margaret had used it all up
Many years ago when her father died she required long treatment
To overcome a suicidal depression
Later she had diverticulitis
And she has a mass in her throat surgically removed
Then a hip replace
She needs another one but obviously that will have to wait
Now she has to get all those balls back up in the air I got to get my kids out of here
We done came a long way
You from the projects
Semi moving living on my own
The last 7 years
Paying regular rent
I didn't ever want to go back
The projects
My needs are all my life
That project will destroy
Especially young men
You don't have a chance
You got people that's in the gang over here it'll swallow your kids up
I had to go
It came to my house
So
It's what I say
Even people that got money and
Power
Don't walk around with your head up high
Some people look at you like all your beneath me your this year that but I'm still a person I have a heart I haven't been since I might not have got there
Forget
But I'm working towards it
You treat people
How you want to be treated rather they have a dollar in my pocket a penny or you
A millionaire
Because
You never know when it's your time
Anything can happen
You might be on top of the world tomorrow but it can end for you to next day
And you will go through poverty what we going through
James Baldwin once observed
Anyone who's ever struggled with poverty knows how it's
How extremely expensive it is to be poor
If you're poor you pay more for public transit
Because you can't afford a monthly pass
Or you rely on old cars that break down and cost more to fix while paying gas prices that have out
Run your wages
You pay more for car insurance because of where you live
You pay more for rent
And your place is worth
If you're poor you're unlikely to eat healthy meals
Because healthy food costs an average of $45 more a month
Minimum wage
You can't buy any food cheap
Sleep because it cost more in poor neighborhoods
And without spare cash
You can't even save by buying in bulk
You're less likely to have a bank account because of
Soaring fees and penalties
You cash checks at places that take a cut
You also pay a higher percentage of your income in state and local taxes but no rest of us do
And so on
It's Death By A Thousand Cuts and no way to staunch the bleeding
As Baldwin wrote
1 feet have simply been placed on the treadmill forever
Yuan 30 by now and nothing you have done that's helped you to escape
The track
What is worse than that
The nothing you have done
And as far as you can tell nothing you can do
Will save
Your son or your daughter
Bonita same disaster
Possibly coming
And
Like I know
I know that people construct their lives in such a way where there is zero margin for error
On some level I think every parent who isn't
Made of money
Lives in that state where
Any moment
Drop everything to go deal with a sick kid or whatever
But this was that
Ordinary experience
Taken to a degree that was
Shocking was truly shocking
That you could see somebody making it and then suddenly they fall and they fall so hard and so quickly
And
For no other reason than they just got black
You know from me
To hear that
FICA so yes the shooting was
Uninvited and unexpected
But
Then comes the eviction
And then comes
The refusal to amend
Or in any way
Spoon the eviction
In the face of what is
Obviously
Well that's because people
Find Lisa saying if there is any police action on your property
You have an instant eviction
I mean it isn't instant it's 3 weeks and they won't
Stop it they won't stop at for anybody I've heard this
Over and over again that
Wasn't just because of some recalcitrant landlord
That
Is
What goes on every day
In America
That's brookledge them from
On the media what we played you was part of a series called busted America's poverty myths produced by mirror Sean
Arma and Eve Claxton edited by Kachi Rogers they produced Series in collaboration with wnet is Chasing the Dream
Dream poverty and opportunity in America are all five episodes of busted if you go to on
Onthemedia.org
Property you can also subscribe on iTunes or wherever
Listen all five of the episodes there
We definitely recommend you do that cuz there's so much more than we were able to get into and it's great
I'm rubber
Thanks for listening
This is Jacob from Dallas Texas Radiolab is produced by J dilla
Beef is our director of sound design Soren wheeler is senior editor Jamie York is our senior producer
That includes Simon Adler Brenna Farrell David Gable Matt kielty Robert krulwich
McEwen Latif Nasser Melissa O'Donnell Ariana
And Molly Webster with help from Tracy hunt naggar fatalii Phoebe Wang and Katie
Ferguson are fact-checker is Michelle Harris