Are you awake
On New York public radio radio W China flight on York
Video downloader
Okay so the
The other day I bet by what we say we are
Radiolab
Okay so the other day storing called listen to the studio
Hahaha
And there was a giant
Human sized rodent sitting in the engineering seat very large rodent was Richard Millard West
Cuz it was a puppet head that we had toured with who is that under that big straighting elastic
Maybe you guys should go
Oh my goodness
Is it
Is this Alan
Oh my God oh my God
Price of the story is the recent storm God
I want to surprise us is it somewhere around now is the 15-year
Crazy to say 15 year anniversary of making radio
15 years I know we have some tape for you guys
Seems like you got to have someone around who knew you when you know okay
So we settled in we didn't really know what's going on and then horn did something truly evil
She's somehow I don't know how probably are could have helped.
Her hands on the very
First
No
This is my nightmare
The very very very had hoped these tapes and that would never surface but she found him
They're on BitTorrent for a second I thought they had disappeared
So happy but then
2002 very first one
God don't start
Please make the CD crash right now
Every radio producer
Has this idealized image in their head
If you out
Maybe you're sitting on the couch
Drinking coffee
Staring out the window
Maybe you're the person who's driving
Pullover
To really concentrate on a story
Whatever the case that image
Radio producers brain
You
The Listener
Why they make
The only thing
We don't get paid much
You look around these heavy recorders in Mike's
New look
Thank you silly
In those headphones I have to wear if it doesn't matter
As long as you are there
Listen to what they make
WNYC is about to embark on Annex
We're calling it The Radiolab
Great documentary radio stories of different sizes
Shapes
Colors
Different places all over the planet from different times even
Mix it all together
Like this
Big group of people and places
But it'll take 2 hours and 59 minutes to go
Puyallup 2 hours and 15 minutes
2 hours 3 hours he was it 3 hours show every week
Every freaking week every week 8 to 11 every Sunday night
Huge
A huge hunk of airtime where no one was list
I'm right here
I'll be your
Curator
Guide Maybe
How about DJ Ave.
Oh really
That's terrible it doesn't work at all
Every moment every moment
Explain like the show is just super different back then
The idea of it back then was to just take all of these documentaries from around the world and smash them together
But would end up happening is it like I would line up three or four things
And I would have liked a 20-minute hole
Which I would start to experiment and that's
Those spots were what the show grew out
What's up so that was in 2002 and then I met you the following spraying
And then we are later the whole year later
I know there's a year worth of that
And by the time I met you back
In New York
You were so sleep-deprived okay so we're a little bit and then we start talking
At the moment
When Robert got involved with someone I'll never
So I was trying to fill one of those 20-minute holes I had done an interview with a memory research
Picture
And it was just one of those
Science interviews. Now we're super familiar with we're like the scientist is using all this latinate words
I couldn't figure out what she was saying but it's
Still seemed interesting
I just couldn't understand it and so Robert and Ellen and I had breakfast one day at kitchenette
Foundation rest
We go to for breakfast every week and we were sitting there and
I was like I got this interview I don't know what to do with about memory and I
Here's what I think she's saying I think she's saying something about how memories are never the same you're always constantly making them and then you just like
Snapped into this
Stingray
Suddenly you're playing this like all these characters
Al and I were like oh my god let's just go into the studio and have him do that you want to hear a little
Taste of the sort of curious what would this is this is one of the ones like we did the memory and forgetting at the podcast
But this is
Free this is before that is over
Earlier doesn't 3 I think
Your list
2 radio
On
Rock radio
Radio
Wa
Jad abumrad this is Radiolab
We're coming up on the Kitty Hawk
Centennial
100th anniversary
First human-powered flight
Couple weeks
And I was looking at the picture today
Now you wearing
The Wright brothers you know the one Orville's on the plane it's just taking off Wilbur is
Is running alongside there
Maya beach the beach
Deserted
Looks really really
Cold
Look at this photo
How much pitcher in the history of
Anyone who's ever been born as Citadel
Thousand times
I couldn't help but be wowed I mean look what they did
They got their crazy box
Into the air
Couple hundred
Feed whatever
Was wasn't
That great a distance but look at us now
Slime
Over the Atlantic
5 hours
$200
We're going to talk about that
And the real question is
How is it we can do all that
And still not understand some very basic things like
Common cold that's the example of how is given
What about memory
What up memory
House of David Feherty
He was a pogo stick I'm going to jump on it 50 times
What about tissues
Let's random way to get it
Play eventually talk about Kitty Hawk or was that just already know
But let's let go a little bit further for this week
Creative
Describe axon begins with a reading from theater director and actor Simon McBurney
You have to literally remake it
Every time every memory
Did you remember
Is differ
Because it is remade in the very present that you remember
Another words
In order to remember
You need
The imagination
Simon McBurney performing a monologue from his play pneumonic
Are the show Studio 360
And with me in the studio to explore these ideas a little further
Is mr. Robert krulwich from ABC News
Robert
You've reported on this right yeah I never actually met Simon
McBurney but that's
Remember something
You need an active imagination is understating it really
Staging a house
Let's just take the situation we're in right now
Okay I'm sitting here in front of you or about what
3 feet apart or something like that
So when you look at me right now
It takes actually the light that's bouncing left my face a tiny bit of
Time to reach your retina
But by the way I arrived upside down and have your brain write me
A little bit of time for the sound of me this sound right now you think
December to travel at 750 miles an hour from edu okay arrested in that ear that you have
That's a travel through those hairs that you got in your ear
That's a turn into electricity and have to go to the
Placing your brain where sound is lie
I'm in touch with me if I would have touch you right now have to travel electrically to your brain that would take a little time
God the smell of suppose I put some licorice in my mouth
The smell of the licorice come out of my mouth
That you would have to
Travel all the way to your nose keep your nose into the place where smells like
I'm in your brain has to take all these parts
And pull them together into this thing that you think is going on right now
Please let me get this straight
You're saying that
At this moment
Yes and this one
Antoine
I hopelessly lost
Some people say that you don't have to live in the moment this is the moment
Fort
It's a memory
Everything
Isn't it
Wow
So what's everyone up under this
Mommy
This one
You say it has already happened before it even had a chance to become this moment but let's say we want to remember it later
What do we do it's interesting what's going to happen
Is you're going to
Take
The touch the sound of smelling everything that's in your brain from that moment with you all sitting lodged in different places
You going to reassemble it pull it back
Together again I use the interesting thing
20 minutes from now
Really hungry
Dim the licorice number the liquid part of the licorice part will somehow Loom a little larger be
Because you want
Itachi susanoo
How you're feeling in the moment that you're remembering has a lot to do with what you remember
Let's just take a simpler phrase like
Jack and Jill went up the hill to fetch
Kapiel of water right
If you want to recollect that
Praise
But suppose you just had a wonderful
Sting
Jill when you think of when you reassemble it
It'll go
Jack and Jill went up the hill
Season see the Jill thing is so
That instead you just confirm extraordinary Haiku you have
Gloriously, spectacular Hill
Can I hear the thing when you reassemble this time
You think
Jack and Jill
What up
See the hell now the healing this has got all the MPN I got it so you're always remembering
Differently each time depending upon this reminds me of
We have any player this
It's amazing to me that at such an early point
The business of
Deconstructing puzzles
Switch I guess a lot of what we did
Took on this very big
Particular quality
This kind of
Razzle Dazzle Of Anything could happen in the next second I don't know who's going to say the next thing
But there's something beautifully organic about it when it's done
So today we're celebrating 15 years
Of making Radiolab coming up after the break we're going to play the first thing they were podcast
It's not something you can get on iTunes
It fell off iTunes a long time ago
Play the first
This is Lisa Kenny calling from San Diego
Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of science
And technology in the modern world more information about Sloan at www.slha.org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help this summer I'm hosting a show
And I request for those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
We're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments
Brilliance
Basically I want to hear about those times when I did something
It just means you bring back and say whoa
Maybe it was the moment that our kids you've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lesson
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of the musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed they're ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the
Specific moments where
Kid does something super smart but it doesn't have anything to do with the test
If you have a story with us
Go to radiolab.org Brilliance and record a short audio mess
Again that's radiolab.org / brilliance
Thank you so much
Ava back
So
The first episode we were podcast literally the first but it was among the first few
With an episode about time
I do remember
Playing it to my wife
I was always scared cuz she's a New York Times Reporter I thought I was to learn to like the company
And she came out of the kitchen in
I really like
Call me if you feel like it
Is one of the one of the early military like maybe this
Are podcast
80 years ago
Probably very few people have heard this
You're listening to radio on New York Public Radio public radio WNYC
You know this music trust me
You heard it your entire life
The reason you can't recognize it now
Because the composer born 1770 intended for this moment the one you're hearing
The last two seconds
Like that
However have you been a whale
Beethoven might have written his Ninth Symphony this way
Changes that for us would take
An instant
Transpire over minutes and a movement
Eyeglass
6 hours
That's a fact what this is
Beethoven's 9th Symphony digitally stretched from its normal 60 some-odd Minutes to last an entire
Day 24 hours
And if you sit for the entire 24-hour duration of the peace as people do from time to time
You realize that this music is not simply slower
The slowness unlocked something in the original
Maybe was there all along we couldn't hear it
Play with the meter music is mostly about me or after all
Music has a different story to tell a secret
Locked up inside the routine change the routine
Making discoveries
That's what we'll do this hour
We'll look at time so closely will discover new things about it
Listen to Radiolab on Jad abumrad my guests tonight for the next hour to help me wrestle with time is the science
Robert krulwich
ABC News Nova and Nightline how are you sir
I'm very well I like this bathing in Beethoven thing you got going on right now
Dropping in on a performance that happened recently in San Francisco
Where people listen to it
The course of an entire day Woodbury
A day
So we're first
Let's begin with the guy who I
I think you'll find that he thinks very deeply about time in fact
In a very gentle kind of way you could say he's
Time obsessed
You heard of the neurologist Oliver Sacks
The man who mistook his wife for a hat
All right
So I was over
How's this is me
Actually over at
Jackie Chan
I don't know where this is rather than I have not experienced
Some years ago in action 1993
When I got a
A message for my
Publisher
Very sad that off
For that 21st birthday
They that Jubilee
Asking if we would like to select
The previous 21 years and white
When I got this message
I thought for why don't I choose 90
Can 72
The first of the
Witches
Very Vivid and important
Xiaomi
Auntie
Was he good witch my mother died
Pocket whistle
In which height
Completed Awakening
And these two events
In some way
I was actually
In the car when I
Tautphaus
I picked it up and I
MacArthur and I was driving
Map to Canada
And I had to take the
What are with me so I
I spoke 1972 allow
And by that time
I thought. Why don't I do 1973 as well
By the time I did you get the Montreal or used
Hope you took about
How about how
Half an hour
By the time I got to the Canadian border
I was up to 1987
Anthem
I didn't pack make an extra Loop
So that I could compete Fitness
However it turned out
Venti
The most recent to us in the late eighties in the 90
I did not
What county have such
PeaceHealth
Memories
And they seem subjectively shorter
Sometime I guess we all know this
Is a very
Plastic thing
And it's like
Glasses and other times
But because Oliver is so inquisitive
Investigator Hartman
He's looked
Inside
I'm beginning when he was
10 11 12
He wanted to get inside
Time
I had to I had to
Lots of boyish interests
And these pre-adolescent Pinterest
So they won't suck a bee sting when I became an adolescent
But one of them was chemical chemistry about
One of them was photography and I had
Dog, cameras
I'm one of the most plants
And in particular
My mother was faithful to her arms and the God was full of
I love the way in which the
The Kill.
Fiddleheads on cruises of films
Would answer
And it was almost as if time was with her
Rolled up inside Amazon
Time itself
Unfold
Connect PC to stay with pets
Take a a day or two
To do this
And I wanted to see it
It made me think of these Christmas things when they're blowing
Lisa
Paper trumpets
Because I'm sold
And so
I set up my camera
On a tripod
And at least in the daytime
Take pictures at night I didn't have a flash then
I took a series of
Pictures every hour or so
Off the phone
And then showed these rapidly
Putting them together in a
And this way then
What
Took a day or two or several hours to happen
What's compressed into several seconds
So the compression of time
Social classes
Fascinated me
If Oliver sex can make a baby Fern unfurl
How about this
Radio producer Tony Schwartz
Can do the same thing
With his baby niece
What Inception sound
Here sped up for your appreciation is Nancy Schwartz
Birthday age 12 in 2 minutes 12 seconds exact
Jack and Jill went up the hill
To fetch a pail of
Jack fell down and broke
Jill came tumbling
Palace Beijing
Can I say to you
Toy Story
How do you say I want a puppy and a whistle
Ocwen
Ella hat
Address
The ballerina cast
That's why it got that way
Santa Claus can't bring his
You can cry
Tony Exum
Lillian house
If you have to make him housebroken
If you mix Valerian in the apartment
Cat describing with a newspaper
Sirius he doesn't do it again
Kick-Ass boat
What do you think of the Russian sending the dog up in the satellite
Well
I Hope You Dance
Get hurt
But if he does I'm sure they'll send up America
School I had to do a report on some place
And I'm doing a report on Hawaii
Android and we're taking notes and doing research
December we're going camping in a
In the month of July this summer I'm
Step for the whole month of July the summer I'm going
To go to Brownies Sleepaway Camp it's all girls
You messed my hair and it's very special for tonight it's just the way I wanted to know page
High top
That's why I like it
I'm taking guitar lesson
That's fun
I take drama lessons at
School that's great
And I've been working on the school newspaper I might be a distraction
Next year
And
I've been discovering boys
You know what that is what's up what you just heard
The parent clock
Apparent
That's kind of cool cuz the kid gets older
You can't
Deny the fact that you must be getting older too when your son has hair on his legs
But this is true this is how the whole world works
It's a it's a everything is a clock I guess
By the way that was Nancy Grows Up in the audio flipbook recorded and arranged by the great radio producer Tony Schwartz
And to Smithsonian folkways recordings
And also to you
Ceramic rollers for joining me today on our program
To talk about
My question
If we got an example of what you just called
Parent clock
You got other kinds of time you don't like like personal time getting out of bed time
Existence really time was measured by its lunch time it's wake up time
Rye trying to Milk The Cow time
Events or task time tasks * how do we get from TASC
And personal time
2 clock
That's interesting
Let's go back
To the 1800's imagine a guy will call him old is Old Town AAA
Zoltan
What time it is
Okay so
Walking to say big B's Tavern
Is that right
Of course it's right however
Instead of going into the tavern Hannigan at the exact same moment
Deutsche bank building
How can I help
3 minutes
Is it right though
Yes it's right at that very same moment suppose instead of going to the top of the bank
He gone to the hotel
Can I help you or you tell me the time
Alex19 pasta
Trophy Tavern
33 past the hour at the hotel 19 pass the bank 3 pass what time
Is it really
In Sandusky at the question the answer is
There was no official time in sendai
What do you mean there's no official time and said there wasn't any known 1850
The government didn't have a Time
Celina Ohio in the 1850s you'd have as many times
As it were clocks in the town
So there was no reason
You think about it to synchronize it if you're clocking like what 4 minutes or 10 minutes different in Sandusky and 1850s
Who cares
Until
The railroad changed every
Once the Wheel Road King is open while to take
I don't know
How about the 303 to
Okay
If you want to take the field. How would he know when it was 303 I see where you're going with that if you went by the Banks
Need a ride
A half hour ahead of time
Can you buy the hotel clock
Chalk for the sake of their business really real roads created railroad time and again putting up clocks are there
Makes sense and because the railroads were so important
The Tavern we have to get its beer deliveries from where
The banks would have to get their cash from the railroad in the hotel
Real-time becomes everybody
So what happened to local
Will local time disappeared
Really yeah it local time means that when it's noon in Sandusky the sun is directly over your head
By 1880
That wasn't true anymore
The real Road
Head instructed Sandusky that from now on
It's noon would be 20 minutes later
So they could fit into the railroad schedule noon over 20 minutes
I put it to you
Sonos series that people fought against the Rebellion are the railroad
Oh there were time Wars and certain towns were part of the town would go to Railroad time but the other part would deter
Permanently stick with what used to be local time at different times in the town
Wow it's almost like as a personal freedom time in a way represents
Your own identity
And they would you want to give up their identity
Money man Sandusky I meant every other Town eventually conform to Railroad time and that is how time became
Standardized
I'm became Zone
Time to Kill
Clock reference
You ask somebody what time is it they don't say you know it's bedtime or just lunch
I mean look up with this
A look at the clock and the railroad today
Moana lost every 60 Minutes every 12 hours
Download lots of Pi
There's an interesting connection to explore here
And it has to do with horses
Horses
Dimension railroad companies it just so happens that the owner of the biggest railroad company Leland Stanford
I don't think
Who's really into speed
Any old really fast horse
The horse's name is oxygen
Accident
I know I know
Story goes this horse
Subject of a gentleman's bet
It's it's a myth
Stanford so far as we know it was not a betting man that's Rebecca solnit she would know she wrote a book about this called River of shadow
The focus of her book
If the solver of the back
It was an argument
There's no evidence that there was money on it
Mini cases argument on Stamford news Railroad by sending around the following question
When a horse gallops do all four of its feet leave the ground and wants to be thinking
I don't know it's not a question I'm afraid we ever ask anyone but at the time it was a big question cuz they had no way of knowing
Smooth faster than eyeballs conceit to Leland Stanford wanted to prove it a horse at all four feet off the ground at one time
And he was recommended to Troy Bridge
As a photographer to capture this along comes eadweard muybridge
She can take a picture of the horse at exactly the right instant
See whether I'll for fever off the ground and saw the bet. The problem
Cameras in those days were very
Slow or fast exposure would be maybe a second or several seconds was going to push for
Photography to suddenly be able to capture Motion in a 500 of a second otherwise you just got blur
Black
Imagine that first step out of the world of the blur
When Richard stretch the wire across the racetrack
Attached it to the shutter mechanism on its camera oxygen the horse gallops by
Trip The Wire
Freezes the horse
Mid gallop
Steals him right out of the flow of time
Doesn't just take one photo he takes
See Place 24 cameras in a line one after the other with 24 tripwires stretching across the racetrack
Worship everyone
24 Frozen unblurry
Horses so what it what are they seeing
All the pictures from the series of a horse running in some of those photos
Show dachshund yes with all four feet off the ground
So the camera here
Unlock
A secret is it lets us see something you could never see before because this camera
Essentially stops
Exactly
Meanwhile says Rebecca mortgage
Became fascinated with learning more secrets of time
Secrets locked inside basic human movements a splash
Walk of pirouette
Boy fidget photographs Rushing Water he was obsessed with water and his landscape pictures
So obsessively has people pour water splash water pour water over themselves poor pictures of water
Pour water into glasses
Splash water out of basins
Bathing water
And you can see all these droplets Frozen in mid-air
This one particular photo Robert work
You see a sheet of water
Spend it in the air
Hovering over the splash
Metallica ghost
Take all those frozen moments in line and one after the other and play them back and you've got
Flow again
Albeit artificial flow
Recall movies
Movies
But the next time you're feeling stressed out you said yourself I'm stressed I need to go to a movie to relax
You should know
The technology that made the movies is exactly the same which sped up the pace of Modern Life with stress you out which led you to go to
When the first wave movies were used with the film Factory workers doing repetitive tasks
Find out how to make this task more efficient
Maybe too slowly is this the right way
Dumb and slow them down and then use that to teach
Everyone else
And then when World War II came
This was not just now in the cause of efficiency this was a life-or-death matter cuz this is how you beat Nazi
All the scientific devices of chronology a machine Manufacturing
Time and all hands must be
There's a whole nother way to think about
Time can be a weapon in
It can be
The most
And natural
Thing in the world I learned about this from a book by Jay Griffiths
Called sideways
Let me just
Bottega stop here at the clock
Even though you don't like
But there's too many cool Cox in your box
There's a spice
Yes
Sucks that you can see when it's really dark and if you can see that he just waking up at 2:35 and you really didn't want to wake up
Sprinkles for a long time
In the night you don't have a way of seeing what time is inside somebody invented
Spice Coke so you can
Castaway
Tonight's
So that would be maybe kind of
Cinnamon for about 1
Contemporary fit
Figured you sitting there in bed
And you stiff the time
Tweaked Isis
The clock of birds this is the political
Assassin bugs like the you can fly but in the hooded butch but
When they sing in the morning
The children
Totally understand that.
Gallatin Valley View dinner because of the house
When they said sing that lace afternoon pools
That's a signal for children
Go back home
DeForest in central Highlands in Papua New Guinea
Is the auction that is very sorry
Difficult place to be in won't start and it said children would need to know
At what time to start heading for him
Now how about it 1751
And Carl Linnaeus famous
Catalog categorizer of everything that you can see
You can see by the blooming of differ
Flowers what time it was
Some kind of something that blooms in the morning and then folds up like a morning glory
Would be there in the morning and then in the evening an evening primrose
Yes you're all plants that open for an hour or two and then close
So you're walking by
And you see a blush of what's a pink then you know it must be the morning or just a blush or probably must be lunch time or whatever
Yes exactly exactly
Very good Garden
Be able to do that yes isn't it isn't it unconnected
Andaman forest in the Andaman Islands in the Indian Ocean
People have a scent calendar
Which I find most beautiful I did because some what it was is a way of kind of describing the months
By the sense of certain fruits and flowers
Timer
What time is everywhere in nights at what I wouldn't want to things I want to do with the whole book was to say you know we think of time things to do
In fact for most of the world's most of History
Time has been absolutely embedded in nature and some beautiful eyes
Thanks Robert will be back in a moment
You're listening to Radiolab on New York Public Radio
So that was a butt chug
Of the first thing we ever podcast was a show about time
And
It's in honor of our 50th birthday
Because there's a itsfunneh Robert like there's
We just looked at the radar RSS
WeChat
It's a I don't know what it stands for it it's the thing that like feet iTunes
When you go on iTunes and you see all the episodes
Suzhou to see
What was there
And other some limit that's that iTunes places in the number of items that you can have in the feed
And they're like a hundred fifty or something and we realize like
150 early episodes have fallen off
The feed a really yeah that way we were a backless like at random house that would be like Hemingway and fit
Fitzgerald have fallen under the floors exactly select
Huge number of old episodes of falling off
And I start looking at that list and on that list or some episodes that are weirdly relevant now
A whole bunch that are just completely not relevant
And I was like I think
I want to pull some of those back into the flow
Because it'll give us a chance to like sort of just
Reframe them and Rick think about them and update them and sometimes
Science gets old and needs to be updated but sometimes gets refreshed by something is happening in the real way
World's yeah
So what the plan would be is Maybe
You know in the coming months we would go
We back for us
Just like 1413
1512 years back
And resurrect things and throw them out and see who wants to take a smack at them now
And what it is things have changed
Yeah it was more interesting
Early wrong now
In a fascinating way
Advantage of getting all of this
You can ask
You can play with your memories
Exactly
And not be a rabbit
There you go
All right well that was
That was something
Yeah we'll be normal
Hey this is Liza and that it would be unlikely to pass up a staff credit
Radiolab is produced by Jad album Rod
Doing keep is our director sound design
Sternwheeler senior editor
Jimmy York is there senior producer
Our staff includes them another David Gable truth behind
Not guilty Robert krulwich
Annie McEwen
Like if Nassar Melissa O'Donnell
Aryan whack and Molly Webster
With help from Valentina bolognini
Phoebe Wayne and Katie Ferguson
Is Michelle Harris