Chat here so
Next week
We're going to launch a new miniseries here on Radiolab
Molly somebody who
If you listen to the show for a while
Like you know her voice
You know our Vibes been reporting
Mostly sign stories here to Radiolab for about 5 years
She's begun to host the show on occasion
And next week
She's going to start up a month-long series about the
Seemingly ordinary but in truth utterly bizarre and magical and deeply weird and ethically
Brought
Business of humans making more of themselves
No this is a beat that evolved over time
And I thought as a Prelude to Molly town
Let's play one of the big
Foundational stories that got her and all of us thinking about this whole world
I'm not sure that we ever spent so much time
Energy and money frankly reporting a story
That's the one you're about to hear
Those of you who have heard this check back in with us in a week for those of you who haven't
I think this is actually one of the best things we've ever made
In case here it is
And next week
It's on
Are you awake
Northern listening to Radiolab
Radiolab WNYC
Jmj rodheim Robert krulwich
Webb's Jacques Webster
And today we have a
Nella's birth story
We're calling this
Birth story because that's
What it is we're going to tell you about babies who are very recently bought a new one day
Will turn to their parents and say to them
Tell me how I got here
What's the weather
What's my story with my story
And the parents in this case
What's a well
That's complicated
Really
It's a collaboration with a a team of reporters in Israel called Israel story
They are a group of folks who do so
Long-form reporting and storytelling
Baby dragon Hebrew for 3 years and they are in the middle of their first
English language
Right now
NBA exactly and this is a particular my echo silver and your hymen
And this Story begins
With Maya
It was party we were all dancing Israeli music in the middle of java
Busy birthday there at her apartment
In the sky tall
How was dancing with his
Partner
These are friends of yours is kind of a Megastar in the deaf community in Israel cuz he transfer
The news in the TV to a deaf people to sign language so he's like a little guy in the corner of the TV
Is Parker
With an R
Is a psychologist that works specially with children that are autistic
Anyway they're at the party so we were dancing all together and then then
How old was omigod maybe it's going to be the list party that I'm in cuz I'm going to be a parent
Endnote
Only apparently I'm going to be a father for 3
And then we were like
Oh my God
3 babies
How's that going to happen
It turns out how that was going to happen
Is a crazy story involving
4 countries
And hundreds of thousands of dollars
Antelyes all that
But we should
Go back a bit
The first thing that I saw in Palace is a
Is his ability to be a father
Really yeah
How so because
He was a good man you know it was very gentle
Really in adults
The family
I don't want to describe a tomato
Every did you see that like on first meeting or was just like four months in
Make a rear he's established to work with autistic people in to take notice for every
Find
Of communication and man
And I understand other people and to analyze them so
Remind me immediately after
X
You say okay
I want children so
Are you interesting I wrote a Manifesto back my future what I want to do what I want to do
My career is kind of night vision
And
I gave it to him and I said this and this is what I want
Define at the bottom place
It was a contract it's like this is what I want if you want to join me
So let's do it until what was your reaction to the
To the manifesto
I like it
It's look like
Someone new
Future
If your own parents have any either of your parents have any views about that
Think don't do or think so weird
Jack
Suffice to say their families
Did not approve
Especially
When it came to the idea of them having kid
How to have those kids
That is a quest
Basically there are two options if you're a gay couple and you want to have kids
There used to be three options at CU Chi my towel from Israel story here is how he Maya laid it out for us optional
Number one which is not as much of an option you could adopt a kid from a third world country
Recess over the last few years what happened is it those third world countries figured out who was adopting their babies and one by
I want
The Bandit for gay couple
Yeah the second option which is becoming very very popular Nizoral is sort of the new family sodas called in Hebrew
Sort of getting together with another woman who wants to be a mother but doesn't have a father
And then they do a joint Parenthood they all live in the same house kind of like divorced parents
I get along really well
Before the processing everything is like in the contract tell them you said that earlier
They try this route
Target in Ephraim one of these friend to where they do the co-parenting
But then
I spoke with Dad and ask him listen it's very important for me to have a baby of my own
Hey with my sperm
And I said to him
I want to try but I don't carry
In the end we have only one baby
In your sperms
It will be my baby
The same
I think I was more stubborn
Amir could really explain why it was so important to him just
That was important
But reflecting on it later Maya from Israel story put it this way
It's very Jewish and Israeli I mean
Fisher nuts
In the Israeli mainstream if you're gay or if you are different
And you'll have your own baby
It's like a signature of being part of the game
You know whatever the reasons Amir and tal talked it over
And then they went back to the swim until
Offered to do the co-parenting and we ask her if she can obligate us to bring
Two children one of them
House burns in one of my own
Indian she said
No
At this point a year ago
So then we decided that maybe the best
Option will be option three is
Is surrogacy
Of course if you're gay man that you take your sperm
Take some extra woman
But your sperm in those eggs into the womb of a second woman
Who carries a babysitter
But surrogacy is
Illegal in Israel
Industrial if you're a hetero couple you can use as really Woman as a
If you're gay
You can't so there's a big problem but that problem also creates a big demand
As you can imagine
Are quite a lot of
Gay couples in Israel
And soda companies
Spring up basically offering International brokering of
Sperm eggs in the ovaries
Babies Outsourcing
You can see this play out every year at these conferences in Israel conferences where they get perspective parents together
We are here for the first time in Tel Aviv big room of people said amen
Chelone
BC what happened to these conferences is at surrogacy agencies will get up and basically sell their products do we now offer
Surrogacy in
Mexico
Panama United States
Ngozi basketball game
LSU baseball game
These agencies will find women in all of these places who will serve as a surrogate for your child depending on which
Country you choose whether or not you provide the donor eggs or they do or million other factors
The cost will vary
We offer very competitive prices for example $36,000 complete start to finish in Mexico
38000 in
Thailand 5085 thousand hundred fifty thousand
That's excluding the donor of course but we have a good selection of donors
Who is the lawyers you have session with
Tell him you went to two of these conferences successive years
Coming back from the second one we take a calculator and just
How we can make
Freezing my honey money way
Yeah they figure if they go with a company that does surrogacy in the US
$150,000 or is that lawyers
Lawyers
Hospital
Star delivery the egg donor
There is a lot of people that we need
To pay niece's keep my when you pay that money
You are not guaranteed a baby your by a process
Yeah
We don't buy baby
One of our friends did
This kind of process in five times
And it still didn't succeed
5 * yeah
They figured with that kind of risk
Doing in the US list
Too expensive
Until they started looking at surrogacy agencies
Which operate in India and Nepal
Because over there you can do the same thing and it will cost you about $60,000
Does almost half price almost a half price yet
Now
What are the things called Lehigh is it in 2013
Basically outlawed surrogacy
For gay couples I mean you if you can do surrogacy in India
By the way in the pot also outlawed surrogacy if you are Nepali woman you cannot be a surrogate
Period but there's sort of a loophole
Indian women are allowed to be surrogates in the pilot just Nepali women aren't allowed to be surrogates and if so what ends up happening
This really strange situation looks like it Basel
These agents in Northern India will find Indian women
Move them across the border into Nepal I'll take them all the way to Kathmandu where the surrogacy agencies have
Set up shelter houses in work with local Hospitals and Clinics
My sister
Vuitton damier the decision
To do it this way
Was not easy
They they had like different opinions.
Had the bigger issue with the moral
Concept of this process
It was like
This is the thing that we need to do I want to be a father. How was
Was very hard for him if it's
It's immoral to do
Things like that
To use
Another woman to
Give
Me
Present like that
And I know she will never
We'll see
This baby anymore
Is it immoral because you're essentially like just
Using a woman's body or
You can say cuz like he's using
Other people
Bad luck
For his own good
Yeah she has no choice
She's not doing it
Out of freedom
She's just doing it for the money and maybe not morally okay that's will
Use this weakness
Tell him you went back and forth on this for months and eventually the argument that won the day
Who is this
They're going to do it with this agency called Lotus which
To their understanding
Paid the surrogates
$12,000
I mean service racks
8 in Indian rupees would that be the dollar equivalent
$12,000 now
For a rural women in India
That is a massive sum of money
They figured this one just helped her survive it will change her life
She'll be changing their life
And they'll be changing hers
Maybe this was
Kind of like Alfred
They get money
They can change their life they can buy a house
They can send the
Her children
School
A2 line in the University
When I felt and understand
Would be life changer
And dates nuts
Today
Exploited exploiting
Seoul
I agree
Started the whole process
One of the main issue was Peak the egg donor
In like who are these women like where do they come from
They're from the Ukraine that is not a country expected to be thrown into the mix of country is reason
The eggs are from Eastern Europe are generally because
That way because they're white so it's like cheap White
That's quite a phrase
So you have like a website and you see a lot of pictures of woman and then you need to choose the most
Jewish online
Dating service I think it was the most
3DS act that I didn't live very long time
Lady
How did you decide which criteria you wanted an in a donor mom
The first one was high you wanted someone talk
Why why was height your first one cuz
It's more
Is it too late
When you're high
Yeah okay then she has distinct eyes
They showed me a picture
Light brown hair
She has this nice nose
You know very strange was very uncomfortable to choose
For me it was very
Improving OU for everything
Eugenics
Now
6 delamere Head Beach one of the baby with their own sperm they told Lotus we would
Like to rent
Who wins
One of each sperm
To try to use like to surrogate mothers
50 $60,000 each pregnancy
Again no guarantees
So
Donamire they give Lotus their sperm a little cups Lotus freezes the sperm send it to a hospital Nepal the Ukrainian woman
The egg donor has flown to Nepal her eggs are harvested somewhere along the way
2 North Indian women are moved across the border into Nepal
Finally the doctors that Nepali Hospital take these really sperm injected into the Ukrainian eggs grits and embryos end
Implanted embryos
In the rooms
Of the Indian surrogate
4 countries
1 baby
A few months ago by they get the news that both
Surrogates are pregnant process
Set work one is pregnant with twins three babies and all
They're sent
Sonogram pictures of the
Surrogates pregnant bellies
I all the time clock on the pic
Picture of her all day ultrasound pictures
All the time looking on my cell phone
Excel says there wasn't really much you could do cuz
345 months
Not much happy
Six months in
Six 6:00 in the morning Donna from Lotus
Cola
And I'm Yours answer the phone
And I hear him say okay
They're okay
I wake up and say what
Because
It was too early to early how early about 8 weeks ahead
Circuit was carrying twins and giving birth I was crying
This is the surrogate carrying tilesbay
Which turned out to be two babies
Yes it will you on the plane the same day as getting that car
Wavy flight from Tel Aviv to Istanbul
From Istanbul
It was very
Crazy day
And then Gill is going to talk as friends who was also in Nepal for surrogacy to commit to the hospital
Well
I was shocked
Because
Gilly was
So tiny Gilly was 3.8 lb
His brother Duvall 4.8
Enzyme
I was very
Cat
To touch
He says he expected the twins to stay in the hospital for a month
But the nurses
We're like
Tomorrow
I thought I don't have enough time to think cuz I understand tomorrow I need to take them home and to be alone
And I never
Take care of
Beanie Babies
So
IAC
I said to the nurses
Teach me how to feed them
And after 3 days I took them home
So where was the
Surrogate during these days when she at the hospital I think she was in.
Because she had the
A cesarean
Surgery I was asked
If she's okay if she needs something
They said you cannot see air
Until she signed all the papers
And then
You can see her
The papers have been signed because she's giving up all her
Paternal rights and if she doesn't want to sign on
This paper but we can lose the baby
Crazily complicated but basically they needed Israel India and Nepal
To all recognize that they were the uncontested
Hanging in the air
As a recent case in Thailand
After baby is born
Changed her mind
Lake and his Husband believe the surrogate decided to try and keep the baby
Because she found out they were gay
We had a little bit of anxiety let's say they will
Going to know
But the baby is going to grow
In the house with two dads
Unicase tall is in the Paul with the twins
Amir is back in Tel Aviv
Couple weeks go by and then
Tyler called me and said that my dad the second circuit
1 baby
And day after
Dual Istanbul
Plane from symbol
And then it was very very very nice that we went
Play with the babies would like no parents no friends no phone on falling
Snow world to visit first
Block Survivor
Relationship with the babies
For the next month they lived in an apartment in Nepal
Just them and their three babies
Learning to be dads
Waiting for the paperwork to be done
Now the paperwork incidentally is a beast
Because after the surrogate sign away their rights
Babies have no nationality
Then there's suddenly illegal in the country
The guys have to
Take a DNA test send it to Israel
Verify then they got to get a passport for the baby's then several sets of visas need to
Begotten
A doll that means
Multiple trips
To the Israeli m
And it was on one of those trips
Did they learn
It was really weird because we went over there with our
Kids together Park
And over there
There was another ceragon from a different agency
An Indian woman and standing next to her was an Israeli woman who happened to speak Hindi and we just so you know
Curiosity we
Ask her to ask
The surrogate in Hindu
How much is she's getting
For the whole process
But the service was very shyness not very delighted to speak about the money
Which made them even more Curious so they persist
And then we discovered that
She gets only 3000 to your soul or something like that
$3,000 for the whole pregnancy was like
$12,500 supposed to go to the surrogate that was at least as understanding
This was a different woman from a different agency in this was just one woman's account but still
In your narrative you describe that you thought that the reason that this was
Okay
Need to do the surrogacy is
Because you were afraid uses this would make a
Changing the life of the woman that was a life-changing sum of money
Timaeus as they walked away from that meeting wondering if they should do something in Israel
Call the agency at the very least say hey we heard some rumors I'm sure they're not true but what do you
We started to ask question but then
Literally the next day
Orinda scenes of death and destruction from Nepal today after a powerful earthquake that started outside plug mongoose
The death toll is now over 5,800 nearly fourteen thousand were injured
Officials say it is the most destructive earthquake to hit Nepal
In more than 80 year
My said she was in New York in a meeting and she gets his voice mail from tile
Shouting an earthquake that happened
And here we save the babies and we got down to the street where half-naked we don't know what to do and he's cry
Crying over there and then
Suddenly
Stop
The heroes
The connection
It was
Like 12 hours with no connection to them
We didn't know if they're alive or not
You know everything was
Unknown I don't know how but that'll
Buche cell phone and we just ran Barefoot as they ran out of the apartment down the street half name
Naked holding the babies
And the phone
On the way they ran into their friend Gail who had four babies and other couples with two babies
We are in this street and we already
And 9 babies
They actually got a video on Todd's phone you see tall only in shorts
A bunch of other couples holding babies and they're all literally standing
On a pile of rubble
Has her standing there a guy with a badge walks by
Your policeman
You're from the American embassy
Where is Riley citizen
We have here
9 babies
We need help
Please we don't get food for the baby
Thank you
So they took us into the embassy
The US Embassy or the
They went to the Israeli Embassy
And Israeli Embassy sort of went into emergency mode gave us some blankets
And they put up put out tents
And shortly after the news cameras arrive
How tall is the tallest he's like in the median cop because he's there he's going to sign language
Translator
I'm so he realized that he doesn't have any way of communicating back home that he's alive see if I says tell shoved his way
Wait for the one
Television cameras
Started signing
12 hours after the the earthquake by so she got a call from a partner back to Tel Aviv and she said
They're on the news now
I can see child speaking sign language to his parents saying everything is okay there alive
Free baby star with them
And are waiting to the rescue team to come and take
Melissa cameras also captured
Was the scene
Hadn't really been grass
Go this whole thing has been going on kind of quietly now you have an international earthquake
Everybody's watching the television and in the middle of the story they're like 10 Israeli babies and gay people and
How many
Whoa cuz there is another agency that also
Babies
Yes
Moving from Nepal to Israel
Maya says when the images of those 24 babies Splash docker
Cross Israeli TV screens
In these ready media search way she broke out one side of the argument was okay we are
Using women and it's 6 on Morrell in from the other hand there was like okay nice ready for
Are gay couples they don't have a lot of choices
Evan was asking what do we do with all these babies
And a surrogate's there was like a huge argument in the Israeli media
About the questions of there are women that are waiting to to give birth and we need to bring them to Israel
Give birth here cause the father is are here
So they would fly the women to Israel have the baby and then slide them back
But I do know I think that's legally
They could not do that
Because that just it feels like kidnapping a lady
And so it went what happened was it very quickly Israel sent over
Search and rescue and Medical Aid delegation
And all the babies
And their parents they were basically just all put on a plane
Instead of the process was expedited and they just brought everybody over to Israel
Back in Israel a parade of newborns
It will celebrate together
Knowing the medical stress they've been through
Very much aware that many in Nepal
Are still going through it
So what happened to the surrogates
Any idea they check
With the agency what is the situation with the surrogate mothers and the answer was that
Two of them are Becky Mindy already
And they weren't there
India earthquake
And what about all the circuits were in the Paul but hadn't given birth yet
Yeah I mean about them there's a big question I mean
No one knows
They were like a worried fathers in Israel
All my thoughts and my prayers are for the surrogate mother and
For The Unborn Child
Tell him you made it
Backed Israel with their babies
Define but
There is still a lot of
Have you guys
I would still be wondering after all
These both of these women gave you as you point out a remarkable gift
Both of you believe that
You hope
Both of you hope that
That gift was well rewarded
Was life changing
But both of you don't know
At this point
Just a little suspicious that maybe it wasn't
I don't know you have this funny feeling you need to
Find out whether they got paid what you
Thought you'd paid them yes like this is why we're so glad that we made the connection with you guys
I said we heard that you can
Finding Maybe
So
We started
Kind of a whole new Legos
Hello can you hear me
Oh I hear some other things too actually it might just be static on the line but it kind of sound
The ocean
Switch off the fan
Give me a sec
A producer Molly Webster was able to track down a reporter and Indian the luncheon of bomac
And she asked her if she could
Find a surrogate
It's okay so you're giving me a name right
I actually called that person in Nepal
Location of the clinic doctor and she said that yes I will
Touch with one of the surrogate
And the next morning we supposed to touch base again
But then again she just totally went in communicating
That's been the same day I open my mail and there was a mail from Israeli no Adam asking me like
Just like to stop the search for some time
Yeah I was so near them
As far as we understand what happened was it the doctor contacted lotus lotus contact to tell in a mirror saying
Call off the reporters you're putting these women's lives in danger
Someone in their Village sees a reporter hanging around
They'll know those women were surrogates that's not something you circuits want people to know
Stop
Here's up here's my understanding you guys correct me if I'm wrong is that we we had asked someone to looked for them
And that person got kind of clothes and then word got back to the agency
And that's great some pressure
Foresta changing
You know that's really what we started staring at right now
How to respond
We heard that there was a real threat
Are there live
Because of the culture of the society that they live in
One of them was Muslim
I don't know if
Is the Muslim societies going to accept
The fact that she
Carry the pregnancy to a gay couple
And to swell
And two Israelis
Yeah
That's a very
Very
Weird fairy
Delicate
Situation
We don't want anything that
Met her
The surrogate well I mean we want to tell the story
We definitely don't want anyone to get
But I do feel like we have an ethical obligation to hear from the women who do this
If not V specific women in this case then
People who represent lyrics
Create candy bar
It would be it would feel wrong for that to be a voice that we don't
I don't know out
It's like
It's for us it's it's a we don't want that anybody will contact our surrogate
And if it says that it's not going to be without the story so let's do it because
It's not worth it for us
Okay understood understood
We won't make any further attempts to contact those to those two
Just so we're all clear I think what I'd like to do is to continue to pursue
People who have been in similar situations but are not in any way connect
Potoo
Those two women or do you guys
Okay
I mean again we need to wear what do you make sure that
Hey
Nobody's going to be hurt
Absolutely
That's where we left things at on a mirror
And then
I'm sorry change
A lot
Play Radiolab this is Sally cooling from Melbourne Australia by the Alfred P Sloan
Foundation enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world to mention about slime. W.
Jw.org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help this summer I'm hosting the show
And I request for those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
We're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments
Brilliance basically I want to hear about those times when I did something
It just means you bring back and say whoa
Maybe it was the moment that I kids you've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed are ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the
Epic moments where
Kid does something super smart but it doesn't have anything to do with the test
If you have a story with us
Go to radiolab.org Brilliance and record a short audio message for us
Fan that's radiolab.org / brilliance
Thank you so much
Hey I'm Jared I'm Rollin I'm Robert krulwich
Molly Webster Radiolab and we will return now to our collaboration with Israel story producers Maya kosovar and
U-high my towel
Story of Tamir and their three babies now
That's how it started for us
The story of two guys trying to ask
Kids
Around the point of the earthquake
The story really shifted
Attitude for the entire world
Cuz we've been concentrating the tail so far on the father's been with 20
For some odd
Babies that's an awful lot of women who have to carry those
Baby so what could they be thinking what is the
Story about them how are they feeling about this
Transaction
How much are they getting it will it actually change their life
These are some of the questions we had we gave those questions to Molly
And she should have ran with
In the months after the earthquake
I guess you get to the
The political situation in Nepal
Change how everyone started looking at surrogacy change
Once everyone saw these
Pictures of all these babies outside the Israeli Embassy being put on airplanes
Sent back to Israel it just
Cracked open his huge debate not just back in Israel but in Nepal and India even internationally
Basically you had groups coming out and saying like
You know the feminists were saying this is exploitation and we're just using these women for their wombs and their op-ed articles about should we be
Be shifting women across borders is it the way you want to do surrogacy
And then
Turn of the next thing that happens
Three weeks after we talked to Thailand mirror
Is that Nepal actually
Decided to ban circus
Completely
Completely Straits for both same-sex couples foreign couples local couples and for 4
Nepali women couldn't do it and Indian women tend to come into their borders and do it
No more surrogacy no more loophole
No more surrogacy normal pulse but then the confusion was that
They banned surrogacy but there were still a pregnant surrogates on the ground
And so they sort of existed in this
Gray Zone
And in the midst of that was when we went out to try and find surrogate
In Nepal all the circuits are kept in what are called shelter houses which are just like
Houses that agencies rent out that have a lot of pregnant women
Houses like the rumors are that they move the houses
Further away from the city center
Attract less attention
And so what we found Nepali reporter
This beast in Kathmandu article trying to get into one of the shelter houses
So
The shelter house is actually quite far from the main city center
Almost half an hour 40 minutes drive from Kathmandu
It's all on a Hilltop because these are the outskirts of Kathmandu where new settlement of just started
It was actually a
School building
Which they turned into a shelter because I think the school are left after the earthquake
The moment I reached the first floor I was so surprised it was very noisy a lot of children playing around
And turns out a lot of women bringing the young children if they're too young to be left alone
Really yeah and how many women were there
Still around I think 20 or 22 women.
20 or 22 women on the first floor of this building
This shelter house is run by another Israeli agency so not Lotus but a different one and we're guessing that
Most of the women were carrying babies for Israeli cup
And it is the women I saw who outside the room or who had their doors open
They seem to be around 32 early 40s
Really the first time I saw I saw the first woman I talked to him
Arguing
She was wearing like a mustard color
Sorry
She had some Bangles all the women had some Bangles in the hands and Mitchell
She said she was 36 years old
Megabox
From Kolkata
Bolivia
She has two girls
Berkeley asked how old are your girls
She said 8 and 12 so
How did you get the number
Never could you ask like why are you doing this
And the woman said
I'm doing it for them it's because you know we have a lot of
Financial problem my husband deserve
Rickshaw driver and we don't make enough and
Tallapoosa bottle made in Delhi
And ultimately she said she had no other way
To raise money for her daughter
To get married because
In Hindu weddings
The bride's family pays off the groom in the form of a dowry the plan was to use the money from surrogacy
For the day
She's been in Kathmandu for 3 months
So she was in her first trimester
Have a name a lemon for Cody Astor
Disco guy
Does she know who the baby is for
She said no
Michelle Elizabeth
But you knows it's not her
And actually all the women that prakruti talk to her very very clear about this
Cesar Millan
This is a job
Weeble wobble
The second woman I talked to
30 years old
Also made in Delhi also two daughters
She looked all dressed up she was already to as issue about Lee somewhere and then I realized her husband is here
Just given birth
And she put the job sentiment pretty plainly
So she said and I'm translating here
Map by Celine Dion I will gladly
I will get the baby from my womb
If I was think this is my baby then how will it work I have two children
I cannot take this child home
I will have to give
I have no sadness
No problem
Anytime for Kodiak these women are you
Afflicted we have trouble getting the baby up she always got the same answer
The only said they would happily give away the child
If a baby comes out right now I just give it right away and then she laughed
Did you get a sense that these women didn't want it
Known that they were doing this
I mean some of them did and some of them didn't
Because some women would like to go but now that I'm here my neighbor's my family everyone
And then when Mercury Aster
I have an opinion is it right or wrong
She answered
No I'm here for the money
I would not listen to any opinion
If it was wrong I would not come here
But some of them was like why would I tell anyone you know there's one Temecula
32 years old Beijing nail polish on and she had lettuce pink lips
Stick on wallet
She said people in my Village simply do not believe these things this week
The one can have children by getting injected or taking medicine
They won't believe this
She kind of do badan us with
How some of the people in a village
I done something similar when they
Bred cows or fishes
You said like maybe they'll understand
But my family would not understand
She says nude williger
I have told lies to them
So how much in the end of it do they make
I asked him how much money do you get here
3.5 lakhs
What is that mean in dollars
So if you do the conversion today
It's 5300 US dollars
And the way it works is that they get paid a small amount of money every month that they're pregnant and then at the end they get a lump sum
Prakruti said that for these women at the end of the pregnancy that lump sum is like let's say around
What's $3,000
Which is the amount that telling me or heard outside the embassy
The total sum that they have when they go back home is quiet
You know it's not
A lot
So $5,000 is
Yeah what's the difference
Tutor to see if this was a number that was just coming out of that shelter house or if it was something that was
Like the going rate I guess
We talked to
Sixer gets here in India
That same rate around $5,000 kept coming up and we did hear a range from one surrogate in this was about
A friend of hers
We heard as low as 1000
A surrogate getting only $1,000 for pregnancy
Yeah
Hello
Jerusalem calling
New York answering
Ultimately we took this information back to telling a mirror because
This was originally there question
So let's talk about the money partner
Alright so
The last time we talked to you
You
Thought you're paying your surrogates $12,000
Yes I around if
We've been off reporting and it seems like the number that's coming up most consistently for what surrogates are reporting
As their rate 5300 US dollars
What
It's just too much
Tulo
Really yeah
I want to cry
We explain to them that if you actually look at the contract the line that looks like it's
Payment Straight Talk
Do the surrogate doesn't actually say this is
Payment for the surrogate
It says it says payment to surrogacy
Services
And it's sort of like once you
Adding that second word
It opens the door to all kinds of things
She's getting less than 1/2
Then it's like
Felix tacos
It's okay to get the money
So who got the money
That question it hung in the air for a few weeks
Until
7 minutes before I go into something
Who is the head of lotus which is the agency that town Amir used in Nepal
She had just
At the morning I talked to her she had just flown in from Nepal to Israel and I caught her in a car on our way back to the
Where in she's going to fly off to Australia
After how much do surrogates actually get paid
I can tell you through that I work in India
Tell you exactly
How much is
She saying she has no idea and the reason she has no idea
Is because
She said this and other agencies I spoke to said this is that when you're working on the ground in foreign countries
Under the Umbrella of surrogacy
You are dealing with a lot of middlemen and the Middleman have middlemen and there are submental men
The people who find women in India who get all the paperwork done who get them to the Border who get them over the Border
Then bring them to jump all
Someone be sending catmandoo gets into the shelter house
And all those people
They need to get paid
I truly don't know
After the agency know how much
Exactly how much goes for her competition for her
I can tell you I was thinking about
I would feel conflicted
As the head of an agency to be like
I think the money is going to some people that I just don't know like
I think I would niggle at me
Well that's a good thing that you're doing what you're doing
Let me know
Macaron
Look the whole world and say okay
Brighter
I cannot deal with all the problems in the world
To give him as much
As possible
We paid the money
This woman gets
Life
And now we understand it
Not exactly like that
It's not right
I think we're deep question here underneath after everything is
Is over
Is
When
When we do a generous thing like we give people families who couldn't have families
But that becomes a business
Is there something about
The business of making a family
That
Is always going to be a little trouble
And there are no perfect ways to do this
Or is there
A way to pull this off in some
I just don't know
I mean like
I still have
Three more embryos of thyroid
In the freezer in a file
I don't know if the next time I would not
Do the process may be in the states
The US is like an entirely different
Surrogacy seen which were just not going to get into here
The interesting thing that that Donna said and head of another agency
Was that they think that in the next like 5 to 10 years the US will be one of the only countries where surrogacy is still happening
Things are closing down
Most of the Stinger closing down
CIBC Nepal has a band
Thailand it looks like in a few days after this
Peace comes out that India May banat for foreigners Cambodia there's rumors that they're about to ban it and even
Canada there talks of new restrictions on surrogacy
And this is these are bands like not just for same-sex couples but
Every single people
LOL
And the main reason for the all these bands in restrictions as worries about
Explain women
Yeah
Guy feel weird about
Because kitchen Furyk
If you're trying to
If you as we heard these women are making a business
Decision whether or not we agree with it
Entirely separate thing they are making it
Decision then we're going to take it away
In order to
Protect ham fields
I don't know
Funny cuz it's * it also feels
If you just think like we have these women can decide how they're going to use their own by
It's a little extra little black divorced
Totally is
But by the same token
It's not wrong for a
Society
Say hey there certain things
Won't allow we won't give you that choice be
Because we
We find that the choices
Itself is
I mean
Spare would like one of the arguments against
Banning it is that
Is that
They're still
Demand
For sure gif
And that that's not going to go away and so it just pushes
Underground underground in so
And then that way it's a lot
Yeah Shady
But the other thing was
Does that then prakruti actually went in
Talk to the women about life
Job does for
Obtuse about Saigon
Like you okay so it's not
The crazy amount of money we thought it might have been its $5,000
What is a24
Mesut Ozil
Medicine
One woman said that you know when I get this money
I'm going to go back home and start something on my order status
Do you know my own deal Enterprise
All of them wanted to use this money to build a house is it okay
Hey can you buy a plot of land in New Delhi for 5 grand
When do they take the money and they go back to their original Village
And they use it there to buy a small plot of land that's totally doable and it's actually no small feet
Land is so important in our Societies in South Asia Asia it raises your
Socioeconomic status
It's something is passed down through
To generation so you're like creating something
Thanks for your family
And if you're one of the women that maybe already have land the thing you can do with that $5,000 is build a house on it
And it's a very small like a mud house
Keep in mind like these women
Their day jobs are all made
It's right and so they make less
Then $100 a month just said they had it not been for this I mean they would have never
Probably never owned this much money at
At a single chance
The more than that like
When you go into this
At least when I went into this the thing that I expect
Did you see was like okay
ATL Airport desperate women that are being forced into this
Like right they've been dragged
Across the border
I think the thing that I was
Surprised to see when I looked at the transcript
Was that
Even though these women don't have a lot of options and yes they are poor they had chosen to do this
Out of
The Limited options that they had they looked at them all and they thought like this is the thing that I'm going to do to get what I want
It felt like these women were making a choice
I asked him
Bubble level
What if you're given a chance to go abroad letter Dubai
Guitar because
A lot of women from India and Nepal Dakota one of them said that you know.
Dubai
Like why would I do that that would be very far away he says that hear the kids can come their husbands can visit
The FED will
The circuits get good medical care of doing the whole 9 months and in for the whole nine months for sending money back home
There's one less mouth.
I think it'll be
I mean the way we passed judgment you know YouTube
Spt on these women but I think
Babe the very aware of what they're doing
They might be exposed to do some level like you said but it seemed like
The women
In some ways it there in charge of
Deciding how they want their life to be end
We don't have
Duplicate them with
With Petit
Marshmallow
The last woman that prakruti spoke to
Choose a 32 year-old woman from Darjeeling she spoke in Nepali
And
She told boccuti
That's my mama
Wikipedia
I came here in March
My Embryo transfer was done once but I don't know if it was due to the earthquake or something else but it didn't get heartbeat
And it got washed
She said that
She lost the
Fetus
In 2 months and
Which I did twice on her identity City topic with your birth certificate
4 qt how does
You feel with a child.
Washed
Surrogate
I felt bad
What to say
Ignore ignore
It felt like it was my own
Okay by Christina
And they won't give money if it's unsuccessful
Dino Dana Campbell
I'm like
I didn't know if you miscarry you don't get paid yes yes
She says it's treated like a business
You get paid for every month you say
Successfully carry
And if you do lose the baby depending on where it is in the pregnancy part of the money is refunded to the intended
Put on relaxing Sapa Satya go with that diliman by the Texas Medical Center Garba night
Most of my friends
Had
Successful stories
Share back in Delhi
Some of my friends made a house
What's with the money
Cymbalta
I felt good
Suffolk acceptance rate
She basically says she wishes she had done this earlier because now with the band
She's being sent back to her Village
You still weeping a little
Of what could have been if she was
You know if the eggs were healthy enough before Health has alright 150 couldn't Allah
Carnival in Tucker
Bucuti will you come again if this opens back up and try again
Repeating ones
Alto
Surrogate
Yes
I will come
Producer Molly Webster
There's something on your face that says we're not quite done here what do you want
Thinking about all the different ways we thought about the
Store along the way of making it I mean you can read it as like this is a story about the business of family making
The Outsourcing a babies
You can hear the story about exploitation
All these different things are happening in the story
This is also a story about the inventiveness of people
You mean what do you mean by that I guess what I mean is like
The way that cultures will
Cross-fertilize in this really unexpected
Needs reaching out and fighting each other half world away and there's a kind of symbiotic benefit
Even while it's troubling and may be unfair but still kind of there and look so III
Actually we talked about the store in any number of ways but I also feel like one of the things to have in your sick this is a story about dreams
About aspiring to have a better life and how in this case those aspirations meat industry
Really uncomfortable transaction
Let's think
That's what we should do next
WesBanco
So many people
Begin by thanking
Posit is real story in my exclusive air
We have just
How many people does guy's story
Check them out it's it's really.
PRX. Org and Israel
Story. Org
Which one you were telling us about
There's a story that they did last season
Which they went
To every town in Israel that has herzl
Speaker system
Like the George Washington Israel
They'll have heard so streets they knocked on 48 cuz it was found in 48
Knock knock
Who's there and they open the door in a interview whoever's on the other side of the door
It's just a wonderful
Cool idea and they get to meet
Crazy quotes of Israel
Cute sexy these real story team at the Barry Finkel
N2 are reporters in Indiana Lantana bhowmik and Anna Paul Burke Rudy Rai
And the international reporting project for connecting us
Porters and translators in different country
We talked to a lot of agencies of for the story surrogacy agency special thanks to doron Mamet and dr9 up
Patel tour translators Tome Wasserman I akif Karthik ravindran turn away Franz and out of car
Which is a Nepali Community organization Outerbridge
Queens
Send. Thanks to Ivan Zimmerman / music special thanks to Noah's GYN to the Balkan beat box production
App for this story from Andy Mills and the pieces produced
Reported
I'm Jared I'm Rod, Berkowitz
Emily Webster
Thanks for listening
One last note
We should
Tell you that telomere
Did meet their surrogates
Very briefly one time
And
It's kind of a cool moment we couldn't figure out where to put it in this
Story
But we have that seen on our website at radiolab.org
It's worth listening to
Message
Five Prime phone number
Guy and I'm a guy
Show me the credit
Post offices
Not guilty
Molly Webster
Alexander & Alexander
Are fact-checkers honor
He's a doctor and Michelle Harris
And this message