Northern listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
Who I mean I don't have a real good game plan for for how we start the show but in the in the in the spirit of the show
Drop into that that
Real up staff meeting
Yeah I remember it was a very
If you would like
What
Tuesday
Text set up recently we came up with this
Challenge
Challenge Yahtzee for the Radiolab staff are we getting together
An inappropriately stodgy conference room there is sore and dialing in Wisconsin
Yeah the paper
Everybody take a deep breath I had warned them ahead of time that something big was coming
It's nothing something that obviously
We got over that little bump in the road I just I basically outlined that
This challenge
We came up with a little a little plan
September 27th
Bourbon release
A baby story
We're seven stories really end between today
And that date
You will have to pitch report record produced
Sad story
You will have that much time to do it
I will be putting it up
In other words
We're giving them like a week to pitch a story
And then a week to make it about breaking news
So something that just happened
Or you just worried about bears
So I'm calling the whole thing Bad News Bears
Redbeard sort of in the in the room so long
Tell me if I'm right it just happened to her
Rattata weather text Jen
This is this is one of those like that you know we're already talked about Princess and the Pea like this ap14 mattresses down here that just bought
Hottest music one of the puppies that's been bothering me
The length of time it takes it to make these stories sometimes I can feel too burdensome
I'm going to just like do an experiment where we short cut the hell out of that
This way to put it was just a strange juxtaposition
I want you guys to go out now
Find something that is hot new and sudden and just breaking like a real reporter
Or
Bears
Life is such a weird
Here's your husband go then you're going to get paired up I'll do those pairings in a second
That story has to be under 10 minutes
The story must have some point
Include audio from the movie Bad News Bears
Original
The story is complete assembly the recording from outside the office
Any relation
Have to be done in conversation
Have to be staring at somebody across the glass
Not going to track solo line
Before I do your teeth your parents
Are there any questions
How how are we defining break
Breaking news had a reasonable question
I would give you a little bit like I would maybe be willing to accept something from last week
Otherwise
Today forward
Yep
Why would you do this
Accurately
Define
Women's Aeneid
I'm Jared I'm Robert
Chinatimes I'm sorry
Is Radiolab
Today we are Breaking Bad News Bears
Okay so everybody went out from that meeting and again the task was to reiterate the breaking news story
Wreg news story bear or bears
Week one week to do everything yeah. Go out you got to get the tape you got to come back put in the computer cut it up
Adamusic right thing we are a producer so that
Crepes a check that's so that means we end up as a grand total of
4 stories
Yes
Starting Bowie Starman
How about Molly what's your inside
Well I will say that we have checked both boxes
To fear we have a story that is both about bears
And
Breaking news
You're kidding
You do get extra points so alright you there
I am
Great life
We give this guy
My name is Matt montanye
And I am the director of Public Works
For the City of New Bern
And you got quite the task ahead of you huh
Destruction perks
Landfill
Hurricane Florence come to last week in New Bern
This is a live looking New Bern as the water has really overtaken this there's Relentless rain and wind
Brought down trees if you've been watching the news at all over the past couple weeks I've probably seen Uber
Turn on TV
As you just heard it was one of the towns that was hardest
Hit by Hurricane Florence
Homes were destroyed tens of millions of dollars
Destruction
Trees were knocked down
And with those trees
How come power lines
With the power lines down the lights go out thousands of people are in the dark around here about
Flooding in Newburgh
And we got historic houses that were built in the 70s
And as director of Public Works it's Matt's job department is
Yeah the construction debris from the houses that are being gutted
I'm actually at the disposal site
30 tractor trailer trucks
Are lined up getting ready to roll out the storage unit debris cleanup
But
What we called mad about was the the cleanup of something far smaller
This bear is not supposed to be here
Far less vital
Right now but I'm sure they'll get them back
Beef soup
Maybe just as
Let me see let me see history grade
Are downtown is a really beautiful six maybe eight square blocks where you see
Beautiful porches this is local restaurant owner and our town was settled
Swiss settlers
And if you look up the meaning of burn
Switzerland
Burnley bear
Enso over the next 300 years they really random
Set high school mascots the bear they have a city flag that has a little black bear on it
Saikai
Not to their pass right where they came from but it's also they've got all the
Bears in the woods surrounding them Simon found out a lot of fat bears in the woods okay black bear ever recorded from Craven
County North Carolina and the wave is bear sort of
Obsession taking hold is that they have
Bear statues
All over town stand up on their hind legs
Probably somewhere between 6
So that being said you'll bears everywhere including the morning of September 14th
Hurricane
Hurricane Florence came in and buy Fountain midday Water started to seriously start Rising again
Play Bangkok wework
7 ft
By Thursday night I mean it it happened in some places just extremely quick to tell buddy and
A few other locals
Took it upon ourselves that we needed to go out and help people and they would go to areas outside of the downtown and they
They were just banging on Doors
They look in the next six to eight hours this water is going to be over your head in flood your arm and you need to get out
Now and get you a shelter
Meanwhile back in the downtown with with the waters continuing to rise
Is closest we are to the river we received 8 10th Street North downtown area
Strange things started to happen
Does giant bear statues that
4 years Japan looking out over the town
Did the rising flood water actually managed to pick
Them up
Yeah they all sit on concrete slabs but
Deal with the amount of water we received a lot of
Many of them were lifted cement and all
An inverted
Floating there standing up
Bobbing gently along
A lot of them
Alot of men that Flood lyrics
They say move the downtown through the alleyways
Just down the street
Others
Floated on four blocks
Oh my God
Just Close Your Eyes hear the hurricane
See the water
Lymph astonishingly
Watch the Bears go by
And then as the water recedes there
Gently set down
And left
In
Distill
Slightly flooded
Waters of the downtown
Wow that's a whole new view photos of
These bears
Started showing up startup by release
Local residence
Started posting to social media
And then it was
Saturday morning
You know the first day that the winds really had
Started and I was getting up
Play just assess damage of everything that was outside but he's at home he wakes up in the morning he goes down the door of his
Apartment building
Is it up and it's just like
My God
This town has just been destroyed
I got branches everywhere the rain is still laughing and there was a lot of debris and stuff flying and
It looks just right in front of him
Right outside the doorway right there on its side
Inntravel little bit of a puddle of water
Is a bear
One of those floating bear statues
Had ended up
Annie's apartment
And he immediately recognizes it as the city hall bear
So you have on there a lot of the colors and scenes from the city of New Bern so you have on their head back of the bear is
Painted yellow like the New Bern Flags the middle of the bear is painted with the North Carolina
State flags and then the shoulders and head of the bear are red white and blue
And that bear represents our entire city
And there was
Run from my doors
A gentleman happen to just be walking by in the street
Who was
Living on a block-and-a-half away from me and he helped me pick the beer out and grab the back legs the other guy grabbed at front
Legs front back whatever they grab the market across this I'm presumed to be probably still 6 inches of water
Washing through the 3 and then Florence is like not done right cuz it's sad over the coast for a while so the
End of gone down but like the rains are still torrential there's like
I mean flood watch has a week out with it
And there's a bush right behind City Hall
With a little bit of an Alleyway in between the bush
And the building
So we put the Bear in between they are because we knew it would be hidden enough
Yeah buddy Bagels he took the bareback across City Hall in
Few days later they're actually getting ready for
President Trump was going
And so Matt montanye head of Public Works
Goes down to City Hall to like
Parrot
I was asked to go down there and make sure we had a flag on City Hall and make sure was flying high
We took a couple spot the bear go over to it
Big pick up the bear
The market to the platform
Set it back on the concrete pedestal like it was that
Alter screw one side of it into the bear's foot and then put the other side into the concrete slab
When should do that I'm all for the lights
Step back
And take a take a breath
And then a raise a new American flag
And I move on
If you wiping a tear away
Young I'm just going to get GI
But I could
No it's nice when you when you have
Something
That represents your heart
As odd as it may be to be painted plasticine
Barrett image
But still
That's called we're back
Are we aren't over
Optical Francis Scott Key
You're still there
When you look at the grand scheme of it
Bears
It's not that important but
What kind of
Symbolizes that will put a newborn back together
We need you need a symbol to get behind
And R symbol in the city
Are the Bears
Pokemon Go download
And alright so what's
So so what's that was number one
Story number one act what next
We got well
Who is Pat Walters and Bethlehem PA
And what well
Let me let me do this
Should we talk about
The thing about the thing
Okay yeah
So this is a story about
Park right here right behind
Bobcat
Can you prob
Hi hello
Rob is
Who's Rob Devin is a comedy writer he works in the city for a really long time like
Like 10 years plus working for The Colbert Report just basically like a high-rise living city guide
About a year-and-a-half ago heinous
Spouse can be moved update
With the rain
What the
Stuff is happening
They bought a little white house with a big yard and the
Beautiful mountain ridge in the distance
Foggy in the
Like a building
In Manhattan
Cheerleading things
And pretty quickly after they get there they realize there's all this food growing in their yard
Apple trees and then they find a Pear Tree Inn kale and pumpkin pumpkins
How old is the Garden of Eden
Had you ever had
Trees that grow
Fruit or food before
Right in the center of this yard
Peachtree
And we had so many pieces I think we pulled like
200 Alta Street Jimmy Jam and Pie and sauce and he's everything
Pie baker
We had a ton of Pi
Though the next
The next year rolls around and Rob it is like rubbing his hands together like
Yes
Peach time you know that they're ready because they come off when you gently
And if they're not coming off yet they're not ready yet
So it was in the part we were like
Waiting
And ready for it to start to happen
When e
Here's Sandy yellow from the back
At the house
Three jumps up
Does the back window and and see if it was a bear
It was a it was a I mean
You can't mistake it sitting there
Like
Winnie the Pooh on its butt
And I was just reaching up
All lazy to the train was pulling off a peach and it would like
Look at it
How do I put mouth pain with drop it and it would reach up for another one
It was just time of the time of its life
And I love that it's sitting
Not only was it sitting its back was to
Which I found also
Very upsetting in ways I couldn't totally articulated a time I was like you need to be more
Aware
Someone's house
Taking their food
He jumps up he grabs is tearing that he uses to punish his cat
And I ran outside
And I started shaking it
I wouldn't even take a video of it
And then Sandy his fast is like
By the house will sing like a dog
A mic
Although the Bertolli freaked out it
Booked it
Back into the woods that way they walk up to the Peachtree and Peachtree has been
Like Matic
The parts of the tree that are
60 below
We're pretty much
Stripped
Peaches are there just always Peach pits and like half-eaten peaches got it around and every one of those is like a
Repeat that they're not going to have like a pie crumble they're not going to have the feeling that
Just
Los
Nnn's
Determination I was like no
I can't
I don't want this to keep happening at this point
See
The pieces that are left
And I would like them to be hours
I think the bear has had his fill
And this has to stop now so
They go back inside
And Rob immediately Google's like how to deter bears
And then at some point they come across a website that says
The one thing that bears are very afraid of is
Human voices
Yeah so I was like
Pink
The what I need to do is make a giant
Play with the pots
And play it
A podcast
Yeah and so he takes
This old iPhone with a broken screen and
He then begins to build the
Spare deterring
Podcast
Device
I have a telescope
Has a mechanical mouth
Power Banks
Hayden get
To charge your phone when you travel and stuff
And a Bluetooth speaker
That I connected directly to the phone covers that whole thing
With a recycling bin on top of these logs
So he hook belt thing up
And he
Loaded with entire catalog of
Reply all
Reply all this is a show about the internet
5 Brooklyn kids
Reply all is this podcast
Barbie's two guys
PJ Vogt and Alex Goldman
This is absolutely an entire team of incredible people who produced the show but anyway yeah Rob just happens to like reply-all
It was it was something that we were comfortable with
Yes
PJ Netflix
Touching
Garden
So
Meaning of
Just curious what you thought about
Your podcast being used as
Scarecrow
How do you feel about that Alex
I think I thought it was great
Like I got the only I thought they were very limited range of
I'd like to Russia to be like the duct tape of pod
You can do all kinds of
Yeah so far we've only
Had to listen to it scare bears
But yes it's not like there's a there's one aspect of reply-all that
I might be particularly effective
At
Scaring away
A bear
I can still laugh laugh
PJ's laugh
Imagining a bear that was like
How big is people
I'm going to walk a little closer on Mariposa Street and then I was like
I do like I do mostly feel like I feel like I'm supposed to
I got mostly feel good that it
It's like useful
Was a terrible irony is here's a city boy who escaped the city Lynch the love the peace and quiet and then
I just peace and quiet invaded and turn it back into a city
Is it yeah I mean they're there their that take Brooklyn just followed him up there
Convertible
I'm sure though it kind of felt reassuring to have that like going in the background
You know that your bear tutoring machine is doing its job it was an instinctual choice
I felt like continually revealed itself to be the right one
How do you check that first morning
The pizzas are all safe
Cuz I'm the evening reply-all continuing to play
Next day he goes out and there's
No sign of any bears and she gets like 10 peaches off the tree and then the next day no bears again
T-Pain Alex they're still talking about the internet and there's like 20 peaches off the tree over the days
How many peaches did he capture
From the bear encounter at the bear
Had eaten about 40 peaches
Space on the bucket cleaning up the
The mess
How many peaches the bear had taken from him the way it should
Check out
I got we got about as many pieces
He thinks it
He and Cindy got like 40 pizzas to so like 5 Ian PC than he's thinking I win
At least I didn't lose
We tied
And so anyway
The end of writing this entire story on Twitter
The story of how was happening in my yard right now
And
It got a
Big response and I was a little surprised
I think that the number of
People who took the Bears
Height
But I was like that's the problem I can't the bear have some
Not up to you just for you like
Bear apologists
Do they understand that there are there's food sources
Been the one Peachtree and Rob dubbins yard
Like clearly not know
The way I see it is like
If Rob had domesticated the Bear Race it to only understand that food gave her metri and then sent it out of the woods there
But other than that that's ridiculous
I'm not taking
The morality of it
The bear doesn't like
Reply off
Rockets
Do you think on any level the bear
Got something out of listening to the show
Now
I don't we just don't do that
Where there's a mine
What if show designer
Would bears in mind sound like
Radiolab
Oh my God is enough
Radiolab presents
Listen real talk here okay do we we like bears
We like me we could do many more episodes I got to go in particular we've run across so many in it and they there
Run across so many things about bears that we've got we've got the whole bear season week or Hilo
You decide that right now
We could try again see if with anybody in the house we're going to do a nun.
Next up is Matt kielty and Rachel
Music with breaking news app
Melody Lane
I just wanted to go barreling minutes or something
Yeah
Dango
Okay well if we
Start all the way
The Tip-Top we drove out to
Oak Ridge New Jersey
Which is about an hour and a half
The city here
Out for a story
Bear
Surprisingly
Oh that's.
But not just any pair of famous bear the most famous bear you could say
Hi how's it going my name is Matt
I'm Rachel we're reporters
So we we showed up
Totally unannounced in this house woman answer
Shut the door
Suspicious we explain Who We Are
Marissa Marissa
McAllen
We we need a husband Greg who just got home from work
So Greg Waters around the backyard
Really beautiful
Huge Forest
Then
I already tried that the kids
Thanks so much lettuce indoors basement
Accountant there
Richard Sherman
Yeah I guess so
We were just curious like I mean Maurice was tell us a little bit about the first time she saw the bear
Like when when did you did she tell you about that when you do first
Yeah my wife's on the 1st
First time I caught up just a glimpse of him
But at the time I videotaped
It was actually the third time I saw
So
It's the summer of 2014 at night or so
And
I was hanging out on my deck
When
TVs
Despair
Coming from the woods up towards the street
Black bear
So I ran out I got my cell phone and just started videotaping with an older
Samsung Note
Three it's like a shaky video
Brakes are just like painting the phone all over the place to try to find it with the phone
Marisa's outside
Yeah
She gets another video video to video of me taking a video of the bear
So you catch walking up
Is front yard
He's going down his driveway and he's looking he still looking for the spare and really like what you just see
A little picture Astley
Slice of suburban America is just like Sim
You see some trees Road Grass everywhere
And then there it is there it is
All the sudden Greg Zooms in
On this Lake
Blurry
Blob that is moving across his neighbor's driveway
Amy Adams green butt
What you see is this
Black bear that is a bipedal bear
Walking on its hind legs
Walking across the
Street
Like a human
Oh my God
Wait that's the bear that the bear
The bear is just straight up walking on two feet you could totally be like a kid in a bear suit like it's like actually
The first time I saw it I was like that is what my dad looks like when he stumbled out
Of the hallway in the middle of the night without his glasses on
Still motoring motoring and also serve puttering pottering with purpose
Okay so Grey Goose
Great great great great guy.
Filming this
Yeah I'm over in the front yard of my house
Watching this walking bear that's what I see him walk
Up my neighbor's driveway into the street
Then the Bears to the bear at the Crossing
The street over into another Neighbors
Front yard front yard right now
And
Somewhere off camera
You here
Their neighbor
You know that's a bear
You know that the Bear right
Okay
Through your house
Look up
Go get her
That the video lasts for about
3 minutes and then
Stop supporting
So we got the video we watch it go through the woods
Stop 5 go inside after giving the kids bath
I just take it I want to share with some people so I threw it on YouTube
An hour and a half hour later after it upload Zoe go and send out a couple emails to like some friends
Family just be like hey I thought this weird wild bear walking
Like check it out and that's it
Go to bed
And then the next day
Greg check
People from viral media companies it's family members somebody put it on Facebook it was spreading on Facebook and
I was blown away
But then
All these other people's videos
Because this bear is being spotted
Bolivar town
Videos are like
Lake of the bear
Coming out at night time early dinner time
I like walking around the woods
Beatbox better than you.
Strolling down neighborhood streets popping his head into garbage cans
Going through people's backyards
It was like it was amazing
He would come like right there
You know right there
Disappear tree over there
Getting to Paris
Out of the tree
It was great to see him
You know because he
Eventually folks in town give him the name titles
Good Morning America national news
A black bear
Walks on his
Timeless
Bright like a human kind of like
Oh my gosh like what a fun cute adorable animal doing something that looks like a human that's so fun
Well
Sort of everyone
Which is
Where we get to Lisa
Tomato
So basically we heard about Lisa she was like a big player in this whole life
Love affair with pedals
3 Guion died with the Down Under dining room table okay
Like where
When did you first
Learning the bear
I don't remember the exact date I don't even have a hard time with years
But I think it was in 2014 that
She was on Facebook I saw a post about this bear and he was
In a
Video walking by
And I was like oh my God this is so sad like you want me to think it was like
Funnier
Now I thought it was sad
Why does the video make her sad
Accuworx animal rescue and she's rather than being like just
Wow for her when she wants a video
What she saw was a bear that was
Injured
So the thing is that if you look at some screenshots of petals close up you'll see if she
Really had no hands
One was like amputated
Like I stabbed it was like pretty much missing and the other one was
Just broken
Mangled
At least that that's why he walk on his hind legs
I mean I'm sure he ate whatever berries or whatever he could get
Because he couldn't use his paws is why he was walking around these neighborhoods
Because he was starving and he couldn't feed himself
Her first thought was we have to help this bear
So
She gets in touch with a couple women they start a GoFundMe campaign helps a pedals raise $25,000 in my
4 days
To basically Dart him transport them and house them at this place called The Wildlife orphanage there's a couple other why
Wild bears there a couple of Pam like retired
Circus Bears if you will
There's a pond a lot of trees and its price
You know it's not a zoo
So
The best thing to do with petition
The state of New Jersey to Justina Lake
Do it cuz that's against the law for us to just start a bear and
Put them in a truck and take them so they get his petition going it ends up going at like around the world
Gold light 400,000 signatures
Date for all ready to go everything was in please
Interstate
Has
We're not doing that
Really why well so I got in touch with the Press people at njdep which is like being
Environmental
Department of New Jersey and basically they said
We have no interest in commenting on this
White why would they not even comment well I think you can understand that
If
You know the rest of the story
Has a lot more
Story
That you don't know
Alright let's hear the rest then
Okay what's up what you basically have if you have a collision of two ideas
About black bears
And what they are and what they need
So that's John welham magazine
I knew more about it earlier works like before he got famous
He's written a lot about animals including pedals and explain to us that what you had was this device
Where
On the one side you have people like Lisa
When they looked at the bear they thought
It's injured struggling
We gotta get out there
But
On the other side
Do you have the state of New Jersey
Came out it from a completely different
View point where they
You know we're just as interested in
Calling code helping the bear and making sure the
The Berrics
You know
Livid
I don't know best life I supposed to say
But they wanted to go by in a very different way as far as they were concerned it wasn't it was a wild animal
And you don't take a wild animal out of the Wild
Unless absolutely necessary fact that you saw this bear walking on two legs
There is a real Survivor
This is like a feet of evolution like this pair of all
To survive we should just let him do his thing
Davis still out there being a bear
It's the right thing to do
So this is
This is the part of the story
About pedals that we
We haven't told you yet
So
Petals was first found in 2014 first showed up
Shut up again the next summer and then yeah even early 2016 their videos of pedals and then nothing
And then a bear that has become a national sensation is
Is Dad the bear known as pedals
So in October of 2016
News broke that pedals
Batman killed
Turn the bear hunt on Monday
A place in New Jersey
A familiar story played out
This morning over the apparent killing of a
The fame blackbear
There was anger protest
Kill the bear
Dick piece of s*** death threats against an innocent Hunter
Selfie
Family
People have actually threatened to burn down his business
People posted photos of his home his wife's name and in the midst of all this
I think everybody out there should
State of New Jersey
People were angry at the state
Did nothing
About the bear
Where was the bet when people report is it Saturday injured for years
This is there
Where were they then
I was so rough
Had my moment you know
But people sent me bear things
You know like I have
I have like the little through the bear on top of the radio and
Sabrina got me a picture that looks just like that all the time
Beautiful artist that doesn't even know pedals but
Made this picture of a bear that looks just like I'm in
Just cool
About you know it's just
People thought
YouNow
They saw how hard
We fought
But the book is the best
It really is
And what's the writer's name John Williams
Yeah I talked to him he was nice
I remember being like
You want to what
So
John axley Road
Obituary for
Do you have a copy of the school
Is the New York Times Magazine's annual lives they lived
Got it
I just thought you know the way I've always
I thought I'd like the lies they lived
Bowie picture
You know it's about this many people
Interesting way to talk about the world that we live in
Janet Reno
Pedals the bear
One reason why I find conversations by animal so interesting is because
Animals always have no comment
Right there
You basically have groups of human being
Turtles eating around like a little screenshot
The pedal standing
Trying to figure out what to do with it walking towards the mailbox in the mail
Yeah and this is actually the picture that I used on his
Our version of Lake rest in peace petals memorial page
Yeah me too I felt like God you want me just to read the end of the Piece Special
Okay
Do you know the circumstances what is a hunter knew that bears identity before he or she fired
Weather panels.
Spend some time on all fours
Had been distinguishable from an ordinary bear
Whether he's been standing upright in the wilderness looking for posterous
Inconspicuous
Inconspicuously like himself
That is the best posture the reproof
What is resilience
Might have marked in for death
There's never clear what we owed pedals exactly
You could argue that allowing pedals to live in the woods
Be hunted like any other bear with an act of respect
Validation of his wildness
You could also argue that it was a gruesome lapse of human compassion
Pedal stood for something we may never agree what it was
Do you guys
Even the how did you
There wasn't a clip in there you didn't use a clip from the movie The Other clip the movie
Well a matter of
Bad we do
Where does this is where you send that thing again
Kim
We call
Bulshit
On your stupid rules
Play It Again
Bulshit
And yet in doing so you follow this
The beauty of it
Now
All right we're going to do or you take a little break
Are going to clear the air and come back with a couple producers to level up with more respect
Euros
Morning moments
Hi this is Jason studstill calling from Seattle Washington
Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred
P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of science
Send technology in the modern world
More information about Sloan @www
Sloan.
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents
Aunts and uncles teachers we're looking for stories about what we're calling
Tiny moments
Brilliance
Basically I want to hear about this
Times when a kid did something
It just means you lean back and say
Well
Maybe it was the moment that I
Kids you've been reading to 4 month started reading back
To you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lesson
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of their music
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed they're ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the
Epic moments where
Kid does something super smart
It doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story
T-shirt
Go to radiolab.org
Flash brilliance
Mrecorder
Short audio
And that's radiolab.org
Flash brilliance
Thank you so much
Chad Robert Radiolab Breaking Bad News Bears and we got three bears story so far
You know maybe this is the moment when I should admit that
Everybody broke repair
I can see that coming
You know and you woke up in the morning full of them figuring excitement would you do the hard news or would you right away
What you do the bad news
Like what I was hoping actually and I mean immediately Molly Simons had a little bit
Like the hurricane you just come in but I was really hoping was it somebody was going to get us
Solid Rock Solid breaking news about bear
Kind of thing and I actually had one in my sights that I was just sitting on waiting to see if anybody got it so
Something that the Trump Administration did though most people to know actually the seeds of it were planted during the Obama Administration wasn't
The grizzly bears
Came off endangered list it and in the wake of that there was about to be for the first time in almost 50 years
A hunt around Yellowstone
Because the Grizzlies have gone from like you know whatever it was a hundred left
2 now around 700
They've also started encroaching on
Makers campers hunters and Ranchers
These are the ideas that once you do list them which should be a success say they came back we can do list them now but also the same time that means that
We can start
Column
Mechoulam yasso the ranchers are geared up to get their licenses and head out there and have this hun
And at the last moment there was a court case and a judge said no no not time to do the Hun
And that happened a couple weeks ago and then that just at hunting season he's before the hunt or whatever it was I guess
What is the reason from the judge
I think clearly like some activists if they're not yet ready this will damaged
The population in so yeah the judge had kind of like that maybe that the administration hadn't shown
Enough recovery to Warren
Hunting
And but that then just two days ago that of that ruling got to have like either confirmed her upheld or whatever it is and now that
Functionally actually means that the grizzly is not
Dlisted
That it is still on the endangered species list and there's even some amongst
Bear
Turn Folk
You talk to you then they're not
Quite sure what to think because
If you're going to have an endangered species list you need to occasionally have
An animal come off of it
Hey need to win to win otherwise you just lose the political will to even
Yeah totally do it or you or you just
Show the doing it is pointless
You're going to lose them eventually sold on you never get off right now you need someone to get off and I guess
You know you can probably go back and forth for a lot about whether it's
Time for the
Yellowstone Grizzlies to be off or not but
Yeah so nobody got
That but but don't we have one more
On story and it comes from
Annie McEwen and lots of knots
Verses about bears
Some ways both really is another
Using the sense that it's recent but it's breaking news in that we're staying stuff
That is true about the world that has not been reported before
So it's
Breaking news about bears
Yeah I think so okay where do you start
Restart in the far north
In the Arctic Islands in Canada
Wintrust place you can imagine
With an Inuit Hunter named David katana
April 13th
Denying
I live in a small community
People and everybody knows
Pretty pretty lady
Anyway he told us the story of a hunt that he was on that was unlike any hunted ever been on before
Where he caught a bear
That was unlike any Berry you never seen before
What happened April 2010
Me and my wife were going hunting badgers nice morning
Shoffner
Top mesh weather in his wife said it understood used in Scooby-Doo
They're called up a I just don't like the snow machines that use mechanical device
They happen this canoes they headed across
The sea ice
And then they're heading towards
Cuz Island that are playing in camping in this empty cabin
You got to that cabin
Open account at the cabin with damaged Persian bears
Why they do that immediately
Anime side let's go back to another cabin
True love anniversary
Start heading back
Look for in the app
Afternoon following the court in court to a cabin
There was a hill
And I could see some traffic coming down
Down to the cabin
Fresh Bear Tracks around this
They're coming back
And that's the approach if they see that this
Cabin is also been Rancid
The bear has gone in
He broke the window
Okay well we'll continue on
So this is a third cabin they pass wow
The door open
Made a message say is it normal for a polar bear to go into cabins and throw mattresses at
Portable Thornridge Drive
Start tracking it again huacachina cop Holloway
And at this point they start getting a little worried
Because these tracks coming toward the community
Georgette Colfax
1/4 cabin ransacked and 1/5
Jesus been through and right next to the sisters A6 cabin
I noticed you're not open
Too close to the cabin this is this presumably the next
Destination for the bear
Sure enough
Is bear was Heidi
Grandma cabin
Constricted body
Start running
Shaw
Esthetician
Stop my steering for my rifle on a sled
Back of my heritage
Stranger standing up
I know
But this bear
Feeling better
Is differin
Something is off
I took a shot at
I hit it
He kills the bear
Mdlottery
They approached it on their schedules they get off
Despair
Looks
Strange
It's a blonde bear
Once you catch a grizzly bear before and that was my first time
Amber Lakes are dark. Boots and socks or whatever
Circles around
Wow interesting so he takes it back to town and he checked in with this government officer
Can I take a look at it and he's like David
I think this might not be a polar bear
Might not be a great leap
It might be a hybrid
Hybrid bear
Yeah like a little bit of both little bit of both
And David had never even heard of that before I have never actually heard of that it's not a common thing to happen
But a few years before David the bear
Extremely rare
Creature shot and killed in the Canadian Arctic first one ever was caught in the wild
Grizzly polar bear hybrid media
David Attenborough included
Bound passenger
Got really excited
So we've known for a while that it's happening out there and even David has encountered a few more
Out there in the wild
Two little teddy bear cubs
For sale hybrid
So cute this is some kind of crossbreeding between these two species
But
The crazy twist was when when this guy David Katana shot this thing at
This particular pizzly Berry sent it off for genetic testing
It's called the first
Second generation bear
The mother was
Polar bear half grizzly
And a father with a for Boost
This Bear That David shot
Is the first indication that
These bears are fertile
Which is something that you wouldn't think if a horse and a donkey
Say what
Together making me all those mules can't then have Offspring I thought that two different speakers
Different species
The branch off evolutionarily like hundreds of thousand
Pretty much the same time that we broke off from the Neanderthals and so be like us
Meeting a neanderthal
Odin the you know the
Crown Heights bar something and going home person and creating
Creating a specific it sounds like you had
Franklin Ave April 10th call me
Wait wait
Do they branch
Instead of the police and The great leap branches
At the same time is left in the neanderthal
Are around of a ballpark I mean all these are ranges so okay
I thought that's not
That doesn't work
What it kind of
Shouldn't work
But Wildlife manager Marshall Brannigan says
Sorted does I'm kind of against the bylaws
Terminology that we use for
Breaking the rules
But neither
Grizzly bear
Has been growing over the last few years
Mission in action
Grolar bear might not be considered a rare creature
For too long of general idea about this whole new species
Is it linked to the changing climate
Because now these two species are overlapping
Canada's grizzly bears North Wild
Polar Bears are losing much of their eyes
Spennymoor
Thailand
Polar bears
Have
Hair covering the bottom of their feet
Grizzly bears do not but it pads
Fit knee pads
Has like partial hair
Recovering
Feel like maybe you get the best of both worlds you know grip or whatever but also your your warm
So it's a good thing to be one of these half hybrid Vigor Best of Both Worlds
This is the new bear in town
Yeah
The may become increasingly common
That's kind of like a necessary we got interested in and that's the story
That has been reported
But then last year this paper came out and it
Kind of completely changes the story
And are we at the place where the where the the bears become breaking news
This is even more interesting than that first
It's way way weirder
It could more dramatically play out like on an HBO miniseries
Lay it on me
So last year a paper came out and it's signed if we talk to you Marcia Branigan is one of his co-authors
It is a basically made a big giant list of every
Sighting of a hybrid bear
And of all the genetic analysis to like every time we've seen this happen in The Wire
And all the information we could possibly glean from that
And what you found was it every single one of these hybrids can be traced back
21 female
Polar bear
One single bear
Really
Names
Bear 1096
Is she is she is literally the mother of all hybrid
Wow so there's something about this polar bear that seem to attract Grizzly gentleman
Or she was just interested in Grizzly gentleman
We mostly just have kind of guesses of how it went
Down since there were no Witnesses this is Elisa McCall she's
Staff scientist at polar bears internet
But we think
Could have happened
Is that there was a female polar bear and maybe she did have some you know interesting personal preference for brown bears or May
Maybe it was simply that
She was an estrus
And a Milky Way There
So she's giving off a scent that she wants to mate okay they leave the stinky butt
Trails and so males will follow them on the ice what are those smell like
Oh my gosh do you know I've never smelled that but I know to a male polar bear they smell good that's all I know
But as the female put downs
McNally Footprints the males are like
Oh yeah and they'll follow her for you know days and it's cute though actually put their feet right in
Footprints yeah so maybe there was just
This really aggressive brown bear grizzly bear mail
Follow the female track
XM could have fought off other
Polar bear male maybe this is a case of of like
Consensual but if you look at sort of like the genetic analysis it looks like animated with tutu
Grizzly bear she had babies with
Two different grizzly bears
And with one of them she had babies
Years apart oh so she's had three letters with with
This was two different grizzly bear
Interesting
Singer from the
3 non hybrid bear
So this is narrowing
Scope really quickly
Yeah just like species why'd you know new adaptation
It's just like
There's this one lady who has this one king
Strange Place Savannah
Those were just the only dudes around I was thinking like oh my God maybe this bear is a genius
Things like ice change around her and you think I need to save my DNA and the best way to do is to put it
With a grizzly
Is there doing better than I am that's hilarious I mean
Yeah I imagine that
Bears
Unfortunately
The hybrids are kind of a mess to be honest they were really well suited for land or for ice they were such an in-between bear
That they really just weren't that
Grizzly bears are so well adapted
To life on land and finding food got the big hump they've got the big whitehead they've got these long
Claws for digging they don't have fur on the pads of their feets they don't need it polar bears are
So well adapted for the ice they've got a much
Smoother Sneakerhead that helps him get in and out of seal hole they've got thicker sharper claws to grab seals and help them walk
Their fur is
Halo eye which helps trap warm air against their body is in the hybrid
They're like this weird in-between so their head is kind of like
Not really sleep but not really boxy kind of this weird in between They Don't Really blend in that while with the ice
Soar with the land cuz they're kind of this creamy color
And then there for itself is depending on where the Furs on the body
Is like a mix of
Halo but not Halo like
So yeah it backfired on
Nerf that was her
Is Marathon hot
But I like that idea don't these pizzly bears are just
Probably not
The new
Horizon of the bear that will
Accident
Top of that
So okay so it if you're Imagining the family tree right so there's a mama polar bear
With these two grizzly bears at different times write a letter to Dad in the stepdad
One of the kids
A daughter
And she's the only one who's had kids
And came from her
But it turns out that all those third-generation Bears including the
Bear the David
Katana shot
That bear the
The daughter bear she mated with her father
Wait
There's some sort of incest
Parts of the eye
Let's so weird
Kind of like dated the stepdad sort of thing
Yes or no
Yeah she slept with the same two dudes with her mom.
Oh my God
Gosh now we're going from HBO to like
Shakespeare
Yeah I like Greek
Tragedy years now all the sudden it looks less like a species wide
Movement for life will find a way
And it looks a little more like this is one crazy intro
Wow
So what do you make of that
Maybe this one like crazy inbred family is the
First
You know quite awkward attempt
What may become like
Might be like Evolution driving forward making shaky step up their shaky status
It's not like pretty the way you expected it to Ranchi because sex
Like like
Animals try things
Flights
This could maybe this is going to keep going but but
Only time will tell
There's no way for us to know
And one last thing which is
Kind of an ass
Afterthoughts but but maybe not
Because while it's not
Clearweather are polar bear family is is an awkward evolutionary step forward
Or just
Freaky
At what we do know
Is that nature is not
Zachary scheidt
When it comes to being sexually
Creative
7th Ave yes
So it turns out at the Museum of Sex they have this exhibit called The Sex lives of animals and my brother was coming in
Newtown Barn shy with the horns
And we thought incest is on theme I will send both of us I'm glad you got there cuz my mind went there and I was like
Well organized this before a thing but just so you know but then
Just made it all that more uncomfortable
But anyway you also didn't know about any of this
Cheap
A really
But we we got guns that room and Anna very nice woman and Steffy Spicer sodas around and
We learn just like
Nature is
Trying
Crazy stuff
Give me a give me a like a like a like a little
Sex through their blowholes crazy tongue penis
It comes from Aliens
Oh wow do you have threesomes
There's all kinds of
Butt stuff
Clitoris is another thing I'm starting to feel like I've been in here a while.
Being a little
Please
Then you'd like an abstinence room for brothers sisters are there a minute
7 Minutes where's the celibate
Space free passes to the boobie bouncy castle Italy Jimmy got to do it
We didn't usually
Add pictures to my parent
That's wonderful you and the Bear show right there
Meq and lots of Nasser and his brother Jim is a gym
Yes
Real quick special thanks
I think the windy card also to composer Anthony plug in the Fourth Movement from his fantasy movements titled very fast in May
Performed by the phonics
Tuba euphonium quartet
Off their album titled nuclear breakfasts
Available from Potenza music
And Stephanie Spicer at the Museum of Sex and
Also course
Fairmont 09
And thank you started for free
What's wrong with this woman
This whole idea into the hopper and come out with the with what we came out if you just came in
You go have a nice yet we'll say goodbye
Sorry and I'm sorry wheeler
Thank you listening
To play the message press to start of message
And this message