Are you awake
Listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
3-2-1 hey I'm chat album Radiolab and today we have
A
A legal case
Well it's actually
It's it's really more than just illegal
Suitcase
It's it's
What my husband and I referred to as a mental magnet
Once you start thinking about it it won't go away
It gets under your skin this is Lisa Lerman I'm a law professor at Catholic University
Epi Columbus school of law where she teaches legal ethics and she said that not too long ago with me and our producer Brenna Farrell
Who brought us the story
And under whose skin
It also seems
Yeah
It just made me
Not know whether to side with my head or my heart
And up
Take me to jump in and say this episode contains
Some violence and explicit imagery in it
If you're listening with kids
You
Just know that going in and you might want to skip this one
So to get the story started
Shirking Tracy my name is Jim Tracy and I'm going to Ward winning journalist
Glens Falls been reporting on this story since about 2,000 he's interviewed hundreds of people and I think there is
Isn't he he's been so focused on it is that
It's pretty close to home for him
I live in the foothills of the Adirondacks is where the Story begins
So Saturday night July 28th 1973
For young people
Go camping in the Adirondacks
Pulled off the road beside Road off Route 30
They made up a makeshift campsite
Grass clearing they set up two times and went to sleep for the night
And on Sunday that you know I woke up
And
About 9 a.m. campers
Hurt somebody walking outside their
Their time
And I'll suddenly heard the zipper
And the time go up and what they saw was as middle-aged man. Into the tent
Look like a conservation officer he had a fedora with a feather on it sunglasses a rifle he had a buck knife
Binoculars around his neck
And very calmly he told them
Almost politely to step out of their time which they did the other two campers
You're all four of them rounded up together
And they're kind of standing in a semicircle
And then the man cock the gun and said listen to I've killed before and I'll kill again
I'm going to take your gas by don't want to get caught so I'm going to tell you the trees
They started marching the kids off into the woods
Took him into the woods near a brook in pairs a 2 with him behind them
The kids of course were scared out of their wits by themselves
You nosey pointed the gun at him and then the last one he type
So after we had the four people tied
He went back to
The first boy 18 year old fell down blue ski and the forest
They couldn't really see what was happening because you're clearly
And I'm
They heard vomiting sounds when they heard Phillips voice get really high and
They knew something was happening something bad was happening to him what was happening with his buck knife
Stop in 5 times in the chest and when this happened three of them and their Panic were able to break
Loose and start running Nick fiorello ran to his car Carol and malinowski ran through the woods
But the man caught one of them
David Freeman he took the boy back to the campsite
And he had them lay down in a ditch next to him to kind of monitor the situation I guess
Supreme Inn in
The killer laying in the ditch an hour
The man command at the other two campers the ones we gotten away had managed to alert
All sudden they spotted them killer
And Freeman
Laying down in the ditch and when they did Freeman got up and ran towards the man screaming for help saying he
He's got a gun he's going to shoot
And a man with a gun
Just kind of stood up
Calmly and coolly walked into the forest
And thus began
What was at the time the largest man on State history state police cars parked almost
Does far up the road as you can see when the Manhunt commenced on Monday morning many deputies in the State Police standing by
It was a scene like a never been seen before up there
Roving patrols man armed with all kinds of weapons rifles shotguns bloodhound
Helicopters game right now like Monday or Tuesday they had 200 men on the case
Out of the Woods eventually find the man's car and they're able to run the license plate and it comes back with an ID
837 year old Robert Garrow Robert Francis Garrow Sr of Syracuse New York
Looking forward today he was an ex-convict in prison for rape of 7 years
Alpine with a 30-30 rifle a knife and the story was on every TV station CBS ABC and NBC
So by Tuesday people got panicked
People loaded the rifles they block the doors for the first time and we've noticed a lot of people leaving around here
People left the area so fast
They left behind coolers on what happened with Carol was able to use those camps and
That food in those drinks to survive about 400 men now
The police
Follow a lead that he had stolen the car and he had been sighted and they
They're kind of closing in on him
And then the 12th Thursday August 9th 1973
Very very hot day one of the hottest of the summer officer named Hillary LeBlanc
Sparta Gyro
He said freeze or drop your gun something to that effect
And Carol started running
LeBlanc fire four times
Got him in the back
The arm in the foot
Darrell went down once got back up and kept running chasing through the forest
Distant very short time they saw Daryl and he was laying down in the mud
Cuz he was just laying there
But that you know I took his pulse and everything and he was certainly alive
Put him in an ambulance and they rushed him to the nearest hospital in Plattsburgh and According to Jim a couple of
Cops go with him
They're going in the whole time because they think that you might have been responsible for an additional murder and for a girl who's Gone Missing
But he wouldn't talk
At this point
Did the story that I'm interested in really get started
It's known as the buried bodies case and I think one of the things
So fascinating about the
Case this is my professor Lisa Lerman use the conflict
Between what a good lawyer should do
And what a good person should do
In the situation
Required to the guy at the center of this conflict was a man named Frank Armani
Frankie charmany
The lawyer in Syracuse
I never know whether to pronounce it
Arman AR
Terminator
That's Mary Armani
Frank's wife
Harmony
But it is
Armani
Couple months ago pretty sure Simon Adler and I went up to visit them
They live right outside of Syracuse New York
Mister Money is now in his 80s he's retired
My name is Frank
Armani
And I was the attorney for Robert Carroll
Where do I buy I love to have you start wherever you like how did this whole
Story start for you
Give a bit of background
Mitt Romney told me that when he was a kid
You got picked on for a couple different reasons and he said he was always a guy that it wouldn't walk away
Lightfoot
Fights
Physical fights
I'd like standing up for the little guy and that's partly why he became an attorney
Search for a Defender
You're fighting to stay
And Taryn and he's doing really well he's well-respected had a good reputation
But
Thanima Robert Caro
Black hair strong man
To take him out
Need a 45
And I just had that feeling that this guy
Is dangerous
And a lot of things are going to happen
This is a year before the Manhunt
1972 Frank remembers he represented in
At first onto pretty small things
A school teacher has a salted his child he was under the suit of school and I
I talked him out of it
And then he had an automobile accident I represented my back
But then
Pretty quickly
Dark Gyarados charged with trying to kidnap two college kids
That case got dismissed but then
Melissa see some young girl kids very young girls age 10 and 11 Guerra was released on bail
He skipped his court date
And just disappeared
And then we pick up where we left off
The murder The Manhunt
An August 9th
The night girl got captured
Frank gets a call
From girls wife
Telling me that you wanted to talk to me Armani to represent my impression is that Armani
Didn't want to do it in my mind I'm saying what the hell do I want to get involved in this
Go for it never handled a murder charge from murder case you didn't know
How the problem was Gary wouldn't talk
Any lawyer except for Armani attorney
Eventually decides to go and talk to the judge you've been assigned to the case
And the judges basically like
We have an obligation to provide the council
That this guy wants
So I mean unless you have a good reason why you can't do it
I want to appoint you his public defender
Anna Ronnie agrees
And so at that point
He has to defend Carol
Yeah
So this is reporter Jim Tracy again
Together as friends or families picnic together to help them with this case
As co-counsel because I felt I needed support LG was the top criminal defense lawyers
In central New York I need someone with brains and guts
So our money goes to talk to belge
I just need backup that's it has no money in it
The prosecution had three eyeball Witnesses they had his car at the scene of the crime and they had his two-week flight he was
Guilty and I said come on I'm not going to try to prove you didn't do it send
Maybe girl murdered this kid maybe it was because he had temporarily gone insane
I'm telling you about my Siri and have that Armani tells him
We pulled this off a while but eventually
I'm in
Frank
Now we're into late August 1973
I got there they want a big girls room on the fifth floor of the hospital
Police are standing guard
They walked into the room
I haven't seen them in a while
We greeted each other and we talked
And just a picture this
Jim told me that the room they put garro in was what he described as a training observation room which meant that it had
Does big window that ran alongside girls bed
So they could keep an eye on it and the cops are stationed right outside
Just
Watching
And According to Jim and I should save her different accounts about this but apparently the cops had brought in a lip read
To try to see what year was saying I don't think you can do that
That's not legal I think that's
Probably not okay but from the cops perspective they think that he's involved in recent merch
Murder and missing girl
And they think that girl could still be alive
So they want to know
Absolutely anything they can that's going to get them closer
2 solving that murder and finding that girl
But at the same time the defendant has to be able to share absolutely everything with the lawyers and know that there
In that safe space of that relationship because we have
Sixth Amendment right to counsel and the Fifth Amendment right
Not to incriminate oneself
Free meet speakers attorney
Then we have no real Justice sister Army and LG
They need as much information about what Gareth has done as they possibly can get so they can start to build
Their defense
I don't like surprises
I'm the kind that wants to know everything
Wow so so what that as a lawyer you're in a strange spot here
He needed to get from Garrow his story and it needed to be just that me didn't want the cops in on it yet
Don't know if there is TAPS in the room or what so they're turn up the TV turn up the fans but
He was playing games so he talked basically about anything but
But the cases
Kept saying he couldn't remember you couldn't remember and they're they're trying to convince him like
You got to talk to us if you're going to have any shot Lynch Mob out there
There's Witnesses in Cairo new
He could be going to prison he could be going to prison for a long time maybe 25 to life and pedophile in prison
Careful things and get rough
But they tell him if you talk to us
Maybe we can get you not guilty by reason of insanity
Only defense to help get Garrow into a mental hospital instead of a prison that was the Galt
If you have anything to say
Took several conversations to get Garrett at this point
But finally
Portosol out
At this point it was just belge in the room
And I told him
Yes he had killed them booski
And it also killed other people too and the episodes
When Garrow kills people seem to have
I followed a like a pattern you would get these intense headaches
And you know become psychotic and do horrible things
When it came to the details keep tended to not remember but then
Girl mentions two particular girls who were then missing
And his parents had no idea where they were twenty-one-year-old Susan pads and another girl 16 year old Alicia Hawk
Susan pets
Bus from Chicago she's a girl I mentioned earlier cops were already looking for her hoping that girl might have some information
Earlier that summer
Her boyfriend had been found murdered the two of them have been camping and Susan have been gone ever since
Alicia Hauck
She's a high school girl from Syracuse
She gone missing just a couple of days before Susan
Everybody thought
She might have just run away
But Garrett told the lawyers
That he had killed them and where he had left their body
One odd thing about the arrows
Description of the incidence
He doesn't say I killed her
He says
She got stabbed with my knife
Like it wasn't even him doing the stabbing right
Like this is
What do you do first and foremost you have to ask yourself
Is this
True you know your client is obviously severely mentally ill this could be
A dream he had it could be a delusion if you're going to go and
You know craft an argument and in
Preventive strategy you need to know
What actually happened
Don't you walk out the door
He grabs Frank and he says let's go
So they they sleep outside
I get in the car
And
We take off to go look for the bodies
Caro told lawyers that Susan pets was in an air vent of a
Close-up Mineshaft
The mine is up in Mineville an hour south of the hospital
Are you scared are you excited like
You scared you're concerned yet fear you're a fool if you don't
In the rearview mirror they got a little spooked State Police
So eventually they pull over get out of the car
In
Went into one bar where one of Francis belge
Lady friends
What's hanging out
We're about 30 minutes build you talk to her then asked if he could borrow her car
Door
Took off driving the lady friends cartoon
Until they got back on the highway and they drove through the Adirondacks until finally they get
Here as far as we're going to go
Okay we can walk
Up to this old abandoned mine
Went out there last February with reporter Laura mckinstry and
The town supervisor of Mariah TomSka the father
So this is a road that goes to the mines or what is
It was this sort of hilly area off the side of the road
Jamberry I see that day
This hair
This used to be in Allroad 1
We're walking up a very wooded
Hill
Fairly steep ever no leaves
And all the trees were
Black and Clarice Calico
The only way they could have came in here
So
Here we are in
Our Sunday suits
And here we go trudging through the
Forest
Looking for the key
Respect
Notable Works looking around
And then
We found this
What are vent
You see the airshaft here they find this air shaft which is just a hole in the ground
Couple feet across
That shoots up from
Down in the depths of the Mind be careful that this is giving me such
Yeah you don't want to slide down in there
And so they couldn't see anything
Down the hole
So Frank Armani lay down on the ground at the
The edge of The Mineshaft got a flashlight that he takes out my feet
And let me down in there
And as Frank got lower down into the hole
I could see her snake
The blue shoe
A blue
Sneaker
Bandana leg
I said to myself this son of a b**** did it
And yells back up to bail to get out of here
Put me back up
Eventually belge found the other body
Alicia house party
Choosing a cemetery where Garrow had said he'd left her
But Armani wasn't there when told you found
So what ensued
Was a very long struggle
Where the Warriors
Try to figure out what to do with the information about
The bodies of these girls
So what's the other play that out what
What are your options
Sure so option1 we've got to call the police
We've got to tell the prosecutor
These are missing kids
We're the only ones who know you know shouldn't we just call the police
No you can't
You just can't
We took her know to keep the confidences of a client under the current rules
Which app developed quite a bit since
The time is 7
Anything that is related to the representation of a client
Is under the confidentiality umbrella
So
You're not supposed to
Tell anybody
Step to prevent reasonably certain death or substantial bodily harm
That will be
That is it can be or will be
Right so
So in this situation the two girls are dead
Then there's no future crime it's over
It's done
And even if
The parents of the missing girls in question
Are frightened and waking up and even if they have hired
Detectives and even if the local police are combing the woods and the taxpayers are paying for that
But there's no ifs IFS
People are already dead then you do the lawyers
That's right
It's a really tough job to be a defense lawyer you
Have a very particular part to play you you have a roll
And that roll
Isn't what you think as a person is
Good and right and what you would do for your friend or family member that situation what your role is
Is today
Play the part of a system in which you're the one
Who stands up for the guy that everybody else
Hates
Even if
Everybody hates you even if
Maybe you hate yourself a little bit you have
To do your job and that job is to be in the role of the person
That fights as hard as they can for their client
The lawyer is
The agent of his client
Only only the agent or Contour also a citizen and a member of the part of the justice system in
There's a there's a
There's a double murderer here
And family seeking to find out what happened he now knows what happened
Right is there a week your building on
On the side of tell just tell
Help
Of course
Yes and I knew Mr Hogg from Bowling
Persis
The other daughter my daughter were in the same class and I knew him from churching
You have to be an animal doctor
Feel
Vanquish is apparent
Of the family
And yet you have your duty as a lawyer
You're caught between the two more morality
So now what does he do coming up that hard
Spot gets even harder
We'll be right back
Hi this is Lizzie from Arlington Texas
Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world more information about Sloane at WWE
W. Sloan. Org
Okay hey I'm Jared I'm Rod I'm Robert krulwich
This is Radiolab
And no
Get back to our story from producer Brenna Farrell
When we left it there where they were stock right
Need it with a new this thing believe the client was very guilty of something they found the bodies of these
Two girls
Now
What's their next move
Well
So they decide to
Plea bargain
The take this information to the prosecutor and
Say I have information that will help you solve some cases
Some cases yes
And in exchange I want you to give me
A better day
Get Garrow into a mental off
Instead of a prism
Oh so right away they're going to use this as Leverage
That was
The idea
You going to give a little and you're going to take a little while that's kind of gross no yeah he's trying to get a better deal
For this
Murderer but I mean if you think about it from Frank's perspective
He's got this information
As a person he doesn't want to have to keep that secret so if he plea Bargains then that's a way for him to get some clothes
Lawyer for the family because he can give the information to the prosecution but he's also not selling out his client
So crazy again
I called a meeting with Henry McCabe from the state police
And the district attorney at armories office
And
When they met
Army Belgian search the briefcases of the VA in the investigator make sure they weren't wearing a bug
Because they're paranoid there's going to be a wiretap or some sort of bug
And then bailed you presents
The deal he says listen I've got information on two bodies
I want you to agree to put my client in a mental institution instead of sending them off to prison
And the prosecutor apparently very quickly puts two and two together and then immediately thought
Holy s*** are you talking about Susan and Alicia like these are the two girls that we are
Most concerned about we think they're alive
And belge said I'm not telling you anything unless we have a deal
Both the VA in the investigator. That the lawyers were absolutely ludicrous
They thought they lost her mind get a better sentence for a murderer by offer
Is murder victims Are you seriously bargaining with people's lives
Yeah but also I'm sure that the prosecutor do
That this was doubtless
The highest-profile case
That would ever come to him and so as the prosecutor you're not going to look so good if you give a deal to this
Reprehensible man
Know well what the hell's the difference is you gonna get life
No matter what
How many times you want to give him life but the meeting only lasted like 5 minutes
Collapses completely to back up a little ways
That was particularly devastating for Armani because just the day before
Susan Pat's father flown in from Chicago
To Syracuse I remember mr. pets
Coming to my office
Any side can I meet with you and talk to yuan
An Armani agreed to it so he comes in
Takes a seat from father to father is there anything you can tell me about my daughter I mean
The papers
Think that that Daryl probably has something to do with her disappearance is there anything at all
That he's told you that that can help me
I couldn't tell him anything they can't tell you there's nothing I can tell you
Remember trying to
Assure him that
I've got a meeting set up
All I can say is it's what state investigators
The prosecutor on the case
They could have some information
Trying to
Give them hope
We will bring it to a conclusion
I thought we would
But we did
So then when Mr pets leaves Mr Armani
Elisabeth
He threw a bunch of books
We got through the phone basically just you know destroyed his office
Just trying to relieve
That I couldn't help the man because he's looking right at this man knowing exactly
Imagine what he's going through like Armani had lost
A brother
Was much younger
Is 4 years younger than
Is an Airforce pilot
And in 1962
Plane went down and he was lost at sea
So after that Armani said his mother
She be up at night crying she would like go to bed at night
Cheerleading
You know she couldn't
Ever recover from it
Because you can't you know you just
You don't really know but you know
So
I can understand that
And that's
You know that's partly why this was so hard for her money because
When that plea deal fell apart that
Was his
Chance to try to get this information to
The family
When's The Plea fell through he didn't have any other options for sharing that information he was stuck
What's up
What happens next so they have to go to trial and that means that Armani and Dolce have to knuckle down
I tried to present an insanity defense
Meanwhile
Armani he said he couldn't sleep he was having nightmares
Running down your back
Go sit at the kitchen table drinking coffee and is waiting for the morning paper to come
Because he was just alone with that he was
Alone with the secret
And he knew
That moment the police are
Trying to find these
She knows that the parents are holding out hope that they might still be alive
You're questioning yourself
Very young
You're hurting people
Tell you begin to wonder am I in the right profession
You know you're looking for a
You're looking for a way to give
The information on
You know Monica synonymous call
Sure
Well
If I'm going to do it I want to do it openly yeah
I don't know
Did he ever
Fever break
No
But according to him know my mind
I was doing what I thought was the proper
Ethical legal moral
Moral
Thing
Tutu
And then
In December of 1973
5 months after the girls disappear
Their bodies happened to be discovered
Within two weeks of each other
Susan's body is discovered by two kids were playing up in the mines Alicia I guess I think a student from
Syracuse University which is right next door to the
Cemetery is walking through an instant balls upon her until she's discovered then to
And then six months later summer of 1974
Even though
Robert quiroz trial for the murder of the blue ski begins
Apparently beaten Not Guilty by reason of insanity
Turn order to make that case what they decide to do is is to put Guerra on the stand
And Carol would tell his whole life story to shock the jury's mind including all these murders and
Police rapes to see that he was at the time he was not
Sharon Smith Channel 6 News
So
The trial opens
The courtroom is jam-packed
Prosecution starts they have really good case that got a good lawyer from Syracuse that joined to help the guy from Hamilton
County
And then it's
The time for the defense
To start their case
Te Velde stands up and he calls his first Witness
Robert Garrow
To the stand
Girl gets on stand and he
Starts telling his life story and it's
Horrible
Severe beatings and abuse by parents
Girl education you basically gets
Sent off to a farm 2
Work like as an indentured servant when he 7
You're slaughtering Bolognese 8 years old weird stuff like that he starts like drinking blood having sex with the animals
And then
He starts admitting to
A series of rapes
Throughout his adult life
And
He
Admits to killing
Alicia and
Susan
And what happens next
Nobody's quite sure if it was a slip-up or maybe it was on purpose but when garrow's talking about Sue
Susan pets
Belge
Says
Is that the one I found
So the cat was out of the bag then the next day Belgian Armani pull depressed
Conference to try to explain why they haven't told anyone
They had the duty to protect their clients secrets
Is disgusted
World you're going to convince your average non-lawyer everybody turned against them
Greek and Avalon of Justice prosecutors let out that our money in Belgium and actually tried to use these dead girl
As leverage for garro the headlines in the Syracuse papers would say bodies used as Pawns in a game of war
Who is bedlam getting death threats in the mail
Play how can you live with yourself kill you at one point he finds a dead fish in his car his wife
Find sunlit Molotov cocktail in the backyard started to carry a Shotgun in the car
Are kept in the house so we could sleep
Paris
That was the worst moment of my life
Awesome horrible thought
I had some more
June 27th
Robert Garrow is convicted for the murder of philip domblewski
He's given the maximum sentence he's given 25 years to life
In a maximum-security prison
How did how did that feel
Free relief
Yeah you know
It's over what
But then it is up to the grand jury at self in their investigation to determine which charges
Green against the
Pretty soon after the verdict Armani and bailed you learn that they could be facing criminal charges
No one's really sure exactly what those might be but it could be something like tempering with evidence
Obstruction of justice or
State public health law
And the provision that says that the body must be given
Quick and decent burial
And on top of that
Greatest amount of controversy is the one over the attorney-client privilege
There was an ethical complaint filed against Armani and belge so basically they were then facing disbarment
An investigation into the ethical complaint
That would drag on several years
LG started drinking heavily abandoned his law practice and moved to Florida
Armani talked it out but he suffered no one wanted him as a lawyer anymore
What else can I do
To make a living
He was just
Barely getting by for a little while I think of all the stress and pressure
Takes its toll
In fact he has a heart attack
Well this is all going on
But eventually
The criminal charges are dropped and the ethical complaint
Is the Smith
And the reason in a
Opinion of the court and the the State Bar is it Belgian or money did
Was right
What they did was good
Exactly
According to the law and my view is Frank Armani
You know real life
Shiro
I would say you know people
So admire Atticus Finch in the difference between
Atticus Finch and Frank Armani
Is that Armani is real person
Eliza told me about this panel she organized back in 2007
What is for the American Bar Association a big conference on professional responsibility and there were about 400 people in the
The room most of them lawyers
They were there to watch
On stage
The featured speaker Frank Armani
And it was love
What is this what is that feel like in did you ever think you'd
Get to that point
When you were in the midst of the hardest parts
No
Never dreamed
I don't think I was a hero I just was a lawyer that did his job
I mean
I was a good lawyer
At least I thought so I everybody
And now it over 40 years later
This case let's talk about and what Armani and belge did
Dead bodies case
Staton law schools across the country everybody
Teaches the case it's like a touchstone
What it what is
People say so I went to a couple of classes I went to one legal ethics class and I also went to a criminal defense
Dance class here in New York that was being taught at 4.
I agree his duties to his client he represents
His clients
Interest
Stiff and then sitting in on his classes and in talking to law professors
I think one of the reasons that
That this case is hot so widely is because
Professors can point that they can point to a real human being at the center of a really tough legal situation and they
And say in this situation
This is what a lawyer should do
This is what a lawyer should
Should be
From the moment I started thinking about this story
I always wanted to talk to the
Families involved which
Proved really difficult
Wrote letters
To both families and I made a bunch of phone calls
And understandably no one wanted to talk to me
But eventually
I did Tsar corresponding
With a family member of one of the
Victims
And she didn't initially didn't want to go on the record but we emailed and
And after Fue
Phone calls
She ended up changing her mind and decided that she did want to go on the record
With me on the phone call
Would you mind
Telling us who you are
Your name in
Occasion
Okay I'm I'm Roberta pets
Susan
Mother
Susan was the girl from Chicago
She's a college student who died
Gone missing while she was camping with her boyfriend
End
Shih Tzu Armani and algae found in the mine
As I've explained before my interest really
In the story of has to do with the fact that it seems that
That it's become
Sort of a key part of how a lot of legal ethics
Classes talk about the concept of confidentiality
And so I sort of wanted to just
Start
With that idea to ask if that's something that you knew that law schools are teaching and and
If you had any feelings or thoughts of
I had no idea that this was being taught in law school
And I'm pretty horrified to think that
This is what
Is considered to be
Correct
Cuz I don't think it's ethical at all and to think it's being taught at the right way
To do things
In an ethical classes
Totally incomprehensible
And was the first that you'd heard that it wasn't out when I have reached out to you it was
In talking to you that I know that yet
Maybe they Odyssey
Not only about the criminal who they're trying to defend
But what about the victim
And I think that that should at least be
An equal thought nevermind
If not
A greater consideration
Did it did you have a feeling
Did that you really weren't taking into consideration as as all of this was happening
Yes
Only
My husband and I when we first heard that she was missing
We flew
Immediately in
Went to the police station and
When we were there
Sitting
With the police
They received the policeman at the time that we were with received a phone call that Danny's
My daughter's boyfriend
What his body was found
And that's that
All we knew and we never really had any updates
Nobody told us what was going on and
Obviously there was no closure and it was just
Getting worse and worse
And then the only other time we were contacted by the police
Read some Authority I can't even remember who
Was when her body my daughter's body was found like 5 months later
And in the meantime of course we were all going crazy Mike
My father is a matter of fact
Even went so far as to contact the cycle
That's how
How important it was and how it was our entire life during that period
And as far as
Visiting the lawyer which my husband did
It was a total lie lie
The lawyer
Maybe he considered it to be ethical but what he was doing was lying to my husband
And causing us more months
Abhor
And this is what is being taught in law school
So anyway
Just to try to be third ever involved
As far as I've
Encountered anyone
By law professors law students there when they approach this as it's with a lot of sensitivity and they are
They are struggling with the pain that I think the
Instinct is to side with the families and to imagine what they went through but my feeling is that
How could
Any of us possibly imagine that if we hadn't gone through it
And so I guess that's
That's why I was hoping to talk to you too kind of
Let you have a chance to
Communicate some of that
Experience
How to really communicate in words
I mean 40 years later I'm still
I like it and it's soda struggle to
Disgusting
Because
You'll never go away as long as I live
I don't know I guess
Wondering
We've been talking a lot of
Bad stuff and wondering if there's anything you would like to say about
Susan that the doesn't have to do with any of this that you would want people to know
That you want to share I don't
Nothing you don't have to
Well
What can I say she was
She did receive her degree posthumously
We we didn't go and pick it up at
Boston University
Difficult for us
And
And Danny who is her boyfriend had been just that summer
And he had a full scholarship
Andrea graduated just a year before and
So true life
And I'm sure the other two children him
Great futures
I haven't been true
It's just a horrible tragedy
It's
It's so
Horrible
No
To be in their position
Do I have to live through that
I mean
How do you relate Lucina tartar
I'm worried what excuse is there for
To protecting the person to kill her
No justification you can justify it in my mind
I don't expect them to accept it
But
That's the way it is
I'm going to get just a minute of
Silence up here if it's okay
I can hear this
Echoes of dogs on the mountain things tend to travel up to
What the hell is going to bounce around
Water I think it's
From deeper down in there dripping I can't tell
Where is ripping everything up here is
Frozen solid
Sure what that is
I think I'm going to turn back around
Frozen puzzle
Flowers
Bankstar producers Ferrell and Men
Kiltie and to Jim Tracy who's currently writing a book about all this the working title is Twisted soul
Thanks also to Tom alibrandi author of privileged information with Frank Armani also to learn schoolyard
Terror in the Adirondacks Cheryl by Fordham University Leslie Levin and the students at the University of
Etiquette School of Law Clark D Cunningham at Georgia State University's College of Law Debra Armani Brian Fair
Jennifer Brumback Nick Capaldi Che and archive researcher Stephanie Jenkins
Start of message
Radiolab is produced by Jed abendroth Dylan Keith is a director sound design suorin realtor is senior editor
Jamie York is our senior producer
Our staff includes Simon altar
David Lee Roth College
Andy Mills Latif Nasser Melissa O'Donnell Aryan whack
Molly Webster without from Alexander and Leon
Stephanie Tam and Mccalla Winger
Checkers art David Asher Michelle Harris
And this message