Listening to Radiolab
Radiolab WNYC
Come On Eileen
Hey this is Radiolab on something that's a little bit unorthodox today least for us
Yeah if you listen to the show in the last
10 years
You understand it like
We like to edit
Brightwheel
Do you like a good at it
Or 70 but today play something that has
Almost no edits at all
It's just a conversation
Which is of course the foundation what we do
These long
Rambling
Occasionally profane
Error
Strewn conversations that we've been at it into something coherent
Today
I want to show you the messiness no edit
This is a
Chunk of a conversation with science writer Carl Zimmer
He came and sat down with us
A while back
Can we talk
4 hours
Two of those hours
Became the basis for
Crispr podcast it was a few podcasts to go this about Gene editing
Then we kept on going for another two hours and he told us
This story actually two stories with rolling play one
That I thought was really cool
It's about this
New way of looking at life
It's not a
Yeah we can get through this a lot faster than
I really like
How do I I need
Perfect perfect way to describe
Biological bomb Okay so
Chappie
After 2
The story monster
What's the Once Upon a Time
So
Once Upon a Time
Being
I say what
Once Upon a Time being before 2003
We basically had two kinds
Of
Living things on
That we had
Cellular life and we had Myra
Send
There was nice and distinct
And clear-cut
And so
Cells included
It's our bodies made of cells and
Bacteria which
Single-celled
All the other
Things that can grow and let their cells divide they have DNA they have proteins in the mail.
And then over here you have virus
Viruses were just little packages of genetic material that
Would go from cell to cell and use the cell to make new virus
Enter inside of the mall they had with jeans
And
A couple proteins that
What then
Hijack
Their house seem like soap
Soap
Preliminary
They don't even maybe not even qualify as life right
They can't grow on their own
They can't generate their own energy
So
Austin Eliza Schuyler life we
Mii Maker
Kind of fuel called ATP
We need that
Do every little thing in our body and virus
Oasis don't make ATP so
Can we say that life is
Ice cells and multicellular being
And
Then there's a
Like sort of
Pseudo life
When you have these little
Yeah yeah a lot of people a lot of Sciences don't really think viruses are truly alive
Even though they just have to take advantage of life
To make more copies
Custom questions of viruses they don't have a wall around them in the way they sell cells are walls
Essential ER walldorf
They might have a protein shell
Ends and so you know when the flu virus goes into a cell that protein shell
Breaks open and the genes and proteins inside come out that you have containers
The contain them forgot for a while
Isn't that one of the
Somebody who had a had a list of
Rules that make you alive and what was in that container was one of those rules
If they have the container
Right so the problem with viruses that they have
Some of the things that we think are essential for life
But not quite all of them so
It's been convenient just to say viruses are not
I'm over there cuz I don't have everything
That cellular life has
What is Heather now
Got a virus
Gotcha
And then
So then what happened is that there was a scientist named
Timothy rowbotham
In England
Who was investigating a
Timothy Rudolph
English name in rowbotham with a fuzzy robots and was was working in Bradford
City in England
And
She was
Looking at the kinds of bacteria that might be growing in
A hospital
Yeah like they're they were having some problems with pneumonia outbreaks in Saint and he's like okay what
Growing around
And so he went to
Turn off cooling tower
Pur water on top of the hospital and he took a sample in the
Went and put it under his microscope and he's like some interesting bacteria are all here so
Very interesting bacteria that
Didn't I look like anything I've seen before
Stop and just kind of crawl around to weird places and just snatched little snippet to
Scummer what Woody
John is a microbiologist
So it would be good to know like I mean
I don't like about just do it just go scrape little
It's a rocker
What are 10 words the world I mean microbes are everywhere so microbiologist go everywhere to find microbes so there
Steven Universe
Water tower on hospice
Received it with you in a in a kind of an investigatory role he was trying to help them
Help them figure out which bacteria
Make music
I'm that was one of the hopes
But he was
Thinking of doing a survey because you know their diseases like Legionnaires disease which
You know I grow in these desert containers of water
You know that's
There there's some concern about that
That's so you know better to get to know what's growing
Tow
He's particularly taken by one
Thing that he assumes is bacteria and it's got a kind of interesting kind of rounded shape America
And when bacteria around you can call him
Cocci
A caucus
I'm so he names this Bradford caucus
Give it a name
That's why the caucus name it comes up as referring to the shape
Except
Streptococcus
Is because it's
It's round
I did not know
The things you learn
So so
He's trying to study this thing and it's trying to
So one when your machabeli just the way you study bacterias you get them to grow
And he can't get this to growlies feeding at things in a cell
I crying why is it not growing I can't figure it out and
Eventually
You know he e just hit the hit the wall
And unfortunately
His lab
Got shut down
I'm in so he
Basically said okay I don't want to
Throw the stuff out
I'm going to
I'm going to give it
To some of my colleagues in
It was it wasn't dying which was growing scientist named Bernard lascola
And is called
And they going to put a butterfly
And then he just says I'm
You just set that aside for a while and doesn't you know
Was just more bacteria you know and end
Ads for some reason
He decided to
I'll take a look at this Bradford caucus
You know I'm like what was this thing that that robot them
I was talking about
So he looks at it and he says
Okay this is the size of
Bacteria on butt
It looks like a gigantic virus
A virus is usually very small
Exactly
Tell bacteria to a virus is like
Like hundreds of times bigger hundreds of times
Hotel Queen Mary 2
Writing that he looked up close and he was like
What is this thing
This doesn't look right this this
If I didn't know better I'd say this
This was a virus
Vis-a-vis based on
Internal Orion
Chichen Itza pyramids
Mexican that had the protein thingy and host of viruses they have a shell
Beta protein
And the shells going to compose a plate
So it kind of looks like a soccer ball
Says a very distinctive look
Okay
It look like that
Didn't look like bacteria
It's like wait a minute
You could this be a virus
This would be like in maybe like finding an enormous soccer ball
In the woods
Yes to he's found the
The Leviathan equivalent
Virus
Right it didn't make sense it was good it was kind of crazy
In that microscopic round to say maybe this is a vine
Wait to dinner
To Brad Mumford what's his name again
Timothy rowbotham
Rowbotham
Didn't have this
Realization
He hadn't looked at it closely enough
He looked at it
But he just didn't somehow put that pussy
Did this is a virus and click Formosa Tuesday Wednesday
And it's
If it's likely that other people were looking at the same things in years before
I'm thinking there bacteria
Here's a big fear something the size of bacteria
Because viruses are always small then they that you wouldn't think of
Spell viruses
Are always small in the sense that
They were discovered because they were small
The basic design what scientist did was they they discovered viruses by filtering
Fluid from a sick plant or sick animal
Through a filter porcelain actually and it was so small that that
Anything the size of bacteria got trapped in the porcelain and anything smaller
And lo and behold I could find things that could cause sickness
In that fluid
Cast of the film
What's the discovery of viruses meant he was innately small because that's how you feel
That's what they were looking
So they were probably Generations the scientists who were looking in through microscopes
Saw some interesting around saying and assumed it was
Is bacteria and was probably a virus
F*** is this giant
Giant Leviathan
Virus
I seen that was his question
Well I mean would that he first he had to really establish that it wasn't so what happened was that
I'm eating look very closely at it and kind of work at its chemistry
And the more I looked at it
The more
It look like a virus he started
Abdul
Start acting looking at its DNA which hadn't been possible before
Turned out that its DNA resemble
The DNA viruses not have any known
Bacteria
I didn't have
I didn't actually didn't have the the the
Equipment for making fuel inside of it
And
Then the real kicker was that
He found out how to grow it
What he had to do was he had to stick
This thing inside of
Amoeba
And then out of the ameba will come
Laura Bradford caucus
Just like a virus
Exactly like a virus so you need to change the name for Bradford Cox
This is something else so they named it meme
Mimi viral virus
Because they were in France and memes
In the in a French Opera
He was mimicking
Yeah
Mini Me
Is that like a French word for Mac
I think I just took another beginning of mimic and added it to virus
I guess it's the same thing twice meme
I get it
Yeah
So this so
This is what I mean this was really bizarre when they published
The report on this in 2000
Three men people really scratch your head because
Remember you no ordinary viruses have you know maybe 10 jeans
This one had a 1018 GMC
When you have 10 jeans go to the gene site so you have a protein capsule
So you can
Swim Tuesday so when you land on the soil you can borrow in
And then explodes
Make baby
It's not much to being a virus than just
Need a few genes for that
Does this thing have particular talents that the other viruses didn't have
It's okay well so what's one thing that's really interesting is
What happens when it goes inside
Host
An amoeba
It goes in
But instead of
Kind of
Shutting off that protein coat and just
Spilling out its contents it actually goes in
And
Stays
As it was
Mainstays lights
It's called a virus Factory
Once it's inside there their they're
It's this thing they call the virus Factory
And it basically is able to
To do
Things
Vino components come into it and then
Then it was her work it has enzymes that can
Refashion them and then they
Outcome the components for new job starts going to the nucleus of the already existing cell
So interesting so it it it wouldn't you like to know
It sucks up some stuff and yeah it has it's beautiful sort of they called a Stargate
Because it's shaped like it's a doorway shaped like a
Estar and things come in and then
And then I have another Stargate
They Ducati desert manufactured things come out and then in the Sally assemble into new job
Giant viruses
It spits out the raw materials and then self-assemble into a giant
A giant Leviathan no baby how did they get out of the
Do they explode to the surface
They did not blow out
Yeah that's like a totally that's a totally different name into the machine
It's already there cuz their parents
Use the living thing
This thing is I have a weird kind of
Respect for the
Oh yeah it's it's amazing and you don't want the amazing things about it is that
It can get its own virus
It gets there are
Call Vero sages and they actually go into the virus Factory
And high jacket
Intercity outcome Vera face
Oh wow yes soon as he live virus Factory that's what a virus want
Now the virus has its own virus Factory was going to get
It's going viral viral
Right
Weird
Back that weird is the right word I say
Write notes on 2003 you know you could say well this is one weird virus
But these are just as well I wonder what else there is
It's like
Did that score the basic so they said okay Scott all this extra genetic
Power
But he's doing this sort of special circus act here it's building its own Factory
And it's just
Behaving differently, so maybe it just needs all those jeans to do this
Special things to me
How much is it when they looked at these you know 2018 jeans most of them didn't match anything anyone at found before
Your new jeans
Jeans yet that you couldn't even guess at what they were at this is got to be
We from life is like
Aliens from Saturn
Is that where you driving with the story
Not quite but I still waiting so they look at all the G they look at the the chemistry of
Like this as it's no namae don't find any matches for this little thing
For most of the genes they couldn't find a match
Yeah you can look at it I mean what is it what is this and where does it come from cuz it doesn't seem to
I have the smell of of Earth life
Yeah I got that it uses DNA
I mean it is has protein and uses our chemistry but it's it's
Doing something
And so these scientists said well okay they looked in in English
Hospital
Meowth water
Cooling tower let's go look at one here in France
And they looked
And they found another giant virus which is even bigger than the one that they
Already found
She says this is a cooling tower phenomenon of our rooftop biology
Well it's excitement Galore it's more like the drunk looking for the keys under the lamp
You know
It's like
You know that openness wherever you look there that we know that we know there was viruses found in one
Water tower so let's go look in another water tower
Like that's our safest bet
And hey we found an even bigger one you know which they
Which even bigger it was even bigger yet so instead of 1018 jeans it had
1059 jeans
So they named this one Mama virus
Mimi's first cousin Mama Mimi didn't do it was
Did it also build a virus Factory so it's like so there's something there's a common theme here we
Ready to die of two giant viruses doing the same thing
Dennis the whole Stargate and everything
Oh yeah
What's weird is that you know the mama virus has a bunch of genes that Mimi virus doesn't have
So it's like
And again don't match anything
So I don't know what to do
Some of them look like they're involved in
Building proteins
Which doesn't make any sense because viruses are not supposed to do that
So it's it's this is all completely confusing
But then they said okay
Maybe we need to kind of get away from the whole body
It's our thing and you don't widen our little will you go back to the opposite of a water tower would be like the bottle
Bottom of a well or is it or do you go to a library and look in the interior of
Old
Parchment books
Now you start looking at places like new look
You look in the ocean
Or you looking sediment
Or you look inside animals
More or you
Look in the soil and
They start
Finding
Giant viruses over and over and over again
Really yeah in all those places
Emmanuel inside of animals like in animals tummies or something
Yeah so they they went to
Disease researchers went to Brazil
And said let's go
Look at animals
Can find giant viruses
And they found a new species in
Cows and they found a new species living inside of
A monkey
And these were where they finding giant or giant virus
Are the numbers of genes are going up and up and keep finding new record breaker
So so the
The biggest one right now
Is called megabox
The summer movie
I mean there's
In the world
In a world
Trackosaurus you know I was like this is like I I'm wondering what they're going to do
As I keep finding bigger ones
Because you keep my having to find support
Where was Mega founded
Mega I believe was found in the ocean
And how many genes does Mega have
Mega
Has
Okay so where is not actually the biggest
It don't have the most genes but it's not actually the physically the biggest
Giant virus
Which was
So this is this one is called a Pandora
Let me guess
Clean up in a sealed box and then they opened it and will it straighten it had this bizarre
Are shaped like an urn
Completely nuts
There's no urn-shaped
Like crazy
Nmun the urn
That remind somebody of
The myth
What's a Pandora's Box was actually an urn
I'm tired that's a very learning make you happy because they found it
So what they did was
Are these Russian scientist they are clapping with
Dug up
Frozen tundra
That had been frozen for 30000 years
And they said let's follow this out and see what's in there
What kind of things have been asleep for thirty thousand years
Beginning of a sci-fi movie
Among other things they found pets
They found pandoravirus
And they not only did they find it but
Cebu day when they let it warm up a bit
And then they
Gave it to me but at checkout they they did it
Wow and how much bigger
The first
Giant virus-induced
Attitude with
Lego
An elephant sized Mouse
Compared to that elephant size mouse how much bigger is
Maybe it's more specific Hanabi I need to look at the numbers you know
Are kind of going from I don't know Elsa
What you getting
Bigger and bigger and bigger
Mina pandoravirus is bigger than a lot of that
Bacteria
These things are now being found
Everywhere you look
They are incredibly common
Baby mini able to get
Giant viruses out of people
Really
Yeah
WeChat what's up where are you find them in the person in our intestines or something
I believe they
Found one sample in somebody's lungs
And another sample was found in someone's blood
But it's really hard to tell whether they're
Actually like actively invading us and and making us sick
And maybe
7 rating amoebas they can
Invade human cells
Comedian human sellers
Surprisingly similar
Or is it just kind of along for the ride with some amoeba that
Infect us
Or does it kind of drift in and when people are sick their defenses are down
No we don't know if giant viruses have anything to do with human disease but
Let me know if you have a category problem here and there if you've got a giant
Virus that
Virus like in its General
Shell
But it's making proteins it's got a
Bunch of jeans
Viruses don't have your already bigger than some bacteria should we call it as its own set
At this point
That's what people are arguing about
Right now I mean keep that line between viruses and cellular life and just put the Giant
Viruses with the viruses
Or do we kind of
Blair the line Abyss feels like it's on its way from one category to the other so that's one of the big questions
What way did this thing
Go and Emmylou
What's that mean
Well
How do you get a job
Like how do you how do you well that and so
So
Will get to the
Henschel answer
Answer to that question
China's totally fast
After the
Hi there this is Kirsten recording from Orlando Florida Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan
Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloan at www. Sloan. Org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help this summer I'm hosting
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
About what we're calling tiny moments
Brilliance basically I want to hear about those times when a kid you know did something
It just means you lean back and say wow how did they do that maybe it was the moment that I kid
Did you been reading to 4 month started reading back
Do you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons and you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of their music
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed are ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the specific moments where a kid does something super smart
It doesn't have anything to do with a test if you have a story
T-shirt with us
Go to radiolab.org brilliance
Record a short audio message for us
And that's where you're at. Org / brilliance
Thank you so much
AJ Radiolab so William return to our conversation with science writer Carl Zimmer
What's an unedited conversation
And we were talking about
Giant
Virus
And what
They can teach us about life which really starts with a simpler Quest
Like where the hell they come
How do you get a giant fire
Like how do you
How do you well that and so-so
One clue comes from those jeans
So now that they're finding more Marty giant viruses
They're defining enough variety of them they can they can look for a service and some
Common genes that they share some some
Common mutations in genes and their finding actually that that
Looks like giant viruses might actually belong to one
Lineage
They're cousins they have a common ancestor
Yasso the tribe
And if that's if that's
True it could be an incredibly old tribe
These these giant viruses could be a lineage
Conceivably that you know goes all the way back to you know the early stages of
The dawn
I really owe like a black back to the very beginning of life on Earth
2 that are right yeah
I mean maybe
When
Cellular life was getting started
But the question is what were the giant viruses like then
Now some people have said well no giant viruses actually started his teeny tiny viruses and they've just been like
Gathering up new jeans
Through Time
I'm just been getting bigger and bigger bigger
But
You know number the people who actually study giant viruses and it really you know
Help us understand the most they're saying no we don't think so
We actually think that
These things
Started out
As
Cellular life
They were cells
Are full-blown sales
You mean they were from the other side of the roadway where the cellular life. They switch
The Heights
So yeah they change teams
How to know that
Like I can't have a plant that becomes an animal how did they sedate
Started off as like what we would call
Call creatures
And then they started actually alive
You know they think they re standing out there in the air the water or the
Grounder like some free living microbes
Yeah and then why would you go demote yourself this is this is your problem with Paras
Websites you keep saying mean things about parasite
I had a choice
It's between being Ace intake having my own integrity and choosing to make a living on my own or just
Suck love you I would just live on my own
Excuse me for I know you like parasites
Do not use that that passage is a recording play it's already been cut
So wait a second so you recording to this Theory you have a man's true nevertheless
We have a microbe that is
That is
Doing its thing and then something happened
Okay what is the something
It becomes a parasite
Becomes apparent
You know maybe a symbiont here basically what it does is it starts living inside
Another
So you need gives up its Integrity as in as a as a free
Life
Former free-standing life whatever that means
It's got a
Shell
What kind of border
It's making its own energy
It's
Replicating in the way that
Let the beginning at the beginning at the beginning it can make its own energy
You can grow it can divide and do all the things that living things to do and then for some reason it chooses
Require
Some other creatures existence for its own it has it has to
Become dependent on some other organism
For it's very very exist
Well it's flip it the other way and say it discovers a wonderful new home
Inside of another cell
It comes in as I got like I love leaving my Park Avenue apartment for a dark cave
Exciting opportunities real estate
Imagine you're like Bear Grylls
Okay let's imagine
You are like
Hiking around and killing your own food okay II
Let's just try to picture that's okay Robert.
You're you're getting your dear you're starting your own fires you're going on and on and on and you do that for
For like a few years
And then
And you're walking through the jungle and I'm very very skinny not going well
College that the Haggard Hunter
Let's say you're doing this in Minnesota
All right sounds like cold
Okay
And then suddenly like
You you get there's a break in the forest and you come across a
Giant
Mansion what is this place and you open the door
And inside
There's like conveyor belt
Swell ice cream and steak
You know and end their slippers waiting for you and you know anything you need it
It's somebody else is taking care of it there is one thing you left out when I walk into this Magical Kingdom is it
Doesn't let me out I can't leave
Ever again because I am become so dependent on its natural wonders
But I lose my Independence my integrity
Have a very very things I walked in with
We did literally
Music
We did and I did point out to you at the
The time that
You are quite
Dependent on
Are there species
Do you want me to bring us
Weather Stacy episode 32
It has eyes will roll right out of their sockets
It sounds like becoming big being able to take advantage of another cell
Evolutionarily speaking is is a great way to go
Because
You have all these things taken care of for you
Now
According to this
Siri these days
Mysterious ancient
Microbes
Started going into these cells
And reproducing there and then
Going out again and then finding another host cell to info
Are they making like were they making their host sick
Probably yeah
Probably because giant viruses are not good
To get to see this is this complicates your Mansion metaphor
Tiny bit because what it means is that you go in the conveyor belts when you feeding yourself and having a good time but then you're filled starts to
Muck up the place and it starts to collapse from within that doesn't sound
The Strain the metaphor bad boy
Goy
Rob Roy
So so you you spend some time in this wonderful Mansion you you rest it's warm it's comfortable so on you you you
You eat
Bullet with your filth
You start a family
You know
And then I'll send you and your descendants
Leave the Mansion the messages collapses from all the damage you did do it
But you know actually you see in the distance there's another mansion
Just go over there now you feel like rested and ready and like you have it all we got to do is get over there
So let's just go that we don't have to we don't have to stop to to kill a deer we just go to that next mansion
The ice cream is waiting
I still got to walk
So I need my legs
So to speak to the next mansion
But I don't need the powerful muscles that I would have needed to kill the deer I can let you know so you don't need
You need
You know let's say that you were you know
You don't even need the knowledge
I've had to kill a deer we blind dumb
Fat
Zodiac where you end up
They get rid of they start getting rid of these jeans
And how does that happen
You know a random mutation comes along and just cuts out a bit of DNA them you're fine
Yeah
That's okay I needed a moment worth
Oh there goes a big chunk of me
I don't need that
I did that the regular kind of mutation
That happens all the time
Turn your your your successor
Being
Travels with lighter
I was able to succeed just as well
Right so you know if if if if
You know it if we are born you know which was a part of our DNA that's deleted that had some you know
Hemoglobin genes in it like
Good night
Like that bad and mean
But you know but if you cut out a gene
That
This giant virus no longer needs because
It's got everything Supply to it
And it's host
Find self
The check that check it out so you have this
So the idea is that you did these viruses
The giant viruses but they actually
And
Did Eddie Eddie how fast does a giant like these
Imagining
Back
In the beginning
There was there was not Mega not Jai nobody likes
Cellular near me
Joy's Independence
Size-wise it's a
Blimp
It's a massive thing
And then suddenly starts to shrink
I bit by bit by bit
What at what rate does it
Start to shrink and shut itself
Well
It could be that
These
Giant viruses were finding
These giant viruses that scientist
Are finding
Could be shrinking very very very slowly
Could be
That
There are other viruses
That made this transition that
Tranq faster
So maybe
Maybe
The race to the bottom maybe some some maybe some tiny viruses are just
Former giant viruses
That just shrink relief at least to the bottom it's just a different way of thinking about life you
You generally assume
Being a multicellular organism yourself
That little things
In some deep sense
You know you're not supposed to say this
Want to be big
You don't want to
I know
I know but most people unlike you a****** most people
Think they're better than the podcast it's better to be more complex than to be simple but
Hear you're talking about a different Voyage all together
It might just work out for you to be simple rather than complex
Well given the dead viruses are insanely abundant on this planet I mean there are
By some estimates
To the 31st power viruses on Earth
Think about that like it's a it's a
You know it's a 1 with 31 zeros
I mean
Inconceivable
How many viruses are on
It's their world
So
Apparently you know Nature has not agreed
What is interesting like thinking about how
How
Lifeguard
Smaller
Simpler
If it's true that this trajectory is a
SS
Common as you say that
That thing start out sometimes
Start up big and then
Learn to live inside other things and in the process get smaller and smaller
I want smaller in this is actually maybe
What happens to a lot of viruses not just some viruses
It anyway it gives the virus and honorable history
I don't know why I feel that way
This boy isn't going to
I don't know but then I mean
Abandonment
Reliving past right
They gave in to The Temptations of the Mansion full of
Steak and ice cream
It's true but I've always assumed in this is
Not
Something wanted
Seem that viruses were
A kind of Proto organism
They Were Somehow at the beginning of something and I never quite got going
Yeah but this is you're actually saying that these viruses are
In a way at the end
At the end but there at the
I don't know how to quite use the words that I want to use
The snakes feel something at the end of something out of the beginning
Like you just took that you just took what I consider to be the beginning
And you've now made it then
And end
An end that's interesting I never
Yeah. So I can go in different directions
And how far can a Traverse
Journey
Go I mean can you go from like
How big did that
It was never liked
Turtle with
With a with things
All right now
Like a giant dinosaur
No
Sorry I know there are things going I believe they're going to mixes Owens
Which
Started out as free living animals
And have become
Parasites and they're just down to just a few cell
Hay Day
Myxozoa animals you don't mean animals in the way that animals
My pet my pet jellyfish
Really really
So you're saying a jellyfish size
Thing has now reduced itself to a tiny Speck microscopic parasite
Get the
I don't even say it because you can't do it if you're that small
That's insane
Andrea Lee
Like it going from something you can see and would want to avoid while swimming
Down to something that you might even just breathing without even knowing it
You blowing my mind
Shrinking
Mixes
Message
How do you spell that
Myx
Xxio 8
I'm trying in my mind to construct a scenario where we
Like the mixes on
Could begin to shed
Like if we were living inside then like not the iPhone with the eye
IHome
The IUD you know but the but the fact is that we can all we have
Cast aside some things
You know what a weak acid
Well we can't smell better I know that
I know that'll better and we used to be able to make her own vitamin C in our own bodies
Our own bodies were vitamin C Factor
Really
Wait what what change that
How did we want to let go that it sounds great
Sunshine vitamin C vitamin C
Well if you are sitting around eating fruit all
Fruit which is loaded invited
AMC
Then
If you get a mutation on your vitamin C Gene well
Yep you're fine cuz you're you you're getting your vitamin C from somewhere else you don't feel that lack
You don't start getting scurvy because
Feeding yourself on fruit and then
That mutated Gene May then spread out and end up
Being and every member of your species
What seems to happen to us I mean you can literally Lexi like these we have these broken vitamin C G
So sometimes we trying to yeah
Okay so there you have it a raw conversation with
Science writer Carl Zimmer about
Shrinking
Shrinkage in life
No usually would have these conversations
Cuz you just talkin and cuz you don't really have like the encyclopedia sitting right next to you you get a lot of a little things wrong
Deals with facts names dates whatever
And then you know you fact check it later
So In fairness to Carl as we're fact-checking we gave him the chance to listen back to the raw conversation
Make a couple of amendments
This is fact Checker Carl
Scolding rambling Karl
Okay we were saying that
This microbiologist Tim rowbotham took a sample to France but actually it was another microbiologist
Turtles that did it
Small but important sorry Richard
And Mama virus turns out to have a thousand 23g
Then I started talking about virus
At the time in 2011 it was indeed
The biggest virus known
1120 games
Okay however there was in 2013
A another virus found
Called pandoravirus now I was saying that this was something found the temperature in tundra wrong
This was on the ocean and this virus
Has
A whole lot of jeans how many
Ed has
2500 2500 I mean that's way more than a lot of bacteria
Also a certain point in we to refer to Pandora viruses being the biggest virus in size
I see that that stinks you go to
Hippo virus
The house it seems that since we talked as evidence that there might be a couple separate
Lineages of giant viruses
One may have evolved
From Big to small as we talked about but another one might have gone in the usual direction from small to big
There's one last thing that I see so apparently apparently I didn't quite spell metazoan correct
This is how you spell mixes on my xoz oan apparently I missed one of those
I can't remember
I mean I would be lying if I said I didn't think a little bit less of you
Okay xtro back in
Petco's in to Radiolab people interviewing stupid people
That's funny
That's a great taglines
Hugo okay
That's our new tagline
Thanks for listening
Is James Jordan from Tulsa Oklahoma Radiolab is produced by Jed Adam Rod or staff includes burner
Farrell ellenhorn David Gable Dylan Keith Matt kielty Andy Mills Latif Nasser and Kelsey Padgett area
John wack Molly Webster Soren wheeler and Jamie York with help from Damiana marchetti Molly McBride Jacob
Gibson & Alexandra Lee Young
Fact Checkers are Eva Dasher and Michelle Harris