Hate Radiolab it is Molly Webster before we start the show I want to say two things
One of which
Thank you
Couple of weeks ago we asked you to donate to support the show and you did
And we are so so grateful
Which brings me to the second thing
We still need more of you
This is a stat that I was handed today
Most people listen to Radiolab for about
Two and a half years before they become a member
Can you imagine that that's like
What's a going to a potluck dinner
For two-and-a-half years
Every week
And never bringing a dish
Or going to
Two-and-a-half years of weddings and never bringing a gift
Or asking people to follow you never following them
You wouldn't want to do any of those things until I know that you want to become a member today
Go to radiolab.org
Donate
The average donation is $75 but we're happy with whatever you can give
And
If you donate before April 30th you and a friend could win an all-expenses-paid trip to New York City
We
Will take you bowling once you get here
So go to radiolab.org donate
And thank you
Are you awake
Listening to Radiolab
Radiolab WNYC
I'm Jedi been wrought iron Robert Froehlich is Radiolab and this is reporter Julia Longoria
Nothing. Let's do it so where do we start
You took a trip
Site of two trips
The first trip inspired another trip
Let's start in Denver Colorado
Where
I wanted to speak to this
Young man
Giancarlo very young man
Giancarlo Mari
He's 9 years old what are you doing today
Well I'm from eating lunch
So currently I'm not asking my grandmother hug so yeah
So currently that
Trying to turn me on
And
I wanted to talk to him because there's this
Particular chapter in his family history
That
Presented this thorny question to the United States of America
Do you feel like you're like a descendant of immigrants
Sort of like
Not all the way like
You're in the car
Carson immigrants
Cuz
People from Puerto Rico back then like 19
98 I think
Maybe it was actually 1898
And what happened in 1898 was that the United States had gotten sort of gravity
We grabbed
The Philippines we grabbed
Guam and we grabbed
Puerto Rico which is where John Carlos family was from and
Just a few years after Puerto Rico became part of us
Great grandmother it's either great great or grate
Grandmother don't remember you it was his great
Great grandmother and her name was Isabel Gonzalez
She was on a boat she was on like
Like they used to be like both
From going from here she was traveling alone and pregnant from
Puerto Rico to New York City
When the boat arrived in Ellis Island white men
Wood
Go out in like select like people like you can't go not allowed you can't go where's your spouse not allowed
She was stopped at Ellis Island because all women arriving
At Ellis Island who were pregnant
We're stopped and examined and some of them were turned away a little historical assistir from Christina Fonseca
I'm a professor of law at Columbia she says when those guys tried to pull Isabella side
Said you can't even stop me much less question me or get in my way at all
I am coming from Puerto Rico which is part of the United States
I'm an American citizen
And citizens cannot be stopped at the border Christina says around this time a lot of people a lot of goods
Like fruits and with a shipment of orange among other things started arriving in the US
From the newly acquired territory
And all of these new arrivals
Posed a sort of existential question to the US
Are these
New colonies
Part of us
Or are they something else
So a bunch of these cases like
Isabel Gonzalez's case ended up in the Supreme Court
And they eventually became known
Collectively as
The insular
The insular cases
What does insular mean
Miss contacts
Insular actually means relating to an island it also means
Parochial or
Close minded at the time when the United States annexed
Puerto Rico the Philippines and Guam it still have territories that had Oklahoma to Arizona
But it had not yet become States
So territories were not new
However
These territories seemed very different to the American public they had different
Cultures different
Races
They didn't seem
American enough
So the judges are dealing with the fact that these new islands are now
Part of the US
But they also have this public opinion in their heads and they don't want to let these people all the way in so in the
Case of Isabel Gonzalez they ended up saying we're not going to answer the question of whether Puerto Ricans are actually us
Citizens
We're just going to say they're not immigrants
And if that's not confusing enough
They went on to say that Puerto Rico Puerto Rico is foreign to the United States in a domestic sense
That sounds like nonsense
The dissenters in the case
That it sounded like nonsense nobody understood exactly what that meant it's like almost textbook
Doublethink right like it's like foreign but the mess
Math textbook having it both ways
Do you feel like you're Puerto Rican
Gordo Vegas
If y'all
American
Parsley just partially why
Cuz I'm also
Little bit
Irish I think
The Irish
Well yeah on Dad side you know your friend
Just backup go ahead and say so today on Radiolab we're continuing our thought that we had in the last episode
So we did about citizenship about what it means to belong to a place or country
The last episode we spend some time in Switzerland think about cowbells but this time we've got a story that
It's a little bit closer to home
Yeah and
This next part is really what blew me away and actually inspired my second
Shortly after the insular cases Congress stepped in and they pass the law to make it so that
Anybody born in Puerto Rico is an automatic US citizen
Congress
Did the same thing for the other major territories I mean they can't vote for president they don't have a vote in Congress
But at least the people born in those territories are automatically
US citizens
Except
41 place
A cluster of tiny little Islands in that great blue expanse the Pacific Ocean between Hawaii
New Zealand
Call American Samoa
The only place in the world
That is US soil and people who are born here are not citizens
So is it true yes
Sissy
Attention existing only place where the whole like my baby is born the u.s. Air Force
Doesn't happen
Cracked
They become what are they
In their passport they have a US passport but on the last page it says
This person is not a US citizen
.
US national
A child born in American Samoa
Will not become an automatic citizen they have to go take the test they have to pay close to $800
And you can't even like there's no immigration office in American Samoa so you have to go
To some other part of the states
Stay there for a few months
And apply in order to qualify
So it's it's
And it's not just weird I mean it
When I first looked into it it seems like this hold over from this
Really racist time in our history
But
Then
I started making calls
Two American Samoans
Living in American Samoa
End
I realized
There might be
A more complicated reason why
American Samoans
Still are not US citizens after all these years
So I decided to get on a plane
After a 25 hour trip
I landed in the middle of the night
Went through border security
That I walked out of the
Of the airport which is really small
Very nice to meet you and
People I had email
Showed up to the airport
To greet me with lady with like flowers and
And I appreciate that was just like the hotel picking me up but it was like this woman who I haven't even talked to you on the phone but you knew I was
Coming from far away
And then more and more people who I talk to you showed up
Wait David So instantly it felt
So welcoming
Anyway I got to my hotel that night
And then the next morning
I stepped out of my hotel Ocean
You and it was
Josh
Incredibly gorgeous, I saw the pictures of what no one told me
Who is amazing
Huge
Lush
Mountain
Bright green mountains
Only palm trees pastel colored
Houses tucked into the side of these cliffs
American flag
Flying high
Just stunning
How big how big is American Samoa
Well
It's a cluster of islands with the main island to Tukwila
Is about 50 square miles with about 50000
Lane Road
Whiskey like the main route
There's just one main road
That you drive so if you if the oceans on your
Right you're probably going east
If the oceans on your left you're probably going west
Angie
I spent 12 days there and it was just kind of like riding back and forth and back and forth
With different people
With who had different ideas of
What the island was about
Which is really interesting seeing the same places
Through different eyes
I'm so
It is this
The first stop I made was to meet with a guy named
Hi
Charles alive Lima
Really smiley
Silver hair thin Rim glasses wearing a floral shirt and flip-flops
Almost everybody at the courthouse was wearing flip-flops
When I caught up with him he was actually meeting with a couple of Samoan men who were in the middle of a Landis
Which is basically the rights of the Chiefs
Coldest top of this mountain
But the reason I wanted to talk
Is that he has a case
Right now pending before the federal courts
That's basically
Isabel Gonzalez in 2019
He's arguing that
Denying American Samoans Birthright citizenship
Is unconstitutional
So I believe that
When you were born in American Samoa
You're American
An unusual American but you are still on now in Charles case he's with sometime ones call afakasi
My mother was born in
Auburn New York mom is white and his dad is from Western Samoa which is not part of the US
Is parents actually met in the states
His dad was in grad school in DC
And
My father and mother could not get married in Virginia
Because of the
Anti-miscegenation laws this was back in 19 over East
Cuz I'm a mother kept trying to insist
The Samoans are not
Black they are something different because now he looks too. But they were actually able to get married
Hayden Washington DC
And they moved to American Samoa where Charlie was born
And you think that Charlie would be an automatic US citizen
And this is a child is born in the u.s. territory but she had to go cuz they had to register at the closest Embassy
His mom a US citizen actually had to register him in a foreign country
The closest Embassy with all the way in New Zealand
You know it doesn't make any sense in it
And it's against the principles of the United States really says the fact that American Samoans are not autumn
Ematic citizens by birth is hiding a lot of in justices that are going on
Justices that could be remedied
If you didn't say oh well we are your National
You can be treated differently
Hiking boots
Should I be here
So I drove around with Charlie
For a while
And
And everywhere I saw signs of threats of natural disaster
Tsunamis typhoons earthquake
You showed me the Town Center which is really just a cluster of
Pastel colored buildings
These are all the Old Navy
And the original US Naval Base which is really where this whole thing got started
So the US Navy showed up in American Samoa in the late 1800s
Samoa
Extremely fractured Germany and the UK were hanging out there too and there were fights among Chiefs decor
Bought the islands about who owned what turf
And us may be offered the island of American Samoa protection in exchange for
Congo Bongo Bay Harper
Super barber in the South Seas possibly in all the Pacific
Wanted that protects
American Samoans
They said that's great. It was a good deal
One of their High Chiefs his name is Moana
What's
Basically telling everybody know it
Have the Americans come in
End in 1900
They made it official
Some Samoan Chiefs
Signed what they called a deed of session
The Handover sovereignty
The United States
And according to Charlie at the time that they did this
They thought
They had become US citizen of course thanks to the rulings in the insular cases they actually hadn't
And then
1929 Congress
Took up the question of whether American Samoans
Should be US citizens
And they just said
No and really some of
Vile racist statements being made back their 1929 against it
We don't want any
Of these
Is Savage racist would never be able to understand
Our system fast forward 100 years and
Charles is basically trying to overturn Isabel Gonzalez
Case
His first attempt to do that
Hi I'm here at
Was to represent this guy named Lineage 2
Actually got in the rental car and went to visit him while I was on the island
TV One
A side note there are no addresses in American Samoa
Great thank you so much I asked sorry I got lost
Which makes it virtually impossible to find anyone
But I found them
Funny story
What is taobao
Green trimmings white hello
How are you doing
Leonard Scott White hair purple floral shirt on
Taking a drag from a cigarette shooting
Leaning Water Tower
I'm a retiree
Taking care of Family Matters here at home
I am
Not working anymore
Lennon was actually a police officer in American Samoa
He moved to California and live there for a while and he wanted to be a police officer there too
But soon as you came across my my status is that while I'm sorry
A tall
You're not a US citizen
So therefore
You cannot
Become
A California Highway Patrol
They told him he would have to become a citizen first
Which involve paying hundreds of dollars then
Taking a test
I'm not going to do that
I'm not going to spend a penny I might American
.
And that's why Birthright citizenship is so
Important it
Solidified that if you are born on us soil you are equal to everybody else
So in 2012 with the help of Charlie and a lawyer from Guam name Neil Weir
Linen suit the US government
Saying they violated the citizenship Clause of the Fourteenth Amendment
That's how I ended up
In Washington DC
Bathing the footsteps of the US Supreme Court
Lena says he just wanted the court to give some kind of explanation
Why American Samoans have been treated
Why why me why keep us the runaround
But
When it got to the supreme court date
Declined tip
Share the case
2016 they just refuse to make a decision on it
Why are they so afraid to come out just nine of them
Today Charlie and Neil have another case going with some American Samoans in Utah
Hopefully this second time around
Supreme Court
Will Prince
Opposition
Or at least
And so
At this point of my trip I was curious
How
Other American Samoans
Even ones who aren't in the states trying to get a job
How they felt about this case
In about citizenship
I assumed that
They would be behind it because
Who wants to live in this like
Foreign but domestic put for in limbo space
But public service announcement
Then I talked to this guy
His name is Papa out anger
Goes by
Dan
He's on the radio reading from the American someone Constitution all the time which is kind of weird
Radio reading from the Constitution
Tatoosh allowed
Cool weird
And actually when he heard I was looking into the citizenship question he got a hold of me okay
Okay go ahead
So you'll be coming West on the main road
So I hopped in my car so I just
Paid the wrong left
Got a little bit lost again
Little familiarity where they don't need street signs
You'll be alright
But eventually I did find it.
Where should I park if you want to come in
Yeah yeah yeah let's go as soon as I arrived
You jumped in my rental car because he wanted to show me what they call faasamoa
Kristoff
It's going around around so we drove down to the center of the village of Leon
One of the larger Villages about 2,000 people and it's on the Southwest coast of the island
Okay great to meet the high Chiefs of the village
Or magnetized at their known
I'll come out
Hello
My name is robot eopa right hair broad shoulders
Kind smile
Of the Villi
And
High talking Chief Maiava
Got a buzz cut in a white v-neck
What's bring you down here to our
Ugly Village
And I asked the Chiefs like
Would you want to be citizen straight up
Would you
Would you want to be are you a US citizen
Nope
Do you want to be
I want to pee USA
Citizen
Myself
I want it
And cheap robot the oboe was like
Why
Because
This is the part of America
So I want a p
A real American
It's my kids all live in the states
I served in the US Military
Thank you so much I really appreciate
Preciate it okay
IGun Dan kind of like Steps in and starts talking to him in Samoan
Permanent
Yahoo
Aqi fighting like
Why
And I was like what's going on
And then
Okay. Now I understand
End
I don't want to answer that question
Until I
Prepare myself
To explain to
Before you go
I want to think about it and yeah
Because I wasn't really sure what
Do you think about
That but then
Dispel started to ring
And she might have explained that
They have a curfew in the village of Leon at on Sundays at 6 p.m.
For 15 minutes
Everyone has to stop what they're doing and pray
Meditate
Wait that's the law
Yeah I mean
It's not quite law
But it is the rule in this Village and some others and it is enforced
And I was talking to the chief Wednesday
Yam rolls around and the bell rang and I was like oh what happens now and he's like well
I just drive around and make sure that everybody's following the curfew
And then he asked me if I wanted to come along with him and I was like
Yeah and he was like bouquet great
We'll take your car
So we literally got into my car
And I'm holding the microphone for the chief as we're doing
The Ride Along
Please tell me where to go
OK Google
Stop
Wechat
Went up and down
The Main Street
It's like
A little over 15 minutes is a very small village
Along the street there are
Young man
They're called the all manga
At the Young Men's
Club
These guys
Just line the streets here
Lined up
And wearing white shirts and red lava lava
Skirts
NHS it what do they do they just yellow people
They just stand there kind of watching
And so there were some people who got caught
I just have to stop
Sitting there on the side of the road for 15 minutes until it's over
They don't force them to pray but they're just supposed to have quiet time
Set for men
For 15 minutes
What happens if you don't do that anybody across these laws and everything for the old days
You're very handsome
Appendages
Cheap my Ava told me that back in the old days like 1800s
You would just immediately get kicked out of the village
We don't want to see them no more which means you had no food no protection
Letgo
Death penalty
Those days
You know but you know nowadays we don't have to do that we would do it like once
When I was talking to you for a puppy oppa he told me that
These days a pretty common punishment would be like making the person feed the whole village
Should I mean
Picked a lot of food
50k pekin 50k turkey tail
50k star
Wahoo
+ +
But cheap might have a told me you know if you keep breaking the curfew over and over again
You can still get kicked out of the village
Which piscine happened a few times in his life so it's okay
So so one of the arguments that is made is like this would not pass muster under the US Constitution
Yeah
But the thing is like
These guys aren't really the government
If you look at it one way it's kind of like a gated community or a country club you opt-in to living there
And you opt into
You know
Living under these
Rules
But the fear is that if everyone born on the island were automatically granted citizenship
Then a bunch of other us laws might
Start getting applied here to
And they wouldn't be able to do things like these curfews the reason why
Such an existential threat to American Samoans to become US citizen
Because the 14th Amendment also guarantees equal protection under laws American Samoa
Become Birthright citizens
It's not long before everyone born on this island is given that equality under the law
But that word equality
Historically and even now
That's such a
Difficult complicated word to get around
Because
US citizenship is not something that's
Applied in a pure
Way
It's saying that historically mixed with a free market
The ideal of equality it actually gets mixed in with other realities
Capitalism and interest
The people in power and the artificial population of lands that were
People by native peoples
And the results have been time and time again that indigenous people have ended up losing their land
Or cultural practice in someone's we have a saying
Original know it is a Monday mandala
Hello Panda
Careful that you are so
Eager for the fish
Did you end up losing your net
K
Let's be careful of that
That we
Don't go after US citizenship
And forget that we have so much to lose
Arnett being our land and our natural resources
In our culture and our language
Things that have been lost by so many other native peoples
Are you a US citizen
Yes
Manny's people here are you a citizen
There there
So are you saying well I'm sure you're saying
If you are you a citizen why should everyone else become US citizen
Feel as a US citizen do you feel like you've lost something
I is it individual haven't lost something
Because I am part of an extended family
That lives on family land
So so
Could they not live on family lands as US citizens
Yes technically speaking here I am a US citizen there many of us who are US citizens
We could live on family land
We do live on family
XOXO what I want understand like what is it about granting US citizenship Birthright us
Citizenship to even more
And then he explained to me that
There's a law in American Samoa that says you have to be 50%
Blood
Samoan blood
To own land like even if someone person wanted to sell me or like
Give me their land
They couldn't by law
So
Someone from some country
Say
Main everyone picks on China these days so maybe
Someone from China music
And a
The laws changed and it
The law says anyone born here is a US citic
Okay
So this person here
I'm trying to let you know
Build a business becomes a wealthy businessman
From China
And one day he wants to buy land
Endnote
Lord say well no we can't sell you these lands
Everybody says no I want to buy that land and I have the right to buy that
Okay
That's what I'm talking
About that's the threat
Finally he was like think about it like if everyone born here is a Birthright Citizen and everyone has equal rights
Here it's not long before a Chinese person is born here
The US citizen they have equal rights to the land as someone's to
And then things
They could sue to make that
Blood Simon law illegal
So
Maybe not in one generation but in a couple Generations
Blood someone with loser land
That's a threat
I guess you have to imagine what would Hawaii be like
If they didn't lose all their lands the way that they had
Siwik to us Hawaii is what we never want to become
You know you land at the airport in Hawaii who do you see where are the Hawaiians
You know for us to look at Hawaii
You still look at a sad story
You know
So
But everything I say you have to also remember we're loyal and patriotic people
It's worth pointing out that
American Samoa has one of the highest rates of military enlistment of any US state or territory
They say the Pledge of Allegiance at school in the morning they learn US History learn about the US Constitution
But this is still our home
Right now we still have to protect
Do you think what's Happening Here
The land
The curfews the sort of thing do you think it's unconstitutional
I can give you the literature that says it's
A repugnant
To the US Constitution
So you do think you do think it's uncommon
You think it's on Cox
Why people stay on Earth
I'm not saying it's unconstitutional
But
We do understand that there is a view that it is considered
Racist and I'm constant
But it's also
It gives us a chance
To survive
Coming up
That balancing act that he's doing this with weighing
Of things which
I'm pretty
You're not cancer
What's going to get a lot more personal
The break
Hi this is Megan and I'm calling from a cloudy Ithaca New York
Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloan
At www.scoan.org
Hey I'm chantaboon rice radio glorious story about love the question before
For us is should people born in American Samoa
The automatically be citizens of the United States of America that's the question just because they're born.
Exactly and
For the break we heard about some land ownership laws
Zetor
Constitutionally questionable
Yeah and the more people I talk to
The more Tangled
The reality of blood
Laws for land ownership.
Hey how's it going
All right because
You kind of run out of people to marry
It's okay first just like your name
Genevieve
59 Greg I talk to this one woman Genevieve Greg who runs
For company there and how long have you lived here
My whole life
Except for 7 years I live in California
And what are the first things you told me was
I have a feeling to end like this island so small
Corey Wright
So basically there has to be intermarriage
The running joke here is like when a sound when I get to invitations
For the same wedding that we know we go
Add to family member
Play this is like
That show Cash Cab confess
Now
Genevieve herself 25%
Yes
Her mom is half Samoan and my dad is Canadian
When I was younger
I never knew I was white
Nobody's I never knew I was wait till I went to California After High School does she like realize she was white one time
I'm at a bar in California when someone was like nevermind
Whatever that means let's go
Itsfunneh at one point
We pick up her friend
How do you look like crap
Okay so this is Julia whose name is too many snow goes by money
Tell her the white girl
Money is actually way darker skin than Genevieve but she grew up in California and talks like she
She's from the state
Thank you very much
Lights
You're The Darkest Hour volume
Darkest Polansky Samoan word for white person
Waiting I'm a little confused what's
Who's whose who know the point is
My ear is 100% blood Samoan
But she's not that culturally xiamen she doesn't speak the language very well she's
Only spent a few years there
Whereas Genevieve is very culturally someone has spent most of her life there speaks perfect someone but
Because she and her sisters are only 25% Samoan blood because we're not 50% she can't
Technically own land in American Samoa
Her mom recently passed away and try to block we planned to her and her sisters even if it was written in
Well that it was us
Inherited we inherited it
We can't get it because we're not 50% and this blood loss effects money
Because of her son
Samuel Pucci brought along in the car
Maya took away video game and he
Freaked out
What's going on
Yes my son
Drama
Anyway it affects her son because his dad
Is American without one drop of someone's blood
Sol Samuels kids
Will only be able to own land if he has them with a half or full blood sample
Your testimony kids you can marry white girl
Mom I got my glasses
It's tea time
That's okay
And then another name that came up
Is that
Genevieve interestingly is
She loves you
And she has a partner who she wants to marry
My first
Are you planning on a second I don't know we'll see how good she is but seems like
Marriage is not legal in American Samoa
We couldn't be
Public affectionate with each other or
Be a couple my mom still was like whatever you do need to do it inside the bedroom like we couldn't even be in
House in like give each other a hug or something
Doesn't that we went through a couple years of really
Rocky
Relationship
And then
So here you got
Genevieve and my two people who the Constitution applied here the way it does in the states
It seems like
Their problems will be solved
Genevieve would get her land and my son could have kids with whoever he wants to
And maybe Genevieve down the road could marry whoever she wants to
Do you wish you could
Get married here
Yes or no I mean
I don't have the same views as other gay people like
I'm a Republican and
People always ask me how can you be gay in a Republican and a female right
I have certain views like I'd rather have Financial stability at the end of the day then be able to get married to someone you know I draw
Try to be rich and with someone then
Poor and Mary
Because in the end we're going to divorce either way right
First time in American Samoa and I don't know like
I don't know anything what do I know
But but
But I'm like trying to think about like
Growing up on Michael being a US citizen like matters and it's like it comes with all these rights
Freedom of speech freedom of religion freedom of
Equality under the law and stuff like that
Are yours we have them with high system so
All that stuff is
Does it matter
Where is freedom of speech until they say
I'm speaking
Yunnan
Go get coffee
She for everybody so that yeah that doesn't take place.
Now
Even though Birthright citizenship wouldn't necessarily change all that
I still expected them to what Birthright citizenship for American Samoans
But
They both told me
No
Are you a US citizen are you
Yay
We have learned that an American can I get what if
Reserved
Fundamental rights
Would be enforced
Stigmatizing
Couldn't deny you those
Who wouldn't
People could sue in federal court
And enforce
Yeah
He was problem
RR Spike
The Grinch
Care about that
Before my move gear sheep
Was living in California
She married an American bought a house
Raining in in the states
Nothing here
Nothing
What changed
Like Nu like did you notice something change in you
Oh yeah
I love this I would never move back to
Here
I get to spend more time with my kids
I think that
And we we get to spend more time as a family
You don't own our own are our own business we would never be able to do that in the states
You don't people who buy a house in the states I called Man U
You know you made it whatever you bought a house your homeowner
I'm like no way that
We've learned that fax that was such
Bulshit
We don't use credit anymore we don't use none of that f****** s*** that they have out there we don't we don't
We are not in debt
We are
Text but what we have
Here
We're happy
I was so blinded
Life truly should
Is Rip life
We live like everyday
I love it
A lot of that isn't it a lot of that like
The fact that you do have land like you own land
Yep
Off of it
But at the same time
They did both agree that these land ownership laws about blood are
Kind of messed up
And Charlie a lalima the lawyer on that citizenship case we mentioned
That's what he thinks to
He's actually asked him to
Help try to get her mom's land
That's this whole citizenship case again
It somehow you were special down here
That you're entitled and able to do a lot of these things that are Peyton Lee
And even worse in my mind is
Actually does want to preserve someone ownership of lands
But just to do it in some other way because he thinks the blood rules are just
Illegal and other basically a kind of Jim Crow law
So there was a case actually two two years ago
And I try to explain to Monty and Genevieve
That you could see the fight for citizenship as a fight against the insular cases
In which
The Supreme Court Justices called territories like American Samoa
Quote possessions inhabited by alien races
And said they were unfit for Anglo-Saxon legal Traditions he thought it was very racist and he wanted that the US gov
Yeah it's it's it's it's explained
Like work.
Because
Is he feels like someone's are in a limbo a little bit
Legally
Well let's go back to the 1904 figure out what the
Move on with your life right now
And honestly
Leaving the car with those two
It did make me wonder
How common is their perspective on the island
So my name is Juliet
I spent a bunch of time wandering around for the next couple days
Taking a very informal poll
Ask you a couple questions that okay
If it were put to a vote
Would you make
American Samoans automatic citizen
Becoming a US citizen
At first it seemed like it was just a lot of
No because I
Always got to be mindful of what happened to blonde when he States took over Guam we're truly blessed in the sense that we were
Keep a culture or land this one someone veteran
With a make America great again baseball cap
I don't I don't want to be a US citizen to be US national
I don't want to
A Japanese or Chinese
And I'm up
The same thing
Us
You know I rather be a some more you know
What did you order here
Fish fillet and then interesting lie at McDonald's
What do you think of that idea
I think that's a great idea idea because that's going to be out
Fair I got only
Yes be great because
Gay marriage when buffini is there called what
Men At Birth but end up
Dressing like women here we do have partners
They do live with them but you are kind of accepted in society but they're just not allowed to marry who they want to marry
It's not recognized by law
So
But that's totally okay in the US
And in particular when I talk to immigrants
From Korea China the Philippines Tonga
Most of them wanted citizenship
In the city
Automatically granted
Of course why not
I wish I wish I wish
Maybe God help me
For the non American Nationals
That you don't pay property Hawaii that be great if
Iffy
If they become citizen
This is something else that Charlie Auto Lima brought up with me
I guess
Do you have kind of started to talk about
Injustice has
Cheer that are kind of
Swept under the rug without
Citizenship
I think mostly it is how immigration will be handled
American Samoa you told me
You have immigrants coming to the island for work
And because American Samoa controls its own borders
And because
He says there's locks enforcement of immigration laws some people talked about corruption
You have situations where immigrants end up here on questionable visas
Stripped of their rights to wages and fair working conditions
And in some cases
It hasn't been very
Good you know
What some of the foreigners
It's a lot of abuse
But if you do become a citizen then and if
US immigration
Service comes on actually
Just the laws
Requirements
Farmers coming
Work here
Daniel
Probably see
Change
I am serious as you were doing these interviews how are you processing all this
Kind of
Making my way across the island and there were some people
From this was a really
Personal thing other people had these high ideals of Rights of others no high ideals of Samoan culture
But I did meet one person who
Kind of held all of these
Ideas
In her mind that once
Thank you and her name is
Tisa
IMovie
Hello I'm the infamous she's the woman from the famous
Barefoot bar in the South Pacific
She run
Tisa's Barefoot bar
It's a series of Follies or grass roof wooden structures on stilts
Thank you
Pretty magical and they are right on the water of this beach
I like a beach which is a Marine reserve
And actually stayed in one of the following overnight
And you
Step out onto the sand in the morning
And every shell
Moved
It was
Bursting with life
As for the pictures pin
Yeah the pictures
Raise a credible
Then what's the time here
Picture of a little bit I've been wrong
Just about many trails to see how far I get
Hahahahaha
What where has the grab the trails of like taking you
Taking me to
Foreign line in on the West Coast
She has flags from different countries and states hanging up in her bar
And she has a unique perspective on American Samoa I don't know why I just am so disappointed that the
That we ended up this way
Was very content with what little we get
And there's no waves bandana by the people don't know what their rights are people don't know they don't speak up
I appreciate these guys speaking up about the citizenship
Because at least that's a bold move showing that maybe somebody's thinking I have tendency to think
As you can hear in my voice my thumb
Lisa told me she went to the US Mainland for the first time when she was 16 years old
Looking for anything better I was just
Curious about what the other boy the world really looks like coming from this tiny lower.
So she went to live with her aunt in San Diego to go to high school there
Noise 60 I ended up following the Black Panthers the Black Panther
Had arrived in San Diego by that time I was curious
Say okay what are these people cuz all I hear is bad stuff
Solution I want to be the meetings of them
Newspapers were passed out posters post where the black people were gathering and we plan to keep the faith
The necessary to to liberate himself improve their lives
And they were actually citydog encouraging all the kids
Black kids blue kids whatever color kids to go including someone's like me
You go to college and I did and she said she also sat in on meeting
Things in the women's movement
Still have a job to have respect not be viewed as a piece of meat my whole purpose of hanging around whenever these big
Rally's and I listen I watch
Just learn and
Make a note
Learn and make a note and sitting there in the back of those meetings
Inevitably I keep thinking about how she begins to think
Men control their wives their children their daughters have no right to speak up
The way things work at home
Just isn't
Just so much Injustice year for women
The fact that women were not cheap
Women were abused
And young girls
Domestic abuse out of frustrations and this is why I love someone and they never want to come back here
But Lisa and her 20s decided she would come back
Yeah I never felt that California was my home I was just a student of California
And I learned a lot
I learned a lot about my rights as a woman and I'll earn my right to speak up
And she brought those lessons back home
When I came back I was
Very vocal
I spoke out I never back up
From any man
And so when my when I ran for governor so she ran for office we have our campaigning for political
Office
The song One Way you don't speak out against anybody
As we still don't
But I went against all that
Am I spoke up I spoke about rights
You have these rights that you can
Advocate for
But no one would do it because people were free and the Chiefs
My Dad's cousin
That he was a governor and he brought all the planning a big Who's Who the big
Cheap the big boys
They came to Dad
An acid
Ask him if you will please tell your daughter not to run for governor
Because that
That's what cheese do
And my father told me
Well she's so own person
She's going to do whatever she wants and she can do that she has those right
And I'm not going to tell her no
I love them forever for that but he didn't like me because I was
Because I was not the daughter
That I was supposed to be I was very vocal
Tara Strong voices I hear me
Did you win
Oh no I just serious I would never win
But I was very vocal
I was just out there I did not care I wanted because I learned from America you have the right to speak
And that was very big for me
And so she believe she's like the one reason why I am
Proud to be an American
Is that
We have rights
Does
Some part of the Constitution protect our rights
So again here we have a person who you think would absolutely support
Charlie's fight to get American Samoans US citizenship
But
No
I hope not it's not a good idea
Yeah I know today is still the wrong thing to address
She said it's not worth it
Wow
No way it's not worth it because
For when she thinks
You know American Samoans are already
Running off to the US
To bind like what they think is going to be a better life and US citizenship would probably make that drain
Rain on the island even worse
And then
For life on the island culture I need to protect
And it always my need to be a US citizen
It's not about me at all it's about my island is about my people it's about my family's about my Village
It's about this wonderful community so I will never go up and try to
Change anything if they're not with me I've learned that the hard way
I've learned that and I'm humbled by it
Because
Well communal system out your system
It's a very system that's keeping us alive and together I guess I'm wondering like what what about the communal system do you
You think would would definitely go away
No like what what is it about the communal system like that is completely incompatible with being a citizen
The Western ways is individualism it's about individuals rights mine my real estate mile
But for us it's about protecting all of us
I'll communal rights
So is complete opposite
Of the American system
If you bring in a whole bunch of immigrants is going to disrupt that Village it's already doing that
Why
People who move in and cite their rights I have the right I have my
Freedom to do this
That's not what it's about
In the evening we have a bell for everybody to enter their home and do the meditation to these people come in and look at us
Everything foreign us last already with us but but I mean like the people
People who are coming
I like they're already popping right and they're already having kids here we're becoming Nationals right like maybe that ship has
Yeah but if the land was still preserved
It's a joke I've seen all the land has been reserved the government turned them over and sell and make profit
Improve it
All right
Wow
She spent time with the Black Panthers ran for office
Still feels somehow
The
Existential threat to the Island's culture
Overrules those
Those rights
I don't know it
I mean it's the calculation in her head
But
I remember sitting there on the beach NJ
Not being able to wrap my head around it
I spent two Sundays in American Samoa
I went to church services
Not everybody goes to church but the island is about 98% Christian
Many people
Hold me
The center of faasamoa
I'm sitting in those pews
Watching people of all ages
Sing and interact with each other they all know each other
Looking out for each other
Is a feeling of
Belonging
Citizenship
Is about belonging
Belonging to the US tends to come with its own set of
Right
And responsibilities
End
It struck me that
The set of ideals which I hold so dear so many of us hold so dear
That people here
Would see them as a threat
To their survival
So I went back to Charlie Ally Lima
So I would actually talk to Dad
Fandango
Yeah so he
Ikea
Do you want to fight
I told him what Pisa had told me and then I got told me
Basically like Hawaii is a cautionary tale like
Why is it considered retail
It's interesting because
What do you mean saying is I don't trust America
That's that's what that means
And he told me
He doesn't think that this community would
Necessarily have to change
Cautionary Tale
History that happened
Hundred year hundred and ten years ago
Okay that was a hundred and ten years ago America
I would like that
Have they change
Jim Crow around any more of the ideas you know
You know
The real question is do you trust the US government
To do the right thing
Custer Federal
I personally believe that
If you don't trust the government get out of that government
He was like so we Samoans need to make a decision about Who We Are
If we want to be part of the us or not
There shouldn't be this in between
Constitution is a document that
Something that we should all aspire to we may not reach that but we always
That's why we still believe in it and I still have faith in you can go to the courts and
Get any problems rectified but
I lose that face and I'm just
Do you think what would make you lose stuff
Producer Julia Longoria
This story was reported and produced by Julia almost citizens
Tells the story of Isabelle Gonzales Doug Mack author of The not quite States of America which helped Inspire the story
Belinda Torres Mary and John person the Torres family for welcoming us to their home and thank you to Pongo Pongo chores
I like to say thank you again to Pongo Pongo Tradewind tours
Oh yeah yeah
And finding a Ada and her family and to Justin manga Vassar Daniel Holland David herdrich
Neil Weir and equally American witches his organization
Yeah I was planning to sail off I think right is
Okay okay I will see you the next time
Yeah I'm chat Avenue
You're listening
My name is Tim and I'm calling from Cleveland Ohio
Relapse created by Jarrod album run and is produced by Soren wheeler
Dylan Keith is our director of sound design
Suzie lechtenberg is our executive producer
Our staff includes Simon Adler
Becca Bressler
Rachel Cusick David gamble Bethel Hampton
Tracy hunt Nora Keller Matt kielty Robert krulwich
Julia Longoria
Annie McEwen
What is Nasir Melissa O'Donnell
Sarakari
Ariana whack
Pat Walters
Molly Webster
With help from Shima Ellie and Niall Danesha
Are fact-checkers Michelle Harris