Are you awake
Northern listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
Relative if you can remind your mind back to a time when your life wasn't dominated by Alan Funt and Candy Camera like how did
How does it start
So I first
A lot of
People I did not grow up watching candid
Camera I never heard of Candy Camera
Candid Camera
Have you heard of The Declaration of Independence that ring any bells
No
Actually no no BS
A founding father
Of a difference
Hey I'm Jared Radiolab when you least expect it
You're expected today
Time in r
Media history we're like the line between show and life
Was really clear
Then Along came a guy named Alan Funt who muddy that line in a way that was fascinating but
Fakta spiritual
I think those bite marks around all of our butts
So check your tush
And listen to the story for my producer lattof
First heard about Kenny camera few years ago and I when I did I just
Dovinh
Like I just
Binged
All of I I watched every single clip I go again
And then that's around the time when I found out that it's
Started as a radio show which was even more interesting to me because I was like
A Rios
How does that even make
What is that even what would that be
So I called up one of the
Few people who have
Studied
That's right
So I'm Jacob Smith an associate professor at Northwestern University School of communication and the director of
Northwestern's Masters in sound arts and industries
Kind of wonderful kind of creepy backs
You just want to start with
World War II
Yeah
So during what war was working in the signal Corps
The electronic communications
Sperm for the Armed Forces at a time
So fun teaser a few years out of college by this point he is stationed in Oklahoma at Camp Gruber
And his job there is to make
RadioShack
For the Armed Forces Radio one of these
The grape grape grape
Basically the show
Burnt wood gets old
You're stationed at the camp to come into His Studio
And talk about their gripes
Barracks in about the food in about you know their girlfriend is cheating on him back home or whatever you know things that were bothering
Not a very good idea for morale
Oh I think it's a great idea from around really good if I would imagine it would bring the soldiers down
Together
Fair enough
Anyhow so he's bringing these soldiers into a little recordings
Studio one of the things that he found with it as soon as the red light would go on
To indicate that recording was going on
They clam up
They would get tongue tied
Mike fright micro
Mike fry in any tells me stories about how it was amazing to see these soldiers
Who would go out in the battle
Without maybe blinking an eye but
Break into a cold sweat
At the thought of sitting in front of Michael
So what was what does he do also disconnect the red light
And record them secretly
So basically you bring them in and say okay let's just do a practice round let's just talk over the things the kind of things you will talk about
And then
When then finally they were ready to start I already got it
He would get better material
When they didn't know they were being recorded
Would they be okay with that likes will you just collect mission after work
20 more
It's a sort of Truth deferred
You might say but according to Jacob Smith front was like
This is a
Great trick yes you know the red light goes off in the great Booth but a red light goes on infant's mind
And so after the war he pitches this idea as candid microphone
Which goes on the air on ABC in 1947
This is Sonny Fox
And he was one of the original guys to work with Alan
Microphone
I can eat just so happy
When he came into our
Studio we manage
Him on
Power
Can you hear me
I can't. That is tepid water
Tepid water and I'm sorry the water snot
Up to Snuff
Why is my
Hot water now all of a sudden not so driven would have helped
Alright okay we're here to talk about much more exciting
So when you were working with Al-Anon candid microphone
What was he like how did you see him like
Adam is a very able very bright
Young guy at
I had a face of an Everyman
These big chipmunk cheeks
Stratus shorten a little plump
Covers about 5
And you could
Charm U when he wanted to
Xiaomi right out of your shoes
Or he could be overwrought
Amy had this huge
Tony says when they were just starting to show sometimes Alan would get so mad
It's like spring pencils another producer
Weather only four of us and II
That was it
That was the core of what we did
I will have to do everything
How long was the Arbiter obviously of whether we did something that didn't just have these two what was like what was the goal
Nicole was too and I wish to reflect
People
SAR
In their unguarded
We try to bring you the Real McCoy on can the microphone that's the beauty of everyday
We go out to the studio in the world everyday life
Sociologist Erving Goffman called bugging the backstage
What we would do is everyday sunny and crew would go to their office in Manhattan
2 room office
Jidenna
I think up ideas
Separately scratching our heads
What about this
Barber shop or a magazine
Maybe that's something we could
You know
Restaurant shoe store
So what they do is they take this big clunky portable recorder
It was like a suitcase it wait I think maybe
60 lb but they put a handle on top
Opposite of supporter
He says that they would lug around this massive suitcase
Do whatever it was a recording
And they try to hide it
So that no one would see it so they could record this
In all these different locations including the women's bathroom
I really don't
Vinyl
The teeth they gathered front was disappointed to discover that was the most uninteresting
Garbage you could imagine it was
Frustrating it doesn't have you know the nice shape
The rise and fall
Climax
That I'm is going to keep listeners hook now
That presented us with any problem
Better half hour show
But they needed to fill
His house
Desperate I was I was having a date
First date with a young woman
I bugged my car
And try to see how she would sound on a first date
She found out about that was not amusing that was the last
How did it go though it was not virgin
Desperate to get stuff
It's unlikely things
So here they had this show that was supposed to be about real people real talk everyday conversation but turned out that
So then the question became how can we mix it up how can we Stir It Up how can we
Change this into something more spectacular
And that's when Alan Funt added a little
It's something that Jacob Smith
It's called I was calling at the Rio
Instead of just letting people Yammer on which didn't seem to work
You got to get in there
You got e-juice the action
To get that right shape the man with a hidden Mike had a good one when he dropped
Mike is like his
Strange situation
She would go into a tailor shop with a microphone up his
Please
And he would ask the guy
Oh you can handle like here's another one play the moaning Trump this is Sony's
He says that
One day they called remover
To come over to their office
And inside the trunk the Hoover didn't know this was a guy
And his job was to
Sound Erie
2 basically mon every time to move or tried to move that trunk
Just be very gentle weather
What is it
Nvm just just take it
Resume supplies I want to know
Christmas begin
I'm laughing now
Give us a slip
20 minutes
I'm going to have a signature that delivered that I won't have signal time
Avocado such great mother
Fralin
What's getting people into situations where they were frustrated.
What kind of noise
There's no noise you don't hear anything
Come on. We've been waiting since last night
This thing out of here and just keeps going and going and going
Good morning what it is just driving them nuts
Until finally
Is your $20 they look for another truck
They lose their temper
Choose music
And that
The climax
That's the
Closure now the whole thing has a shape
It it starts slow and then
Crescendo Crescendo crescendo boobies inventing this new kind a new format of
Entertainment
It's totally obvious
But this is
Basically like
Reality TV in a nut
Like
This is one of the first time
Where you have that familiar hybrid of of this
Highly artificial and constructed situation
Within inside of it snippet of life
We've all been there
Situations where we've been frustrated when we don't understand what's going on
Situations where we bewildered
So what would start pushing
Tweaking it changing it trying out new permutations and sometimes
It's very much like a fly on the wall
Another these days
I'm kind of poignant
Segments
Of listening to
, time to get up
A wife trying to wake up her
15 minutes
Alright I am beautiful
Temperature Matt guilty so intimate
Is what so incredible
In this one forgot the white to be in on the go
Come on darling
Just leave me alone
Would you please get up
Go away
Tom
How do I get to take a shower
You go get lost
I don't like you talking to me that way once and for all I am six
What do you mean
Very nice
So you know you get this
Is beautiful backstage
Glimpse of everyday life
But
Where do we stop
And obviously it did prompt
Let her stuff you hisses and catcalls
Have you heard the one where I was just listening to it the other day where
We're listening write in to complain about that one
Yeah yeah that was actually cool yeah you tell us tell us about it well so
A few well-chosen ones that really made out of
She's writing in to complain that this was in a crossing a line
So what font does is he goes up to her door to talk to her
But it goes with a hidden mic
I wonder if I could have
Couple minutes of your time
Is that alright
The other day about one of our programs call a candid microphone
And I got it from your letter that you don't like it very much
No I don't
Fallout what are some of the things you find objects
Well I don't like it because I think it's snooping
Avenal prison
Out and out
Snooping
In your letter you said
Is that a little more strongly you said you thought were a bunch of dirty sneaking spy
Well
I suppose that the time and I was listening to the program I felt that way
Look at these people in their homes extemporaneously about the
What was it that you went into Sandman bedroom
Oh you mean the one where the wife awake in the house
We didn't know we were talking for speaking for the public. Started put him in a bad light
Why you may have something there but don't you think it's funny that sounds a man makes when he awakens
They're funny but they're only for him though in his own bedroom and I'm sure he doesn't enjoy having the whole world know about it
What you think most people are nervous and self-conscious in front of them
Not anymore I think most people text you a microphone very nicely
You said you talked to us about the same way if you know you know you were talking about microphone right now
Aveeno different
Let me show you this is
And what you just said is
Is ready to go out
From coast to coast is that make any difference
Faint dead away am I not coming in here and talk to you
I think so at the moment
This conversation may not be worth a nickel but would you like to have it on the air
Because I want the whole world to know
I miss 7
Oh my God that's amazing she just switched actually nnn you can hear in her voice.
Right I have this one adviser her name is
Is Jill Lepore she have this idea bastardizing it but
To put it crudely like we all kind of have these
To drive
OneDrive
Privacy
We
Don't
Want people in our bedrooms listening to us that is
The height of
Christina
And then on the other hand we have
Disk drive for
Publicist
It's exciting
Exciting to have
People pay attention to
And these two drives to drive for privacy in the Drive-Thru
Publicity are sort of
Competing in a
Two coming up that tension
Well just takes off
Literally tax break
What's the weather
This is Josh the rush calling from Los Angeles Radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan valve
Station enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology
In the modern world
More information about Sloane @www.
. org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
This summer
And I request
For those of you who
Who spend a lot of time with kids parents
Aunts and uncles teachers we're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments child brilliant
Basically I want to hear about those times when I did something
It just means you lean back and say
Maybe it was the moment that I
A kid you've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of their musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class
Music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the
Epic moments where
Kid does something super smart
It doesn't have anything to do with it
If you have a story
Go to radiolab.org
Flash brilliance
And record a short audio message
Fan that's radiolab.org
Slash brilliant
Thank you so much
Tatum Jad abumrad Robert krulwich Radiolab from a producer
Nasser about
Allen Funt the man with a hidden microphone where we left off he just made a radio show called
Candid
Mike Wells it did in fact
People like this program was it a hit
Yeah it moves pretty quickly to television
Candid Camera
Allen Funt in the spring of 1949 the show premieres on NBC
Show it's the exact same from setup weird or frustrating situations try and catch
Reactions
But when the show goes out on TV
A lot of viewers think that it's mean-spirited
That the subjects
Being somehow
Mystery that there were critics who were
Very unnerving
Set by there were people certainly do the critics say oh man I made a list
Tear of
Of a whole bunch of that criticisms from the 40s and 50s
And they're great their likes to know like they're so sweeping so okay so
So there was this one guy in the New Yorker this is in 1950
Who said and I love this
For my money
Candid camera is
Sadistic
Poisonous
Anti-human
And sneaky
What year was another
Hold on there is another kind of great
String of object
There's so many of
Another guy for different guy from The New Yorker
He found Alan Funt
Horse
Nagging
Suspicious
And misanthropic and to make matters worse
Zestfully cell
But I mean I think that becomes Canada PR problem that he has to fix
And according to Jacob
It was not a small problem no even all through the 50s
It's on and off doesn't really get its audience
It moves around different Networks
And all the while he's tweaking it and changing it adapting it
Early 60s
She hits on
Second little tweak
That would make all the difference
Fonts term was
The reveal
By 1962 he locks it and you start to see this thing happened over and over
The end of segment
Classic reveal is let's say
Dad is in a diner and there serving this guy if tiny little teacup
And he wanted a big coffee mug
Serving the tiny little teacup what's going on
Guy gets pissed off and then previously but would have let that keep going but now
What is the guy is about to blow
Punch someone out
And they kind of grab the guy in their life
Santa camera
They show him the hidden camera
On
Camera and as he's looking at that hidden
And he's like
Huh
The camera Zooms in on his face
MMG
What did actually happen
Cool people in place
It's for that very moment because one of their first reactions are to turn away or to cover their face
So he would sometimes have to physically restrain them and turning them towards the camera
So they can capture
That one
Weeding
Moment
And in that moment you see so much on their face they're they're angry they're embarrassed or ashamed of confused
You don't know how to feel a tendon
Right that moment
Fun says
The magic word
You're on Candid Camera
And it's all everything's everything is that okay
Where is the where you least expected
Addicted you're the star today
Smile
You're on Candid Camera
Something something Hocus Pocus
It's your lucky day it went from being like this
You Alex
This works
Much better I take it out I was hugely successful it was one of the top-ranked shows from
Basically all of the early 1960s
Million different tens of millions of people watched it
And I think part of the reason why was it
Without that sort of meanness it bled out the meanness and people could now
What it really was which of these
Kind of a little
Peepholes into
Human Nature
The first one I ever saw was the the elevator sketch
Do you know the elevators now headed to walk me through the elevator sketch
It's just really simple
It's really
Simple and it's so beautiful
The gentleman in the elevator now
Is a candid stop
Basic setup is guy walks into an elevator there's a hidden camera
He doesn't know
Is a fella with his hat on
In the elevator
He is like everybody else wearing his overcoat and a hat and he stands in the middle of the elevator and then
All of the other people in the elevator who we later learned hard
Confederate
They
They take offense
Take off their hats
And one by one by one what have up to have top five hats off
Open elevator door in he's just sort of standing there awkwardly and then he just
Assertive
Hesitantly is he just takes off his hat and then holds it in front of his you know chess
Maui
The procedure
Then all of the people around him they put their hats back on
Anthony started laying around and like it's almost it's
How many of this is somewhere between conscious and subconscious level and then he sort of just puts his hat on
It's really funny it's really really nice guy wasn't clearly just was trying
To fit in in this weird way it's interesting I never
Watch the T
But it's weird like we
When I was 7 we still
We would say all the time like
Smile you're on Candid Camera even though I've never seen the show
It was like the idea of the show is like in a way way bigger than the actual show
Yeah, came up but it but it was less about
Kind of
Investigating human behavior and more about
Vanity
In this weird way it was like this idea that
You
Tiny sliver of your private life
Could be
Exercised and then broadcast
To the world
And that idea
That idea would get away from
Fontaine it would go all over the world and then it would
Come right back and vitamin
The botanist
Really funny and strange
What what happened
Well
Okay it starts like this
Hi there
What's the story with this
Oyana
Maryland
The ex-wife of Alan Funt and
Where do you want me to stop over on the plane okay
Newark Airport
Maryland funds daughter Alan Funt daughter
Juliet's
My mom my dad my baby brother and I are on a fly
Straight flight to Miami and a half
So may I don't have any personal recollection of it
Tempered glass
Ameron flight a largely uneventful flight
For about the first 20 minutes
Maybe an hour who knows
They're about a hundred miles or so offshore and
You know the bathroom all of the sudden
A man stood up in the back of the flight
And he took out a knife
Any put it to the throat of the one of the flight attendants and he walked her
All the way down the center Island
Passing every pass
Easter on the flight
I did hear noises which were a little bit different
In the back
Does Fred Weaver retired Eastern Airlines pilot he was one of the flight crew and next to him
Circo pilot Lowell Miller they were second breakfast
You know I hear the knock on the door and I just open the door and I turned around to see who it was there she is
The flight attendant with the hijacker provider with the knife up against your throat
Shane
Kuba Kuba also was staying that his friend had a bomb in the back of the airplane
I do write this I said
Here we go
The stewardess was walking around
Talking with all the past years asking them if anybody knew how to speak Spanish
Coach 11 years old at the time I didn't think much of it
Until
Till the announcement came on the loudspeaker
Gets on and says ladies and gentlemen ladies and gentlemen we have some gentlemen up here that want to go to Cuba so
We're going to Havana
And then came the part of the story that I've been told was the waiting
The
Frozen
Silent
Staring at each other
Waiting
But then
This one woman
A few rows away begin to recognize my
And she began to look and look back and forth to other folks and point a little bit and there was a slow
Building of her certainty
And then all of a sudden
And sad
Second we are not
Being hijacked
It's a Candid Camera stunt I'm quoting him
The plane went absolutely crazy
Pension Thrift off of
People were lined up with
There are sickness bags to get autographs from my father
My dad is
No I know it's not me I'm not involved
BRB hijack
And they said come on Allen
We know it's you just trying to persuade people he's not getting any purchase
Behind him
Disease
A priest
He runs over the priest will you please help me convince these people this is not a
Maniac Is For Real
You can't get me Allen
Are we supposed to see a guy with you by the clerical collar everything
Where is the hijack
Terrifying people up in the cockpit
But eventually at some point
He hears this kind of commotion from first-class and so he does open the door and he pokes his head out
And everybody begins to applaud and applause
We're not totally sure about that last detail might be in Embellishments
Bored
Seems clear is it around this time Alan Funt
Starting to feel
Keeping so successful at
Bugging the back
Messing up the line between private and public in real life in Showbiz
Couldn't when he needed to we couldn't reassert that clearline I was worried
That he was going to come up with some idea to try to
Mitigate this situation and deal with it
What's he got so frustrated that he decided to just
Deal with the hijackers himself yes
So it starts formulating
Plant
Grab the guy I'm not going to the floor and my mother sang
Playing alone sit down before he's going to be like
Apparently the flight attendant had to tell him to sit down what happens now will you have you took it to the point where
Now the plane is landing in what I guess the people in the plane think of
Florida
People the front of the plane notice Cuba Cuba correct into the terminal what greeted as the plane is
Open to buy Cuban Military Officers
I saw a Cuban Soldier a gun in his hand and he had bandoliers you know with lots of bullets on him
Maven Circle the airplane
And it seems at this point everyone on the plane maybe the first time
Would like
Everybody really got it
But it was a hijacking
That was finally the reveal
Just really late
The Story Goes when they're getting off the plane when he's Cuban soldiers are escorting them off the plane he was standing in his seat
Twisty
Aspective
Human psychology all the passengers were
Filing down the aisle past him he began to take there
Feelings out on him
And they became angry at
And each one of them
Had sort of their own grab bag of curses for him as if he had tricked them as if he had
Set them up in some way
Person in that line from to my father and said
Smile my ass
Magic happens
Claw my ass was closing remarks
Business
Smile my ass
Tell me the meaning of this scene
Is that
Here's a man who
He has helped create a situation with people
In some kind of peril don't know if they're in Peril that they've been blinded
By the device that he created
It's suggest
It's the beginning of something
Blurry witch didn't used to be
As much as funny like when I hear that
Plane scene it's like I'm almost nostalgic for that kind of confusion cuz we have now is like
Actually way more confusing I think
Yeah cuz we all have these cameras are always taking these
Candid
Pictures of ourselves with like
Obviously
In series are candid but they're not really candid because we've taken like four of them in the one we choose we put the filter on and
Nowadays
Smith talks about
Is that that's pretty sure Matt kielty and he was her
Turn off mic
Clear hashing this out
Now what
Fun
Look at it
The faces they make
Poking
Who know their
Did they know
I'm trying to
Figure out what they
And how they work
Trying to figure out what part of that post is real
Exact
What he's really saying is that is that everyone who comes and Allen Funt
End
And the people on the plane like the confusion is trade basic
Like if you're going to go on Facebook when you were little bit of an allen fun if you're going to go on Twitter to do the thing you're producing each other
Then if you're actually trying to figure out how the other people are reacting to your how you read them or how they're reading you yet
A little bit like
You're stuck on the plane cuz you don't know what's real and what show
In a way
You split an infinitive half as opposed to xiamen and
The audience now everyone is in the showman and the audience
Both Park
It's like I think we're Allen funding ourselves
Enormous thanks to our producer lots of Nasser also co-producer Matt kielty and a special thanks to
Fun family
They couldn't have been more accommodating and we're generous Elsa Jim Zack and the Eastern Airlines employee Sissy
Let's want to close by wishing our producer Lynn Levy
A heartfelt
Thanks and good luck as she walks down the hall to work with our colleagues at Studio 360
We love you in
Miss it
I'm Jedi runtime Marakovits
Thanks for listening
Start of Messi
Hey this is Juliet Funt reading the credit
Zackass
And I was asked to read you the credit
Here we go
Brenna Farrell
Dylan Keith
Matt kielty Robert krulwich Andy Mills
Latif Nasser healthy Paget Ariane Black Molly Webster Thorne wheeler
New York
Alexandra Lee Young
Abigail keil
And Alexandra Brennan
Michelle Harris
That's it okay
Smile
You're on radio.
And this message