Are you awake
Northern listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
So how did you guys ever find out about
How to get into it
I think it was somebody was reading about it
This is manoush zomorodi
Was we are we with you reading about it right
MSR producer Alex goldmark
His name is McNutt
Name at least
And dimes please
Like we actually read it and it was
Weird and interesting and brought up
Lots
Technology is remaking what is possible for individuals
And for institutions and for the international order
Young Jedi runtime Roberto which is Radiolab so here we are at this moment in time where we at we are face
Faced with these decisions
About what we want our future to
To look like
There are fewer and fewer technical constraints on what we can do
That place is
A special obligation on us to ask tough question
About what we
Should
With our friends down the hall manoush zomorodi and Alex goldmark there on a grape podcast
Note to self pay will be our guides
Into the world
Of McNutt yes my name is Ross McNutt
Sub McNutt
As I refer to him
He's an ex-military guy 20 years in the Air Force I enjoyed it
I did a lot of good like combat military
Yah mean
I think he's actually special
My background I've got a PhD in Rapid product development out of MIT
And what I do is I teach young people how to build new systems
And the new system that's a system that we want to talk about that kind of began in 2004
Ross was teaching a course at a Military College
Was that the Air Force Institute of Technology here in Wright-Patterson in Dayton
Does one day in 2004
Are the whole school gathered together
Pharrell
And our commander got up in front of the whole school and said we need to do something to help
The war effort
Terrible violence today in the city of Basra at that time in the Iraq War
You're not going well suicide
IEDs going off
All over the place is going off everywhere soldiers being blown up
Weak I got blown up
Recon
And to be honest with you in 2004 it looks like we're going to lose
Psoriasis he gets together some of the students some of his colleagues and they decide Lena let's sit down and see if we can find
Find a solution quickly find a solution
To figuring out who is planting all these roadside bomb
Yeah
Bombs going off of pretty easy to detect
And images
The problem is
How do you go from
Bomb going off backwards in time
To be able to figure out who planted it
So
Somehow
It just came out
Are you guys sitting around
It was at a bar
We're working on the back of the napkin
And withdrawing out different ideas and turning around and seeing what happens
They're just like hey let's he's playing just try this let's try that
They had this one stock and we sort of
Through this out on the back of an MBA
Making it
Took a little while
38 students working
Confirm me for 2 years
But eventually they developed what became known as
Project Angel Fire
You're at work to take a small plane and on the belly
The plane they hook up his array of cameras
Start the camera system we design and build
Super hayat
Men the pilot
Takes off
Flies the plane High over Fallujah
Military we were up at about 15 to 16 thousand feet to stay out of the Missile Range
On the ground in Fallujah and I look up what would I say
You wouldn't see us
You wouldn't hear us or you wouldn't see us
Over Fallujah circle circle circle
Click
Click every second takes a still image of the entire city of Fallujah 25 square miles
And then teams it down to an operator we take a picture
Processing Down Lincoln
Process it Down Lincoln
Every single second
To the plaintiff snapping picture after picture after picture which cures what makes the system so powerful
The operator on the ground has what say an entire day's worth
Of the high-res pictures of the entire city of Fallujah
And let's say there's an explosion at least 20 people were killed in explosions on the market
11 others
First the operator would pull up the most current image of the city
Zoom into the place with in Fallujah where it happened
And then click
Click click
In one second increments go back in time
And see who was there what happened the last time somebody fiddled around in that
Yeah you like okay I might have gone back to ours and
It's bad car
Fast forward
Click the canal follow that car forward
In time
To see where it goes
You see that it went to
House in another neighborhood 2 miles away
Well that's where you dispatcher troops to write that
Basically we be able to send either the Special Forces then I the Marines in
Intuitive
Take appropriate action
It's not like they release a lot of
Think about how well their
Technology has work
But you will find several quotes from office
Saying that yes
Project Angel Fire disc
Save lives
But the reason why we decided to do the story is because it's not just a military thing right like with a lot of
These Technologies they may be stored in the military
But then they trickled down all the way down
To all of us
Actually in this case trickle-down
To Dayton Ohio
Ross Group Incorporated
Yabby weird producer and emails and I actually went to Dayton Ohio
To visit Ross
At his best
Persistent surveillance systems persistent surveillance
Write that essay
Orwellian
These are the lenses and the motors here basically control it
So first we went over to his Workshop where he actually works and makes the camera
These are more powerful than some of the best military systems
Like we could see him actually making them and how they get attached to the bottom
The airplane
Oh so many airplanes then we went over to the hangar where he has all the airplanes
Beautiful Dover all we got 27 airplane
Africa
Oh my God it's big and then he showed us their Command Center
And this is where you have a bunch of people sitting in front of these enormous screen
This is like your viewing room
Yeah and this is where all the
Plane pictures end up
Because Ross is basic idea and taking this technology from Fallujah to a city like Dayton Ohio
Basically this is just as large a problem as we doing
Afghanistan and Iraq only it's not IEDs it's crying
We've had a lot of major events this year we've had four officer-involved shooting so far this year our homicides are up this
Here to this is Dayton Police Chief Richard Biehl
I talked to him last summer
Couple years ago
Ross call them up
Was like look a city like Dayton Ohio we've got 28,000 crimes a year
About ten thousand part 1
Murder rape
Salt 10000 part 1 crime
Comes out to be 480 million dollars
A year but McKnight is like for the about the price of a police helicopter we believe that we would be able to decrease
Crime by 30 to 40
Percent
30% decrease in that is 155 million.
The Dayton Police were like
Basically setup
The test
In June of 20
12 for a five-day flight
Hip Hop
This see for ourselves
What it was capable of doing
Isn't the plane up in the air
Started doing its thing
Buju
And within just a few hours
There is a
Call of this a breaking entering a
In progress with the description of an irregular random moving
This is Angie horn
She's the one who called 911
Almanor lunch break
And she see the moving van
Pull up in front of her neighbor's house
Guy gets outbreaks in
Start smoothie
You know we immediately called the police and they got their relatively quickly from what I remember
He had already taken off
Now normally in a case like this the police would be like
Well how do we follow
We don't know where he went
But this case
The police contact persistent surveillance systems and ultimately
James Alex blasingame I'm the senior analyst for the company
We're about 5 minutes until he sees this little grainy white. Appear in front of her neighbor's house
Is the vehicle here that we're wanting to track what vehicle I don't I barely see anything so the image looks blurry
But the human brain in the human eyes are very very evolved to pick out movie
You gotta understand that from two miles up a car looks just like a random shape
People they look like
Alex has trained himself to
Pick out Lube
Going to put a tag down and where he's at places in Orange Circle over that random little shape
And then quickly quickly moves forward forward forward follow him to his real time location
Alex follows it up some roads finds out that it is parked in a parking lot six blocks away because up the people on the field
Does go over there they get there they see the guy
Is your truck full of stuff
They send different cap over to pick up the witness
Yep that's the guy
Yeah this is minutes later
No kidding
That Could Have Been a Murder
I could have been armed robber
It could have been a lot of
This is so weird is like having a superpower but it is actually better than Batman you can't go back for the
Timeshares
Superhero
I just feel sad
It's like
We're all just he's little.
It just seems like the antithesis of what a lot of
Police Department seem to be trying to do in the aftermath of
Staten Island
Other
Horrific things
That have happened
Which is getting the police
On the sea
Making personal connections
Creating relationship
There's nothing in this system
That prevents you from having affect
The community policing
Battle by the way this may dramatically help
That community relations
The reason they're putting body cams on
Fun police officers is try to get the police officers
More respect
Old because they
Well this lets us watch all the off
25 ski
Malaria
But then you can watch so many other people
Here's other things that people in Dayton do
Like Romeo and Juliet they sometimes meet without the
Their parents permission
In the playground
Smooch
There are going to be divorce lawyers who going to be tracking Aaron spouses
Is there going to be traffic police work
Watching who goes through the red light there going to be Realtors were wondering who are how many tenants do
You really have in that building and I guess
This thought might beat it
If the information exists
That will show what my pixel was actually doing then
Then I'm a little less
Free
There is a
A clear trade off
Between
Security price
And
You know in our major cities where we have
Tens of thousands of Major Crimes
You are a lot less free when you can't leave your
House at night
Is obviously a
Huge advantage
To knowing what you know
But then there's a huge
Sing
To knowing what you
Acknowledge all by itself is sort of
Is pregnant with
Funny
You know what here's my problem with with
Was it all of these private
It's like when you talk about these technology
The advantages are always so concrete
And the trade-offs
Always feel so abstract
I feel like there is there certain there's something being lost here but I can never quite put my finger on
Twitter
Oh Dad that weirdness that you're feeling
It's
Can I get
A lot weirder
Hey this is Jenny Lanahan from Round Lake New York
Radiolab is supported in Paris
By the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloane @www
Phone. Org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help this summer I'm hosting
And I request for those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
We're looking for stories about what we're calling tiny moments of childhood Brilliance basically I want to hear about
Kids you know did something
It just means you lean back and say wow how did they do that
Maybe it was the moment that our kids you've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lessons and you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin
Maybe the kids in math class you noticed they're ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the
Specific moments where
A kid does something super smart but doesn't have anything to do with the test
If you have a story please share it with us
Go to radiolab.org brilliance
And record a short audio message
And that's radiolab.org / brilliance
Thank you so much
AM General Murad I'm Robert krulwich Radiolab and
Continue our collaboration with manouse emirati and Alex goldmark from Note 2
Self and my septic is and remains
Eyes
In the sky
In the situation we left it is at mnuchin one of our producers and emails have gone down to Dayton Ohio to talk with Ross McNutt
Check out his technology
How are you feeling
I was feeling like
You have not convinced me I do I am not
Gone for this
And then I saw was my
And that
Well
I mean that's what made me start to think otherwise
Where is especially the time we did this the average
300 murders a month
52 kidnappings a week 300 murders a month
Yeah
McNutt the gang they got a contract we've been asked not to say
For whom
And they went down south set themselves up in a hotel room got the plane up in the sky and then whoever the client was started
Bringing them crime reports
So this is kind of what you never want to see happen but this is kind of why the system was up
Alex pulled up on the screen is very grainy aerial shot
Avoir as This Is War
It looks like any city right you've got like grids of streets
Cars and houses
Like over on the left of the screen
Key points to the start little square it's a vehicle
It's going down the street
This is a female police officer she was actually headed to work
On this morning
All kind of go through it here there's her house
Her car is parked outside
You see that like little pixel gets in her car
She pulls out of her driveway that was her home
Start to drive to work
And then right when
She leaves
If you look up
Here points to the upper left
Several cars were parked
Up on the corner
Soon as she left her driveway those cars
Become active
So this is a Stakeout
Yeah they were waiting for her to leave
He's so zoomed in
That you can see it's like a Tic Tac moving down the street
And then two more Tic Tacs come alongside
Until they get right about
I hear clicking forward on the photo and you see these cars just inch closer
Kind of hesitate there which is
Unfortunate
So she's driving down the street and Thursdays
Is cars following behind her
And then
There's this car up ahead of her
A vehicle that had been parked here for
15 20 30 minutes all the sudden
Backs out into traffic
And seemingly slows them down almost gets in an accident right here
Which gives these guys
Enough time
Ketchup
Is where there go
Pull up beside her
And then suddenly
Alex says
Right there this is the point
Where are the first car pulls up and shoots her mouth
Whole time she was shot in the head multiple times in the head right here
She's actually going to roll through the intersection
Her car continues to go even though she's been
Gunshot in the head
There's a park
Car behind the tree
And you'll actually see this parked car move
When she runs in
And then these guys
Takeoff
It was
Not fun to watch
But
What happens next
Made me really start to understand what this technology is
Real quickly just
Show you some of the other takes that moment
Horrible moment and then he starts to like shoot back and forth in time
Bad before the murder hears his path after the murders actually takes the two cars from that murder and you see
He draws on the map you see that they meet up with two other cards that were involved in a different word
One murder becomes two two cars become 4.
And if you follow all four of these cars drawing lines as they move through the city
You find out who they meet up with four becomes KAIT8 becomes so on and so on and you have all the
These lines crisscrossing the city and then you see that a whole bunch of those card
Are headed to one place
This house
This house appears to be there cartel headquarter
And
That's when you start to think
Oh that's how you have to take something
Like this down
It's not a One-Shot thing like solving the crime
It's about cracking an entire system
In fact
This is Andy Harris
When I was doing some
Some background research on this part of the story
I spoke
This one
Source from the US government who told me
That
This information that roster
Did you showed us
It was one of the primary tools
Used to dismantle
An entire cartel Juarez in that
Apparently
The leader of that cartel
Was responsible
Something like
Murders
Cigarettes
Cigarettes again so how are you feeling at this point
Happier
Scared
Feel ashamed of myself
Because I thought all the reason why I'm so excited about it is
Because it's in a country
I don't live
And I'm an outsider and I think of it as being met
Stop
So it's okay for them but it's still not okay for us
What did you think Andy
I mean
Like this is where I
Stop being a good journalist because I picked a side
It feels wrong
Cannot solve these crimes
Things that we can solve
And what is his plan is on top of New York
Good
God really
From me it became
Could you remember like after 9/11 when you'd walk down the street and you hear the F-16 circling over the city
I just remember the feeling in my stomach was like nausea like I felt
Stick it felt
Grossed it felt like we had no autonomy over ourselves and at that point I was scared enough that I could live with it but right now
Now I don't feel that way
And
Look at it's a very privileged position to be able to say that we
Shouldn't have it
I get that
I've became a convert
Because
Somebody got kidnapped
And if we had an eye in the sky we might be able to get the kids back in a few
Minutes hours
Compared to like you see the stats on Amber Alerts they're not good
What we're talking about is like and I'm not saying that I'm like anti McNutt
Not at all but what I'm saying is like
It's very easy to paint it as
We're going to get bad guys and I just don't think it's that
McNutt & Co they seem like decent people they have set limitations for themselves they have said they
I will not use photography that could get any closer they've made a moral choice
With that how do we know other people will make the same moral choice
Even though this thing might solve
A ton of crimes
Might save lives
It's still not worth the risk
Because
It just asks
Level up
Of trust
In government
That we shouldn't
We shouldn't get
Is that what you're saying
For now yes
So
Back to dating what would happen in Dayton
Well I was pretty impressed
That was pretty impressed
After that five-day demo the
Police chief Richard Biehl
I recommended
That we
Enter into a contract
What is valency
And so
They took it to the city Commission
Alison Carey Gregg New York
According to Carrie gray director of the city Commission office
For the city of Dayton Ohio city commission was interested in the in the presentation
But they decided that before they go forward they should have a public forum
So they could just
Hear from the people
There was about 75 or so people there and he says that the people of Dayton
People of Radiolab a note to self
I'm very divided
A quarter
Of the people
Where
Supportive of this technology and they were
Frustrated with the amount of crime their belief was I'm not doing anything wrong so I don't care what
People see me doing
We want this implemented and we want it implemented very broadly Bring It On they were basically in the
Then there was another group
Slightly smaller but not my mind maybe 15% believed
This was a grotesque
Invasion of privacy and some of the people spoke in
Very impassioned
Terms
So yay
I think they calling it grotesque invasion of privacy would pretty much reflect the weight and the way this group was feeling
Proved him and that there was no way that you could trust government
With this volume of information and this breath of information
So you had your Pros in your cons
The rest of the people like the majority maybe had some feelings one way or another but just didn't have enough information
And so they came and kind of
Eye mask
Questions
Like how long will persistent surveillance systems keep the images
90 days
How far can the zoom in can they see my face
Know something it'll ask questions
Which carry seems to think that they could have answered they could have gotten everybody on board
But in the end
Even though the room was basically divided into
The three parts
The naysayers were so loud and so impassioned
That these would have defined the
As we do so we took that lesson to understand that
There was going to be
Some significant
Education that was going to be needed and some significant hurdles that we're going to have to be crossed
Before that we were able to do a broad-based implementation
And
Based on the amount of time
What's going to have to be spent
We decided there were other more immediate techniques that could be used it could be invested in and we took the money
That could have been spent on this
And spend it on some other activities
It seems like what you're saying is it like
It was just going to be too hard to get people of the hurdle so I guess it's not worth it
Yeah
I think that's probably probably accurate So the plan is off
Table saw
It's off the table for right now
But that doesn't mean that it's never coming back on the
I think it's fair to say
Frustrating to him
Right now we've got about a hundred and fifty million dollars for the proposal sitting out there for a large number of cities Baltimore
Moscow weekend
There were waiting for them to me
We've done Compton and Jerome Compton psych maybe like maybe dating is like maybe
Whole lot of babies out there
They're analyzing as we are looking at a
Turnpike or something yet traffic in New Jersey
Understanding traffic
We look at congested areas which are typically especially in that part of the country
Exits and on-ramps any kind of Junction in a highway sometimes you just want to scream
I think that might be 10 times
Thank you and thank you
Yeah sure
Search like this hour of course the Medusa Meridian Alex goldmark also to Dan Tucker and George scholz
Everybody listening right now to go to iTunes and download the latest podcast from notes
To self the show that's all about
Grappling with the difficult questions living in the digital world and their latest podcast
It's got a story that I don't believe anyone else has really told it's a story about another kind of technology that can serve C
Into your private
Play spaces and this one
Is arguably
Way more invasive than the one we talked about this
Note to self on iTunes check it out will also link you there from radiolab.org
I'm Jad abumrad Robert krulwich
Thanks for listening
We watching
Eminem I'm here to
Register my concern regarding the Airborne surveillance that was discussed earlier
A great eye littlest resistant play
Do military contractors watch over the road
I'd also like to register my
Concern with the so-called surveillance program this was the stuff of science
Fiction when Orwell wrote 1984
What policies did Satan have in place to prevent
Using the data in a racially biased way
This piece was produced by animals and we had original
Music from
Donkey
Received at 4:50 p.m.
Hey it's very similar OD the host of WNYC use note to self Alex goldmark with the credits
Their staff includes Brenna Farrell ellenhorn
Latif Nasser Melissa O'Donnell Kelsey Padgett
Molly Webster store in Wheeler and Jamie York with help from Daniel
With help from Damiano marchetti Molly Jacobson and Alexandra Lee Young are factors are
Usher and Michelle Harris
And this message