Are you awake
Listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
Hey I'm Jared I'm Rod Heim Robert krulwich
It's already 11:00 here we are in this moment we're about to get started with another election cycle another I
Iowa Northern New Hampshire
Caroline and all of that this is the time when we were going to have to tell you some stuff and you're going to have to decide what matters to you
You and the three organs on this podcast
Cat is about a mon
Shockingly recent
A moment of win
What reporters
Decide to tell on what people
Will decide the value
Really changed
So we can
Take you back
To an evening in 1980s
Tom Fiedler a splitter reporter
The Miami Herald
It's late at night
He's in his office
That my desk and just infect packing up to go home my phone rang and I'm thinking I was by my wife and she's wondering
I haven't left yet
Set all right I'll pick it up pick up the phone turned out this
It turned out it was not a voice he recognized
It was a woman's voice maybe in her late twenties and she said to him I have something you need to know
It was a tip about one of the most powerful and charismatic man in American polity
Former Senator Gary Hart Who at the time was not only the most likely candidates
Become the Democratic nominee
He was very Potter
We going to be
Next president
Her words to me
Gary Hart
Is having an affair with
My best friends
And she told him basically
I can prove it
And I and I wish I was
Rather
I guess so
Thomas tracpipe
Any thoughts on how what do we do
Now if you're of a certain age you probably remember the story probably know what happens next but even if you've never heard
Heard of Gary Hart you still probably know the outline of the story
The accusations dial
Not have sexual relations with that woman and after that the whole damn wall-to-wall media thing
Which just goes on and on and on until you want to take your head off your shoulders put it on the sidewalk and beat
With a baseball bat
But the thing that's easy to forget
Is it it wasn't always
Like this no
Heart was the first
To walk into this Vortex of social forces
And after that the rules of political journalism in politics change almost immediately
That by the way is Matt
By national political columnist for Yahoo news wrote a book about this incident what you called all the truth
He's out of surgery this is the moment Gary Hart 1980s
7 win
Political journalism slid off the
Even argue
When it
Finally got Siri
Well you know this flashback a minute cuz I think if I think the context is important
1984 heart kind of comes from nowhere it's a whole new ballgame
I'm in the race for the Democratic Presidential nominee runs for president dorms New Hampshire
Play to a clear-cut victory over Walter Mondale and becomes a political celebrity
Let's country cannot stand for more years of Reaganomics for the rich
Gary Hart a Democrat and proud of it
Misses tall good-looking Democrat he's got great wavy hair I mean dashing
Handsome charismatic
And young this is Leslie Stahl TBS
She's covered politics for 40 years now works for 60 minutes he was cool and smart
Women liked him too he's an empty Orthodox Democrat very liberal anti nukes
He is sort of the Bill Clinton before Bill Clinton
He doesn't get the Democratic nomination in 1984 Walter Mondale.
Buy a nose butt
When Mondale gets
Crushed by Ronald Reagan
Heart is immediately
Presume to be the next nominee the party at a time when
These things were more obvious
So fast forward to 1987
Like it or not campaign 88 is underway and the leading contender
When it is running double digits
Higher than any Democrat Annie's projected to beat George Bush
The Republican
Next president United States Gary Hart
It felt like
Look this is a guy
Who is
Changing power
I'll take Sue is unafraid
To speak the truth who is willing to be
Really clear about what he wants
That's Kevin sweetie he was Hearts press secretary in 1987 he joined the campaign
Just a few years out of college
23 I'm idealistic
The first time we we really met
He I was wearing a necktie with
Pictures of Lincoln and Washington
That's the ugliest
Ever seen in my life
Set my mother Maiden
Well that's a good beginning
Remember why
He was really liberal and socialist
Unafraid
Do you spell
He said heart placed an extraordinary amount of emphasis on not just winning the campaign but what would they do
Do when they
Gotten off
He commanded
That attitude
So they rode out all these position papers on
Foreign policy energy International Trade the budget even what would his relationship with Gorbachev
There was something about
Heart and something about
What happened on the cow
And where it did feel like
The kind of campaign that I haven't seen since
When does the subject of what goes on below the belt come up if it all
I will
There were rumors
Definitely
By this time there are a lot of whispers about his personal life in a lot of speculation
He's been married to his
College sweetheart Lee for very long time they've been separated twice
The long separations enjoying the separations he's dated openly in water
So it's a well-known
Fact of life in Washington where he is essential
I'll figure it has a lot of friends in the Press Corps that he's dated
Now that he's dated people for extended periods of time that he and his wife have a troubled marriage
Not together and not together he stayed on Bob Woodward's couch for a little while when
She kicked him out at one point
Nobody wrote about that the reason they didn't write about it
Was because of a very
Old
Very well-established
Convention could go back to the 20th century Franklin Roosevelt
Lyndon Johnson Dwight Eisenhower
Gyros
Towering figure
Their personal life simply were not in play
Take the example JFK
Leslie Stahl says when the Press was covering him vast numbers of reporters
Knew that John Kennedy was cheating on his wife
That was no sick
But we wouldn't have
Reamed
Printing.
Even if the Whispers were loud enough to spread around the country
It just wasn't done is a thought pay
Nobody does
Forget about it
Or hey that has nothing to do with
With steak
I think the feeling was the so what
You know we all get to have a zone of privacy
And assumption was that what happened in your private Zone
Behind closed doors had nothing to do with whether you were going to be a good president or not
I mean through a certain
Uncertain
Standards I guess
This is the world that hard
Still thinks he's living in that as long as it doesn't burst into public View
It won't be a star
The map by says that world is X
Changing
Because of a political earthquake
Just over a decade
Before
Talking about the Watergate break-in
Knocked out breaking that wall five people have been arrested and charged with breaking into the headquarters of the Democratic National Committee
Yale arguably the biggest scandal in White House history
Yeah Nixon tapping phone line compiling enemy list
And for the reporters covering neck
It really is an embarrassment
You had an entire White House Press Corps
Political process
Campaign dresser
I followed this man Richard Nixon for decades
And somehow either missed the fact or failed to report the fact
He had some significant psychological issues and was paranoid
And could be corrupted I think there was a sense that
We let the public down
Leslie Stahl remembers it this way regular White House Press reporters
They should have been digging
Chipping away chipping away chipping away they should have been looking behind the curtain and so right
After Watergate
Reporters became tougher
Saying okay
We have to be skeptical about
Everything
And in particular
The characters
Meaning suddenly your makeup your personal Behavior who you are and your private moments
Matters a whole hell of a lot for the kind of President you can be in whether or not we can trust you
As a publicly
What character is the subject tonight of our weekend Journal
What Americans choose president's personal character traits are important
A great deal of scrutiny
I remember
There was a bit of a shift in
The kinds of reporters who are covering Nashville
They had a different orientation
And they were really interested
That's Kevin Sweeney again he says he was initially fresh
Grated 5 reporters
Strange obsession with things that we're not really
Issues important issues in the campaign like age there was some confusion about heart Sage the fact that
He changed the family name his signature changed at a certain point is life he says when those stories
Usually popped up I I thought it was a false set of issues I didn't really take it seriously
Came to the rumors of quote womanizing or marital infidelity
You felt like you needed to talk to
I I did say it if if anything is happening it needs to stop
I mean this can't whatever it is I mean I understand he said you know nothing's
And he shot back and said they have no right to cover that that
That's ridiculous it's not an issue that you know why is that an issue that's not their job
And I kept pushing back tonight on max
Kara weather
I don't care what you think
This is the new Conte
Text that exist now
I don't know why or how
The rules of chain
The rules of chess
Joe Webb
This brings us back to
Did Tom Fiedler the Miami Herald he was covering Gary
Heart going with him to all the stops
Iowa
New Hampshire and so forth
And at
Seems like at every stop along the way
Someone some reporter wood
Raise
Her his hand and would say what about the rumors of his woman I
Dump says that he would see reporters asking all these questions and he he was a little bit trouble so on April 27th
He wrote a column
Asking the
Is it ethical for journalists to be even raising this kind of a
Of a question
Tonight I really came down to the conclusion that unless
The
Mediamaster reporters involved had actual proof
That this was a problem that he was a womanizer we just shouldn't be printing that
Column runs on a Monday morning
That night
He gets the call
The voice on the other side says Gary Hart
Is having an affair with
My best friends
Stumps truck as we know I told her that
My position had to be that I couldn't believe what she had to say unless they would
And I'm finally she said my friend is going to fly up to Washington
Next weekend and she's going to spend the weekend with Senator Hart
She said so all you have to do is buy a ticket on that plane
I thought well
Would that be ethically
Okay what is inbound and what is out about
I mean character was his new obsession political journalism but according to Matt by no one had taken that character
Into
A candidates bedroom
That was new
This is inbound because
Gary Hart was publicly
Denying that
He had been carrying on affairs with
With anyone
Clear oftentimes when Gary Hart was asked about these rumors
Never asked directly to
It's about the rumors
He say something like that
It's no one else's business
Now why is it not anyone else's bills
Because it is
No but hasn't been the business of the American public for 200 years and it isn't today
He say something like that
The Fiedler says
A couple times when he's asked he did say something that amounted to an o
Such as if there was any truth to these allegations it would have come out long before the kinds of answers that
Work non-denial
Denial another phrase
Came out of Watergate so my view at that
Point was if in fact there was
Proof
That he was carrying on an affair privately while publicly insisting that
There really was no Bass
To this event that was irrelevant issue relevant to his
Performances
Dispute future president yes
Was a question of integrity
So we thought the only way that we are going to
Find out if
If what the caller told us is
Is true is
We've got to
That's coming up next
Hey sweet Eliza coming from Milwaukee
Radioactive supported in part by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation enhancing public understanding of Science and
Biology in the modern world
More information about Sloan at www.scoan.org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here I'm a producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
About what we're calling tiny moments of brilliance
Basically I want to hear about those times when I did something
It just means you lean back and say whoa how did they do that maybe it was the moment that I can
Kids you've been reading to 4 month started reading back to you
Or maybe the kid was a piano
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the margin of their musical score
Or maybe the kids in math class you noticed are ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the
Epic moments where
A kid does something super smart but doesn't have anything to do with the test
If you have a story please share it with us
Go to radiolab.org brilliance
Record a short audio message
Again that's radiolab.org / brilliant
Thank you so much
Hey I'm Jared I'm Ron I'm rubber
Call witnesses Radiolab getting back to the story
Tip
Saying
Can they carry hardest
Having an affair
He thinks himself this is in bounds
If it's true
Therefore
You've got to catch him
Who's editor tells a colleague of his Jim McGee to go to the air but telling you this is what you're going to do you're going to look for a while
Woman who looks like a model that's how the woman on the phone describes
Frenchie's described as a model blond in her mid-twenties and call me back if you see it
This guy Jim race to the airport spots this attractive young woman fits the description of course we
Later knew was Donna Wright so he boards the plane they land in DC he follows her out of the airport to a cab
He runs to another cab jumps that any says follow that cab just like the movies The Witch picked who
He loses her for a while but then eventually you get to the house where he thinks
Heart and this lady should be Han he's not there more than a few minutes when the front door opens and
Now comes the young woman on the arm of a very handsome man
Jim had never met Gary Hart had no idea what your heart look like
I really couldn't pick Gary Hart out of a lineup
That's when I really thought we have got
To go to Washington
And that's what they do the Harold Matt by again they send a team of reporters investigative reporters NC
Delorenzo photography to Washington we arrived Saturday morning they stake out his townhouse
I'm thinking my gosh somebody will surely notice that there are four five of us lurking as problem
Fight word it's May and one guys in a parka
Disguise himself infielder who the candidate knows is in a jogging suit and he's pretending to jog around the street all day long I would
Change clothes a little bit
Occasionally I would run without the jacket
Other times I would just be wearing a t-shirt and shorts that you run around around around
What you'd expect from a newspaper are proton quotes takeout went on all day into Saturday night and it got dark
And then
Front door opens
Outcomes
This man and outcomes
The blonde woman part walks out with Donna Rice
Arm in arm Keys quickly realizes something is wrong
Any kind of makes the surveillance they see him he sees them he turns her back around they go inside go back inside the
Townhouse
He sent her away through the back door and then he comes back out of the townhouse
Hopsin's car
And starts to drive off
So our photographer starts the chase Senator Hart car he drives a couple blocks up streets
Down Streets back and forth he gets out of the car
Following Ducks around the corner be losing for a second then they're running to catch up and then baked
And there's hard
There is the presumed nominee of the Democratic Party
The most important Democratic politician in the country
And they're confronting each other
Infer moment
Standing in the alleyway behind hartstown house they just stare at each
Because there is no script
At this moment
Ultimately
Pepe reee he asked what who are you
Well we're from the Miami Herald and
He didn't really say anything
So
So I told him that
He wanted to know why he was meeting with this woman in his townhouse
A woman who at that point we knew
Had spent the night with him he says in Myriad ways myriad Times
I'm not going to tell you that
That woman was
This is private
This isn't public but he says there's no Affair which he would maintain Forever After
And I ultimately he's had. I've said enough
And he turned and walked inside
Slam the door
We did tell him though he said we're going to write this story
Unless
We you give us a reason as to why
Explain this to y
What we are seeing and what we're concluding is wrong
He never did
So we kind of look at our
Cells and said well now what do we do
Ultimately the call was
We have the proof
We feel we needed
We know that publicly he was saying these things and we now know that privately he was engaged
So they ran back to the hotel room Fiedler frantically typed out the story
Gary Hart
, who's presidential campaign has been dogged by rumors of womanizing
,
Friday night and much a Saturday with a woman who came from Miami to meet
I finally went back and I I probably slept for three or four hours you're going to do the story The only thing that
It gives me pause as if you're under this standard you lose Jack Handey certainly
Yeah lose Woodrow Wilson
I think
So
You lose a lot of
People
You might not want to lose but you know I a leap to the conclusion that the
The public would vanish
A person for that
And I I don't
I don't go there
So are you worried about how it's going to land
That's a pretty sure Jamie York
Terrified
Apus jobs
And the next morning political world explodes
Gary Hart truly became a firestorm
Park 12
The Miami Herald reports
Washington townhouse that Story begins ricocheting around the country on
So by Sunday
Very apparent that only has heart in trouble
But the entire culture of media around politics
Text has changed in some very dramatic way
And when you think about the mindset of
The television people the radio people the newspaper people
Is there any
Self Doubt there is there people in a shoe is this really a question
Some of his ability to conduct matters of
State is that question being asked there's a tremendous amount of self
Not everyone agrees that such intense public scrutiny is necessary there was widespread feeling the Miami
Miami Herald was put on the defensive at week Fiedler and his colleagues have done was wrong
You know that's not a bomb
What business is it
You staked out a guy in his home
What is a up
Sneaking around in the bushes
And one reason is this
Nobody knows where this is going to lead
Set a precedent
Should reporters be staking out George Bush's house
Bruce Babbitt House Joe Biden
There's generally the sense of
But you know
What was he thinking
Part is to blame
Gary Hart
And didn't he understand that things to do
Changing doesn't the public maybe have a right to
Cancel the newspaper that began the controversy is not backing down
This was not character assassination
This was character suicide
He did it we didn't even ask that debate heats up over the ethics of its coverage of Gary Hart
So there was there was a real conflict
The all the various Echelon of media respond to this differently the New York Times refuses to
To touch it originally The Washington Post is deeply conflicted
And as for the
Publix
An unscientific Herald telephone pole
63% of the caller said they thought the paper was making too much of a fuss over Gary Hart in the polling shows
Was that people think the media overstepped
You still pulling very strongly he's winning in the public mind according to Leslie Stahl most people seem to be with
Willing to compartmentalize
Most people
Can split off
How's it going to be as president
And you know is he cheating on his wife will not clear that the tide was going to take heart out
At all
So how did his team try to get ahead of the story they scheduled a press conference in New Hampshire
I don't know flight over Kevin Sweeney is press secretary
Epson I remember
Asking hard question something like have you ever been unfaithful to your wife
And he shot back at me with angry so I don't have to answer that
Question that's a question that that I can answer to God to my wife but it's not a question that I need to answer in Polish
That's a dangerous question to be asked
We don't want to go there
And I just said that's a great answer just hold that anger that's that's an appropriate response
Then we get to the press conference
Heart and sweetie walk into this colonial-style room Dartmouth College
Lights everywhere the room is filled wedding it's hot as more media than anyone's ever seen packed in it's a really
Intense environment has very little buffer
And he's handling the questions
Again really pretty brilliantly time goes on
Adjustment your character on issues that affect their lives and their families their Nation that's what this campaign is
Firing on all cylinders and heart goes through you know 30 minutes 40 minutes of questions and then
In your remarks yesterday raised the issue of morality and you raise the issue of fruitfulness
At some point he calls on young reporter named Paul Taylor and Taylor
Walks him through a series of question
Said you did nothing in Morrow did you mean that you had no sexual relationship with Donna Rice last weekend or any other
Do you believe that adultery is involved
Senator have you ever committed adultery
Earnhardt looked out at the Sea of reporters
Nope no politician has ever publicly been asked that
Broad Direct
The question about his personal Behavior it really just
It shocked the room
We don't know what your heart was thinking of that more money
Did not want to be interviewed on today
But it's clear that she said yes or no to that broad of a question that his entire married life
Have you ever
Adult to read that word ever his entire married life would suddenly be in
As far as we know no other person in his situation in history
That ever been asked
To drag that much of themselves
In the Limelight
Turn on Space you can see that he knows if this is never going to end I mean he he knew how many women eat seen over the years he could Envision them
Small being paraded
Through the papers
He could tell already that there was all this news
Cowboy press and that
Political process
Following along that he was never going to be able to talk about his agenda
And
Heart stumbled around for a minute
And ultimately
He says
I do not have
I hope I don't have to dance
When I heard that response
I felt
The tone
Was such that it is
It felt like
It felt like he is exhausted
And he can't take
And I
I was offended
I
I really in that moment. This is just
Wrong
This has nothing to do with with what
What is necessary to run this country
And I just thought this is not
This this this is not
Wiki We're not gonna survive
And that moment
Effectively does Hemet
What time is it
Gary Hart his finished as a presidential candidate Harry Hearts Cuomo campaign is only 3 weeks old was simply no putting
Putting the genie back in the bottle of appearances yesterday worm obscene campaign has been hammered to its knees asking
The same questions again and again today after what may be remembered as the most disastrous week any presidential can
Candidates in Diridon years
The heart told anaid
Let's go home
Couple weeks later that
Famous image of Gary Hart and Donna Rice
Comes out the National Enquirer
And
That's it for people my age like that that image
Donna Rice
Sitting in his lap
Get the shirt on the face
Monkey Business
That's that's the thing you remember
According to Matt by you can look at this whole story because Tom Fiedler taking that call
Paul Taylor asking that question
As this moment when all these forces
Way outside of Gary Hart's
People come together
Not Justa sink his campaign but the change political journals
Profoundly
But
As with all cultural shifts
There's more than one way to look at this so just for a gut check
We put the whole story time Fiedler
Can we have you introduce yourself
I'm Cokie Roberts
But now we can who you are like
Part 2
56 Grant mpre
But I'm a political commentator and author
Cokie Roberts bellezza yeah reporters were injured
Hidden character more app
But it wasn't just that it's important to keep in mind here is that there were many more women
Covering Canada
It's at that point then there had been but
The four
There were women on the bus
And in the case of
Gary Hart
Several of those women had had
Personal encounters
There were times when you be in a room where he had to hit on every woman in the room
So
This was not somebody that
Women who recovering campaigns
Ignorant of
And the other thing to keep in mind
Robert is that
IHome
Women's movement
Did talk
Quite a bit about the
The personal is
Is political
And because the way women were treated with something that
We thought and I continue to think
Is a
A good gauge of character
And there was something of a sense that
Have you treated women like Kleenex
So
We work
Expanding the universe of what was a major Cara
So then are you kind of are you kind of routing Fiedler on absolutely
Finally somebody
Nevada and fight and thank God it's
As much as you were cheering them on was there any concern that that was changing the rules
Journalism
Why
Because
The rules of Journalism were constantly changing
As they should
According to Cokie Roberts this was less about journalism
Then
About journalism catching up
With the ethics of the time
Look we elect our presidents
Are based on who they are not on what
Policies they stand
It's different from any other office
The voters need to know as much as they can humanly no
About that
So is there a line for you is there a place you won't go in taking the full measure of a
I am not
If a president that I can
There's nothing you wouldn't touch
No
We not have to know that it was true
Sure but
No
Leslie Stahl had a slightly
She's fabulous cookie robber
I didn't go there that's interesting
I just didn't want
I just didn't want to ask about it I didn't want to go there
I'm telling you this
Even though
I covered Watergate
And would have asked
Any number of question
It's about character
You know it's open season fell as the public needs to know this but you know
Sex is really a hard place for me to
Cry
So
I agree
Re with it
But I also have my own
Opinion
That
There's propriety
And
I'm old-fashioned I guess am I I don't know
I'd intended
Quite frankly to come down here this morning
Read a short carefully-worded political statement this is Gary Hart statement
A few days after that person
Saying that
I was withdrawing from the race and then
Quietly disappear
And then
Frankly tossing and turning all night by myself
Hell no
I'm not going to do that because it's not my
My style and because
I'm a proud man and I'm proud of what I've accomplished
In public life
Some things may be interested
That doesn't necessarily mean they're important
We're all going to have to seriously question the system
Selecting our national leader
That reduces the Press of this nation to Hunters
The presidential candidates to being hunted
Politics in this country take it from me
Is on the verge of becoming another form of athletic competition or sporting match
We all better do something
To make this system
Work
We're all going to be soon rephrasing Jefferson to say I tremble for my country
But I think we may in fact
Get the kind of leaders
We deserve
No we did reach out to mr. heart for comment
Explain to him the story we were doing
He wrote back this
Response
Thank you for your letter and the invitation to participate
Story
No I did not
Become president
My life continues to
Asteroid nearly
Rap someday someone will tell that
But for now
I have no interest
In revisiting what many consider
A turning point for the nation
Fun in just
I do believe that the
Full and accurate story of that event
Remains
VTOL
Chine
Gary Hart
Very special thanks to Jamie York New York
Joe trippi you can find a link to Matt buys book all the truth is out the week politics went tab
Floyd on our website radiolab.org
This piece was produced by Simon Adler
And
Next podcast will be exploring these issues in a
Totally different car
I'm Jared I'm right
Are we approved
This message
Hi this is Leslie Stahl
I am reading the credits of the Radiolab show on Gary Hart
Radiolab is produced by Jad abumrad
Going to do it again because I don't think I did a bum a bum
Abram rad
Staff includes Brenna Farrell
David Gable Dylan Keith Matt kielty
Robert krulwich Andy Mills Latif Nasser
Alien wax
Bobby Webster store on Wheeler and Jamie York Alexandra Lee Young
Tracy Honda
Stephanie Tam and Michael Loranger
Fact Checkers and Michelle Harris
Your session cannot be continued at this time