Listening to Radiolab
Radiolab WNYC
Hello
Play wanted to bring back a story that's what I mean one of my personal favorite stories that we've done
This particular story we are in 2015
So a lot of you may not have heard it
And it goes like this. I'm Robert krulwich Radiolab
Nick farago
Get a story from
Reporters
I'm a freelance filmmaker freelance reporter writer
Radio producer
Too many slashes
Story that goes back about 70 years
It's it all feels like
Unreal in some way
There's something about the story that just
You hear it you can't help think about now
Should we start with with
Air currents or I go with I want to start with
Can we go to Thermopolis Wyoming
Cuz that was
It was one of the first
Really well documented
Lenox
Thermopolis
My homie well as it's the first week of December 1944
This is Ross going historian he would have looked it's pretty much the definitive account of the story about to here
Hangout Thermopolis Wyoming December 1944 and there are three whiners
At a place called The High Line Coal Mine which is outside of the mouth
They step outside the mind one evening it's just about dusk
And just as they step out of the mind they hear this whistling sound over their heads and then a moment later there's
A tremendous explosion
And they see this
Rising cloud of dust about a mile away across the valley they turn into
Look it's Dusk and so in the fading Twilight they can't be sure exactly what they're looking at
But above them they're sort of this
Fluttering white circle just floating there
They made sense of it by thinking it was a parachutist
They watch this
Parachute as it's drifting away from them they get in their car and they chase after it
Until eventually they lose sight of it in the Darkness
Right around that same time
About 500 miles away in Colorado and his dad are working in the barn
When they hear an explosion they run outside and in their yard
There's just this
Smoldering crater
In Wyoming a nine-year-old boy playing in his front yard here's an explosion all throughout the winter of 1944
In Burwell Nebraska strange
Parachute things native residents hear a loud explosion just start appearing in the skies All Over America
Napa California lame deer Montana 20 or so miles from downtown Detroit
Over Farms Nogales Arizona slipping behind Hills Rigby Idaho everybody who sees
These things all of them have different explanations
Or what they think they're witnessing
They think it's a plane crash on oil tank exploding the US military sends out an APB to local police station
Sing We need information
What are these
Testing testing
Enter Sheriff Warren hide my name is Mary and Hyde Warren Hyde actually died in 9
1989 so the oldest son of sheriff I we talked to his son he had a presence about him that
He kind of commanded a room
Jeff Hyde was a big guy black wavy hair brought of the shoulder narrow at the hips got send got on his head
One day he's at his office North of Salt Lake City
When
His phone ring
From what I understand dry farmer called him said there's a strange contraption
My field some kind of
Balloon parachute looking thing floating around so he jumped in the car and
Went hell-bent-for-leather out into the Blue Creek area there's this crazy story where he rushes out to this Farm 10
Investigate
Pops out of his car rips off his belt
What does 38 pistol to the man can run with a 38 pistol on his waist
And took off after the bloom
Here's what he sees in that field
He was
I mean if you look at a picture of this thing it's this huge globe
30 ft in diameter
Paperwhite
And I'm coming down
From this globe are these thick
40 ft ropes
At the bottom
Attached to it is a
Is a heavy metal Chandelier
With bombs
Hanging off the bottom
And Sheriff hide
She sees this thing runs onto the field
Grabs onto the Rope
To maybe tight down
But just as he grabs it
Augusta wind comes by lift him up off the ground like he was paper
And so he's dangling from the ropes of this thing the balloon is above him the explosives her are below him
And it takes him across this Canyon
And he's holding on just dangling from it still trying to Wrangle it like like some bucking bronco VLAN
And again he tries to tie it to a
Juniper Bush or something but the wind catches it again and goes back over the canyon back to the first side back to the
The first signed I started float around the field he kept wrestling this balloon for a long time he's nauseous
From being spun around on this balloon his vision getting blurry his hands are becoming raw from the Rope but he
He feels dislike sense of Duty the government wanted one of these balloons his territory so he's got to take it
Down that's right he finally
Lets himself free fall so he can grab it again so his weight will jerk the balloon to the ground
Then finally the bloom came down in and kind of a little Ravine where Sagebrush were girl
Going in a rooted been exposed on the side of the Ravine from a Sagebrush and he hooked his arm around the
This route then he was able to hold a balloon without being carried into the air
So you actually captured him a personal letter of thanks the end up shipping all of the f
Evidence off to the Aberdeen
Military
Research facility where they have gathered
All this different evidence from all over the country
And
After looking at this stuff
For a while
They were able to tell that
Apparently this bomb
Was not of any particular American make
And match known characteristics of Japanese bombs
Cyst Japanese
But it's impossible
To send a balloon across the Pacific Ocean at the
Disappointments never
Never been done I mean that it's
Basically an intercontinental ballistic missile
So they're trying to figure out where it's coming from
They thought maybe they were being launched from submarines
Maybe they were coming from beaches in North America from saboteurs there was even speculation at one point and maybe
They were coming from Japanese internment camps
In North America
Then two days before Christmas 1944 in Alaska
A Native Alaskan trapper
Trax wind down
And it has
Sandbag
Still attached
To the bottom of string
And that
Turns out to be the key to the mystery
Sand yeah well that just saying there's a lot in there
My name is Eliza bergslien and I am a forensic geologist we call the police to help us understand this next part what
Was the sand for the balloons was sent to Washington DC
Just some scientist
At the US Geological Survey right away they discover that there's no Coral so you don't have finding no
No Coral cold water now they look at the diatoms Marine 5 oz
Stop at fossil mollusk by compiling all of these different characteristics put that all together
The other where would you find these diatoms these minerals that you wouldn't find Coral though all those different pieces of information
Altogether the geologists are able to determine that there are
2 or perhaps
Three beaches
In the world that fit all of these qualifications
Where they believe the sand could have come from
And all of which are on the east coast of Honshu the largest of
Japan's four main islands
You can get that
Kind of specific from Sandy yep
That kind of
Pacific Tree incredible I so they came all the way from these particular beaches on the coast
6 thousands of miles across the Pacific Ocean
Why would the Japanese choose to
To deliver
Buy balloon
It's a strange choice
After Pearl Harbor in as like they whenever you know they could be playing
Well
Iowa temperature history in the making it grew directly out of the Doolittle Raid
Back in April of 1942
When is Raiders took off from an aircraft carrier
Deep in the Western Pacific and drop bombs on
Tokyo and Yokohama and Kobe and a number of other cities across Japan
In the history of aerial Warfare they didn't do a lot of damage
Physically but it was such a shock to the Japanese
To think that their Homeland could be invaded that these planes could actually fly over the Imperial Palace.
The home of the emperor and if you little bit holder the palace I just realized that he went all the way down town in Tokyo
Oh yeah right over the city
And so immediately after the Doolittle Raid and Order went out
It was just find a way to bomb America
Japan's Navy
TV is stretched so thin at this point in the war
There's no way they can pull off something like the Doolittle Raid they didn't have aircraft carriers that could get their plane
Close enough to the US Mainland but what they did have
What's the wind
Today we call this the Jetstream that name didn't come along until after the war at that point we barely knew about the jet stream
But
Prior to and during the war the Japanese did an extensive research into these winds Okay so
In 1924 there's this meteorologist name blah Saburo issue
And he goes to the top of a mountain
And he releases a bunch of these
Little paper weather balloon
And he discovers that
At about 30000 feet up there's this River of fast-moving air speeds up 275
5 miles an hour
Drink anything and it's Miss pollen insects
All the way to North America within days
And after the Doolittle Raid they thought maybe if we were to release a bunch of balloons
And just the right place at just the right time
Maybe this jet stream of Erica
Push these balloons across the Pacific Ocean
Toyota.com
So this is Tesco Tanaka choose interviewed in this independent documentary called on Paper Wings
America
In 1944 she said she was a teenager
When the Japanese military came to the school and basically
Turn it into a factory
She and hundreds of other school children
Were conscripted to begin making this
Special kind of paper out of mulberry wood
Called
Handmade Japanese traditional paper
This is my house Sheena
Who now works at the noborito institute in Japan
Lottery choir
12 hour days
Making thousands tens of thousands
Of these sheets
Gluing them together
Why didn't they have adults in the car
They were all Fighting the War 1
Young Thug's home good
Full
Stop
Big big girls had a certain dexterity for the neighbor make the Nimble fingers
I think I read that long
Okay my
And after they finished
Producing the balloons
And after the blooms were strapped with bombs
They were shipped off
To those beaches
And
Just
Letgo
People from the Japanese side watching them take off
Said they look like
Huge jellyfish swimming through a pale blue sky
These perfectly silent Vehicles the only sound was
The rustling of the paper is they took off
How many were launched
From November 1944 to April 1945 they launched 9000 balloons
Now
The engineers in Japan who designed this
Faced a very serious problem once we got the balloons up into the jet stream and they were cruising along their floating it to be
He's from fifty to a hundred miles an hour
But every night temperatures are going to fall to -40 centigrade
And the fixed volume of hydrogen inside that envelope is going to contract the balloon is going to
Lose altitude
Drop out of the jet stream and down into the ocean all together
So to solve this says Ross they what they did was this
They took 32 sandbags
Harlem on the balloon and then connected those sandbags to an altimeter set to a preset minimum such as 35
Thousand feet in the nighttime
Wind balloon
Loses altitude
The altimeter
Will engage
Trigger fuse
Which cuts off one of those sandbags
And dropped it into the ocean and now
The vehicle will resend back into the jet stream cuz it's lighter cuz it's lighter so these
Balloons the riding the jet stream a 10 every night they start to descend but then off we go a sandbag
And then go back up and whenever they cooled off enough to drop same thing drop then rise
Drop then rise
Over and over
32 times until every sandbag was gone
Once all the sandbags have been dropped
Now you have
Only the bombs remaining and the bombs are held in place
With the exact same mechanism is the sandbags
And now by the very same system the bombs are the last to go
And presumably the balloon is now somewhere over North America
So it's a sandbag countdown
21 I hope I'm in Oregon right
In what it was in Oregon or whatever the idea was that it would
Drop its last bomb
Float away
In basically self-destruct
They I guess figured it would be it would be more terrifying
They have bombs raining down silently from above with no calling card at all
Then with the Japanese calling card
Sounds of the last time baggage drop
Not only the central payload is left
This is audio from a declassify Navy instructional video made about these
Balloon bombs in 1945
Jesus soldiers
How to what to do if they find one of these bombs and how to Defuse The Bomb
But I think the most interesting thing about the video is this text that's written in
Huge
Block letters
Right at the bottom of the screen
It says
Do not eat the Enemy by publishing
Or broadcasting or discussing
Information
Can be a powerful tool can be a powerful tool for good and a powerful tool for evil
This is Professor Mike Sweeney and I'm a historian of wartime censorship
And he says that immediately after those first balloons landed there are few stories that appear in the local newspaper
Farwest
Stories about
A Japanese attack
On the mainland of the United States
Time in Newsweek even picked it up saying we're not sure what these are but you know are these the Japanese spies coming here
And on these balloons this a large-scale attack what is going on
And then
Very shortly thereafter
Just three days after this time and Newsweek article
The office of censorship initiated a press blackout
This blackout on news
They sent out memos in telegraph's to all the major wire services
So you pdap in the ins
Saying keep any news of these Japanese balloons
Off the wires and out-of-print any stories about these bombs will have to be approved by the appropriate authority of the
The US Army if you wish to publish or Broadcast News about
And why would they want to keep the secret
So the government's
Ideas about why balloon Bob should be censored in particularly armies ideas were number one to avoid panic
These things are instruments of Terror right
You can't be afraid of something you don't know
Exist
Number two
Is avoid helping Japan
It was thought then that if we printed exactly
Coordinates
Particular bomb Landing
That this would help
Japan
Better Target
The Bob and the reporters think about
The gravel sometimes what they complied
Everyone
In the news industry was as patriotic as the rest of the country that is the vast majority of journalists supported the war
Of course if you screwed up
Can you send out a story that got American life skill you could be prosecuted under the Espionage Act for them or can you imagine what your listeners
We would do if you were the radio station if itis
Killing 100 American sailors
To the newspapers and radio stations kept their mouths shut
Which meant that
Most Americans
Never even heard this was happening
And more importantly the Japanese
Weren't really hearing about whether they're bombs made it or not
So
They probably concluded that it was basically a failed experiment which largely it was
Of the 9000 released virtually none
Cause any damage
And certainly not any Terror except
For this one balloon
That's coming up
Hi this is whale calling from Northumberland England
Radiolab is supported in part
By the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Enhancing public understanding of Science and Technology in the modern world
More information about Sloan
Www.slha.org
I hate everybody Pat Walters here producer at Radiolab
And I'm here because I need your help this summer I'm hosting
And I request
For those of you who spend a lot of time with kids parents aunts and uncles teachers
About what we're calling tiny moments
Brilliance basically I want to hear about those times when a kid you know did something
It just means you lean back and say wow how did they do that maybe it was the moment that I kid
Did you been reading to 4 month started reading back
Do you
Or maybe the kid was a piano lesson
And you suddenly noticed they were doing advanced math on the musical score or maybe the kids in math class
I noticed they're ready music in the margin of their geometry homework
We're interested in the small specific moments where a kid does something super smart
Anything to do with the test
If you have a story
T-shirt with us
Go to radiolab.org
Brilliance
Record a short audio message for us
And that's where you live. Org / brilliance
Thank you so much
I am jad abumrad I'm Robert krulwich
This is Radiolab with our story from reporters Peter Lang Stanton the Nick farrago about
The 9000 Orso balloon bombs
Japan sent to America in 1944-45
Did rain down on American soil and created
Nothing really nothing happened
No damage
No Terror
Nothing
But then we get to this tiny little town called Bly
Tumi
There's no place like old why
Plies the sleepy little logging town at the base of Gearhart mountain in South Central Oregon lot of pretty scenery
Ancora Connor who just heard was born and raised there do you know everybody in your
They're just like a big family out there
In the forties when Cora was a young girl there about 700 people living there but we did all kinds of fun things we had
Ana fish fry up at dog lake
Huge
Catfish fry
Up there the whole town staying all night
But back home the next day and the winner of the canals with
Freeze over that have bonfire and ice skating party is in
It was a fun place to live
Can you tell me about
Good morning
Sunday see what happened to have time to think
Saturday I think May 5th that's all I can remember
Yep that does May 5th May 5th 1945 was a beautiful day the Sun was shining bright
Right and the Reverend Archie Mitchell
And his wife Chelsea
Who was five months pregnant with her first child Sunday School
The church took occasionally up there they took their
Sunday school class out for picnic there were five children that went along on that
Ages 11 to 14 and one of the kids we called him Dicky
He had a crush on my sister who is Billy younger than me
And they want her to come on this picnic so they came by and stop the pastor
That's why I stopped the kids all piled up
Ca Stockton weather
Yeah trying to talk to convince my mom to let my sister go or both of us or whatever
But Mom didn't want us to go cuz Saturday was our chore day
And my day to work the switchboard which should usually make me pretty angry but it was my job
And that
She said no. No weight while my sister didn't really want to go because she really wasn't
Encouraging this relationship too much
Educate ya
No
So Archie and LZ and the five kids get back into the car they drove up to Gearhart Mountain a couple miles up a Logging Road
Passing Forest Service guys working on the road they go a little further to where the road comes near Creek
Can Archie pull the car around
Impart
The kid jumped out of the car and started running down towards the creek
LC
Who was
Pregnant as I mentioned that she was feeling a bit carsick
She jumped out
To get some fresh air into chase after the kids
While Archie went around to the trunk of the car to get out the fishing poles in the picnic baskets Etc
One of the children
Saw something on the ground
A large
Canvas
White grey balloon of some kind spread out on the ground
Call of Duty other children to come have a look
The children
NLC apparently gathered in a tight Circle
Around the balloon
Archi later reported that while he was getting the picnic basket out of
The trunk
His wife called yuan
Honey
Come look at what we found
He turned and just took a few steps toward them
And at that moment
We'll never know exactly what happened
But apparently one of the children reach down to pick up
The device
The bomb detonated
All five children and Elsie Mitchell
Were killed in
The forest service guys down the road we're close enough to hear the blast they come running when they hear the explosion
And they see
Archie Mitchell has run to the site
And his wife's
Clothes were Ablaze
And Archie was kneeling over his prostrate wife beating up the fire with his bare hands
On our last day in Bly we went to visit the site where the bomb went off
The middle of nowhere
It's just a chain
Fenced off area
A little pain
And are these tall
Pine trees
This is huge cuts in the tree
Is a shrapnel cutting the tree yeah yeah
Assassin
It's not healed
Erie place
Course I didn't know what was going on
This is Cora Connor again
At the time she was at her job watching the switchboard
When
The guy that was working up there for the 4 service come rushing into the telephone office and I mean he was
Scared
Pure White and scared and I thought my God what's going on what's Happening and he came in and made the call
Elected the naval base in Lakeview in about a half an hour later
Casino
Big imposing military guy comes in he was all
Metals and always full uniform you know
And that he must have made it it seemed like in the blink of an eye
And I thought my God what has happened and then when the he talked over the phone I knew what was going on he said they had had a ball
Explode up there
Let's fight both the casualties
And then he talked to me he said you not talk to anybody about anything that you've heard
Not your mother not anybody he says now you're not tagged League of this office
But then I was just
Jelly I was so terrified
Tea leaves and
The word is is trickling around spreading around town gone wrong
And they gathered at the phone office because the phone office those everything in the whole valley and they knew I knew what
What was going on and that's when it all hit pretty soon
There is a crowd outside screaming and yelling at me and yeah we know you know what the
Going on you better come out and tell us we're coming in there and you're going to tell us what's happened and
Are your neighbors and people that yeah they know
Replace I probably knew every one of them I was about that you could imagine
The state I was in and mr. Paskey Dicky's father
Dickie was the boy who had a crush on Cora's sister tell you exactly how he has dress that day he had on a
Red and black checkered
Aunt shirt
And his red hunting
Cat at the time all I knew is that his son was missing
You stood out there and he shook his fist and he yelled and he scared me half to death
Threatening to come in and
All right he says you know what's happening let us know what's happening
And I couldn't do anything
Except I set there
All day
You know I really really
Tore me apart
That was just in a complete fog for days
Not ever
Never talked too much about it
Within a day or so the military told most of the town
What actually happened that day
And then a short time after that
A big armies truck while I was too big army trucks and stop right out in front of our house
We wondered what was going on you know you're
Little town like that anything different everybody goes to the window and takes a look
And
CARICOM
Okay this is awfully hard
A woman and a little kid jumped out of the back of that truck
She was Japanese they were on their way to the tulelake
The Japanese
Internment camp nearby
And she screaming and crying and praying
Please we need water
We need water for it was thought it was really hot that day and they were in a canvas covered truck
Jammed in there
And
I grabbed the picture of a bucket or whatever was there in the kitchen
Filled it with water and started out the door by that time they were
Throwing rocks at that lady and her kid
People in that time we're so terribly
Upset
And they were throwing rocks at her
And mom would let me go and I screamed and cried at my mother cuz she wouldn't let me go says you can't go out there they'll throw rocks
I Won't Let You Go
And did they stay that's pictures in my mind
And I pray to the Lord
To forgive the people that were doing that
Try to
I can't accept it there's nothing can make me accept what happened
I thought that was the most horrible thing in the world people could do a woman and child that had nothing to do with the bomb
Nothing to do with the ward nothing
Still hard
How can people be that way
It upset me so horribly bad
What did want to talk about it
I can talk for 40 years
It's weird like
Is a kind of weird
Scary symmetry this whole thing like
The Japanese
Military
Find crate
Terror
What they felt after
So they want to make the situation where I like
Bombs were falling silently from the sky we couldn't even tell where they're coming from
Almost
The gods were dropping
But we kept it quiet
Nobody panicked except
By not saying anything
At least in this one small incense
I created exactly the situation that the Japanese military wanted
Me not on the scale that they wanted but like and its effect
It's like a concentrated version of the thing they're trying to create but that's the
Problem
That's not a problem
5 is
5 is a sacrifice
What is it
Five six people
Yeah they're what they were there 125 million people
I think I've been all the more than you can see
What it would have been like
Listen to the store
You could see what it would be like if
If the story had been well-known
I've Been Told
Person to person
Everybody was looking up and wondering
With the next
Strange things coming from
They wouldn't play with there might have been panic
But those kids wouldn't talk on the boulevard stats
The choices they would have known
Hey I'm sorry
Jumping here I just know that we don't have Ross much longer
In order to respect your time
Separates Randy Mills who worked with Nick and Peter on this
On story
Before they kick you out
The only last question I
Out of my listings
Like why is it that we don't know about
I've never heard of this
Before
I don't know Robert Hugh farthest
Sephora nearby quite why the hell is this not a thing we know
I think it's directly an outgrowth of that censorship policy
At the end of the war the war department destroyed all of the evidence they didn't want these any evidence of these bull
Balloons
Just out there in general circulation
This is one of those
Footnotes to the war
That you know at the end of the war
Just never
People people forgot about something that they didn't know about anyway
Ross are there any more out there
That is a very interesting question
It's estimated by the war department
That of the 9000 release
They thought that maybe 7 to 10%
Of the total
Would have survived
The transoceanic Crossing in arrived in North America
That's 900
300r confirmed
As having arrived in North America
So that means there are
Dozens
Perhaps
Hundreds
That arrived in North America but we're never accounted for
In the 10 or 12 years immediately after the end of World War II
A couple dozen of these things were found
Found several in Oregon in 1948
When in Alaska 1950
T v
When an Idaho in the early 1960s
And then the recoveries
Stopped movie where they live like the one in Oregon if you touch them
Now here's the fascinating path
Last October October of 2014 I kid you not it was ahead of me
And he stopped and said
A couple of loggers
British Columbia who are doing some survey work
The remnants of a Japanese balloon that had been on the ground for 70 years
We definitely work in remote areas and
In general
Down through there are those special days where you where you see things that no one else gets
This happened just
A few months ago
I tell you if you're hiking if you're out in the woods in the Pacific Northwest
Watch where you step
By the way Google fugo
But that's the code name
In Japan for these weapons they were called Fujiko F fujio cells of the name of Roscoe his book
The Curious history of Japan's balloon bomb attack on America
Thank you to Peter Lang Stanton and to Nicaragua for their reporting
Extensive
Reporting
Also thanks to Elon a soul whose documentary on Paper Wings
Big sweater dress
You are the Japanese voices in the middle of the story that came from her documentary
Also are we original music this hour from
Couple folks Jeff Taylor Michael Manning David Wingo
Justin Walter
Weihai Productions board from animals and Damiano marchetti
And if you want to see
These balloon bombs we have some incredible pictures on our website radiolab.org
One more thing
Since this episode first aired we we got some sad news
Cora Connor
The woman you are telling the story of
B&B 16 operating
Switchboard at the Blythe telephone office
Wuxi passed away in December 2016 at the age of 87
She was a member of the Klamath County Historical Society in Oregon
And she continue telling the story of the Bly balloon bomb
Throughout
I'm Jedi runtime Robert krulwich
Thanks for listening
To play the message press to start of message
Hi
This is Alyssa. Feinberg
Cars from Factory home of the Ruth Bader Ginsburg action figure in Gowanus Brooklyn
Radiolab
Was created by dada
Is produced by three wheeler
Filling pieces art director of sound design
Suzie lechtenberg is our executive producer
Stop include
Simon Adler
Becca Bressler
Rachel Cusick
David Gaba
Bethel habte
Tracy hunt
Nora Keller
Matt kielty
Robert Froehlich
Annie McEwen
Lottie's master
Melissa O'Donnell
Sarkari
Aryan black
Pat Walters
And Molly Webster
Without
Oh yeah
Audrey Quinn
Danielle Dennis
A fact-checker is Michelle Harris
And this message