We want to finish the night with a salute to a guy who's been on our program and part of our family pretty much from the beginning
I have known him
Morgan 35 years
Early I'm going to Radiolab started I asked him if he'd help us out and send us a few story ideas he didn't send us a few
He sent us bushel
Tales of chemistry in medicine
Hallucinations music people so many
Extraordinary people that he knew founder help
Cuz I just doesn't run out
Dr. Oliver Sacks
Neurologist author
Is a guy who notices
Everything is deeply interested in everything that happens around him and to him and tonight we're bringing it back on tape
But what the last may be his final offering Frost as many of you know
Dr. Sachs recently was diagnosed with liver cancer
Have you wrote about this in the New York Times he said he plans to spend the time that he has
Left writing
Be with friends not doing interviews but he did agree to share his thoughts
Exclusively with that with us tonight
For you to gather here
Cuz he's one of our family
So as I've done for decades now I went over his house in Manhattan with my mic
Am I sent to him
I just need to know what just
A month-and-a-half ago you were fine
And then
What
I see beginning of the ride was fine
On the 3rd of January I feel Canelo
Quia
And I tossed some dark urine
I thought I said little girl bladder attack
Didn't pay that much attention
But thought I better get things
And then
The X-ray with
Expected only to show a couple of ghosts
Chode
I'm drugs
Off 6th
And my liver
Iolo my doctor said
He didn't know what his will and I would need further tests
I
I knew what they were
I said it's hot
He's right the doctors eventually confirmed
A cancer that has been found in his eye 9 years ago had spread to his liver
Were you
Peyton
Or
Relieve or consor
I think my first feeling was one of
Overwhelming sadness
They're also things
I will see
And I will do
One or two people have listened to me in the
Controlling me
But f*** it it's not like we all die
It's like you have four months
Has that has your property is your prognosis at this moment cuz I know you had an well if it gets revived
It depends of course on how is the cancer response to treatment sand
Or how quickly it spreads
Sofa
The metastasis from my eye
Only in my liver
I told they love liver
The Isle of liver as well
And then one of the magical things I did was going to have to live for Nom Noms
Sudoku
I'm thinking that liver looks better than mine Parkway
This is what he's like instead of being frightened by the thing is trying to kill him he's thinking about loving liver and liver lover
Looking for Connections in one really doesn't stop he
He just notices it case in point
A few months ago
His doctor said to him We're going to run up a line
Up your liver and ineffective going to straight shave off or start some of the cancer cells first on one side
Going to be out there to see if I can give you a little more time
But they warned him honesty metastasis
Die
The hutong farias and Pleasanton
Send me exhaust you text your system bad
And at one point shortly after the procedures
I started talking and it off
Strangely
And as I was talking I was inviting
You'll be the first person to see this
So he showed me a notebook we're showing it to you
In just a moment you can see their sort of
Writing there on the left it's all he's writing a book actually children's book about the elementary table
But as he was writing if you if you look to the next
Page
I see that it gets a little bit
Wobbly the letters and then
And then there was some
Crossing out there
Yes I see all the dramatics
Do icing
Changes
It actually is
There's a large
Slash across it and then you get seems a little incoherent at the palace
Okay
Edible
Advantage delivery
Krypton made
All this happened to the course of 10 minutes
He's doing here he's figured okay I'm writing at a constant speed
I know pretty much how fast I write and so I can time this out I can figure out exactly how long it took me to sleep
Into delirium out of this delirium
Animal Medical Way
I think this was a lovely illustration
Who puts in a timeline of delirium
Coming like that
When are you more likely
Unusual for any doctor and a man of science you don't seem too worried at all
Become incoherent or strange
You're not showing it to me as it's like how interesting I was crazy here for a little bit
The truth is Oliver is fascinated by what goes on in the human mind no matter how strange he gets up there
I went time when he was a young resident in California driving his bike and by the way I I should
Show you what you look like back then when he was
Driving his bike is I think it's him
In New York
I kind of you know
Hello
In the sixties he was also a champion weightlifter they called him doctor Squad
And in this picture that you saw you here that's him raising 600-lb
In order to win a trophy like this is that that you was a champ and
And you can see more pictures like these cuz we have signed copies of all of his new Memoir out for sale in the lobby
Pretty good book too by the way this time
And 1960s
In addition to being muscled out however
Was a serious recreational drug take
And because he's Oliver
He was extremely curious about his high as no matter how weird they were
1 time for example he took
20 pills that he shouldn't have
And then to my surprise
How does a spider on the wall
Set hello
Have a voice like that she's also
Famous mathematician
And the tongue
It cost me a lot of the technical question as to whether Russell had a
Exploded
Frigga spavital
And we had this
Conversation
Cuz you you trust your perceptions
Mineo's later when I mentioned this to an entomologist friend Cornell
Philosophical spider
Taking it all in talking spiders
Whatever the generosity of his curiosity
Becomes profoundly moving and transformative
What he's treating his patients I want to tell
1 * here really quickly do to demonstrate what I mean
I never once had a patient when he called mrs. OC
She was
An old woman she was 88 years old living in a nursing home
And one night she was awakened Jarred awake by a loud sound
I wish
Hillsong
And she thought about somebody left the radio on but when she looked
3D when the room is Oscar roommate
Soundasleep which was odd because the song was really loud
The doors after that
It was another song
Another song
Leaving my roommate can't hear the songs because the songs are
Are coming to the fillings in my teeth I've heard that's possible
But no her doctor told her
This is something in your head you need to see
A neurology
Which led her to doctor sax
That when he met mrs. OC he she could barely hear him the song sung by the female voice for coming and coming she
He was frightened and justifiably worried that you was going crazy but Oliver said no no I'm going to do some tests and when he was done
He said he found a slight stroke or condition that triggered musical epilepsy 87 production of music and
Your brain
Normal. You might say Okay me about the diagnosis and he thought that the songs would probably faint it'll pass or they would be
But Oliver did not stop
He doesn't stop
He kept talking to her
She told him she was born in Ireland in the 1890s her father died before she was born her mother when she
He was only 5 she was sent to America
Look for the water for beating Mason.
She had no conscious memory of the first five years of my life
New memory of Ireland
You should always help us as a kid and painful side
Lack of forgetting
Efficacy
We asked her about the songs
What are they like
I miss Associated well I think they're lullabies
Can you sing them for me she did
And then after checking them not sure who I'll ever figured out that these songs what happened to be popular
Irish ballads from the 1890s when Mrs OC was a little baby
And I gave him an idea
Isn't science
It isn't in any traditional way medicine
He just told her a story
And it goes like this
You don't have nobody remembers anything that happens to you when you're one or two or three
Well there was a Siri wants not honored much today but it's sad that those earliest memories
Get locked away deep in our brains in a special safe
The weekend never open
So let's suppose mrs. OC
And you are struck by some
Reezy chance
Open the lock that none of us can break
And release those first memories
In you just for a little while
So that the voice you're listening to
Home
Maybe that isn't a radio voice
Let's play
That it's your mother's voice
That's true missing mother
Enjoy the ripe old age of 88 you finally get to be back in your mother's arms
You get to be a baby again
Images of the Seas thought about
Okay
It's sort of fits
I'm an old woman with a stroke
Can an old people's home
But I feel I'm a child in Ireland
I feel my mother's arms I see
Ikea voicing
United
Shortly thereafter the songs began to fade the pauses widen
Miss Associated been so frightened by this music in her head was now
Sorry to see the songs go
But it was Oliver who noticed how those songs that touched
Who noticed that the songs might become a comfort to her because that's what he does
He listens close
He can hear another person's
And this is really the profound puzzles for me
About Oliver
Because reading the new autobiography you see that while he was so full of heart as a doctor in his own life
Linear relationships that really mattered
It turns out he didn't get a whole lot of effect
He was for a long time a lonely guy I'd say he was
Very lonely
And he's talking about that now for the 1st
Let me talk about love for a minute
In this book you tell the story of your
Of your very first love of fellow by the name of Richard
Selleck
Can you just tell me
What happened with
He was a load Scala I talked with him.
A poet
And handsome
Beautiful
Beyond belief
An eyesore
Fell for him
Although I didn't say anything
Because I was from
Very haunted by my mother
Accusations
What is your mother
Well
To go to a couple of years back then my father
How to open the conversation I was about to go to Oxford
Father son
Conversation
Any setup
You don't seem to have many girlfriends
And I said
No
Wishing the conversation
Stop
He said I'm
Something's wrong with girls
Semi I said know that that's fine
Tattoo prefer boys
And I said well
Yes I do
I said I've never done anything
But I do
Then you knew that then I knew that then I'd know.
6 euros
Probably sometime
What's 12
And I said don't tell Mom
She won't be able to take it
But my
Father
Did tell my mother in the night
And the next morning she came down with him
I somehow want to see the face of humba
Enraged me
And among other things said
Joann Abomination I wish you would never been born
And then she has something to shut up
And said nothing for 3 days
And
The match was never mentioned the game and highlight
Anthem
2 years later
I found myself
First time in my life
Falling in Love
This was the gun guy Richard
Oliver the time was in college
It was a very positive feeling why didn't know what it was one which I did Express
But I did
Say so with my heart my mouth
To what you said
And Richard
Clipped me by the shoulders and he said I know
He said but I'm not that way
But I love you in my own way
And I was glad I have said that I'm glad this has been received in such a warm February
I thought you might be friends for the rest of all
Lives
But then one day he came into me said he'd been bothered by finding a lump
In his groin and he was worried
Could I have a look at it
And I looked at it and I felt it
And it was hard on
Tethered
Turned out to be a
Tiki malignant
Form of lymphoid T-Mobile
School tool
Sarcoma
Anthem
He never spoke to me again often
I don't know whether
Since I've been the first to recognize the ominous impulse
He's told me about
Harbinger of death or messenger of death
What happened
But you you were left with the with the child
Yeah yeah yeah
Few years later album medicine man they mellings young he was a sailor
He liked Oliver he was into weightlifting they became close friends
And they began living together and was in love with him and love
Physical contact with him and leave work out and they dressel and ride motorcycles kind of tightly and never talked to
About what might or might not be happening between them but one day
They were together and Oliver was giving Mel a back massage with smell off and asked him to do and
I love doing that
And Oliver says sometimes he get a little
You know
Excited
And so love to say gave no excuses indication it was okay
But but but one day
Things went a bit too far
And I got soda
I went over the bridge just before the Big Bang
Metal immediate resources. Happen
How to shower
Adam said I icon
Don't stay with you anymore
And then I found that
Very
Cool and upsetting I'm hot
And it's made me feel
I don't want to have anything to do with
People
I must have
Falling in Love
Kenosha lights with anyone
Again
And he didn't share his life with anyone for a long long time
In fact
He told me a story about something that happened
Maybe 8 years ago
I had I was just joining The Faculty of Columbia
And I was having a
An interview
And at one point the interview
She said I have something weather
Private Law School
Would you like Miss Edgar
Your system to leave and I said no she's
Pb2
Or my affairs
And I did say
Thinking she was going to ask me about 6
I said I haven't had any sex
What's 35
I've been sacked when she was going to ask me my social security number
Tell the truth is I didn't do anything about it because he didn't think he could I be chosen Richard lost Richard
Chosen mail lost mail what is the point he was thinking
Finally and who knows
Waiting for why these things happen to people
But a man came along who for the first
Chose Oliver
I admit bilious I miss a number of people because I've been
A manuscript or proof
A book
And I'm in intimacy grew between us
I don't think I quite realized how deep it was but then there was a particular episode
In Christmas of 09
Meineke
Kmart
And in his
Serious
Way she has a serious
Is careful what you say
He said I
I have conceived a deep
Love for you
I have conceived
I got a few extra words I have
Okay was he scared to say I love you
You know she likes the English language
Input
More cautiously and yet most strongly
I think that's a beautiful way of putting it
And then I realized
At that moment with his
Saying that
But I had conceived a deep love
And I
Good God has happened the game
And I'm in my 77th year
Next and things
Basically have gone
Happily ever since
Unsurprising meme
Because then again I'm not dealing with or what I'm dealing with a food
I'm dealing with an individual
I'm not dealing with a with a condition defined by medicine
Hello
So Oliver still doesn't know how much time he has left but for the moment as you can hear
His mind is totally impact you still riding he has two books in addition to the one you find in the lobby that he's writing and the
Children's books
Bunch of New Yorker stories in last few months and a New York Review of Books story
He's got energy to spare so I want to do one last thing for we close
And this comes from yet another conversation I had with him it's a story I know Oliver wood Heat
Because he's not a capital I religious
But he is somebody
Who definitely Embraces mystery and for a long time
He's been mystified by a color called
Indigo
Which Newton had inserted
Between blue and violet
I know no two people seem to agree as to what
Indigo was like
And then
So I built a episode of chemical Launchpad meaning took a lot of
Face of amphetamine
Genital arousal
Vincent asset
Analytical cannabis
And when I was fishing today
Stones
I said I want to see
Indigo
No
As if in reply
Does it feel by giant paintbrush to appear. Huge trembling
Pear-shaped blog
Of what I instantly realized
Was pure
Indigo
Are on the White Horse in front of me
It had a wonderful luminosity
And in particular I am a religious person
I thought
This is the color of Heaven
And I live water ecstasy
And then suddenly disappear
He says he had one more moment like that this time no drugs
He was in a museum staring at an Egyptian artifact he sees this read and color back again just for a Beat
I was given 5 tantalizing seconds
Of of radian ineffable
Beauty and then again it Banner
And that was 1965
And I've never seen in to go soon
But who knows you know
Sunday
I like the
Dr. sacks make it to see that color
Again