Kate this is Chad
Just wanted to throw it in extra episode indoor
Murphy dandanah from movie that we're really
It about
But first
Couple weeks ago I
I stepped in here and I laid out a challenge grant that we've gotten from the how Foundation
The deal was if you remember
That is 700 of you guys listening step forward agreed to kick in $7 a month to support them
Making Radiolab then the towel Foundation would give us 70 Grant
Help make the show
So again
700 people
Decide to donate $7 a month we get 70 grand that was the deal all right so how do we do it
How did you do you crushed it just
Rushed it okay we needed 700 people
As of right now I think we're at somewhere over 3,000 you did so well we did so well
The Thao Foundation just came back to us an up the ante full-on stretch goal because here's the thing
3000 people is amazing but that is just percentage of the people who actually listen to the spot
So they're thinking is let's capitalize on this momentum get the other 99.9% involved
So their new stretch goal is it they have agreed to match any donation that comes to Radiolab
Right now up to 10 grand so if you decide to make the seven bucks a month
Deal that becomes $14 a month if you decide to do a one-time donation 60 bucks
That's not 120 tile will match it and this
Reminder this is how we're able to do you know the year-long investigation in the police shooting or the
Nuclear chain of command the name last three that we've done this is how we pay for it
And this challenge Grant will allow us to go farther
So if you're down go to radiolab.org match
Or you can text
The word match
To the number 69866
Getting texts the word match the number 69866
Little formal pop up and you can donate in a matter of seconds and thank you
Alright so tonight
Is
The premiere of a movie we're really excited about
It's called The Immortal Life
Of Henrietta Lacks
Stars
A&M homecoming actress maybe you've heard her Oprah Winfrey
And it is based on the book of a very very dear friend Rebecca
Skloot best-selling book
You will watch this
The movie in a couple days on HBO but in the meantime we're just so proud of Rebecca
Thrilled that this movie is getting out to a wider audience
Everyone should know
So none of that
We're going to play for you a document to reproduce with Rebecca we worked on it for a few years with her while
She was sort of formulating the book
Includes tape you won't hear anywhere else
Will you move me closer
And the story
Is about a tumor that expands
I never stops
Begin to 1950 a black woman in Baltimore
Is in her bathroom
And she discovers pretty much all on her own
Did she has cancer
It's all it's all a bit of a mystery how she initially knew this but she knew it was there
Not she called it she
Had told her cousins for a while that she thought there was something
Wrong with her
With her womb
And she climbed in her bathtub
And she
Put her fingers up inside of herself
And found this lump chapter 1
Interlocal doctor
I happen to be an attending at that time the guys she eventually ended up seeing
Johns Hopkins University
Was this fellow doctor Howard Jones
Wow what you came in to see you can you tell me anything about what you would like
Well she was a
You don't remember anything I really don't
But you remember her tumor right anything like it before or after
It doesn't look like a normal tumor it was it was deep purple and a quarter
Slightly raised
I think it was red Jello there is something very strange about the way I look
So doctors took a sample
These little teeny tiny pieces
Lab for diagnosis and in this case since it was Hawkins they would take an extra piece
And give it to
Man named George guy
So George guy was a researcher who works at the Hop
You got a deal with the clinic at anytime they got a patient with cervical cancer they give him a tiny piece
If the tumor
What he really wanted to do his main mission
She noticed his scientists everywhere we
They wanted to find a way
To grow human cells
Outside of human
In a dish
George guy had been trying to do this
Working on this project
And why exactly
It's sort of like it's her like having a little tiny bit of a person in it in a lab that
Detached from them so that you can do whatever you want with them
You know you can't
Bombard some person with a bunch of drugs into
Wait to see how much they can tolerate before their cells all explode
But you can do that in cell culture
You're so this is like
This is like the basic thing you need to study human biology you need cells in a dish yes
Rimowa
Anytime they tried to grow human cells in a dish
I would die
Yeah
They died
This is George guy's former lab assist
Can you just tell me your name mean
My name is Mary
I'll put my maiden name in there
Troy kubicek
Mary lives just outside of Baltimore about an hour from where she used to work with George guy such as
Show me some pictures and he's sitting at
Atom microscope
So I can have you back
He said he seems like a really big guy like
At least six five judging the picture
And then every slide that you showed me he had kind of a crazy smile on his face
A man is what I always
Mary says they were completely stumped at why the human cells always die
But they just did
On the day that George guy walked in and married to with a little chunk of a nameless woman cervical cancer inside
No one expected anything while he was doing that well he probably
Everhope
But
I was eating lunch now that you know it's not going to grow I'm going to finish this sandwich
That's what I did
No I went in and
Cheapest house in food
Turn on all the machines and left
Came back the next day
Bandai
So she came back the next day
They were growing
And the next day
Still growing they just kept plugging along
In the net group
A lot
Becca says they doubled in size every 24 hours
They just grew all of a sudden you know I care
Transferring them
Making more
YouTube transferring them
Making mortar tubes
They were very reliable and stronger they just kept plugging along
Dark Knight
Officially she died of
Uremia witches
Like toxicity of the blood because she wasn't able to get rid of the toxic waste that
Usually goes out in your urine
Not herself
And tell us this story
Is a privilege to introduce dr. George guy with long after that George guy appeared on TV
Holding in his hand a little bottle
Like an alarm which we have grown
Quantity of cancer
Did you want to look at the photos and uplifting
Until you go to the Hopkins archives and look up
George guys pictures and videos
Okay this is
Phone can hear your cell phone then it hits you
Omigod swirling hurricanes of cells just like thousands of little pot
Some small and some very large
Make a note to leave them under the microscope
It's indescribable
Why hers
Just sort of took off and grew and the other ones
The day of tried before didn't is just a little bit of a mystery nobody really knows
For unless George gynuity had
Disney cell line
What's what they'd all been waiting for
So early on
Right after this one died George guy sent Mary
Back down
Get more cancer cells from the court to the morgue yeah
Really
So I went down there
And they are
Corner I don't know
Dr. Garg
Pair to anywhere standing
Danaher
Feet sore
Meanwhile she's
It's like she was flying out there she's already open
I got some samples
Cornell Tech
What you look like
I could look at her face
I couldn't look at her
The only thing I looked at where her toes and they had chips
Nail polish
What was it about the nail
Oh cuz it was chipped
Cuz you know that she hadn't been able to take care of her nails grow long
Time if they got
Like that
And it's show that she was proud of her so
Not everyone wears
Nail polish
Post
Over the next several months
Well this woman's body lady composing the ground
George guy in Mary produce
Hundreds of thousands of
Versailles
Are tumor cells and he named them
The Hela strain
Hela
Like hela hela no one would actually know why you named them that for about
Two decades but what he did with these cells
You know we would be unusual nowadays
It's like if somebody now found a cell that was special they run off to the patent office and then sell it to Merck
Fredonia books
Hey just passing out freely in trying to make any money off
Nice nice
New things
Could help science
Mary says it George guy begin to send hila all over the world
Pretty soon she was in hundreds of labs
And this was in the midst of the polio epidemic
1951-52 you know schools are being closed kids are being kept inside
Enormous effort to develop polio vaccine
Problem was in order to develop a vaccine you had to have enough
Poliovirus
Univ quantity to be able to study in the lab
And I had no way of making enough
So what are you doing well
One of the guys
Guy
One of the guys the guy had sent
DSL still your friend of guys discovered something
Kind of amazing
Which is it polio
Loved the hela cell put polio inside a hela cell healing would copy and in the process make more polio
Xerox El no matter what you want to do
Make a copy make a copy make it pop
Yeah so now that a way of making polio you that could just be a
Polio Factory
And so
The government me to factory look at Tuskegee inst
Ketut literally a factory said they had
He's big you know stainless steel if active culture medium that works for rotated constantly
Autoclave screw sterilizing other equipment Arroyo with snails
Buy microscope
Crazy frankensteiners to give mode they had
Machine like an automatic pill dispenser and it had the surgery on arm
It's worth
A certain amount of
This culture medium filled with
Fuel cells into a tube of Industry
Yeah it is absolutely the cells that were produced satisfactory she says were used to test the polio vaccine
The test
In North is the largest field trial ever done
At its peak
The Tuskegee
Hila production Center
Was producing. 6 trillion cells week
Maui
Kind of inconceivable
That was actually only the beginning such a backup because this Factory led to an even bigger one
It was for profit rate
That second Factory was the first
Time
Any human biological material was commercial
To this was the first biotech
Basically when they first started mass-producing
What sort of things were done to the
Problems
Investigate
Click anything you can imagine
Do they infected Hela cells with every kind of virus
Titus
Equine Encephalitis virus yellow fever herpes measles mumps rabies whatever like you just any
And this was just
This is a revolution for scientific research on chemotherapy drugs Hela cells went up into the first
Space mission
Really
Yes if they were Hela when to spay Louis and to say such a every time I hear that you're like
Why I mean
Because the premise was
To see what happens to human cells
In zero gravity to know if we're going to be sending people up into space what's going to happen to them up there
Inhumans dead
Sheetz
The Fells
What's actually skip forward in the story to the point where that
The Flipper
We just heard that pronoun confusion
Gets
Personal
Know what would happen
Okay the late 60s
Revolution in science and now there are hundreds of cell lines not just he livid
Hundreds
Somewhere along the way
Scientist discovered that
Sheila is so aggressive that she's actually been contaminating and taking over
All these other cell lines
What you just said she
But I get your point
And she doesn't know
It
Does it in The Stranger
Just way he was elves can you know they can float on desk
We can ride I can what
They can float on Dust particles
Yes so they can they can hop out of addition to
Get on a particle and
Out the door
Stairs down the hall and he'll self to allow drops into into dish cell culture where there's other cells growing
And because he will sell their sort of powerful
Salisbury
Take over
So on the heels of this catastrophe someone at Hopkins decides
To make a test
Let's make a test
It will allow us to genetically determine if a cell is Gila or if it is
How to make a long story short
This desire for a genetic test
Lead scientist II Men journalist
To ask a question which amazingly for 25 years had not been asked
Who was this woman
And that's when we found out her name
Henrietta
Lacks
This is the sound of Rebecca reading henrietta's medical Rec
First time
Can I have this
Is a 30 year old colored woman
She sitting with
Henrietta's youngest daughter Deborah
2nd of November to this is again
Just bring it with you
Henrietta had five kids when she died at the age of 31
Most have no memory of
Especially true of Deborah
Was only 15 months old and I don't
Remember anything about my mother
Yes she
You know she
She gets in her entire life
Just a Longing To Know
Her mother was and did she lie
Dancing and I always wanted to know what she
Like to do what she
When
Would you like to eat that you breastfeed Deborah she was she was really sort of
I was fixated on that idea she wanted to know
If she was breastfed
I don't know what I would give up just to
Just
Half a hair tie
It's a see her
Homework
So in 1973
When a scientist calls the lacks family never hears
That little bit
Of the mother that she never knew are still alive
And oh by the way can we take a blood test from your family's or having some contamination problem when you do genetic marker
Blah blah blah what is you could imagine
Took me by surprise it really did
It was really confusing I mean how much is it how much of a sales is out there you know eventually she went online
I found thousands and thousands of hits
Like for instance on HELOC loans
And Deborah had heard
And various journalists
In the past to come to her and mentioned you know
Dolly the cloned sheep
End
Dad you know your mom
They did this with your mom to meaning that's actually where the technology started
The first cells ever cloned were Hela cells
But that was just clone yourself
Not cloning an entire being
But that
Distinction
Is very complicated
For somebody who doesn't know what a cell is
Between what
Journalists I told her and Googling
Can relax and clone thought there were thousands of
Cloned her mother around and
You mean like a bunch of Henrietta
Walking Street walking around
Rebecca says that one of Deborah's biggest fears
Is bumping into one of these clones
You know she would say I would have to go talk to her and she wouldn't know that I was
Daughter and
And and I don't know that I
Handle that
Wow sound so fantastically how could someone believe that they're copies of her mother walking around but at 1.25
5 years after their mother died someone called and said hey
Piper still alive and you know we've got enough of her so that they could wrap around the Earth
Travel time to Des Moines all bets are off
Not to mention that it's actually not that crazy
Is your DNA is in yourself
So if your cells are taken out of you and they still grow
What is Nats w
Alive of you but it's clearly not you and it's going on and on that some
It's a funny middle space that's for sure
So here's what happened is Rebecca went off in search of Henrietta Lacks
Every so often Deborah would come along
And sit with her as they interviewed you know anyone that could find friends family and eventually over many many
Years
Picture does emerge
This woman was she was born in in Roanoke 1920 Virginia
10th
Of the 11 children but at least she was the one that stood out everybody talked about her as just being
You know she was the catch oh my goodness I don't think I could stop her
This is Sadie Sturdivant henrietta's cousin
Did it for myself but it was very
Brown eyes brown hair
Snake tan complexion
Everyone they spoke with zeroed in on the same few points
First she was really
Meticulous about her nails
Always has very deep red and second Henrietta just had this she was very strange
Forthright
MicroCell
Unfortunate thing is it when it comes to her life
And how she lived
There's not a ton of detail
So this is when
But in that hotel room
Flipping through the medical record
They did start to get some detail
The Hedgehog
Write about
How she died
Wishing a lot of pain when she died this was the hardest thing
She was eventually in an unbelievable amount of pain
Complains of pain
In the right lower quadrant wailing and
And crying and you know moaning for the Lord to help her and
According to the records doctors tried everything morphine they injected
Gibson alcohol straight into her spine
Pain
Spider the alcohol
Injection last week to have these fits of Team through spasms
Waves of pain would hit her and she would rise up out of the bed and brush around
The bass Tracker to the bed and
Her sister
Along with one of her friends
In one of them would tighten the straps and the other one would put a pillow in her mouth so that she wouldn't bite her tongue
If I just had the chance
To take care of
Now
Dealing with how her mother died was one thing
Cells
Made it more complicated
Whatever her mother was alive and he sells them how
So if that's true that
Left very big questions and the first of them
For Deborah was how can
I'd rather rest in peace If part of her with part of her soul is being in a shot up to the moon and injected with l
Chemicals in a radiated and bombarded it so painful
No one you know that
Had her sales on
The backward donkey going to Turkey
You know in the airplane
Just born all over the world
I just don't know if she worried about them
She worried that it hurt
Your mother
The cells with Ebola
Does somehow her mother feel
The pain that comes with ebola and had a scientist ever like sat down with her
Me just explain to her like this is no never
Nothing cuz it's you that wouldn't be that hard to explain it like
When you take cells out of a body it's kind of like when you cut your fingernail
Off it just doesn't that your fingernail doesn't keep growing and living after you cut it off
It's a it's really hard there is no other example of
Some way that you can take something from someone's body
And have it keep living and not have a person feel it
And all these worries sister Baga
Began to build and Deborah's mind
And Dill
And Bill
At her cousin's house
Other cousin Gary
Tooth broken out in hives
She was telling him all the stuff that she recently learned can almost hear it on the tape she says to him
Can't carry the burden of these cells anymore
Do it
I don't want to try to do
And I have been started trying to talk her down and he was trying to talk her down
And then just out of nowhere he just started
Singing
And he started preaching
He held her head in his hands
About Buffet
Thank you for being awake
You make a pass in the mail
You called the mountains skip like lambs
Thank you Lord
Thank you
Thank you Jesus
Hallelujah
Hurry up
Hey man
Batman
And she just
Feel like a man
I feel like
She didn't realize it then
That night
Deborah was on the verge of a stroke
One of the most striking moments of the stories when the two of them visit Hoskins
And
Debra meets her mother's cells for the first time
The scientist finally contacted
Christoph lengauer the scientist to invite us into his lab to see the cells
He had projected them onto a screen
Appliques cuz the way they were stained and protected
So they're very it's cereal looking they're very assertive there they glow you know I mean when you think about angel
Filtrate you think of something glowing Christopher turned on the screen and she just
Xiamen Deborah gist
Gas
200 times bigger than what they really are
Chain of cells
Kristoff gave the he gave her a vial of the cells that you can hold in her hand
And it came out of the freezer so they're cold and she sort of her hands together with the
Violin her hands or warm them up in
Blue on them to keep them warm
And then she just threw whispered to the cells it was
Incredible sheep just raise them up to her lips and she said
You famous
Nobody knows
Just a week before Rebecca and I spoke in the studio she got
Got a call that Deborah had died she had a heart attack and died in her sleep
Okay so
As you may know at this point
That segment was based on Rebecca
Exclusive book The Immortal Life of
Henrietta Lacks
Amazing book
It cannot
Right when we released at
Hispanic
Couple years now
And recently we met up with
Rebecca inch
Chicago
Just get an update came out of that but
Twitter just took off
Scholarships for named after Henrietta
Honorary doctorate monuments Highway placards and historical landmarks and buildings named after
High school called Henrietta Lacks High
Hela high for short B while the book is it
Exploding she went on this like insane book tour members of the lacks family began to join her and started off with just
Relax would go in
User on stage
It's Q&A
And people started cheering
And scientist ending up saying
I want to tell you what I did with these cells and I want to tell you why this was important for me and I'm sorry it was hard for you and
People reaching out I'm alive today because of this a drug that your mother sells help that Oliver
You know I do this in my lab and they just it never stop
The flood which is an away with Deborah always wanted she wanted to go
To every event she wanted to be on every television show she had her dress picked out for Oprah like
You know 8 years for the book came out you know she was
Deborah wanted this is
Exactly what she always do
But then
Just last year
Something interesting
Troubling so yeah so March 2013 to 3% is from Germany sequence
The original in Publisher online
Where anyone can download at
Please click button I downloaded it was is there
And they did not ask the family and my initial reaction when I saw this press coverage was
They did what
Because
Within the Hela genome
There's also
And some of that
Was Pat 50% kids in 25%
Potentially to her grandkids
But one of the things so they put out a press release when this genome sequencing on it had a little
Frequently asked questions of the press might
And one of them was
Can you learn anything about Henrietta or her or her children from this you know the answer is no.
And I do and I believe that they
But they believe
But this is a misconception you can in fact learn about people and in fact you cannot even hide
People's private information if you try and so
Researcher
Took the genome and created
Essentially
A report on Henrietta
You have
X percent chance of
Bipolar disorder
Alcoholism obesity has this huge range of things and
Some of it is yes there's some real
Potential privacy violation like with the Alzheimer's jeans and things like that bit of information about your family
Will not tell you
Was it support this dude
May did he
List all these things are describing to me
So I called The Lacs
Did you know that
Let me think about this and Rebecca head cold you know
They did not
Any kind of bothered us because we're saying okay
Why wasn't a family involved with this decision maker
That was Jerry lacks Gary Lacks
Y.
Laxus granddaughter back in the 50s you had Henrietta Lacks
Versailles weather
Removed without her family's knowledge
Can you go in the 70s
My dad and his siblings
Mito blood samples
Used it for research
They didn't give consent
Then you come 2013
And you have
Henrietta's
That's out this though it was her medical records being
Published publicly
Another first question was
Can you get them to take it down
Until we can figure out what it is what it means
So I reach out to the scientist and said
Black family you know
They replied immediately they took it offline
Immediately
And then I contacted Francis Collins
The head of the NIH I also reached out to
Kathy Hudson who
Used to run the genetics and public policy Center at Hopkins and is now over at the NH dealing with a lot of these issues
Shout to them
And said somebody needs to try to
Help black men get consent to me need to just
Go back
Pretend like this is starting
Now
And just do it probably should have happened in the first place and that's a might have been like a couple of weeks after that several weeks after that
That they had a meeting with NIH
That was my mom myself my sister my dad my uncle My Brother David
My cousin Ron Rebecca skloot she was asking or not
Conference call
All the nhbooks drive up to Baltimore
Doctor College Kathy I sending it was like we were excited like
With the director they all met
Listen to everybody you know
Listen to all
Cassandra listen to all quiet
What can be done what can be done
The last time we asked about everything you could possibly imagine when over you know
The information about Geno
Gene sequencing the basic science of genomes to get a clear understanding of
What DG No Limit
Defiance
We all want to stop science
But yet we don't want
Certain information to be just broadly available
Publicly so they laid out three options one was we don't release any of them at all and then there was a second option which was released
Sit with
No restriction
Just put it out there like the Germans did
And then there was corruption which was really sit with restrictions
Dover NH wood house it
On their own servers
And that in order to get access to it you would have to send an application at said this is the research we're going to do that would be
The committee formed that was a group of scientist
And then some members Alexa
The Hela genome
Committee one grandson child and one great-grandchild My Brother David and my cousin Veronica and this is the option
So yeah there's this company and they just
A few weeks ago
Saw their first batch of applications
In the news hit and it was the first time that they were part of the news
Sole the third generation
Like Jerry lacks was on
MSNBC Live doing an interview about this
She never done this before and they were in every newspaper and it was
Everywhere is pretty exciting and we are stepping into the spotlight is it's the grandchildren
Third and fourth generation blacks
16 great-grandchildren is there snow right now and that's
Yeah the other thing that is an undercurrent for all this is Deborah's gone
She was the one who was
Just so forceful
And so dedicated with
Getting
The information out there about her mom and you know what I look at
The four years since the book came out
Yeah there a few moments
The standout is incredibly emotional
This
The first meeting
Sitting on the
Speakerphone
Listening to
This
Meeting these high officials sitting at the table and and have
Sincere concern about
Alquest
If she could have said what what do I dream might someday happen
That would be what she would have described how I've been I can just imagine her just sitting there and she just laughing rocking back and
Twiddling fingers
Absorbing all of this
This excitement
I want to thank Rebecca skloot for giving us her rot Apes her book The Immortal Life of Henrietta Lacks is true
Truly spellbinding
Can get more information at radiolab.org sign up for a podcast there radiolab.org
Hello this is Rebecca skloot
Radiolab is produced by dad Adam read our staff includes ellenhorn Michael Raphael Doran wheeler
Miller and Howard
At Walter's with help from a d-marion errands and and Sharon Shattuck specials
Thanks to Tim Clark and Timothy
Why isn't it
Wisniewski
The name exclude I'm allowed to stumble on people's last name