Wait wait
Listening to Radiolab
Radio WNYC
Hi I'm Robert krulwich
I am not Jedi bomber
I'll do modest thing to do I'm a new summer ODI
I host another podcast
At WNYC Studios note to self
Frequently enough
Thank you sir there we are yes and I am here pinch-hitting for Dad for a little bit
To spread the word that this is an important time for Radiolab Robert
The year the giving time of the year we're about to do I say
Pink
Will Be Kind of Wonderful
Because
We who make the show and you who listen to this
Show don't often have a chance
To get together so in the next bit of time what we're going to do is we're going to pass
We've invited some of the p
People who normally listen to come on the show and people who Donnelly make the show come and listen
When mixing it up a little bit
It's a strange menagerie of humans and we want to just go to the zoo of us
That's coming right up but if you'd like to hit pause just for a second and make a contribution right away like right now
You can enjoy the episode knowing that you already done the thing that you were supposed to do that we're going to be on our knees begging you to do what
You've already done it I guess that's already
You already
Solve the problem
Do you want me to take you
Robert is beating around the bush
Radiolab relies on the
Support of listener contributions
Listeners like you yes
Who make all the stories that we put
Also it's time that we extend a hand to you are podcast listeners
Invite you to make a financial contribution
So that Radiolab can keep these episodes coming your way it is super easy to do
We asked you to go to radiolab.org donate to give
Or even easier if you live in the US
Open up your phone
Probably what you're listening on anyway
Open up the messaging app
Type the word Radiolab to the number 6 9 8
Fix it
That'll get you started
But suppose you live in Montevideo Uruguay or in Zagreb Yugoslavia
A country that no longer exist what do you have to do then
Let's go to radiolab.org donate that's what I always do whenever I'm in Central Europe
Southeast America
It's really easy so don't be intimidated
Now
As we promised it is time for you to meet some people who you here on our show but have never really met
Aryan whack produces a part of my show she's never met them either so this was her chance to find out about them
Our chance
To find out about
What is this Terry
Did I lose you
Hi how are you how are you in your email
Why don't you know
All right so I decided to call this woman that I have just been desperately curious about
Years now
Since I've worked here
The reason well I've been wanting to reach out to you for a while because
Part of my job here is to listen to
All of the spots that come in for our underwriting and I like
Choose the reason produce them and put them into the episodes I need to go in
Tobacco for a second we have our listeners
Submit underwriting reads via the app
And
We put them into the break of our shows if you've listened to the show with any regularity you've probably heard this
Jesus carry babcock lumish
Support for NPR comes
From Empire
Tara babcock lumish
Does everything on one of them
Terry babcock lumish
The terry Babcock lumish harry babcock
Hairy back.
More than 300 times and I I know that if
In a pinch I need a spot quick I know that there's going
To be a reed
From Thierry Henry Babcock
Are you tired
That's why I wanted to call you guys cuz there's three of you that
Leave I mean read almost every single piece of copy I put up
And so especially you know I think you probably been doing it the longest out of any of them so I remember like when you
Movie. Coughlin
New York from Lake cold Spring
Terry Babcock
What sound of Honolulu and like I know it like when your husband is around
Brian Babcock
Chocolate milk
Carry the occasionally like he'll pop and I feel like I kind of know you
I mean it is all day sound like evidence that I
Gathered from your phone calls in the background noises and what not
You're awesome this is really funny
What's your hypothesis
My hypothesis will you live
In
Cold Spring for a while and I was like she doesn't
She sounds
Too young to be like a like a snowbird so I didn't think that you guys had moved for the weather
Like somebody must have gotten a job down there
You have grandkids
And I was surprised I had heard that a couple of times
Or at least I sound like little kids
To me baby.
Anything because
Mariners gear
Yeah I would love the real story
No reason why I should have gotten mixed up with an army guy
So he's active duty military
And so we moved
4 years
With his army assignment
Summer 2014
Assignment to Hawaii and that's where we live
Crown actually that makes me so happy
Have you ever heard yourself
When like you listen to Radiolab have you ever heard one of your reads
You can spend no
On a regular basis I'll get an email from
A former student or a friend or
Thing that they heard me on Radiolab
That I feel still
The tax firm
But no it never do you have a favorite episode
I don't know but I think
One of his things that I love is that you
Things that are very complex
And you make ardidas letters
Phenocrysts
Videos are black hole
You make them nauseous
Interesting
But accessible and exciting and then I remember it
Yeah
Well
I mean there's
Frequently
Thirty different drafts of an episode
It's hard to like hear the finished product
That's just a listener
Try again and not being like I didn't deposit that
P there
You know like other room tone there I could have smooth that out something you know and I meant I miss that a little
I guess I mean like I want to know like why you do it like why why you're so committed to like give
Driving test
In this particular way
So
I feel like what you've asked of us
Is solo
NC weather
Public Radio
Or it's me
It's something I can do
Okay
Yeah whatever we've lives as one
No it really is a soundtrack of my life and
I could be wrong but I feel like for plenty of people they're concerned that they can't give a big chest
That
DeSean Jackson
I think about
No Ethan just a little tiny
What would happen if your coffee
I think people feel like that's not enough but
And I don't
I think we should underestimate
And
So
It's going to be New York if I can take you for a cup of coffee
I'll be happy to
That would be great thank you so much
Really enjoyed this conversation
I didn't know if you were
Man Down
Really
Menucha here's the thing about Terry is that she's one of a lot of
Who tunison
And then kyna
Join in
We have a very unusual audience
Awesome audience Radiolab listeners of the best
But in very particular ways like
Like when you meet them, I really whatever that thing you do they don't do that
Very specific
Either complements or arguments but it's
Their listeners
Meeting Dave listen
Robert I think what you're saying is the listeners you listeners not only do you give
Your time you give your brains the brain remember you give contributions
What is what keeps Radiolab on the air
And in order for 2017 to knock it out of the park like 2016 did
We need you to keep doing that if you were just sitting here talking about like
Maybe okay maybe now
What would you do right now if you want it
You would go online to radiolab.org donate
To give
Is Radiolab spelled
It's two words or one now it's just one or even easier just
Text that one word
Radiolab
2 the number 698
Fix it
To get started that's if
If you're in the US
In any case so you can get it handled in a matter of seconds and Wheatland
Yeah we really do
I know
Introduction to one of our listeners
I recently met
The three things that I say I love about this country
A festival
You're drinking water coming out of your faucet
It's insane
Yo-yo thirsty in the middle of a shower you just open your mouth when you're done
It's incredible
So this is mayank Mishra he's a graduate student in ecology at princeton university
When is Bike Lanes
Fantastic
Yeah
Because I said
You should try riding a bike in Calcutta Ohio Deli it's
It's
It'll definitely get you closer to God
That's what ya God does exist in India
So my aunt started out as a civil rights lawyer in India often defending people who he thought have been
Give without cause
He left for the United States
In part because he had sued the man who was
Simply became the prime minister
Of India
And he thought maybe I
You should go somewhere else
Dove and the tub thing I love about this country
Was internet I mean just
Really great internet where I could listen to things
All the time
And also I heard Radiolab was when I first started listening to podcasts
I first met my time after giving a lecture up at Princeton University came up afterwards and he said you owe
I want to tell you about the
First time I heard
Keurig Radiolab
Okay so you was on a road trip with some of this
Fellow students so I was supposed to be navigating
I was just graduating from my masters in public administration from Princeton
We would done with
School
But he was still getting to know each other
Because
You don't know if he was done with it we knew each other but we didn't quite know where everyone came from
And people going
The beach house the entire class
Was going bad
Tifosi farewell and you don't spend a
A few days together
And I was supposed to be navigating and I got everything wrong
And we went miles away
And I song talking about
How I have to deal with the loss of my father than my grandfather
Boots
Michael's friend
And
Have you also having to deal with the fact that we were going to leave the
Place behind
And leave this
Community behind the feud filmed over the past two years the first one
I had in the US
Someone said you were busy
Incredibly
Greed Episode by Radiolab on
Life After Life I think of
That was our afterlife episode it was a series of meditations
Undeath this hour we ask that question I did what happened
At the very moment when you slip from life to the other side and what happens after
And resulting it I was just stunned silence
Susie
Entire thing
And once the
Was it seems that's always stuck with me
Is the
I remember you were talking about a group and it said
What happens when the group dispersed some people go their separate ways
Does a group die or do they carry
It with them this was a short fiction p
Peace by the neurology
Is David Eagleman which was right on our show by the actor Jeffrey Tambor
When soldiers part ways at War's end
The breakup of the platoon figures the same emotion as the
Well the death of a person
Participants
Gamble away feeling that they were just part of something larger than themselves something they into it had a life
Even though I can't quite put a finger on it
In this way death is not only for humans but for everything
That exist
And it turns out that anything that enjoys life
Enjoys an afterlife
And then there was something about when you pass away
What happens to the
Do the things that make you up when you die
You agree
My orgasms
Of which Eureka MO
Weather in sheets of Scandal
Communities of spleen by with your death
Did they don't die
Instead they they part ways moving off in their separate directions mourning the loss of a special time they shared to get
Actually haunted by feeling them
Everyone's playing Parts in something
Larger
Femdom self
Something
That has its own life
Something that
Macon
Are they
Butterfinger
And I think I don't know I had not told about things that way
I'd never thought about where life begins and
Raiden
And my uncle mentioned another Eagleman piece that causes a year
There was this one thing that you said which was
That's one way of looking at death
Is
When the Lost person
Speaks your name
That's when you're gone
There
R3
Guess
Now the first is when the body
The second is when the body
Consigned
Foot in the grave
The third is that moment
Sometime in the future when your name is spoken
For the last time
With my father and my grandfather
You know the TV
Forget them today
UWE
Stop bossing on their stories in
No one remembers him
That's when
That's when they're gone
That's actually gone
So you're listening to this
Are they any other people listening and there's this kind of Deep Quiet in the car
Yeah and then what
So that happened and then that was my introduction to listening to podcast
So then I started listen to Radiolab more
And who did you have a lot of time on your head about what's going on after school what happened
So what happened was
Even in school
I've been a loyal
I had reached this point where I thought
You know I was done with human beings I was done with human right I was done with all of that stuff because I felt like
The we were just
Too far beyond
Receiving
And I feel like
Clearly this is not where I should be
Because there's
A big Oval Drive trivia some affinity
But what are you what are you decide to
Do
What was the news
I wanted to go back to school
I wanted to study ecology
And I attended the
That's awesome
Ecology
I'm completely blew my mind and I decided
You look good I'm not on the right path maybe this is about
Should be on
I remember we was living in Brooklyn right across from the botanic gardens
And
Even through the winter I go there and I will listen to Radiolab
Honda
Everytime I think of Radiolab I think of
Smiles and tears
So streaming down my face
Because
There's always
So much emotion to tell if backed into it
Babysitting the
In the cold
In the snow in the botanic gardens no one else around
With a small notebook
I'll listen to Radiolab and every time something would come into my head at jot it down
So sitting there in the botanic gardens listening to us like what what what
To the Dufour
So open me up and help me together
Did both things right
Open me up to
The new world
If ideas and Thompson
A community of people who
Also have similar thoughts
You also want to find out more about what
Going on
And also help me together because I was
Sold by myself
I'm very very fortunate
Have my wife with me and she was
Let me she's been a huge bill of Sapulpa
We have bolts
So to step out of our comfort zone
An affordable Visa
To some extent
Because of Radiolab
Every time I hear the
Opening credits of Radiolab
It feels like I'm just stepped back home from the cold or something it's just
You don't shake off
All the snow from your jacket
Unsettling
You do feel like you sort of
Solve something
I hope not
I hope not but I totally feel
Are you happy about where I am
It's interesting
Because
If you if you listen to the show we do we never solve anything
That's right yeah
You never do
So you know what this was
This is something I've been thinking about a lot recently and I was speaking to a very close friend about this
I was thinking about what is the rule
Scientist
And I found it
More recently been there have been things that make me
Wonder what the scientific Community is looking out for some time
I think sometimes
Will Solace caught up in
Our credibility and the fact
We must maintain The credibility and we shouldn't break rank
Put new one
Becomes a scientist because they read a really credible
Scientific
FIFA
Bereaved did they become scientists because they're inspired by
This world around them and they're just really curious about what's going on
You inspired me to
To be more curious
Beretta
To recognize that we don't have answers
And sometimes just looking for questions
Is enjoyable it's a lot of fun
What I do together
To be looking for things together to go on this treasure hunt
Around life together
That's home
Robert I think I might be in love with my uncle
When we shook hands I remember like holding onto his hand like for an ex
Extra beat because
When you do this for a living you don't expect
Do anything much more than tell a story
But if you can
If you can help somebody get out of a hole or climb a mountain or change
No change a life then like that
Cherry
On top
Super duper cherry on top and I happens
Carly
Not on off and on
Show
So that's really cool
And
And I just had to
Just say like if you listeners if Radiolab has touched your life
At some point in this past year doesn't mean they had to have a career makeover
It was just like it made you smile or it made you think about something a little bit
Differently
We ask you to remember you're part of a community and this community
Is held together with listener contrib
It really is what keeps
Radiolab
So let's suppose you were in the mood to give
Radiolab something how would you go about
Play easy rock
Okay let me just take me through it slowly and step-by-step
Stewart fast. Org donate
You listening on your phone it's really easy opening up
Messaging app that you got there
Very good
Text the word Radiolab spelled fully out
To the number 69866
Six nine
Now what
Oh now okay I'll leave it a story to tell producer Eddie McEwen
Who was who wanted to meet somebody
Well you don't want to meet her so here we go
Okay so a few months back we did a story called alpha-gal
I'm getting nervous
And the star of that show was a woman named Amy Pearl get my EpiPen
Allergic
To radio greatness
That I know of has been really exposed to that yet
I'm Robert.
The story was about any pearls
Allergy to red meat and how she got the allergy to red meat so I'm going to tell you anymore she goes in the story lesson right now
But the reaction got from the audience on Twitter and in comments on our website which is insane you should we get kind of like
You know the outcome and hear their love the show hate the show where's
Science stuff like that
But this time it was just like this
Huge outpouring of deep deep love for Amy Pearl
You don't get that girl her own show she's incredible she changed my life Amy Pearl for president was one of the tweets
And I felt the same love her that everyone else did in my Java the show is again a lot of cutting tape and sound design and
Music and stuff like that
So I never actually like met her before but I met her through her voice
And I also
Thought how she's very wise
In ways I feel like I really need in my life right now
And so this is one way to get more it'll bring more Amy Pearl back into our lives again which feels good
Good hello hey
Also it was sort of an opportunity for me to ask
A question I wanted to kind of
But I recently moved here from a really small town in Canada and I'm
Trying to
Figure out how do I be a human being in the city and
Just letting you know not let it well I mean it's like
I mean do you ever hear there's a famous saying
Did you ever hear it
If you can make it here
If you can make it anywhere
It's up to you
New York true everything is so hard in the city
I mean forget it it's like
I'm like I have to renew my driver's license or driver's license you're a big trouble oh my God everybody
It's not going to work out for you Amy I don't know about start a support
Everything
Unlike all you have to do is go for a minute like
Where my mom lives in Connecticut and I go up there and she's like
I'm going to return something at Costco on my quad what are you kidding me I'm Only Happy for 2 days
How to be easy
Do you like drive up
Driving to a party
Get out of the car
Walk 1 second nice to meet you let me help you you're all set thanks so much by get back in the car driving
Tattoo your driveway park in the garage
I don't know why the sea
City so hard
What do you do like what
What do I mean
Well for sure a good thing about being in the city as if
You know
If you want to do good
You keep you can like I'm sure between now and the time you get home tonight you can like
Pick up someone's pain like
Vermont like tell somebody they have they have like toilet paper on their shoe
Help someone who seems lost for like smile at someone
Seems down there be like oh my God I love that book that's like you have every opportunity to make someone else's day better
You could just be like
I'm a superhero
If something happens I'm going to rush over there and something might happen any second City it's like you know
And it's like
When you're walking around the city
I always find treasures like if
If you lucky
In the gutter
You just like
Pick up some
Forever Barbie and it just seems like
So great and like
Can you tell me
What's your
What's with the last time you really saw the city as beautiful
Oh my God
God I think the last time I saw
The city is beautiful
Probably
Last night
It was very dark and I got my dog and we went out like on the Block that I walk on
All the time
But somebody had
What's all the leaves and there was
A pile of
Oakley
On the side
And the light from the house
Lectin
Every oak leaf look like
Meloetta
MSN there such a pretty shape and I was like oh my God
These are just being thrown out by the tree
These are not even like of Youth and I was like well every single year it grows up
Brand new Leaf
And then dropped it off and the girls another one dropped it off and grows another one drops it off at a must-have for like 200 years of Michael
Imagine how many leaves the tree drops off in like where does it all go and like what is all that energy coming from and why
Doing it
And it smells good
Pretty
Probably covered in dog piss but I didn't get that close
And I thought it was really beautiful and it was like
It was a good moment
Amy Pearl
Bath
You don't like she was so when you hear Amy Pearl talk about anything
Dog pee is fine
Because Amy Pearl is what is what you would call a moor inn
F
Tea
What's that a natural storyteller
There's no way yes there's no way she can't make everything interesting
And cheats to win this tape came in when we heard it we want oh my
My god get her on the air
Friend don't take her off
We could just live on a mean girl
Now listen though Robert there's a reason why
We were able to get Amy Pearl on the show
Feel precious but don't always
Do the thing that precious things have to do in order to keep
Keep other precious things alive and well I don't know what that means but I think it was an attempt to say in a poetic way they
People who love the podcast
And give just a few dollars
Make this work
Possible and exactly what I'm okay
And I want to add something we actually have some really great radiolab's swag
Yeah
There's a don't pretend you're not wearing the hoodie all the time very warm pudding
And if that's not your bag
There's a bag actually there's a knit winter cap
There's a t-shirt
There's lots of Swag and it you know what it is
I feel like listeners when you wear the Radiolab swag I see you on the street
And ice
I'm sure that when we look at each other we give
You can get the swag without making just a little donation
And we ask
Funny you ask Robert let me
Tell you radiolab.org donate
Or even easier
If you're in the u.s. text the word Radiolab to the number
If you're on your phone
Next up a story about a boy his mom football and lettuce Nasser left if is our producer
Helium
You missed out with me broadcast this but he wanted to get into the game as it were
And here's
What happened next
Yeah and I actually chose
Our football episode American football it was actually the first episode I was on staff for
Checked it and it had all kinds of things that had a story about the history of football in the forward pass in the car
Carlisle Indian team but it also had kind of what is the big question now
What's the future the game
And that
Question was
Perfectly encapsulated
By this interview with this woman
Emily Bartell
You could add something like
She want
I'm on a Bartell I'm a Libra enjoy long walks on the beach
So this story came to us from our senior editor storm we literally just heard back there
And basically The Story Goes Like This
Tony Bartel is from a family that lives and breathes and bleeds
Football her dad Mel Farr the Superstar was a star running back for the Detroit
Lions he was a two-time pro bowler both her brothers were professional football players until 4 Monday 1
First son Parker
As soon as the doctor
Saw his third thumb
We're going to the NFL baby yes and then Parker's 10001
Announce
He's the biggest thing he walked out the room
I'm still going with 3rd Stop
She signed Parker up to
Play Little League when he was 4 years old
Immediately they named in the tank
The moment he gets on the field he is just
Wound through kids getting touchdown after
Touchdown
But this is where things get complicated because
While Parker is on the field
Dominate
Monet has a relative
Who played football for a very long time and was experiencing symptoms of CTE
Chronic traumatic encephalopathy
Which is the what comes from like
Concussion questionnaire
Symptoms include memory loss sometimes bouts of anger
In this case
It was
Depression it was
Suicidal Thoughts
It was
It was getting phone calls
Like hey I need you to come
Come get him
Because
He's having dangerous
Thoughts
And money told us that eventually her father started experiencing symptoms of CTE as well
And that
Put money in a very
Difficult position
Because on the one hand she believed that children should not play foot
But then it's exact same time she believed children should play football
Did it say
Great sport
Jasper Parker
Parker
How do you like the season
His favorite things
Were the trophy and the pizza party at
Had no desire
You want to play again next season
Now
Now our favorite moment of this whole story and allow listeners to
Who's win
Parker comes home from school and sits down with Soren and Monet and Soren ask
Look if you don't like football anymore do I go sports
I really want to do synchronized
What is a chair
Is that true
Mostly because when I saw something about it
Kind of cool like
People are doing a lot of cool swimming tricks so I kind of thought it was
Something for me
Just you playing me
Are synchronized swimming you like you're like this has been contacting me about football and I'm going to tell him that I
I want to do synchronized swimming
I know you like it
Oh yes I'm going to do
And so
Hello hello hey Monday how you doing
Hey I'm good with you how are you today because at like every time now that I see football in the headline
And I I think of her
And I wanted to see how she was doing
Alright also like
Eat like that
I need interview with your son just
Like ice
Think about it all the time he's kind of my hero it has grown legs
I swear it's because of
That interview I was contacted about a month ago from ESPN
Really
Stout to me and they came out here and spent three days
Interviewing Parker
Following him around
You can't tell Parker anything now he thinks he's
Hot Shi
He has now
Said in the interview with ESPN and you know I know they weren't waiting for him to say he was going to be a synchronized swimmer
Now he switched it up
He wants to play dodgeball
Good sport Baldo there's a lot at there's a lot of hit like
Unlike synchronized swimming dodgeballs kind of
Contact sport yeah he's not going to eat here
Please God phone gym
I just think this kids
Live embarrass the crap out of me
But that the series is about the love of football
And you know they said aside from
Packers
You know
Let their up having such a present
In NFL in my immediate family
It was the thing of that ox
Seymour on the fact that I love
Football so much
And that football is
Still extremely you know dangerous you know my father passed away last year
So sorry
My dad passed away in August
The last year which
Threw us all for a loop
My dad was like the healthiest person that we know
And he
He dropped dead
Talk to him that morning the Monday and
At 7 p.m. that evening he he just
You just kind of slipped away
And we got his results back
Send his brain and spinal cord
And my dad was at stage
3 of 4 with CTE
And that's the kind of thing you can only find out after
Is Dad right exactly was that where you started
Expecting that at all
We knew my father suffered from CTE
That jokingly would say my
Having a conversation with my dad towards the end of his life
Would be like I'm 50 First Dates
Because my dad will
Helm Hill
Talk to you like I don't remember such a
Remember you remember such as
But you don't really
You know you don't
Think about it
And then getting the results back for my father
I'm like God
You know
Space force
Is Mike Webster
Just to jump in here Mike Webster was a former professional player
Who was suffering from Amnesia dementia depression
You died at the
Fees for CTE it's Junior sale
Junior Seau was another former professional player
Shot himself in the
Winchester 243 or
CH4 is something
But these families are
Suffering
Because they're watching their loved ones
You can't take it anymore
So they think that taking their lives
Is the easiest
Way to go that's the only way to calm whatever it is it's going on in their mind
Because I can't explain what's going on
I'm thankful I didn't have to do that
Cried when I watched
I Cry
When I watched
Because I can't imagine
As a mother
Sister
As a wife as a daughter I can't imagine
Watching my dad on my brothers or my uncle or my cousin
Go through life like that
Because both of my brothers are exhibiting signs now
That's all I can really think about is
Now what about them
Soulgazer what can you do what can they do
That's the crazy thing
You can't prepare for it
You can't
You can't stop it
Is absolutely nothing you can do
And still with that
Football every Friday night cuz my nephew
I'm happy
Now that
I can laugh at
Smile because I was completely
I I I turned into like
A vampire
When you just out of nowhere when you're just
Okay talk to you later
And then there never is a later
That that
It's a tough one
Did your dad
Before he died
How did your dad feel about
Football how did he feel about that
Tte how did he feel about all of the
Stuff
If you ask my father
He would tell you
I would not have changed
If you look at my my dad
English growing up you know
My dad
Was it an ear where it was separate but not
He didn't have indoor plumbing
She had to drink from a colored only water fountain
I didn't tell you he's a man I ain't never had a dress code once I got to know that feel like what is this
My throat
You know
Sol Bean
Being smart and black wasn't enough
If you would have been black and didn't play football even as smart as my father was
Where would that if
You know what have gotten him to
Two dinners at the White House would have gotten him the private chat would have gotten him
You know the house
Private school education and all that
Would being a smart black guy
In the early forties in the forties would that have
What would I have done
She was able to
To build a life
Playing for the Detroit Lions is owned by the 4th
Family
And then being able to go and internet Ford you know in the offseason
And then opening up a Ford dealership
And then from there branching out to what 14 new car franchises
But she left with with all of us
To be able to carry on that Legacy
It won't be in for in vain
We have started a foundation with
Building on it little by little just trying to figure out
Where and what Avenues we want
It going we know education is huge
And you know that would just want to bring awareness especially to mothers who put their young children and
As I did
Just to be aware
Of what
The dangers are
Are you willing to sign up for that
So now I'm going to I'm really thinking of
Tricking Park
But however he
She is his Middle School mascot
Oh really well I guess I was the mascot of my high school what what is here cuz I was
Griffy the Griffin
Give her curves the alligator I forgot the alligators name
But he's the alligator
How did you like being the alligator he loves it
He has like a costume that he wears
He wears the entire furry
Head every
Turn in
To some kids
Who is this kid
He he he starts dabbing and Mikey's this other kid
It's so my husband the first thing my husband says
He's like the mascots they still get a ring right
So now I'm like
We're going to keep you in Mascot Chisholm
Whatever it's called
Because their scholarship
Scott scholarship
There are mascot scholarship
Yes
I don't think it way ahead of time you go in
He's developing like dance moves or like are there such thing as like he gets it
On Fridays he
The kids in the morning he's got to get there early
You don't put on his costume and he's out there in the carpool lane greet the kids as they come to school he does the
Special events at the school like
He did the Fall Fest
Festival
And the truck
Free
A man and one of his teachers one teacher of the year award
We got to go to the teacher of the year award ceremony as a mascot
Like he's just living it up I hope he
He wins all the mascots dollars
And is
Makes it pro you know
Is it is it is probably cut throat
Take GoPro for mascot
Yeah I don't know how that goes I don't even know how that
I've no idea
To see when we get there and how much do they get paid you know all these other books
Engineer
Okay I'm sure he won't let you go with you could do both
Absolutely
Thinking about what you said about your dad
I hope for Parker that
She will be able to get that Angie
Engineering you know that being smart will be in
Or if you want Stevia mascot he can get all the scholarships go to whatever school he wants he does not have to
Put his body In Harm's Way if he doesn't want right he doesn't have to
My oldest nephew
Trey
Until recently I had the title in the family
He played football but he
Made a plant hey I don't want to go pro
I'm going to play in college but Imma go to a college that's going to give me a head start for the Browns
Brown
Wondering did well and now he's off doing his brown thing and in San Francisco making great money as a
The young black guy because he was smart
Not because of football
So what I'd love to see my son in the football jersey
Sure
But am I
Surreal to see him in the alligator outfit
So we can offer you as soon as a mascot scholarship that is really beyond our reach Mei menu.
Have to choose your animal and we have to make the uniform
So we can't it's comp it's a hard it's fun but it's a hard world
So we're going to stream on when when we think about you instead of thinking about animals
Those are griffins
Where can you just think of you
As
Generous
And now manush
Yes if I
Wanted to be
Generous yes what would I choose
To do you would go to radiolab.org
/ donate
Or even easier you could text the word Radiolab to the number 69866
To get started
A little form pops up Robert and you can donate in a matter of seconds
And then you can go back to thinking how
Awesome radio labs
First
Spin-off was two more perfect world that's going to be coming up in 2017
Cuban listen to us through this past year
I noticed and your joint of the whole lot of people that we never heard from before
Became blisters to something we called more perfect
It just show about the Supreme Court of the United
Red States
That we thought of it because we thought the Supreme Court was going to be interesting and now of course
2017 yeah we were right
In space
Because what's going to happen next year is got to be
Dispute that will be near the center of a lot of conversations
A lot of people
2017 so this
More perfect show is coming back in the spring
More episodes and so people who want to hear it again it's coming
Listener support is a critical component of more perfect it's a critical component of Radiolab
Any amount that you can give
Just make a gift any amount
Make a gift and show
That you understand that this is the
The time to get a year-end tax deductible
Matter in a year
So yeah we like to join us both because you want to and just because of thinking
Should right now if you know what I mean
Next Robert a story that captures that Spirit of doing for others
In a way that few
Hi my name is Tracy hunt I'm reporter here at videolab and I wanted to talk to someone who has a very different
Relationship with giving lacera
Hello Sarah Gray
Oh hey there you are
How are you I'm good I'm still good
Sarah was the star of the show that we did a little while back called Grace donation
I guess I'm like a little bit nerd famous now
Will just nerds know who I am you don't need to listen to Radiolab
Just a quick recap
Sarah
Tell the story about how she was pregnant with twins
Thomas and Callum
And something was wrong with Thomas
Doctors told her that he had anencephaly
Being bored
He said he could see that
Because one of the twins had a round skull
And the other one had a bumpy skull
She ended up giving birth to both of them and Tom aside six days later
The Washington Regional transplant Community they sent a van over to our house
He picked up his body and took him to
DC
Children's National Medical Center
So the story was about how Sarah ended up going on this journey trying to find out what happened to all the bits in
Pieces of Thomas that were donated so she talked about for example going to Duke University where they were using cord blood from her
Twins and they're actually researching the disease that killed Thomas anencephaly and going to University of Pennsylvania
Talking to women there who was studying this I cancer that mostly affects children call retina
Blastoma eventually sarin Ross visited Aruba's lab
She gave them a tour
And she showed them Thomas's retina
She still has
Samples of it in her
Freezer
Tiny little
I don't know tiny little vials maybe you
Third the size of your pinky filled with frozen liquid
Liquefied
Right now it didn't look like much but it was amazing to think of how many
People were involved
Getting the samples there
Like we had to
Approve it we had to fill out this paperwork done the doctor had to come and remove the eyes and I had to be process
If not I have to be
Shipped up there that they have to
Do whatever DNA process they do in
I don't know valuable
Maybe even priceless
The simplest
Since the show came out she released a new book called A Life Everlasting
And I just really wanted to get on the phone with her and just talked about what the impact of the show has been and what's
Going on with her life
And one of the first things I found out was that she had a new baby
Yes we have a baby girl that she was just born in June congratulation thank you
He's doing great
This is Thomas's brother
He can now read a little bit
The first grade
And he's liking his
Sister
What what have you told him about Thomas
So he knows that he had a brother
I was a twin who had a very very very bad boo-boo on his head
Yeah and that's why he died
Let me just explain you know
Sometimes kids die that's just part of life
People in other cat diseases just like grown ups
And it's okay to die
Does he ask you questions about Thomas
Can we visit the grave maybe one or two times
The year and
When he was younger he asked
Is Thomas scared under the stone
So when he was probably maybe two or three
Questions like that were hard cuz
You know I don't
Explain the afterlife I don't understand
Myself
Yeah so I just told him no he's not scared
You know he stinks of Thomas's being in heaven
But he also asked me it'll can you tell me what is it like in heaven
I said
You know it's really like her
Wringing my hands are cold what do I say
Well you know some people think it's a place you go when you die
Some people think it's got clouds and
McCallum just goes up
You look it up on your phone
What you wanted a picture
IPhone
Do you know this way to be real but be real but this is what people think you show me a picture of God
You know stuff like that but you know sometimes it's hard and then sometimes it's easy
And also since the show Sarah has kept on donating in fact when her daughter Jocelyn was born
Born
I was inspired to donate
Placenta and the umbilical cord
It was turned into four different
Skin grafts that are good
Used
And surgeries
For burn survivors
And also the umbilical cord blood went
To research
But also she's been inspired to track down the people who have donated things to her
Idea
For checking.
Blood donors when she was in the hospital with the twins she actually had a traumatic delivery she lost half of her
Blood and she ended up getting a transfusion from 11 different blood donors
So I emailed the blood bank and I've met with them
And they have sent out a thank-you letter from me
To those 11 people and when Sarah was in the hospital with Jocelyn Jocelyn actually got some donated breast milk
And I ended up saving the bottle
Actually framed it like you do
Just tears me up to think of
Strangers donating
Yeah
But you know the breastmilk place
And I said this is my donor ID for the breast milk
Can you tell me who who are the people that donated this milk can I see
Tell him thank you and this is all kind of
Like I know I sound like a donation weirdo but
You don't think you receive and you give them
I think it's neat to make the connection find out how that really work
Since we've recorded the episode with you have you heard me like anything new come out of the research using your sons
Tissues
So there's a study that came out
On tissue that could be my son's cornea this lab in Boston
They've been studying corneal blindness because when your corneas are damaged those cells
Would you lose them that they're never coming back they don't regenerate their just
Dad
Have corneal blindness
And so they're trying to figure out ways to regenerate them so corneal cells
And they wounded them
And then added umbilical cord blood to those cells
And they found some
Early-stage steps to show that these
Corneal cells might be able to regenerate with stem cells which I believe is
Kind of weather getting out of the possible
Stem cell eye drops
Deer Vision back
Oh wow
So this is like way way way it's the beginning of
You know what if situation and what if we could make eye drops like
You talk like that the research
How often you do whatever I feel like it does it feel like you're kind of
Lake kind of
Continue in your relationship with Thomas in some way by by checking on these things I don't I don't know what you call it
I feel like Thomas
You don't he lived
And he died and he made this
Contribution
And I'm like a spectator kind of
Watching
How is contribution is
Affecting other people
Yeah and I'm
I'm more like learning from him
Then having a relationship
Abraham Butler
Yeah yeah yeah I'm not sure that relationship is the right word I was just trying to like
It's almost
I don't know I I don't want to say like it it's like he still there and nothing like that I just
You know like he's
I can still very much a part of
Your life
In some way
Yeah he's still relevant yeah
New Life did not just affect my fan
Is life affected
Many other people and in fact Sarah told me that eight months after the show came out she heard from the
Miss couple in California
In California they had twins
And unfortunately one of them died
Unexpectedly
And I believe they ask
Could they donate and groupset
You can't donate for transplant cuz your child is too small
And if it will be her Radiolab can we donate to research
And they said
Yes
And their daughter was able to donate eight different tissues to eight different studies
Yeah and in fact the retinas
Went to the same
Lab in the same researcher
That received my son's retina
LOL
I know the other weird thing is that they're twins were born on the exact same day as my twins
Pets
Bethel Park
I'm really I'm really kind of speechless of that
Now that happens
It is for me it was bring back so you know when my child died
Cilic
Google control
But being able to donate gave me a sense of control
Back that you know at least this is
This is one thing I can
In control
Great
So I was glad that it had that
Impression hot.
Sarah talking to me about
Trying to regain a sense of control
In the face of
Unimaginable grief
Remind me of something else she said at the end of Grace donation
Are you stupid
Like the universe
Treated people the way it should
And now I don't really believe that
But I'm
I do believe that
There are
Really amazing
Kind people
In the world
And
Science and medicine has something to
I started feeling that
Thomas his colleagues
Endoscope
And that he was a valuable partner
In the
Important research that was being done
Can I feel 10 even more fundamental shift almost like I had felt like I was a boat on an ocean that was like
Rocky and choppy with waves
Can I have this feeling that I am not the boat on the ocean
Like
The decisions that I make
Are changing other people
I'm supposed to just I'm about getting slapped with Waze all the time
Pets make me feel
Purple
Sarah gray speaking with Radiolab Tracy hunt
I think that really is a perfect way to wrap up some of these catch up stories that we've been doing during this
Episode of Radiolab stories that really have impacted
The Radiolab crew and you are listeners
And make sure I'm ready I'm just
I want to thank you for just
Happening here at Jad will be back in January
Open Wunderlist
It's been more than that it's been like cozy
Yasso
Someone say repetitive not me but it's not me
How to say cozy
I would like to thank all the people who been pooping ice but you done
Something during this time and if you haven't done that something
What they say one more time what the doors must have
Done yes indeed
Well and if you haven't that's okay too this is the time to do it it's the season of giving and the moment is here
You've heard how people can act and give to each other on this episode and big and small ways
And we hope you're inspired and that you make a gift in whatever amount works
For you
But we ask you to please do it now. Org
/ donate to give
And there's also a text option as well you to text the word Radiolab to 69866
I get you started and you'll be able to complete your donation in a matter of I would just a sec
Thanks for joining us
Thanks Robert thank you