It is a full UNIX implementation and that it does support virtual memory.
It's not one of the small UNIX like coherent or minix or something like that.
It tries to support everything.
It's ..  there are UNIX system that do more than Linux, but there are UNIX systems.
So it has special memory memory mapping, full TCP/IP networking.
Even though there have been rumors, it's not very stable, it is.
Most of the time [hahaha] it has System V inter process communication and BSD sockets, and it has full UNIX file systems, and it's not the System V 14 character limit file system, but it has 255 characters file systems.
And the 14 character file system and the DOS file system and so on.
Oh, sorry, I didn't even mention it's free.
I mean, I take take it for granted that it's free and it's very open.
If I were a marketing department I'd call it open Linux, [Laugh] but that's why not.
As I'm not.
I just call it Linux and tell you it's open.
And free, and it's written from scratch.
So you don't have to pay AT&T or anything at all.
Um, okay, ah, it's available by FTP, so.
If you want to know where, I can put it down later or something like that.
Okay, this is a small slide.
And I run out of room, so I'll just try to tell you anyway, ah.
The main thing about Linux.
Is the good hardware support, it actually runs on more hardware than any other PC UNIX, that's at least my guess.
SCO might be close.
Or it might be slightly better, but Linux
has drivers.
For almost anything out there except the new stuff DEC puts in its PCs that we had terrible problems getting Linux running on the DEC PC or in the uh.
Whatever ya it also.
Has.
Support for lack of hardware.
So if you don't have hardware like a co processor, it will emulate it.
Uh.
If you want to use something like DOS, which I suppose you don't, but if you want.
To use it.
You can use it together with Linux, either under the Linux.
DOS simulator or side by side by rebooting into DOS, some model systems actually take over the whole disk.
I think BSD ..
They're early version certainly did.
I don't know about the newer ones.
Uh, it's also very useful for personal use due to the low cost, low cost of the actual operating system, which is free.
And the low cost of the hardware it runs on, you can get an unbeatable
price performance system uh, it's also pretty expandable.
Uh, due to the fact that you can .. if you're really hurting.
You can write your own drivers and
Whatever.
Uh, you also.
With a full Linux system like on the cdrom, you get a complete system with X11
Compilers like gcc translators like p to c small talk and so on me anything plus.
10 or 20 editors, and so on.
Anything you want. uh for the professional user, it's mostly useful for software development.
If you do work in a SunOS (?)
system or similar and do UNIX programming.
You can have a whole machine running Linux
Academic use due to the fact that you have sources available.
For now, additional costs and you can implement your own features.
You can test out your theories.
I know Linux has been used in academia too
Test out things like new file systems test out uh,... behind large address.
Space machines they simulated, a 64-bit machine using Linux, and I know that somebody submitted the paper on it to [?] somewhere USENIX?
Last year, I don't know if it was actually accepted.
But the largest reason for running Linux is technical superiority.
It's simply better than anything out there in the world.
Ah, it's faster.
It's smaller, it's [FIXME] mean or it slices dices, and so on.
It runs endless loops in under 6 seconds or whatever works on everything and
And works very well.
Uh, I know people have started using Linux because it's free.
And so on.
So it's the cheap alternative.
I also know people who have actually actually switched from a real UNIX
to Linux, because it's faster and it's more stable.
On the other hand.
You may not want to use Linux.
There's a noticeable lack of support uh.
There are Linux companies out there.
I know they're in the US.
There's one Finland and uh, but obviously you can't call a 1 800 number and just ask for support.
On the other hand, you do have support in electronic form.
If you are connected to the network.
There are five Linux News groups who are there to support you uh.
And there are mailing lists too, but that may not be quite what you want.
Also, the documentation of Linux is kind of sparse.
Um, it's mostly in electronic form.
I know of three books in German.
Sadly enough, I don't speak any German.
I know one book in English.
Which is available both electronically and in paper back.
But you are not going to get
kind of 5 meters of documentation, when you
Which may be a good point after all. Also,
It doesn't run many commercial programs.
If you want to run, okay, Windows Write or something like that, it doesn't run on Linux yet.
Uh.
Math math lab.
Has been a problem in some circles.
There are alternatives, but they are general.
Have problems, things like that also one problem with Linux is actual.
Trusting the system because it's three people tend to think okay.
You get what you pay for, which.
Is kind of irritating.
For me personally, also, while it's technically superior, it does have some technical problems.
Ah, while I said it runs on almost everything I meant.
It runs on almost any PC, it does not run on the Alpha yet.
It also does not run on
SPARCstation, so you are stuck with Solaris in that case.
I'm actually hoping to have an alpha board at home.
For testing for half a year, so we'll see what comes in. What?
Excuse me, [question from audience] uh.
There is 68k port going on.
For the older max, but.
It's actually for for the Atari and
AMIGA computers.
And uh, I doubt it will ever get ported to the Mac.
The documentation on the hardware level is kind of kind
Sorry, the Power PC, maybe also the code is kind of young.
The hell of kernel is less than 3 years old, so uh parts like networking.
Still do have its own stability problems.
Uh, there are small
limitations like the memory mapping actually only support three dominant things on fives right now.
So you can't map in a file into memory, write to memory and and the file changes.
You can only map them[?] read on.
Okay, I hope, everyone.
Everybody knows what Linux is
So we'll take up why why it's been written.
Ah, the obvious answer is DOS, a PC hardware is getting lots better, but the operating system certainly ...
have not been getting better as fast as the hardware.
So when I bought the computer, I didn't want to run DOS.
Instead, I bought a small UNIX system called Minix.
Written by Andy Tanenbaum of Amsterdam.
And run that.
But the limitations of that system just resulted in me
actually, starting writing my own.
Ah.
The reason I couldn't use real UNIX
was because real UNIX costs, lots of money.
Ah, it's become cheaper now, I hope partially because of the Linux, but back three years ago, a real UNIX
full license costs something like 20,000 Finnish markkas.
Which is what 5000 dollars 4000 dollars.
So for students with no money at all, it's not really a an option.
Of course, those are just the the kind of motivations you you want to say the real motivation, of course.
Was just to have fun and write something interesting.
Uh, it's also turned out to be highly educational, and you get if you write your own operating system.
You get to travel all around the world and see interesting and weird people. Like yourselves ..
Actually, what you need to write your own UNIX is a) you have to be star craving mad.
But that's not a problem, at least from limited experience I've had with the UNIX people.
So so I have 4 kind of four main points.
You have to be totally ignorant if you know what you're doing, you obviously do.
I also know that this is not worth.
I mean, if you know the semantics(语义) of select() how many people know select()?
Okay, well, you're.
Out already, you don't want the implement select() in under UNIX so on,
also, you have to be an arrogant bastard, because assuming hypothetical question,
assuming you were writing your own operating system under a system.
called Minix, which has been written by a very well known.
professor inside of the operating system community.
Assuming you will be writing it, and this professor publicly announced
your system was worth nothing and was obsolete before it was saved(?) and written.
What's your reaction?
a) you think he's probably right and forget about it,
b) you think, okay, I'll try anyway or
c) ha. what does he know anyway, if you answered c, then okay, you might be in for into in the running.
Yet actually, this was not a hypothetical question, as you might tell.
But what's actually what's happened.
So okay, once you've got the system running up and running and doing something,
you have to actually have this time, you have to continue with it because there's gonna be
problems and you're going to hit your head against the wall
several times, so you'd better just keep on going, and then every once in a while,
You have to have some inspiration.
Ah, I can solve this problem this way.
That's actually the smallest part, I think.
Okay, over to some dates, ah, I bought my PC in early 1991.
That was after having gone through a UNIX uh class at the university,
so I had seen my first UNIX half a year before that, uh, I'm decided all at once that I wanted to use CUNIX? at home,
too. So I bought the Minix system and what I didn't start out to do was write an operating system.
Instead, Minix lacked terminal (?feature), so I wrote my own, and I actually wanted to test out my new machine at the same time.
So I decided, okay, let's see, this machine has
multitasking capabilities in hardware.
So let's do it by doing two tasks in the terminal emulator, quite like kermit does.
But we do it in hardware all the way, so I did a very simple program.
Well, actually, it's not very simple because the
386 protected mode hardware is very hard to actually program, that was a terminal emulation.
That's where it all began and then.
I kind of added features, and soon it was the GNU Emacs of
terminal emulators and I called it Linux.
This was in.
Well, in.
August 91 I actually had a system that leads something useful, so I made it public in September.
To get some feedback.
And to be quite frank, at that point, it wasn't worth very much, it's booted, it ran a shell.
It ran GCC, which was might .. kind of first milestone.
But if you tried to compile a big program, it's crashed because the buffer handling didn't work out very well.
Uh.
So I kind of worked on that.
And by November 91.
Really worked very well.
And people who had used Minix's before were starting to switch over because Linux give things faster, work, better on past machines and so on.
By that time.
I got the problem that I had 8 megs on memory.
Which was ampful? by my standards back then
And could compile the kernel with no problems at all, but people who had smaller machines like just two megs
also wanted to start playing this, and they couldn't compile the kernel because they didn't have enough space for for gcc,
so just to get one of those people off my back.
I sat down and wrote the virtual memory in 3 days before Christmas, 91 ah.
It actually worked.
But had so many bugs that the last one was found kind of half a year later, last or so, okay.
Then in May of 92, we.
Actually got X11 release 5 working at that time, it was
really a port (移植) of the official X consortium X11 code uh a month later, Linux got into the XFree86 projects.
That's what we're using now, which is kind of it's X11 R5, but it's got lots of enhancements for the PC.
And then I skip lots of things.
Networking got started with X, drivers got written and so on.
And this March, I released.
Version 1.0.
All in all.
It took a pretty exactly three years from from beginning of coding to 1.0, which is not too bad.
Okay.
I don't know what your reaction is.
But I know I get the question pretty often.
Why make it free, you could be the Bill Gates of Finland by now.
If you hadn't it actually I struck off by answering, no.
I wouldn't, because if I hadn't made it free would never have developed as it has,
I probably had thought it's an interesting project and continued for half a year on it.
And then I'd say.
Okay, this is nice, and I had left.
Making it free and available for lots of people adds a lot to your motivation.
You get kind of you, get the feed back.
That motivates you to continue developing the system.
Uh, I got lots of nails for the first few releases, which.
were not really usable that they're kind of.
Still kept me going, and the feedback also results in in bug reports.
So you fix the bugs faster, because you actually notice them.
Uh, it also results in lots of new ideas when I started out writing
Linux I didn't know what a PTY was, and as I mentioned, I didn't know what select() was.
I was totally clueless about UNIX.
And I got lots of good ideas from making it public and letting people say.
Hey, why doesn't this one support select()?
I'd like to use select()
I said, what? okay, so.
also testing, especially on PC hardware testing, is a real problem because PC hardware is junk, the processor is good.
Actually, I like the 386.
It has too few registers but
it's a solid piece of hardware, otherwise, but the surrounding
hardware is very varied and do it doesn't always work the way it's supposed.
So when you do a PC port of UNIX, you are in for lots of surprises, and I think SUN
noticed this with 386 Solaris, which I think is dead, maybe not officially,
but it didn't seem to work on as many machines as they had hoped.
Also, not just testing, but people actually wrote drivers, so peripherals I couldn't even test because I didn't have them.
Other people wrote drivers for and uh now Linux has drivers for something like
10 different SCSI uh controllers, of which I have just
one, and I didn't even need to write the driver for that.
So I say I'm the father of Linux.
But actually, I've written probably less than half of the code in the kernel.
Uh, the disadvantages of making it free, I'll start off by saying these are the disadvantages people expect they aren't real negative comments.
You may be a bit afraid about people would say about your coding style, hey, this works, but.
Actually, I have gotten very few negative comments at all.
Most of them were from the aforementioned Andrew Tanenbaum
Also making it free under the GPL.
People start wondering.
Don't you feel bad about it?
If people take advantage of your work and sell it for lots of money.
Actually, nobody has sold it for lots of money, but.
The CDROMs that are going to be a ?rough adult?.
They are being sold by for money, and no, I'm not getting anything for it.
I don't mind, frankly, I enjoy the publicity and getting.
Fly flight over the world and so on.
And okay, no economic gain already.
It's [inaudible] there.
Uh, I expect to get some economic gain from it.
I'm pretty sure I will get a job working at some company someday.
Okay, we a bit early, maybe by now, the user base.
Which I have no idea about how large it is.
It's large uh Linux is probably the largest PC UNIX in the world right now.
Uh, I have no firm numbers, but I expect 100000 machines
running Linux to be a lower bound.
The only numbers I have is that the CDROM was sold in 10000 copies.
For the first release.
And people who who get it by FTP are probably
more, more usual, so so Linux is actually pretty popular.
There are lots of different different distributions.
The ones being raffled out, are, what, trans america tech, okay, there's the [inaudible] I already mentioned.
There's a couple of CDROM distributions that are essentially just copies of the ftp sites, and some other.
I think I personally have five CDROMs.
Different CDROMs and I don't do anything with them.
Because I don't have a drive.
Uh, there's also kind of disk copying services going on one in Canada, probably a few in the US.
And there are lots of different distributions.
Just being made available by FTP.
I don't actually do with these distributions.
I just do the kernel sources and let other people then compile it and make a complete system of it.
So and so I try to not have to do with those things.
Also, Linux is finally getting some media recognition uh PC Week
Uh.
Had it as their product for the week here.
A month ago, perhaps.
So we hope that the user base will actually grow.
Then off for some comments about the future
uh with the 1.0 release, I got a few
questions about a) will it continue to be free and b) will I continue to develop it and the answer to both is
In fact, there is already a 1.1 source tree
Is available at the PC in the in the hall across building the new release is.
Adds memory management and networking capabilities, and I'll obviously be continuing
work on the Linux for at least the next few years, if if interests keeps and keeps up
Also will add or work on adding source compatibility.
We.
None of the standards are actually ratified(批准生效) right now because it seems to cost a lot, but there has been some talk about actually ratifying Linux as POSIX.1
And possibly some other standards, I have the XPG 3 manuals.
I've opened and once they were boring and I closed them again, maybe somebody else will do the work.
For [inaudible], so we can always hope.
Also, while i'm not very excited about the idea, uh Linux is moving into the direction of binary compatibility with those through the DOS simulation, which actually works pretty well right now, it's still considered to be alpha software.
But it's available.
And runs most, most normal DOS programs.
It doesn't run games very well.
But you can use it for Word Perfect and so on it also it
even works under an XTerm, a bit
slower and you know, that's completely.
We are also working on, and indeed, it works already again.
The porting, the standard.
Intel binary compatibility specification.
Version 2 ACEBC S2? to this is done through loadable modules, which change the personality of the system so that the system calls operate the way.
The standard wineries expect them to. This is not part of the standard kernel right now, but people report that
with the patches.
It actually runs SCO binaries of Word Perfect under X.
So that way.
We'll get some commercial support for people who need the commercial programs.
Also, then, perhaps most exciting product would be a
Windows emulation there's work going on with a
a project called WINE, which will should
be a free Windows emulator
For the X uh, it's not even close to ready yet.
It runs the most important program, which is the solitaire game.
But that's about it.
There's been rumors of.
The SUN will be product whatever they call it.
There's also been rumors about a third product for Novell, which I may come into a bit.
Uh, the idea is that with Windows emulation
You could actually run a large number of
Good programs, which suddenly.
Now run only under a large number of bad operating systems.
And some future too, I already mentioned the 68k port, which is at Linux 1.0 standard, but
Is not complete at this point and doesn't run on on very many machines.
It runs on some AMIGAs.
There is a booting Atari port, but it's a step in the right.
direction also, there has been a lot of discussions.
About supporting Linux to some of the more interesting RISC, newer RISC processors like the DEC Alpha and the Power PC.
I have a contact that.
Netherlands who is going to contact the Finland.
Who is possibly going to get me a DEC Alpha machine.
We don't know. Also ...
Work on documentation.
And support is is is still going on, so there are the books I already mentioned.
There are more on the way, the kind installation and system administration guides needed to to get the new user going.
Also, companies like novel,
which, as you may know, owns the UNIX source licenses.
There, well, so.
Small article in PC Week again April 25th, that said.
Novel is actually going to release
Or possibly going to release a.
CDROM containing not UNIX ware, but Linux.
Along with a Windows simulator.
Looking glass X windows interface and so on, this may or may not be reality.
But it at least shows that people and companies are looking into Linux.
As a viable(切实可行的) alternative to commercial software.
I'm afraid that's about it.
I'll do the step dance after the second session.
I see you survived the first one.
There wasn't any real problem, was there.
Are there any problems?
Like to remind you of two things
So if you haven't already done, want to drop your card or your badge in the bag up here for the drawing, we're gonna be raffling off two autographed copies of the trans American Linux Linux CDROMs, and also, i'd like to thank John Hall and digital equipment corporation for making these talks possible.
Stand up, John.
I would have took your fine Irish temper, so if there are any questions, please line up behind the mic far away.
1 question.
Do you know if any of the major.
Uh database companies like Oracle.
Or Sybase or any of those folks are planning on pouring their products to Linux?
The question was, do you know any major database companies planning to port to Linux?
And the answer is no.
I have no idea and.
I'm not a database person myself, so that I wouldn't have even looked into it, thought it.
Could you write.
Could you write down the ftp sites that have the one point of.
Yeah.
Does anybody have a pen , right.
Is this one.
I assume most of you aren't Finnish and one of you is.
But in the US.
The main sites are tsx-11.mit.edu
sunsite.unc.edu this one is in.
Um, maybe this one is also, but with a capital L
There are lots of others, but.
These are the two major ones in the US.
Actually, I might add that.
If you do get this UNIX distribution, the best one is.
At this point seems to be the one called Slackware.
Which should be images slackware.
On sunsite, I don't remember the exact location on tsx-11.
That one.
Contains enough documentation to get you started and.
And lots of things.
It's a completely UNIX system takes up 130 megs of your hard disk
if you want to install it at all, okay.
Any other question.
Anthony Collins international Potato center in Lima
following on to the previous question, I was going to ask if anyone knew whether Oracle version 6.
would run on the Linux, what could you, I guess the question was whether Oracle version 6 would run under Linux uh.
I don't know anything about Oracle versions.
I know they're only.
Oh, okay, there are a few databases running under Linux and they're just
What the GNU one, which.
Is called metal base or something like that, so I think the older versions of the ingress.
I think. I can add the observation that Oracle version 5 is available and runs under xenic.
Well, it might.
Actually run under Linux with the iBCS2 patches.
I haven't tried.
I actually have no System V software at all, so I haven't tried the iBCS2 patches at all.
I kind of I started off from scratch, so I don't have any.
Installed base of software I could try on.
Sorry, okay, any other questions.
Okay, if not.
Let's draw some names, you get to do that.
I get to do that.
From the bottom of the bucket and.
David E Ellis.
Vice president, chief scientist, rocket scientist and director.
Of Albuquerque operations.
And before in my life, and then the second person.
Timothy Cook, computer specialists from.
I'm not going to pronounce this one.
[ Inaudible ]
Congratulations, I just won a free copy of the Linux
Okay.
Oh.
Yeah, he did say he was going to be tap dancing and doing traditional Finnish folk dances in between the sessions. Where's Christie, she was going to accompany.
Could we take this after the second talk.
Uh distributions like where, okay, i'm told.
It's.
Okay.
Instead of the images.
Images and distributions, okay, what it's I'm actually not certain I was, I'd I'd have thought it was images slackware, but.
It might be images, distribution, slackware or it might.
Be just distribution like.
And you'll find the issue you have.
A working directory listing route
hopefully yes.
Uh, there are no public domain ports of Motif, but there is a commercial version of Motif, which.
Sells for 89 dollars for the limited version.
100 and something dollars for the development version
Actually, they are selling a motif package, which it's labeled motif.
I understand, but it actually contains a complete Linux distribution so you can just buy a cd.
ROM and gets Motif and Linux. Motif isn't available
for free anywhere.
There is now currently a Linux journal as well, and in fact there might be two people from the Linux journal here.
If you're if you're here, you want to identify yourself by looking at each other and saying, hi, I work with you.
I know they were going to come.  I'm not sure if they're here or not.
They are.
There's all two of them.
Um.
You'll find a lot of the vendors are advertising in the journal, and it's actually a pretty good source of information as well as the news groups and as well as quartering Linux and talking to him.
So anyway, next session.
[..] tells a little bit about.
The window manager included in the in the X11 distribution.
The window manager there are actually several ones, the best one, in my opinion, is O feeble window manager.
Which was written for Linux originally, but now ported to several other architecture.
Which is kind of a based on TVMs sources and then added lots of features.
Nifty features it's almost completely customizable.
There's open look if you want that.
Not if you already mentioned TVM CTVM, they're all available, but if you want.
I actually appreciate a few more questions.
So I don't like my step dance.
Okay, we can just go on and.
Stop for early, maybe.
You're you're not getting out of the tap dancing that easy.
Why don't you have a seat, relax and take a deep breath, have a beer.
And.
A question where
Frank Dennis, Hahnemann University, Philadelphia, and it's just of curiosity, what are people actually.
Doing with it.
What's the most ambitious application of Linux that you know?
Oh.
Ambitious, ambitious? oh.
Like challenging?
well, the most challenging is writing operating systems.
Uh, I know Linux is used.
For.
Linux on PCs used for as cheap X terminals at one hospital.
I don't know at which, so you can't avoid it if you are there uh.
I also know there's Linux PC.
On Antarctica, doing some kind of mail forwarding or similar,
I know there's a Linux PC on one large super tanker, which is used to as a FAX forwarder.
With satellite tooling console.
Ooph hard to say.
It's rumored AT&T has a Linux lab with Linux machines.
But that's.
Ya, alright.
Yeah, probably.
Well, I'm going for.
A master of sciences, but I've been going for that now for five years, I expected to take at least two more years.
Okay [inaudible name] organized consulting, I'm believe I'm here because I disdained Finnish folk dancing.
So.
I just question as long those lines.
How old are you with your background.
Computers how long you've been doing this.
How long do you sleep every night, things like that.
Only only one question at a time.
And please go to the end of the line after asking each one.
Uh, what was the first one?
I'm 25.
Year 24 actually yeah, hard to keep track 24 years old started when I was 11.
On a VIC-20, if it's familiar to any of you uh, then moved on to Sinclair QL, which.
Probably isn't familiar to any other.
Uh, which taught me never to buy a small.
Machine that wasn't supportive, so I bought a PC even though it had done.
Uh.
I do sleep 8 hours a night.
I lied when I said I didn't sleep pretty much.
The fact that I.
Use lots of time on Linux, just means I use less on my studies and on my work.
Did that cover everything.
OK, and I even have time for my girlfriend and cats occasionally.
Well, I'm.
We're teaching assistants at the university, which means.
Studying at least actually part of my work, so I can can say i'm working you, and when i'm working on Linux.
I'm also.
Sadly supposed to program something for me because of windows, which I have no clue at all about, but we'll see.
I gave
the Swedish small introduction to computers course last fall
So I I'm kind of a
do-it-all kind of guy.
Uh, what?
I don't know.
I didn't write it, but it's definitely commercial, something.
Like a 10000 dollar source license.
And then you have decision by the MIT folk wrote it. and whatever OSF folks, sorry, I don't know anything.
I'm just sit here,
question Andrew Potter, Rochester Institute of Technology.
I just thought i'd let you know some of the things that's happening with Linux.
Um, it's growing very rapidly, and its uses are just about anything that anyone uses a UNIX system for on an academic campus.
We've got people doing mosaic development and setting up a worldwide web server on it.
A large number of students have come on to the campus network with who are computer science programs and use SUNs in the
for their academic studies have have set up Linux on their their pcs in their dorms and their network,
or they even using some of the network connectivity tools that are come with the
Slackware distribution um some of the network tools that have become that are very exciting is one.
Called term that a lot of users use, uh, it's a it's a poor means.
Let's.
Get the next best thing to SLIP connectivity where you actually log into a UNIX machine over a dialogue line asynchronously and come to the shell, prompt.
Start up this client program that essentially redirects ip sockets back to your own machine so that you can run IP applications on your own machine or TCP applications on your own machine,
and they are redirected as if they are coming from the machine that you're on so that you can send X servers back or you can send the Mosaic equivalent Mosaic clients and a number of other things on your machines.
This is actually.
You know, a number of people are doing this at our site.
If people are using it for their mail engines, they're using it for you name it.
Whenever anyone uses a UNIX System IV in an academic environment.
Linux was doing it, and in many cases better.
Rick Tangan, Rocketdyne Division, Rockwell International.
One of our system administrators, has observed that he prefers the Linux interface to the HP-UX interface.
He says Linux is much more professional.
My question is.
What feature do you want to see next in Linux?
What's on your wish list.
I'll come to some of the Kernel features in my next talk.
Actually, I.
Really like to have a Windows emulator. Because
one of the things I miss.
Under Linux now I said it myself under Linux is that there is no good word processor there.
These slides.
I am ashamed to admit were done under windows, so I'd like to have a Windows emulator just to be able to do my slide on the one true operating system
Thank you.
Okay.
Well, I guess if there's no more questions unless you want to take a quick break, okay, do you want to take a quick break two minutes.
2 minutes break in case somebody is.
Coming for the second talk 2 minutes break and do you need an escort again.
Or do we have your word, you'll come.
I'll come back
Okay.
I got, okay, they're.
[ inaudible ]